<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Convergence, the next stage in technology, may wind up being a different creature than expected.</title>
    <meta content="29NECO$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203309"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEW ECONOMY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schiesel, Seth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Columns/New Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000529T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E7DD1F3DF93AA15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1026" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Convergence, the next stage in technology, may wind up being a different creature than expected.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Seth Schiesel</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schiesel, Seth</byline>
      <dateline>DANA POINT, Calif.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Seth Schiesel column says the interactive world of information and entertainment that was supposed to be achieved through convergence of television, telephone system and the Internet has yet to arrive and, when it does, will probably take forms much different from those generally envisioned today; says that while bandwidth capacity in nation's long-distance fiber optic networks is increasing exponentially, no more than 2 percent of nation's homes currently log on the Internet with anything more powerful than an analog modem; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>OF all of the buzzwords in the technology industry, perhaps none is invoked as blindly, reflexively and totemically as ''convergence.''</p>
        <p>Talk to a senior technology executive these days and you will probably hear about how television, the telephone system and the Internet are converging to create an interactive world of information and entertainment.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>OF all of the buzzwords in the technology industry, perhaps none is invoked as blindly, reflexively and totemically as ''convergence.''</p>
        <p>Talk to a senior technology executive these days and you will probably hear about how television, the telephone system and the Internet are converging to create an interactive world of information and entertainment.</p>
        <p>But, in fact, convergence is not really happening, at least not yet. And when it does, it will probably take forms much different than those generally envisioned today.</p>
        <p>That is not a conclusion a visitor might have expected to bring away from the annual Vortex conference that ended on Friday here on the Pacific Coast. Vortex is about convergence, and it may be North America's most concentrated gathering of top communications investors and executives. But according to an automated polling service at the conference, the Vortex attendees gave convergence an overall letter grade of D-plus for now.</p>
        <p>They recognize that even though billions of dollars are being spent on convergence, immense obstacles remain. And in the end, convergence will be far less than universal.</p>
        <p>At the first Vortex conference two years ago, the mood about convergence was positively giddy. ''Two years ago here I remember people looking at the new carriers, the Qwests and Level 3's, and thinking that they were just going to make convergence happen,'' said a senior technical executive for a big local communications carrier. ''I think what's impressing me this year is a new sense of maturity -- sobriety even.''</p>
        <p>A 21 percent drop in the Nasdaq will sober up just about anyone in the technology business. And it has. But beyond the financial picture, the emerging sense of realism about  convergence seems based on a simple and renewed appreciation of the mundane technical obstacles that stand in its way, and on some newly creative thinking about what sorts of services will best embody it.</p>
        <p>Technically, convergence is the last mile. That sounds obvious, but the last few years, at least some technology pundits, executives and investors have drooled over the exponential increases in bandwidth capacity in the nation's long-distance fiber optic networks and mistaken that for convergence.</p>
        <p>But for all of the leaps in long-haul capacity, no more than 2 percent of the nation's 100 million or so homes currently log on the Internet with anything more powerful than an analog modem. The last mile of the nation's communications networks -- or the first mile, depending on who's holding the mouse -- is the part that actually touches homes. But this crucial link has not kept pace with the rest of the network.</p>
        <p>The digital subscriber line technology that local phone companies want to use to deliver torrents of Internet data over traditional copper phone lines has had a particularly tough time living up to expectations. D.S.L. is far more difficult to put in place than was originally thought. And the bandwidth, or speed, it delivers is far less than was first contemplated.</p>
        <p>In early 1998, when many of the nation's leading computer, software and local communications companies formed an alliance to support D.S.L., they thought it would generally deliver 1.5 million digital bits a second to consumers' homes. Today, it is unlikely that more than a quarter of the few hundred thousand households with working D.S.L. are consistently receiving more than a million bits, or a megabit, a second. Industry experts say that most D.S.L. households probably get only around 500,000 bits a second, at best. (Cable modems, the main alternative to D.S.L., more frequently deliver megabit-plus speeds, but in some ways those communications pathways are less reliable than D.S.L.)</p>
        <p>Of course, even 500,000 bits a second is still an order of magnitude faster than the 53,000 or so bits a second that can be delivered by today's fastest analog modems. But consider that a single channel of TV-quality video, using compression technology, requires at least 2 million bits a second and often requires more than 5 million bits a second; it becomes quite clear that for the great majority of consumers, television as they know it is not going to be converging with the Internet soon.</p>
        <p>But then, merging TV with the Internet is probably the wrong goal, anyway. Television is a one-way, centrally created and distributed medium. It is not the killer application for the Internet because the Internet does not operate like TV.</p>
        <p>And yet, most demonstrations of converged applications that include video, including those at Vortex, are essentially television with some interactive buttons, like ''buy now,'' or ''chat about this program,'' tacked on the side of the screen.</p>
        <p>''The trap is when people think about this new media strictly in the context of the old,'' said Michael O'Dell, chief scientist for Worldcom's Uunet operation, the No. 1 Internet carrier. ''I have a problem believing that the future of the Internet is a bad version of cable TV.''</p>
        <p>Rather than take the form of merely repackaged traditional media, the most successful converged services will probably be cut from wholly new cloth to take advantage of the specific characteristics of cyberspace.</p>
        <p>Napster, the service that allows users to swap digital music files, is a perfect example. And some technology experts believe that Napster is already consuming more of the Internet's bandwidth than is the leading Web site, Yahoo. Rather than simply selling compact discs online or putting radio stations online (the aural equivalent of adding a ''chat now'' button to a TV program), the very nature of Napster's service emerged from the Internet.</p>
        <p>In fact, Vinod Khosla, the venture capitalist from Kleiner Perkins Caufield &amp; Byers, said trying to repackage traditional media online was actually hindering the deployment of  broadband communications and converged services in general.</p>
        <p>''When you're trying to migrate old services to a new medium, the barriers are high and the payoffs aren't that great,'' Mr. Khosla said. ''But when you have a new service, maybe the barrier is high but I'll climb over it because the payoff is higher.''</p>
        <p>NEW ECONOMY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
