<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ligtenberg to the Rescue As the Braves Hang On</title>
    <meta content="NL27.$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203300"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NATIONAL LEAGUE: ROUNDUP"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Atlanta Braves</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000529T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E3DE1F3DF93AA15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="635" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ligtenberg to the Rescue As the Braves Hang On</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By The Associated Press</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Andruw Jones, Brian Jordan and Chipper Jones hit home runs in a cooled-down Enron Field, leading the Atlanta Braves to a 6-5 victory over the Houston Astros yesterday.</p>
        <p>The Braves' reliever John Rocker walked the bases loaded in the ninth inning and was pulled. Kerry Ligtenberg escaped the jam without allowing a run, getting Richard Hidalgo to ground into a game-ending double play.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Andruw Jones, Brian Jordan and Chipper Jones hit home runs in a cooled-down Enron Field, leading the Atlanta Braves to a 6-5 victory over the Houston Astros yesterday.</p>
        <p>The Braves' reliever John Rocker walked the bases loaded in the ninth inning and was pulled. Kerry Ligtenberg escaped the jam without allowing a run, getting Richard Hidalgo to ground into a game-ending double play.</p>
        <p>The one-run loss was Houston's 13th in 14 games this season.</p>
        <p>The Astros lost more than the game. Moises Alou left the game with tightness in his left quadriceps muscle one day after outfielder Roger Cedeno was placed on the 15-day disabled list. Alou was listed as day to day.</p>
        <p>The Braves got the early lead in the first regular-season game played at Enron Field with the roof closed. It was 72 degrees inside with the air conditioning while temperatures outside hit the 90's.</p>
        <p>Rocker walked the first two batters in the ninth, threw a wild pitch and then intentionally walked Ken Caminiti. Ligtenberg relieved and retired Daryle Ward on a shallow fly ball and, on a full count, got Hidalgo to bounce into a double play for his his third save.</p>
        <p>ROCKIES 7, PIRATES 6: In Denver, Todd Helton hit two home runs, including a leadoff shot in the ninth inning that lifted Colorado.</p>
        <p>Helton tied the score, 5-5, with a three-run homer in the fifth.</p>
        <p>Helton, who ended an 0-for-13 slide with two hits Friday, went</p>
        <p>4 for 4, raising his average to .406.</p>
        <p>Jason Kendall, with his father watching from the Colorado bullpen, went 4 for 5 with 3 runs scored, and Wil Cordero added a two-run homer for the Pirates.</p>
        <p>Colorado erased an early 5-0 deficit and got an impressive effort from relievers Julian Tavarez and Gabe White (4-0). The two held Pittsburgh to one run and three hits in four and a third innings.</p>
        <p>The bullpen set the stage for Helton as he hit the first pitch from Jason Christiansen (1-3) into the bullpen beyond right field for his 15th homer of the season.</p>
        <p>CUBS 3, GIANTS 2: Jose Nieves's sacrifice fly in the 11th inning gave Chicago a victory at San Francisco, just the Cubs' eighth victory in 24 road games this season.</p>
        <p>Henry Rodriguez opened the 11th with a double off Aaron Fultz (1-1). The pinch-runner Chad Meyers moved to third on a groundout and, after a walk, scored on Nieves's fly to right.</p>
        <p>Daniel Garibay (1-1) pitched two hitless innings for the victory. Rick Aguilera pitched the 11th for his eighth save in 12 chances.</p>
        <p>DIAMONDBACKS 7, BREWERS 3: Tony Womack extended his hitting streak to 22 games and scored twice, and Arizona stretched its team-record home winning string to 11.</p>
        <p>Luis Gonzalez also homered for Arizona, which has won five straight over all. Milwaukee has lost four in a row.</p>
        <p>Steve Finley hit his 18th homer and drove in three runs, raising his National League-leading runs-batted-in total to 51. His two-run homer in the fifth inning tied the score, and Jay Bell singled home the go-ahead run in the sixth.</p>
        <p>Armando Reynoso (3-4) allowed two runs in six innings. Byung-Hyun Kim retired the last five batters for his fifth save in six chances.</p>
        <p>NATIONAL LEAGUE: ROUNDUP</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
