<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At 102, a First Author Recalls Slave Relatives</title>
    <meta content="29DAWS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203326"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dawson, George</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Glaubman, Richard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, Dinitia</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Life Is So Good (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000529T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07EEDD1F3DF93AA15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1714" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At 102, a First Author Recalls Slave Relatives</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DINITIA SMITH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smith, Dinitia</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>George Dawson, 102, who only began to read at age 98, is co-author of Life Is So Good, story of his life growing up in East Texas among relatives who had been slaves; Dawson lives in Dallas, where he attends adult education classes; interview during visit to New York with co-author Richard Glaubman, teacher from Washington State; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the annals of publishing, few people have had to wait as long as George Dawson to see their name on a book jacket. Mr. Dawson is 102. But then he didn't begin to read until he was 98.</p>
        <p>This year, Mr. Dawson, who now reads at about a fourth- grade level, and Richard Glaubman, a 50-year-old elementary schoolteacher from Washington State, published ''Life Is So Good'' (Random House), based on Mr. Dawson's account of life growing up in East Texas among relatives who had been slaves. Both are listed as authors. The story is told partly in Mr. Dawson's words as recorded by Mr. Glaubman.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the annals of publishing, few people have had to wait as long as George Dawson to see their name on a book jacket. Mr. Dawson is 102. But then he didn't begin to read until he was 98.</p>
        <p>This year, Mr. Dawson, who now reads at about a fourth- grade level, and Richard Glaubman, a 50-year-old elementary schoolteacher from Washington State, published ''Life Is So Good'' (Random House), based on Mr. Dawson's account of life growing up in East Texas among relatives who had been slaves. Both are listed as authors. The story is told partly in Mr. Dawson's words as recorded by Mr. Glaubman.</p>
        <p>''Life Is So Good'' is an unusual history of a segment of black American life in the 20's and 30's, propelled by Mr. Dawson's acute powers of observation. It is about a dangerous era when the Klan was on the rise, lynchings were common and it was unsafe even for a black baseball team to beat a white team.</p>
        <p>A few weeks ago Mr. Dawson visited New York City for the first time from Dallas where he lives, accompanied by his 65-year-old son, George Jr., a retired civilian communications employee of the Army, and Mr. Glaubman. There was a party at the Century Club. There was a book signing at a Barnes &amp; Noble branch, a ride on the Staten Island ferry and the rare experience of room service at the hotel, with Mr. Dawson signing his name for it.</p>
        <p>He moved through it all at a good pace; people don't have to slow their stride for him. Mr. Dawson hasn't lost any hair to baldness, doesn't have false teeth, wears reading glasses only sometimes. And although he has some hearing loss from working with heavy machinery in a dairy, he gets by without a hearing aid. He has never spent a night in a hospital. These days he sits rather quietly, politely answering questions.</p>
        <p>''I lived right. Ate right, whatever I wanted to. Never smoked,'' Mr. Dawson said over breakfast of toast with jam. And the last time he had a drink, he said ''was in 1928.'' He went on: ''I didn't love it. I just did it because the boys I was with were doing it.''</p>
        <p>But as interesting as longevity is, ''Life Is So Good'' presents perhaps a more interesting story, one fashioned from on-the-ground insight into the strategies that many black people devised to survive the perils of life in the South at the turn of the century.</p>
        <p>For much of his life, because he could not read or write, Mr. Dawson didn't live by the written calendar, so dates are sparse.</p>
        <p>He was born in a log cabin in Marshall, Tex. His parents were farmers; unlike many blacks of the rural South who were sharecroppers, they owned their own hardscrabble piece of land. At age 10, Mr. Dawson witnessed the lynching of a 17-year-old friend, Pete, who was accused of raping a white girl.</p>
        <p>The day of the lynching his father gave him a piece of advice that endured. ''His suffering is over, son,'' he said, according to the book. ''Some of those white folks was mean and nasty. Some are just scared. It doesn't matter. You have no right to judge another human being.''</p>
        <p>Since then, Mr. Dawson has wasted no time with bitterness, he said. According to the book, the girl's baby was born white, but, as Mr. Dawson remembered it, ''No one said nothing.'' He states in the book: ''I guess by then most folks, white folks anyway, had all forgotten. I didn't forget.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Dawson didn't go to school because he worked from the age of 4 alongside his paternal grandmother and great-grandmother, combing cotton and pressing sugar cane. They taught him slave songs, which he can still sing, and told him stories. His grandmother, Charity, recounted the day when she was young and her master, ''Mr. Lester,'' told his slaves they were free. Some were afraid to leave, others remained as sharecroppers. But, as Mr. Dawson relates, they were enslaved again, accumulating debt at the plantation store because they couldn't count. Eventually Charity's family enlisted the help of a field hand, Tom, who knew numbers. The family worked off its debt, and Tom married Charity.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Dawson was 12, his father, Harrison, had to hire him out to a white farmer for $1.50 a month, he wrote. As a young man he built levees for 50 cents a day, worked in a sawmill and laid railroad tracks. He often worked hungry.</p>
        <p>The book spins out his continuing adventures. He rode the rails, landing in Mexico in 1923, astounded to discover that a black man could be served alongside whites. He pitched on a Negro baseball team. In 1926, while breaking wild horses on a farm in the Texas Panhandle, he encountered a 16-year-old girl, Elzenia.</p>
        <p>''I was a rough boy,'' he said. ''I was just clowning, that's all. That bought her.'' Elzenia became his wife. She died about 15 years ago, he said.</p>
        <p>All along, Mr. Dawson said, he pretended he could read. He signed his name with an x. He would make his seven children read their homework aloud to him. His son George said he never knew his father could not read or write until he was in the Navy in Korea and Vietnam and did not get letters from him. And because Mr. Dawson could not write, he was unable to file for promotion in his job at the dairy.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, all his children attended college. Two are now deceased. Surviving, besides George, are Amelia Parks, 72, who worked in a medical library until she retired; Dorothy Jiles, 64, a kindergarten worker; Cecelia Ervin, 60, a homemaker; and Darrel, 51, a manager for the United Parcel Service.</p>
        <p>After Elzenia died, Mr. Dawson married three more times, all women he met in church and all of whom have died. ''I had four good wives,'' he said. ''I didn't fuss with them. We sit down and agree with each other.'' One reason that he hasn't saved money, he said, is that he wanted to give each a dignified burial.</p>
        <p>After Mr. Dawson retired from his dairy job in the late 60's, he continued working, mostly as a gardener. In the book he describes the day the woman who was employing him brought him lunch to eat on the back porch with her dogs. He was hungry, he said, but he refused to eat.</p>
        <p>''I am a human being,'' he told her, according to the book. Quiet refusal could be said to be Mr. Dawson's modus operandi.</p>
        <p>Finally, at 90, he retired for good. He received $520 a month in Social Security. His house was dilapidated and leaked. He continued to care for himself. His house was so ridden with mice they invaded his groceries. He solved the problem by putting a potato on the floor for them to eat, which stopped their bothering him.</p>
        <p>When he was 98 he heard about the adult literacy class at the Lincoln Instructional Center, in his old neighborhood high school, and signed up.</p>
        <p>''I learned to read my ABC's in two days -- I was in a hurry,'' he said.</p>
        <p>His teacher was Carl Henry, who came out of retirement from the school system to work at the center. ''It took him about six months to learn how to read simple words,'' Mr. Henry said. Mr. Dawson now reads his Bible every day.</p>
        <p>''I wanted to teach him to print,'' Mr. Henry remembered. But Mr. Dawson insisted on learning cursive, which was harder.</p>
        <p>In 1998, Larry Bingham, a columnist for The Fort Worth Star-Telegram, wrote an article about Mr. Dawson. It was syndicated in The Seattle Times, and Mr. Glaubman spotted it. ''I thought, 'How does he have so much courage to start?' '' Mr. Glaubman said. It could make an inspirational story for his students, he thought. Mr. Glaubman had lost his father the year before, he said in the book, and felt an emptiness.</p>
        <p>Mr. Glaubman decided to visit Mr. Dawson, and Mr. Dawson agreed to let him write a book. While he was researching and writing, he often stayed at Mr. Dawson's house. The two alternated cooking and in the evenings played dominoes and watched ''Jeopardy.'' At first Mr. Glaubman wrote a children's book. But he realized he had more to say, so he began an adult version.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Glaubman wrote, he was conscious of Mr. Dawson's mortality. ''You think, 'You've got to finish before he dies,' '' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Glaubman's children's book was turned down uniformly by publishers. But an editor put him in touch with an agent, Harriet Wasserman. Ms. Wasserman read the adult version and quickly sold it to Random House. Mr. Glaubman won't reveal the advance but described it as quite decent. The initial printing was 100,000 copies.</p>
        <p>At first, Mr. Dawson wanted to use his half of the advance to renovate his house. But the house was in such disrepair that it has been torn down. He is building a new one and has moved in with George temporarily .</p>
        <p>For years, Mr. Dawson's routine has been unvaried. Up at 5 a.m., he has a cup of hot chocolate, two pieces of bread and a glass of hot water. When he was living in his own house, he was picked up by Mr. Henry each morning and driven to literacy class.</p>
        <p>Inevitably, the question of mortality lingers in the air. But Mr. Dawson said he was not afraid of death. ''I want to rest,'' he said. ''I have no fear, no worry.'' When death finally comes, he added, he knows that he will finally be in a place that he calls ''Gloryland.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
