<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Agassi Hopes for Same Result In Place That Changed Career</title>
    <meta content="29TENN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203335"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TENNIS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">French Open (Tennis)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Agassi, Andre</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clarey, Christopher</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">French Open (Tennis)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000529T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E1DB1F3DF93AA15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1289" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Agassi Hopes for Same Result In Place That Changed Career</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER CLAREY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Clarey, Christopher</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, May 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Andre Agassi, playing in charity exhibition in advance of French Open, recalls 1999 Open victory; photo (M)0</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Today was, as usual, a dress rehearsal for the French Open: a day when the matches are best-of-one and the pressure almost none; a day when the gate receipts refreshingly go to charity instead of to agents, money managers or the players themselves.</p>
        <p>But for Andre Agassi, today was more a day for remembering and reflecting on the last French Open than looking forward to the next. Today, he returned to the center court where he had experienced the biggest rush of his long career and heard the cheers from an excitable French crowd that had helped lift him to last year's title. That experience -- rallying from two sets down against Andrei Medvedev in the final -- set in motion a chain of events that would alter a lot more than his ranking.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Today was, as usual, a dress rehearsal for the French Open: a day when the matches are best-of-one and the pressure almost none; a day when the gate receipts refreshingly go to charity instead of to agents, money managers or the players themselves.</p>
        <p>But for Andre Agassi, today was more a day for remembering and reflecting on the last French Open than looking forward to the next. Today, he returned to the center court where he had experienced the biggest rush of his long career and heard the cheers from an excitable French crowd that had helped lift him to last year's title. That experience -- rallying from two sets down against Andrei Medvedev in the final -- set in motion a chain of events that would alter a lot more than his ranking.</p>
        <p>''Well, I mean, how to put it into words is difficult,'' said Agassi, for whom words usually come easily. ''This was such a marking point in so many respects. Changed my career last year, and my life hasn't been the same on or off the court. I just hope my life doesn't ever change this much again in a 12-month period because it can only be not good if it changes that much.''</p>
        <p>Before Roland Garros last year, he had recently gone through a divorce. Now, he is dating last year's women's champion, Steffi Graf, who is now retired.</p>
        <p>''You know a year later, it's like it's a lifetime ago,'' Agassi said.</p>
        <p>The center court has evolved, too, although not quite so clearly for the better. Two of the four grandstands have been demolished and refurbished. And even though the Art Deco elements have been carefully re-created, the stadium feels slightly different now. Because the stands rise higher in a hurry on two sides, the court now seems more intimate, less aloof and, in that sense, somewhat less Parisian.</p>
        <p>''Even to a beautiful arena like this,'' Agassi said, ''it's always a little sad to see things change a little bit.''</p>
        <p>And yet, the opponent in front of him in today's charity match was only a pleasant reminder of the past. Arnaud Clement was two points from beating Agassi in the second round last year before the American rallied to eliminate the Frenchman in five sets. Although it did not count this time, Agassi beat him again before scribbling a few autographs and then facing the press.</p>
        <p>''If I would have lost to Clement last year, that certainly would have changed everything, but I think the match that did change everything for me last year was against Carlos Moya in the Round of 16,'' he said. ''Because that's when I was really down, and when I really started to hit out on my shots and when I realized that if I play aggressive and bring my game to the table, that gets it done.''</p>
        <p>He has been getting it done with remarkable regularity since then, compiling a 27-1 record in the last four Grand Slam events. Considering that the one loss came in the Wimbledon final against its six-time champion, Pete Sampras, he should have no regrets. And even though he has not reached another final since January and the Australian Open -- playing sporadically in recent weeks because of minor ailments -- he said he has no regrets about that, either.</p>
        <p>''I went to Zimbabwe, played there, then Scottsdale, Palm Springs and Key Biscayne and then kind of quickly realized that you can't be at your best every week,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''You can do it for a year, a year and a half, where you just commit to giving it 150 percent every time. The results can happen for a certain period of time, but then it quickly becomes about, where do you want to be at your best? I just kind of made the decision to downshift and really get myself in position for those things that I value the most.''</p>
        <p>Those would be Davis Cup, the Grand Slam events and the Olympics, in which Agassi will defend his 1996 gold-medal title in Sydney, Australia, in September. Whether he can defend his French Open title is an open question.</p>
        <p>''I feel much more prepared this year than I was last year,'' he added. ''But I wish I wasn't prepared if it means I'm going to win again. Things happen out there that you need to get through. Last year, I had three different matches that technically I should not have won. It has little to do with how well you play starting a tournament as much as with how well you play at the right time.''</p>
        <p>On clay, with its emphasis on exhausting rallies, winning also has much to do with fitness, and Agassi said he took no days off when he returned home to Las Vegas after losing to Dominik Hrbaty in Rome 17 days ago in one of his precious few clay-court matches this year.</p>
        <p>''I contend that to win here, you have to be physically at your best,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Such pronouncements cannot be of much comfort to his compatriot Lindsay Davenport, second-seeded player in the women's draw. Like Agassi, she won the Australian Open and then, unlike Agassi, went on to dominate much of the early hardcourt season until a foot injury -- linked to arthritis -- knocked her out of action for six weeks. The good news was that her layoff allowed her to spend more time in California with her new boyfriend.</p>
        <p>''It's fun to have something else going on in your life,'' she said. ''You look more realistically at your career. You even look past your career.''</p>
        <p>But as soon as Davenport returned to tournament play at the Italian Open earlier this month, she wrenched her back during practice. After a week of intensive therapy in Paris with her coach, Robert Van't Hof, she is no longer considering a withdrawal. But she has never considered herself the player to beat, even though she, like top-seeded Martina Hingis, has now won all the Grand Slam events but this one.</p>
        <p>''It feels weird,'' she said. ''We always joke about it, Robert and I: who would have thought I'd be in position to win all four? But his whole point with me the last four months is you have to try to enjoy this challenge being put in front of you here: 'Don't take it as pressure because at the end of the day if you don't accomplish it, it doesn't matter.' ''</p>
        <p>Unlike Hingis, Davenport did not grow up playing on clay and viewing a victory at Roland Garros as a sort of birthright. Nonetheless, Davenport has lost to the eventual champion the last three years in tough matches, pushing Graf very hard in the quarterfinals last year.</p>
        <p>''I have been working on my slide, but I'm actually just paranoid about going over on my ankles; so paranoid about it that I can't get over that,'' Davenport said. ''But I remember talking to Monica Seles, and she said, 'I never slide and I still won the French, so don't worry about it.' And, you know, Andre doesn't slide either.''</p>
        <p>TENNIS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
