<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TRANSACTIONS</title>
    <meta content="29TRAN$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203412"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000529T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401EEDE163CF93AA15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="678" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TRANSACTIONS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
        <p>American League  BOSTON RED SOX -- Activated SS Nomar Garciaparra from the 15-day disabled list. Placed INF Jose Offerman on the 15-day disabled list, retroactive to May 25.  CLEVELAND INDIANS -- Placed RHP Paul Rigdon on the 15-day disabled list, retroactive to May 22. Activated RHP Jaret Wright from the disabled list.  NEW YORK YANKEES -- Activated SS Derek Jeter from the 15-day disabled list. Optioned INF Alfonso Soriano to Columbus of the International League.  OAKLAND ATHLETICS -- Placed LHP Mike Magnante on the 15-day disabled list. Optioned RHP Luis Vizcaino to Sacramento of the PCL. Recalled INF Adam Piatt and selected the contract of RHP Scott Service from Sacramento.  TAMPA BAY DEVIL RAYS -- Placed OF Jose Canseco on the 15-day disabled list, retroactive to May 25. Recalled OF Randy Winn from Durham of the International League. Optioned OF Quinton McCracken to Durham. Moved LHP Wilson Alvarez from the 15- to the 60-day disabled list.  TEXAS RANGERS -- Activated OF Rusty Greer from the 15-day disabled list. Optioned RHP Danny Kolb to Oklahoma of the PCL.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
        <p>American League  BOSTON RED SOX -- Activated SS Nomar Garciaparra from the 15-day disabled list. Placed INF Jose Offerman on the 15-day disabled list, retroactive to May 25.  CLEVELAND INDIANS -- Placed RHP Paul Rigdon on the 15-day disabled list, retroactive to May 22. Activated RHP Jaret Wright from the disabled list.  NEW YORK YANKEES -- Activated SS Derek Jeter from the 15-day disabled list. Optioned INF Alfonso Soriano to Columbus of the International League.  OAKLAND ATHLETICS -- Placed LHP Mike Magnante on the 15-day disabled list. Optioned RHP Luis Vizcaino to Sacramento of the PCL. Recalled INF Adam Piatt and selected the contract of RHP Scott Service from Sacramento.  TAMPA BAY DEVIL RAYS -- Placed OF Jose Canseco on the 15-day disabled list, retroactive to May 25. Recalled OF Randy Winn from Durham of the International League. Optioned OF Quinton McCracken to Durham. Moved LHP Wilson Alvarez from the 15- to the 60-day disabled list.  TEXAS RANGERS -- Activated OF Rusty Greer from the 15-day disabled list. Optioned RHP Danny Kolb to Oklahoma of the PCL.</p>
        <p>National League  HOUSTON ASTROS -- Traded INF Russ Johnson to Tampa Bay for RHP Marc Valdes and assigned Valdes to New Orleans of the PCL. Recalled INF Julio Lugo from New Orleans. Placed RHP Mike Maddux on the 15-day disabled list. Purchased the contract of Valdes from New Orleans.  NEW YORK METS -- Recalled RHP Jim Mann from Norfolk of the International League. Optioned INF-OF Mark Johnson to Norfolk.  ST. LOUIS CARDINALS -- Activated LHP Scott Radinsky and RHP Matt Morris from the 15-day disabled list. Placed RHP Mike James on the 15-day disabled list, retroactive to May 26. Recalled RHP Alan Benes and LHP Mike Matthews from Memphis of the PCL. Designated LHP Mike Mohler and RHP Darren Holmes for assignment. Optioned LHP Jose Rodriguez to Memphis.</p>
        <p>BASKETBALL</p>
        <p>National Basketball Association  NBA -- Suspended Los Angeles Lakers G Brian Shaw one game and fined him $2,500 for leaving the bench area during an altercation in Friday's game.  DALLAS MAVERICKS -- Agreed to terms with Don Nelson, coach and general manager, on a six-year contract extension, the last three years as general manager only.</p>
        <p>Women's National Basketball Association  NEW YORK LIBERTY -- Traded G Carolyn Young to Portland for F Tari Phillips.  ORLANDO MIRACLE -- Released F Amber Hall and G Shawnetta Stewart.  SEATTLE STORM -- Traded their third-round 2001 draft pick to Houston for F-C Andrea Garner and Houston's third-round 2001 pick.</p>
        <p>SOCCER</p>
        <p>Major League Soccer  LOS ANGELES GALAXY -- Signed MF Ivan Polic.  COLLEGE  SAGINAW VALLEY STATE -- Named Angela Jackson women's basketball coach.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
