<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Market Place; Public Offerings From '99 Falter in 2000</title>
    <meta content="29PLAC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203312"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Norris, Floyd</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Market Place</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000529T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E3DD1F3DF93AA15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1349" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Market Place; Public Offerings From '99 Falter in 2000</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FLOYD NORRIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Norris, Floyd</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Floyd Norris Market Place column on change in market sentiment that has caused some of the strongest initial public offerings of 1999 to decline in 2000; graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On the list of 1999's best initial public offerings, Ditech Communications and FreeMarkets Inc. came close to being bookends. Both were among the best performers of last year, with Ditech's stock ending the year up 611 percent from its offering price and FreeMarkets' ending with a gain of 750 percent. Each could show rapidly growing sales over the previous two years.</p>
        <p>But that was then, and this is now. So far in 2000, their fates have diverged as much as any two stocks could. Ditech's share price is up nearly 90 percent this year, while FreeMarkets' is down by nearly the same amount.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On the list of 1999's best initial public offerings, Ditech Communications and FreeMarkets Inc. came close to being bookends. Both were among the best performers of last year, with Ditech's stock ending the year up 611 percent from its offering price and FreeMarkets' ending with a gain of 750 percent. Each could show rapidly growing sales over the previous two years.</p>
        <p>But that was then, and this is now. So far in 2000, their fates have diverged as much as any two stocks could. Ditech's share price is up nearly 90 percent this year, while FreeMarkets' is down by nearly the same amount.</p>
        <p>As it turns out, the companies and their stories were never very similar. Ditech, a maker of echo cancellation equipment for telephone companies, was profitable but uninteresting to many investors when it went public last June. It got off to a dull start, rising 14 percent the first day it traded, and even that modest lift was possible only because the company  placed its shares at the bottom of the price range it mentioned when it filed to go public.</p>
        <p>FreeMarkets, on the other hand, was a phenomenon. A business-to-business Internet auction company, it went public in December at the height of Internet speculation, when its losses did not faze investors. It sold shares for three times as much as it had sought when it first filed to go public, and found that even this was not nearly enough to meet the demand. The shares leaped 483 percent the first day of trading.</p>
        <p>So what has happened since the beginning of this year? Ditech has grown faster than anyone expected, and is in a business that has not worn out its welcome on Wall Street. Its share price is up 88 percent this year. It did, however, drop 5 percent on Friday, closing at $87.8125, despite posting quarterly results that were well in excess of published forecasts. That could be an indication that investors are beginning to look around for technology stocks where there are still profits to be taken, and taking them.</p>
        <p>As for FreeMarkets, it has reported growing sales, but the bloom is off the rose when it comes to money-losing Internet companies. Its stock price is down 89 percent in 2000, closing Friday at $37.25. Those who got in at the offering price in December, and held on, have seen a massive paper profit completely evaporate, and have lost 22 percent of their money. Anyone who bought on the first day is down 87 percent.</p>
        <p>Unfortunately, FreeMarkets is more representative of what has happened to last year's hot new offerings than is Ditech. Of the 50 best-performing new offerings of 1999, as calculated by CommScan, 46 have declined in 2000.</p>
        <p>That performance is a testimony to just how far stocks can fall when market sentiment changes. A few of the companies have plunged because their operations have not lived up to expectations. But the decline of many of the companies cannot be explained by their business performance -- any more than the original soaring prices could be explained.</p>
        <p>The performance of those stocks in 1999, from initial offering price through the end of the year, ranged from a gain of 2,723 percent for Internet Capital Group, the best performing offering, to 540 percent for Software.com, which ranked 50th. That so many new offerings went up so far was a testimony to just how hot the market was.</p>
        <p>Now, the market has cooled, and the air has come out of many of the stocks long before their results have shown whether or not last year's optimism was justified. The average performance of those 50 stocks is a loss of 52 percent. Since March 10, when the Nasdaq stock market peaked, the Nasdaq composite is down 37 percent, while the average performance of the once-hot 50 is a drop of 67 percent.</p>
        <p>Still, there are plenty of profits that have been made in the stocks. All but 15 of the stocks are trading higher than they did the day they went public, and only two -- FreeMarkets and Bluestone Software, a maker of software for Internet companies -- are trading below their original offering prices. A third, Ventro, trades for its original offering price.</p>
        <p>Ventro, which went public last July as Chemdex, an Internet seller of chemical equipment, renamed itself in March as it announced plans to broaden into other areas of business-to-business Internet service. It is down 92 percent since March 10, the worst performer over that period.</p>
        <p>Internet Capital, No. 1 in 1999, is down 85 percent so far in 2000, as the attraction of a company that owns stakes in many other Internet companies has faded. Even so, it is still trading at twice the price at which it ended the first day of trading, and for more than four times its original offering price.</p>
        <p>Internet Capital doubled the first day of trading, a performance that once would have seemed extraordinary, yet for much of last year was almost routine.</p>
        <p>But the stocks that had the biggest first-day gains have, in general, proved to be disappointments thereafter. Seven of the 50 stocks quadrupled on the first day of trading. Six of those seven are trading below where they ended that first day, with the only exception being Sycamore Networks, which markets optical networking products. It is still up 24 percent since that first day, but it is trading for less than half its peak price reached in early March.</p>
        <p>The other big movers the first day, all of which are trading for less than they fetched that day, are Ask Jeeves, an Internet search service; Akamai Technologies, an Internet content delivery service; Foundry Networks, an Internet switching service; Chinadotcom, an Internet company that provides Asian news and services to other Internet companies; VA Linux Systems, a distributor of software and computers using the Linux operating system, and FreeMarkets.</p>
        <p>There is one final measure of just how far some of the hottest issues have fallen. Brocade Communications is now up 2,111 percent from its offering price, making it the best performing of 1999's initial offerings to date. But it has plenty of unhappy shareholders. It is down 43 percent from its peak in March.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
