<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>High Hopes, Backed by Investments</title>
    <meta content="29SIMM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203362"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Bedford-Stuyvesant (NYC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pristin, Terry</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Simmons, Robert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greenwood, Monique</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pogue, Glenn</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000529T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400EFD71F3DF93AA15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="703" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>High Hopes, Backed by Investments</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TERRY PRISTIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pristin, Terry</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Black entrepreneurs Robert Simmons, Monique Greenwood and Glenn Pogue comment on opening businesses in Bedford-Stuyvesant, Brooklyn; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For many years, Robert Simmons would drive past a vacant lot near the eastern edge of Bedford-Stuyvesant and dream of opening a restaurant there. Subsidized homes were going up all around that area, but the people living in them had no place to go if they craved a sit-down meal.</p>
        <p>Now they do. In July, Mr. Simmons opened Choices, an immaculate plant-filled family-style restaurant at the corner of Fulton Street and Ralph Avenue. It has purple awnings, floor-to-ceiling windows, roomy booths, a menu offering ''soulful, West Indian, Caribbean and other cuisines,'' and long lines when Bedford-Stuyvesant's many church services end on Sundays.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For many years, Robert Simmons would drive past a vacant lot near the eastern edge of Bedford-Stuyvesant and dream of opening a restaurant there. Subsidized homes were going up all around that area, but the people living in them had no place to go if they craved a sit-down meal.</p>
        <p>Now they do. In July, Mr. Simmons opened Choices, an immaculate plant-filled family-style restaurant at the corner of Fulton Street and Ralph Avenue. It has purple awnings, floor-to-ceiling windows, roomy booths, a menu offering ''soulful, West Indian, Caribbean and other cuisines,'' and long lines when Bedford-Stuyvesant's many church services end on Sundays.</p>
        <p>And this is not the only new enterprise in the neighborhood displaying Mr. Simmons's signature purple awnings. He also owns the laundry next to the restaurant, a beauty parlor across the street and several businesses farther west on Fulton Street, including a health club, a billiards parlor, a smaller restaurant and a second laundry.</p>
        <p>Altogether, Mr. Simmons says, he's plowed $3 million of his own money into Bedford-Stuyvesant, the proceeds from selling seven McDonald's franchises, two of them in the neighborhood.</p>
        <p>Mr. Simmons, 52, was raised in St. Louis and worked for McDonald's for seven years before the company asked him to move to New York in 1988 to take over a franchise at Fulton Street and Throop Avenue. McDonald's arranged the financing that enabled him to get started.</p>
        <p>Ultimately, Mr. Simmons said, he felt the need to strike out on his own. ''I wanted to see if I could use my talents somewhere else,'' he said. ''I no longer wanted to be boxed in to limited menu items or pricing structure -- the corporate thing.''</p>
        <p>Kathryn Wylde, the chief executive of the New York City Investment Fund, a private company that seeks to stimulate job growth, describes Mr. Simmons as a ''pit bull personified.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Wylde helped Mr. Simmons get space for his Choices restaurant in a new strip mall developed under the Anchor program, a joint venture between the city and the New York City Partnership, a major civic group, that was financed by Chase Manhattan Bank.</p>
        <p>''He saw the diversity of the market needs in his own community,'' Ms. Wylde said. ''He has the focus and ability to execute that has allowed him to deliver businesses to meet those needs in very creative ways.''</p>
        <p>As an African-American, Mr. Simmons belongs to a group that is vastly underrepresented among business owners in New York. In a survey conducted two years ago, the New York City Investment Fund found that blacks owned only 2.9 percent of the businesses in the city with employees, even though they make up about 25 percent of the population. (Asians, by contrast, constitute about 7 percent of the population and own 7 percent of the businesses with employees.)</p>
        <p>But Mr. Simmons is not the only entrepreneur with high hopes for Bedford-Stuyvesant. For five years, Monique Greenwood, the editor in chief of Essence magazine, and her husband, Glenn Pogue, a freelance broadcast engineer, have operated a bed-and-breakfast, the Akwaaba Mansion, on McDonough Street.</p>
        <p>In 1998, they opened a restaurant, the Akwaaba Cafe, around the corner on Lewis Street. Since then, they have acquired all the properties adjacent to the cafe. They plan to operate a coffee lounge in one of the spaces. Their tenants will include Bedford-Stuyvesant's first bookstore and an antiques shop.</p>
        <p>''We hope that we're providing the inspiration for other people to invest in businesses here,'' said Ms. Greenwood, who has lived in Bedford-Stuyvesant for a decade. ''We have incredible homes, but we don't have the kinds of services that other people in other communities take for granted.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
