<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Devil Rays' Struggles Continue</title>
    <meta content="AM27" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203298"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="AMERICAN LEAGUE: ROUNDUP"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Tampa Bay Devil Rays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Tampa Bay Rays</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000529T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E3DE1F3DF93AA15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="670" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Devil Rays' Struggles Continue</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By The Associated Press</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>John Olerud's two-run single snapped a fifth-inning tie yesterday and the Seattle Mariners went on to a 6-3 victory over the struggling Tampa Bay Devil Rays, who have lost 11 of their last 13 games.</p>
        <p>Brett Tomko (3-2) allowed three hits in five-plus innings, and the visiting Mariners got two run-scoring singles from Mark McLemore to win for the second straight time after beginning a six-game road trip with three losses at Baltimore.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>John Olerud's two-run single snapped a fifth-inning tie yesterday and the Seattle Mariners went on to a 6-3 victory over the struggling Tampa Bay Devil Rays, who have lost 11 of their last 13 games.</p>
        <p>Brett Tomko (3-2) allowed three hits in five-plus innings, and the visiting Mariners got two run-scoring singles from Mark McLemore to win for the second straight time after beginning a six-game road trip with three losses at Baltimore.</p>
        <p>Kazuhiro Sasaki pitched the ninth for his sixth save in seven opportunities. Five Seattle pitchers combined on the four-hitter.</p>
        <p>Tampa Bay (15-32) has dropped eight series in a row and has the worst record in the major leagues.</p>
        <p>TIGERS 4, BLUE JAYS 3: Deivi Cruz stroked a run-scoring single in the ninth inning to lift host Detroit.</p>
        <p>Doug Brocail (2-3) pitched the last one and two-thirds innings for the victory, holding the Blue Jays hitless after relieving Hideo Nomo.</p>
        <p>Paul Quantrill (0-2) walked Brad Ausmus to start the Tigers' ninth. Ausmus moved up on a sacrifice bunt by Jose Macias and scored on Cruz's single to right.</p>
        <p>Dean Palmer hit a two-run homer for Detroit.</p>
        <p>TWINS 10, RANGERS 5: Corey Koskie hit a bases-loaded triple, and Butch Huskey added a two-run double for host Minnesota, which lost all 12 games to Texas last season but has won four of the five games played between the two teams this year.</p>
        <p>Joe Mays (2-6) won for the first time since May 3, and Midre Cummings and Cristian Guzman homered for Minnesota, which picked up its 12th comeback victory of the season.</p>
        <p>Ruben Mateo hit a two-run homer and David Segui had three runs batted in for the Rangers, who fell to 2-3 on their current nine-game road trip.</p>
        <p>WHITE SOX 14, INDIANS 3: Jose Valentin drove in a career-high six runs for host Chicago and fell a single shy of becoming the first American League player to hit for the cycle twice in one season.</p>
        <p>Valentin hit a two-run homer in the first inning, a bases-loaded triple in the second and an R.B.I. double in the third.</p>
        <p>The White Sox, who led by 14-0 after seven innings, opened a two-and-a-half-game lead over the Indians in the A.L. Central. Cleveland lost for the fourth time in five games.</p>
        <p>Carlos Lee homered and drove in three runs, Frank Thomas hit two R.B.I. doubles and Magglio Ordonez drove in two runs with two singles for Chicago.</p>
        <p>ATHLETICS 4, ORIOLES 0: Tim Hudson allowed one hit over seven and one-third innings for his fifth straight victory as Oakland ended host Baltimore's four-game winning streak.</p>
        <p>The lone hit off Hudson was a fifth-inning single by Will Clark. The sinking liner to center popped out of the glove of a diving Terrence Long.</p>
        <p>Hudson (6-2) walked four and struck out five. He was lifted after issuing a one-out walk to Greg Myers in the eighth.</p>
        <p>Hudson allowed only two balls out of the infield and permitted only one runner past second base in improving to 5-0 over his last six starts.</p>
        <p>ROYALS 6, ANGELS 5: Dave McCarty hit a game-tying, two-run homer in the ninth inning, and Carlos Beltran scored the winning run in the 10th on a sacrifice fly just past first base as Kansas City beat host Anaheim.</p>
        <p>The Royals, who rallied from a 5-3 deficit in the ninth against Troy Percival, won for the 12th time this season in their final at-bat.</p>
        <p>Dan Reichert (3-3) pitched two hitless innings for the victory.</p>
        <p>Percival, who leads the A.L. with 14 saves, blew his third chance of the season in the ninth.</p>
        <p>AMERICAN LEAGUE: ROUNDUP</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
