<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Taiwan Leader Goes Nameless in China</title>
    <meta content="Y29BEI$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203385"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Censorship</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Taiwan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chang Huei-mei</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chen Shui-Bian (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rosenthal, Elisabeth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Taiwan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Taiwan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Censorship</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000529T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E5DF163CF93AA15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="918" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Taiwan Leader Goes Nameless in China</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELISABETH ROSENTHAL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rosenthal, Elisabeth</byline>
      <dateline>BEIJING, May 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Chinese state press has been filled with reporting about Taiwan and its new government since March, but is not alloed to mention name of Pres Chen Shui-bian; authorities avoid any concrete evidence of Taiwan's boisterous election or of Chen's euphoric inauguration; photo of Taiwanese pop star Chang Huei-mei, who joined banned list after she sang at inauguration (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the best-selling children's series Harry Potter, there is a character so disturbing that Harry's friends refer to him only as ''He Who Must Not Be Named'' -- as if mouthing the name Voldemort would somehow solidify the demon's existence.</p>
        <p>President Chen Shui-bian of Taiwan is clearly China's Voldemort.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the best-selling children's series Harry Potter, there is a character so disturbing that Harry's friends refer to him only as ''He Who Must Not Be Named'' -- as if mouthing the name Voldemort would somehow solidify the demon's existence.</p>
        <p>President Chen Shui-bian of Taiwan is clearly China's Voldemort.</p>
        <p>Since his election in March, China's state press has been filled with reporting about Taiwan and its new government. The papers have parsed the new president's every sentence and micro-analyzed his administration's intentions.</p>
        <p>But in this daily cascade of print, there are several words that have  never appeared in major Chinese media outlets, forbidden by government order: ''Chen Shui-bian,'' the new leader's name. And the word ''president.''</p>
        <p>Instead, reporters and editorial writers have had to fall back on a handful of approved circumlocutions, all devised to dance around the fact that the man they call, for example, ''the new leader of the Taiwan authority'' was, after all, recently elected the island's president.</p>
        <p>''No media outlets are allowed to use his name, at all,'' said a Beijing journalist. ''And even though so many articles are written about Taiwan, we can't write what we like. Papers are only allowed to print what the central government has agreed upon.''</p>
        <p>Of course, words in the Chinese press are carefully chosen -- or omitted -- and carry political messages. Discussions of sensitive subjects routinely involve a state-sanctioned vocabulary and punctuation. And few topics are more sensitive than Taiwan, which Beijing regards as a breakaway province that must, by force if necessary, eventually be reunited with the mainland.</p>
        <p>And so ''Taiwanese independence,'' for example, always appears in quotation marks, a political ''(sic),'' indicating that the author recognizes the error, even absurdity, of the phrase. The election of Mr. Chen, whose Democratic Progressive Party has in the past supported independence, has caused particular consternation.</p>
        <p>But even many Chinese journalists are perplexed at the decision not to use Mr. Chen's name.</p>
        <p>''I can see why they wouldn't want to use the term 'president,' since we don't recognize Taiwan as a country,'' said a Chinese reporter. ''But not to use his name? Everybody here knows about him.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, the Chinese government seems to want to eliminate any concrete evidence of Taiwan's boisterous election or of Mr. Chen's euphoric inauguration earlier this month.</p>
        <p>State television carried no images of the events. And, although Mr. Chen's inauguration speech was carefully dissected in every major Chinese newspaper, none have actually carried the text. Within hours, however, copies were circulating on the Internet.</p>
        <p>Chang Huei-mei, a Taiwanese pop star also known as A-mei who is wildly popular here, followed Mr. Chen into the realm of the unmentionable after she sang at his swearing-in ceremony. From that day, China's state media were told they could no longer run her advertisements for Sprite soft drinks. Mr. Chen's name has appeared in the major state media only once since he announced his candidacy last fall. On March 18, his election day, the state-run New China News Agency issued a two-sentence report: ''This evening the electoral activities for the leadership of the Taiwan region concluded. The D.P.P. candidate Chen Shui-bian won 39.3 percent, the independent candidate James Soong won 36.84 percent, and the KMT candidate Lien Chan won 23.1 percent.''</p>
        <p>The press here refers to other Taiwan politicians directly and frequently, including the former president, Lee Teng-hui, and Mr. Chen's vice president, Lu Hsiu-lien -- though invariably to heap scorn and criticism on them. (The Beijing press referred to Mr. Lee, during his tenure, as the ''so-called president.'')</p>
        <p>Ms. Lu has been as outspoken in her support of Taiwanese independence as Mr. Chen has been circumspect on this issue. At a recent briefing for foreign journalists, a Chinese official gave the following explanation for not using Mr. Chen's name:</p>
        <p>''Lee Teng-hui and Lu Hsiu-lien are diehard separatists and incurable in this regard, so we name them,'' he said. But as for Mr. Chen, ''We will heed his word and his acts, so we try to distinguish him from the others.''</p>
        <p>A former official of the Communist Party's Propaganda Department explained that the decision made a certain sense in terms of the norms of propaganda, and keeping options open as relations with Taiwan's new leadership evolve.</p>
        <p>''Chen is the elected leader and China must deal with him,'' he said.  ''When the government is conducting a propaganda offensive, if it names the target, then the target has entered a 'blacklist' and it's nearly impossible to back off the condemnation. So by keeping Chen's name out of it -- it seems silly and childish -- but it's a way of keeping room for maneuver.''</p>
        <p>Some journalists suggest that Chinese authorities forbid the use of Mr. Chen's name because they cannot decide what honorific to apply. ''Mr. Chen -- that sounds too polite,'' said one journalist. ''And of course, President Chen is out of the question. So what we've arrived at for now is to just call him 'the new leader of the region of Taiwan.' ''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
