<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Metropolitan Diary</title>
    <meta content="29DIAR$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203339"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Metropolitan Diary</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000529T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06EEDB1F3DF93AA15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1133" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Metropolitan Diary</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Enid Nemy</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DEAR DIARY:</p>
        <p>David Merrick's death reminded me of an event I've always considered a small part of American theater history. Around 1968, I worked for a company that supplied equipment and personnel for a television show that visited famous people, and Mr. Merrick was one of the subjects. The taping took place in his office above the St. James Theater. I supervised the setup and  stayed when the interview was over to make sure things were in order.</p>
        <p>Mr. Merrick eventually came out the stage door and stood, waiting for his car. ''Hello, Dolly!'' was then in its umpteenth year at the theater, and people going to the matinee were streaming by and talking about how wonderful they expected the show to be. I finally went over to Mr. Merrick and said: ''You know, all these people are going by talking about the show and they have no idea you're the one responsible. It reminds me of the final scene in '42nd Street.' '' He replied, coolly, ''I've never seen it.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DEAR DIARY:</p>
        <p>David Merrick's death reminded me of an event I've always considered a small part of American theater history. Around 1968, I worked for a company that supplied equipment and personnel for a television show that visited famous people, and Mr. Merrick was one of the subjects. The taping took place in his office above the St. James Theater. I supervised the setup and  stayed when the interview was over to make sure things were in order.</p>
        <p>Mr. Merrick eventually came out the stage door and stood, waiting for his car. ''Hello, Dolly!'' was then in its umpteenth year at the theater, and people going to the matinee were streaming by and talking about how wonderful they expected the show to be. I finally went over to Mr. Merrick and said: ''You know, all these people are going by talking about the show and they have no idea you're the one responsible. It reminds me of the final scene in '42nd Street.' '' He replied, coolly, ''I've never seen it.''</p>
        <p>Not knowing to take a hint, I launched into a description of the movie, finishing with the shot of Warner Baxter sitting near the stage door, unrecognized and ignored, while the audience passes by raving about the show he was responsible for.</p>
        <p>Mr. Merrick listened and then said: ''I never see anything made before 1950. It makes me feel old.'' I backed off -- but I never doubted that I had placed the seed for what was to become one of his major musicals.</p>
        <p>TONY MARSHALL</p>
        <p>This takes some thinking. The young woman's voice, obviously directed at a companion, drifted into the window of George Capsis's Charles Street apartment: ''Everything I hate about New York, I love about L.A., and everything I hate about L.A., I love about New York.''</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>Riding home from a downtown orchestra rehearsal on a No. 6 subway train, I watched a lithe young man showing off for his girlfriend and other chums. He casually placed his palms on the floor, then kicked off and stood on his hands -- legs straight up and motionless -- for about a minute, as the train waited in the station. He then swiveled his still upside-down body so that he was facing in the direction the train would move. When it did accelerate, he started walking on his hands in the opposite direction.</p>
        <p>For an encore, he grasped two vertical poles, kicked off until his shoes were flat against the ceiling of the car and maintained that position for about 30 seconds. He looked like a statue. ''Mankind was not meant to do such things,'' I said as the performance ended. I've never seen better, even in a circus.</p>
        <p>DAVID SPIELBERG</p>
        <p>Monica Sands was on a 79th Street crosstown bus recently when the driver added some much-needed comic relief during the crowded rush hour. ''We're coming to Central Park West,'' he announced. ''Transfer to the M10 bus and the B and C subways -- that's B as in basket and C as in case.''</p>
        <p>PHILOSOPHER CATS' ODE TO THE HUMAN HAND</p>
        <p>The human hand is a wonderful thing,</p>
        <p>With or without a wedding ring.</p>
        <p>The human hand can stroke a cat,</p>
        <p>The human hand knows where it's at.</p>
        <p>The human hand can scratch a chin,</p>
        <p>The human hand is really in.</p>
        <p>The human hand can scratch a neck,</p>
        <p>We'll find a rhyme, we will, by heck.</p>
        <p>The human hand can scratch a rump,</p>
        <p>And leave the fur in a funny lump.</p>
        <p>The human hand can break a fast,</p>
        <p>Here comes supper at long, long last.</p>
        <p>The human hand can brush us well,</p>
        <p>The joy of that is hard to tell.</p>
        <p>The human hand can make our beds,</p>
        <p>When we have to rest our sleepy heads.</p>
        <p>And now before we decide to part,</p>
        <p>May we say ''thank you'' to the human heart?</p>
        <p>NATALIE SILVERMAN</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>Palm Pilot users are becoming as ubiquitous on subways as people who use cell phones above ground -- and I am one of them. I ignore the unwritten prohibition on conversing with other anonymous riders. I beam (wirelessly transmit) a joke of the day and best wishes to other similarly equipped passengers as they sit across from me planning their busy schedules, working on expense reports or just playing solitaire on their electronic  organizers.</p>
        <p>The surprised recipient of the message usually looks up and, with a wide grin, acknowledges membership in our high-tech club. We leave the train feeling cheerfully connected.</p>
        <p>I only hope that someone doesn't figure out a way to beam us advertising!</p>
        <p>BRIAN KELLMAN</p>
        <p>Jean Handley and two friends had just had a lovely day -- an afternoon at the Metropolitan Opera and a good dinner with wine and impeccable service. Leaving the restaurant on West 54th Street where they had dined, they looked up and saw a full moon rising above the city.</p>
        <p>The magic wasn't yet over. Walking past the University Club, they stopped to admire a magnificent urn of white tulips being loaded into a van. The driver noticed them, paused in his work, reached into the van and handed each of the women a nosegay of daffodils. ''If we doubted it for a moment, we knew then that we were in Manhattan and spring was in the air,'' Ms. Handley said.</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>The doormen in our apartment building perform many acts of assistance for the residents, but the other day I witnessed the ultimate. As I entered the lobby, one of our doormen was trying to fit an earring into the pierced ear of a well-dressed white-haired resident.</p>
        <p>MARIE CONNORS</p>
        <p>Andrea Schechter likes the line used by an acquaintance who told her husband, ''I'm going out for some retail therapy.''</p>
        <p>COMMENCEMENT</p>
        <p>You gather on the Quad at Queens,</p>
        <p>at Hunter and St. John's.</p>
        <p>And in a final burst of childhood,</p>
        <p>you toss your cap,</p>
        <p>like a square black Frisbee,</p>
        <p>into the clear spring sky.</p>
        <p>Onward, onward, it spins,</p>
        <p>reaching out,</p>
        <p>to touch your hopes,</p>
        <p>take a peek at your dreams.</p>
        <p>Then gently it floats down.</p>
        <p>Now your future begins.</p>
        <p>MICKI DOLAN</p>
        <p>Phyllis Levenson's 7-year-old grandson, Fred, introduced a visiting playmate to his grandmother. After the introduction, the two boys walked away and Mrs. Levenson heard Fred say to his friend, ''Well, how do you like her so far?''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
