<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For the hungry, gadget-loving motorist, a microwave oven in the glove compartment.</title>
    <meta content="29PATE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203317"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PATENTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Milk</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cereals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Microwave Ovens</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Inventions and Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fast Food Industry</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Katims, Jane</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perlman, Daniel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Walker, Jay (Priceline.com)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lim, Walter K</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Krause, Arthur A</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Innovation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Columns/Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fast Food Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Home Appliances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dairy Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Inventions and Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000529T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E1DD1F3DF93AA15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1094" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For the hungry, gadget-loving motorist, a microwave oven in the glove compartment.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Sabra Chartrand</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Daniel Perlman and Jane Katims patent microwave oven built into the area now used for glove compartments in most cars; Jay Walker, founder of Priceline.com, and two co-inventors patent system of offering fast-food diners a choice of fresh food or food that is a few minutes old, the point being to reduce waste; Arthur A Krause and Walter K Lim patent a breakfast cereal coated with powdered milk to which water can be added on camping trips or wherever there is no refrigeration for milk (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ANYONE planning a road trip this summer might be interested in recent inventions for eating on the go. A long trip with children in the car, for example, could be eased by a video monitor attached to the back of the driver's seat -- or perhaps a dashboard microwave.</p>
        <p>Daniel Perlman and Jane Katims, both of Arlington, Mass. have won a patent for a microwave oven built into the area now used for glove compartments in most cars that would be big enough to hold a coffee cup or a fast-food container. A hinged door opens downward like traditional glove compartment doors, creating a shelf for holding containers or cups, and for serving food. An additional cup holder would slide into the microwave cavity, to prevent beverages placed inside the oven from tipping and spilling.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ANYONE planning a road trip this summer might be interested in recent inventions for eating on the go. A long trip with children in the car, for example, could be eased by a video monitor attached to the back of the driver's seat -- or perhaps a dashboard microwave.</p>
        <p>Daniel Perlman and Jane Katims, both of Arlington, Mass. have won a patent for a microwave oven built into the area now used for glove compartments in most cars that would be big enough to hold a coffee cup or a fast-food container. A hinged door opens downward like traditional glove compartment doors, creating a shelf for holding containers or cups, and for serving food. An additional cup holder would slide into the microwave cavity, to prevent beverages placed inside the oven from tipping and spilling.</p>
        <p>The inventors say they decided to replace the glove compartment with a microwave because ''many items which were formerly stored in the dashboard area, in particular, the dashboard glove compartment, are now stored in new more accessible door pockets, seat pockets and a centrally located storage console located between the two front seats.''</p>
        <p>The microwave would draw power from the car's battery or alternator, and the inventors write in their patent that ''a high voltage transformer and the power inverter can be placed behind the engine firewall.''</p>
        <p>People who still need the glove compartment for gloves, maps and other papers could store them in a container designed to fit inside the microwave. When someone wanted to use the microwave, the container and the objects it held could be removed. The microwave would only work when the insert is pulled out.</p>
        <p>The inventors suggest several other safety features, from blocking the oven from working at all when the car is in motion, to allowing it to operate but preventing the door from opening until the car is stopped, to keeping the oven from operating during acceleration, braking or sharp turns. When the oven door is opened, the patent application says, an alarm will warn the driver ''to avoid any sudden start-up acceleration of the vehicle which could result in a food spill.''</p>
        <p>The inventors added recessed areas to the inside of the microwave and its door so any spilled liquid or food would collect there. Controls for the microwave, including a timer, power setting and on-off switch, would be placed on the dashboard within reach of either a driver or front seat passenger.</p>
        <p>The inventors won patent 6,060,700.</p>
        <p>New Choices For Fast Food</p>
        <p>Travelers who prefer fast-food restaurants could soon face new choices at the cash register. Jay Walker, the founder of Priceline .com, and two other inventors, Andrew Van Luchene and Joshua Rogers, have won a patent for a system of offering fast-food diners a choice of fresh food or food that is a few minutes old. The point is to reduce waste in restaurants where food is prepared in advance.</p>
        <p>With the patented system, restaurants would use a microprocessor to record the time foods like hamburgers and french fries are prepared, and to track how long the food sits in food warmers before being sold.</p>
        <p>Then, when a customer orders a plain hamburger, for example, the system would know what similar foods are available that were prepared earlier than the burger. If cheeseburgers or chicken sandwiches were prepared before the hamburgers, the system would know that those foods were already headed toward the end of their shelf life. It would offer to substitute one of them, either at no additional charge or for a discounted price -- say, a smaller surcharge for a more expensive order or the amount of change due the customer if it were less than the full price of the food.</p>
        <p>The customer might be offered a cheeseburger instead of the hamburger, for example, or a double cheeseburger instead of a regular one. Thus, the restaurant would sell a double cheeseburger at a reduced price that it otherwise might eventually have to throw away, and the customer would get a deal on his meal.</p>
        <p>The inventors believe that as the burgers under the heat lamps age, their value decreases and they can be substituted for cheaper menu items. For example, the customer's original order for a plain hamburger might be replaced with a cheeseburger that is 6 or 7 minutes old, or with a double cheeseburger that is 10 or 12 minutes old.</p>
        <p>Fast-food restaurants do not regularly announce that they prepare some food minutes before it is sold, and this system would draw more attention to that practice.</p>
        <p>Suggestions for replacement orders would be drawn from categories set up in a database that tracks the turnover of food. Any food ordered from one category, such as chicken, might be replaced with another menu item from that same category, the inventors say. The offer for such substitutions could either appear on a monitor at the cash register, or be explained to the customer by a cashier.</p>
        <p>Mr. Walker, Mr. Van Luchene and Mr. Rogers won patent 6,052,667.</p>
        <p>How About Cereal With Its Own Milk</p>
        <p>Breakfast on the road, at a camp site or in a hotel room often means breakfast far from a refrigerator. Those who still want a bowl of cereal might soon choose a brand that comes with its own milk. Many breakfast cereals are coated with sweeteners, flavorings and colorings, but two inventors say none has thought to coat cereal with powdered milk.</p>
        <p>''And so, Arthur A. Krause and Walter K. Lim, men of great genius apt to invent and discover ingenious things, come now with an invention they have discovered,'' the two men from California write in their own patent application. ''By applying a special coating onto the surface of cereal pieces, a food product is created where one may just add water to the product and the result is a delicious cereal and milk combination.''</p>
        <p>Nonfat dry milk powder is bound to cereal either by slightly rehydrating the dried milk so it becomes sticky, by misting the cereal so the powdered milk sticks to the surface, or by coating the cereal first with sugar or a sugar substitute. Later, a hungry traveler has only to add water and watch as ''the milk coating dissolves and separates from the cereal and combines with the added water.''</p>
        <p>The inventors say cereal coated with dry milk can be packaged and transported without any special storage measures. They received patent 6,051,262.</p>
        <p>PATENTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
