<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Embarrassed Suitor: Gore's Courtship of Big Labor Grows Less Ardent</title>
    <meta content="Y24GORE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201970"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE CHINA TRADE WRANGLE: VICE PRESIDENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">China-International Relations-US</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Organized Labor</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Pittsburgh (Pa)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">American Federation of Labor-Congress of Industrial Organizations</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Automobile Workers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Seelye, Katharine Q</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sweeney, John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yokich, Stephen P</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Pennsylvania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Pennsylvania/Pittsburgh</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Organized Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000524T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E4D7163DF937A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1009" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Embarrassed Suitor: Gore's Courtship of Big Labor Grows Less Ardent</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHARINE Q. SEELYE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Seelye, Katharine Q</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 23</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vice Pres Al Gore's support for China trade bill opposed by labor groups that back him has been ambivalent, even as he hopes to show he is not beholden to labor and will break with important constituency over principle; he cites disagreement with labor's stance at convention, Pittsburgh, of union once headed by AFL-CIO president John Sweeney, who has essentially given him pass on bill; Stephen P Yokich, United Auto Workers head, scores Gore's lobbying for bill (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On the eve of the China trade vote, while the Clinton Administration was still nailing down support for the bill's passage, Vice President Al Gore flew off to Pittsburgh. The Steel City, one of the nation's last redoubts of big labor, was host to a conference of the service employees union, the home base of the president of the A.F.L.-C.I.O., which has devoted itself to killing the legislation.</p>
        <p>Heading for union turf at such a juncture is one more sign of Mr. Gore's ambivalence, if not toward the bill, then toward his public association with the bill.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On the eve of the China trade vote, while the Clinton Administration was still nailing down support for the bill's passage, Vice President Al Gore flew off to Pittsburgh. The Steel City, one of the nation's last redoubts of big labor, was host to a conference of the service employees union, the home base of the president of the A.F.L.-C.I.O., which has devoted itself to killing the legislation.</p>
        <p>Heading for union turf at such a juncture is one more sign of Mr. Gore's ambivalence, if not toward the bill, then toward his public association with the bill.</p>
        <p>Even as the administration is trying to round up last-minute votes, the vice president was engaged with labor out of town rather than working against it on Capitol Hill.</p>
        <p>''Which side is the vice president on?'' Representative Charles B. Rangel, the New York Democrat, said in an interview. ''He doesn't want to offend anybody.'' Mr. Rangel said that Mr. Gore had called him about the bill but that he was already supporting it and that there was not much point to the conversation.</p>
        <p>The service workers' union and its former chief, John Sweeney, who is now president of the A.F.L.-C.I.O., have essentially given Mr. Gore a pass on the China bill, but not everyone in the labor movement is feeling so generous.</p>
        <p>The president of the United Auto Workers today offered one of the most blistering assessments of Mr. Gore's actions on behalf of the bill. Mr. Gore has been two-faced, the union president said, and is driving the auto workers into the arms of one of the auto industry's enduring nemesis, Ralph Nader, who is also running for president.</p>
        <p>''He has tried to have it both ways on China,'' an outraged Stephen P. Yokich, president of the 1.3-million-strong auto workers union, said of Mr. Gore in a statement today.</p>
        <p>''One moment, presidential candidate Gore is telling the labor movement that he believes human rights, workers' rights, and environmental protections should be included in core trade agreements; the next, Vice President Gore is holding hands with the profiteers of the world and singing the praises'' of the trade agreement and ''lobbying'' for it.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore, speaking to reporters in Pittsburgh, brushed aside the attack, saying the election was a long time away and that he would not entertain hypothetical questions.</p>
        <p>Still, criticism from a putative ally goes a long way toward explaining Mr. Gore's reluctance to take a more visible role in promoting the trade agreement. The Gore campaign has hoped that the vice president could use the issue to convey that he is not beholden to labor and that he is willing to break with an important constituency over principle.</p>
        <p>''I just want to tell you forthrightly I don't share your views on this particular issue,'' Mr. Gore said to several thousand service workers today.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore has said numerous times that he supports the trade agreement, and he took part in a White House pep rally to advance it. He also has said that he has called members of Congress to lobby on behalf of the bill.</p>
        <p>But as he runs with labor's endorsement and seeks to energize union workers behind his candidacy, the degree of Mr. Gore's support has been questioned.</p>
        <p>He caused consternation at the White House in February after labor leaders said he had indicated that he would negotiate a tougher pact than Mr. Clinton negotiated. Administration officials were worried that Mr. Gore's stance could give political cover to Democrats who opposed the bill. Mr. Gore then wrote to the nation's chief business lobbying group, the National Association of Manufacturers, to reassure it of his support.</p>
        <p>Congressional Democrats who oppose the measure said that many among their number had no sign that the vice president was actively working for passage. And one business lobbyist, who did not want to be identified, put it this way: ''The vice president's enthusiasm has been spectacularly underwhelming.''</p>
        <p>Unlike Gov. George W. Bush of Texas, Mr. Gore's Republican rival for the presidency, Mr. Gore has not devoted a speech to the single topic of the China bill. When Mr. Bush addressed it last week at a Boeing factory in Everett, Washington, his impassioned remarks gave the appearance that he was more closely allied with President Clinton on this matter than Mr. Gore.</p>
        <p>Today, Mr. Bush met with Republicans privately on Capitol Hill and reiterated his support for the bill. Members said afterward that he asked those who plan to vote against it to reconsider their vote.</p>
        <p>It is not clear whether Mr. Gore's lower-key approach will advance either his beliefs in economic globalization or his political aspirations.</p>
        <p>Stephen P. Hess, a presidential scholar at the Brookings Institution, a liberal research organization, said that Mr. Gore's blurry approach raised legitimate questions. But he also suggested that Mr. Gore's posture over the bill has reinforced an impression that the vice president is overly cautious and calculating. ''You feel that Gore really is an internationalist, but for heaven's sake, why doesn't he come out and say it?'' Mr. Hess said. ''Everything has become so calculated.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton, too, has shown some calculation. He had planned a national television address Sunday night on the trade bill, one of his most important foreign policy objectives. But he canceled it when it was clear that the bill was dividing Democrats and would have raised the awkward specter of Representative Richard A. Gephardt, the Democratic leader from Missouri, who opposes the bill, giving the official response to the president of his own party.</p>
        <p>Democrats say the unions have riven the party, in part by running commercials against some members who oppose the bill while they have essentially given Mr. Gore the kid-glove treatment.</p>
        <p>''A lot of people are concerned just how committed the unions are to hurting members of Congress and how they use a different standard for the vice president,'' Mr. Rangel said. ''We don't want them to be cruel to the vice president, but we're running for re-election too.''</p>
        <p>THE CHINA TRADE WRANGLE: VICE PRESIDENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
