<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Common Heart and Uncommon Brain</title>
    <meta content="24PROO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201918"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Manhattan Theater Club</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Auburn, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weber, Bruce</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sullivan, Daniel</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Proof (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000524T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E4DE163DF937A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1219" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Common Heart and Uncommon Brain</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRUCE WEBER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Weber, Bruce</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bruce Weber reviews Proof, David Auburn play being presented at Manhattan Theater Club under direction of Daniel Sullivan; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Have you noticed how many well-educated characters are holding forth on New York stages?</p>
        <p>The physicists of ''Copenhagen,'' the accomplished playwright of ''The Real Thing,'' the literati of ''The Designated Mourner'' -- all are challenging, and charming, audiences with the force of intellect. Lyman Felt, the self-justifying bigamist of ''The Ride Down Mount Morgan,'' makes his case with the well-reasoned eloquence of a philosopher, and even in a romantic comedy like ''Dirty Blonde,'' the lead male character is a film historian. Forrest Gumpism may still be alive in the land, but one thing this spate of excellent plays reminds us is that learning is desirable, not least because it enriches the emotions. In case you've forgotten, intellectuals are people too.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Have you noticed how many well-educated characters are holding forth on New York stages?</p>
        <p>The physicists of ''Copenhagen,'' the accomplished playwright of ''The Real Thing,'' the literati of ''The Designated Mourner'' -- all are challenging, and charming, audiences with the force of intellect. Lyman Felt, the self-justifying bigamist of ''The Ride Down Mount Morgan,'' makes his case with the well-reasoned eloquence of a philosopher, and even in a romantic comedy like ''Dirty Blonde,'' the lead male character is a film historian. Forrest Gumpism may still be alive in the land, but one thing this spate of excellent plays reminds us is that learning is desirable, not least because it enriches the emotions. In case you've forgotten, intellectuals are people too.</p>
        <p>Happily, this trend is being perpetuated with ''Proof,'' an exhilarating and assured new play by David Auburn that turns the esoteric world of higher mathematics literally into a back porch drama, one that is as accessible and compelling as a detective story. The play, which opened yesterday at the Manhattan Theater Club, is fundamentally a mystery about the authorship of a particularly important proof, a mystery that is solved in the end; it is also, however, about the unravelable enigma of genius, and the toll it can take on those who are beset with it, aspire to it or merely live in its vicinity.</p>
        <p>In that service, the play takes great pains to depict the study of mathematics as a painful joy, not as the geek-making obsession of stereotype, but as human labor, both ennobling and humbling, by people who, like musicians or painters (or playwrights), can envision an elusive beauty in the universe and are therefore both enlivened by its pursuit and daunted by the commitment. It does this not by showing them at work but by showing them trying to live and cope when they can't, won't or simply aren't, and in so doing makes the argument that mathematics is a business for the common heart as well as the uncommon brain.</p>
        <p>As directed by Daniel Sullivan and performed by an exemplary cast, ''Proof'' has the pace of a psychological thriller, and if its resolution (''lumpy'' rather than elegant, to use a word that one character uses to describe the titular proof) tilts toward the sentimental, the characters deserve to be hopeful. As one woman exiting the theater ahead of me said to her companion, ''It's like 'Copenhagen' with a happy ending,'' an oversimplified review, perhaps, but in spirit, close enough.</p>
        <p>At the center of the play is Catherine, a young woman who is about to bury her father, a once-great mathematician at the University of Chicago whose final years were beset by madness. Played with stirring unsettledness by Mary-Louise Parker, Catherine has inherited her father's handwriting, his humor and, to an indeterminate degree, both his genius and illness.</p>
        <p>''A taste for the mysteries of numbers is excessively rare,'' the German mathematician Karl Friedrich Gauss wrote to Sophie Germain, a gifted young French woman, some 200 years ago. Catherine has the letter memorized. Its acknowledgment that such a predilection is particularly rare in women is a source of pride and inspiration to her, but it makes her fearful as well; she has witnessed firsthand the jumble that mathematics can make of a working brain. Having quit her own studies years earlier to care for her father, she is, as we see her first on the eve of the funeral -- and her 25th birthday -- at the intersection of a haunting past and blank future. Drinking cheap champagne from the bottle on the back porch of the house she now lives in alone -- to anyone who knows Chicago, John Lee Beatty's staunch, brick set will locate the play precisely -- she is disheveled, bitter, immobilized by depression.</p>
        <p>Ms. Parker is immediately vivid as Catherine, a woman whose sense of defeat is both circumstantial and self-imposed, someone who is aware she has both brain power and sex appeal in spades but trusts neither enough to exhibit them.</p>
        <p>She is herself only with her father (Larry Bryggman), who appears intermittently in both flashbacks and dreams, dramatically risky scenes that are skillfully integrated into the narrative by Mr. Auburn and performed by Mr. Bryggman and Ms. Parker with the sad -- and occasionally droll -- resignation of people holding onto a lifeline of mutual understanding.</p>
        <p>Eloquently snappish in her self-pity, Catherine is, with everyone else, an intimidating presence, except that her body language, in Ms. Parker's performance, can't help but be a fetching plea for salvation. Her inner conflict determinedly keeps at bay her well-meaning sister, Claire, a nonmathematician (she didn't get the family's more troublesome genes) who, as played with a fine blend of anger and concern by Johanna Day, is understandably exasperated by her sister's obstinate antics and wants to sell the house and bring Catherine back with her to New York where she won't be alone with her demons.</p>
        <p>Fortunately for Catherine, she is being courted, shyly but insistently, by Hal Dobbs (Ben Shenkman), a former student of her father's who has been going through the great man's notebooks hoping to find unpublished revelations that may be masked by deranged scribbling. Perhaps conditioned by his chosen profession, Hal doesn't accede to rejection readily, or maybe he doesn't recognize it; he is moved by Catherine as much as he was by her father. In a role written both to acknowledge and debunk the stereotype of the socially inept math nerd, Mr. Shenkman wonderfully evokes the hesitant charm of a young man whose self-awareness tells him that he is more than brainy but less than suave.</p>
        <p>Do Catherine and Hal belong together? That, pardon the expression, is a complex equation for any two people to solve. As their mutual affection and trust waxes and wanes over the course of an autumn weekend, the issue of genius -- who has it and what does it portend? -- turns out to be the elusive variable.</p>
        <p>But ultimately this is emotional math, the sort that everyone and no one understands. Without any baffling erudition -- if you know what a prime number is, there won't be a single line of dialogue you find perplexing -- the play presents mathematicians as both blessed and bedeviled by the gift for abstraction that ties them achingly to one another and separates them, also achingly, from concrete-minded folks like you and me. And perhaps most satisfying of all, it does so without a moment of meanness. ''Proof'' reaches into remote cerebral terrain and finds -- guess what? -- good people. Intelligence a virtue? Q.E.D.</p>
        <p>PROOF  By David Auburn; directed by Daniel Sullivan; sets by John Lee Beatty; costumes by Jess Goldstein; lighting by Pat Collins; sound by John Gromada; production stage manager, James Harker; production manager, Michael R. Moody; associate artistic director, Michael Bush; general manager, Harold Wolpert. Presented by Manhattan Theater Club, Lynne Meadow, artistic director; Barry Grove, executive director. At City Center, Stage 1, 131 West 55th Street, Manhattan.</p>
        <p>WITH: Larry Bryggman (Robert), Mary-Louise Parker (Catherine), Ben Shenkman (Hal) and Johanna Day (Claire).</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
