<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Journeying Through Spain Into the Future</title>
    <meta content="24WINE$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201932"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="WINE TALK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Spain</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Ribera del Duero (Spain)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Prial, Frank J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Columns/Wine Talk</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Spain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000524T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E6DC163DF937A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1715" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Journeying Through Spain Into the Future</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Frank J. Prial</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Prial, Frank J</byline>
      <dateline>PEDROSA DE DUERO, Spain</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Frank J Prial column on the wines of Ribera del Duero region of northern Spain; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WE had been driving all day, had tasted a lot of wines and were, frankly, starved. So we watched impatiently as Manolo Perez grilled 40 tiny lamb chops over vine cuttings.</p>
        <p>We were in the small cook house off the dining room at the Bodegas Hermanos Perez Pascuas, one of the best-known wineries in Ribera del Duero, in northern Spain. When we finally sat down, we paired the succulent chops from baby lambs with some of the bodega's best wines, several vintages of its Vina Pedrosa, one of the most sought-after wines in Ribera del Duero.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WE had been driving all day, had tasted a lot of wines and were, frankly, starved. So we watched impatiently as Manolo Perez grilled 40 tiny lamb chops over vine cuttings.</p>
        <p>We were in the small cook house off the dining room at the Bodegas Hermanos Perez Pascuas, one of the best-known wineries in Ribera del Duero, in northern Spain. When we finally sat down, we paired the succulent chops from baby lambs with some of the bodega's best wines, several vintages of its Vina Pedrosa, one of the most sought-after wines in Ribera del Duero.</p>
        <p>The dinner and the wines were special because they showed how far Ribera del Duero has come. When I first visited northern Spain, almost 20 years ago, it would never have occurred to me to venture outside of Rioja, then the country's only serious area for the production of red wines. Today, Ribera del Duero is one of Spain's fastest-growing wine regions.</p>
        <p>In the United States, Spanish wines were once found almost exclusively in Spanish restaurants. They are suddenly popular everywhere. American wine fans are discovering regions like Navarre, Priorato, Toros and Ribera del Duero that were virtually unknown a few years ago. Even Rioja, the best known of all the Spanish wine districts, is back in fashion. And it still dwarfs the others: All of Ribera del Duero annually produces about 1.5 million cases of wine, while some of the larger Rioja bodegas have more than 2 million cases aging in their cellars.</p>
        <p>The region of Ribera del Duero is about two hours north of Madrid in the province of Castile and Leon. It stretches 68 miles along the banks of the Duero River between Soria in the east and Valladolid in the west.</p>
        <p>Grapes apparently were cultivated and wines made in the Ribera del Duero by the Romans, but modern plantings date from the Middle Ages when French monks brought vine cuttings to the Cistercian monastery at Valbuena de Duero about 20 miles west of Pedrosa. Ribera del Duero is not a monoculture region; corn, vegetables and sugar beets are grown here, along with the sheep that provided us with the lamb chops at Perez Pascuas. Fifty years ago, vines were pulled out to plant the more profitable beets. Now new vineyards are seen everywhere.</p>
        <p>Paradoxically, while the Ribera del Duero was dismissed as a serious viticultural region as recently as the 1980's, it has been home to Spain's most famous winery, Vega Sicilia, since 1846. Vega Sicilia wines, which are blends of local grapes and Bordeaux varieties, developed an almost legendary reputation for their scarcity, quality and staggeringly high prices, a reputation they hold even today -- but with lots of competition.</p>
        <p>Originally, the Ribera del Duero was a region of small unskilled winemakers. Cooperatives were set up in the 1950's but their wine was not much better.</p>
        <p>No longer. In a tasting of some three dozen Ribera wines put on for us by the Consejo Regulador, the regional governing body for wines, there were at least 20 that I would rate as very good to outstanding. In addition to the bodegas discussed here, I was particularly impressed by the wines of the Bodegas Valduero in Aranda, and not just because the winemaker, Margarita Madrigal, has such a lovely name.</p>
        <p>Like all the better Ribera wines, the Valdueros have depth and intensity and show a restrained use of oak. If there is any fault common to many of the Ribera del Duero wines, it is the vanilla taste imparted by the excessive use of new oak.</p>
        <p>The man who changed everything was Alejandro Fernandez, who had made a fortune designing machines to harvest sugar beets. As a boy, he had made wine with his father, and in the 1970's he realized his dream -- a bodega of his own at Pesquera. Inspired by Vega Sicilia, he determined to make wine in his own style, using only local grapes, especially tinto fino, which is virtually identical to the tempranillo grape of the Rioja.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fernandez now operates two huge bodegas in the region to keep up with the demand for his Pesquera wines. We had lunch with him and his daughters, Eva Maria, a trained enologist, and Lucia, who handles the business side, one rainy afternoon at Condado de Haza, the newest Fernandez bodega, in Roa de Duero.</p>
        <p>Warmed by a crackling fire and a succession of local dishes, we tasted through -- drank, actually -- 10 or 12 wines ranging from his regular Pequeras to Janus, a famous gran reserva, a sweet red wine best forgotten and a heavy port-like red from Toro, a relatively new wine district west of Valladolid.</p>
        <p>Spanish laws allow for three categories of fine red wine: crianza, reserva and gran reserva. Crianza is a wine released for sale in its third year after having spent at least six months in barrel (in Rioja, 12 months); reservas must spend three years in barrel and bottle, of which a year should be in barrel; gran reservas must spend two years in barrel and three in bottle or vice versa, and cannot leave the bodega until the sixth year after the vintage.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fernandez's original enologist was another legendary figure in the region, Teofilo Reyes, creator of Protos, a wine almost as famous as Vega Sicilia but, until recent years, only within Spain. Mr. Reyes now makes wine under his own name at his own bodega in Penafiel, in the warmer, western part of the region, near Vega Sicilia, Pesquera and Protos.</p>
        <p>Like the Napa Valley in California, Ribera del Duero has begun to attract outside investors who have succumbed to the romance of wine; Francisco Rodero, the fashion designer from Barcelona, for example. Mr. Rodero, who was born in Pedrosa, owns the Bodegas Rodero, just down the road from the brothers Perez Pascuas. Rodero wines are sold in the United States under the Carmelo Rodero label.</p>
        <p>The Perez Pascuas, by the way, are veterans by Ribera del Duero standards. Their bodega dates from 1980 but they were making wine at the same site long before that. They grow all their own grapes, many of them on 40-year-old vines.</p>
        <p>Several of the best bodegas in Ribera del Duero are actually just outside the legal boundaries of the appellation. One afternoon we dropped in on Mariano Garcia Fernandez at Bodegas Mauro in the village of Tudela de Duero, which is almost in the suburbs of Valladolid.</p>
        <p>Once the winemaker at Vega Sicilia, Mr. Garcia now focuses on his own wines, which are rich and concentrated but not as powerful as the Vega Sicilia wines. He said he would like one day to rival his former employer with Terreus, an impressive gran reserva.</p>
        <p>Also beyond the viticultural pale is the huge Abadia Retuerta at Sardon, east of Tudela, a former monastery converted into a winery by Novartis, the giant Swiss drug manufacturer,  which has hired Pascal Delbeck, long associated with Chateau Ausone in Bordeaux, as winemaker. Like Vega Sicilia, Abadia Retuerta uses Bordeaux varieties in some of its wines. Its 1997 is a blend of 65 percent tempranillo, 30 percent cabernet sauvignon and 5 percent merlot.</p>
        <p>I had been told that visiting Vega Sicilia would be a memorable experience, and it was. An immense new winery, just nearing completion, looks as though it might have been designed by Frank Gehry, whose Guggenheim Museum in Bilbao is two hours to the north. At Vega Sicilia, stainless steel, brick, rare woods, superb lighting and extraordinary artwork have produced a building only a few other wineries in the world could match.</p>
        <p>We tasted through all the Vega Sicilia wines, from the simplest, Tinto Valbuena, through the rare Unico, which usually contains about 20 percent cabernet sauvignon and normally spends about 10 years maturing, first in wooden vats, later in barrels and finally in bottles. I've tried Unicos before. Typically, the one in barrel at the bodega was an exceptionally big, rich wine.</p>
        <p>Whether it could ever be paired with food is questionable. It doesn't seem as if it would want to share the spotlight with anything.</p>
        <p>At a smaller Vega Sicilia winery nearby we tried Alion, a new wine the bodega is developing, as well as samples of a variety of experimental wines. Some of them included wine from Toro, which is being promoted as another trendy wine area and produces big rustic wines resembling zinfandels from the Sierra Foothills in California.</p>
        <p>One winemaker I didn't get to see in Ribera del Duero but would have liked to is Peter Sisseck, a Danish born and Bordeaux-trained enologist, who works for several bodegas but also produces his own wines in a small bodega in the riverside town of Quintanilla. His first vintage of the wine Dominio de Pingus (only a few cases were made) sells for about $500 a bottle when it can be found.</p>
        <p>Rave reviews from several wine critics, including Robert M. Parker Jr., whetted the appetites of collectors around the world. When a ship carrying most of the wine to the United States broke up at sea, the wine was lost and the price of what remained shot up.</p>
        <p>I had a chance to sample the wine at a restaurant in Bilbao. Like the Vega Sicilia and a few California cult wines, it is tremendously rich and concentrated and seems to overpower anything paired with it. Not that most purchasers will have that problem. Five hundred dollar wines are trophy wines, meant to be shown off, not drunk.</p>
        <p>WINE TALK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
