<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No Big Surge in Sex Programs Is Expected From Cable Ruling</title>
    <meta content="Y24CABL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201985"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pornography and Obscenity</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Supreme Court (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rutenberg, Jim</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pornography and Obscenity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000524T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E7D6163DF937A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="709" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No Big Surge in Sex Programs Is Expected From Cable Ruling</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JIM RUTENBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rutenberg, Jim</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>None of cable television systems affected by Supreme Court's overturning of law that requires them to limit sexually explicit channels to late-night hours seem eager to announce expansion in hours of such programming, notice that could offend subscribers; analysts say technological advances expected to make scrambling universally effective would have made law obsolete in few years (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Supreme Court's decision on Monday striking down a law that required many cable systems to limit sexually explicit channels to late-night hours will most likely reap a modest increase in profits for programmers but is not expected to hasten a vast explosion of sexually oriented material on cable.</p>
        <p>Under the old law, cable systems that did not have the sufficient technology to fully scramble the signals of sexually explicit channels for non-subscribers were allowed to make those channels available only when children were unlikely to be watching -- from 10 p.m. to 6 a.m., the Federal Communications Commission had decided in a regulation applying the law.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Supreme Court's decision on Monday striking down a law that required many cable systems to limit sexually explicit channels to late-night hours will most likely reap a modest increase in profits for programmers but is not expected to hasten a vast explosion of sexually oriented material on cable.</p>
        <p>Under the old law, cable systems that did not have the sufficient technology to fully scramble the signals of sexually explicit channels for non-subscribers were allowed to make those channels available only when children were unlikely to be watching -- from 10 p.m. to 6 a.m., the Federal Communications Commission had decided in a regulation applying the law.</p>
        <p>Now the cable systems that the court's ruling affects, which in all reach about 18 million homes, are deciding how to respond. None seemed eager yesterday to announce an expansion in the hours of sexually explicit programming, notice that could offend their subscribers.</p>
        <p>But analysts said they did not expect sexually explicit cable offerings to increase significantly in any case. They also said the law would have been obsolete in a few years anyway, because of technological advances that are expected to make scrambling universally effective.</p>
        <p>''I view this primarily as a technical ruling that is more important for its First Amendment implications,'' said Chris Dixon, a media analyst for PaineWebber.</p>
        <p>The Playboy Entertainment Group, which owns four sexually explicit channels and brought the challenge upheld by the Supreme Court,  said its growth had been stunted by the law because cable carriers were loath to give up channel space for programming that was available only a relatively few hours a day. And executives of the company said that even with the systems that carried the Playboy channels, the limitation in hours had cost Playboy about $4 million a year in revenue.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Dixon said that despite the Supreme Court's decision, many cable companies that had refrained from carrying sexually oriented programming would probably remain  hesitant, because of limited channel capacities. ''The problem is not whether or not programming is appropriate, it's whether or not there is space available on the dial or on the set-top box,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Those systems that do carry the explicit channels have until now taken up the other 16 hours of the day on them with ''filler'' programming, which draws few viewers.</p>
        <p>It is not as if demand for the sex channels is extremely high. While explicit programming, available predominantly on pay per view, is somewhat popular, it does not draw blockbuster ratings. Larry Gerbrandt, senior analyst at Paul Kagan Associates, said the cable companies brought in revenue of $954 million from pay-per-view programming last year. Of that total, sexually explicit programming accounted for $177 million, he said.</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Gerbrandt said he expected many of the cable companies  affected by the ruling to expand the channels' hours, primarily because there is easy money to be made for all parties: the cable companies receive half the revenue from the pay-per-view sales.</p>
        <p>And while the viewers of sexual content are relatively small in number, Mr. Gerbrandt said he expected them to take advantage of the expanded hours where available.</p>
        <p>''I think it provides a boost to the category,'' he said of the ruling. ''I don't think it causes it to explode.''</p>
        <p>Tony Lynn, president of the Playboy Entertainment Group, who on  Monday expressed great enthusiasm about the justices' ruling, was more temperate yesterday. Mr. Lynn said he expected the expansion of his channels' hours to take time, because there were hundreds of cable systems that had to decide individually whether they wanted to take advantage of the change in law.</p>
        <p>One cable executive, who spoke on the condition that he not be identified, said his company would most likely expand the hours of the Playboy channels, but quietly, so as not to stir community opposition.</p>
        <p>''There are customers out there that want this kind of programming,'' he said. ''It might not be the majority, but you cannot be tyrannical. ''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
