<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Excerpts From Bush's Remarks on National Security and Arms Policy</title>
    <meta content="Y24BTE$10" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201995"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Missiles and Missile Defense Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Arms Control and Limitation and Disarmament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Text</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Missiles and Missile Defense Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Arms Control and Limitation and Disarmament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000524T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E6DE173DF937A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="3401" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Excerpts From Bush's Remarks on National Security and Arms Policy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Excerpts from Gov George W Bush's remarks on national security</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Following are excerpts from a transcript of Gov. George W. Bush's remarks yesterday in Washington on national security, and the question-and-answer session that followed and included a brief remark by Gen. Colin L. Powell, as recorded by The New York Times:</p>
        <p>Opening Remarks</p>
        <p>Today, I am here with some of our nation's leading statesmen and defense experts. And there is broad agreement that our nation needs a new approach to nuclear security that matches a new era.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Following are excerpts from a transcript of Gov. George W. Bush's remarks yesterday in Washington on national security, and the question-and-answer session that followed and included a brief remark by Gen. Colin L. Powell, as recorded by The New York Times:</p>
        <p>Opening Remarks</p>
        <p>Today, I am here with some of our nation's leading statesmen and defense experts. And there is broad agreement that our nation needs a new approach to nuclear security that matches a new era.</p>
        <p>When it comes to nuclear weapons, the world has changed faster than U.S. policy. The emerging security threats to the United States, its friends and allies and even to Russia now come from rogue states, terrorist groups and other adversaries seeking weapons of mass destruction and the means to deliver them. Threats also come from insecure nuclear stockpiles and the proliferation of dangerous technologies.</p>
        <p>Russia itself is no longer our enemy. The cold-war logic that led to creation of massive stockpiles on both sides is now outdated. Our mutual security need no longer depend on a nuclear balance of terror. While deterrence remains the first line of defense against nuclear attack, the standoff of the cold war was born of a different time. That was a time when our arsenal also served to check the conventional superiority of the Warsaw Pact. Then the Soviet Union's power reached deep into the heart of Europe to Berlin and Warsaw, Budapest and Prague. Today these are the capitals of NATO countries.</p>
        <p>Yet almost a decade after the end of the cold war, our nuclear policy still resides in that already distant past.</p>
        <p>The Clinton-Gore administration has had over seven years to bring the U.S. force posture into the post-cold-war world. Instead, they remained locked in a cold-war mentality. It is time to leave the cold war behind and defend against the new threats of the 21st century.</p>
        <p>America must build effective missile defenses based on the best available options at the earliest possible date. Our missile defense must be designed to protect all 50 states and our friends and allies and deployed forces overseas from missile attacks by rogue nations or accidental launches.</p>
        <p>The Clinton administration at first denied the need for a national missile defense system. Then it delayed. Now the approach it proposes is flawed, a system initially based on a single site, when experts say that more is needed. A missile defense system should not only defend our country; it should defend our allies, with whom I will consult as we develop our plans. And any change in the A.B.M. Treaty must allow the technologies and experiments required to deploy adequate missile defenses.</p>
        <p>The administration is driving toward a hasty decision on a political timetable. No decision would be better than a flawed agreement that ties the hands of the next president and prevents America from defending itself.</p>
        <p>Yet there are positive, practical ways to demonstrate to Russia that we are no longer enemies. Russia, our allies in the world need to understand our intentions. America's development of missile defenses is a search for security, not a search for advantage.</p>
        <p>America should rethink the requirements for nuclear deterrence in a new security environment. The premises of cold-war nuclear targeting should no longer dictate the size of our arsenal. As president, I will ask the secretary of defense to conduct an assessment of our nuclear force posture and determine how best to meet our security needs. While the exact number of weapons can come only from such an assessment, I will pursue the lowest possible number consistent with our national security.</p>
        <p>It should be possible to reduce the number of American nuclear weapons significantly further than what has been already agreed to under Start II without compromising our security in any way. We should not keep weapons that our military planners do not need. These unneeded weapons are the expensive relics of dead conflicts, and they do nothing to make us more secure.</p>
        <p>In addition, the United States should remove as many weapons as possible from high-alert, hair-trigger status.</p>
        <p>Another unnecessary vestige of cold-war confrontation, preparation for quick launch within minutes after warning of an attack was the rule during the era of superpower rivalry. But today for two nations at peace, keeping so many weapons on high alert may create unacceptable risks of accidental or unauthorized launch.</p>
        <p>So as president I will ask for an assessment of what we can safely do to lower the alert status of our forces. These changes to our forces should not require years and years of detailed arms control negotiations. There is a precedent that proves the power of leadership. In 1991, the United States invited the Soviet Union to join it in removing tactical nuclear weapons from the arsenal. Huge reductions were achieved in a matter of months, making the world much safer more quickly.</p>
        <p>Similarly, in the area of strategic nuclear weapons, we should invite the Russian government to accept the new vision that I have outlined and act on it.</p>
        <p>But the United States should be prepared to lead by example because it is in our best interests and the best interests of the world. This would be an act of principled leadership, a chance to seize the moment and begin a new era of nuclear security, a new era of cooperation on proliferation and nuclear safety.</p>
        <p>The cold-war era is history. Our nation must recognize new threats, not fixate on old ones. On the issue of nuclear weapons,  the United States has an opportunity to lead to a safer world, both to defend against nuclear threats and reduce nuclear tensions. It is possible to build a missile defense and defuse confrontation with Russia. America should do both. . . .</p>
        <p>Questions and Answers</p>
        <p>Q. I'm just trying to clarify. When you say that we should be prepared to lead by example, are you saying that you'd be prepared to reduce America's nuclear arsenal whether or not the Russians follow suit?</p>
        <p>MR. BUSH. Yes, and I would hope ----. Yes, I am, and I would work closely with the Russians to convince them to do the same.</p>
        <p>Q. If they don't do the same, are [unintelligible] arsenal [unintelligible] this nation?</p>
        <p>A. Oh, I would never do anything to put our nation at risk.</p>
        <p>I will work with the secretary of the defense to come up with a level of weaponry consistent with the notion that to deter -- to keep a notion to keep the peace to deterrence, but at the same time make a clear signal to the Russians that we are willing to reduce our arsenals to assure them, and to assure the world, that we're a peaceful nation, we have peace in mind.</p>
        <p>Q. There are many Start III negotiations under way to bring down the level. Do you think the levels being talked about are insufficient? Could you explain what [unintelligible]?</p>
        <p>A. The definition of sufficient reductions is going to be determined after I consult closely with the secretary of defense and the defense establishment in my administration, the people in my administration.</p>
        <p>Secondly, Start III should not be an excuse to limit our ability to develop an antiballistic missile system.</p>
        <p>Q. Governor, are you saying that we ought to share the national defense system with our allies in NATO and perhaps even with our allies in Russia as well? When you say ''protect our allies,'' who do you mean?</p>
        <p>A. I mean people in Europe, for example. But I also mean Israel. I, yes, I think we ought to consult closely with our allies.</p>
        <p>As to sharing information and technologies with the Russians, it depends upon how Russia behaves, depends upon how Russia conducts itself as a member of the family of nations.</p>
        <p>Q. Governor, would you share that technology with Taiwan?</p>
        <p>A. I think we ought to own the technology, but I'd be willing to use it, if need be, to uphold the Taiwan relations law.</p>
        <p>Q. Governor, President Clinton will be in Moscow in a week. What are you authorizing him or what would you like to see him do at the negotiations? You're saying that you'd like to see the number of warheads brought down. Would you like to ----.</p>
        <p>A. What I'm really suggesting is that he not hamstring the ability of the next president to fully develop an antiballistic missile system to protect ourselves and our allies. As I said, no treaty, no agreement, would be better than a flawed agreement. I'm concerned that this administration is not fully devoted to the development of a antiballistic missile system that will work.</p>
        <p>Q. Governor Bush, this is the second time that you've talked in kind of detail about a national missile defense system. In The New York Times you talked about the cost and how you would pay for it in context with your tax cuts, saving Social Security [unintelligible].</p>
        <p>A. We have a $4 trillion surplus. I intend to reserve over $2 trillion of that for Social Security; about $1.3 trillion for tax cuts. The remainder will be available to meet priorities.</p>
        <p>Secondly, the cost of an antiballistic missile system is worth the cost to protect ourselves, to protect our allies. The ability to determine the final cost will be the ability to determine, you know, what the new research in technologies look like, and the current treaty prevents us from fully exploring all options when it comes to the effective deployment of an antiballistic missile system.</p>
        <p>Q. Governor, at the [unintelligible] United Nations conference in New York last Saturday the United States and four other nuclear powers agreed to [unintelligible] nuclear arsenal [unintelligible]. Do you support that agreement? Are you still opposed to ratification by the United States [unintelligible] on the comprehensive [unintelligible] and how soon would you work for the nuclear disarmament [unintelligible]?</p>
        <p>A. I will never reduce the levels of the nuclear stockpile of the United States to a position where it would jeopardize our safety and security. And, no, I don't support the comprehensive test ban treaty.</p>
        <p>Q. You're willing to review the U.N. defense policy. Are you willing to review the U.S. policy regarding Cuba?</p>
        <p>A. I'll review the policy toward Cuba when Fidel Castro has free elections, frees prisoners and has freedom of the press.</p>
        <p>Q. Governor, [unintelligible] question this week on China. Are you satisfied that the administration has done everything it can to get P.N.T.R. passed? Do you believe it's going to pass? And did you yourself lobby for it?</p>
        <p>A. Well, I said a pretty strong statement in Seattle the other day, and a congressman walked up to me last night and said, ''You know something? I want you to know that because of your strong statement, I'm voting for the bill.''</p>
        <p>I'm going to go to the Hill today. I'm going to encourage members to vote for it. I think the president's given it his best shot. And I was happy to see the vice president finally emerge and make a statement.</p>
        <p>Q. There's going to be four debates this coming fall ----</p>
        <p>A. How do you know?</p>
        <p>Q. Commission on ----</p>
        <p>A. Oh, O.K., I see. According to Mr. Gore, he wants 60 debates.</p>
        <p>Q. Well, the commission says that you have to have 15 percent in the polls to get in on the debates. But the consensus seems to be that if it was you and Vice President Gore, you're going to put the country to sleep ----</p>
        <p>A. Really, well, I appreciate that objective analysis.</p>
        <p>Q. Would you agree to have Ralph Nader and Pat Buchanan on the debate?</p>
        <p>A. And all the rest of the candidates, too?</p>
        <p>Q. No, just those two.</p>
        <p>A. Why not all the rest?</p>
        <p>Q. Because they have 5 percent; the rest have minimal.</p>
        <p>A. Well, maybe they'll be surging in the polls by then. We'll worry about the debates on the debates at the appropriate time. . . .</p>
        <p>Q. The Russians seem to regard the A.B.M. as the cornerstone of security. You are saying that you will get out of A.B.M. My question, are you willing to talk to the Russians before you make your final decision?</p>
        <p>A. Of course.</p>
        <p>Q. You will?</p>
        <p>A. Absolutely. As I told your foreign minister that I look forward to working with Mr. Putin and explaining my point of view and my attitude about the post-cold-war era.</p>
        <p>I'm going to look him right in the eye and say, You're no longer the enemy. And we're not your enemy. Surely we can work together to bring certainty into an uncertain world.</p>
        <p>I look forward to that, and I think it's going to be very important for the next president to clearly state the intentions of the United States, that we're a peaceful nation and that we look forward to working together with Russia to keep the peace, that the world has changed dramatically.</p>
        <p>Q. So talking about military might, how do you define the national greatness of the United States? Do you think that the national greatness of any country should be defined by military means?</p>
        <p>A. National greatness of the United States is how we love each other, how one neighbor will help another neighbor, whether or not we can educate our children.</p>
        <p>The one thing I won't do as president is to allow our military preparedness to slip below levels necessary to keep the peace. I won't let the morale in the United States military deteriorate like it has under this current administration. I understand it's important to have a well-focused, well-paid military to keep the peace. And I'm going to assure Mr. Putin that that's exactly what my intentions are and that we should work together.</p>
        <p>I'll also assure our allies and friends in Europe of the intentions. It's important for us to strengthen our alliances, which I'm going to do. . . .</p>
        <p>Q. Are you talking about unilateral reductions in American deployed weapons? And if the Russians didn't reciprocate, would you keep to those reductions? And are you also talking about reducing stockpiles?</p>
        <p>A. I'm talking about reduce -- both. I'm talking about making sure the level of stockpiles and deployed weaponry is such that we can keep the peace and have a strong deterrence.</p>
        <p>I recognize we're in a different world, and I'm going to send that signal to the secretary of defense to analyze the world the way it is today, not the way it used to be when the -- it used to be when the Soviet Union had a powerful presence and what now are NATO countries. It's a changed world. And our attitude ought to change. And ----</p>
        <p>Q. If the Russians don't reciprocate ----</p>
        <p>A. Well, hopefully they will. I'll look forward to working with the Russians. But if they don't, the level of nuclear readiness is going  to meet our needs. It's going to meet the needs of the United States of America. I will never put our security at risk. . . .</p>
        <p>Q. You mentioned that you would review American policy toward Cuba once Fidel Castro held free elections and a free press and other standards of democracy. In this week we're in the process of reviewing and possibly changing policy toward China. And I think it's a constant source of confusion in some countries about what is the difference between China's Communist government by those standards that we judge Cuba in terms of a free press, free elections, oppression of minorities, oppression recently in China of a spiritual movement with no political intention. What's the difference?</p>
        <p>A. The difference is, as far as I'm concerned, that we're trading with an entrepreneurial class in China. That by trade with China that we're encouraging a group of entrepreneurs and small-business owners to be able to get a taste of freedom, that we're giving them an opportunity to grow.</p>
        <p>That's not the case in Cuba. In Cuba we're trading, in essence, with a government-controlled entity. And my worry is that capital flowing into Cuba will help prop up the Fidel Castro regime.</p>
        <p>My belief is by trading with an entrepreneurial class in China it will enhance the spread of freedoms in China. And there's a big difference.</p>
        <p>Q. So the standards that you mentioned before was about free elections and freedom of the press, none of which exists in China.</p>
        <p>A. Yeah, but it's also a standard, which I failed to mention, that there's the standard who we're trading with. Who we're doing business with.</p>
        <p>When we trade with China, we're trading more and more with people that are in the private sector, entrepreneurs, and free enterprise is taking hold in China. And I think that's going to be a measure to the extent freedom takes hold in China as well. And I think there's a big difference.</p>
        <p>Q. Governor, either here today or in a meeting on Thursday [unintelligible] would you ask General Powell to be your vice president or running mate? And/or take another position, especially [unintelligible] as secretary of state?</p>
        <p>A. I'm not going to tell you. Well, I'm not going to tell him what I'm going to talk to him -- I'm not going to tell you what I talk to him about. I hope he's for me, let me just put it to you that way. . . .</p>
        <p>Q. Can General Powell answer that question on his attitude on both vice president and some other candidate position such as that [unintelligible]?</p>
        <p>A. You don't have to if you don't want to.</p>
        <p>GENERAL POWELL. I think I've answered that on many occasions. The answer's well known. I won't take any time away from the governor to belabor you with ----</p>
        <p>MR. BUSH. And don't you ever accuse him of being smarmy again.</p>
        <p>Q. Governor, this program to defend the country against missiles has been problematic from the beginning from a technological point of view both during the Reagan administration and your father's administration, now during the Clinton administration. What technology do you see out there that makes you hopeful that once you implement your program you can actually defend this country against an incoming ----.</p>
        <p>A. What I see out there is a couple of things. One, the world has changed a lot since the 80's. Science is evolving. Laser technology is evolving. There's a lot of inventiveness in our society that hasn't been unleashed on this particular subject.</p>
        <p>And, secondly, I see a treaty that makes it hard for us to fully explore the options available, the options available to keep the peace. And there needs to be an administration with a firm commitment to exploring all options and all opportunities. Be able to understand, you know, whether or not a space-based system can work, like some hope it can. And under this administration we have -- I don't think there's been the full commitment to determining what the opportunities and options are for the country. And I think it's important to take a full look at whether or not we can keep the peace. I'm going to remind people in this country ----</p>
        <p>And the interesting fact is a lot of people think we can defend ourselves against an accidental launch. I think if you were to ask Americans, they will tell you that we've got the capability of defending ourselves. But it's not the case. And I believe the post-cold-war era dictates a different way of thinking.</p>
        <p>Q. Governor, a follow-up from another question, are you [unintelligible] money question related to the program?</p>
        <p>A. I'm against soft money.</p>
        <p>Q. Are you prepared if necessary [unintelligible] to fulfill this broadening vision that now extends to defense policy?</p>
        <p>A. I don't have to, I'm not going to have to do that. There is enough money in the budget to do so. And there are savings to be had. And there are savings to be had in the budget as well. And I believe there is ample money to do both.</p>
        <p>Q. Governor, are the people arrayed onstage behind you this morning involved in the formulation of this [unintelligible]?</p>
        <p>A. Of course.</p>
        <p>Q. And have they all agreed to advise you on foreign policy and defense matters?</p>
        <p>A. Yes, they have. And I'm honored to have their support. I'm honored to have their opinions. I've told my supporters I was interested in thinking differently. As we go into the 21st century I want a different point of view when it comes to how to keep the peace. And it's the right thing to do for America, and it's the right thing to do for the world.</p>
        <p>Thank you all for your time.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
