<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Must Be the Shoes as Testaverde Slips</title>
    <meta content="24JETS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201953"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Jets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Battista, Judy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000524T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E1D9163DF937A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="751" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Must Be the Shoes as Testaverde Slips</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JUDY BATTISTA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Battista, Judy</byline>
      <dateline>HEMPSTEAD, N.Y., May 23</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article describes scene at New York Jets minicamp; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Vinny Testaverde disappeared from sight today, briefly slipping behind the horizon created by his linemen during the first practice of a four-day minicamp for veterans, the Jets' hierarchy may have suffered a few nervous moments.</p>
        <p>Testaverde slipped as he released a pass and he fell near the feet of Coach Al Groh. But out of the corner of his eye, Groh could see that Testaverde was not clutching at his left leg, as he did when he tore his Achilles' tendon in the 1999 season opener last September. That agony was not fissuring his face again.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Vinny Testaverde disappeared from sight today, briefly slipping behind the horizon created by his linemen during the first practice of a four-day minicamp for veterans, the Jets' hierarchy may have suffered a few nervous moments.</p>
        <p>Testaverde slipped as he released a pass and he fell near the feet of Coach Al Groh. But out of the corner of his eye, Groh could see that Testaverde was not clutching at his left leg, as he did when he tore his Achilles' tendon in the 1999 season opener last September. That agony was not fissuring his face again.</p>
        <p>Testaverde was down, wearing the wrong pair of shoes for the damp artificial turf, but the hopes for a new season had not slipped away again.</p>
        <p>''Ray Lucas came running over to help me up,'' Testaverde said. ''That was probably a good test for me, too, to know I can roll the ankle and get up.''</p>
        <p>The next significant test for Testaverde will come when he faces live competition in a preseason game, but he conceded he had a nervous stomach for a few days preceding the start of this camp, with the anticipation of rejoining his teammates on the field consuming him. He is in the eighth month of a recovery that is supposed to take between eight and 12 months and he thinks that if he had to, he could play in a game tomorrow, although he still must regain strength in his left leg.</p>
        <p>''I don't really think much about it on the field,'' Testaverde said of the injury that finished last season before it could get started. ''I just go out and try to react. My arm feels fresh. It's not my arm I'm worried about. I'm worried about the speed of the game, how it goes in my mind's eye.</p>
        <p>''I'm anxious to get through this week, with the two-a-days. I haven't worked the Achilles' hard to know if it can hold up to that test.''</p>
        <p>The reassurance that Testaverde's return provides, of course, is especially meaningful for a team that has to find a way to fill the gap -- both on the field and in the locker room -- left by wide receiver Keyshawn Johnson. Center Kevin Mawae, who played down the departure of Johnson, predicted that as long as Testaverde remains healthy the Jets would return to their soaring fortunes of two seasons ago, when they went to the conference championship game.</p>
        <p>Testaverde said he does not lobby coaches to acquire players, but he spoke today of how well Cincinnati's Carl Pickens, who will most likely be released by the Bengals on June 1, would fit in with the Jets.</p>
        <p>Groh took a lengthy pause before responding to a question about which receivers had caught his eye in practice, then praised Dedric Ward, Fred Coleman and Dwight Stone, adding that he thought the existing Jets receivers could collectively replace Johnson's contributions. But Testaverde seemed determined not to let Johnson's departure spoil his own return.</p>
        <p>''With the work you put in through rehab, the running and the lifting, I'm not going to come in with a bad attitude because we lost some folks,'' he said. ''If it turns out to be a bad season, it turns out to be a bad season. But it would be wrong to start out with a bad attitude.''</p>
        <p>EXTRA POINTS</p>
        <p>Quarterback RAY LUCAS, who became the odd man out when AL GROH declared the rookie CHAD PENNINGTON the quarterback of the future, said he was not bitter about his situation. ''That's how the business is,'' Lucas said. . . . Linebacker BRYAN COX, who had surgery Dec. 10 to repair torn stomach and hip flexor muscles, said that while he feels good, he is still not completely confident, although Groh praised him. ''I'm nervous about cutting,'' Cox said. ''I'm still trying to build strength. It's just psychological.'' But Cox, who said on the day KEYSHAWN JOHNSON was traded that he did not want to be part of a rebuilding process, has changed his perspective on the Jets. ''If it was rebuilding, you wouldn't be talking to me,'' he said. . . . The Jets re-signed kick returner and wide receiver DWIGHT STONE and signed the rookie free-agent wide receiver BRANDON CAMPBELL from Eastern Michigan.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
