<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>W.U.S.A. and M.L.S. Agree to Cooperate on Women's League</title>
    <meta content="24SOCC$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202026"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SOCCER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Women's United Soccer Assn</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Longman, Jere</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000524T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E1DC173DF937A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="519" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>W.U.S.A. and M.L.S. Agree to Cooperate on Women's League</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JERE LONGMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Longman, Jere</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Women's United Soccer Association emerges victorious in its attempt to become sole operator of women's professional outdoor league that is to begin play next spring (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bargaining from a position of strength, the Women's United Soccer Association emerged victorious yesterday in its attempt to become the sole operator of a women's professional outdoor league that is to begin play next spring.</p>
        <p>Major League Soccer, the struggling men's professional league, announced that it would not apply to the United States Soccer Federation, the sport's national governing body, to start a women's league.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Bargaining from a position of strength, the Women's United Soccer Association emerged victorious yesterday in its attempt to become the sole operator of a women's professional outdoor league that is to begin play next spring.</p>
        <p>Major League Soccer, the struggling men's professional league, announced that it would not apply to the United States Soccer Federation, the sport's national governing body, to start a women's league.</p>
        <p>Instead, the W.U.S.A. and M.L.S. announced plans to cooperate on marketing, promotion, scheduling and stadium development efforts, which could lead to doubleheaders and cross-ownership, with the eventual operation of a women's expansion team by the M.L.S. and a men's expansion team by the W.U.S.A.</p>
        <p>Yesterday's announcement represented a watershed moment in the history of women's sports in the United States, given that the men's soccer league essentially acceded to the terms demanded by the upstart women's league. Women's soccer on the national team level has been more successful on the field than men's soccer in this country, and more visible, too, since the victorious run by the United States national team in 1999 Women's World Cup.</p>
        <p>The W.U.S.A. has received commitments from all 20 members of the World Cup team.</p>
        <p>''We are excited to know that the plan we hoped would be going forward will be sanctioned,'' Carla Overbeck, captain of the women's national team, said on a telephone conference call.</p>
        <p>Both the men's and the women's leagues stand to benefit by cooperating. The W.U.S.A. will maintain its administrative autonomy, while taking advantage of M.L.S.'s know-how in starting and operating a soccer league and of potential M.L.S. audiences for doubleheaders. Together, the leagues can work to build 15,000 to 20,000-seat stadiums specifically geared to soccer.</p>
        <p>By cooperating with the W.U.S.A., the M.L.S. will be able to promote itself through commercials on the cable networks that are underwriting the women's league, expanding its reach toward the middle class and upper-middle class suburban audiences that the W.U.S.A. is expected to attract. The M.L.S. had been concerned about competing head to head with the women for the suburban audience.</p>
        <p>The W.U.S.A. pre-empted any real chance for an M.L.S. bid by signing the top women's stars and by gaining $40 million in investment from such cable entities as Discovery Communications, Time Warner, Comcast and Cox Communications. The investment group is headed by the W.U.S.A. chairman, John S. Hendricks, whose companies include the Discovery and the Learning Channels.</p>
        <p>The league, which hopes to average 6,500 fans and which will pay an average salary of $40,000, plans to start in April 2001 in Atlanta, Boston, New York, Orlando, Fla., Philadelphia, San Diego, the San Francisco Bay Area and Washington. The W.U.S.A. will announce rosters today, with Kristine Lilly expected to go to New York, Mia Hamm to Washington, Brandi Chastain to the Bay Area and Julie Foudy to San Diego.</p>
        <p>SOCCER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
