<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Croshere's Can't-Miss Kind of Night</title>
    <meta content="24PACE$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202074"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Indiana Pacers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Robbins, Liz</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Croshere, Austin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Indiana Pacers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000524T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E2DA173DF937A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="925" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Croshere's Can't-Miss Kind of Night</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIZ ROBBINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Robbins, Liz</byline>
      <dateline>INDIANAPOLIS, May 23</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses play of Indiana Pacers forward Austin Croshere in victory over New York Knickerbockers in first game of playoff series; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The dunk was a satisfying ending to Austin Croshere's breakout night.</p>
        <p>Sitting in the Indiana Pacers' locker room after Game 1 of the Eastern Conference finals, Croshere plunged his feet into a blue tub of ice water, numbing his sprained right ankle and his chronically pained right foot. Steam could have enveloped him upon contact, and none of his teammates would have been surprised.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The dunk was a satisfying ending to Austin Croshere's breakout night.</p>
        <p>Sitting in the Indiana Pacers' locker room after Game 1 of the Eastern Conference finals, Croshere plunged his feet into a blue tub of ice water, numbing his sprained right ankle and his chronically pained right foot. Steam could have enveloped him upon contact, and none of his teammates would have been surprised.</p>
        <p>Croshere was just that hot in the Indiana Pacers' 102-88 victory over the Knicks tonight.</p>
        <p>Until this season, Croshere, the Pacers' No. 1 draft pick out of Providence College in 1997, had played one minute of playoff basketball.</p>
        <p>''I sat and watched the playoffs the last two years and I built up a lot of fire,'' said Croshere, hand-picked by Coach Larry Bird. ''I don't feel like I pulled my weight at all.''</p>
        <p>Tonight, Croshere, the Pacers'</p>
        <p>6-foot-10-inch sixth man, pulled his weight when the Pacers' leading scorer, Jalen Rose, was struggling. He pulled the Knicks' defense out wide and Marcus Camby off balance all night, pulled four 3-pointers from his pocket, and in turn, pulled off a team-high 22-point performance from 28 minutes.</p>
        <p>Croshere was only 10 days removed from spraining his ankle in Game 2 against Philadelphia, and was not quite 100 percent tonight. Not that his teammates could tell.</p>
        <p>''I don't think I've ever seen him play this well,'' center Rik Smits said of Croshere after he sparked the Pacers early with 8 first-quarter points, finished with 16 and then watched from the bench as Croshere dominated. ''His ankle felt better. He was looking good in practice and he played smart, too, tonight.''</p>
        <p>When the Knicks were focusing on Reggie Miller or Rose or Smits tonight, Croshere found himself open. ''I'm sure I wasn't their primary focus,'' he said.</p>
        <p>And in that respect, Croshere could be just what the Pacers need in these playoffs, just what the Knicks had last year.</p>
        <p>''I was telling him that Camby was their X factor last year and he's going to have to do something for us this year,'' Miller said. ''He had to box Camby out. But more so, he did a good job of extending their defense and that provided a lot of opportunities.''</p>
        <p>Croshere took advantage of the opportunities when they counted most, scoring 11 points, and hitting all three of his 3-pointers in the decisive fourth quarter that closed out any Knicks comeback.</p>
        <p>''His role is to come and play with force, rebound, be aggressive, catch the ball on the block, face you and basically have you at his mercy,'' Indiana's Mark Jackson said. ''Score, drive, pull up. When he's in a rhythm, he's a nightmare after dark. He's never reluctant; he wants to shoot. When he gets more and more confidence, he's going to be unbelievable. His future is very very bright because he can do so many things.''</p>
        <p>That is what Larry Bird saw when he drafted him in the first round in 1997. Since then, Croshere has been slow to develop and was saddled with injuries, most notably plantar fasciitis, which has inflamed the bottom of his foot this year.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, with constant tutoring from Bird, Croshere has responded this season, which was critical after the Pacers traded Antonio Davis to Toronto. Croshere, 25, became the Pacers' fourth-leading scorer (10.3) and second-leading rebounder (6.4) during the regular season. Tonight, he more than doubled his scoring totals and had the best game of the playoffs.</p>
        <p>''He opened up the game for everyone,'' said Rose, who was able to find his shooting touch finally in the second half, scoring all of his 17 points then.</p>
        <p>Dale Davis also benefited, pulling down a game-high 16 rebounds and scoring 4 points.</p>
        <p>''The great thing is when you finally get the minutes,'' Rose said. ''When you get the ball, you got to make the play. Austin has been making plays all season long for us. Hopefully we can continue to feed off that.''</p>
        <p>Bird added: ''Austin played an all-around great game. His No. 1 job is to keep Camby off the boards, which he did.''</p>
        <p>Camby had only three rebounds.</p>
        <p>Only a few minutes before, Bird had reminded Croshere that just because he was featured on television, following his great game, he still had to listen. Croshere has been Bird's pet project.</p>
        <p>Bird has constantly harped on Croshere to be aggressive, to drive to the basket, rather than pull up or fade away. Tonight, he did.</p>
        <p>''My foot is O.K.,'' he said, adding that his ankle is almost fully healed. ''The foot is something that won't be completely better until I rest. I'm just getting used to playing with the pain.''</p>
        <p>In the previous series he had played sparingly following the injury.</p>
        <p>''I was just doing my part.''</p>
        <p>And more.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
