<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="24FSUM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202022"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000524T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE4DC173DF937A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1209" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-13</p>
        <p>Israel Quits Lebanon; Guerrillas Pour Into Zone  Shiite Muslim guerrillas reclaimed the Israeli-occupied zone in southern Lebanon and rode abandoned Israeli tanks through village after village, six weeks before the Israelis planned to shut down the military buffer zone they controlled along the border.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-13</p>
        <p>Israel Quits Lebanon; Guerrillas Pour Into Zone  Shiite Muslim guerrillas reclaimed the Israeli-occupied zone in southern Lebanon and rode abandoned Israeli tanks through village after village, six weeks before the Israelis planned to shut down the military buffer zone they controlled along the border.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Prime Minister Ehud Barak declared an end to Israel's two-decade occupation of southern Lebanon, as the last Israeli troops and pro-Israeli militias pulled out of what was once known as Israel's security zone.</p>
        <p>A13</p>
        <p>Debate on China Trade Bill  The House opened debate on legislation to grant Beijing permanent normal trading relations, as a final round of horse-trading with undecided members reached furious intensity. A vote is set for today.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Push to Ease Cuba Embargo  Powerful American farm groups, sensing a shift in sentiment on Capitol Hill, are pushing Congress to soften the 38-year-old trade embargo and to permit the export of food, medicine and medical products.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>U.S. to Revise Arms Controls  The Clinton administration will overhaul controls on arms exports to friendly nations for the first time since the cold war, officials said. The changes are intended to reduce the red tape involved in the licensing of technology sales, information sharing and joint ventures between governments and contractors.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>U.S.-Indonesia Military Ties  Senior defense officials said the administration had quietly resumed military cooperation with Indonesia, eight months after cutting ties following massacres in East Timor.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Visit to Russian Germ Lab  The State Research Center for Applied Microbiology invited 200 scientists from 10 countries, Western officials and an American reporter into what was once a crown jewel of the Soviet germ warfare empire. The center says it is determined to conduct only peaceful work.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Germany to Reduce Its Army  The defense minister accepted a recommendation to overhaul and shrink the draft-based army, which is still set up to fight the cold war.</p>
        <p>A5</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A16-23</p>
        <p>Bush Backs Arms Cuts And Antimissile System  Gov. George W. Bush, flanked by prominent figures from four Republican administrations, called for a ''new approach to nuclear security,'' one that includes possible unilateral reductions in American nuclear weapons combined with a robust antimissile defense system. Mr. Bush said he wanted to reduce the size of America's nuclear arsenal to the ''lowest possible number consistent with our national security'' and below the levels called for under the START II treaty with Russia.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush discussed his broad agenda with House Republicans.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>Assessing Ruling on Cable TV  Analysts said they did not expect sexually explicit cable offerings to increase significantly in the wake of a Supreme Court decision striking down a law that required many cable systems to limit sexually explicit channels to late-night hours.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>Best Water in Rural America  Water from a 5,000-year-old source beneath Independence Village, a 40-unit housing development for the elderly in Montville, Conn., was judged the best tasting in a competition sponsored by the National Rural Drinking Water Association.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>SCIENCE/HEALTH</p>
        <p>Insulin and Breast Cancer  High levels of insulin in the blood augur badly for women with breast cancer, a Canadian study found. Women with the disease and high levels of insulin who received standard therapy were about eight times more likely to develop a recurrence and die of the disease than women who had normal insulin levels.</p>
        <p>A22</p>
        <p>Penalizing Medical Lapses  The Clinton administration said it would seek authority from Congress to levy fines of up to $250,000 on scientists who violate federal human research rules, and $1 million on the universities that employ them.</p>
        <p>A23</p>
        <p>A Benefit From Caffeine  A study of 8,004 Japanese-American men in Hawaii suggests that coffee may prevent Parkinson's disease, with caffeine the main factor -- the more the better. But the researchers said it was uncertain whether their results would hold true with other ethnic groups and with women.</p>
        <p>A17</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-12</p>
        <p>Tour Company's License Is at Risk After Bus Fatality  City officials said they would ask a judge to suspend the license of New York Apple Tours, a day after one of its double-decker tour buses fatally struck a 71-year-old actor in Midtown. The accident renewed concerns about the company's long record of environmental, safety and traffic violations.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton Cites 'Differences'  Hillary Rodham Clinton said there were sharp differences between her and her new Republican opponent, Representative Rick A. Lazio, and she criticized him for saying he would accept the Independence Party's support, even if Patrick J. Buchanan were that party's presidential candidate.</p>
        <p>B5</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio criticized Mrs. Clinton for using ''chauffeured limousines,'' referring to her Secret Service escort. ''This is the way most New Yorkers travel,'' he said during a subway ride, though he was unsure of the cost of his borrowed MetroCard.</p>
        <p>B5</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>B11</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>B12</p>
        <p>Board Member's Second Job  Irving S. Hamer Jr., who is leading a Board of Education effort to integrate the Internet into the classroom, is co-chairman and a significant stockholder of a company trying out an Internet test-coaching program in city public schools. No laws have been broken, and officials say there is no conflict of interest because no contract is involved.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>College Enrollment Prediction  Enrollment will swell by some two million students -- to 19 million -- over the next 15 years, with black, Hispanic and Asian-American students accounting for 80 percent of the growth, a study said.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-12</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-8</p>
        <p>Indiana Takes Game 1  The Pacers beat the Knicks, 102-88, to take the early lead in the Eastern Conference Finals.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-24</p>
        <p>United-US Airways Deal  United is to announce today that it will acquire US Airways for $4.3 billion, creating a carrier with the biggest share of passengers from Boston to New York to Washington.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Time Warner Scheme  Southwestern Bell is to file complaints with the F.C.C. and Texas regulators today over a Time Warner scheme that used employees' bogus service requests to find where Southwestern Bell could provide high-speed Internet service in Houston. The complaint will also ask that the incident be reviewed in light of Time Warner's proposed merger with America Online. Time Warner said the effort was a local one and should not have been conducted.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Stocks Continue to Fall  The Nasdaq plunged to its lowest level in six months, as the broad stock market declined for a fifth consecutive day. The Nasdaq lost 199.66 points, or 5.9 percent, to 3,164.55; the Dow fell 120.28 points, or 1.1 percent, to 10,422.27; and the S.&amp; P. 500 slid 26.86, or 1.9 percent, to 1,373.86.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Suspicion in Japan  Tokyo's omission of an important piece of information on quarterly growth has invigorated critics in and out of government who have long contended that the ruling Liberal Democratic Party manipulates economic data for political reasons.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>DINING</p>
        <p>F1-10</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A24-25</p>
        <p>Editorials: Drug laws that destroy lives; Peru's tilted election landscape; Topics.  Columns: Paul Krugman, Maureen Dowd.</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E6  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E11  Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2  Weather</p>
        <p>D8</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
