<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>City to Ask Immediate Suspension of Bus Line After Fatality</title>
    <meta content="24APPL$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202023"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Buses</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Apple Tours</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Walker, Randolph</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chivers, C J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Forero, Juan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gould, Judith (Judge)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Buses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000524T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E3DC173DF937A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1363" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>City to Ask Immediate Suspension of Bus Line After Fatality</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By C. J. CHIVERS and JUAN FORERO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Forero, Juan; Chivers, C J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York City officials say that they will ask Administrative Law Judge Judith Gould to suspend license of New York Apple Tours immediately, day after one of its double-decker tour buses fatally struck 71-year-old pedestrian Randolph Walker in Midtown Manhattan, accident that once again set off concerns about New York Apple Tours and its long record of environmental, safety and traffic violations; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>City officials said yesterday that they would ask a judge to suspend the license of New York Apple Tours immediately, a day after one of its double-decker tour buses fatally struck a 71-year-old pedestrian in Midtown, an accident that once again set off concerns about a company with a long record of environmental, safety and traffic violations.</p>
        <p>New York Apple Tours, which operates scores of buses out of Midtown Manhattan, rapidly increased its business during the city's tourism boom of the 1990's, operating a sort of London-on-the-Hudson tour of New York from its familiar red double-decker buses.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>City officials said yesterday that they would ask a judge to suspend the license of New York Apple Tours immediately, a day after one of its double-decker tour buses fatally struck a 71-year-old pedestrian in Midtown, an accident that once again set off concerns about a company with a long record of environmental, safety and traffic violations.</p>
        <p>New York Apple Tours, which operates scores of buses out of Midtown Manhattan, rapidly increased its business during the city's tourism boom of the 1990's, operating a sort of London-on-the-Hudson tour of New York from its familiar red double-decker buses.</p>
        <p>But as the company has expanded, it has been the subject of a growing number of complaints, and since October the city's Department of Consumer Affairs has been trying to revoke its license, citing a pattern of abuses of city, state and federal laws.</p>
        <p>Deputy Mayor Joseph J. Lhota said yesterday that at the next regularly scheduled hearing in the matter, set for Thursday before Administrative Law Judge Judith Gould, the city would seek the immediate suspension of the company's license, pending the outcome of the case. In the accident on Monday, at Ninth Avenue and 45th Street, the driver was not licensed to operate a bus and was driving on a residential street where buses are generally not allowed.</p>
        <p>''We were moving against them because of the number of traffic violations and the number of accidents they have had,'' Mr. Lhota said. ''The tragedy yesterday is provoking us to take the revocation hearing that we are going for and ratchet it up.''</p>
        <p>The city's promise of action came as a second driver for the company was cited by the police for driving without a license in a case separate from the accident on Monday, which killed Randolph Walker, an actor.</p>
        <p>Patrick Dwyer, a lawyer for Apple Tours, said, ''Our hearts go out to the family and friends of the victim.'' The company could not discuss specific allegations, Mr. Dwyer said, but he said Apple Tours was cooperating with investigators looking into the accident. He also said the company adheres to safety regulations.</p>
        <p>''New York Apple Tour buses are inspected regularly and pass New York State Department of Transportation safety inspections every six months,'' he said. ''We have an excellent safety record, and our drivers go through a rigorous training course which includes a driving test, written test, video instruction and medical test.''</p>
        <p>Although the city's move to halt the company's operation immediately was welcomed by those who have long battled Apple Tours, many of them questioned why the administration took so long.</p>
        <p>In its nine years of operation, the company has been the source of continuous neighborhood and consumer complaints. Since 1996, the company has received 1,800 nonmoving violations and been in 140 accidents, Mr. Lhota said.</p>
        <p>It has also been cited by the state for circumventing vehicle safety inspections, and it pleaded guilty in Federal District Court last fall to claiming falsely that 70 double-decker buses imported from Britain did not have to comply with federal safety and environmental standards because the vehicles predated those regulations.</p>
        <p>''It's been a pitched battle since they started to do business in the City of New York,'' said State Senator Thomas Duane, who as a city councilman first proposed legislation in 1994 to keep the buses off residential streets. ''They've broken every rule and regulation they could possibly break. They have lied to the community and us. They've broken every promise. But the city continued to reward them, with more stops and more permits.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, since residents of Greenwich Village first complained in 1993 about the noise and pollution caused by the company's fleet, the list of objections and violations has continued to grow.</p>
        <p>In August 1995, the City Department of Consumer Affairs ordered the company to take all its buses off the streets after the company was accused of illegally switching permits at state inspections. The company's buses were back on the road after it paid a $100,000 fine and agreed, among other things, to remove its vice president, Harry Grant, as an officer.</p>
        <p>Then, in September, the company admitted to the United States attorney's office in Newark that it had lied about the ages of its vehicles to avoid meeting federal safety and environmental standards. The company, which was then based in Fort Lee, N.J., pleaded guilty to falsifying documents with three federal agencies, the Customs Service, the Department of Transportation and the Environmental Protection Agency.</p>
        <p>Apple Tours had told the agencies the buses were made in 1967 and were therefore exempt from federal safety and emissions standards, but the buses were actually newer. In a plea agreement, the company pledged to pay an $800,000 fine and bring its buses into compliance with federal emissions and safety standards.</p>
        <p>However, the company has not paid the fine. Under the plea agreement, the penalty is to be paid upon sentencing by Judge John W. Bissell of Federal District Court, but the company has not been sentenced because it has continued to dispute the terms of its plea agreement, said Michael Drewniak, a spokesman for the United States attorney's office in Newark.</p>
        <p>Past and current city officials said that the federal case in New Jersey gave the city the grounds to begin trying to put the company out of business, and that the accident on Monday strengthened its case.</p>
        <p>Jules Polonetsky, who was the city's commissioner of consumer affairs last fall when the case began, said New York Apple Tours had been the source of complaints for years.  But he said many were about pollution, parking or traffic violations, and because the department's mandate is to protect consumers, the complaints did not directly fall under its jurisdiction.</p>
        <p>But when the company admitted falsifying documents, he said, it allowed the city to assemble a much stronger case, incorporating the federal action with the hodge-podge of city and state complaints to show that the company was irresponsible and deceptive.</p>
        <p>''The new evidence of their smuggling buses into the county gave the department grounds to begin a serious license revocation action,'' Mr. Polonetsky said.</p>
        <p>Citing this action, Mr. Lhota said complaints from the community about the city's pace in seeking to close the business were unfounded. ''The long and the short of it is we actually are in a revocation hearing right now,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The administration's decisions came as another driver for New York Apple Tours was charged by the police. Police officials said that in response to Mr. Walker's death, the city's Traffic Control Division deployed a bus inspection team near Columbus Circle yesterday, and the officers arrested Richard Burks, 32, saying he was driving the double-decker bus with a suspended license.</p>
        <p>Mr. Burks, who was taken into custody at 3:10 p.m. as tourists were stepping off the bus at Central Park South and Seventh Avenue, was held overnight pending an arraignment today on charge of aggravated unlicensed operation of a vehicle, said Officer Louis A. Cruz, a department spokesman.</p>
        <p>And in addition to the action yesterday by the police and the mayor's office, the company also faces the possibility that it will be forced out of the city's tourism agency, which it joined in 1992 and to which it has been paying dues ever since.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
