<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>United Veteran Likely to Take Control</title>
    <meta content="Y24CHI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202027"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="AIRLINE DEAL: THE CHIEFS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Airlines Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Airlines</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leonhardt, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gangwal, Rakesh</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wolf, Stephen M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goodwin, James E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000524T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E0DC173DF937A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="862" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>United Veteran Likely to Take Control</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID LEONHARDT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Leonhardt, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>US Airways chief executive Rakesh Gangwal and chairman Stephen M Wolf are not expected to be part of new airline that will be formed when United Airlines acquires US Airways; James E Goodwin, chief of UAL Corp, parent of United Airlines, is expected to assume control; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two years ago, James E. Goodwin was a senior vice president at the UAL Corporation, the parent of United Airlines, with seemingly few prospects for career advancement. This morning, he sits atop a company that could become larger than any airline the world has ever known.</p>
        <p>A 33-year veteran of United with a down-to-earth style, Mr. Goodwin, who became chief executive of UAL last year, will oversee not only the largest airline in the world if the company's purchase of US Airways goes through but also one that suddenly has twice as many passengers in the Northeastern United States as any other airline.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Two years ago, James E. Goodwin was a senior vice president at the UAL Corporation, the parent of United Airlines, with seemingly few prospects for career advancement. This morning, he sits atop a company that could become larger than any airline the world has ever known.</p>
        <p>A 33-year veteran of United with a down-to-earth style, Mr. Goodwin, who became chief executive of UAL last year, will oversee not only the largest airline in the world if the company's purchase of US Airways goes through but also one that suddenly has twice as many passengers in the Northeastern United States as any other airline.</p>
        <p>Top management at US Airways, including Stephen M. Wolf, the chairman, and Rakesh Gangwal, the chief executive, are not expected to be a part of the combined company. Both had been with UAL -- Mr. Wolf, a chairman and chief executive for seven years until the 1994 employee buyout of United Airlines, which he had orchestrated, put him out of a job; Mr. Gangwal, in a number of senior posts.</p>
        <p>Mr. Goodwin, 55, joined United in 1967 as an accountant after graduating from Salem College in West Virginia. In the years that followed, he moved his wife, daughter and son from one city to another as he climbed through management jobs, eventually running United's maintenance center in San Francisco and then its overseas operations.</p>
        <p>By 1998 he was in charge of the airline's North American business, but his ascension seemed unlikely to continue. The chief executive at the time, Gerald Greenwald, planned to retire in 1999, and his hand-picked successor, John Edwardson, was UAL's president.</p>
        <p>But after Mr. Greenwald and Mr. Edwardson clashed on a number of issues with the company's powerful unions, which together own more than half of UAL, labor leaders blamed Mr. Edwardson. They saw him as a tough, conservative executive. With veto power over succession, they were able to prompt his resignation. Mr. Greenwald turned to Mr. Goodwin, who had a long track record of working with the unions, to be the next president.</p>
        <p>Even so, virtually nobody, including UAL executives, saw Mr. Goodwin as the leading candidate to become the next chief executive. He had little experience representing the company in public. Most insiders expected UAL to turn to an outsider -- much as it had chosen Mr. Greenwald, a former Chrysler vice chairman, in 1994 -- for its next boss.</p>
        <p>Indeed, UAL's board hired the executive recruitment firm Spencer Stuart to conduct a broad search, and the board eventually whittled the list down to one: Louis R. Hughes, a senior executive at General Motors.</p>
        <p>All the while, the tall, bearlike Mr. Goodwin was winning favorable reviews for his performance as president. He raised his profile by meeting with investors and members of Congress, and improved his public speaking , analysts said. He also worked with the airline's managers and unions to lift United's weak on-time performance.</p>
        <p>Given Mr. Hughes's somewhat rocky history of working with unions at G.M. and Mr. Goodwin's long track record working directly with union members at United, the representatives of the pilots' and machinists' unions on UAL's board made their preference clear. In March 1999, the board named Mr. Goodwin chief executive.</p>
        <p>Since then, he has tried to capitalize on his long history as an insider. ''He's much more hands-on and much more engaged with the employees than Greenwald was,'' said Glenn D. Engel, an airline analyst at Goldman, Sachs. ''He's very visible among the employees.''</p>
        <p>That visibility, and the early union backing, have not, however, translated into smooth labor relations.</p>
        <p>United's employee stock-ownership plan and current contracts, put in place in 1994 to rescue the airline, expire this year, and management and the unions have been negotiating to sign new contracts. The Air Line Pilots Association and UAL had said they wanted to agree on a new deal before the old one ran out, an almost unheard-of achievement in the airline industry. (Airline employees are required by law to continue to work and negotiate once a contract expires.) The two sides failed to do so, though, and last month had to ask a federal mediator to step in. In recent weeks, as some pilots have declined overtime work, United has had to cancel a number of flights; the union says the company is to blame, for failing to hire enough employees.</p>
        <p>The International Association of Machinists' contracts, for almost 50,000 workers, expire this summer.</p>
        <p>Mr. Goodwin's experience with the unions seems to have done little to help the tenor of the talks, analysts say. The pilots have even named Frederick Dubinsky, a combative labor leader who has handled previous negotiations with United, to lead them in the talks this time.</p>
        <p>Now, say analysts, with labor talks and a merger on the horizon, Mr. Goodwin, the chief executive who wasn't expected to be, faces the toughest test of any transportation executive in the country.</p>
        <p>AIRLINE DEAL: THE CHIEFS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
