<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Oops in Time Warner's Battle for Internet</title>
    <meta content="24NET" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Front Page; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202007"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Industrial Espionage</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Houston (Tex)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Time Warner Cable</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Road Runner (Co)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Southwestern Bell Telephone Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Communications Commission</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Labaton, Stephen</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas/Houston</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Espionage</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000524T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E5DD173DF937A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1011" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Oops in Time Warner's Battle for Internet</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN LABATON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Labaton, Stephen</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 23</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Time Warner Cable and its affiliated Internet service provider, Road Runner, offered their Houston area employees rewards for ordering and then cancelling high-speed Internet service from Southwestern Bell to locate areas competitor could and could not service; abruptly dropped incentives after two employees turned fliers advertising them over to Southwestern Bell; blames error of judgment by local managers, corrected when regional managers learned of effort; Southwestern Bell plans complaints to Federal Communications Commission and Texas Public Utilities Commission (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the annals of corporate espionage, the plot to learn about one of Time Warner's leading competitors in the fiercely competitive high-speed Internet market was not particularly subtle.</p>
        <p>A flier accompanying the paychecks of Time Warner Cable's Houston employees this month offered them a choice of free Internet service or the chance to win $100. ''To qualify,'' it said, ''we need your help in accomplishing our objective which is to locate areas in Houston that Southwestern Bell (our competitor) can and cannot service with their high-speed online service.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the annals of corporate espionage, the plot to learn about one of Time Warner's leading competitors in the fiercely competitive high-speed Internet market was not particularly subtle.</p>
        <p>A flier accompanying the paychecks of Time Warner Cable's Houston employees this month offered them a choice of free Internet service or the chance to win $100. ''To qualify,'' it said, ''we need your help in accomplishing our objective which is to locate areas in Houston that Southwestern Bell (our competitor) can and cannot service with their high-speed online service.''</p>
        <p>To get the reward, employees of Time Warner Cable and its affiliated Internet service provider, Road Runner, were instructed to call Southwestern Bell, order high-speed Internet service, cancel the order if it was confirmed, and report their results to an administrator in Time Warner Cable's Houston office.</p>
        <p>The ruse was apparently intended to find out precisely where the telephone company was technically able to offer Internet service and exploit any weaknesses in its market.</p>
        <p>But the incentives program ended abruptly last week after two employees turned the fliers over to Southwestern Bell, which then demanded an explanation from Time Warner.</p>
        <p>Time Warner said today that the effort was an error of judgment by local managers and was halted as soon as a regional executive learned of it. Nonetheless, Southwestern Bell says it will file complaints Wednesday with the Federal Communications Commission and the Texas Public Utilities Commission.</p>
        <p>The complaints will ask the regulators to open an investigation of the incident and force Time Warner to repay Southwestern Bell for its expenses in processing the orders, which can be as much as $370 for each order, plus legal costs. It also asks the federal regulators to examine the incident as part of the review of Time Warner's proposed merger with America Online, the nation's largest Internet service provider.</p>
        <p>The Time Warner program illustrates the lengths to which companies are going in the struggle for control over the high-speed Internet market, the new frontier in telecommunications. The nation's leading telephone and cable companies are investing hundreds of billions of dollars to compete for a nascent market that by all accounts will transform both the industry and the way consumers communicate and buy goods and services.</p>
        <p>Southwestern Bell's service, based on a technology called digital subscriber line, or DSL, can reach only those customers within 12,000 to 17,000 feet of a central office. But it is rolling out a costly new fiber optic pilot program, called Pronto, that could increase those distances and make it more competitive with cable Internet services.</p>
        <p>This afternoon Time Warner said that the intelligence effort was halted as soon as Ron McMillan, president of the Houston division of Time Warner Cable, learned about it and that it had violated the company's ethical standards.</p>
        <p>''We've looked into the situation and found out it was a local decision by a midlevel manager,'' said the statement from Time Warner's corporate headquarters in New York. ''As soon as management in Houston found out about it, they stopped it. It was a mistake and won't happen again.''</p>
        <p>Time Warner executives would not say how many employees received the flier, who started the program, or whether anyone has been disciplined over the incident. One executive said that about 20 employees called Southwestern Bell before the program was stopped, about a week after it started.</p>
        <p>Executives at Southwestern Bell said that Time Warner's program was not like the traditional kind of marketing intelligence done by most companies, who might, for instance, send an employee to check the prices and variety of a competitor's products. Rather, they said it was both anticompetitive and fraudulent, and that it might have been quite costly for Southwestern Bell.</p>
        <p>Unlike orders for traditional telephone service, the Internet service is expensive to process, costing the company as much as $370 in engineering and other expenses incurred by the time a customer gets a confirmation letter. Moreover, the program took place as Southwestern Bell, like other telephone and cable companies, is already being swamped by a backlog of legitimate orders and consumer demands for quicker and more reliable installation.</p>
        <p>''Our operating people are up in arms about this,'' said James D. Ellis, general counsel of SBC Communications, the parent of Southwestern Bell.</p>
        <p>The discovery of the Time Warner program is another possible public relations blow to the company -- after its short-lived decision to remove programming from ABC, a unit of the Walt Disney Company, from its cable systems during a contract dispute -- and it is certain to be seized upon by competitors.</p>
        <p>Indeed, in its filing with the F.C.C., SBC is expected to cite the episode as further evidence that regulators should require significant divestitures by America Online and Time Warner before approving their merger.</p>
        <p>''The actions apparently undertaken by Time Warner against Southwestern Bell in the Internet access market should be of particular concern to the commission since they come on the heels of Time Warner's unjustified actions in its recent dispute with Disney,'' Mr. Ellis said. ''While the Time Warner decision to cut off ABC programming in its dispute with Disney illustrated Time Warner's willingness to exercise its market power in a heavy-handed manner, this episode may illustrate its willingness to use underhanded tactics to improperly enhance its position in the broadband access market.''</p>
        <p>While they acknowledged that the company had erred, Time Warner executives said it would be inappropriate to use the episode to draw any broader conclusions about the proposed merger with AOL.</p>
        <p>''Our commitment to choice competition and innovation has been absolute and unchanged since the day our merger was announced,'' one executive said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
