<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Navratilova Returns, And Wins</title>
    <meta content="24TENN$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202079"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TENNIS: ROUNDUP"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Madrid Open (Tennis)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000524T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05EEDA173DF937A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="489" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Navratilova Returns, And Wins</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Opening round results of Madrid Open tennis tournament noted (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It looked as if Martina Navratilova had never retired.</p>
        <p>Back after five and a half years, Navratilova, 43, made an impressive return to professional tennis yesterday as she and South Africa's Mariaan de Swardt won their opening-round doubles match in the Madrid Open, beating Rika Hiraki of Japan and Meghann Shaughnessy of the United States, 6-3, 7-5, in 69 minutes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It looked as if Martina Navratilova had never retired.</p>
        <p>Back after five and a half years, Navratilova, 43, made an impressive return to professional tennis yesterday as she and South Africa's Mariaan de Swardt won their opening-round doubles match in the Madrid Open, beating Rika Hiraki of Japan and Meghann Shaughnessy of the United States, 6-3, 7-5, in 69 minutes.</p>
        <p>Afterward, Navratilova said she had been nerve racked, adding, ''I expected to have more fun than I did.''</p>
        <p>It was Navratilova's first preparation for a return to doubles at Wimbledon, where she has won 19 titles, one shy of the record. She also is scheduled to play doubles at the French Open next week.</p>
        <p>''I haven't come back,'' Navratilova said. ''I decided to play Wimbledon and I wanted to prepare for it. I never said I would never play doubles again. I retired from singles.'' (AP)</p>
        <p>STANFORD SWEEPS TO MEN'S TITLE: Stanford rallied to win the doubles and the Cardinal swept Virginia Commonwealth in the singles yesterday in Athens, Ga., to claim its 17th National Collegiate Athletic Association men's tennis title, 4-0.</p>
        <p>The unseeded Rams (27-5) appeared poised to win the doubles when Stanford's Ali Ansari and Scotty Scott closed fast to win at No. 3, 9-7, over the unrelated Sanchezes, Jose and Fernando. It was 13th title in the last 16 years for Stanford (28-1).</p>
        <p>Stanford ace Alex Kim, named the most outstanding player in the team tournament, defeated V.C.U.'s Daniel Andersson, 6-4, 6-2 at No. 1. (AP)</p>
        <p>AGASSI AND HINGIS SEEDED NO. 1: Andre Agassi and Martina Hingis were named as the top-seeded players for the French Open, the second Grand Slam of the season, which begins Monday in Paris. Agassi, who won last year's tournament, was seeded ahead of his fellow American Pete Sampras. Behind Hingis are Lindsay Davenport, Monica Seles and Venus Williams. (Bloomberg News)</p>
        <p>GERMANY BEATS U.S.: Pete Sampras lost to Tommy Haas, 7-5, 6-2, as Germany beat the United States, 2-1, at the World Team Cup in Dusseldorf, Germany. Sampras lost his second-straight match at this event and is 1-3 in his comeback from a thigh injury -- not an encouraging sign less than a week before the French Open. Haas had never beaten Sampras in four previous matches. Rainer Schuettler beat Vincent Spadea, 7-5, 3-6, 6-1, to secure Germany's victory even before the doubles. Alex O'Brien and Jared Palmer won the doubles for the single American point, defeating Haas and David Prinosil, 7-6 (3), 6-7 (5), 6-3. (AP)</p>
        <p>MEDVEDEV ADVANCES: Third-seeded Andrei Medvedev of Ukraine, sharpening his game for the French Open, beat Christophe Rochus of Belgium, 6-4, 6-4, to advance to the quarterfinals of the Raiffeisen Grand Prix in St. Polten, Austria. (AP)</p>
        <p>TENNIS: ROUNDUP</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
