<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; This Team Could Score With Nielsen</title>
    <meta content="24ARAT$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202064"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Indiana Pacers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Araton, Harvey</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Harvey Araton</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Indiana Pacers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000524T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E5DA173DF937A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="843" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; This Team Could Score With Nielsen</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HARVEY ARATON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Araton, Harvey</byline>
      <dateline>INDIANAPOLIS</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Harvey Araton Sports of The Times column on Indiana Pacers winning first game of NBA Eastern Conference championship playoff series against New York Knickerbockers; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT took one early play  Mark Jackson passing in the lane between his legs to Jalen Rose and Rose throwing outside to Austin Croshere for 3 -- to remind us how expressive and joyful this sport can be. It took one game to remember that basketball with offense can still be fierce, and how much the National Basketball Association owes the Knicks for saving it from more Miami Heat.</p>
        <p>On a night when no one could have blamed the bedraggled Knicks for waiting until tomorrow to compete, it took one electric second-quarter run for them to let the Pacers know they too have some weaponry to unload. After nearly climbing out of a 19-point hole, the Knicks faded and lost Game 1 of the Eastern Conference finals, 102-88. Don't worry, the Pacers know they are in for a long, draining series -- ''a dogfight,'' said Reggie Miller -- and one that will be infinitely easier on the eyes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT took one early play  Mark Jackson passing in the lane between his legs to Jalen Rose and Rose throwing outside to Austin Croshere for 3 -- to remind us how expressive and joyful this sport can be. It took one game to remember that basketball with offense can still be fierce, and how much the National Basketball Association owes the Knicks for saving it from more Miami Heat.</p>
        <p>On a night when no one could have blamed the bedraggled Knicks for waiting until tomorrow to compete, it took one electric second-quarter run for them to let the Pacers know they too have some weaponry to unload. After nearly climbing out of a 19-point hole, the Knicks faded and lost Game 1 of the Eastern Conference finals, 102-88. Don't worry, the Pacers know they are in for a long, draining series -- ''a dogfight,'' said Reggie Miller -- and one that will be infinitely easier on the eyes.</p>
        <p>It did get a tad pontifical during the last few days of the Knicks-Heat war, with those proclamations of its being the most hotly contested basketball since the invention of the ball. Though his expression didn't change, you could hear the snicker in Larry Bird's voice yesterday when he said, ''I can remember some pretty tough series that I played in, too.''</p>
        <p>Thank goodness there can still be a team that embodies Bird's creative soul. Mixing Rose and Croshere into the old, familiar Pacers' equation was too much for the Knicks in Game 1, with the court spread, the driving lanes open, the 3-pointers flying, with 10 connecting, with a half-dozen Pacers in double figures, with the eye-opening total of 32 assists.</p>
        <p>If you are David Stern, you like this team and are not worried about losing the New York market in the next round. If you are Stern, whom would you rather market to America next month -- Bird, possibly in Los Angeles against his most celebrated playing opponent, or Jeff Van Gundy? The Hall of Famer, who is about to ride off into the sunset, or the unglamorous lifer, who drove a Honda to work before it became a compacted movie prop in The Charter That Ate The Airport?</p>
        <p>''But people aren't going to see Larry Bird playing when they tune in,'' Jackson said, trying to debunk my inverted conspiracy theory. The New Yorker in him still can't forget the Larry Johnson 4-point nonsense of last spring, and worries what the league may be cooking up.</p>
        <p>New York is the preferred television market but the Pacers have this beautiful Conseco Fieldhouse, with its heartland history and cozy charm. They have Reggie, the 200-pound nerd who slips into a phone booth and transforms himself into the playoff assassin. They have a power forward named Dale and the center who looks as if they lifted him from one of the trophy cases with the 1950's memorabilia. Now they have the Sprewell-like Rose and this brash big kid, Croshere, who leaped off the bench and capped a 35-point first quarter with a circus shot and then lit up the perimeter the rest of the night.</p>
        <p>''I was telling him that Camby was their X factor last year and that he's going to have to do something this year,'' Miller said.</p>
        <p>Vast tracks of middle America can relate to these Pacers as the mom-and-pop shop who have been shut down four times now in the conference finals by the well-heeled superstore, by a young brute named Shaq and big-market bullies from Chicago and New York. After the Knicks left them earthbound and broken last spring, they traded the rugged Antonio Davis for a high school kid who collects his allowance and sits on the bench, but they somehow have emerged -- take note, Coach Riley -- as a more versatile team.</p>
        <p>The Knicks were just better last year, and Van Gundy outcoached Bird. Less than a great bench coach, Bird has nonetheless been a strong leader, the perfect image shaper for his home-state team as it built this special arena that should help keep the franchise humming against the big-market odds.</p>
        <p>Win or lose, Bird says this is it, three years and out. And if the Lakers do survive Portland and the Pacers make it out to Los Angeles next month, rest assured that Stern will be happy to live with the Pacers in the finals, with a posed shot of Bird and Magic, now a minority Lakers' owner, to beam around his global empire.</p>
        <p>It has never been a reach to think that an official might subconsciously be influenced by his own perception of what's good for the league. But that's where the conspiracy conversation should begin and end. The Pacers have nothing to worry about if they continue playing the way they did last night, and neither does Stern.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
