<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Troubled Survivor</title>
    <meta content="24COUP" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202000"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perez-Pena, Richard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Silver, Sheldon (Speaker)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bragman, Michael J (Assemblyman)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000524T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02EFDE173DF937A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1313" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Troubled Survivor</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD PEREZ-PENA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Perez-Pena, Richard</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, May 23</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>News analysis contends that failed coup attempt against NYS Assembly Speaker Sheldon Silver lays bare what everyone in Capitol has known for years: that many of his troops are deeply dissatisfied with his leadership; contends that Silver was politically weakened by Michael J Bragman's attempt to overthrow him (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>He has survived, for now. But the failed coup attempt against the Assembly speaker, Sheldon Silver, laid bare what everyone in the Capitol has known for years: that many of his troops are deeply dissatisfied with his leadership.</p>
        <p>Mr. Silver, a Manhattan Democrat, was weakened by the events of the last week, when the majority leader, Michael J. Bragman, tried to overthrow him, culminating in a floor debate Monday that aired much of the 98 Democrats' dirty laundry with jaw-dropping frankness.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>He has survived, for now. But the failed coup attempt against the Assembly speaker, Sheldon Silver, laid bare what everyone in the Capitol has known for years: that many of his troops are deeply dissatisfied with his leadership.</p>
        <p>Mr. Silver, a Manhattan Democrat, was weakened by the events of the last week, when the majority leader, Michael J. Bragman, tried to overthrow him, culminating in a floor debate Monday that aired much of the 98 Democrats' dirty laundry with jaw-dropping frankness.</p>
        <p>The question that legislators, aides and lobbyists were asking today was not just whether Mr. Silver could deal effectively with Gov. George E. Pataki and the State Senate in the remaining three weeks of this year's legislative session, but whether he would face a challenge -- from Mr. Bragman or someone else -- when it is time in December to elect a speaker for the next two years, and whether he could face down that challenge.</p>
        <p>''It's sink or swim time for him,'' one of Mr. Silver's closest advisers said today. ''He either changes things or he's gone.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Silver plans to embark on an intensive schmooze campaign to solidify his standing in the chamber, according to people close to him, and his allies predicted that he would learn from his mistakes and emerge stronger for the experience. But appearing vulnerable, as Mr. Silver has at times over the last week, can give ideas to pretenders to the throne.</p>
        <p>At a news conference today, Mr. Silver, flanked by dozens of colleagues who had sided with him in Monday's showdown, was more defiant than chastened. He declared it to be ''the time for healing,'' but a moment later added, ''We're committed to governing the house the way we see fit.'' Of Mr. Bragman, he said, ''We've cut the cancer out of the leadership team.''</p>
        <p>For most of the six years he has headed the Assembly, Mr. Silver has been the subject of the same complaints raised by Mr. Bragman: that he is secretive, that individual legislators are not involved in decision-making, that they are ordered around by the speaker's staff, that they have trouble gaining an audience with him, and that he informs them of positions they are expected to parrot, rather than seeking their opinions. Assembly members often ask reporters what is going on with their house's leadership, rather than vice versa, a situation that many of them find profoundly humiliating.</p>
        <p>Previous speakers may have been just as autocratic, but were more accessible, at least giving colleagues the impression that they were being listened to. Mr. Silver also suffers by comparison to the current Senate majority leader, Joseph L. Bruno, who by all accounts is more open and inclusive than his predecessors.</p>
        <p>Mr. Silver acknowledged the criticisms only obliquely today, and would not say if he accepted any of them. The Democratic majority, he said, would ''make a determination as to which, if any, of those items have any credibility.'' Asked if he would do anything differently in the future, he said, ''Yes, sir, absolutely,'' but the closest he came to specifics was to say that the Democrats would rule ''in a more open fashion.''</p>
        <p>When a reporter said 20 Assembly Democrats had voted against him, Mr. Silver, raising his voice, interrupted to say: ''First of all, there was 19, not 20. Number two, 80 percent said they were happy.''</p>
        <p>Not exactly. Yes, 78 of the 98 Democrats voted against Mr. Bragman's motion to suspend the rules and allow for removal of a speaker during the middle of a two-year term. But that did not mean they were happy with Mr. Silver's leadership.</p>
        <p>In fact, from the Assembly floor Monday, and in conversations with Assembly Democrats over the last two weeks, two of the most common views were these: right message, wrong messenger; and right message, wrong timing.</p>
        <p>''I, for one, Mr. Speaker, am not prepared to brush aside the issues that have been raised,'' Assemblyman Robert Ramirez, the powerful Bronx Democratic leader, said during Monday's debate, before voting against Mr. Bragman's motion.</p>
        <p>This is no mere case of inside baseball. Speakers have traditionally wielded nearly unquestioned authority over the Assembly, with the ability to pass or block legislation almost at will, and none have been overthrown by their own party in more than 60 years. In dealing with two Republicans, Mr. Pataki and Mr. Bruno, Mr. Silver is the only Democrat and the only representative of New York City in the Capitol's ruling triumvirate.</p>
        <p>If they see Mr. Silver's grasp on his house as weakened, the Republicans will be tempted to exploit the opening, appealing to the more conservative Assembly Democrats to make common cause with the 52 Republicans in the house to try to pass bills over his objections. More likely, the Democrats might simply be too distracted by their internal struggles to negotiate and pass bills of any kind, leaving major issues like gun control unresolved for the year.</p>
        <p>Republicans are already predicting that the Democrats' divisions will divert enough attention to weaken their efforts on behalf of Hillary Rodham Clinton's Senate campaign.</p>
        <p>Some Democrats said they opposed Mr. Bragman's coup effort for that reason alone, saying he should have waited until the biennial election of a speaker this December.</p>
        <p>Assemblyman Roger L. Green, a Brooklyn Democrat, referred to the dissidents' list of grievances. ''There's only two issues I disagree with,'' he said. ''But this is not the time.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bragman's greatest weakness in his power move is his own reputation. Far from being thought of by his colleagues as an agent of reform, he is seen as a relentless arm-twister, deal-maker and fund-raiser who has been friendly with the tobacco and gun industries. Mr. Bragman scoffed publicly at his downstate colleagues' tooth-and-nail battle to preserve rent regulations in 1997, and is seen by liberals as insufficiently committed to abortion rights.</p>
        <p>Assemblyman Scott M. Stringer, a Manhattan Democrat, conceded today that he had often been critical of Mr. Silver. But he added, ''As a New York City Democrat, the notion that a coup is going to be brought upon us and elect a pro-gun, anti-tenant speaker to me is unacceptable.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Silver and his defenders assert, with some justification, that, playing defense against a Republican governor, the speaker has won several important legislative victories, like increased school aid, prekindergarten classes for 4-year-olds, preservation of the rent laws and a major new effort to provide health insurance for the uninsured. But his allies concede that he has at times been ineffectual in battles over public opinion.</p>
        <p>The speaker has also attracted criticism for involvement in politics beyond the Capitol walls. He worked to undermine Peter F. Vallone, the Democratic candidate for governor in 1998, and has been viewed by some critics as doing the same thing to the state comptroller, H. Carl McCall, who is laying the groundwork for a run for governor in 2002. In fact, Democratic officials say Mr. Silver has signaled that he and his aides will no longer work behind the scenes to promote the gubernatorial prospects of Andrew Cuomo, the federal housing secretary.</p>
        <p>All indications are that Mr. Silver has not routinely committed one of the sins that the dissidents attributed to him: strong-arming people into following his orders. Veteran legislators say he has been less punitive than his predecessors, sometimes to his detriment. Reports of Mr. Bragman's maneuvering for power surfaced in 1996, but Mr. Silver left him in place as majority leader.</p>
        <p>''While other people have said it to me over and over again during the four years, I chose not to believe it,'' Mr. Silver said. ''In hindsight, I'm guilty of one thing: probably being an optimist and a nice guy.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
