<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Chase, the Eager Acquirer, To Buy Investment Boutique</title>
    <meta content="Y24DEA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202020"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Beacon Group</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Chase Manhattan Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holson, Laura M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Boisi, Geoffrey T</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lee, James Bainbridge Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000524T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E4DC173DF937A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="769" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Chase, the Eager Acquirer, To Buy Investment Boutique</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAURA M. HOLSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Holson, Laura M</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Chase Manhattan acquires Beacon Group, private Manhattan investment and advisory firm founded in early 1990's by group of former Goldman, Sachs deal makers; terms undisclosed; Chase plans to name Beacon's founder, Geoffrey T Boisi as vice chairman and head of investment banking, replacing James Bainbridge Lee Jr (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Chase Manhattan has agreed to acquire the Beacon Group, a private Manhattan investment and advisory firm founded in the early 1990's by a group of former Goldman, Sachs deal makers.</p>
        <p>The terms of the deal were not disclosed. But Chase plans to name Beacon's founder, Geoffrey T. Boisi, a former Goldman banker who once held the No. 3 executive position there, as a vice chairman and head of investment banking, replacing the sometimes outspoken James Bainbridge Lee Jr. Mr. Lee, who started the investment banking department at Chase 18 years ago, said he wanted to spend more time with his family and his banking clients.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Chase Manhattan has agreed to acquire the Beacon Group, a private Manhattan investment and advisory firm founded in the early 1990's by a group of former Goldman, Sachs deal makers.</p>
        <p>The terms of the deal were not disclosed. But Chase plans to name Beacon's founder, Geoffrey T. Boisi, a former Goldman banker who once held the No. 3 executive position there, as a vice chairman and head of investment banking, replacing the sometimes outspoken James Bainbridge Lee Jr. Mr. Lee, who started the investment banking department at Chase 18 years ago, said he wanted to spend more time with his family and his banking clients.</p>
        <p>The acquisition is the latest in a recent series that Chase, the giant New York-based banking company, has embarked on in an effort to expand its mergers-and-acquisitions talent pool and shore up its investment banking operations.</p>
        <p>Last year, Chase executives actively courted brokerage firms hoping for a blockbuster combination. With none in sight, Chase began snapping up smaller companies. In April, it announced the $7.7 billion acquisition of Robert Fleming Holdings, the British-based investment management firm with operations in Asia as well as Europe. And in December, it bought the San Francisco-based Hambrecht &amp; Quist with the hope of gaining more equity business in lucrative technology industries.</p>
        <p>''We feel good about these deals,'' said William B. Harrison Jr., Chase Manhattan's chairman. ''They fit. They are smart.''</p>
        <p>Since opening its doors in 1993, Beacon has attracted a roster of prominent deal makers, including David Coulter, the former president of the Bank of America, who was ousted a year and a half ago when the company was acquired by NationsBank.</p>
        <p>''We were growing by leaps and bounds,'' Mr. Boisi said. The 14 partners there were at a point where they had to either grow larger or stay small. ''We did a lot of soul-searching in recent days.''</p>
        <p>In fact, the move may be as interesting for Mr. Boisi as it is for Chase. Mr. Boisi, 53, will now compete head to head with rivals at the Goldman Sachs Group, where he started his Wall Street career. He joined Goldman as a summer intern in 1970 and in 10 years worked his way up to become head of mergers and acquisitions. (He still keeps a photograph of Goldman's weekend football team from those days on the wall of his office.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Boisi advised on some of the biggest deals of recent years, including the pairing of Texaco and Getty Oil as well as the Philip Morris acquisition of General Foods.</p>
        <p>In the mid-1980's, he was promoted to head of investment banking and oversaw Goldman's expansion abroad, including founding the global finance department in 1987. But in 1991, he left Goldman to focus on One-to-One, a national charity he co-founded that matches disadvantaged youths with adult mentors. It has since been renamed the National Mentoring Partnership.</p>
        <p>At the time, Mr. Boisi, then 44, said he wanted to spend more time with his family. But Wall Street executives speculated then that he left because it would be several years, if at all, before he would be considered for Goldman's top spot.</p>
        <p>It did not take long for him to return to Wall Street. In 1993, Mr. Boisi started Beacon with a group of former Goldman partners who specialized in niche areas.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lee, for his part, will focus on what he likes to do best: cutting checks and deals. He has been largely responsible for expanding Chase's syndicated-loan business, helping finance blockbuster deals like last year's $34 billion takeover of Telecom Italia by Olivetti, and the pending $58 billion acquisition of the MediaOne Group, the big cable company, by AT&amp;T.</p>
        <p>''You can't overestimate how hard it is to run one of these large investment banks, given the world is in Internet time,'' Mr. Lee said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Harrison said it was only in recent months that he had approached Mr. Boisi, whom he has known for a few years and who has advised Chase on deals.</p>
        <p>Over the next several months, Beacon's 120 employees will be integrated into Chase's private banking, mergers and acquisitions and wealth management departments. The deal is expected to close on July 1.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
