<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TRANSACTIONS</title>
    <meta content="24TRAN$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202080"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000524T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04EEDA173DF937A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1273" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TRANSACTIONS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
        <p>Major League Baseball  MLB--Suspended Seattle Mariner INF Mark McLemore for five games and fined him an undisclosed amount for an on-field altercation during a game against Tampa Bay on May 20.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
        <p>Major League Baseball  MLB--Suspended Seattle Mariner INF Mark McLemore for five games and fined him an undisclosed amount for an on-field altercation during a game against Tampa Bay on May 20.</p>
        <p>American League  CHICAGO WHITE SOX--Activated C Brook Fordyce from the 15-day disabled list. Recalled RHP Kip Wells from Charlotte of the International League. Sent C Josh Paul to Charlotte. Designated RHP Tanyon Sturtze for assignment.  MINNESOTA TWINS--Claimed 3B Casey Blake off waivers from the Toronto Blue Jays and assigned him to Salt Lake City of the Pacific Coast League. Designated LHP Benj Sampson for release or assignment.  TAMPA BAY DEVIL RAYS--Activated RHP Jim Mecir from the 15-day disabled list. Optioned RHP Cory Lidle to Durham of the International League.  TEXAS RANGERS--Recalled OF Gabe Kapler from Oklahoma of the Pacific Coast League.  TORONTO BLUE JAYS--Sent LHP Eric Gunderson outright to Syracuse of the International League.</p>
        <p>National League  PHILADELPHIA PHILLIES--Called up INF-OF Pat Burrell from Scranton-Wilkes-Barre of the International League.</p>
        <p>Texas League  SHREVEPORT CAPTAINS--Announced the sale of the team at the end of the season.</p>
        <p>Midwest League  KANE COUNTY COUGARS--Announced INF David Paulino has been transferred to the Florida Marlins extended spring training camp and Florida has reassigned INF Drew Niles to Kane County from Portland of the Eastern League.</p>
        <p>Northern League  NEW JERSEY JACKALS--Released P Mike Riveles and OF Wilton Person. Placed INF Josh Brinkley and P John Mangieri on the inactive list.</p>
        <p>BASKETBALL</p>
        <p>National Basketball Association  NBA--Fined Portland Trail Blazer F Rasheed Wallace $10,000 for failing to make himself available to the media during designated media interview periods and Portland $25,000 for failing to ensure its players comply with NBA media interview rules.</p>
        <p>Women's National Basketball Association  SACRAMENTO MONARCHS--Waived C Heather Quella and F Jess Zinobile.</p>
        <p>FOOTBALL</p>
        <p>National Football League  ATLANTA FALCONS--Released WR Chris Calloway. Signed WR Mareno Philyaw.  DENVER BRONCOS--Signed LB Ricardo McDonald and G Ian Beckles.  HOUSTON--Named Paul Russell college scout for the southeastern region.  MIAMI DOLPHINS--Signed QB Mike Quinn to a one-year contract.  PHILADELPHIA EAGLES--Named Lance Carl college scout for the west coast and Richard Shelton college scout for the southeast and southwest.</p>
        <p>Canadian Football League  CALGARY STAMPEDERS--Agreed to terms with QB Mike Moschetti. Deleted WR Marcus Dowdell and RB Jaime Kimbrough from the roster.  EDMONTON ESKIMOS--Signed LB Singor Mobley.  HAMILTON TIGER-CATS--Signed LB Phillip Thompson, Jr. and DT Doug Madoski.  MONTREAL ALOUETTES--Signed QB Reggie Slack.  SASKATCHEWAN ROUGHRIDERS--Signed WR Dylan Ching and WR Hudson Clark.</p>
        <p>arenafootball2  ROANOKE STEAM--Released QB Al Clark.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
        <p>National Hockey League  COLUMBUS BLUE JACKETS--Named Stacey Segal manager of community development and Colleen Tedrow administrative assistant.  NASHVILLE PREDATORS--Claimed F Sean Haggerty and F Mike Watt off waivers from the New York Islanders.  ISLANDERS--Acquired RW Trent Hunter from the Anaheim Mighty Ducks for a 2000 fourth-round entry draft pick.</p>
        <p>International Hockey League  CHICAGO WOLVES--Announced the return of C Derek Plante to the team.</p>
        <p>East Coast Hockey League  JACKSON BANDITS--Re-signed LW Brian Callahan.  TOLEDO STORM--Announced it has ended its affiliation with the Tampa Bay Lightning. Fired Todd Gordon, coach.  Western Professional Hockey League  FORT WORTH BRAHMAS--Signed C Sean Brady.</p>
        <p>SOCCER</p>
        <p>Major League Soccer  DALLAS BURN--Placed MF Mark Santel on injured reserve.</p>
        <p>COLLEGEs</p>
        <p>AUBURN--Announced sophomore DB Brandon Reed has been dismissed from the football team for violating team rules.  CALIFORNIA--Named Brad Agoos men's assistant soccer coach.  COLLEGE OF CHARLESTON--Named Phil Kahn men's assistant basketball coach.  DELAWARE--Named Jim Sherman baseball coach.  DOWLING--Named Tim Boyle men's lacrosse coach and Noreen Duffy women's assistant basketball coach.  DUKE--Promoted Joanna Sparkman to associate director of sports information.  IOWA--Named Meaghan Nitka assistant women's field hockey coach.  LEHMAN--Named Steven Schulman men's basketball coach.  MEDIALLE--Named Jim Koerner baseball coach, John Malark softball coach and Jamie Fiegel women's lacrosse coach.  NEBRASKA--Named Mark Manning wrestling coach.  PLYMOUTH STATE--Named Keith Byrnes men's soccer coach.  STEPHEN F. AUSTIN--Named Mike Hopson men's golf coach.  SYRACUSE--Named Brian Gunning assistant director of athletic communications.  TIFFIN--Named Brian Campbell softball coach.  YOUNGSTOWN STATE--Announced the resignation of Derek Kellogg, men's assistant basketball coach.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
