<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For a Favorite Son, Allegiance on Display</title>
    <meta content="17CONN$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223231"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vice Presidents and Vice Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Haven (Conn)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zielbauer, Paul</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lieberman, Joseph I (Sen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/Joseph I Lieberman</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut/New Haven</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vice Presidents and Vice Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000817T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E1D8173EF934A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="645" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For a Favorite Son, Allegiance on Display</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAUL ZIELBAUER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zielbauer, Paul</byline>
      <dateline>NEW HAVEN, Aug. 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article notes that while New Haven's most famous resident, Senator Joseph I Lieberman, appeared tonight before Democratic Party delegates and national television audience, many supporters back in Connecticut gathered to watch and cheer him and share what they say is visceral sense of pride (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>While New Haven's most famous resident, Senator Joseph I. Lieberman, appeared tonight before Democratic Party delegates and a national television audience, many supporters back in Connecticut gathered to watch and cheer him and share what they said was a visceral sense of pride.</p>
        <p>''It's a special feeling,'' said State Representative Michael P. Lawlor, one of about 80 Democrats gathered at Tycoons, a corner bar here, to eat chicken wings and watch the speech on a rented large-screen television.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>While New Haven's most famous resident, Senator Joseph I. Lieberman, appeared tonight before Democratic Party delegates and a national television audience, many supporters back in Connecticut gathered to watch and cheer him and share what they said was a visceral sense of pride.</p>
        <p>''It's a special feeling,'' said State Representative Michael P. Lawlor, one of about 80 Democrats gathered at Tycoons, a corner bar here, to eat chicken wings and watch the speech on a rented large-screen television.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Lieberman strode on stage in Los Angeles and the applause there and in the New Haven bar crescendoed, Mr. Lawlor added derisively, ''Did this happen with Dick Cheney?'' The bar party was given by State Senator Martin M. Looney, Democrat of New Haven, who invited every party member he could find.</p>
        <p>''It's a sense of celebration,'' Mr. Looney said between backslaps. ''This is the first time we've had anyone from Connecticut on the presidential ticket.'' Tonight's gathering, he went on, was to acknowledge ''a sense of community and a sense of shared pride and getting ready for the hard work ahead.''</p>
        <p>As Mr. Lieberman spoke of his family background and hammered away at the policies of his Republican opponents, the partisan crowd here cheered, sometimes longer and seemingly louder than the delegates in Los Angeles. On the walls of the bar were several hand-drawn posters announcing ''Liebermania'' and ''Mazel Tov, Joe.''</p>
        <p>During the speech, Norma Rodriguez-Reyes, another New Haven Democrat, beamed with pride. ''It was really intense,'' she said afterward. ''I felt like we were part of the convention. I felt as if we were all part of one big family here. This was a time when no one recognizes any difference between us.'' Her favorite line, she said, came when Mr. Lieberman acknowledged that ''behind every successful man, there's a surprised mother-in-law.''</p>
        <p>James D. Newton, a former New Haven mayoral candidate, clapped enthusiastically for Mr. Lieberman as he left the stage. ''Joe Lieberman made a powerful speech tonight,'' he said. ''I think he made it very clear that there is a racial divide that separates people in this country.''</p>
        <p>Like many others here, Philip Voigt, a New Haven alderman, said he had come because of a mixture of personal and political allegiance to Mr. Lieberman. ''We've seen Joe move from being attorney general to United States senator,'' he said. ''One of our own being selected for vice president, it's real personal pride.'' And besides, he said, ''Joe's son is in my wife's synagogue.''</p>
        <p>A few miles down Interstate 95, in the Stamford living room of Alex and Vita Lionetti, 10 of the senator's former Stamford High School classmates were holding their own Joe Lieberman party. Everyone had known Mr. Lieberman since he won the ninth-grade class presidency, a year before he was voted king of the sophomore sock hop, which he did not attend because of measles.</p>
        <p>To prepare for this evening's speech, the Lionettis laid out an array of cheeses and crackers on red, white and blue napkins and paper plates and posted a few American flags and old photographs of Mr. Lieberman on the walls. ''We got a little patriotic,'' Mr. Lionetti admitted. As 10 p.m. drew closer, everyone paged through high school yearbooks and settled in for a large, nationally televised dose of Joe.</p>
        <p>''It was a great speech for Joe Lieberman, to try to let people understand who he is,'' Mr. Lionetti said after Mr. Lieberman left the stage. ''The family items were probably the most telling,'' he said. ''Sometimes you don't really hear him say a lot about himself. I think a lot of people like to know the guts of a person, and I think they really got to know Joe Lieberman as a caring person.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
