<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Finding Ways to Rehearse Without Being Cursed; Musicians Improvise, and Go High-Tech, In Search of Places to Practice Their Riffs</title>
    <meta content="17PRAC$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223276"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Noise</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dewan, Shaila K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Noise</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000817T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E0D7173EF934A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1425" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Finding Ways to Rehearse Without Being Cursed; Musicians Improvise, and Go High-Tech, In Search of Places to Practice Their Riffs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SHAILA K. DEWAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dewan, Shaila K</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses perennial problem facing most New York musicians in finding suitable place to practice their craft without incurring wrath of neighbors; several musicians discuss their experiences; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For most New York musicians, practicing without the interruption of a broom handle banging on the ceiling is a perennial problem. Practice rooms are expensive, and there are only so many rooftops. So the solutions have become more and more creative, from using high-tech gizmos to funnel an instrument's sound into headphones to retreating to the privacy of a boat deck.</p>
        <p>The musicians tramping up and down the narrow stairway of Smalls, a jazz club in a Greenwich Village basement, readily grouse about the practice problem. ''People will almost never complain about a TV,'' said John Mosca, a trombonist who leads the Vanguard Jazz Orchestra and has been evicted from an Upper West Side apartment for soundproofing the floor. ''It's an inalienable right. But about practicing, people will complain immediately.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For most New York musicians, practicing without the interruption of a broom handle banging on the ceiling is a perennial problem. Practice rooms are expensive, and there are only so many rooftops. So the solutions have become more and more creative, from using high-tech gizmos to funnel an instrument's sound into headphones to retreating to the privacy of a boat deck.</p>
        <p>The musicians tramping up and down the narrow stairway of Smalls, a jazz club in a Greenwich Village basement, readily grouse about the practice problem. ''People will almost never complain about a TV,'' said John Mosca, a trombonist who leads the Vanguard Jazz Orchestra and has been evicted from an Upper West Side apartment for soundproofing the floor. ''It's an inalienable right. But about practicing, people will complain immediately.''</p>
        <p>Knowing that is the case, Mitchell Borden, the proprietor of Smalls, extends the come-one, come-all largess he offers customers ($10 for 10 hours of music, plus free soft drinks) to the jazz cats who play there. The club, which used to be a restaurant, came with a walk-in refrigerator, coincidentally soundproof, where Mr. Borden now keeps a piano. Musicians practice there at all hours, even during performances. Mr. Borden also keeps a large black book in which musicians can sign up to use the club as a free rehearsal hall during the day. He is, Mr. Mosca says, a saint.</p>
        <p>But such generosity is rare. Practice rooms, $25 an hour at a minimum, are out of reach for many musicians who need a few hours a day to do the kind of bleating musical calisthenics that build fine motor skills but can induce migraines in involuntary listeners.</p>
        <p>Some musicians are lucky. Marco Katz hasn't rented a practice room since 1988, when he moved into his 1969 Nautaline houseboat, the Misty. Mr. Katz, 48, a freelance trombonist who often plays in schools, said the boat is an ideal place to have jam sessions. But not because he can motor the boat out of earshot -- it doesn't run. Rather, he said, it's because the ''characters'' who surround him at the 79th Street Boat Basin, where the Misty is docked, have a live-and-let-live attitude. One neighbor used to come over and bang on the door during rehearsals, Mr. Katz recalled. ''He'd say, 'I have a complaint about the music. You guys aren't playing loud enough.' ''</p>
        <p>Another time, Mr. Katz said, his jazz quartet was playing on the marina's wave wall at sunset, when a sailboat full of tourists disembarked. ''Just another service offered to you by the city of New York,'' he told them. One guy laid a twenty on them.</p>
        <p>A friend of Mr. Katz's, Johannes Pfannkuch, 39, has another kind of retreat, thanks to a longstanding deal with the West End Presbyterian Church on 105th Street and Amsterdam Avenue. In exchange for playing at church services once in a while, Mr. Pfannkuch, a classical trombonist, practices in the sanctuary or the choir room almost every day, sometimes with his Meridian Brass Quintet. ''I can play loud, which is something you have to do once in a while,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The church has a bonus feature: remarkable acoustics.</p>
        <p>Mr. Katz's boat reminded Rod Baltimore, an old-timer in the music world who owns International Woodwinds and Brass on 48th Street, of practicing hi-jinks that crossed the line to criminal trespassing. Two musicians, a clarinetist and a saxophonist, once unmoored a construction barge under the George Washington Bridge and went floating down the Hudson, playing away, Mr. Baltimore said. ''Before they got killed, the Coast Guard had to rescue them.''</p>
        <p>Another clarinetist, Mr. Baltimore remembered, took a rowboat to the middle of the Central Park Reservoir to practice late one night. Some weeks later, walking through the park, the man was chased by the mounted police, who asked him if he had been the culprit. ''He said, 'No, I don't even swim. I'm afraid of rowboats.' ''</p>
        <p>Mr. Baltimore himself used to break into the basement pool of the Paris Hotel on West 97th Street, which used to close at 10 p.m. ''Nobody ever came down there, and we never got caught,'' he said. ''Then we'd go swimming.''</p>
        <p>But the most legendary example of resourceful practicing is Sonny Rollins's tenor sax sessions on the Williamsburg Bridge, atop a pedestrian walkway out of view of the cars. In 1959, at an early peak in his fame, Mr. Rollins abruptly stopped playing public concerts so he could ''get something under my fingers,'' Mr. Rollins, 69, said by phone from Berkeley, Calif.</p>
        <p>He played al fresco on the bridge, warmed by Cognac in cold weather, because he did not want to disturb the neighbors in his apartment building on Grand Street. And he liked the anonymity.</p>
        <p>''People would walk right by and they didn't hardly look at me,'' he said. ''You know how sophisticated New Yorkers are. It was perfect.''</p>
        <p>It was also inspiring. In 1962, Mr. Rollins released an album called ''The Bridge,'' and the romantic notion of a celebrated musician practicing, unrecognized, became the stuff of articles, short stories and documentary films.</p>
        <p>But some practice solutions are born of desperation, not inspiration. For those without a church or a boat at their disposal, standing with one's face buried in the coat closet can become tiresome. Susan Stoderl, 48, said she and her husband, both opera singers, had dealt with the problem for a combined 79 years, hanging tapestries in their bathroom to muffle the sound or singing in the car. But then they found their savior: a deaf landlady.</p>
        <p>''A singer told me about the apartment,'' said Ms. Stoderl, who is co-director of a small company called Opera Nova and who moved in above the landlady in Astoria, Queens, nine years ago. ''I've had full-scale opera rehearsals there.''</p>
        <p>''When she does have her hearing aid in,'' Ms. Stoderl said of the apartment's owner, ''she's just happy to have a good tenant.''</p>
        <p>Musicians who can afford it have chosen a more high-tech route. Kamau Adilifu, a trumpeter who has played in ''The Wild Party,'' ''Guys and Dolls'' and other Broadway hits, has outfitted his Upper West Side high-rise apartment with a $3,000 soundproof glass booth called the Whisper Room.</p>
        <p>Barely big enough for a chair and music stand, it looks like a small radio station booth. When he's inside playing, it's impossible to hear more than a faint melody. He said it was a priority for him not to bother his neighbors or his wife.</p>
        <p>''I've always been very self-conscious about playing the trumpet,''  Mr. Adilifu said softly. ''Much of what I practice, it's not necessarily musical. It's the physical aspects of playing trumpet.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Adilifu said he bought the Whisper Room because he liked to practice at night. ''That's when the muse struck me,'' he said.</p>
        <p>In addition to the Whisper Room, Mr. Adilifu has a newer gadget, Silent Brass, that fits into the bell of his horn, silencing it and channeling the sound into headphones. It can alter the music to make it sound as if it's being played in a church or a concert hall. ''The freedom that it gives me more than compensates for what it lacks in realism,'' Mr. Adilifu said. But it doesn't work for every kind of instrument; saxophones, for example, emit sounds through the finger holes, not just the bell.</p>
        <p>Back in the stairwell at Smalls, as the musicians discussed whether to have a drink or a jam session, a few pointed out that someone who really wanted to practice would find a way.</p>
        <p>But most reminisced about the good old days, when downtown lofts came without plumbing, but also without neighbors, and no one had ever heard of a noise ordinance.</p>
        <p>Mr. Borden seemed of the opinion that even the music, back then, was better.</p>
        <p>His theory: ''There's gotta be a reason why there's such a big rift between good music and music that's considered good now. Maybe that's it. There's no place to practice.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
