<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>McCain Discloses New Case Of Malignant Melanoma</title>
    <meta content="Y17MCC$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223224"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Skin</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Melanoma</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccain, John (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Alvarez, Lizette</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Skin Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tumors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Skin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000817T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E3D8173EF934A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="763" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>McCain Discloses New Case Of Malignant Melanoma</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIZETTE ALVAREZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Alvarez, Lizette</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Aug. 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sen John S McCain is diagnosed with two new sites of malignant melanoma, deadliest and most aggressive form of skin cancer; McCain cancels several campaign stops on behalf of Gov George W Bush in order to undergo further testing; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Malignant melanoma, a potentially severe form of skin cancer, has been diagnosed on the left temple and arm of Senator John McCain, the Arizona Republican and former presidential candidate, his aides said today.</p>
        <p>Aides said Mr. McCain, who was  treated for malignant melanoma in 1993 when doctors removed a mole from his shoulder, was scheduled to undergo more tests on Thursday and Friday at the Mayo Clinic in Scottsdale, Ariz., and did not yet know whether the cancer had spread.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Malignant melanoma, a potentially severe form of skin cancer, has been diagnosed on the left temple and arm of Senator John McCain, the Arizona Republican and former presidential candidate, his aides said today.</p>
        <p>Aides said Mr. McCain, who was  treated for malignant melanoma in 1993 when doctors removed a mole from his shoulder, was scheduled to undergo more tests on Thursday and Friday at the Mayo Clinic in Scottsdale, Ariz., and did not yet know whether the cancer had spread.</p>
        <p>His office said in a statement that after this week's tests were completed, Mr. McCain would discuss with doctors how best to treat the cancer, which can range from minor surgery, if the cancer is caught early, to chemotherapy, in the disease's later stages. Malignant melanoma is the deadliest and most aggressive form of skin cancer and the least common, but if caught early, it is highly curable.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCain, 63, who had been expected to campaign this fall for Gov. George W. Bush of Texas in his presidential bid and for Republican Congressional candidates, will go ahead with a scheduled campaign appearance for Senator Mike DeWine in Ohio on Sunday. But Mr. McCain has canceled other campaign stops, including a few for House members in New Jersey, Ohio and Washington State.</p>
        <p>The skin growths were first detected during a routine examination on Aug. 2, his office said. He underwent biopsies at the National Naval Medical Center in Bethesda, Md., the next day. That night he joined Governor Bush on stage after Mr. Bush accepted the Republican presidential nomination, and the next day, Aug. 4, Mr. McCain was told that the two spots were malignant.</p>
        <p>Since his 1993 brush with cancer, Mr. McCain had been closely monitored by doctors, who periodically removed suspicious moles or lesions from his skin. Most of these lesions consisted of basal cell carcinoma, the least worrisome and most common type of skin cancer. Doctors had declared him cured last year, since his cancer had not recurred in more than five years.</p>
        <p>''I spent too much time in the sun, and every few months I have to go and have some basal cells removed from my old craggy features,'' Mr. McCain told CNN recently, before one of his periodic checkups.</p>
        <p>In December, while campaigning for president, Mr. McCain released reams of medical records. The records showed he had a malignant mole removed from his shoulder.</p>
        <p>Skin cancer is often caused by sunburn and is more common among fair-skinned, fair-haired people.</p>
        <p>David Becker, an assistant professor of dermatology at Weill-Cornell University Medical Center, said such frequent monitoring by doctors was likely to help Mr. McCain's prognosis since so much depended on how quickly doctors detected the cancer. It is crucial for doctors to spot the cancer before it penetrates the skin and enters the body.</p>
        <p>''There has been pretty good evidence that people closely monitored have melanoma caught at an early stage,'' Dr. Becker said.</p>
        <p>But malignant melanoma can be extremely aggressive, spreading quickly. And once it has spread, the cancer is difficult to treat because it does not respond well to radiation or chemotherapy.</p>
        <p>The American Cancer Society estimates that 47,700 American would be diagnosed with melanoma this year, and 7,700 would die.</p>
        <p>For Mr. McCain, the news of his cancer came amidst the euphoria following the end of the Republican National Convention in Philadelphia, where Mr. McCain was photographed with a small bandage on his temple.</p>
        <p>When Mr. McCain abruptly disappeared from the convention after his speech on Aug. 1, there were questions about his commitment to Mr. Bush, his one-time Republican primary rival.</p>
        <p>But Mr. McCain returned to the convention on Aug. 3, and then joined Mr. Bush on the campaign trail last Thursday, at which point he already knew he had been diagnosed with cancer. Last Saturday, Mr. Bush and his wife, Laura, spent the night at Mr. McCain's Arizona ranch.</p>
        <p>''We just came back from a visit to John and Cindy's home and our fondest thoughts are with him and his family,'' Mr. Bush said today in a statement. ''John is a good man and a fighter. He is in our prayers as he battles this illness.''</p>
        <p>Vice President Al Gore also said he was praying for Mr. McCain's recovery. ''One thing about him is he is so courageous,'' Mr. Gore said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
