<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE MARKETS: Market Place; With oil prices increasing and the election season at hand, the cry goes up for OPEC to raise output.</title>
    <meta content="Y17PLAC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223145"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Futures and Options Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Production</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Saudi Arabia</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Organization of Petroleum Exporting Countries (OPEC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fuerbringer, Jonathan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Market Place (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Market Place</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Saudi Arabia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Saudi Arabia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Production</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Futures and Options Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000817T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7DF173EF934A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="988" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE MARKETS: Market Place; With oil prices increasing and the election season at hand, the cry goes up for OPEC to raise output.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jonathan Fuerbringer</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fuerbringer, Jonathan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Clinton Administration wants OPEC to raise oil output as price of oil for September delivery gains 13 cents, to $31.80 a barrel on New York Mercantile Exchange; with inventories in US still near 24-year lows, hope for price relief is in another rise in output by OPEC, and that boils down to OPEC's approving increased production from Saudi Arabia, or Saudi Arabia going it alone; some analysts think more oil will be pumped because OPEC and especially Saudis do not want to threaten economic growth by leaving price above $30 a barrel; graph; chart (Market Place column) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE price of crude oil increased again yesterday, even after an American Petroleum Institute report the day before said that inventories rose by an unexpected 7.4 million barrels last week and the federal Energy Information Agency cited a smaller, but still strong increase of 3.4 million barrels.</p>
        <p>The price jump, with oil for September delivery up 13 cents, to $31.80 a barrel on the New York Mercantile Exchange, pretty much sums up the current outlook for oil prices.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE price of crude oil increased again yesterday, even after an American Petroleum Institute report the day before said that inventories rose by an unexpected 7.4 million barrels last week and the federal Energy Information Agency cited a smaller, but still strong increase of 3.4 million barrels.</p>
        <p>The price jump, with oil for September delivery up 13 cents, to $31.80 a barrel on the New York Mercantile Exchange, pretty much sums up the current outlook for oil prices.</p>
        <p>With inventories in the United States still near 24-year lows, the hope for price relief is in another significant rise in output by the Organization of Petroleum Exporting Countries. And that boils down to OPEC's approving increased production from Saudi Arabia -- or Saudi Arabia going it alone. The group's next meeting begins early next month.</p>
        <p>Some analysts think more oil will be pumped because, they say, OPEC and especially the Saudis do not want to threaten economic growth by leaving the price above $30 a barrel for the American crude oil benchmark, West Texas intermediate.</p>
        <p>In addition, pressure from the United States on Saudi Arabia and other suppliers, inside OPEC as well as outside, to produce more oil will build quickly if the price does not retreat soon. It is not far from the nine-and-a-half-year high of $34.14 a barrel it touched in March just before OPEC's first production increase.</p>
        <p>This week, there have been new rumblings of concern from the Clinton administration, which lobbied hard for increased OPEC production before the supplier nations' meeting in June.</p>
        <p>It was reported on Monday that Energy Secretary Bill Richardson had told a group of energy analysts a few days earlier that the administration was re-examining ways to lend oil to refiners from the Strategic Petroleum Reserve, presumably lowering prices as the available supplies rose.</p>
        <p>Oil would certainly become a presidential campaign issue if the price remained high, especially because of the connections to the oil industry of the Republican ticket of George W. Bush and Dick Cheney.</p>
        <p>Home heating oil prices are already on the rise again. Heating oil for September delivery rose 0.37 cent a gallon yesterday, to 86.88 cents. It is up 13 percent in the last two and a half weeks and is 26 percent above the average price from October through February.</p>
        <p>''I think informally or otherwise, there is likely to be a supply response'' from OPEC before the meeting begins, said Michael Rothman, senior energy analyst at Merrill Lynch.</p>
        <p>But the low inventory situation -- and traders' and speculators' focus on it -- is leaving the oil market far more vulnerable to upward price pressure than it was earlier in the year, when OPEC members debated their first two production increases.</p>
        <p>''We have no shock absorbers,'' said Gary N. Ross, chief executive of the PIRA Energy Group, ''and we are vulnerable to price spikes.''</p>
        <p>Some analysts think that it will be difficult to quickly rebuild inventories. They say that most OPEC nations cannot increase their overall capacity to produce oil, providing them little interest in higher output quotas that benefit only a few. Saudi Arabia and the United Arab Emirates are the only OPEC nations that could produce significantly more oil, the analysts say.</p>
        <p>Then last week, the International Energy Agency reported that several OPEC countries, including the Emirates, were in fact producing below their capacity. Mr. Rothman quoted the agency's monthly report for July as saying that the second-quarter inventory buildup in the 29 members of the Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development, a group of the world's wealthier nations, had been far less than normal for that time of year.</p>
        <p>Saudi Arabia seemed to have succeeded in taking the pressure off oil prices -- and the focus off inventory levels -- when it finally convinced traders, analysts and speculators last month that it would produce 500,000 barrels more a day, a promise it first surprised the oil market with on July 3.</p>
        <p>After wrangling within OPEC, the Saudi message got though as its extra oil began to move. And with that, the price dropped to $27.43 a barrel on July 31 from $30.93 at the beginning of the month.</p>
        <p>But on Aug. 1, the American Petroleum Institute reported that crude oil inventories in the United States had dropped by a surprising nine million barrels in the week ended July 28, leaving inventory more than 40 million barrels below the level a year earlier. The following week, total inventory fell by 2.1 million barrels more, bringing it to a 24-year low of 282.6 million barrels. The price of crude oil was back above $30 the next day.</p>
        <p>Tuesday's report from the American Petroleum Institute revised the previous week still lower, so that the 7.4-million-barrel increase brought inventories for the week ended on Aug. 11 to 286.4 million barrels.</p>
        <p>The only positive factor in the oil price's remaining above $30 a barrel is that OPEC members have an informal agreement to raise production by 500,000 barrels a day if prices stay above a set level for 20 cnsecutive trading days. That level works out to a bit more than $30 a barrel for West Texas intermediate, and the 20 days would be up just before an OPEC meeting the second week of September.</p>
        <p>Of course, the producers' group could choose to ignore this trigger. Or, a little jawboning would be enough to push the price below $30 for a day, starting the 20-day period again. So the upward bias on oil prices would remain until there were clear increases in production.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
