<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="17DIGE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223186"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000817T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E2DB173EF934A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1144" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hewlett-Packard Reports A 23% Jump in Earnings  Hewlett-Packard reported quarterly earnings that beat analysts' estimates, driven primarily by strong sales of personal computers and printers. Its board also approved a stock split.</p>
        <p>Analysts said that a large part of the 23 percent jump in earnings came from higher-than-expected interest income, a more favorable tax rate and other nonoperating contributors. [Page C9.]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Hewlett-Packard Reports A 23% Jump in Earnings  Hewlett-Packard reported quarterly earnings that beat analysts' estimates, driven primarily by strong sales of personal computers and printers. Its board also approved a stock split.</p>
        <p>Analysts said that a large part of the 23 percent jump in earnings came from higher-than-expected interest income, a more favorable tax rate and other nonoperating contributors. [Page C9.]</p>
        <p>N.T.T. Unit in Talks on U.S. Venture  The wireless arm of Nippon Telegraph and Telephone of Japan, the world's biggest communications company, is in preliminary negotiations to acquire a minority stake in the pending wireless joint venture between BellSouth and SBC Communications, two of the Bell local telephone giants. [C9.]</p>
        <p>Prices Edged Up 0.2% in July  Consumer inflation increased 0.2 percent in July, the Labor Department said, reassuring analysts that the Federal Reserve will not raise interest rates on Tuesday. [C11.]</p>
        <p>Cheney's Options Limited on Stock  Dick Cheney, the Republican nominee for vice president, retired from the Halliburton Company with millions of dollars worth of stock options that he cannot cash in until long after a new administration takes office, Halliburton said. The company said Mr. Cheney would not be allowed to sell the options, which he said he would do before taking office, assuming the Republicans win the presidency. Thus, he will have to either abandon the stake or hold it, giving him a large stake in the success of Halliburton while serving as vice president. [A1.]</p>
        <p>Major Stock Indexes Stumble Lower  Blue-chip stocks moved lower as worries about a slower pace of consumer spending dogged retailers for a second day and investors continued to lock in profits on recent gains. The Dow Jones industrial average, slumped 58.61 points, to 11,008.39. The Standard &amp; Poor's 500 index edged down 4.58 points, to 1,479.85. The Nasdaq composite index rose 9.54 points, to 3,861.20. [C10.]</p>
        <p>Profit Drops at News Corporation  The News Corporation said after-tax profit for the company's fourth quarter fell 14 percent. The company has just agreed to acquire Chris-Craft Industries, whose television stations carry the UPN network, which is owned by Viacom-CBS. Rupert Murdoch, who controls the News Corporation, said he was open to negotiating with Viacom regarding the future of the network. [C8.]</p>
        <p>Oil Prices Rise 13 Cents a Barrel  The price of crude oil rose to $31.80 a barrel even after the American Petroleum Institute reported that inventories rose an unexpected 7.4 million barrels last week and the Energy Information Agency reported a smaller, but still strong, 3.4 million barrel increase. That price jump pretty much sums up the current outlook for oil prices. Market Place. [C9.]</p>
        <p>Delivery Services Expect Expansion  The large international delivery companies like United Parcel Service, FedEx and DHL are all expected to play a part in the growth of e-commerce in Latin America because local delivery companies lack the ability to handle an expected expansion. [C4.]</p>
        <p>British Telecom to Increase Stake  British Telecommunications is expected to announce today that it will take control of Viag Interkom, a German telephone operator, by doubling its ownership stake to 90 percent in a deal worth about 6 billion euros or $5.46 billion, according to executives close to the deal. [C4.]</p>
        <p>Summer Reading, Future Earnings  The depressed level of academic engagement in poor households when school is out is responsible for a major portion of the gap in achievement between low- and high-income students. And that gap has economic consequences in that it affects earnings potential. Alan B. Krueger: Economic Scene. [C2.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
