<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>City Shuts Unlicensed Clinic Catering to Chinese Immigrants</title>
    <meta content="17HOSP$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223252"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kershaw, Sarah</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brown, Richard A (Dist Atty)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000817T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E6D7173EF934A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1149" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>City Shuts Unlicensed Clinic Catering to Chinese Immigrants</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SARAH KERSHAW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kershaw, Sarah</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York City officials close clinic in Flushing, Queens, that claimed to have treated thousands of patients, most of them Chinese immigrants, offering everything from traditional herbal medicine to cancer treatments; say neither clinic nor its doctors were licensed; Queens District Attorney Richard A Brown comments; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>During the last three years, a clinic in Queens claimed to have treated thousands of patients, most of them Chinese immigrants, offering everything from traditional herbal medicine to cancer treatments. But neither the clinic nor its doctors were licensed, the authorities said yesterday, after shutting it down and arresting six people.</p>
        <p>Situated at Main Street and 39th Avenue in Flushing, the heart of the borough's large Chinese immigrant community, the third-floor clinic used three names, including the New York Beijing Hospital of Traditional Chinese Medicine, said Richard A. Brown, the Queens district attorney. Investigators shut it down Tuesday and arrested the hospital's owner and five others on its staff, Mr. Brown said yesterday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>During the last three years, a clinic in Queens claimed to have treated thousands of patients, most of them Chinese immigrants, offering everything from traditional herbal medicine to cancer treatments. But neither the clinic nor its doctors were licensed, the authorities said yesterday, after shutting it down and arresting six people.</p>
        <p>Situated at Main Street and 39th Avenue in Flushing, the heart of the borough's large Chinese immigrant community, the third-floor clinic used three names, including the New York Beijing Hospital of Traditional Chinese Medicine, said Richard A. Brown, the Queens district attorney. Investigators shut it down Tuesday and arrested the hospital's owner and five others on its staff, Mr. Brown said yesterday.</p>
        <p>''It is clear that these defendants, who are not licensed to practice medicine or to operate a medical facility in this state, crossed the line,'' he said. The clinic also offered acupuncture without a license, which is required in New York State, he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brown said the clinic came to the attention of the authorities after a patient who became infected after a gynecological procedure sued for malpractice, and the doctors there said they could not be sued for malpractice because they did not have licenses. The woman said that doctors had given her an improper herbal prescription after they removed an intrauterine device. She became ill and had to spend 12 hours in a hospital emergency room, according to court papers and her lawyer.</p>
        <p>Investigators said they seized thousands of medical files, handwritten and in Chinese,  from the center, where doctors in white lab coats wore stethoscopes and tended to patients on examining tables. Law enforcement officials said they were trying to determine how many patients had undergone medical procedures in the clinic.</p>
        <p>The clinic advertised heavily in Chinese-language newspapers. At its Web site, www.theworldhealth.com, it claimed to have diagnosed thousands of illnesses since its founding in 1996.</p>
        <p>On the English-language side of the Web site, the hospital says its services include orthopedic, oncology and dermatology treatment, and reads, in part, ''The New York Beijing Hospital of Traditional Chinese Medicine specializes in treating various types difficulty diseases by adopting combination practice of Western medicine and traditional Chinese medicine.''</p>
        <p>An advertisement in The World Journal, the city's largest Chinese-language newspaper, pictures one of the doctors and reads, ''Famous doctor; good, secret, unique prescriptions.''</p>
        <p>The investigation underscores the difficulties of regulating underground medical clinics that cater to immigrants. Unlicensed storefront clinics and herbal medicine shops that treat patients in their back rooms are common in Flushing, doctors and other experts say. They attract uninsured immigrants who may be more comfortable using Chinese medicine and seeking treatment from other immigrants.</p>
        <p>In many cases, the clinics are staffed by medical personnel who were licensed in their native countries but who have not been certified in the United States.</p>
        <p>Sprinz Chou, manager of a hair salon next door to the clinic, said, ''A lot of people who can't speak English are afraid of going to see actual doctors, and these clinics always say they're cheaper.'' All six of the unlicensed Flushing doctors had trained and were licensed as doctors in China, said their lawyer, Hugh H. Mo.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mo, who is representing three of the doctors in the civil lawsuit brought by the patient who had the gynecological treatment, said that despite the clinic's advertising for other services, ''it is a legitimate business that sells Chinese herbs and food supplements.''</p>
        <p>He said he could not comment on accusations that the clinic was illegally providing medical care for more serious conditions. ''These are allegations that we have to examine very closely in order to see whether any of these allegations are substantiated by the evidence,'' he said. The records seized by the authorities might only reflect prescriptions for herbal treatments, he said.</p>
        <p>The authorities charged the clinic's owner, Shou Dong Wang, 42, of Bayside, his wife, Jing-Yi Hao, 41, and another doctor, Guo-Wu Liu, 84, of Elmhurst, with second-degree assault in connection with the surgery performed on the patient.</p>
        <p>They were also charged with second-degree reckless endangerment, with a scheme to defraud other patients and with violating a state education law requiring a medical license. They face up to seven years in prison, the authorities said.</p>
        <p>Three other doctors, Ying Ming Liu, 71, and Pei-Song Guo, 49, both of Flushing, and Jiu-Song Kan, 31, of Elmhurst, were charged with a scheme to defraud patients and with violating state licensing law and face up to four years in prison.</p>
        <p>All six were arraigned yesterday and all but Mr. Wang, the owner, were released without bail. Mr. Wang was released on $5,000 bail.</p>
        <p>The authorities began investigating the clinic late last year, after the patient, Chunxi Qiao, filed a civil malpractice suit. The doctors argued that they could not be sued because they were not licensed, and the judge referred the matter to the district attorney's office.</p>
        <p>An undercover detective posing as a patient sought medical treatment in the clinic on June 2 and on Aug. 1, the authorities said.</p>
        <p>The first time, he walked into the clinic complaining of shortness of breath and a cough. One of the doctors took his blood pressure, told him it was high and prescribed seven doses of an herbal medicine. The detective was charged $77.</p>
        <p>During a second visit, he sought treatment at the clinic for a skin rash and was examined by the same doctor, who prescribed another herbal medicine and ointment for the rash. He was charged $74 for that visit.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brown said yesterday that his office was planning to expand its investigation to seek out other possibly unlicensed clinics.</p>
        <p>Dr. Robert Crupi, chairman of the department of emergency medicine at Flushing Hospital, said he often saw patients, particularly Asian immigrants, who have sought traditional Chinese medical care before arriving at the hospital with more serious ailments.</p>
        <p>He said the concern was that some patients, including patients he has seen with heart attacks and other serious medical problems, delayed  treatment by relying on the storefront clinics or herbal remedies.</p>
        <p>''We don't dismiss traditional medicine,'' he said. ''One has to respect people's cultural beliefs, and traditional medicine has its place.''</p>
        <p>But, he added, ''delays in necessary treatments can be significant and lead to bad outcomes.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
