<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Wilson a Tattooed, Pierced, All-American Guy</title>
    <meta content="17GYMM$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223205"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="OLYMPICS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gymnastics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wilson, Blaine</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Roberts, Selena</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004/Gymnastics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gymnastics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000817T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E4D9173EF934A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="795" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Wilson a Tattooed, Pierced, All-American Guy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SELENA ROBERTS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Roberts, Selena</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON, Aug. 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Blaine Wilson, five-time US gymnastics champion, practices for Olympic trials; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There is a glint from the small silver stud on Blaine Wilson's pierced tongue, and a request to have him display his latest accessory.</p>
        <p>But as a camera creeps in on America's five-time national champion, the compact gymnast with the defined muscle of a toy soldier refuses to play the part as the tattooed rebel of his sport.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There is a glint from the small silver stud on Blaine Wilson's pierced tongue, and a request to have him display his latest accessory.</p>
        <p>But as a camera creeps in on America's five-time national champion, the compact gymnast with the defined muscle of a toy soldier refuses to play the part as the tattooed rebel of his sport.</p>
        <p>''I'm not sticking my tongue out on TV,'' Wilson said with a smile. ''And when I raise my hand to the judge, I'm not sticking my tongue out at them, either.''</p>
        <p>He knows what the judges will want to see when the Olympic trials begin on Thursday at the Fleet Center with the men's preliminary all-around competition. As a part of his routines, he has a certain image he wants to stick, as well.</p>
        <p>''You have to come in cleanshaven, and you have to be the good old American boy when you walk out there,'' Wilson said today following a training session. ''So that's the image the judges are looking for.''</p>
        <p>He has an image for every occasion. He is heavy-metal and milk-and-cookies, all rolled into one. He has been known to hunker down beneath his headphones and launch into a deep and detached focus on the way to a meet, but he has also been moved to tears on the occasions when one of his teammates, John Roethlisberger, pours out his patriotic soul before a competition.</p>
        <p>''It's fun for me, because we'll go to a meet and he'll be the one trash-talking the other team,'' the more buttoned-down Roethlisberger said. ''He'll be like, We're going to kick them in the . . . you know. I'm like, 'Hey, all right, yeah.' So he gets me fired up by just being himself.''</p>
        <p>Along with his ever-improving talent, Wilson's ability to light up a room with his own style could insert a little star quality back in men's gymnastics in Sydney, Australia. But beneath the pre-Olympic hype, Wilson seems unconcerned with his chances at individual medals.</p>
        <p>It may be just his way of deflecting the pressure -- most believe he has an excellent chance to medal in the all-around competition -- but his primary focus is on pushing his teammates to stand on the podium with him.</p>
        <p>''I think he is the least understood of all gymnasts,'' said Peter Kormann, the men's Olympic team coach. ''He's very complicated, but he's the ultimate team player.</p>
        <p>''His image sometimes is that I'm this tough, competitive guy with tattoos and all this stuff. But I have to laugh. He's not even close to that. He's the nicest guy and the best team player.''</p>
        <p>So much so that he has been known to delay his own routine to watch his teammates. In 1996, Kormann had to tell the judges that Wilson was tired from his previous event and had to take a breather before performing on the rings. Truthfully, Wilson was a bundle of nerves watching one of his teammates, Kip Simons, pull off his routine on the other side of the gym. He needed Kormann to buy him time so he could focus his attention -- and a little mental telepathy -- on Simons. As soon as Simons ended his performance, a relaxed Wilson scored a 9.9 on the rings.</p>
        <p>''He didn't have a thought about the rings,'' Kormann said. ''He was nervous for his teammates. That's the real Blaine.''</p>
        <p>If the real Wilson unveils his best in Boston, he could ease away from the rest of the Americans at the trials, just as he did at the nationals two months ago. His roll of five national titles in a row has left his coach comparing him to Tiger Woods.</p>
        <p>But success tends to add the burden of expectation. In 1996, he was young and naive and relatively unknown as the trials began. Now, he's hard to miss. He's the one with the pierced tongue, tattoos and titles. And no one inside gymnastics has ever asked him to change.</p>
        <p>''If you try to curb someone's personality, your gymnastics is going to go straight downhill,'' Wilson said. ''I think I've been supported. I like to express myself in a different way. And a lot of things have been said about it. But if someone on the team wants me to work out in my shirt in the Games, then I'll do that. It's not a problem.''</p>
        <p>Anything for the team.</p>
        <p>OLYMPICS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
