<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Retooled Lieberman Sticks By Master</title>
    <meta content="Y17ASS$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223263"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE DEMOCRATS: THE CONTEST"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Apple, R W Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lieberman, Joseph I (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/Joseph I Lieberman</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000817T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E4D7173EF934A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1322" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Retooled Lieberman Sticks By Master</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By R. W. APPLE Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Apple, R W Jr</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, Aug. 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>News analysis: Sen Joseph I Lieberman, hastily retooled to exigencies of a national campaign, takes stage at Democratic convention and follows what are apparently current rules of vice-presidential candidacy--praise your master and mute your own views; speech bypasses mention of any issue that might highlight Lieberman and Gore's differences as Democrats strive for ideological identity (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was a new-model Joseph I. Lieberman, hastily retooled to the exigencies of a national campaign, who took the stage tonight as the presumptive Democratic vice-presidential nominee.</p>
        <p>No advocacy of school vouchers or the partial privatization of Social Security, no criticism of affirmative action. No ragged policy edges that might keep the party's core voters from supporting Al Gore. Nothing that might highlight the candidates' differences rather than their agreements.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was a new-model Joseph I. Lieberman, hastily retooled to the exigencies of a national campaign, who took the stage tonight as the presumptive Democratic vice-presidential nominee.</p>
        <p>No advocacy of school vouchers or the partial privatization of Social Security, no criticism of affirmative action. No ragged policy edges that might keep the party's core voters from supporting Al Gore. Nothing that might highlight the candidates' differences rather than their agreements.</p>
        <p>''I've known Al Gore for 15 years,'' Senator Lieberman assured the delegates to the Democratic National convention here. ''I know his record and his heart. I know him as a public servant and I know what it is like to sit with him around the dining room table. We have discussed -- sometimes even debated -- policy issues.  And we have shared private moments of prayer.''</p>
        <p>There was talk about his family, about his immigrant grandmother, his father's bakery route, his wife's family's survival of the Holocaust.  There was a helping of Jewish shtick.  There was a bow to bipartisanship -- ''our opponents are decent and they are likable men'' and ''I'm proud to call many in their party my friends'' -- but also an enumeration of policy differences between the rival tickets.</p>
        <p>But any new proposals will have to come from Mr. Gore himself on Thursday night. For his part, Mr. Lieberman delved even less into the nitty-gritty than did Dick Cheney, his Republican opponent, at the Republican convention.</p>
        <p>Welcome to the world of the vice-presidential candidate (and the vice president, for that matter), where the rules are simple: praise your master and mute your own views.</p>
        <p>On the basis of his record, some people might have expected something a bit more unconventional from Mr. Lieberman, probably unrealistically.</p>
        <p>Bill Clinton was a master at reconciling differences among Democrats of varying stripes. But as William J. Daley, the chairman of the Gore campaign, noted the other day, wearing his best Buster Keaton deadpan, ''Clinton is not on the ticket this year.'' And Mr. Gore has trouble enough with the party's base -- blacks and labor and others who have stood behind it for decades --  without getting into more because of Mr. Lieberman's views.</p>
        <p>It is a measure of Democratic skittishness on this point that Mr. Lieberman has backtracked on several points of importance to the constituencies that the ticket needs to re-energize. But the rejiggering could be costly.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore has a bit of a reputation for flip-flopping and corner-cutting on issues like abortion and trade.  Former Senator Bill Bradley, Mr. Gore's primary opponent, accused him in January of ''using words in a very tricky manner,'' and Gov. George W. Bush, his opponent in the general election, mocked him for having voted one way on guns in the 1980's and another in the 1990's, adding: ''When it's convenient politically, he changes his tune.''</p>
        <p>Democratic strategists hoped that Mr. Lieberman, the man who refused to buckle when colleagues tried to dissuade him from criticizing Mr. Clinton's sexual conduct, would lend the ticket some stand-by-your-guns luster. Much of that could be lost if the senator seemed to be bending to political expediency at this stage.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore and Mr. Lieberman began attacking that problem when they visited the vice president's hometown, Carthage, Tenn., almost a week ago.</p>
        <p>''Believe me,'' Mr. Lieberman said, ''when President Gore decides, Vice President Lieberman will support him wholeheartedly.''</p>
        <p>The vice president responded: ''I think it's a strength and not a weakness, an asset not a liability, to be able to have a different point of view represented in the room at the time that decisions are being made.''</p>
        <p>But that, they seem to have concluded since, was not quite enough.</p>
        <p>There was a day when presidential nominees chose running-mates who provided ideological balance. In 1952, Adlai E. Stevenson, a northern liberal, chose John J. Sparkman, an Alabama conservative, and in 1976, Jimmy Carter, a southern conservative, chose Walter F. Mondale, a Minnesota liberal. But like so many old norms in American politics, that one has gone by the board.</p>
        <p>This year, ideological identity is the real goal for the Democratic ticket, much as the party may have flaunted its ideological diversity in its ''Liberals' Corner'' on Tuesday night. Vice President Al Gore not only selected someone from roughly the same segment of the party --  both have been stalwarts of the centrist Democratic Leadership Conference -- but he and his aides also sought to make sure that Mr. Lieberman fell into line on all the major issues.</p>
        <p>That took some doing, because on some questions, his position was a bit to the right of Mr. Gore's. Not that Mr. Lieberman is a right-winger, or anything resembling one. He may have had doubts about affirmative action, for example, but he will be the first person ever on a national ticket who went to Mississippi to show racial solidarity in the dark days of 1963.</p>
        <p>And tonight, in a bid to reassure blacks and other liberals, he had this to say: ''It's not just the size of our national feast that is important, no, but the number of people we can fit around the table. There must be room for everybody.'' Those words were directly from an Al Gore speech.</p>
        <p>But consider the matter of vouchers issued to parents by the federal government, to be used to pay their children's tuition. In his time as Connecticut's junior senator, Mr. Lieberman sponsored legislation establishing experimental programs for vouchers. He voted for such programs on at least four occasions. But vouchers are anathema to the American Federation of Teachers and the 2.5 million-member National Education Association, a pair of powerhouses that are expected to pour money and energy into the Gore campaign this fall.</p>
        <p>What to do? After he was chosen by Mr. Gore, according to a report in The Wall Street Journal, Mr. Lieberman called Sandra Feldman, the leader of the teachers' federation, and promised that a Gore-Lieberman administration would be resolutely anti-voucher.</p>
        <p>In 1995, Mr. Lieberman voiced support for Proposition 209 in California, a ballot initiative that ended racial and sex preferences in state university admissions. The same year, in a Senate floor speech, he said affirmative action ''is dividing us in ways its creators could not have intended.''</p>
        <p>''If you discriminate in favor of one group on the basis of race,'' he added, ''you thereby discriminate against another group on the basis of race.''</p>
        <p>Statements like that helped to win Mr. Lieberman a reputation as one of the least partisan, most civil and most thoughtful members of Congress. But not among African-Americans, one of the groups Mr. Gore must count upon.</p>
        <p>So this week Mr. Lieberman visited the Congressional Black Caucus to quiet its members' concerns. He told them: ''I have supported affirmative action. I do support affirmative action. And I will support affirmative action.''</p>
        <p>Tonight, he echoed President Clinton's formulation about affirmative action: ''Mend it, don't end it.''</p>
        <p>Similarly he has backed away from the idea of allocating some percentage of Social Security funds for investment by individuals, a proposal at the heart of the Bush campaign.</p>
        <p>In an interview in 1998 with the Copley News Service, Mr. Lieberman said, ''I think in the end that individual control of part of the retirement-Social Security funds has to happen.'' Mr. Gore stoutly opposes that.</p>
        <p>But almost immediately after he was chosen by Mr. Gore, the senator released an unpublished op-ed article entitled, ''My Private Journey Away from Privatization,'' cleared first by the Gore campaign. In it, he said that the promises and the numbers supporting the proposal ''don't add up.''</p>
        <p>THE DEMOCRATS: THE CONTEST</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
