<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Testaverde May Start Against Giants Despite Toe Injury</title>
    <meta content="17JETS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/17/sports/17JETS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223160"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Giants</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Jets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Testaverde, Vinny</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Battista, Judy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000817T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE3DE173EF934A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="816" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Testaverde May Start Against Giants Despite Toe Injury</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JUDY BATTISTA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Battista, Judy</byline>
      <dateline>HEMPSTEAD, N.Y., Aug. 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vinny Testaverde, recovering rapidly from turf-toe injury, may play in Jets game against New York Giants (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jets quarterback Vinny Testaverde, making an unexpectedly rapid recovery from a turf-toe injury sustained in last Saturday's game, practiced sharply today and might play against the Giants Friday night. If he does play, Jets Coach Al Groh said that he would probably start and that his playing time would not be limited.</p>
        <p>But the decision whether Testaverde should play is tricky and carries great risk. Testaverde craves more work as he returns from a 10-month layoff after a season-ending injury on opening day last season.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jets quarterback Vinny Testaverde, making an unexpectedly rapid recovery from a turf-toe injury sustained in last Saturday's game, practiced sharply today and might play against the Giants Friday night. If he does play, Jets Coach Al Groh said that he would probably start and that his playing time would not be limited.</p>
        <p>But the decision whether Testaverde should play is tricky and carries great risk. Testaverde craves more work as he returns from a 10-month layoff after a season-ending injury on opening day last season.</p>
        <p>But if he plays Friday, Testaverde risks aggravating what could be a nagging injury that would have had three weeks to heal. The Jets have a bye week after they play the Giants.</p>
        <p>If the toe were hurt again, Testaverde's status for the season opener Sept. 3 at Green Bay would be uncertain. Testaverde sounded ambivalent about what he should do; he would not even say whether he could play if this were a regular-season game.</p>
        <p>''There's no question I do need more work after missing a year,'' said Testaverde, who has been in for just 41 official plays this preseason. ''The more you get, the better you feel, the more confidence you have in yourself. I really wanted to see what I could do on it.</p>
        <p>''I asked the trainers what the downside was. And they said if I get caught in the same position, with somebody landing on it and jamming the toe, then we set ourselves back. If you want to call it taking a little risk and going out and practicing and seeing where I was just for my own mind-set, it made me feel better about that. The risk would be much greater in a game.''</p>
        <p>Testaverde added: ''At the same time, I'm trying to be smart with this. I'm also trying to prepare for Sept. 3. What's the best decision? What's the best I can do? I'm sitting in the training room, concerned that I had a whole year off and that I haven't had enough snaps in preseason to make me feel like I'm on top of my game again. I feel good enough that if I don't play in this game, I'll be ready for Green Bay.''</p>
        <p>Testaverde said that while he feels better than he did a few days ago, his left big toe is still thick, swollen and sore. He said he walks on the outside of it to try to prevent more swelling.</p>
        <p>When he is on the field, Testaverde moves normally, putting his full weight on the left foot when he follows through, rather than throwing off his back foot (his right foot) to avoid putting pressure on the injured toe.</p>
        <p>Testaverde was initially expected to miss at least one week after sustaining the injury in a game against the Baltimore Ravens Saturday. But on Tuesday, Testaverde returned to practice.</p>
        <p>Groh said today that he would wait to see how Testaverde felt Thursday and in the hours leading up to the game before making a decision. But if Testaverde plays, he will go well beyond making a cameo appearance.</p>
        <p>''If he plays, he's playing,'' Groh said. ''There's no limit. He's our starting quarterback.''</p>
        <p>So far in the preseason, Testaverde is 11 of 21 for 244 yards, with a touchdown and 2 interceptions -- both returned for touchdowns. He declined to classify himself as probable or questionable for the Giants game, citing a team rule that fines players for discussing injuries.</p>
        <p>''It can linger on if you don't take care of it,'' Testaverde said. ''That's what we're trying to do. There's a fine line. I feel pretty good about what I've accomplished in camp. I feel I'll be ready for Green Bay.''</p>
        <p>EXTRA POINTS</p>
        <p>Wide receiver VINCENT BRISBY practiced Wednesday after signing a one-year contract for $440,000 and said he hoped to win a starting job in the unsettled receiving corps. Right now, DEDRIC WARD is penciled in as the starter opposite WAYNE CHREBET. ''I have a shot to be a starting receiver, and that's what I was looking for when I was on the market,'' Brisby said. Brisby, cut Monday by the Patriots, will play Friday against the Giants, Coach AL GROH said. With the rookies LAVERANUES COLES and WINDRELL HAYES and the free agent YATIL GREEN failing to play consistently in training camp, Brisby -- with his knowledge of the offensive system that the Jets and Patriots have in common -- has a chance to step in right away and compete. But Brisby's speed is suspect, and New England quarterback DREW BLEDSOE said Brisby's release was ''a speed thing.'' Groh said: ''I wouldn't put him on a relay team. But we knew that when we drafted him in New England.'' . . . Linebacker ROMAN PHIFER (knee) and cornerback AARON GLENN (ankle) did not practice.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
