<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hewlett-Packard Posts 23% Jump in Quarterly Profit</title>
    <meta content="Y17HEW$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223154"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TECHNOLOGY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hewlett-Packard Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fisher, Lawrence M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000817T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00EFDF173EF934A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="688" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hewlett-Packard Posts 23% Jump in Quarterly Profit</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAWRENCE M. FISHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fisher, Lawrence M</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO, Aug. 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Hewlett-Packard Co's earnings in third quarter ended July 31 beat analysts' estimates; earnings were $1.05 billion, up 23 percent from $853 million in year-earlier period; revenue rose 15 percent, to $11.82 billion, from $10.32 billion in third quarter of fiscal 1999 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Hewlett-Packard Company reported quarterly earnings today that beat analysts' estimates, driven primarily by strong sales of personal computers and printers. Its board also approved a stock split.</p>
        <p>For the third quarter, ended July 31, Hewlett-Packard reported earnings of $1.05 billion, or 99 cents a diluted share, up 23 percent from $853 million, or 66 cents a share, in the period a year earlier. Revenue rose 15 percent, to $11.82 billion, from $10.32 billion in the third quarter of fiscal 1999.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Hewlett-Packard Company reported quarterly earnings today that beat analysts' estimates, driven primarily by strong sales of personal computers and printers. Its board also approved a stock split.</p>
        <p>For the third quarter, ended July 31, Hewlett-Packard reported earnings of $1.05 billion, or 99 cents a diluted share, up 23 percent from $853 million, or 66 cents a share, in the period a year earlier. Revenue rose 15 percent, to $11.82 billion, from $10.32 billion in the third quarter of fiscal 1999.</p>
        <p>Excluding equity gains, Hewlett-Packard had earnings of 97 cents a diluted share, compared with similarly adjusted earnings of 71 cents a share in the period a year earlier. Analysts had expected the company to earn 85 cents a share, according to First Call/Thomson Financial.</p>
        <p>Hewlett-Packard reported its results after the close of the market. Its shares closed at $120 each, up $9.56, on the New York Stock Exchange.</p>
        <p>Analysts attributed the jump in earnings largely to higher-than-expected interest income, a more favorable tax rate and other nonoperating contributors. Overall revenue growth of 15 percent was merely in line with expectations, they said, and the 13 percent sales growth of the crucial Unix business was disappointing, particularly in comparison with sales growth of 42 percent in the most recent quarter for Sun Microsystems Inc., the Unix market leader.</p>
        <p>''The top line was sort of in line with the target, and the bottom line above, but there were significant contributions to the bottom line,'' said Laura Conigliaro, an analyst with Goldman, Sachs, noting that tax considerations added 3 cents to earnings per share, with 6 cents coming from higher interest income. ''It's a good quarter, with evidence that there are better things to come, with some of the strongest evidence from some ironic areas, PC's and printers, where others seem to be struggling,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Steven Milunovich of Merrill Lynch had a more positive interpretation of the results, which came at the end of Carly Fiorina's first four quarters as president and chief executive.</p>
        <p>''Even when you take out the extraordinary items, they appear to have beat our estimates for operating income,'' he said. ''I think it shows that H.P. continues to be on the recovery trail, that Carly's initiatives are beginning to pay off, and that the company is beginning to show some consistency in earnings.''</p>
        <p>Although Hewlett-Packard saw declining revenue from commercial desktop personal computers in the quarter, its home PC business grew 62 percent in revenue and notebooks grew 93 percent. The imaging and printing systems segment -- laser and inkjet printing, and imaging devices -- grew 15 percent in revenue year over year.</p>
        <p>''Last year at this time, we committed to becoming a more aggressive and focused H.P., delivering strong top and bottom line growth on a consistent basis,'' Ms. Fiorina said in a statement. ''Today's results demonstrate the tremendous progress we're making in all of our businesses around the world.''</p>
        <p>Although Hewlett-Packard said its Unix server business had grown by only 13 percent in revenue year over year, it reported order growth of 23 percent in dollars and 43 percent in units. Ms. Fiorina said the company had gained market share at the low end, increased its lead in the midrange, but slowed at the high end, in anticipation of the introduction of a new high-end server line, called SuperDome, in mid-September.</p>
        <p>''How is it that their sales of high-end product dry up when they're in product transition while Sun's accelerate?'' said Daniel Kunstler, an analyst with J. P. Morgan. ''I would say a relative disappointment in Unix was offset by color printing and a strong consumer business in general. Their sense of purpose really should be geared toward Unix because that's where there's margin, and that's where they've lost leadership they think they can regain.''</p>
        <p>A stock split of two shares for one, which was announced today, will be effective Oct. 27. The quarterly results reflect continuing operations and exclude the industrial instrument business that was spun off this year as Agilent Technologies.</p>
        <p>TECHNOLOGY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
