<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TRANSACTIONS</title>
    <meta content="17TRNS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223277"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000817T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03EED7173EF934A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="612" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TRANSACTIONS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sports contract transactions</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
        <p>American League  ANAHEIM ANGELS--Signed LHP Bryan Ward and assigned him to Edmonton of the PCL. Claimed 2B David Eckstein off waivers from Boston.  BOSTON RED SOX--Designated 3B Ed Sprague for assignment. Activated INF Jose Offerman off the 15-day disabled list.  OAKLAND ATHLETICS--Agreed to terms with RHP Tim Hudson on a four-year contract extension.  TEXAS RANGERS--Optioned RHP Johnathan Johnson to Oklahoma of the PCL.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
        <p>American League  ANAHEIM ANGELS--Signed LHP Bryan Ward and assigned him to Edmonton of the PCL. Claimed 2B David Eckstein off waivers from Boston.  BOSTON RED SOX--Designated 3B Ed Sprague for assignment. Activated INF Jose Offerman off the 15-day disabled list.  OAKLAND ATHLETICS--Agreed to terms with RHP Tim Hudson on a four-year contract extension.  TEXAS RANGERS--Optioned RHP Johnathan Johnson to Oklahoma of the PCL.</p>
        <p>National League  METS--Sent INF-OF Matt Franco outright to Norfolk of the International League.  MONTREAL EXPOS--Signed 1B Lee Stevens to a two-year contract extension.</p>
        <p>BASKETBALL</p>
        <p>National Basketball Association  CHICAGO BULLS--Signed C Dragan Tarlac.  GOLDEN STATE WARRIORS--Acquired F Danny Fortson and F Adam Keefe in a four-way trade with Boston, Dallas and Utah. Utah received F Donyell Marshall from Golden State and C Bruno Sundov from Dallas. Dallas received G Howard Eisley from Utah, G Dana Barros from Boston and F Bill Curley from Golden State. Boston received C John Williams from Dallas and G Robert Pack and a 2001 first-round draft pick from Utah.  PHILADELPHIA 76ERS--Agreed to terms with G Jermaine Jackson and F Toni Kukoc.  SACRAMENTO KINGS--Signed F-G Predrag Stojakovic to a multiyear contract extension.</p>
        <p>FOOTBALL</p>
        <p>National Football League  JETS--Signed WR Vincent Brisby.  CLEVELAND BROWNS--Placed QB Ty Detmer and OT Jeremy McKinney on the injured reserve list. Waived DL Eric Chandler, DL Teto Simpson, OL Steve Estes, OL Mike Guilliams, WR Jeff Klopf, WR Kofi Shuck, TE Trevon Matthews and DB Nate Terry.  DALLAS COWBOYS--Signed QB Charlie Puleri. Released TE Chris Smith.  DENVER BRONCOS--Waived OL Rod Milstead.  JACKSONVILLE JAGUARS--Acquired G Brenden Stai from Kansas City for an undisclosed draft choice.  MIAMI DOLPHINS--Waived QB Jim Druckenmiller. Reached an injury settlement of DT Antoine Simpson.  TENNESSEE TITANS--Cut CB Kareem Clark and LB Deon Hunt.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
        <p>National Hockey League  ANAHEIM MIGHTY DUCKS--Agreed to terms with C Antti Aalto on a one-year contract.  MINNESOTA WILD--Signed D Lubomir Sekeras.  PHOENIX COYOTES--Announced the resignation of assistant coach Wayne Fleming. Signed F Eric Healey to a one-year contract.  TORONTO MAPLE LEAFS--Signed D Dave Manson to a two-year contract.  WASHINGTON CAPITALS--Signed D Ken Klee to a three-year contract.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
