<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Essay; Gore's Audible In Bishkek</title>
    <meta content="17SAFI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223131"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions, National (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Safire, William</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/William Safire</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000817T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E3D7163EF934A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="754" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Essay; Gore's Audible In Bishkek</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM SAFIRE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Safire, William</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William Safire Op-Ed column recognizing leadership qualities of Vice Pres Al Gore, notably understanding of foreign affairs, which he says has been glossed over at Democratic National Convention</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In his you-never-had-it-so-good stemwinder the other night, Bill Clinton twice deftly stepped on applause lines for Joe Lieberman. Concentered all in self, the reluctantly departing president failed to impart a single behind-the-scenes anecdote to dramatize the leadership qualities of his loyal sidekick, Al Gore.</p>
        <p>Thus it falls to a scandalmonger who has relentlessly castigated the vice president for his fund-raising excesses to provide a behind-the-scenes glimpse of Al and Tipper Gore under pressure.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In his you-never-had-it-so-good stemwinder the other night, Bill Clinton twice deftly stepped on applause lines for Joe Lieberman. Concentered all in self, the reluctantly departing president failed to impart a single behind-the-scenes anecdote to dramatize the leadership qualities of his loyal sidekick, Al Gore.</p>
        <p>Thus it falls to a scandalmonger who has relentlessly castigated the vice president for his fund-raising excesses to provide a behind-the-scenes glimpse of Al and Tipper Gore under pressure.</p>
        <p>The year was 1993. Air Force Two was taking the vice president, his wife and a handful of reporters around the newly freed states of the former Soviet Union.</p>
        <p>A half-hour before, the pilot had made two aborted passes at the short airstrip in befogged Almaty, Kazakhstan. Because the plane was running low on fuel, he landed at nearby Bishkek, Kyrgyzstan, where the Americans were not expected to arrive until the next day.</p>
        <p>During refueling, the pilot offered to try again to get into Almaty, where a grand state dinner was laid on. A critical go-no-go was about to be decided: Would the vice president demonstrate that the U.S. was unafraid of fog, even at the risk of life?</p>
        <p>I slipped up toward the front cabin, eager to witness Gore make this command decision. Through a slit in the curtain, I could see and hear arguments presented: Oil-rich Kazakhstan, which could be wooed further away from Russia, might be put off by American queasiness about landing. Diplomats fretted. The gutsy pilot thought he could make it on another try.</p>
        <p>Gore glanced toward Tipper. Arms folded, she almost imperceptibly shook her head. I thought: Sensible woman.</p>
        <p>''We're calling an audible,'' the vice president said, his voice like thin ice breaking, his metaphor that of a quarterback making a last-second adjustment. ''Let's flop the schedule. Stay here tonight and switch everything around.''</p>
        <p>He got on the telephone to the two presidents, delaying one dinner and stunning the Bishkek boss with ''You know that formal state dinner planned for tomorrow night? How about you round everybody up and we'll have it an hour from now?''</p>
        <p>It worked. False machismo was rejected, the hosts understood the concern for safety, and we members of the press didn't know the difference between Kyrgyzstan and Kazakhstan anyway.</p>
        <p>That struck me as leadership in action. Gore's creative audible-calling demonstrated a wise willingness in a tight spot to listen to the cautious counsel of his wife.</p>
        <p>What a pity that Clinton could not come up with a similarly dramatic instance of leadership -- perhaps even one dealing with substantive policy that required a profile in courage. But that might have detracted from Clinton's self-image of being in total charge at all times.</p>
        <p>On the rest of that tour of Russia and its adjacent new republics, I had several opportunities to talk privately with the person the background rules require I must still refer to only as a high official with a wooden expression traveling on the vice president's plane.</p>
        <p>It turned out he had been egregiously misinformed by State and the C.I.A. about the upcoming Russian election: the sudden rise of the nutty Vladimir Zhirinovsky came as a complete surprise to U.S. intelligence. And his judgment about certain Russian leaders was, in retrospect, too optimistic.</p>
        <p>But he knew his stuff. The unnameable official had not only done his briefing-book homework, but had a hard-wired strategic outlook that takes years to develop. I disagreed with some of his policy conclusions but had to respect his knowledge of the weaknesses and foibles of his foreign interlocutors and his grasp of the intricacies of high-level wheeling and dealing.</p>
        <p>None of that will be on display in tonight's acceptance speech because foreign policy has no place in either party's convention. With peace a given, the Democratic nominee's message will be ''Don't let them take prosperity away.''</p>
        <p>That does not seduce me. But as Al ingratiates himself with self-deprecating humor and lays out to the assembled teacher-delegates and tree-huggers his vision of a debt-free Treasury, I will not be so quick to join the personality-driven chorus of derision because I remember the audible in Bishkek.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
