<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Political Interlocutor Is Learning On the Job</title>
    <meta content="17HOFF" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223105"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ARTS IN AMERICA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions, National (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lyman, Rick</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sarandon, Susan</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Last Party 2000 (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000817T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E7DB163EF934A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1563" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Political Interlocutor Is Learning On the Job</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICK LYMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lyman, Rick</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, Aug. 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Arts in America column on filming of documentary Last Party 2000, with Susan Sarandon, in and around Democratic National Convention in Los Angeles; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Philip Seymour Hoffman and Susan Sarandon were seated on metal chairs near an open French window overlooking the haze-choked Hollywood Hills, an American flag hanging listlessly from a 20-foot pole attached to the ledge outside.</p>
        <p>Ms. Sarandon, who had just addressed the alternative gathering known as the shadow convention in the chaotic, humid gloom of Patriotic Hall, had come up here to the fourth-floor press room to be interviewed by Mr. Hoffman. He acts as a kind of guerrilla guide to the presidential campaign in ''Last Party 2000,'' a documentary being directed by Donovan Leitch that has been shooting on and off since March. How has it been going? Ms. Sarandon asked Mr. Hoffman.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Philip Seymour Hoffman and Susan Sarandon were seated on metal chairs near an open French window overlooking the haze-choked Hollywood Hills, an American flag hanging listlessly from a 20-foot pole attached to the ledge outside.</p>
        <p>Ms. Sarandon, who had just addressed the alternative gathering known as the shadow convention in the chaotic, humid gloom of Patriotic Hall, had come up here to the fourth-floor press room to be interviewed by Mr. Hoffman. He acts as a kind of guerrilla guide to the presidential campaign in ''Last Party 2000,'' a documentary being directed by Donovan Leitch that has been shooting on and off since March. How has it been going? Ms. Sarandon asked Mr. Hoffman.</p>
        <p>He shrugged his shoulders and tugged at the bill of his cap. ''My head is in about 10 different places at once,'' he said.</p>
        <p>His was not the only crew working with digital cameras in and around this year's Democratic National Convention. At times it seemed as though people with cameras outnumbered the delegates.</p>
        <p>At least six camera crews were scattered around the crowded lobby and sidewalk outside the shadow convention, with as many more in the protest zone opposite Staples Center and on the official convention floor inside. Add to this the individuals with digital cameras clasped in their fists, and it seemed that no corner of the crowded scene was left uncovered by filmmakers. But Mr. Hoffman, who was committing a great deal of his time this year (though not all) to the project, was probably the most famous face among them.</p>
        <p>Many in the crowd had fond memories of the earlier ''Last Party,'' directed by Mark Benjamin and Marc Levin, on which Mr. Leitch was a writer. Shot during the 1992 campaign and released in 1993, it had a short flurry of success, particularly among young audiences, though it was somewhat overshadowed by the critically acclaimed ''War Room,'' a more traditional documentary offering more of a behind-the-scenes look at that year's campaign.</p>
        <p>The actor Robert Downey Jr. was the on-camera narrator of the first ''Last Party,'' the subjective eye through which that year's presidential election was seen. This year, Mr. Leitch said, he felt the time was right to do it again. But with Mr. Hoffman -- the critically acclaimed and prolific young actor, most recently seen on Broadway in ''True West'' and on film in ''Flawless,'' ''Magnolia'' and ''The Talented Mr. Ripley'' -- the tone has shifted.</p>
        <p>''When we did it with Robert Downey, he was like Puck, frolicking through the convention,'' Mr. Leitch said. ''Phil is always very aware of what is going on around him, and he's very intellectual and very much wants to know what's going on. His mantra is: Why should I care? Why is this important to me?''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hoffman was intensely serious and preoccupied as he waited for one of Patriotic Hall's ancient elevators to arrive with a shudder and ferry him up to a news conference on the top floor.</p>
        <p>''One of the main reasons that I decided to do this was because I really didn't know all that much about the political process, outside of the basics,'' he said. ''I think a lot of people don't know much more than that. This was an opportunity for me to learn about it, how it really works, and maybe get more involved and passionate about it.''</p>
        <p>It had been a procession of revelations, he said, about how the political system functions and how difficult it can be to get beyond the oratory and the masks and the security perimeters. He was still digesting it, still learning.</p>
        <p>''I really think that maybe Phil has hit a wall here at the Democratic convention,'' Mr. Leitch said. ''He's been so frustrated with some of the responses he was getting, and tired of trying to get behind the facades. I think he may be on the verge of a breakthrough, where he'll feel compelled to take a stand. I'm excited, because this is part of his character's development.''</p>
        <p>As might be expected in such an enterprise, a documentary on the fly, it is a reasonably disorganized affair. ''I hope you don't mind, the plan keeps changing all the time,'' said Rebecca Chaiklin, one of the film's producers, between cell phone calls setting up interviews. ''We really are kind of a guerrilla operation.''</p>
        <p>The days begin with a meeting at which plans are made for stationing the four digital cameras. But the crews try to remain flexible, able to react to changing events and sudden interview opportunities.</p>
        <p>At the shadow convention the filmmakers had planned to hook up with Bill Maher, host of ''Politically Incorrect,'' but instead found themselves drawn into interviews with Ms. Sarandon, Rep. Tom Campbell and a representative of Ozomatli, the Latino rock group that had been playing in the protest zone when the Los Angeles police pulled the plug on Monday night. Later on Tuesday  they planned to drive into South Central Los Angeles to interview people on the street and then to go back to Staples Center for the evening's official events.</p>
        <p>The group moved like a pack through the crowded lobby at Patriotic Hall. Ms. Leitch was in the lead, Mr. Hoffman close behind, and Ms. Chaiklin tried to follow them and talk on her phone at the same time. Ben Weinstein, the director of photography, watched them through the eyepiece of his digital camera while the sound director, Jordon Pardes, trailed at the rear, his microphone hanging from a pole over their heads.</p>
        <p>''Our plan is to do three things,'' Mr. Leitch said. ''First, we're going to release some of our footage on an Internet site, some issue-oriented material and trailers for the movie, along with links to other campaign-related sites.''</p>
        <p>Then just before Election Day he hopes to have a soundtrack CD available in stores, a compilation of protest songs from the 1960's and 70's, covered by contemporary bands like the Stone Temple Pilots. ''What we're trying to do is to build a bridge between the protest generation of those days and the new generation today,'' said, Mr. Leitch, son of the 60's folk-pop singer known as Donovan.</p>
        <p>Around the same time the CD is released, a one-hour making-of-the-soundtrack program will be seen on VH-1, the pop-music cable channel. And then, around Inauguration Day in January, the finished documentary will be given a limited release in theaters, he said.</p>
        <p>''I was really very much influenced by the movie 'Woodstock,' the way it looked and felt, and am going for something kind of like that,'' he said. ''I especially liked that film's use of split screens.''</p>
        <p>He may try something similar in showing President Clinton speaking to the convention while the police and protesters are clashing outside.</p>
        <p>Hundreds of hours have already been shot, he said, from the primaries, from the campaign trail and now from the two national conventions. The videotapes are shipped daily back to an editing team in New York, where they are logged and digitized and the process is begun to give the film some sort of structure. While a good deal of the material may end up on the eventual Web site, the version shown in theaters will be of standard length, which means a lot of trimming and shaping. ''I don't want it to be longer than 100 minutes,'' Mr. Leitch said.</p>
        <p>As they have moved back and forth between the gatherings of young political activists and the mainstream apparatus of the national parties, the filmmakers have come to see that they are dealing with two fundamentally different ways of looking at the world, two universes that rarely meet and talk to each other, Mr. Leitch said.</p>
        <p>''Ultimately we have to find a way in the making of this film to bring those two worlds together: the world of the people outside the convention hall, the people on the streets, and the world of the people on the inside,'' he said. ''We have to figure out how to make them connect.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Sarandon smiled gently and leaned forward to hear Mr. Hoffman's soft-spoken questions in the noisy babble of the interview room. Mr. Weinstein hovered, Mr. Pardes's boom mike hanging like a pineapple over everyone's heads. They were talking about President Clinton's address to the convention on Monday night, especially the very theatrical lead-in during which he was seen making his lone way through the strangely empty corridors of Staples Center.</p>
        <p>''When I was watching it, you know, I could feel a tear in my eye, I really could,'' Mr. Hoffman said. ''I had to stop myself and say, 'Oh no, I'm getting moved, I'm getting manipulated.' ''</p>
        <p>ARTS IN AMERICA</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
