<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After 87 Years, a Proud Mom's Biggest Moment</title>
    <meta content="Y17PAU$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223206"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE DEMOCRATS: THE FAMILY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parties (Social)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions, National (US)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sack, Kevin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Pauline Lafon</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parties (Social)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000817T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E2D9173EF934A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1083" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After 87 Years, a Proud Mom's Biggest Moment</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEVIN SACK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sack, Kevin</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, Aug. 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Party in honor of Pauline LaFon Gore, 87-year-old mother of Vice Pres Al Gore, is held in Los Angeles on day her son is nominated for president; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On the day that her beloved Democrats were to nominate her beloved son for president, Pauline LaFon Gore sat in an elegant ballroom at the Regal Biltmore Hotel and greeted a long line of admirers who had come to pay tribute to the 87-year-old matriarch of the Gore family.</p>
        <p>She fussed over every guest, whether old friend or stranger, lingering so long in some cases that  Karenna Gore Schiff, her granddaughter, felt obliged to move the crowd along. When Marcia Lieberman paid an unexpected visit, Mrs. Gore rose from her chair and offered a warm hug to the 85-year-old mother of her son's running mate. She made no speech, but blew kisses to her granddaughter after Ms. Schiff toasted her as ''truly an amazing woman'' who had inspired thousands with ''her charm and grace, her grit and determination, and her idealism.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On the day that her beloved Democrats were to nominate her beloved son for president, Pauline LaFon Gore sat in an elegant ballroom at the Regal Biltmore Hotel and greeted a long line of admirers who had come to pay tribute to the 87-year-old matriarch of the Gore family.</p>
        <p>She fussed over every guest, whether old friend or stranger, lingering so long in some cases that  Karenna Gore Schiff, her granddaughter, felt obliged to move the crowd along. When Marcia Lieberman paid an unexpected visit, Mrs. Gore rose from her chair and offered a warm hug to the 85-year-old mother of her son's running mate. She made no speech, but blew kisses to her granddaughter after Ms. Schiff toasted her as ''truly an amazing woman'' who had inspired thousands with ''her charm and grace, her grit and determination, and her idealism.''</p>
        <p>It is a remarkable moment in the remarkable life of Pauline Gore, who rose from humble beginnings to become one of the first women to graduate from law school at Vanderbilt University, who participated as a full partner in the 32-year Congressional career of her husband, Senator Albert Gore Sr., who endured his painful election defeat in 1970 and the death of their daughter, Nancy, in 1984, and who has been a bulwark in the political life of their son, Vice President Al Gore.</p>
        <p>It is also a bittersweet moment for Mrs. Gore, who will watch her son's acceptance speech on Thursday night surrounded by family but missing her husband, who died in 1998 after nearly 91 years of life and 61 years of marriage. They met when she served him coffee at the Andrew Jackson Hotel in Nashville, where both were law students. Together they stoked the young Mr. Gore's ambition, nurturing him for public service from his earliest days and providing him a seamless political resume.</p>
        <p>''They really were a lovely couple to behold,'' said Bill McSweeney, a longtime family friend who recalls the Gores holding hands while watching ''The Lawrence Welk Show'' on Saturday nights.</p>
        <p>Since 1993, Mrs. Gore has endured a heart attack, brain surgery to remove a blood clot, and two strokes, one of which impaired her vision. Her husband trained her to walk again after the strokes, and she now strolls around the family farm in Carthage, Tenn., using one of his old wooden canes. The day after her surgery, she asked her nurses to hook up cable television in her hospital room so she could watch C-Span.</p>
        <p>She has good days, when she is just as lucid as ever and when her extraordinary memory is as sharp as the picture on a new television set. On other days, family members and friends say, she can appear tired and slightly confused. The vice president, who is highly protective of his mother, no longer allows her to grant formal interviews, and she has not done one in three years.</p>
        <p>But there was no sign today that Mrs. Gore, known to all as Miz Pauline, was having a bad day. And her family and friends say she has been completely attuned to her son's campaign in recent weeks and is thrilled to be attending the Democratic National Convention.</p>
        <p>''She is having a ball,'' Ms. Schiff said. ''This is her cup of tea. She is completely in heaven.''</p>
        <p>While Mrs. Gore is no longer strong enough to wage the kind of cross-country campaign she undertook during her son's 1988 race for president, she has not been content to sit idly at the farm. She speaks almost daily to Mr. Gore -- three times on the day of the New Hampshire primary -- and watches the Sunday political talk shows, making mental note of who says anything nasty about her boy.</p>
        <p>She attends Democratic events around Tennessee, took a prime seat at the unveiling of the Gore-Lieberman ticket in Nashville last week and has made numerous unscheduled visits to the campaign headquarters there.</p>
        <p>''She says, 'I just had to come check on you,' '' said Donna Brazile, Mr. Gore's campaign manager. ''She wants to talk to the strategists and the lawyers. She wants to know who everybody is, where they're from. And she reassures us that Al Gore is going to win.''</p>
        <p>Many who know Mrs. Gore well say  politics has been her tonic.</p>
        <p>''She can really be down, and then she'll get involved in the political process and she just seems to draw enormous strength from it,'' said Jerry H. Futrell, a Carthage pharmacist and longtime friend.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Gore has long been considered the most astute political mind in the family, a pragmatic strategist who continues to embrace the old-fashioned notion that politics can be personal. ''She recognizes in this wonderful, sort of uniquely feminine way how the human interaction in relationships are vital to social change,'' Ms. Schiff said. ''She has been a hostess in many ways throughout my family's political life, but a hostess with real power and insight.''</p>
        <p>It was always Mrs. Gore who spent the days before an election with long lists of phone numbers, calling preachers, friends and elected officials to encourage them to get out the vote. Just last Sunday, she went after church to the City Cafe in Carthage and campaigned for Mr. Gore at every table on the way out.</p>
        <p>''She said, 'You know how to pull the lever, and I hope you pull it for my son,' '' said Mr. Futrell, who accompanied her that day.</p>
        <p>Those who know the Gores well say the son drew more of his temperament from her than from the blustery father he followed into the House and the Senate. Both mother and son, they say, are reserved.</p>
        <p>Above all, Mr. Gore seems to have drawn strength and confidence from her enduring presence. ''She has given him the courage, the intellect, the background and the confidence that comes from a strong family,'' said Peter Knight, a former aide to Mr. Gore. ''He always knew they'd be behind him, and you have to have that confidence when you're running for president of the United States.''</p>
        <p>THE DEMOCRATS: THE FAMILY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
