<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No Word, but Many Rumors, On Choice to Succeed Safir</title>
    <meta content="17POLI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223180"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lipton, Eric</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Safir, Howard (Comr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000817T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807E0DC173EF934A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="837" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No Word, but Many Rumors, On Choice to Succeed Safir</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC LIPTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lipton, Eric</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Police Comr Howard Safir's final day at work is tomorrow and Mayor Rudolph W Giuliani has still not named a successor, inspiring elaborate series of rumors about whom mayor favors for post; speculation on Safir's successor noted; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>His police commissioner's final day at work is tomorrow and Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani has still not named a successor, and that has inspired an elaborate series of rumors from circulating about whom the mayor favors for the post.</p>
        <p>The anticipation reached a fever pitch yesterday afternoon, as reporters lined up outside the mayor's office for a routine weekly public safety meeting that occurred at the exact hour some city officials had predicted the mayor would announce his choice to succeed Commissioner Howard Safir, the mayor's longtime friend and adviser.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>His police commissioner's final day at work is tomorrow and Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani has still not named a successor, and that has inspired an elaborate series of rumors from circulating about whom the mayor favors for the post.</p>
        <p>The anticipation reached a fever pitch yesterday afternoon, as reporters lined up outside the mayor's office for a routine weekly public safety meeting that occurred at the exact hour some city officials had predicted the mayor would announce his choice to succeed Commissioner Howard Safir, the mayor's longtime friend and adviser.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Safir left the meeting, reporters quizzed him so incessantly that the usually reserved administrator resorted to humor.</p>
        <p>''Until I leave, I am in control, me and some general,'' Mr. Safir said, an allusion to Gen. Alexander M. Haig Jr., the secretary of state under President Reagan who asserted that he was in control of the White House after the president had been shot. While his last day is tomorrow, Mr. Safir said, he will actually serve as commissioner through the weekend. He said he was sure that the mayor would ''make the appropriate decision, and I'm sure I will support it.''</p>
        <p>The day began with city officials, speaking on the condition of anonymity, predicting that the mayor would name Joseph P. Dunne, the chief of department, a 31-year veteran who supervises patrol services, detectives and the organized crime, housing and transit units. Mr. Safir is said to be backing him. One official went so far as to name the administrator who was expected to get Chief Dunne's job.</p>
        <p>But by yesterday afternoon, other city officials and two former mayoral aides said Mr. Giuliani was strongly considering one of his longest- serving and most loyal advisers: his counsel, Dennison Young Jr. The other leading candidate, according to city officials, is Bernard B. Kerik, the commissioner of correction.</p>
        <p>None of the candidates would comment yesterday. Associates of Mr. Kerik and Chief Dunne said that as of late yesterday afternoon, even they did not know where the mayor stood.</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani added little clarity in his brief comment on the matter yesterday morning at a news conference in the Bronx ''I don't have a deadline,'' he said, ''but as soon as we have an announcement we'll make it.''</p>
        <p>Picking his third and presumably final police commissioner -- the mayor leaves office next year -- has been difficult in part because of the strength of the candidates, the mayor suggested last week.</p>
        <p>Chief Dunne, 52, has an unrivaled knowledge of the inner workings of the Police Department and a reputation a tough but fair precinct commander in Brooklyn who could work in harmony with black and Hispanic residents.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kerik, 44, a former detective, has been the administrator of the city's sprawling and once chaotic jail system since January 1998, significantly reducing inmate violence and controlling spending.</p>
        <p>Mr. Young, 57, would seem an unlikely pick. While he is close to the mayor, he is one of his lowest-profile advisers. But the mayor has a high level of trust in him. He was Mr. Giuliani's top aide in the United States attorney's office from 1983 to 1989 and followed him into private practice, where they worked as a team on many cases.</p>
        <p>Mr. Young has been the mayor's chief adviser on judicial appointments and an important law enforcement strategist. But some people close to the Giuliani administration expressed surprise that he was being considered, given that he would have to deal regularly with the public and the news media for the first time.</p>
        <p>''It would be a very unusual choice,'' said one former Giuliani aide, ''an ultimate insider, conciliatory figure, who does not have his own agenda. It would be a triumph of strict Giuliani ideological purity; no one is more loyal to the mayor.''</p>
        <p>Several mayoral aides said they were trying not to follow the debate over the selection too closely, as they said the mayor was angry during a staff meeting on Monday about news reports detailing where some of his advisers stood on the matter. ''I don't know, I do not want to know,'' one senior aide said. ''I am staying as far away from this one as I can.''</p>
        <p>It remained unknown when the mayor would make his announcement. As a press aide passed out Mr. Giuliani's schedule for tomorrow, which included the vaguely worded ''press availability'' at 9:45 a.m., the aide said repeatedly, without being asked: ''It's not the commissioner. It's not the commissioner.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
