<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Garden Q.&amp; A.</title>
    <meta content="17QNA.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223101"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000817T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00EEDD163EF934A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="692" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Garden Q.&amp; A.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Dora Galitzki</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lily Pad Takeover</p>
        <p>Q. On my small Virginia farm is a spring-fed pond 80 feet across. Where once about a fourth of the surface was occupied by pink and white lily pads, now the entire pond has been taken over, and the fish are dying. How best to cut back the lilies?</p>
        <p>A. Holding your breath and bending over the side of a rowboat to reach underwater and cut them back will gain you a year or so of, well, breathing room before they grow back. Because lilies won't grow in water more than four feet deep, the pond has probably become silted in, making it shallow enough that they can grow all across it. Draining and dredging will help by making the pond deeper. Be sure to check with the state environmental protection department first -- a spring-fed pond may be classified as a wetland, and you will need a permit to change it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Lily Pad Takeover</p>
        <p>Q. On my small Virginia farm is a spring-fed pond 80 feet across. Where once about a fourth of the surface was occupied by pink and white lily pads, now the entire pond has been taken over, and the fish are dying. How best to cut back the lilies?</p>
        <p>A. Holding your breath and bending over the side of a rowboat to reach underwater and cut them back will gain you a year or so of, well, breathing room before they grow back. Because lilies won't grow in water more than four feet deep, the pond has probably become silted in, making it shallow enough that they can grow all across it. Draining and dredging will help by making the pond deeper. Be sure to check with the state environmental protection department first -- a spring-fed pond may be classified as a wetland, and you will need a permit to change it.</p>
        <p>Waterlilies also prefer still water, so installing a recirculating pump to move water will make them less happy while increasing the oxygen supply for the fish.</p>
        <p>Waterlilies and ponds can coexist, however, if you take a few precautions. Plant them in pots, use the natural or man-made slope of the pond or sunken platforms to keep the pots no more than four feet deep. Pull them up every two years to divide and repot them, cutting off any rhizomes creeping over the pots' sides, heading for pond domination.</p>
        <p>Antidote for Hemlock Stump</p>
        <p>Q. Recently, I had a large hemlock tree removed. The stump remains, and I would like some information on how to hasten its decomposition.</p>
        <p>A. The best choice is to have it chipped down to just below the soil level. At least you won't be stumbling over it while you wait for nature to continue the rotting process. In four or five years the remaining roots will rot away. If you want to plant something right there right away, take a pickax and a saw, as well as a shovel, when you go out to dig the hole.</p>
        <p>There really isn't any practical way to speed up the process. Years ago, you might have poured a combustible chemical into holes drilled into the stump, lighted it, and let it slowly smolder away. No neighborhood today would welcome days of constant smoke.</p>
        <p>Of course you can always take the architectural alternative. If you don't like a structure, in this case the stump, plant vines.</p>
        <p>Indoor Tomatoes</p>
        <p>Q. I have grown tomatoes successfully in pots, but they have always been outside. This summer, we put seedlings in my daughter's very sunny southern-exposure window shelf, but inside. The plants grew and flowered but no fruit. Why?</p>
        <p>A. Most likely they are suffering primarily from unrequited love. While tomato flowers are complete, having both male and female parts, the pollen still has to get from one place to another within the flower. Outside, a visiting bee or a light breeze can move the pollen, but indoors it may not happen unless you give them a gentle morning shake when the flowers are fully open, to help transfer the pollen.</p>
        <p>Your bright southern exposure is a double problem. While it still doesn't supply enough light for a plant to make the food necessary for a major production like a crop of tomatoes, it does heat up the space between window and plant. Tomato pollen is killed by temperatures above 95 degrees, so even if the pollen found its way, it might not matter. Only the whiteflies will find the environment to their satisfaction.</p>
        <p>Take the plants outside -- who knows, there might be enough summer left to get a few tomatoes. And next year, leave them outdoors all season, where they belong.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
