<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Web Helps Military 'Brats' Find Long-Lost Friends</title>
    <meta content="17BRAT$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Circuits" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223112"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Military Brats Registry (Web Site)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sink, Mindy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Circuits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000817T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E0DB163EF934A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="963" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Web Helps Military 'Brats' Find Long-Lost Friends</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MINDY SINK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sink, Mindy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Military Brats Registry and other Web sites allow people who grew up in military families to find long-lost acquaintances from childhoods that had them moving frequently around the country and the world; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CAROL PASSAR lived in Pennsylvania for only a year, when she was 13, but she left behind her best friend when the military moved her family to yet another Army base in another part of the country. Nearly 40 years later, she was able to find her long-lost friend through an online registry for military ''brats'' like herself.</p>
        <p>''I saw her name there in the registry list, and I said, 'That's Jeanie!' '' Mrs. Passar recalled. ''And wonder of all wonders, she remembered me, too.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CAROL PASSAR lived in Pennsylvania for only a year, when she was 13, but she left behind her best friend when the military moved her family to yet another Army base in another part of the country. Nearly 40 years later, she was able to find her long-lost friend through an online registry for military ''brats'' like herself.</p>
        <p>''I saw her name there in the registry list, and I said, 'That's Jeanie!' '' Mrs. Passar recalled. ''And wonder of all wonders, she remembered me, too.''</p>
        <p>After exchanging a few e-mail messages, the two women met for coffee earlier this year. ''I recognized her right away,'' Mrs. Passar said with a laugh. ''Her hair was grayer, but all these years later she had the same fun personality that makes her fun to know.''</p>
        <p>The site Mrs. Passar used, the Military Brats Registry (www.military-brats.com), is one of a handful of places where people who grew up in military families can try to find long-lost acquaintances from childhoods that had them moving frequently around the country and the world.</p>
        <p>''When you're 13 years old, you don't really write a lot of letters,'' Mrs. Passar said, ''and these were the days before e-mail, and you couldn't just zap somebody a message around the world.</p>
        <p>''When you travel around all the time, you can't grow attached to a place. You can only become attached to people.''</p>
        <p>The Military Brats Registry is free to use and contains more than 43,000 names, with about 15 to 20 names added daily. It links to another site, Military Brats Online (www.lynxu.com/brats/index.html), that posts reunion messages and reminiscences on military base life.</p>
        <p>The registry was started by Marc Curtis of Redlands, Calif., whose father was an Army sergeant stationed at posts including Yokohama, Japan, and Fort Bliss, Tex. He was also at posts throughout California when Marc was growing up.</p>
        <p>''Military bratdom doesn't leave your system,'' said Mr. Curtis, now 49. ''There's a whole mind-set that you're brought up with. For me, after about 25 years, it started to become very important to find friends I grew up with on military bases.''</p>
        <p>One of the missing links in Mr. Curtis's life were friends from his elementary school in Texas, and on his site there is a page of photographs from his fourth grade class. Of the 30 students in the class, Mr. Curtis has found 12 and met with 4 of them.</p>
        <p>''After 39 years, almost nothing has changed,'' he said. ''I started the registry mostly as a way to find my own friends, and now wanting to help others find theirs.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Curtis said the site ''pays for itself'' through a little advertising and the sale of some items on the site.</p>
        <p>The site is organized by names (maiden names for married women) and high school graduation dates. Once registered, a person can scroll through the site to look for a familiar name or people from a particular  graduation year. Contact can be made via e-mail, which is routed through the site rather than directly to the individual for privacy reasons.</p>
        <p>''After I registered a couple of months ago, I kept checking my e-mail every week,''  said Amy Brown, 26, a schoolteacher in Plymouth, Mass., ''and I got a couple from people that I knew in high school in Scotland, but no really close friends. Then last week I got a call from a good friend who had seen my name on the registry and couldn't wait to e-mail. She had found out what town I lived in and called information.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Brown said she and her newfound old friend were now on a crusade to find more alumni from the Holy Loch, Scotland, schools for a reunion next year.</p>
        <p>One of the reasons people like Ms. Brown have difficulty tracking down old classmates is that military-run base schools are often prevented by privacy laws from providing alumni information, and some international schools have closed, making their records essentially inaccessible.</p>
        <p>There are dozens of individual sites for such schools, where alumni can look for old friends and teachers, many of which are listed on Military Brats Online. There is also the Canadian Military Brat List (www.hub .org/brat</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
