<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dance With Aliens and Save the World</title>
    <meta content="17GAME" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Circuits" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223080"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="GAME THEORY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sega Enterprises Ltd</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">herold, charles</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Columns/Game Theory</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Circuits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000817T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E6DB1E3FF934A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="890" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dance With Aliens and Save the World</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLES HEROLD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">herold, charles</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Charles Herold reviews Sega's Space Channel 5 game; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WITH her pink pigtails, orange gloves and platform go-go boots and a green ray gun worn like a garter, Ulala the space reporter is enough by herself to make anyone want to play Sega's Space Channel 5. At its heart is a simple memory game, but that is its least important element. Here we have the ultimate victory of style over substance, a little arcade game encased in glittering color and driven by infectious dance beats.</p>
        <p>In Space Channel 5, aliens invade 25th-century Earth and force the humans to dance. Ulala, an intrepid television reporter, finds that she can save the human race by copying the alien dances, move for move.  With each victory, the ratings for her program, ''Ulala's Space Report'' (broadcast on Space Channel 5), go up, but every misstep knocks the ratings down.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WITH her pink pigtails, orange gloves and platform go-go boots and a green ray gun worn like a garter, Ulala the space reporter is enough by herself to make anyone want to play Sega's Space Channel 5. At its heart is a simple memory game, but that is its least important element. Here we have the ultimate victory of style over substance, a little arcade game encased in glittering color and driven by infectious dance beats.</p>
        <p>In Space Channel 5, aliens invade 25th-century Earth and force the humans to dance. Ulala, an intrepid television reporter, finds that she can save the human race by copying the alien dances, move for move.  With each victory, the ratings for her program, ''Ulala's Space Report'' (broadcast on Space Channel 5), go up, but every misstep knocks the ratings down.</p>
        <p>If her dancing isn't up to par, her program will be canceled, and the human race will be doomed to an endless disco nightmare.</p>
        <p>Playing the game involves hitting the right button at the right time. The aliens -- short, colorful creatures with antennae and faces like television screens -- do a little dance while calling out their steps: ''Up, right. Left, down. Kick! Kick! Kick!''</p>
        <p>With their cute, high voices and  endless jumping, the aliens could be teaching line dancing to children on ''Sesame Street.'' Using the game controller, you make Ulala do the same little dance as the aliens -- same steps, same rhythm.</p>
        <p>If she can keep up, she can free the humans, who will join her for a victory dance while her director shouts, ''You go, Ulala!'' as if he were a morning D.J. waking up his listeners.  If she doesn't do well enough, she does a dance of mourning, holding her hands to her head and sighing deeply. As the game progresses, the dances become more difficult, with more frequent changes in tempo and more complex rhythms. At times you will have to shoot aliens and rescue humans, making sure to shoot the aliens with your alien-killing button and saving the humans with your human-saving button.</p>
        <p>It's a simple game, but often not an easy one. Usually when people say something is dreamlike or has dream logic, they mean that it is surreal, symbolic or unusual in its form and structure. But Space Channel 5 is like a real dream -- incoherent, confused, filled with senseless events and a story that jumps from one idea to the next in a disjointed, muddled fashion. Whether Ulala is rescuing a mesmerized Space Michael (a Michael Jackson lookalike), outdancing the ultimate robot reporter, Evila, or saving a group of children from a giant dance robot, this game makes no sense whatsoever.</p>
        <p>With chic visuals and music that is somewhere between a James Bond theme and a James Brown hit, all horns and bass, it doesn't matter whether it's really a reporter's job to outdance aliens or whether 60's fashions will be popular in the 25th century. As long-legged Ulala strides along with the beat, walking like one of Robert Crumb's ''Keep on Truckin' '' characters, the player is carried along with her, bouncing in rhythm in his or her seat, game controller in hand, waiting for the next round of competitive dancing.</p>
        <p>The fact that the game was created in Japan should come as no surprise. Japanese game designers have a talent for fast-paced, over-the-top entertainment unhampered by logic but informed by impeccable style. Space Channel 5 is a thrill ride with flashing lights and explosions, psychedelic play masquerading as a video game. It bypasses your brain's logic center entirely, making a direct connection to its center for fun.</p>
        <p>The frenetic choreography, catchy music and Day-Glo colors -- and phrases like ''Groove evening, ladies and gentlemen'' -- all seem designed to shut down your thinking and have you rely entirely on the primal dancer within. Perhaps it is Zen, tearing apart the logical cage of our brain, or perhaps it is nothing more than the video game equivalent of a good party, but whatever it is, it works.</p>
        <p>Eventually Ulala, with the help of two fellow reporters, Pudding and Jaguar, will blow to bits the giant robot made out of televisions and save the world from the dancing aliens. Then you'll be able to read the credits and discover that in keeping with the surreal nature of the game, Ulala's voice is done by someone named Apollo Smile.</p>
        <p>Like a particularly strange dream, the details of Space Channel 5 will evaporate when you wake up, and you'll find yourself with only a vague idea of what happened. ''The aliens were being hypnotized,'' you'll tell your friends. ''There was something about ratings. There were space tourists dancing with cameras and a space keyboard girl and, and well, it was weird.''</p>
        <p>By the end of the day, you won't remember even that much. But you'll find yourself walking along the street singing, ''Up! Up-up-up! Right! Left, down!'' And you'll always remember Ulala standing on the launching pad, saying: ''What's this? Something's up. I'm feeling kind of funky!''</p>
        <p>Space Channel 5, published by Sega for the Sega Dreamcast; $39.95; for teenagers.</p>
        <p>GAME THEORY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
