<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Concorde Is Stripped of Certification to Fly</title>
    <meta content="Y17CON$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223165"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Concorde Airplane</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">France</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Paris (France)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Air France</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cowell, Alan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France/Paris</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000817T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02EFDE173EF934A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1027" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Concorde Is Stripped of Certification to Fly</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN COWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cowell, Alan</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, Aug. 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>British and French regulators withdraw Concorde's airworthiness certification, effectively ruling world's only commercial supersonic airliner unfit to fly until it can be protected against safety flaws behind last month's fatal crash near Paris (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>British and French aviation regulators withdrew airworthiness certification from the Concorde today, effectively ruling the world's only commercial supersonic airliner unfit to fly until it can be protected against the catastrophic safety flaws behind last month's fatal crash near Paris.</p>
        <p>Narrowing their assessment of what caused the crash, investigators said they believed that a tire blowout had sent chunks of rubber flying into a fuel tank, rupturing it and causing it to burst into flames as the plane sped toward takeoff at 195 miles an hour.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>British and French aviation regulators withdrew airworthiness certification from the Concorde today, effectively ruling the world's only commercial supersonic airliner unfit to fly until it can be protected against the catastrophic safety flaws behind last month's fatal crash near Paris.</p>
        <p>Narrowing their assessment of what caused the crash, investigators said they believed that a tire blowout had sent chunks of rubber flying into a fuel tank, rupturing it and causing it to burst into flames as the plane sped toward takeoff at 195 miles an hour.</p>
        <p>Previously, French investigators said a 16-inch piece of metal on the runway had burst the tire, setting off the sequence of apparently freakish events that caused the plane to crash within 90 seconds of takeoff.</p>
        <p>''What is uniquely different in this case is that tire debris alone is thought to have led to this catastrophic accident,'' said Sir Malcolm Field, the chairman of Britain's Civil Aviation Authority, the regulatory agency that ordered the grounding of British Airways' Concordes today.</p>
        <p>Later in the day, the French aviation agency took the same action.</p>
        <p>The revocation of the Concorde's airworthiness certificate -- the document that permits airplanes to fly in the airspace of the authority that issues it -- was the first such action since the United States grounded the McDonnell-Douglas DC-10 for five weeks in 1979, aviation experts said.</p>
        <p>Even if Air France and British Airways -- the only airlines operating the Concorde -- decide that it is technically and economically feasible to modify the aircraft or introduce new safety procedures, the process could take ''months rather than weeks,'' said Mike Bell, a senior official of the British aviation authority.</p>
        <p>Echoing the assessment of some aviation industry analysts, Kieran Daly, editor of Air Transport Intelligence, an aviation Web site, said that ''it will be a finely balanced financial question whether to do these modifications or not.''</p>
        <p>British Airways said it had canceled Concorde service through early September but would resume it on 24 hours' notice if the airworthiness certification was restored.</p>
        <p>Air France grounded its five remaining Concordes immediately after the crash on July 25 of the New York-bound Concorde Flight AF 4590, which killed 113 people in the first fatal accident involving the Concorde. British Airways grounded its fleet of seven Concordes on Tuesday after learning that the airworthiness certificate would be revoked today.</p>
        <p>British Airways gave no clear indication whether it believed that the aircraft, which crosses the Atlantic in about three and a half hours at up to twice the speed of sound, would ever return to commercial service.</p>
        <p>The Concorde has been plying scheduled trans-Atlantic and other charter routes for almost 25 years and came to be seen as an icon of prestigious travel for executives and superstars ready to pay up to $10,000 for a round-trip journey taking half the time of a subsonic flight.</p>
        <p>As British Airways' flagship, Concorde was also seen as an important magnet in drawing high-end travelers to the airline.</p>
        <p>Sir Malcolm, the chairman of the Civil Aviation Authority, said today, ''It is clear to all of us in the C.A.A. that a tire burst alone should never cause the loss of a public transport aircraft.''</p>
        <p>Sir Malcolm said the authority had asked the Concorde's manufacturers -- BAE Systems, Airbus Industrie and Aerospatiale Matra -- to devise a plan to ensure that accidents could not be caused by burst tires.</p>
        <p>Under aviation regulations, airplanes whose fuel tanks are vulnerable to catastrophic damage from tire debris may not be certified as airworthy.</p>
        <p>Concorde's spindly, storklike landing gear is positioned directly below the wings, fuel tanks and engines. But British aviation experts say that the British Concordes were modified to protect the wings from burst tires, but that the Air France Concordes were not modified.</p>
        <p>Burst tires have been a worry for Concorde pilots since the plane entered service in early 1976, British aviation experts say.</p>
        <p>Since then, there have been seven known tire blowouts in which fragments struck fuel tanks without causing fires, the experts said. The modifications to the British Airways Concordes in 1993 involved changes to a water deflector on the undercarriage to ''reduce the energy'' from a tire blowout, said Derek Blackhall, the head of the certification section of the Civil Aviation Authority. Air France's Concordes did not have the same modification.</p>
        <p>But Mike Bell, a senior official of the aviation authority, told a news conference that it was ''quite unique, an unprecedented event'' for a burst tire alone to cause an air disaster.</p>
        <p>Sir Malcolm rejected the idea that the demand for modifications effectively meant that the Concorde would never fly again. ''We would wish Concorde to fly again,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Jean-Claude Gayssot, the French transport minister, said the measures did not necessarily imply the end of supersonic travel. ''Anyone who says it's the end for supersonic flights has got it wrong,'' he told the daily Liberation. ''Traveling fast is going to be increasingly in demand.''</p>
        <p>A British investigator, Ken Smart of Britain's Air Accident Investigation Branch, said the precise links between the sequence of events that doomed Flight AF 4590 last month remained to be established in detail.</p>
        <p>But he did say the tire blowout had sent debris flying, puncturing one or more fuel tanks and allowing fuel to spill out and catch fire within seconds.</p>
        <p>The airplane lost thrust in one engine, then in two, Mr. Smart said. ''The crew had no means to make them aware of the nature of the fire nor to take action against it,'' he said at a news conference.</p>
        <p>He said the safety issues relating to the tires would take ''some time to resolve.''</p>
        <p>The head of France's Accident Investigation Bureau, Paul-Louis Arslanian, told reporters in Paris: ''I hope the Concorde will fly again, but I am an investigator of accidents, not a witch doctor. I cannot read crystal balls.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
