<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Submarine's Namesake City Hurts As Minute After Minute Ticks Away</title>
    <meta content="Y17SCE$12" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223210"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Submarines</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Rescues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Kursk (Submarine)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Kursk (Russia)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kishkovsky, Sophia</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rescues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Submarines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000817T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE2D9173EF934A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="873" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Submarine's Namesake City Hurts As Minute After Minute Ticks Away</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SOPHIA KISHKOVSKY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kishkovsky, Sophia</byline>
      <dateline>KURSK, Russia, Aug. 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Residents of Russian city of Kursk tensely follow attempts to rescue crewmembers from crippled submarine named after city; many local young men are aboard Kursk submarine; map; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Valentina Staroseltseva thought she was lucky, because her draft-age son could have been sent to fight in Chechnya, the worst nightmare of most Russian mothers.</p>
        <p>But Dima, 19, won a prestigious spot on the Kursk, the navy's newest and most sophisticated nuclear-powered submarine, named after the southern Russian city the Staroseltsevs are from.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Valentina Staroseltseva thought she was lucky, because her draft-age son could have been sent to fight in Chechnya, the worst nightmare of most Russian mothers.</p>
        <p>But Dima, 19, won a prestigious spot on the Kursk, the navy's newest and most sophisticated nuclear-powered submarine, named after the southern Russian city the Staroseltsevs are from.</p>
        <p>''We thought the submarine was so safe,'' Mrs. Staroseltseva said  as she watched herself on television talking about her son, whose dream of serving in the fleet has turned into a nightmare as harrowing as anything in Chechnya. ''We called it our submarine. We were 100 percent confident in it. We really believed in it.''</p>
        <p>So much so that young men from the region competed for the privilege of serving on the submarine, with three candidates for every spot allotted to conscripts from Kursk. Dima, who had completed studies at a railroad engineering school, made the cut.</p>
        <p>Since last weekend the crippled Kursk has been lying on the floor of the Barents Sea, 80 miles from Severomorsk, home base of the Northern Fleet.</p>
        <p>In Kursk, Mrs. Staroseltseva and the parents of six other local young men are keeping an anxious vigil, surrounded by relatives and friends.</p>
        <p>They are camped around television sets, silent and tense, clenching their fists as the latest news reports speculate on the crew's dwindling oxygen supplies and discuss failed rescue attempts.</p>
        <p>The hopeful news today is that help from Britain is on the way.  The worry was that Russia waited so long to accept help.</p>
        <p>''I am angry that we didn't let the British come sooner,'' said Mrs. Staroseltseva. ''I keep thinking about why we didn't take this help. I as a mother want everything to be done faster and better.''</p>
        <p>Seeking solace, Mrs. Staroseltseva, a nurse, has been going twice a day to the bright yellow church near her house that she attended with Dima. She recalls the icon he was given by the bishop of Kursk, who blessed Dima and the other draftees at their sendoff last November.</p>
        <p>''I think maybe he is lying silently,'' she said. ''As a mother I hope he is calm. The main thing is not to panic.''</p>
        <p>But to a neighbor and Dima's aunt standing in her kitchen she reveals greater fears.</p>
        <p>''All this news is like a little stab, followed by a little stab,'' she tells them. ''It would be better if it happened all at once.''</p>
        <p>She now recalls that the head of the local military recruitment office, who was close to Dima, tried to talk him out of serving on the Kursk and urged him to serve on land, outside Moscow.</p>
        <p>On Monday she mailed Dima the pens he had asked for in his last letter. When she returned home, the disaster was all over the news.</p>
        <p>Today Mrs. Staroseltseva patiently fielded telephone calls and welcomed a stream of relatives and friends who came to the tree-lined street of one-story houses. The Staroseltsevs' brick house stands at a dead end.</p>
        <p>She describes how her fears that her gentle son would not withstand military life faded with each letter and each visit. While the Russian military is notorious for hazing and harsh living conditions, Dima wrote that he was well fed and had no problems with the officers or other conscripts. Draft dodging is rampant in Russia, but Dima wanted to serve in the military.</p>
        <p>The worried mother was convinced when she saw that after six months her skinny boy had gained nearly 17 pounds. He wore his gold-trimmed black uniform and dashing greatcoat with pride.</p>
        <p>There are several pictures of Dima with his best friend, Lyosha Nekrasov, 19, who is with him on the Kursk. Lyosha's mother calls several times a day to check in with Mrs. Staroseltseva.</p>
        <p>Everyone is frustrated by the conflicting reports on the state of the submarine and the rescue operation.</p>
        <p>''First they say there is enough oxygen only until the 18th, then they say there is enough until the 25th, then someone else says there is only enough for 72 hours,'' said Lyosha's mother, Nadezhda Nekrasova, who called the Staroseltsevs late tonight.</p>
        <p>''First they say they knocked, now they say they're not knocking,'' she said, referring to reports of S O S signals being thumped on the walls of the sub. ''My head is spinning.''</p>
        <p>Until today, the family had received no calls from local government or military officials.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Staroseltseva's salary of about $40 a month is not enough for train tickets to the north for herself and her daughter, Inna.</p>
        <p>With their help and that of the local soldiers' mothers committee, they and the families of the other sailors from Kursk are leaving on Thursday by train for Murmansk, near Severomorsk, a 45-hour odyssey that will tell whether their prayers for a miracle have been answered.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
