<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Returning to Home Turf, Americans Win in a Rout</title>
    <meta content="17SOCC$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223232"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SOCCER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Cup (Soccer)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Barbados</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yannis, Alex</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Barbados</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Barbados</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Cup (Soccer)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000817T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E1D8173EF934A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="631" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Returning to Home Turf, Americans Win in a Rout</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEX YANNIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Yannis, Alex</byline>
      <dateline>FOXBORO, Mass., Aug. 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>US defeats Barbados, 7-0, in World Cup qualifying game (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Barbados, a nation without a professional league, had a chance to embarrass the United States tonight, but the Americans avoided any upset with a 7-0 triumph in a World Cup qualifying game at Foxboro Stadium.</p>
        <p>The Americans entered the game as the only country without a victory and last in their group, which also includes Costa Rica and Guatemala. Anything but 3 points for a victory over Barbados would have been disastrous for the Americans, but they responded well, to the delight of 18,334 fans.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Barbados, a nation without a professional league, had a chance to embarrass the United States tonight, but the Americans avoided any upset with a 7-0 triumph in a World Cup qualifying game at Foxboro Stadium.</p>
        <p>The Americans entered the game as the only country without a victory and last in their group, which also includes Costa Rica and Guatemala. Anything but 3 points for a victory over Barbados would have been disastrous for the Americans, but they responded well, to the delight of 18,334 fans.</p>
        <p>With Coach Bruce Arena making his home debut in a World Cup qualifying game, the Americans were vastly superior, especially after two Barbados players were ejected for violent play by the Honduran referee, Jose Pineda, before the game was 41 minutes old.</p>
        <p>''The team was desperate to get 3 points,'' Arena said. ''We played against a team that was ahead of us in the standing. The results in Guatemala and Costa Rica were not in our favor, but we made progress in those games.''</p>
        <p>Joe-Max Moore led the Americans with two goals in his first game for the national team this year. It gave him a total of 22 goals and moved him into second place on the career scoring list behind Eric Wynalda's 33.</p>
        <p>Eddie Pope, Brian McBride, John O'Brien, Tab Ramos and Ernie Stewart scored the other goals for the Americans, who moved into a second-place tie with Guatemala, which suffered a 2-1 loss to first-place Costa Rica on Tuesday. Costa Rica has 6 points from three games, while the Americans and Guatemala each have 4 points.</p>
        <p>''We needed the maximum number of points, and we got them,'' said Moore, who scored his first goal at the stroke of halftime and his second with eight minutes left.</p>
        <p>''We're in good position now,'' said Moore, who plays for Everton in the England's Premier League.</p>
        <p>Pope opened the scoring with his fourth international goal in the 14th minute from about 10 yards away after a corner kick on the right by Ernie Stewart. Pope controlled the ball and calmly beat Horace Stoute, the Barbadian goalkeeper, with a low shot.</p>
        <p>McBride scored the second goal in the game and the 12th of his career for the United States in the 28th minute, when he took Moore's pass and beat Stoute with a low shot to the right corner from the arc on top of the penalty area.</p>
        <p>After Moore made the score 3-0  with his first of the night, the Americans broke the game open with four goals in the second half, including O'Brien's tally just 29 seconds after intermission.</p>
        <p>The goal by Ramos, who entered the game as a substitute for Claudio Reyna, was the most spectacular of the night, a blistering shot from outside the penalty area. It came in the 72nd minute, and it was the fifth of the game for the Americans.</p>
        <p>The Americans will play Guatemala next, on Sept. 3 at Washington, and will conclude the home part of their schedule with a game against Costa Rica on Oct. 11 at Columbus, Ohio. The United States and Barbados will play the last game in the group on Nov. 15 at Barbados.</p>
        <p>''Before all is said and done, Barbados will have more to say,'' Arena said, referring to the last game in the group for the Americans. ''Right now, our focus will be on Guatemala.''</p>
        <p>Arena and Moore said they hoped the last game in the group would be of no significance. They hope that by then it would be known which two teams from the group would join four others for the final round in the region, which will send three teams to the final stages of the tournament in Japan and South Korea.</p>
        <p>SOCCER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
