<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Town, Awaiting Peace, Reels From Congo War</title>
    <meta content="Y06CONG" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197190"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Congo (Formerly Zaire)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Kananga (Congo)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Crossette, Barbara</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Congo, The Democratic Republic of</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Congo, The Democratic Republic of the</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000506T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E6D91438F935A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1064" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Town, Awaiting Peace, Reels From Congo War</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA CROSSETTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Crossette, Barbara</byline>
      <dateline>KANANGA, Congo, May 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Residents of Kananga, Congo, still reeling from war, are overjoyed that their city has been designated one of four outposts of United Nations mission that will arrive sometime this year; human cost of war is evident everywhere in Kananga, which has no electricity, water for only hour per week and rusting remains of great rail hub; Kananga has been free of fighting, but it has become place of refuge for others with terrible stories to tell; thousands of emaciated refugees seeking escape from endless war are nearby; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>They ran to the side of the road, scores of people waving wildflowers or palm fronds or anything they could pluck from trees lining the route.</p>
        <p>''La Paix!'' they shouted. ''Peace! Peace!''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>They ran to the side of the road, scores of people waving wildflowers or palm fronds or anything they could pluck from trees lining the route.</p>
        <p>''La Paix!'' they shouted. ''Peace! Peace!''</p>
        <p>''They are saying, 'The U.N. is coming and the war will end,' '' a Congolese doctor working for Unicef said as a delegation from the United Nations Security Council rode into Kananga, a town in south-central Congo that seems to be sliding downhill from collapse.</p>
        <p>Kananga has been designated one of four outposts of a United Nations mission bound for Congo sometime this year. Three Security Council members left Kinshasa today to fly here over a vast sea of deep green  jungle and see what is in store for the peacekeepers.</p>
        <p>It was a voyage into the heart of sadness.</p>
        <p>Sir Jeremy Greenstock, the British ambassador to the United Nations, who had pressed for this visit away from the politics of Kinshasa, was moved by the passion of the crowd in a city that has no electricity, water for only an hour a week and the rusting remains of a great rail hub, once the pride of a line that went all the way to Cape Town. Thousands of emaciated refugees who have come to escape endless war are just 50 or 60 miles away.</p>
        <p>''You only have to see their faces,'' Sir Jeremy said. ''You have only to see the faces we saw on the streets of Kananga to see how very deeply they want the U.N. to come here and bring peace.''</p>
        <p>Peter van Walsum, the Dutch ambassador to the United Nations, and Martin Andjaba, his colleague from Namibia, shared Sir Jeremy's bittersweet reaction to the place whose fate might lie in their hands if the  Security Council decides the situation in Congo is safe enough to send 5,500 peacekeeping troops. It was good, they said, to get away from the diplomacy of capitals to see the reality. But the reality was sobering.</p>
        <p>It was soon clear, crossing the rutted streets of Kananga and catching glimpses of the buildings the United Nations mission in Congo may have to inhabit, that this will be a mission with a challenge. And a high price. The start-up costs in the first year alone may be $600 million. And that is just the projection.</p>
        <p>''This is going to be the most expensive peacekeeping operation ever, per head of peacekeeper,'' Sir Jeremy said. And putting it -- and the future of the Congo -- together, he said, is like walking ''on stepping stones in a river in the mist, where you can't see where the next step is.''</p>
        <p>For the United Nations and its members, who will have to pay the bill and send the troops, a policy of ''slowly, slowly'' prevails.</p>
        <p>For Andre Qabwe, a restaurant cook who was standing outside the gate of the provincial governor's palace when the Security Council delegation and the swarm of ministers and outriders arrived, that won't do.</p>
        <p>''We want them here this very night,'' he said, pointing emphatically to the ground between his feet. ''We have suffered too much, and now we need peace.''</p>
        <p>Kananga has a history of hardship. It was a town -- now swollen to a city of 700,000 -- that opposed Mobutu Sese Seko, the dictator who was driven from power in 1997 by Congo's current president, Laurent Kabila. The provincial governor's father was killed by Mr. Mobutu's thugs. But Mr. Kabila's victory has not brought peace or a better life, many people who gathered today said. As in many places in the third world, there is hope that the United Nations will bring not only peace but also jobs.</p>
        <p>It is a tall order for an organization that is not even sure the peacekeeping operation in Congo will ever be deployed, given the fragility of repeated cease-fires -- illustrated today by an outburst of fighting between Ugandan and Rwandan troops who are supposed to be united against Mr. Kabila's government, which they once supported. Does this point to another rearrangement of alliances, the Security Council diplomats wondered?</p>
        <p>For two reporters who visited the village of Katora, several miles beyond Kananga, the human cost of war was evident. Although Kananga and its outlying areas have been free of fighting, they have become places of refuge for others with terrible stories to tell.</p>
        <p>One refugee, Joseph, is 9 but the size of a child half his age in the richer world. He has never owned shoes. But last year he was thrown out of a hamlet under attack 120 miles away and separated from his family, so he followed a soldier here to Katora -- on foot. Once here, a Belgian priest, Ivo Vanvolsem, took him in and added him to his collection of desperate people who have lost the wherewithal to survive in a country watered profusely by rivers, replete with fertile land and studded with diamonds and gold. Here, even the adult men are skeletally thin, the sign of a lack of nourishment.</p>
        <p>Those are the ones who live. Lalula, a woman of about 30 from a distant village trashed by war, saw her husband die. She found her way to Father Vanvolsem with three of her children. One died on arrival, drained by malaria. She has the passivity of the truly hopeless.</p>
        <p>Martin Mogwanja, a Kenyan who is the Unicef representative in Congo, said women caught in the ebb and flow of war were not only victims of family tragedy these days but also among the fastest-growing groups of people infected with the virus that causes AIDS. Often, they are exposed to the disease when raped. In Eastern Congo, he said, women have been raped repeatedly as armies advanced, retreated, then advanced and retreated again. These women carry immense burdens.</p>
        <p>''In all these wars,'' Mr. Mogwanja said, ''the women are always the losers.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
