<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Beliefs; Conservative? Liberal? This bishop proceeds with an effort that's neither. Just important.</title>
    <meta content="06BELI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197174"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <org class="indexing_service">Roman Catholic Church</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Untener, Kenneth (Bishop)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Steinfels, Peter</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Columns/Beliefs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Columns/Beliefs</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000506T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E0DC1438F935A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1045" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Beliefs; Conservative? Liberal? This bishop proceeds with an effort that's neither. Just important.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Peter Steinfels</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Steinfels, Peter</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Beliefs column on Bishop Kenneth Untener, Catholic prelate in Michigan whose views defy stereotypes of 'conservative' or 'liberal' (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two Roman Catholic priests from New York and one out-of-town bishop were sitting in front of the audience. The priests were the ones in black clerical garb. The bishop was the one in a pale blue sweater and a sports shirt.</p>
        <p>This was three weeks ago in the parish hall of St. Paul the Apostle Church on Manhattan's West Side. Bishop Kenneth Untener of the diocese of Saginaw, Mich., was there to address several hundred people at a one-day conference on spirituality and social justice.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Two Roman Catholic priests from New York and one out-of-town bishop were sitting in front of the audience. The priests were the ones in black clerical garb. The bishop was the one in a pale blue sweater and a sports shirt.</p>
        <p>This was three weeks ago in the parish hall of St. Paul the Apostle Church on Manhattan's West Side. Bishop Kenneth Untener of the diocese of Saginaw, Mich., was there to address several hundred people at a one-day conference on spirituality and social justice.</p>
        <p>Bishop Untener is considered one of the more liberal members of the Catholic hierarchy, and not just because he shows up casually dressed at events like this. Although he is anything but a firebrand, from time to time he says things publicly, on topics like birth control and the ordination of women, that a number of other Catholic bishops say only privately.</p>
        <p>On this particular morning, however, Bishop Untener said nothing that Pope John Paul II would not heartily endorse, and he said it all in an easy, direct, enormously good-humored manner that totally won his audience's attention and trust.</p>
        <p>He did not delve into specific social or political injustices, about which his audience probably needed little education. Instead, he stuck to basic theology and spirituality. He unself-consciously made passing references to life after death that could have come from the most old-fashioned pastor. The ultimate focus of his remarks was the Sunday Eucharist.</p>
        <p>At a time when New Yorkers are scanning the horizon for the successor to Cardinal John O'Connor, Bishop Untener's remarks, and an interview with him later that day, are a reminder of the limits of the categories often used to describe church leaders, and not only Catholic ones.</p>
        <p>The terms ''liberal'' and ''conservative,'' for example, are notoriously slippery, depending on whether one is talking theology or politics. A little better is the tool kit of familiar types: the political churchman joining in civic debates, the doctrinal churchman teaching from the pulpit, the administrator making church agencies run smoothly or the comforter offering solace and performing good deeds.</p>
        <p>These stereotypes are not completely useless; nor are the categories of ideology, ethnicity and fund-raising abilities that the news media, as in their reporting on prospective archbishops of New York, readily import from the arena of party politics and presidential tickets. But they are all seriously insufficient.</p>
        <p>What Bishop Untener was eager to talk about, for example, didn't fit any of these categories, and yet, more than doctrine, sex, politics or finances, it may be the key to Catholicism's future in this country. His concern was the quality of Sunday worship.</p>
        <p>Seven years ago, Bishop Untener began meeting with his priests and deacons in groups of five to review and improve their preaching. Each person, including the bishop, was asked to record a live sermon, and the six tapes were sent to the whole group for listening before the gathering. Transcripts of these homilies, to use the more current term, were also made, and a veteran journalist working for the bishop marked them up the way a tough-minded editor would.</p>
        <p>Each group engaged in this process for four meetings. More recently, Bishop Untener has initiated a similar process, but this time with the videotaping of entire Sunday liturgies (again, his own included).  Priests can review their manner of presiding, the degree and nature of congregants' participation and the effect of the music. The meetings will begin, say, with analyzing how one priest or another conducted the opening prayers or the Eucharistic prayer. Always keeping the church's liturgical theology in mind, the participants discuss what ''worked,'' and what did not.</p>
        <p>''The conversations can get very spiritual,'' Bishop Untener said, ''for example, how hard it is to pray, really pray, in front of other people -- not just performing prayer -- so that when Ken Untener says, 'O God,' it is really talking to God. And there's no one single way to do that.''</p>
        <p>Where the tapes reveal general problems of congregational participation, for instance, the bishop has authorized limited liturgical experiments in a few parishes, although not in search of ''a hokey gimmick for each week.''</p>
        <p>One key to this whole process is honesty, he said. For priests, the gatherings can be ''a once-in-a-lifetime opportunity to hear some straight talk from a cross section of experienced peers,'' he wrote in ''Preaching Better'' (Paulist Press, 1999), a practical little book he has written for preachers.</p>
        <p>Another key, of course, is that the bishop is part of the same process as his priests. ''Once the priests found out it's not top down, but helping each other,'' he said on his New York visit, ''it wasn't threatening. It was welcomed.''</p>
        <p>That may all sound egalitarian and liberal. But another key to the process, Bishop Untener said, is that it is mandatory. Is that hierarchical and conservative?</p>
        <p>Other dioceses, including New York's, have set up liturgical teams that are ready to attend and analyze parish liturgies at a pastor's invitation, but by all reports relatively few parishes avail themselves of this kind of critique.</p>
        <p>Bishop Untener works through the diocesan roster of priests in alphabetical order. ''We make financial reports mandatory,'' he pointed out, so why be any less insistent about the quality of worship? Church people say that ''liturgy is the most important thing in a parish,'' he said, ''but that's not where we invest our thought.''</p>
        <p>No archbishop of New York could exercise leadership in the way that a bishop of Saginaw can. The New York archdiocese has 15 times the number of Catholics, 4 times the number of parishes and perhaps 10 times the number of priests in them.  A New York archbishop would have to find and appoint perhaps half a dozen liturgical mentors like Bishop Untener.</p>
        <p>But the real point is not the applicability of a ''Saginaw plan'' to New York. It is that this kind of pastoral strategy and creativity, although it touches on the very heart of church life, escapes virtually all the categories and labels tossed around in descriptions of future church leadership here or just about anyplace else.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
