<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>O'Neal and Lakers Leave Kings in Their Rearview Mirror</title>
    <meta content="06LAKE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197265"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Los Angeles Lakers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sacramento Kings</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lyman, Rick</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Los Angeles Lakers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Sacramento Kings</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000506T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06EFDE1538F935A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="856" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>O'Neal and Lakers Leave Kings in Their Rearview Mirror</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICK LYMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lyman, Rick</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, May 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Los Angeles Lakers defeat Sacramento Kings, 113-86, Los Angeles; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Let the word go forth: The Lakers did not, when push came to elbow, fold like a cheap paper fan. Southern California can now exhale.</p>
        <p>After a nasty scare that saw the eighth-seeded Sacramento Kings drive the No.1-seeded Lakers to a fifth and final game in the first round of the National Basketball Association playoffs, the Lakers decided it was all just a bad dream.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Let the word go forth: The Lakers did not, when push came to elbow, fold like a cheap paper fan. Southern California can now exhale.</p>
        <p>After a nasty scare that saw the eighth-seeded Sacramento Kings drive the No.1-seeded Lakers to a fifth and final game in the first round of the National Basketball Association playoffs, the Lakers decided it was all just a bad dream.</p>
        <p>The Lakers led the game from the beginning and eventually put together a dominating 113-86 victory tonight before a ravenous sellout crowd at the Staples Center. Their next meal, instead of a jumbo bucket of extra-crispy crow, will be the Phoenix Suns, who dethroned the San Antonio Spurs. The Lakers were 4-0 against the Suns.</p>
        <p>Shaquille O'Neal, after two weak shooting performances in the third and fourth games of the three-of-five-game series, suddenly remembered that he could scale tall buildings and bend steel in his bare hands.</p>
        <p>O'Neal scored a game-high 32 points on 15-of-24 shooting. He added 18 rebounds and 4 assists.</p>
        <p>The Lakers shot 52 percent from the field and controlled the backboards, outrebounding the Kings by 53-35. Kobe Bryant added 17 for the Lakers.</p>
        <p>The Kings were led by Chris Webber's 20 points.</p>
        <p>In the second half, it only got uglier. O'Neal and Bryant kept scoring, the Kings kept struggling, perhaps a little less gamely, and the lead increased to 20, then 25. At the end of the third quarter, it was 27 points. Then it went to 30, and then 35.</p>
        <p>A 40-point victory began to seem a distinct possibility. Jack Nicholson, at his customary courtside seat, could only lean back and smirk as he had never smirked before.</p>
        <p>Finally, in the early part of the fourth quarter, Jackson poured his bench onto the court and the Kings had a few opportunities for razzle-dazzle. Maybe the Lakers were feeling merciful. The lead diminished to the low 30's, and bounced around there for a while.</p>
        <p>O'Neal's 32 points energized the Lakers, in about the same way that a firecracker energizes a tin can, and they dealt once again with the bothersome Kings in the way that had been expected.</p>
        <p>The Lakers ruled the ball from the opening tip. O'Neal established position against Vlade Divac immediately, an effortless nine-foot jumper from the left side of the lane. His 20 points led the Lakers at halftime.</p>
        <p>The Kings made a few brief runs, but they did not last long. Most of the first half saw the Lakers cruising with a 10-point lead -- as boring and predictable as a freeway commute -- that extended to 15 in the final minutes, partly because Bryant began to hit more often and began to match O'Neal's pace.</p>
        <p>The big man was the story. He missed a few, and even let the ball be taken away from him once, but he just kept on coming and playing that weird trick where he changes from a lumbering 7-foot-1-inch, 315-pound hulk to weightless sprite in the blink of an eye.</p>
        <p>And O'Neal had to fight hard for some of his points. With four minutes left in the second quarter, his path to the basket was blocked, so he bobbed and was blocked again, so he weaved to the left, blocked again, pumped up and down a few times and then suddenly lifted into the air, without gravity, and lofted the ball silently into the net. At 1 minute 5 seconds left in the quarter, two of his teammates bobbled the ball toward the basket before O'Neal suddenly appeared under the basket, catching both Kings defenders flat-footed, and stuffed the ball home with attitude.</p>
        <p>When the Kings made it two in a row on Tuesday, humiliating the Lakers by 101-88 at Arco Center, Los Angeles went into a full panic. The great new Lakers dynasty eliminated in the first round? By the Sacramento Kings? Not possible. The Richter scale doesn't go that high.</p>
        <p>Still, Coach Phil Jackson counseled patience and confidence. The Lakers had not lost three games in a row at any time this season, and they were not about to do it in the final game of the playoff's first round, especially not at home at the Staples Center.</p>
        <p>Each of the 12 teams that had won more than 64 games in the regular season had gone at least as far as the conference championships in the playoffs, and nine had won titles. And in the 32 times since the three-of-five-game series began in 1984 that a top-seeded team (like the Lakers) had met an eighth-seeded (like the Kings), the No. 8 team had won only twice.</p>
        <p>This was the first time that the Lakers were involved in a decisive, win-or-lose playoff game since 1993. And that time they lost to the Suns -- in the first round.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
