<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Journal; How Fleeting Is Infamy</title>
    <meta content="06RICH" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197175"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rich, Frank</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stein, Ben</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/Frank Rich</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000506T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DEEDC1438F935A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1441" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Journal; How Fleeting Is Infamy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANK RICH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rich, Frank</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Frank Rich Op-Ed column, How Fleeting is Infamy, on triumph of Bill Clinton's stand-up comedy routine at White House Correspondents' dinner; notes his high public approval ratings both as president and 'entertainer-in-chief', and quotes Ben Stein's rueful prediction that Clinton will be last of the over-the-top characters for foreseeable future (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There haven't been raves like this since ''Saving Private Ryan.''</p>
        <p>''One of the best events that I've ever seen!'' -- Regis Philbin</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There haven't been raves like this since ''Saving Private Ryan.''</p>
        <p>''One of the best events that I've ever seen!'' -- Regis Philbin</p>
        <p>''It doesn't get any better!'' -- Sam Donaldson</p>
        <p>''Give that guy another term!'' -- Entertainment Weekly</p>
        <p>The show that earned these cheers was Bill Clinton's stand-up comedy routine at the White House correspondents' dinner last Saturday. If it had been rerun any more often, it might have turned C-Span into E! The president easily bested Jay Leno, the other act on the bill.</p>
        <p>As if to ratify Mr. Clinton's triumph, The Washington Post ran a front-page headline on Monday: '' 'Clinton Fatigue' Yields to Nostalgia.'' The Post cited polls showing that not only would Democrats vastly prefer Mr. Clinton to Al Gore as a candidate this year but that in a recent match-up the president pulled even with George W. Bush nationwide. Granted, this country has a short memory, but isn't Bill Clinton the same guy who was impeached and tried only 15 months ago? It's almost an insult to call him the comeback kid. He's had more comebacks than Elizabeth Taylor, Liza Minnelli and Richard Nixon combined.</p>
        <p>Or were they really comebacks? Writing in The New Republic two months ago, Sean Wilentz declared ''Clinton fatigue'' to be ''an utter hoax'' and ''the latest sign of the growing gap between what the public actually thinks and what the pundits claim the public thinks.'' He pointed out that the president's job-approval ratings -- the numbers most predictive of election results -- have been higher than those at equivalent dates in Ronald Reagan's lame-duck term, even during (or especially during) impeachment. The American historian Alan Brinkley notes that ''if you take away the first two years'' of the first Clinton term, ''he'd have the highest ratings in the postwar era'' of any president. ''It really is remarkable,'' Mr. Brinkley adds. ''For someone who has a hostile Republican Congress to deal with, he seems to exercise more power over Congress than most presidents have had over Congresses of their own party.''</p>
        <p>Nowhere was this more evident than in the Elian Gonzalez denouement. Immediately after Janet Reno's Miami raid, the now-familiar political arsenal of the anti-Clintonistas was rolled into place. Tom DeLay denounced federal agents as ''jackbooted thugs'' -- bizarrely reviving the N.R.A.'s incendiary pre-Oklahoma City rhetoric for the fifth anniversary of the bombing. The Wall Street Journal editorial page floated conspiracy theories in line with its tortuous efforts to link Mr. Clinton to drug-running at an obscure Arkansas airport; this time it speculated that the president might have been blackmailed by Fidel Castro and that Elian might have been drugged ''while in U.S. government custody.'' Enter the auxiliary troops, Matt Drudge and Lucianne Goldberg, whose Web sites offered painstaking exegeses of how the government doctored the photos of Elian and Dad.</p>
        <p>''You bet there'll be Congressional hearings,'' stormed Mr. DeLay on ''Meet the Press,'' echoing cries by Trent Lott and Orrin Hatch. And they'd be run by Henry Hyde, no less! The only missing element from this picture of Clinton hatred in full cry was the corpse of Vincent Foster.</p>
        <p>But where, pray tell, are those hearings? Apparently Clinton nostalgia trumps whatever remains of his opponents' testosterone. Reflecting the president's clout, polls showed that 60 percent approved of the raid and 68 percent didn't want any hearings -- numbers consistent with those balking at impeachment hearings and the Congressional release of the Starr report two years ago. No sooner did the Elian inquisition flame out than Jim Kolbe, an Arizona Congressman, also decided not ''to pursue any more hearings'' on Hillary Clinton's government-paid transportation for her Senate campaign. Such is Mr. Clinton's political potency that James Rogan, a House impeachment prosecutor now battling for re-election in California, popped up with the impeached president in a White House rally for gun control. Surely it's only days before William Bennett concedes to Larry King that, all in all, the Clintons' marriage is more credible than that of the other aspiring senatorial couple, the Giulianis, who can't even fake a truce for the sake of their kids after a cancer diagnosis.  My first sighting of conspicuous Republican nostalgia for Mr. Clinton was in March, when Ben Stein, the former Nixon speechwriter and host of TV's ''Win Ben Stein's Money,'' praised the president in USA Today for showing ''a lot of heart'' by sending top administration officials to the funeral of his father, the G.O.P. economist Herbert Stein. Ben Stein dislikes Mr. Clinton, writes for the Clinton-bashing journal American Spectator and is solidly behind Mr. Bush. And yet he had this to say over the phone this week: ''I will miss Clinton's humanity like I miss Nixon's humanity. You know a person is a person by his failings, and Clinton has a lot of failings. Without that human touch, you lose an important ability to connect with the body politic. Two machines are running to replace him -- the Gore machine, in which everything is calculated and calibrated, and the Bush machine, which is even more so. I don't like the idea of being governed by a machine. I like being governed by someone who has as many failings as I do.''</p>
        <p>Darrell Hammond, the Clinton impersonator on ''Saturday Night Live,'' has a not dissimilar take on Clinton nostalgia: ''I never met anyone who touches people as much as he does. . . . Here was a man caught lying on camera by an entire planet and got away with it and talked his way out of it. He's a scalawag, but darn, he does a good job! Crime's down, jobs are up, the budget's balanced. Who wouldn't miss him? When he gets that little crinkle in his voice, he's selling it to you and you're going to buy.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hammond is ready to go with his impersonation of Al Gore -- possibly tonight -- but is mindful of the vast difference between the two men. ''Clinton only shows you what he wants you to see,'' he says. ''Gore shows you what he wants to show you and everything else. You see the puppet and the puppetmaster. You see the ventriloquist's mouth move. The poor guy is trying too hard. So much preparation, so earnest, so much fumbling and stumbling. He should go out and say I can't act, I can't dance -- or nothing -- but I really want to be president.''</p>
        <p>This shortfall makes it unlikely that Clinton nostalgia will automatically benefit Mr. Gore come fall. If anything, the closest heir to Mr. Clinton so far is Mr. Bush. The president indicated as much in his stand-up routine, when he joked that the Texas governor had hijacked his old Dick Morris campaign strategy of ''moving toward the political center, distancing himself from his own party [and] stealing ideas from the other party.'' The parallels don't end there, or with the unsubstantiated drug rumors that have stalked both men without ever denting their political fortunes.</p>
        <p>In the '92 campaign, Mr. Clinton said that ''the most important thing'' he had accomplished as governor of Arkansas was improving education -- a claim no more borne out by Arkansas's dismal rankings in students' test scores than are Mr. Bush's hyperbolic claims for Texas. Mr. Bush's ''compassionate conservatism'' -- in which the federal government plays bite-sized roles in helping to feel and soothe Americans' pain -- lifts specific ideas from Mr. Clinton's New Democrat policies. Both men also have in common the repellent trait of advertising their toughness on crime by savage brandishing of the death penalty as governors: Mr. Clinton refused clemency to the brain-damaged Rickey Ray Rector; Mr. Bush denied clemency to Karla Faye Tucker and then mocked her in a Talk magazine interview with Tucker Carlson.</p>
        <p>This isn't to say that Mr. Bush is remotely in the Clinton league as entertainer in chief; no one is. Reading up for his game show on presidents who ''were grossly overweight, got drunk and went to all-night parties,'' Ben Stein ruefully observed, ''Clinton will be the last of the rollicking over-the-top characters for the foreseeable future.''</p>
        <p>If we hadn't gotten off the phone soon after, I fear we both would have been in tears.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
