<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gore and Bush Clash Further on Firearms</title>
    <meta content="Y06BUS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197195"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE GUN ISSUE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Firearms</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gun Control</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Texas</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Rifle Assn</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bruni, Frank</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Firearms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gun Control</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000506T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE1D91438F935A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1290" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gore and Bush Clash Further on Firearms</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANK BRUNI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bruni, Frank</byline>
      <dateline>SAN DIEGO, May 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vice Pres Al Gore vows to veto any measure prohibiting cities from suing gun manufacturers, measure gun manufacturers have been lobbying Federal lawmakers to pass; Gov George W Bush suggests he might support bill, noting that in Texas, he signed bill making it very difficult for local municipalities to sue manufacturers of legal product; divergent statements of Gore and Bush continue often tense back-and-forth over gun control that has lasted several days and signaled potential potency of issue in 2000 elections; each candidate has been trying to cast doubt on his opponent's commitment to gun control, and each has tried to tar other by linking him to National Rifle Assn; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The lines that divide the presidential candidates on the issue of gun control came into sharper focus today, as Vice President Al Gore vowed to veto any measure prohibiting cities from suing gun manufacturers and Gov. George W. Bush suggested he might support it.</p>
        <p>Gun manufacturers have been lobbying Federal lawmakers for such legislation; Mr. Gore, in an interview today, pledged to block that effort and questioned whether Mr. Bush would do likewise.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The lines that divide the presidential candidates on the issue of gun control came into sharper focus today, as Vice President Al Gore vowed to veto any measure prohibiting cities from suing gun manufacturers and Gov. George W. Bush suggested he might support it.</p>
        <p>Gun manufacturers have been lobbying Federal lawmakers for such legislation; Mr. Gore, in an interview today, pledged to block that effort and questioned whether Mr. Bush would do likewise.</p>
        <p>''I challenge Governor Bush to make the same pledge,'' Mr. Gore said in an interview with Political Points, the Webcast of The New York Times and ABC News. ''Will he veto any bill that lets gun manufacturers off the hook? Will he fight for the gun industry or for America's families?''</p>
        <p>When Mr. Bush was asked about that at a subsequent news conference here, he said, ''It depends on what's in the legislation.''</p>
        <p>But the Texas governor added, ''You can get a feel for my position by looking at what I've done in office, and what I did in office was sign a bill that made it very difficult for local municipalities to sue manufacturers of a legal product.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush was referring to a 1999 law that required lawsuits against gun makers to be filed, on behalf of Texas cities or counties, by the state attorney general, who might or might not support that course of action. The measure was similar to ones supported by other Republican governors, and reflected their general push to curb civil litigation in an array of areas.</p>
        <p>The divergent statements of Mr. Gore and Mr. Bush continued an often tense back-and-forth over gun control that has lasted several days and signaled the potential potency of the issue in the 2000 elections. Each candidate has been trying to cast doubt on his opponent's commitment to gun control, and each has been trying to tar the other by linking him to the National Rifle Association.</p>
        <p>At his news conference, Mr. Bush said that Mr. Gore had a voting history in Congress of support for the N.R.A.'s positions and a good deal of explaining to do.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Bush's aides circulated a brief document, titled ''Al Gore &amp; Guns,'' that cited examples from the 1980's of Mr. Gore's agreements with the gun lobby, the governor used a news conference here today to cast the vice president as a candidate whose current advocacy of more stringent restrictions on firearms was simply the latest fashion, not a matter of steadfast principle.</p>
        <p>''When it was convenient politically, he voted one way,'' Mr. Bush said, ''and when it's convenient politically, he's changed his tune.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush also refused to back off his suggestion on Thursday that Mr. Gore was once a member of the N.R.A. and, when challenged today to say how he knew that, offered no proof.</p>
        <p>Instead, he reminded reporters that he ended his statement about Mr. Gore and the N.R.A. with the phrase ''if I'm not mistaken,'' and told them it was their job to verify the assertion and Mr. Gore's responsibility to show that he was not a member of the group.</p>
        <p>Pressed about where he had gotten the idea in the first place, the governor responded, ''A little birdie.''</p>
        <p>William Powers, a spokesman for the gun organization, said he had found no evidence that Mr. Gore had been a member. But he said that when Mr. Gore was a congressman from Tennessee, ''he certainly received very high ratings from the N.R.A.''</p>
        <p>Douglas Hattaway, a spokesman for the Gore campaign, said that it could not find any record of Mr. Gore's ever being a member of the N.R.A., and that the vice president ''doesn't have any recollection of it.''</p>
        <p>''But it's an irrelevant issue anyway,'' Mr. Hattaway added. ''Al Gore is standing up to the N.R.A.'s leadership and its increasingly extreme agenda, while Bush is doing their bidding.''</p>
        <p>The exchanges between the Bush and Gore campaigns were touched off in part by a gun control group's distribution this week of a television commercial featuring footage of an N.R.A. official saying that if Mr. Bush became president, the organization would be working out of the White House. Mr. Bush said that was not true.</p>
        <p>His efforts today to turn the tables on Mr. Gore seemed to reflect not only the ascendancy of gun control as a political issue but also Mr. Bush's desire to court swing voters, many of whom favor greater regulation of firearms.</p>
        <p>And Mr. Bush took his swipes at Mr. Gore during his third day of campaigning in California, a state full of such voters.</p>
        <p>In fact, Mr. Bush's campaign schedule here this week represented an especially aggressive attempt to portray the Texas governor as a progressive, open-minded Republican by emphasizing his sensitivity of religious and ethnic diversity.</p>
        <p>In recognition of Cinco de Mayo, a Mexican-American holiday, Mr. Bush delivered a long address here this morning on the shared values of Latinos and other Americans. In it Mr. Bush used more Spanish phrases and sentences than he had previously used on the campaign trail this year.</p>
        <p>And he made a plea for greater acceptance of new immigrants, recalling his introduction, during a walk through Santa Ana on Thursday, to a grocery store owner who had come to California from Mexico with very little except ''a sueno,'' or dream.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's remarks, delivered to hundreds of people at a ''breakfast fiesta'' sponsored by a private group called the U.S.-Mexico Foundation, followed a series of events, encounters and photo opportunities -- many of them filmed by the candidate's advertising team -- that put Mr. Bush together with Latino and Roman Catholic voters.</p>
        <p>The first group is crucial to Mr. Bush's hopes of winning California. The second is key to his success nationwide, and Mr. Bush has been working especially hard to appeal to Catholics since his controversial appearance in February at Bob Jones University in South Carolina, a school with a history of anti-Catholic bias.</p>
        <p>The Bush campaign also said today that Mr. Bush would postpone a speech about Social Security, scheduled for Monday, so that he could attend the funeral Mass for Cardinal John O'Connor in New York.</p>
        <p>According to the Bush campaign document about Mr. Gore's record on gun control in Congress, he supported a measure to remove a ban on interstate sales of rifles, shotguns and handguns; opposed a 14-day waiting period for handgun purchases, and from 1985 to 1990, as a  senator from Tennessee, cast votes that were in line with the wishes of the N.R.A. three-quarters of the time.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hattaway did not dispute that, saying that Mr. Gore's positions had evolved with the growing prevalence of gun-related violence in the country. He also said the N.R.A. is more extreme now than it has been in the past.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hattaway noted that Mr. Gore now advocates a much wider array of restrictions on firearms than Mr. Bush, who signed legislation in Texas that permitted people to carry concealed handguns and seemed in other ways to agree with the N.R.A.</p>
        <p>Recently, though, Mr. Bush chastised an official with the organization for making inflammatory statements about President Clinton. He also signaled a slightly greater receptiveness to some gun-control proposals. And he has tried to link Mr. Gore to the N.R.A.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE GUN ISSUE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
