<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>State Can Seek Full Financial Takeover of Camden, Judge Says</title>
    <meta content="06CAMD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197212"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Camden (NJ)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mansnerus, Laura</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Orlando, Francis J (Judge)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000506T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E4D71438F935A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="531" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>State Can Seek Full Financial Takeover of Camden, Judge Says</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAURA MANSNERUS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mansnerus, Laura</byline>
      <dateline>CAMDEN, N.J., May 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Superior Court Judge Francis J Orlando rules New Jersey can seek full takeover of Camden's financial operations under law governing financially distressed cities; cites city's 'gross failure' to follow state-mandated accounting and budget practices; city has resisted state move to assert budget controls (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Superior Court judge today dismissed the City of Camden's efforts to keep control of its financial operations and ruled that the state can seek a full takeover.</p>
        <p>Citing the ''gross failure'' of the city to follow state-mandated accounting and budget practices, Judge Francis J. Orlando supported the state's argument that Camden's finances were in imminent jeopardy. The court's ruling was needed for the state to invoke its law governing financially distressed cities.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A Superior Court judge today dismissed the City of Camden's efforts to keep control of its financial operations and ruled that the state can seek a full takeover.</p>
        <p>Citing the ''gross failure'' of the city to follow state-mandated accounting and budget practices, Judge Francis J. Orlando supported the state's argument that Camden's finances were in imminent jeopardy. The court's ruling was needed for the state to invoke its law governing financially distressed cities.</p>
        <p>Judge Orlando found that the city was in ''a precarious financial state'' and that the limited state oversight imposed in 1998 had failed to correct its problems. A full takeover would place the city under complete fiscal supervision by the State Department of Community Affairs.</p>
        <p>City officials have resisted any move by the state to assert controls over its $112 million annual budget.</p>
        <p>The mayor was indicted by a federal grand jury on corruption charges on March 30, and when state officials moved last month for a financial takeover, they argued that the mayor would be unable to correct his budget problems.</p>
        <p>The city attorney, John A. Misci Jr., argued in court today that Camden's accounts were in good order.  ''Fires are being put out. Potholes are being filled. Flowers are being planted,'' Mr. Misci said. ''The city's running fine.''</p>
        <p>But Judge Orlando rejected Mr. Misci's argument that the city had caught up on budget and auditing procedures. The judge cited findings that the city's uncollected taxes were approaching $100 million and that it had filed its annual audit more than a year late for the last three fiscal years -- the only municipality in the state to do so.</p>
        <p>''We're very pleased that the judge accepted the evidence we offered,'' said Deputy Attorney General Mark J. Fleming, who had argued for the state. He said Camden was the first city to contest state control in court.</p>
        <p>Mr. Misci left immediately after the ruling and could not be reached for comment later in the day. Calls to Mayor Milan's office late yesterday afternoon were not answered.</p>
        <p>The state asked for the court determination three weeks ago. Today, the commissioner of community affairs, Jane M. Kenny, said the state's Local Finance Board would consider the request at its meeting Wednesday. She said the state would ask for the full authority allowed under the law, which includes control over collective bargaining agreements and the hiring and firing of some city department heads.</p>
        <p>No one knows yet what a full state takeover would mean for the city's day-to-day operations, said Ulrich Steinberg, the director of the finance board. The board, he said, would first have to find out what the city's circumstances are; that has been impossible, the state has argued, because of sloppy record-keeping.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
