<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="06DIGE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197196"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000506T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E0D91438F935A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="951" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>U.S. Unemployment Rate Declines to a 30-Year Low  The Labor Department reported that the nation's unemployment rate fell below 4 percent in April for the first time in 30 years, as employers hired tens of thousands of census takers, restaurant employees and temporary workers and the robust economy showed no signs of letting up.</p>
        <p>There was little evidence in the numbers -- a total of 340,000 new jobs last month and a 3.9 percent unemployment rate -- that the record nine-year-old expansion might be weakening in response to the Federal Reserve's attempt to slow the economy by raising interest rates five times since last June. [Page A1.]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>U.S. Unemployment Rate Declines to a 30-Year Low  The Labor Department reported that the nation's unemployment rate fell below 4 percent in April for the first time in 30 years, as employers hired tens of thousands of census takers, restaurant employees and temporary workers and the robust economy showed no signs of letting up.</p>
        <p>There was little evidence in the numbers -- a total of 340,000 new jobs last month and a 3.9 percent unemployment rate -- that the record nine-year-old expansion might be weakening in response to the Federal Reserve's attempt to slow the economy by raising interest rates five times since last June. [Page A1.]</p>
        <p>Stock Gauges Rise in Light Trading  Stocks rose on the lowest trading volumes of the year as investors seemed to ignore the decline in the nation's unemployment rate. The Dow Jones industrial average jumped 165.37 points, or 1.6 percent, to 10,577.86. The Nasdaq composite index finished up 96.58 points, or 2.6 percent, to 3,816.82, while the Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index rose 23.06 points, or 1.6 percent, to 1,432.63. [C3.]</p>
        <p>Concerns Guilty in Price-Fixing Case  Four drug companies agreed to plead guilty and pay $33 million in fines for taking part in an international conspiracy to fix vitamin prices. The companies -- two American and two German -- are the latest to plead guilty in the Justice Department's investigation of the vitamin industry. [C2.]</p>
        <p>BMW Raises Doubts in Rover Deal  BMW of Germany raised new doubts about the likelihood of a deal with the Phoenix Consortium of Britain, which is supported by labor unions and the British government, to rescue BMW's ailing Rover Cars operations at one of the biggest auto plants in Britain. [C2.]</p>
        <p>Phone Companies End Merger Talks  Talks about a merger between two leading European telecommunication companies -- Royal KPN of the Netherlands and Telefonica of Spain -- broke down. The companies said that a majority of the Telefonica board backed the deal but that opposition ''by an important minority group within the board'' undermined KPN's confidence in the chance for success of the new company. [C2.]</p>
        <p>Cisco In Stock Deal for ArrowPoint  Cisco Systems agreed to buy ArrowPoint Communications in a stock swap valued at $5.7 billion. The deal will give Cisco, the maker of network equipment, the technology it needs to compete in the fast-growing market for devices that can distribute Internet content intelligently. [C2.]</p>
        <p>Oil Is Found in a Big Caspian Field  A consortium of nine foreign energy companies has found oil in a huge Caspian Sea field and has resumed drilling to determine just how much exists. It will be at least another month before the drilling establishes if Kashagan has commercial volumes of oil. [C2.]</p>
        <p>ADC to Buy Fiber Optic Makers  ADC Telecommunications, a provider of technology that speeds the transmission of voice, data and video signals, said it would buy two European fiber optic component makers. ADC, based in Minnetonka, Minn., will pay $872 million in stock for the Swedish laser maker Altitun and will pay roughly $80 million in cash for Ibsen Micro Structures of Denmark. [C3.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
