<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Marathon on Ice: Tired Teams Skate Into the Wee Hours</title>
    <meta content="Y06HOC$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197201"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Hockey League</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Philadelphia Flyers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pittsburgh Penguins</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lapointe, Joe</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Primeau, Keith</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Philadelphia Flyers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Pittsburgh Penguins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000506T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E1D81438F935A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1144" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Marathon on Ice: Tired Teams Skate Into the Wee Hours</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE LAPOINTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lapointe, Joe</byline>
      <dateline>PITTSBURGH, May 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Game 4 of second-round playoff series between Pittsburgh Penguins and Philadelphia Flyers goes into five overtime periods, ending at 2:35 am with Philadelphia winning, 2-1, on goal by Keith Primeau; this is National Hockey League's third-longest game; NHL says that 6-hour-56-minute length in real time is longest game in its history; exhausted players lack both strength and speed in final minutes of game; photo; chart (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the two dressing rooms, during the many intermissions, hockey players consumed what was to have been their postgame pizza. They munched on nutritional energy bars, washing them down with water and other healthful beverages. They stretched to ward off muscle cramps. They talked among themselves about who would get the winning goal that would allow everyone to finally go home.</p>
        <p>In the stands, less than half full at the end but standing room only many hours before, a few fans slept while waiting for the third, fourth and fifth overtime periods of Game 4 of the second-round playoff series between the Pittsburgh Penguins and the Philadelphia Flyers. Others visited refreshment stands that were still open but out of everything but nachos and peanuts. ''Let's go, Pens!'' some chanted, rooting for the hometown Penguins. ''Let's go home!'' one fan shouted in retort.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the two dressing rooms, during the many intermissions, hockey players consumed what was to have been their postgame pizza. They munched on nutritional energy bars, washing them down with water and other healthful beverages. They stretched to ward off muscle cramps. They talked among themselves about who would get the winning goal that would allow everyone to finally go home.</p>
        <p>In the stands, less than half full at the end but standing room only many hours before, a few fans slept while waiting for the third, fourth and fifth overtime periods of Game 4 of the second-round playoff series between the Pittsburgh Penguins and the Philadelphia Flyers. Others visited refreshment stands that were still open but out of everything but nachos and peanuts. ''Let's go, Pens!'' some chanted, rooting for the hometown Penguins. ''Let's go home!'' one fan shouted in retort.</p>
        <p>This was early this morning in Mellon Arena, the site of the National Hockey League's third-longest game. It began at 7:39 p.m. on Thursday and ended at 2:35 a.m. today, with Philadelphia winning, 2-1, on a goal by Keith Primeau.</p>
        <p>Primeau said that he had experienced leg cramps earlier, and that he lost track of periods and the time of night.</p>
        <p>''If I thought of what period it was or what time it was it would throw me off,'' Primeau said.</p>
        <p>His goal, ending a game that lasted 152 minutes and 1 second on the scoreboard clock, helped the Flyers tie the four-of-seven-game Eastern Conference semifinal at two victories each. Game 5 will be on Sunday in Philadelphia. It begins around noon, so it should be over before dark.</p>
        <p>The N.H.L. said the 6-hour-56-minute length in real time was the longest game in its history. In that same time span, the fastest runners could complete the Boston, New York and Olympic marathons and still have time for sprints; horses could run more than 200 Kentucky Derbys.</p>
        <p>Into the fifth overtime period, in a sudden-death situation in which the next goal would clinch the victory, players strived in vain to muster a winning shot. Toward the end, with no strength or speed, they looked like the middle-age men who sometimes pool their money to rent rinks for what are sometimes called beer leagues. Ron Tugnutt, the Pittsburgh goalie, said, ''Everything seemed to be in slow motion.''</p>
        <p>He added: ''This is the wildest thing I've ever been through. The mind kind of shuts down on you. I was just in a daze.''</p>
        <p>He had his reasons. In a normal three-period game, a goalie might face 25 to 35 shots; Tugnutt faced 72, stopping 70 of them, and his teammates blocked another 42. Seven of those were blocked by Darius Kasparaitis, the Pittsburgh defenseman who at the end was victimized by Primeau's smooth move that created shooting space in the right-wing face-off circle.</p>
        <p>''Each overtime you go on it's getting ridiculous,'' Kasparaitis said. ''Some guys are not even hitting anybody, just falling apart. It was tough, but it was a good experience. Sometimes, it was funny. John LeClair was falling all over the place. Both benches were laughing.''</p>
        <p>On Sunday Pittsburgh stages its annual marathon, also the Olympic qualifying race. The Penguins got their marathon three days early.</p>
        <p>''To play that long and that hard and that well and lose -- well, it's rough,'' Pittsburgh's Rob Brown said.</p>
        <p>Jaromir Jagr, the Penguins' team captain who was last season's most valuable player and this season's scoring champion, said when a game goes this long, ''You don't even play hockey.''</p>
        <p>Jagr added: ''It's just skating. I was so tired I didn't feel anything.'' Jagr led his team in minutes played with 59:08, twice what he might play in a regulation game.</p>
        <p>LeClair, Philadelphia's star left wing, caused the overtime by scoring the tying goal early in the third period of regulation. Nobody was certain, but video review suggested the puck might have entered the net after bouncing off a Pittsburgh stick and then LeClair's helmet. ''Something dinged my head,'' LeClair said. ''I didn't touch it with my stick.''</p>
        <p>Pittsburgh's Aleksei Kovalev had scored on the first Pittsburgh shot of the game, before sunset, at 2:22 of the first period.</p>
        <p>''You're not even thinking about what you're doing,'' Kovalev said of the overtimes. ''Your body is playing for you. When you go that long, it's all about luck. You start making moves on defensemen and you can see they're not even reacting. What else can you do?''</p>
        <p>But Kasparaitis reacted to Primeau's move, and Primeau wristed a rising shot over the glove of Tugnutt to end the longest game since March 24, 1936. That was when Mud Bruneteau of the Detroit Red Wings scored after 176:30 to beat the Montreal Maroons by 1-0. In second place is Toronto's 1-0 victory over Boston on April 3, 1933; that one lasted 164:46.</p>
        <p>After his teammates mobbed him and left the ice, Primeau stripped off his uniform and stood in the corner of the locker room wearing a weary smile and gray underclothing, soaked in perspiration. In his hand he held a bottle of water. ''I definitely feel dehydrated,'' Primeau said. ''It was a lot of fun to play in that game. I was surprised that it was only the third-longest game. It felt like an eternity.''</p>
        <p>Because there are no timeouts for television commercials after regulation time, the pace of the game seemed brisk even as the skating of the players slowed down.</p>
        <p>Brian Boucher, the Flyers' goalie, said players were joking that if they won they would get today off from practice. He said his body was cramping and that his skates held so much perspiration that he could ''feel it squashing around in there.''</p>
        <p>When Primeau beat Tugnutt at the other end, Boucher said he heard the pinging sound of the puck hitting the metal part in the back of the net but could barely see the red light bulb behind the cage that signaled the goal. Then came the sound of near silence. ''You could hear that the crowd was so disgusted,'' he said.</p>
        <p>And the crowd could hear the shouts of happy Flyers gathering around Primeau, and their tired hands pounding him on his broad back. ''We're going down in hockey history,'' Primeau said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
