<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>This Is New York, Eileen; People Just Dance Around</title>
    <meta content="06TOWN$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197152"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brantley, Ben</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bernstein, Leonard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Comden, Betty</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Green, Adolph</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fields, Joseph</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chodorov, Jerome</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marshall, Kathleen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Murphy, Donna</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Wonderful Town (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000506T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06EEDE1438F935A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1395" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>This Is New York, Eileen; People Just Dance Around</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN BRANTLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brantley, Ben</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ben Brantley reviews revival of play Wonderful Town, by Leonard Bernstein, Betty Comden and Adolph Green, with book by Joseph Fields and Jerome Chodorov, directed by Kathleen Marshall; Donna Murphy stars; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>All of a sudden the queen of somber is shooting off sparks of light. And not only sparks. Heck, it's more like a festival of fireworks that Donna Murphy is providing in the rapturous Encores! production of ''Wonderful Town'' at City Center this weekend: a spectrum of comic color and shimmer hardly expected from an actress who seemed well on her way to becoming the dark lady of the American musical.</p>
        <p>Ms. Murphy, as you probably know, became a star and a two-time Tony winner in the 1990's portraying paragons of anguish and anxiety: the homely, love-starved heroine of Stephen Sondheim's ''Passion,'' who had sex and died, and the cold colonial widow with a streak of masochism in the reconceived version of ''The King and I.'' There was an extraordinary emotional intensity and professional focus to these performances, but they didn't leave you thinking that if you wanted a rollicking good time, Ms. Murphy was the gal to call on.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>All of a sudden the queen of somber is shooting off sparks of light. And not only sparks. Heck, it's more like a festival of fireworks that Donna Murphy is providing in the rapturous Encores! production of ''Wonderful Town'' at City Center this weekend: a spectrum of comic color and shimmer hardly expected from an actress who seemed well on her way to becoming the dark lady of the American musical.</p>
        <p>Ms. Murphy, as you probably know, became a star and a two-time Tony winner in the 1990's portraying paragons of anguish and anxiety: the homely, love-starved heroine of Stephen Sondheim's ''Passion,'' who had sex and died, and the cold colonial widow with a streak of masochism in the reconceived version of ''The King and I.'' There was an extraordinary emotional intensity and professional focus to these performances, but they didn't leave you thinking that if you wanted a rollicking good time, Ms. Murphy was the gal to call on.</p>
        <p>Now here she is, having stepped out of those hoop skirts to reveal a pair of slim, shapely legs and a very wicked wit. The voice is terrific, no surprise there, but here also as agile in deadpan drollery and dead-on mimicry as it has been in summoning pain. And what about that fine-tuned physical friskiness she brings to everything from climbing the fence of a naval yard to jazz dancing with her handbag strap as a hula hoop?</p>
        <p>Well, who knew? Chalk up another goose-bump-making revelation to Encores!, the series of American of musicals in concert. This splendid annual trio of productions has become famous not only for animating shows consigned to the archives but also for letting contemporary performers shine in ways they seldom do in overproduced Broadway musicals.</p>
        <p>Every cast member on the stage of ''Wonderful Town,'' a 1953 frolic from the immortal trio of Leonard Bernstein, Betty Comden and Adoph Green, pulses with Personality with a capital P: not as shrill cartoon characters but as individuals with idiosyncrasies that just happen to translate as naturally as breathing into song and dance.</p>
        <p>Staged and choreographed with fertile charm by Kathleen Marshall, the series's artistic director, this ''Wonderful Town'' ranks with the best of the Encores! offerings, right up there with ''The Boys From Syracuse'' and ''Call Me Madam.'' (As a wall-to-wall treat, only ''Chicago,'' which transferred to Broadway, tops it.) Once again, what might have seemed like a dusty period piece has the freshness of a newly opened crocus.</p>
        <p>The bright, wisecracking script, which follows the fortunes of two sisters from Ohio in the mad Manhattan of the 1930's, definitely belongs to another era. Yet you don't feel that distance until the show is over. And in the superb hands of Rob Fisher and the Coffee Club Orchestra, what may be Bernstein's bounciest score registers as a brassy siren call to everyone who grew up outside of New York and dreamed of moving there.</p>
        <p>As with their fabled earlier collaboration, ''On the Town,'' Bernstein, Ms. Comden and Mr. Green shaped a swinging, idealizing love poem to a city where everything seemed possible. With a book by Joseph Fields and Jerome Chodorov -- adapted from their play ''My Sister Eileen,'' which had in turn been inspired by autobiographical stories by Ruth McKennie -- the show had critics turning cartwheels when it opened in 1953.</p>
        <p>''The most uproarious and original musical carnival we have had since 'Guys and Dolls,' '' wrote Brooks Atkinson in these pages. But it was Rosalind Russell, demonstrating she had the chops and then some to carry a Broadway musical, who really slayed the reviewers with what Atkinson called her ''sophisticated mummery.''</p>
        <p>Ruth is a wry aspiring writer with plenty of professional chutzpah but minimal sexual confidence. It's her pretty, dewy-eyed sister Eileen (here played by the enchanting Laura Benanti) who gets both the guys and the lilting soprano ballads. To Ruth falls the zinging one-liners, the imaginative novelty songs and some seriously athletic clowning.</p>
        <p>To say that your eyes never leave Ms. Murphy when she's onstage is a serious compliment, since this production is as well cast across the board as any I've seen from Encores! One starts, of course, with Ms. Benanti, currently on Broadway in ''Swing!,'' who plays the winsome Eileen with the matter-of-factness of someone who utterly takes for granted her annihilating attractiveness to men.</p>
        <p>Richard Muenz brings an easygoing dignity to Robert Baker, the magazine editor whose role is a male variation on the unwitting troublemaker usually known as the Girl in other vintage musicals. And the terrific Raymond Jaramillo McLeod stops the show as a domestically adroit football player marking time between seasons in the antic wonderland of the show's Greenwich Village.</p>
        <p>But this is a production in which even small roles are filled with the wonderfully stylish presences of performers like Becky Ann Baker, Gregory Jbara and Stephen DeRosa. And every dancer emerges as a fully defined entity in Ms. Marshall's sparkling, meticulously madcap choreography, which ranges from a River-dancing lineup of Irish policemen to a sultry ballet of jazz club denizens.</p>
        <p>This sense of heightened individuality within a teeming throng is what ''Wonderful Town'' is about. It's a sweet-tempered willfully innocent fantasy of a city where people are simply more interesting, more alive than they are anywhere else, a notion piquantly brought home in Ms. Marshall's parade of bohemians in the show's opening number, ''Christopher Street.''</p>
        <p>A harmless, friendly Manhattan is not of course a real Manhattan. Yet Bernstein's varied melodies, matched by some of the sharpest Comden and Green lyrics, still summon the feelings of what it's like to arrive in New York from somewhere else: the fears (as in the homesick duet ''Ohio'') in the face of Manhattan cynicism ('''What a Waste,'' a trio about the way of all talent in an unforgiving city) and the persistent expectation of wowing the skeptics any minute.</p>
        <p>This callow optimism is pricelessly brought to life in ''Ruth's Story Vignettes,'' a number in which Ms. Murphy acts out the archetypal heroines of fiction written in slavish imitation of writers like Ernest Hemingway and Noel Coward. She is equally adept at conjuring several varieties of the kind of girl she isn't in the mordant ''One Hundred Easy Ways.'' And just watch what happens when the self-conscious Ruth learns to unbend, first with a conga line of Brazilian sailors and later as the leader of a big-band routine in which she finds herself singing like Louis Armstrong.</p>
        <p>Her combination of variety and polish, from the cadence of every line reading to the smallest angles in posture changes, is astonishing. In 1953 Atkinson wrote that Rosalind Russell should be made president of the United States. Times have changed. Ms. Murphy deserves something better. Like a big Broadway show in which she doesn't have to wear mourning.</p>
        <p>WONDERFUL TOWN</p>
        <p>Book by Joseph Fields and Jerome Chodorov, based on the play ''My Sister Eileen'' by Mr. Fields and Mr. Chodorov and the stories by Ruth McKenney. Music by Leonard Bernstein; lyrics by Betty Comden and Adolph Green, sketches for ''What a Waste'' by Ms. Comden and Mr. Green. Directed and choregraphed by Kathleen Marshall. Artistic director, Ms. Marshall; the Coffee Club Orchestra, Rob Fisher musical director. Set consultant, John Lee Beatty; costume consultant, William Ivey Long; lighting by Peter Kaczorowski; sound by Scott Lehrer; concert adaptation, David Ives; production stage manager, Karen Moore; original orchestration, Don Walker; musical coordinator, Seymour Red Press; associate choreographer, Joey Pizzi. Encores! Presented by City Center, Judith E. Daykin, president and executive director. At 131 West 55th Street, Manhattan.</p>
        <p>WITH: Donna Murphy (Ruth), Laura Benanti (Eileen), Richard Muenz (Robert Baker), Lewis J. Stadlen (Appopolous), David Aaron Baker (Frank Lippencott), Gregory Jbara (Chick Clark), Patrick Quinn (Guide and Associate Editor), Steve Ryan (Lonigan), Raymond Jaramillo McLeod (Wreck), Jenny Hill (Helen), Alix Korey (Violet), Stephen DeRosa (Speedy Valenti), Ray Willis (Strange Man, Associate Editor and Ruth's Escort) and Becky Ann Baker (Mrs. Wade).</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
