<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mississippi Forms Commission To Design a New State Flag</title>
    <meta content="Y06MISS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197177"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Flags, Emblems and Insignia</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mississippi</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Firestone, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Musgrove, Ronnie (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Mississippi</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Mississippi</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Flags, Emblems and Insignia</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000506T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E3DB1438F935A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="554" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mississippi Forms Commission To Design a New State Flag</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID FIRESTONE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Firestone, David</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTA, May 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gov Ronnie Musgrove of Mississippi forms advisory commission to design new state flag, day after state's Supreme Court rules that because of legal technicality, state has not had official flag since 1906, when Legislature forgot to include flag in codification of state laws; debate can be expected over whether new flag should bear Confederate symbol; current flag's Confederate cross has been object of criticism from many black residents over years; Gov Musgrove says advisory commission will be diverse group; he voices no opinion on issue of Confederate symbol; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A day after Mississippi learned that its bitterly contested state flag had not been an official symbol for 94 years, Gov. Ronnie Musgrove today formed an advisory commission to design a new flag, guaranteeing a year of debate about whether the flag should bear a Confederate symbol.</p>
        <p>On Thursday, the Mississippi Supreme Court ruled that because of a legal technicality, the state had not had an official flag since 1906, when the Legislature forgot to include the flag in a codification of state laws.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A day after Mississippi learned that its bitterly contested state flag had not been an official symbol for 94 years, Gov. Ronnie Musgrove today formed an advisory commission to design a new flag, guaranteeing a year of debate about whether the flag should bear a Confederate symbol.</p>
        <p>On Thursday, the Mississippi Supreme Court ruled that because of a legal technicality, the state had not had an official flag since 1906, when the Legislature forgot to include the flag in a codification of state laws.</p>
        <p>The Confederate cross in the flag's left corner has been the object of criticism from many black residents over the years, but the court said the flag had no legal status unless the government chose to make it or another design the official symbol.</p>
        <p>At a news conference in Jackson, Mr. Musgrove, a Democrat, said he wanted the commission to ''take positive action,'' but he voiced no opinion on whether the new flag should carry a Confederate symbol.</p>
        <p>''Symbols mean a lot,'' he said, standing in front of a pole bearing the current flag. ''They mean a lot to all of us. We want a good, open, honest discussion.''</p>
        <p>He promised that the 17-member commission would be a diverse group, containing members of both parties and black and white residents. The commission will include 3 members of the State Senate, 3 members of the House and 11 members appointed by the governor from a variety of fields.</p>
        <p>The commission is to recommend a design by May 4 of next year, according to the governor's executive order, which also mandates that the current flag be kept in use until the Legislature acts. The Legislature, however, is not required to approve the panel's recommendation.</p>
        <p>Several white members of the Legislature have already made it clear that they want the current flag to be made official and are not interested in a new design. But many black legislators, who had already vowed to make the flag a major issue in the coming year, have welcomed the opportunity for a new design.</p>
        <p>Opposition to the official use of Confederate symbols has been growing in the South this year, spurred by the movement to lower the Confederate battle flag from atop the South Carolina Capitol.</p>
        <p>That issue may be settled next week when the South Carolina House votes on a plan to remove the flag and place a smaller version in front of the Capitol, but five other states, most notably Georgia and Mississippi, incorporate Confederate designs into their state flags.</p>
        <p>Several Georgia legislators have promised to begin a movement to change the state's flag later this year, and civil rights groups have threatened an economic boycott of the state if it is not changed.</p>
        <p>Up to now, opponents to the flag in Mississippi faced an uphill battle in getting it changed, but the court's ruling has created a much easier opportunity to secure a new flag.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
