<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Another Fine Mess</title>
    <meta content="21REEDLT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000521T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200957"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reed, Susan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fleming, Fergus</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Barrow's Boys (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000521T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E3DE173BF932A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1145" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Another Fine Mess</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Susan Reed</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Reed, Susan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Susan Reed reviews book Barrow's Boys by Fergus Fleming (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Barrow's Boys</p>
        <p>By Fergus Fleming.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 489 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Atlantic Monthly Press. $26.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Barrow's Boys</p>
        <p>By Fergus Fleming.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 489 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Atlantic Monthly Press. $26.</p>
        <p>L ast year's exhibition at the American Museum of Natural History entitled ''The Endurance: Shackleton's Legendary Antarctic Expedition'' chronicled the 1914 voyage of Sir Ernest Shackleton, who tried to make the first crossing of Antarctica. But his ship became trapped in Weddell Sea's pack ice, 100 miles short of its intended harbor. The Endurance was crushed, and Shackleton's 27-man crew was stranded on the ice floes for months before escaping to Elephant Island, from which he then engineered one of the great rescues of all time. I left the show mesmerized by Antarctica's beauty -- and by the lunacy of the expedition. How did these explorers get themselves into such messes?</p>
        <p>''Barrow's Boys'' tells us how. Shackleton was one of the last of a line of tough British explorers who, beginning in the early 1800's, set out for the unknown territories of Africa, the Arctic and Antarctica. England's great expeditionary era evolved as the Napoleonic Wars ended, leaving the Royal Navy with a lot of men with time on their hands. The navy laid off 100,000 sailors, but officers were a different matter. Many had political connections and could not be summarily dismissed. The navy was saddled with 6,000 of them -- a perfect force of explorers.</p>
        <p>Enter John Barrow. Barrow (1764-1848) had been appointed to his admiralty post in 1804 after a short diplomatic career. From 1816 on, he sent forth 30 expeditions, as many as four a year, as part of a master plan to claim the last uncharted regions of the globe for England. The ship captains were more than explorers; they were knights on Barrow's global chessboard.</p>
        <p>Fergus Fleming, a freelance writer, points out that intelligence didn't do much for an ambitious young man in the late 18th century. What got Barrow ahead was patronage. He had been a tutor to the Staunton family, whose friends were well connected to dukes and earls. In 1795, one of them, Lord Macartney, took Barrow to the Chinese court as an interpreter. Macartney then took him to South Africa, where he became interested in geography, mapped parts of the interior, made geological surveys and interviewed Shaka, king of the Zulus. In Africa, Barrow found another patron, Gen. Francis Dundas. In 1803, Dundas's uncle, Lord Melville, was appointed first lord of the admiralty. The day after, Barrow was informed he would be the second secretary.</p>
        <p>On the surface, Barrow presented himself as self-effacing and competent. But underneath, Fleming writes, he was ''a man of ambition, intellect and remorseless application. . . . He was determined to make his name somehow. The route he chose was exploration.''</p>
        <p>Barrow had several obsessions. One was to find the terminus of the Niger River. Another was to locate the Northwest Passage. In 1816, he ordered Capt. James Tuckey to explore the Congo. His whole party was wiped out by yellow fever. In 1819, Barrow sent John Franklin to Canada's northernmost boundaries to help search for the Northwest Passage. It was one of the most appalling Arctic expeditions ever recorded. Franklin's party was ill prepared. His boats were too small to hold necessary supplies and too heavy for portages. The sailors knew nothing about survival techniques. Faced with starvation, they resorted to cannibalism. Franklin, one of the few who made it back, became a hero, known as ''the man who ate his boots.''</p>
        <p>From the beginning, Fleming writes, ''almost everything about Barrow's missions had been wrong -- the orders, the ships, the supplies, the funding and the methods.'' Barrow pushed an explorer named Gordon Laing to beat the French to Timbuctoo; Laing made it, but found a mud town of no importance whatsoever. He was murdered in the Sahara the next day. Capt. James Ross spent two years bumping around the shoreline of Antarctica; his conclusion: it was simply a mass of ice.</p>
        <p>The Northwest Passage became the focus of Barrow's life. ''Perhaps no man in the history of exploration has expended so much money and so many lives in pursuit of so desperately pointless a dream,'' Fleming writes. None of Barrow's expeditions actually navigated the passage; most of them endured years of hardship, wintering on the ice and waiting for the brief thaws that might allow exploration. Capt. William Edward Parry spent eight years there. Franklin's final attempt to find the passage failed. The entire crews of his two ships disappeared, and other explorers spent years looking for them.</p>
        <p>The achievements recorded by Barrow's expeditions were not the grand ones he was after. Parry inadvertently found a cure for scurvy by growing mustard and cress near his ship's heating pipes. James Ross discovered the magnetic North Pole. New locations received names. In 1835, Ross's uncle, John Ross, who spent years charting Canadian coastlines, dared to pose a question: ''What use was there, he asked, in opening an area 'of which perhaps the only satisfaction that can ever be derived would be, that there is, on a piece of paper, a black line instead of a blank'? It was about as productive as drawing 'the anatomy of a fly's toe.' ''</p>
        <p>IF most of Barrow's expeditions were spectacular failures, his men always started out looking good. As Fleming writes: ''In the future there would be no more cocked hats in the Arctic; no more blue serge uniforms and brass-buttoned waistcoats in the Sahara; no more sailing ships in the shadow of Mount Erebus; never again would men struggle with reindeer and sledges to conquer the swirling north polar icecap. Never again, either, would such a disparate and entertaining band of explorers stalk the world -- men such as the obstinate Rosses, the deranged Laing, the pious Parry . . . the charmingly hopeless Franklin.''</p>
        <p>What did Barrow accomplish? He managed to set an amazing bench mark for exploration and got much of the unexplored world mapped. Scores would follow his lead. Livingston and Stanley spent years looking for the Nile's source; Robert Falcon Scott struggled to get to the South Pole and died on the way back. Roald Amundsen, the first to sail through the Northwest Passage and the first to reach the South Pole, cited Barrow's boys as his inspiration. Their stories ''thrilled me as nothing I had ever read before,'' he said. ''What appealed to me most was the sufferings'' that John Franklin and his men ''had to endure. A strange ambition burned within me, to endure the same privations. . . . I decided to be an explorer.''</p>
        <p>Susan Reed is the features editor at Women's Sports &amp; Fitness magazine.</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 21, 2000, Sunday  A review on Page 17 of The Times Book Review today about ''Barrow's Boys,'' by Fergus Fleming, misspells the surname of a notable explorer and missionary in 19th-century Africa. He was David Livingstone, not Livingston.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 21, 2000, Sunday</p>
        <p>A review on Page 17 of The Times Book Review today about ''Barrow's Boys,'' by Fergus Fleming, misspells the surname of a notable explorer and missionary in 19th-century Africa. He was David Livingstone, not Livingston.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Susan Reed is the features editor at Women's Sports &amp; Fitness magazine.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
