<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hobbled</title>
    <meta content="21MESSUDT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200951"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Messud, Claire</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Harrison, Kathryn</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Binding Chair, the (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000521T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E4DE173BF932A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1473" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hobbled</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Claire Messud</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Messud, Claire</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Claire Messud reviews book The Binding Chair: Or, A Visit From the Foot Emancipation Society by Kathryn Harrison; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE BINDING CHAIR</p>
        <p>Or, A Visit From</p>
        <p>the Foot Emancipation Society.</p>
        <p>By Kathryn Harrison.</p>
        <p>312 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Random House. $24.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE BINDING CHAIR</p>
        <p>Or, A Visit From</p>
        <p>the Foot Emancipation Society.</p>
        <p>By Kathryn Harrison.</p>
        <p>312 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Random House. $24.95.</p>
        <p>KATHRYN HARRISON is best known for her controversial 1997 memoir, ''The Kiss,'' an account of her incestuous relationship with her father. A best seller, it provoked widespread debate about the role of the public confessional in our scandal-hungry society. Yet in the course of these discussions, the literary merits of Harrison's enterprise were rarely at issue; the book's content, which catapulted her name to prominence, was -- at least to this reader -- a distraction from Harrison's considerable writerly gifts. The revelation of sensational facts seems all too easy when compared with the challenge of creating subtle fictions.</p>
        <p>Prior to ''The Kiss,'' Harrison wrote three powerful and ambitious novels that amply demonstrate both her meticulous style and her imaginative range. In them she roamed with equal ease from the grit of contemporary New York to the machinations of the 17th-century Spanish court. It is, then, a pleasure to see her return to her fictional calling.</p>
        <p>''The Binding Chair'' is a resonant, elaborately constructed novel, rich in incident, bustlingly peopled, often surprisingly funny. It is also a heartening sign of literary risk-taking. Set over four decades, from the late 19th century until the period between the two world wars, traveling from China to Britain and the south of France, Harrison's book tells the stories of two women, May Cohen, the beautiful Chinese wife of an ineffectual but well-connected Australian, and her niece, Alice Benjamin, each of whom struggles, in her own vibrant but doomed way, to be free of what Alice thinks of as (but doesn't actually call) ''crippling rules.''</p>
        <p>The crippling of May is literal. When she is a little girl of 5 (then named Chao-tsing), her feet are bent within tight cloth bandages by her grandmother, who assures her: ''When you are grown, you will be very beautiful. Your feet will be the smallest and the most perfectly formed lotuses. Your walk will be the walk of beauty, and we will tell your suitors that you never cried out when your feet were bound.'' The deformity to which May is then subject -- and its agony -- lurks at her heart. ''It was, May knew, her feet that held her between one world and the next. On her red shoes, she balanced between East and West, China and Europe, misery, happiness.'' Crippled, she is hardened; she becomes a woman of absolute determination and resilience, a magnificent monster.</p>
        <p>Alice, the younger daughter of May's husband's sister, is May's favorite, her surrogate child. (Fate and May's own ambition have taken two natural daughters from her, two tragic stories that emerge in the course of the novel.) We learn from the outset that Alice has been ''separated from May only once, in 1913, when she was 12 years old,'' after her parents, expatriates in Shanghai, discovered her rolling opium balls for her aunt and packed her off on an ill-fated expedition to boarding school in England. Other sections of the novel, set in Nice in the 1920's, chart a different and more enduring form of separation. Now an adult, Alice falls in love with a Russian named Evlanoff, and in so doing irretrievably betrays her aunt.</p>
        <p>It is a betrayal whose seed is sown in that first departure: in the course of her long train ride across Russia to Europe with her sister, Cecily, their histrionic mother and small retinue, Alice becomes the obsession of a deluded Russian army captain named Litovsky, who imagines that she is his own dead daughter and attempts to abduct her. The unanswered question of why Alice willingly follows him off the train remains the hidden key to her youthful personality; it is a question posed again by Evlanoff, even as her surrender to him re-enacts that childhood scene.</p>
        <p>On that same fateful trans-Siberian train trip lurks another woman who will resurface in Nice many years later and become part of the Benjamin-Cohen family: a bereaved and isolated spinster named Suzanne Petrovna. And in the course of the girls' short but colorful stay in London at Miss Robeson's Academy for Young Ladies, Alice befriends a brilliant but unappreciated young math teacher named Eleanor Clusburtson -- crippled, in her turn, by a terrible lisp -- who returns with the girls to Shanghai and uses her talent to make their father a fortune. (It is worth noting that the family's escapades in London, including May's disastrous visit to Fortnum &amp; Mason in an improvised sedan chair, constitute, along with Miss Clusburtson's unfortunate history, a triumph of black comedy.)</p>
        <p>Harrison intersperses the story of Alice's youth with the even more dramatic account of May's struggles -- of her father's death when she is 12, of her early betrothal and miserable marriage, of her escape to Shanghai and her life in a brothel until she is rescued and married by Alice's uncle, the hapless Arthur Cohen, whose first visit to May is in his capacity as a member of the Foot Emancipation Society.</p>
        <p>Throughout the novel, Harrison is particularly adept at capturing the subtleties and perversities of desire, noting, for example, that Arthur's passion for May is focused upon the very feet he thought to have liberated: ''The tiny foot in his hand shape-shifted. One minute it repelled him, the next it seemed suddenly to express the beauty of the whole female body. Wasn't it all there, in May's foot? The smooth white of her neck, the curve of her breast and hip, the crook of her smallest finger, the delicate, mauve folds of her most intimate places.''</p>
        <p>The family's life in Shanghai during World War I and after is marked by disintegration and disaster: the influenza epidemic takes its toll, as does, more severely, the madness of Alice and Cecily's mother, Dolly, who inadvertently burns down their house, killing both herself and her brother. Her survivors eventually move to Nice, but the girls' father, Dick Benjamin, as well as Miss Clusburtson and Cecily, fades almost entirely from view.</p>
        <p>In the sections set in France, the richness of incident in the women's earlier lives is diminished. Alice retreats to Evlanoff and to sex -- scenes that provide the main characterization of her as an adult and fail, therefore, to characterize her at all. May, having attempted to shake off depression by decorating their new home, adopts a host of charity cases -- the lonely Suzanne Petrovna most important among them, as she is taken into May's bed. And, crucially, the Chinese woman who can barely walk learns to swim. Alice notes early in the novel that ''May didn't do things casually. She wouldn't pursue swimming for the pleasure of it. . . . She must have some sort of a . . . a plan.'' Meanwhile, Alice persistently attempts to help May with her feet, dragging her against her will to a fitting for orthopedic shoes. The Foot Emancipation Society pursues May, in some form or another, to the very end.</p>
        <p>''The Binding Chair'' is an intricately patterned novel. In its sidelong anecdotes and minor characters as much as in its central ones, it explores the theme of brutality against women, of their crippling. (This is traced in all its metaphorical possibilities and illuminates the way that women, as much as and sometimes more than men, are culpable.) The novel also evokes women's ''dis-ease'' and the polymorphous perversities of desire. Harrison's vision is bold and unsparing, portraying a world in which a woman's survival comes at a terrible cost, a world in which people are doomed to isolation, abandoned by all but the weaklings they can control. The novel continually surprises. Its narrative turns and its tonal shifts -- from the rhythms of the epic to those of the erotic, with pauses for comedy along the way -- are as deft as they are unexpected.</p>
        <p>Ultimately, though, ''The Binding Chair'' is a novel whose ambition outstrips its achievement. For all its impressive vitality, it reveals little of the interior depths of its characters. And lacking this, it ultimately lacks a heart. Neither Alice nor May lives beyond or behind her actions, and the elaborate structure Harrison has built for the telling of their stories seems designed more for a clinical juxtaposition of their trajectories than for a sustained exploration of their essences as complex individuals.</p>
        <p>Only in May's terrible but somehow beautiful end -- in which she shows herself monstrous to the last and yet magnificent, and as a consequence utterly human -- does Harrison allow us a glimpse of this woman's carefully guarded soul. These few haunting pages are the novel's highlight, more moving than anything that has come before.</p>
        <p>Claire Messud's second novel, ''The Last Life,'' was published last year.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Claire Messud's second novel, ''The Last Life,'' was published last year.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
