<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Uncle Ed</title>
    <meta content="21GOOD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200963"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goodheart, Adam</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fleming, Keith</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Boy With the Thorn in His Side, The: A Memoir (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000521T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906EFDA143BF932A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1129" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Uncle Ed</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Adam Goodheart</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Goodheart, Adam</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Adam Goodheart reviews book The Boy With the Thorn in His Side: A Memoir by Keith Fleming; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE BOY WITH THE THORN IN HIS SIDE</p>
        <p>A Memoir.</p>
        <p>By Keith Fleming.</p>
        <p>205 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>William Morrow &amp; Company. $24.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE BOY WITH THE THORN IN HIS SIDE</p>
        <p>A Memoir.</p>
        <p>By Keith Fleming.</p>
        <p>205 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>William Morrow &amp; Company. $24.</p>
        <p>Few modern literary lives have been chronicled more exhaustively than that of Edmund White. In three books of autobiography (presented as novels but with only the wispiest fictional loincloths to cover them) he has recorded his friendships, his family dramas and -- especially -- his sexual encounters with near-Pepysian meticulousness. Like many readers, I suspect, I read the first volume (''A Boy's Own Story'') with interest, skimmed the second (''The Beautiful Room Is Empty'') and, when the third volume (''The Farewell Symphony'') came out in 1997, set it down after 100 pages or so, with feelings of guilty relief that there would never be -- or so the dust jacket promised -- a fourth.</p>
        <p>But now, only three years later, here comes yet another memoir of Edmund White's private life. And just when you thought you knew what to expect, there are several surprising things about it. First of all, it is not by Edmund White. It is, instead, by his nephew Keith Fleming, a writer who has had his own share of family dramas, uncommon friendships and sexual adventures. And this author -- unlike his uncle, whose books document the rise of gay culture and gay consciousness from the 1950's through the 90's -- is straight. Fleming got to know White well in the midst of his tortured teenage years in the 1970's, when his divorced parents sent him to live with Uncle Eddie in New York.</p>
        <p>To certain people, this must sound like the makings of a family-values nightmare: a fragile 16-year-old boy leaves his home in suburban Chicago and lands in the swirling center of disco-era gay Manhattan, where his uncle (as one recalls from White's books) treats casual sex anything but casually -- flinging himself at it, in fact, with the grim zeal of an Olympic gymnast in training. And yet, improbably enough, Fleming found in his Uncle Eddie the first really trustworthy parent, and the first happy family life, that he'd ever had.</p>
        <p>''At the worst moment of my adolescence,'' Fleming writes, ''he came to my rescue.'' Like his uncle 20 years earlier, Fleming had been shipped away (to a psychiatric hospital in his case, to a boarding school in White's) by a father who thought that an angst-ridden teenager was an awkward thing to have around the house. And he was indeed the most awkward sort of teenager: listless, oversexed, plagued with disfiguring acne and, just as inconveniently, with a deeply rooted romanticism: the kind of boy who would hop a southbound train because he'd been listening to Arlo Guthrie singing ''City of New Orleans.''</p>
        <p>(Fleming's entire family seems, rather charmingly, to have been slaves to pop music at one time or another. His father ended up meeting the woman he would marry because they both identified with Carole King's ''It's Too Late.'' His mother went through a phase of repeatedly playing Cat Stevens's ''Morning Has Broken.'' The only exception was Uncle Eddie, whose tastes ran more to Stravinsky and Bizet.)</p>
        <p>When, one night in the winter of 1976, Fleming landed on White's Upper West Side doorstep, almost the first thing his uncle did was to get his acne treated by a dermatologist. That did more to cheer the boy up than all those Chicago psychiatrists ever had. Then White went to work on the rest of him: out with plaid pants and floral shirts; in with black loafers and Italian-cut sportcoats! Down with Vonnegut and folk guitar; up with Stendhal and Truffaut!</p>
        <p>Sometimes it was an odd kind of domesticity, to be sure. Think of a Norman Rockwell scene rearranged slightly by Robert Mapplethorpe: ''I'd be doing my homework at the kitchen table at 10 in the evening as Uncle Ed, hair gleaming from a shower, dressed in leather bomber jacket and jeans, said good night to me as he headed out the door for another night of cruising down in Greenwich Village,'' Fleming recalls. In order to pay his nephew's private-school tuition (plus that of Fleming's girlfriend, who eventually became part of the menage on West 86th Street), White got a contract to write ''The Joy of Gay Sex.'' (At that time, he was still a struggling young writer with just one barely selling novel to his name.)</p>
        <p>''The Boy With the Thorn in His Side'' offers the rare satisfaction of seeing a memoirist get memoired. In fact, much of its story has already been told by White in one chapter of ''The Farewell Symphony,'' where Keith Fleming appears pseudonymously as Gabriel. But another surprise of this book is that the upstart nephew actually beats the uncle at his own game. Even if his memoir lacks White's occasional flying leaps of genius, it is funnier, more vivid, more focused. In place of White's tone of wry, ever-so-continental ironic distance, we get Fleming's postadolescent earnestness and his ever-so-American conviction that life is about moving onward and upward as best you can. In place of White's cast of thousands (the lovers, the acolytes, the shimmying conga line of celebrities) we get a handful of Fleming's closest relationships, unfolding gradually across the years.</p>
        <p>And we also get a sense, perhaps for the first time, of the peculiar gravitational force that has kept that immense asteroid belt of friends and admirers orbiting around White all these years. Sometimes while he lived with his uncle, Fleming writes, ''I'd feel like a guest on a TV talk show being squeezed for the best of what I had to say in a few minutes of precious airtime. But there were still plenty of times when in the cloudless sunny day of his eyes I could see something so calm and knowing . . . that to have his attention was almost like being plugged into God. Maybe part of the reason he felt so trapped with any one person was that he was able to put himself so artfully at your disposal that you could never get enough of it.''</p>
        <p>White's books are declarations of independence -- handbooks on making+your way, alone, swiftly through an overcrowded world. Fleming's is about the ways you come to depend on others -- about the things that slow you down, for better as well as worse. It could serve not just as a pocket manual on the gentle art of unclehood but also as a primer on how to, and how not to, raise a teenage boy. Forget the psychiatrists: think Stendhal and new shoes.</p>
        <p>Adam Goodheart is a columnist for Civilization magazine and a member of the editorial board of The American Scholar.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Adam Goodheart is a columnist for Civilization magazine and a member of the editorial board of The American Scholar.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
