<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Outside Tucson, A Family Goes Underground</title>
    <meta content="21FRUG$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200977"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FRUGAL TRAVELER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Caves and Caverns</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Kartchner Caverns State Park (Arizona)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Tucson (Ariz)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rubiner, Betsy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Columns/Frugal Traveler</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Arizona</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Arizona/Tucson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Caves and Caverns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000521T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E1D6113BF932A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2483" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Outside Tucson, A Family Goes Underground</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BETSY RUBINER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rubiner, Betsy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Betsy Rubiner Frugal Traveler article on visit to Kartchner Caverns State Park during family's annual spring trip to Tucson; geological gem in remote mountains was discovered by spelunkers in 1974, and is opened to public on controlled basis; photos; map; list of places to stay and eat in Tucson (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I NEVER knew something could be so cool,'' my 8-year-old son, Noah, whispered as we stepped into the huge ''Throne Room'' at Kartchner Caverns State Park, Arizona's latest geological gem, which was unveiled just in time for my family's annual spring trip to Tucson.</p>
        <p>There it was: the ''Kubla Khan'' -- the tallest known column in an Arizona cave. It looked like a Dr. Seuss concoction: a majestic 58-foot-high pillar of hardened mineral built by drop after drop of water falling into the cave for thousands of years. It was impossible not to gawk.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I NEVER knew something could be so cool,'' my 8-year-old son, Noah, whispered as we stepped into the huge ''Throne Room'' at Kartchner Caverns State Park, Arizona's latest geological gem, which was unveiled just in time for my family's annual spring trip to Tucson.</p>
        <p>There it was: the ''Kubla Khan'' -- the tallest known column in an Arizona cave. It looked like a Dr. Seuss concoction: a majestic 58-foot-high pillar of hardened mineral built by drop after drop of water falling into the cave for thousands of years. It was impossible not to gawk.</p>
        <p>When I read last November that the cave -- a rare living and growing one -- was finally opening for tours (25 years after its discovery) I snagged a mid-March reservation. I'm glad I did. By the time we got to Tucson -- 40 miles northwest of Kartchner Caverns -- tours were booked through May. ''I hope you have a reservation,'' a rental car agent warned us.</p>
        <p>Hands down, the cave was the highlight of our two-day trip around the Tucson area. But as we have learned in other visits to see  my parents (who spend winters in southern Arizona), Tucson can't promise economical travel during the peak tourist season. Tickets to favorite spots like the Arizona-Sonora Desert Museum and comfortable family-friendly lodging for me, my husband, Dirck, and our children, Lily, 7 and Noah, can add up. We try to cut costs elsewhere -- picnicking when possible and hiking in glorious Catalina State Park, just north of Tucson (entry fee: $5 a car).</p>
        <p>Kartchner Caverns was worth the price of $10 to drive into the remote 550-acre park in the Whetstone Mountains and another $40 total for the 70-minute cave tour. What makes the seven-acre cave system special is that it is so unspoiled. Strange as it sounds, Kartchner Caverns was opened to tourists to protect it. The two spelunk ers who discovered the cave on the Kartch ner family's land in 1974 feared that with out making it a state park (which turned into a $28 million project) and regulat ing the number of visitors, Kartchner Caverns would be overrun and ruined like others.</p>
        <p>This helps explain the pricey admission,  the tightly controlled access (three tours per hour, 18 people per tour) and the high-tech gadgets, including a misting system that keeps the cave moist as outsiders enter. It also explains why the tour guides watched us so closely.</p>
        <p>My family easily spent three hours at the park, starting with the hands-on exhibits in the Discovery Center. Noah and Lily made a beeline for the 80,000-year-old bones of a Shasta ground sloth found in the cave. They also had fun squeezing through a replica of the cave hole that the founding spelunkers used. I passed. We all fingered a fake stalagmite -- touching the real ones is forbidden.</p>
        <p>By the time we left for our tour, Noah and Lily had grown very quiet -- a bit spooked, I suspected, after learning about the original spelunkers' crawl through tight tunnels and cold mud into a very dark place. I had the jitters too as we entered the cave through a series of six huge steel freezer doors that help keep out the dry desert air.</p>
        <p>Not to worry. The three cave rooms we visited were wide-open spaces, discreetly lighted so we could see their many treasures. As two guides with flashlights ushered us along a paved, dimly illuminated path wide enough for a wheelchair, it felt like we were in the upper balcony of a dark opera house.</p>
        <p>Looking down, we saw the original spelunkers' footprints in the mud. Looking up, we saw countless mineral formations in countless colors and shapes. We were surrounded by stalactites and stalagmites in reds, grays and browns. Some resembled carrots, fried eggs, popcorn and well-done bacon; others looked like delicate hollow ''soda straws.''</p>
        <p>Our guide treated us more like geology students than sightseers, making interesting observations in terms we all could readily grasp. One drawback: because the tour was so choreographed and clinical, the cave didn't seem quite spooky enough. That changed when we got to the Throne Room, where the Kubla Khan (named after the Samuel Taylor Coleridge poem about a terrestrial paradise) presides. There, a brief light-and-music show helped us experience the cave's intrinsic mystery and romance. The show began with the cave dark and silent enough to hear a drop of water land. Then, like a spelunker's flashlight, hidden lights within the cave illuminated one marvel after another.</p>
        <p>After we stumbled back out into the sunlight, our clothes strangely moist, Noah and Lily were ''sworn in'' as junior rangers, earnestly repeating an oath to protect the caves.</p>
        <p>Next? Fresh apple pie. We found it 12 miles northeast at the Horseshoe Steakhouse and Cantina in the dusty town of Benson. Four slices of pie with wonderful flaky crust and four drinks came to $14.49, a splurge after our prudent picnic back at the park.</p>
        <p>Driving back north, we scrapped plans to stop at Tucson's famous 18th-century Mexican Baroque church, the Mission San Xavier del Bac, when we discovered Lily and Noah asleep in the back seat. (Rule No. 1 when traveling with kids: Don't wake them up.) But by the time we got to our hotel in north Tucson, they were ready for the pool. Our two-room suite at the cheerful Windmill Inn at St. Philip's Plaza, a swanky shopping complex, cost $129 a night, including tax. Had I started looking earlier, I might have done even better, but we liked what we got: a bedroom with two double beds plus a living room with a small eating area, microwave and mini-refrigerator.</p>
        <p>Dinner got off to a shaky start that night when we found an almost two-hour wait at El Charro Cafe, a lively Mexican restaurant downtown. (Unfortunately, we hadn't made reservations.) The apologetic host promised us a table the next night. Moving on, we drove with my parents about 25 minutes east to the Hidden Valley Inn, a bustling restaurant popular with families. The lavish Western decor was more clever than cheesy and the kids loved it -- especially the glassed-in displays of Western scenes featuring moving miniature cowboys carved from wood.</p>
        <p>In a lounge that looked like Miss Kitty's Saloon, we enjoyed listening to Jess Hawk Oakenstar croon Patsy Cline songs at the edge of a busy dance floor. Hidden Valley is the kind of steak place that lists a half a barbecued chicken ($9.99) on its light menu, and mine was delicious. So were the ground sirloin steak ($9.99) and the kids' ''cowpoke chicken'' strips ($4.99). Choosing carefully and skipping liquor, we kept our bill to $66.21 for six. We needed no dessert.</p>
        <p>We stayed above ground the next day, driving 12 miles west from downtown Tucson to the Desert Museum through landscape that really was straight out of a western movie. We passed Old Tucson Studios, where many westerns were filmed. Snaking through winding passes in the jagged Tucson Mountains, we had a breathtaking view of the desert valley that is home to the museum. Hundreds of saguaro cactuses waved at us like happy Gumbys.</p>
        <p>We paid $33.35 for five tickets (my mother joined us, my dad played golf) to the Desert Museum, which is  part zoo, botanical garden and natural history museum. Although it was crowded, the Desert Museum is mostly open-air so there was plenty of elbow room. All the animals --  coyotes, javelinas (which look like pigs), even the mountain lions --  were out. So were the enthusiastic docents with their animal skulls and geology models. Lily and Noah got to pet a small gopher snake. Three hours whizzed by. It was time for another picnic, this one at a secluded table outside the museum.</p>
        <p>We were reminded how miserable a southern Arizona family vacation can be when a sudden storm rumbled over the Santa Catalina Mountains north of Tucson, where we'd hoped to take an afternoon hike in Catalina State Park. Instead we drove past the park about 20 miles northeast to an attraction that's long been on our ''maybe'' list: the Biosphere 2 Center, where eight adults lived in isolation from 1991 to 1993 and now a scientific research center run by Columbia University. We discovered you couldn't see much from the entrance gate and that the tour was a budget-buster ($12.95 each for adults; $6 each for Noah and Lily). So we skipped it and gladly returned to the hotel.</p>
        <p>That night, the host at El Charro kept his promise. For $57.75, the six of us ate well, thanks to the restaurant's enormous portions and delicious signature dish, carne seca: strips of beef marinated in lime and garlic and sun-dried in cages atop El Charro's roof. For dessert, we spent $12.77 at an ice cream shop near the University of Arizona.</p>
        <p>By morning, our last at the inn, the storm had cleared. Dirck took Lily window-shopping near the hotel. Noah and I borrowed some of the hotel's one-speed bikes, hit the dusty trail behind St. Philip's Plaza and rode off into the sunshine.</p>
        <p>The bottom line on a family trip around Tucson</p>
        <p>Our family of four spent about $260 a day on our hotel, meals and sightseeing during a two-day March trip to the Tucson area to visit Kartchner Caverns State Park. Both dinners were for six people, including my parents. Lunch and sightseeing the second day was for five people, including my mother.</p>
        <p>Transportation</p>
        <p>We rented a four-door compact car from Alamo, (800) 327-9633, at the Tucson International Airport for about $50 a day; rates are substantially lower now.</p>
        <p>Hotel</p>
        <p>We stayed at the Windmill Inn at St. Philip's Plaza, 4250 North Campbell Avenue, Tucson; (520) 577-0007; fax (520) 577-0045. It is a three-story pink stucco Southwestern-style hotel with 122 suites, situated in an attractive north Tucson shopping complex. We paid $120, plus $9 tax a night. The suite originally cost $135 a night during peak season from January through April but I got a lower rate with a casual inquiry. In May, rates are $99 or $120 poolside for a similar suite, dropping further in June.</p>
        <p>Our bedroom had two double beds and a handy extra sink. The living room had a small eating area, mini-refrigerator and microwave. We also got muffins, hot drinks and juice delivered to the suite for breakfast, a courtyard pool and Jacuzzi, plus bikes, board games and books on loan.</p>
        <p>Activities</p>
        <p>Tours of the cave at the new Kartchner Caverns State Park are already so popular that reservations must be made months in advance; in early May, tours were fully booked through July. The seven-acre cave system is an easy 45-minute drive southeast from Tucson, nine miles south of Interstate 10, off Highway 90 in Cochise County. To book a tour, call (520) 586-2283. The tour lasts 70 minutes and the walk is about a third of a mile.</p>
        <p>Open daily, the park offers three cave tours an hour (limited to 18 people and two guides), with the first at 8:30 a.m., the last at 4:30 p.m. The tours cost $14; $6 for children 7 to 13. Park officials do not recommend the tour for children under 7 but there is no charge for those who take it.</p>
        <p>The cave is wheelchair accessible, but no electric chairs are permitted; the park can supply a push chair if needed. Walkers are not allowed.  There is an additional $10 charge to drive into the 550-acre park, which also has an interesting Discovery Center with a 15-minute film and interactive exhibits, plus two hiking trails, a hummingbird garden and picnic tables.</p>
        <p>Mission San Xavier del Bac, 1950 West San Xavier Road, (520) 294-2624, is about nine miles south of downtown Tucson. The glistening white church, finished in 1797, is full of exquisite baroque Mexican art and recently underwent a six-year restoration for interior cleaning; exterior restoration is still going on. Admission is free. Open 7 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sunday Masses are at 8 and 11 a.m. and 12:30 p.m.</p>
        <p>We visited the Arizona-Sonora Desert Museum, 2021 North Kinney Road, to learn about the plants and animals native to the Sonoran Desert region, which includes parts of Arizona and California as well as northern Mexico. The 21-acre museum, a 25-minute drive from downtown Tucson, has almost two miles of paths, two restaurants and two snack bars.  It is open seven days a week from 7:30 a.m. to 5 p.m. March through September; 8 a.m. to 5 p.m. October through February. On Saturday nights June through September in the summer, it is open until 10 p.m. Admission is $8.95 March through September, $9.95 the rest of the year; $1.75 for children 6 through 12; free for children under 6. Information: (520) 883-2702.</p>
        <p>Columbia University's Biosphere 2 Center, 32540 South Biosphere Road, (520) 896-6200, is in Oracle, about 20 miles north of Tucson on Highway 77.  Admission is $12.95; $8.95 for ages 13 to 17; $6 for ages 6 to 12; free for children under 6.</p>
        <p>Places to Eat</p>
        <p>The Hidden Valley Inn, 4825 North Sabino Canyon Road, (520) 299-4941, is a Western-style restaurant and entertainment spot about 15 miles east of downtown Tucson. This is a big barn of a dining hall lavishly outfitted with wagon wheels and saddles.  We spent $66.21 for six, without drinks, by ordering carefully. The children's menu has selections in the $4 to $6.50 range including ''little bronco burgers'' and ''gunslinger grilled cheese.'' Open daily, for lunch and dinner, Hidden Valley also has dinner musical shows in a separate room two or three nights a week ($30, including the meal).</p>
        <p>Tucson now has three branches of El Charro Cafe, but we stick with the original, which opened in 1922. It's a hopping place downtown at 311 North Court Avenue, (520) 622-1922. Reservations must be made at least a day in advance. We ate enormous burritos and tacos made with the house specialty, carne seca (strips of beef marinated in lime and garlic, then sun-dried). The total came to $57.75 for six, including a couple of margaritas. El Charro is open for lunch and dinner daily.</p>
        <p>After our picnic at Kartchner Caverns, we drove 12 miles to Benson, for apple and cherry pie at the Horseshoe Steakhouse and Cantina, 154 East 4th Street, (520) 586-3303. Four slices of pie, two iced teas and two glasses of milk cost $14.49.</p>
        <p>BETSY RUBINER</p>
        <p>FRUGAL TRAVELER BETSY RUBINER, a freelance writer based in Iowa, visits Arizona frequently.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">BETSY RUBINER, a freelance writer based in Iowa, visits Arizona frequently.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
