<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>What's Wrong With the Tonys? A Lot</title>
    <meta content="21GURN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200994"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER/THE TONY AWARDS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tony Awards (Theater Awards)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gurney, A R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/Tony Awards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tony Awards (Theater Awards)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tony Awards (Theater Awards)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000521T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E0DE1E3BF932A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1394" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>What's Wrong With the Tonys? A Lot</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By A. R. GURNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gurney, A R</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article by playwright A R Gurney, who recently resigned as Tony nominator, on problems plaguing Tony Awards; notes disappointing amount of original or serious work on Broadway, citing influence of televising awards show, battles over what is and what is not a Broadway house, rigid categories unsuited to new material, and annual influx of pre-invested and pre-endorsed English and Irish works (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EVERY year or so it seems that someone points out the problems that go with the Tony Awards. This year I'd like to take a turn at it.</p>
        <p>My experience is somewhat limited, because I was a Tony nominator for less than two seasons, having resigned earlier this month, before the nominations were completed. I accepted the position because I wanted to contribute something to the profession that has nourished me for more than 40 years. I looked forward to seeing some good shows -- for free! -- and, after a series of illuminating discussions with knowledgeable colleagues, proudly presenting a distinguished slate of candidates to the Tony voters.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EVERY year or so it seems that someone points out the problems that go with the Tony Awards. This year I'd like to take a turn at it.</p>
        <p>My experience is somewhat limited, because I was a Tony nominator for less than two seasons, having resigned earlier this month, before the nominations were completed. I accepted the position because I wanted to contribute something to the profession that has nourished me for more than 40 years. I looked forward to seeing some good shows -- for free! -- and, after a series of illuminating discussions with knowledgeable colleagues, proudly presenting a distinguished slate of candidates to the Tony voters.</p>
        <p>As it turned out, the amount of original or serious work was disappointing, the discussions were limited by fiat, and the rules sometimes required us, as nominators, to endorse work we either might not have seen or might have felt was substandard.</p>
        <p>The major culprit in all this, as in so much of American life, is television. We all know that television and live theater don't mix very well, but Broadway producers need the annual Tony Awards show to fill their houses over the summer. On the other hand, the CBS network needs lively, telegenic material to satisfy its sponsors. Hence, the Tony administration committee is contractually obligated to produce at least seven musical numbers, or ''entertainments,'' for the television show, preferably to be introduced by recognized celebrities, whether they have anything to do with the theater or not.</p>
        <p>To fulfill these obligations, the Tony nominators may have to nominate more shows than they might want to, and from these, the producers may have to select the more conventionally televisable sequences. Plays, of course, don't normally work well on the tube, so whatever gestures are made in this direction are usually unsatisfactory. What the public finally gets is a distorted view of what is happening in the American theater.</p>
        <p>There is also the corrupting influence of real estate. The definition of what is or isn't a Broadway house is complicated. Yet the Tony is traditionally a ''Broadway'' award. Eligibility is limited to works presented in certain theaters in Manhattan of at least 500 seats, though most eligible theaters are much larger than that. Year by year, houses are admitted or excluded from this distinction, depending on various considerations. In any case, it's as if only books published by major publishers, or movies produced by large studios, were worthy of consideration. Maybe this distinction made sense 40 years ago, when Broadway was the locus of new and exciting work, but now, when most of what is innovative and thoughtful in American drama seems to be happening elsewhere, these limitations seem ludicrous.</p>
        <p>An additional problem in the Tony procedures is the fact that the traditional categories no longer make much sense. New ''plays,'' like ''Dirty Blonde'' or ''The Green Bird,'' look a little like musicals, whereas new musicals, like ''Contact,'' look mighty like ballets. There are more and more single-performer shows (Dame Edna, Jackie Mason) that need to be acknowledged.</p>
        <p>Finally, the fact that plays like ''Waiting in the Wings,'' which has been around for 40 years, or ''True West,'' which had a long Off Broadway run in the 80's, were proposed as best play of the current season simply because they are now playing on Broadway strikes me as disingenuous, as if pre-owned cars were to be thought new simply because they move to a glitzier showroom.</p>
        <p>The Tony administration committee recognizes these difficulties by annually coming up with various modifications, adjustments and special awards. The result is an Alice in Wonderland-like croquet game, where the wickets move around, the balls scurry away and the mallets curl up and eye you angrily.</p>
        <p>Then there is the spring infestation of English or Irish works. Over they come at Tony time, pre-invested and pre-endorsed in London, with their own directors, scenery and distinguished actors. Critics and Tony voters, starved by then for works of substance, welcome them enthusiastically and, for a few months, American audiences can pretend to be in London. At the same time, American producers make money without much risk, and British actors fly home with Tonys in their overnight bags, after a summer of acting in American air-conditioning.</p>
        <p>Because the Tony Awards telecast in June is so helpful in keeping a show alive, a large number of productions bunch up every spring, jockeying to open before the early May deadline. The 24 Tony nominators and the 705 Tony voters breathlessly rush to visit as many as three or four shows a week, while whatever was produced earlier in the season fades into insignificance. This hectic confusion is hardly conducive to serious reflection, while the lopsidedness of the spring season, when most of the good seats are reserved for people who don't have to pay, does little to encourage a more balanced habit of theatergoing for people who do.</p>
        <p>I was aware of some of these concerns before I agreed to be a Tony nominator, but I thought I could live with them. After all, good producers in the theater are rare these days and should be given all the help they can get. If they need television to sell their shows, so be it.</p>
        <p>So be it, too, if the present Tony system causes the season to be overloaded with musicals; after all, some of them are pretty good, and our first-rate designers, choreographers and dancers get a chance to strut their stuff.</p>
        <p>One also has to admit that the substantial number of free seats in prime locations offered by producers to Tony nominators and voters during the spring season enables many stalwart theater professionals to attend shows they otherwise could not afford.</p>
        <p>As for the British invasion, who can gripe about settling into an elegant Shubert theater to hear English actors say witty things?</p>
        <p>And if the Tony arbiters mess around with the rules, at least they're trying to keep our beleaguered enterprise alive. So why not leave things alone?</p>
        <p>Because the system is becoming destructive to good theater, that's why. It's beginning to feel as if the free seats were bribes for pinning the badge of excellence on endeavors that are for the most part nostalgic, commercial or safely telegenic.</p>
        <p>Original and serious work may occur somewhere else, as various other prize committees insistently remind us, but the spring Tony hoopla tends to drown them out. These are the only awards, after all, bestowed primarily by theater people on one another, and we should dignify them with professional reflection and discussion. I myself felt compelled to resign from being a nominator because I simply could not find time to attend every show, and yet was not allowed to abstain from voting in categories where I had not seen all the candidates, or where I could not endorse an entire slate.</p>
        <p>Yes, the current procedure probably brings more summer tourists to the winning shows, but I wonder whether it is driving away more serious audiences, and marginalizing those works that try to do what good theater has always done: namely, to look at who and where we are.</p>
        <p>All this could just be sour grapes, because I personally have never had much luck with Broadway and probably never will. Yet I keep thinking that if the League of American Theaters and Producers and the American Theater Wing, which together put on the Tony television show, agreed to an amicable divorce, the situation might improve.</p>
        <p>The producers could present as many musicals as the network requires in something called, say, ''Broadway 2000,'' without having to include plays or pay for the hundreds of free seats for nominators, voters and their companions.</p>
        <p>The wing, meanwhile, which owns the Tony trademark, could appoint carefully constituted committees to present its awards at an untelevised, congenial gathering of theater folk, a la ''All About Eve.'' Under these circumstances, we might hope that the Tony Awards would still retain enough clout to help fresh and significant work thrive, whether on Broadway or anywhere else.</p>
        <p>THEATER/THE TONY AWARDS A. R. Gurney is a playwright.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">A. R. Gurney is a playwright.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
