<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sex, Drugs and Subatomic Particles</title>
    <meta content="21PONGOT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200955"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Poniewozik, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Robbins, Tom</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Fierce Invalids Home From Hot Climates (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000521T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E3DE173BF932A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="668" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sex, Drugs and Subatomic Particles</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By James Poniewozik</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Poniewozik, James</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>James Poniewozik reviews book Fierce Invalids Home From Hot Climates by Tom Robbins (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FIERCE INVALIDS HOME FROM HOT CLIMATES</p>
        <p>By Tom Robbins.</p>
        <p>415 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Bantam Books. $27.50.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FIERCE INVALIDS HOME FROM HOT CLIMATES</p>
        <p>By Tom Robbins.</p>
        <p>415 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Bantam Books. $27.50.</p>
        <p>IF there's one thing more irritating than a self-appointed policeman of conventional morality and dogma, it's a self-appointed outlaw against them. In ''Fierce Invalids Home From Hot Climates,'' Tom Robbins, whose cosmic-absurdist, stoner-philosophical novels have moved undergraduates to scrawl ''So true!!!'' in the margins for decades, has again deputized himself to carry the freak flag of irreverence and fleshly indulgence. And if you're moved to ask against whom, lo these 30 years since Woodstock, you're clearly too hung up for this trip.</p>
        <p>''Fierce Invalids'' is a sort of gonzo ''Celestine Prophecy,'' one that sends its hero, Switters, on an erotic-spiritual quest. By trade Switters is a pistol-packing C.I.A. operative, but he's a hedonistic and undogmatic one, which gives Robbins license not only to lampoon the Man's uptight ways but to make it sound like an inside job. Dispatched to release his kooky grandmother's pet parrot into the South American jungle, Switters encounters a shaman who takes him on a mind-expanding hallucinogenic trip (natch) and reveals that the secret to transcendence is laughter (natch, again), a message our hero carries to America, the Middle East and even the Vatican.</p>
        <p>Anyone familiar with Robbins will recognize Switters as a lightly camouflaged, if heavily armed, author surrogate, a trickster god bearing the Robbinsian theme that we bring evil on ourselves by taking things too seriously (say, by criticizing his books). If you agree ardently enough, you may like this novel despite its own yuk deficit. (In one of several belabored jokes, Switters is obligated to spit whenever he says the name ''John Foster Dulles.'')</p>
        <p>One thing is certain. If you agree ardently enough with it, this novel will like you. For a champion of open-mindedness, Robbins shamelessly rigs the debate for his characters, setting up countless sepulchers for Switters to unwhiten, giving him long arias connecting sex, subatomic particles, God and freedom. He is ''on the run from the Killer B's,'' he says: ''B for Belief. B for Belonging. The B's that lead to most of the killing in the world.'' (So true!!!)</p>
        <p>Robbins's satisfaction with his outre protagonist borders on smugness. Then it sashays straight across that border. Switters, we are told, is ''a champion of the beautiful in an age when beauty had been voted out of office by philistines on both the right and the left.'' He is asked, by an order of renegade nuns, to ''teach us how one might remain sensitive and compassionate, yet still enjoy oneself in such a defiled, destructive age.''</p>
        <p>It's not as if Switters had no flaws: he lusts for his teenage stepsister; he gets drunk and boorish; he's a pedant. It's just that we're meant to take the ''flaws'' themselves as virtues, to laugh them off as a college girl laughs off the drunken passes of a professor who once hung out with Ken Kesey.</p>
        <p>Indeed, a tinge of Woodstock-era snobbery has crept into Robbins's work. Of a teenage character he writes: ''Suzy's generation was unforgiving of dishonesty, and rightly so. Alas, it remained rather blissfully unaware that it was being lied to by corporate America . . . a hundred times a day.'' It's one of several passages in which Robbins manages, in the same breath, both to pander and to condescend to his backpack-slinging audience.</p>
        <p>''What bothers most critics of my work is the goofiness,'' Robbins once told an interviewer. In fact, the wacky plot is one of this book's saving graces, as are the frequent well-made sentences. Two characters who've just stopped kissing are connected by ''a thread of spittle . . . as if they were continents linked by a single transoceanic cable. Then, with an inaudible pop, they were disconnected.'' Robbins the writer can turn out prose like this with one hand tied behind his back. Too bad Robbins the philosopher is content to turn it out with one hand patting himself on the back.</p>
        <p>James Poniewozik is the television critic for Time magazine.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">James Poniewozik is the television critic for Time magazine.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
