<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Food; Thermodynamic</title>
    <meta content="21FOODLT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="93" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200988"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'Neill, Molly</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine/Columns/Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000521T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E7DE1E3BF932A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1713" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Food; Thermodynamic</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Molly O'Neill</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">O'Neill, Molly</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Molly O'Neill Food column on varying cooking times to create summer's contrasting flavors; recipes; photo (M)3</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Summer glories in the raw, the crisp, the au naturel. Salads, crudites, cold soups like gazpacho, salsas, fresh garden-vegetable sauces for pasta, sushi, steak tartare or carpaccio -- these foods appeal to warm-weather appetites and the desire to cook as little as possible.</p>
        <p>Summer also revels in the singe of the grill, the caveman char, the ritual of the open flame.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Summer glories in the raw, the crisp, the au naturel. Salads, crudites, cold soups like gazpacho, salsas, fresh garden-vegetable sauces for pasta, sushi, steak tartare or carpaccio -- these foods appeal to warm-weather appetites and the desire to cook as little as possible.</p>
        <p>Summer also revels in the singe of the grill, the caveman char, the ritual of the open flame.</p>
        <p>Between raw and cooked is a wealth of options -- from the barely cooked to falling off the bone. And it is this combination of textures and temperatures that adds variety to summer dining.</p>
        <p>No other season's ingredients lend themselves so willingly to transformation simply by varying the length of the cooking time. Heat initiates chemical changes -- the breakdown of cell walls, transformation of sugars, rearrangement of proteins and, in some cases, evaporation of bitter-tasting compounds -- that result in a sweeter, mellower taste.</p>
        <p>For example, when carrots or sweet peppers are raw, the cell walls are so firm that they restrict the release of sweet-tasting compounds in the mouth. Cooking breaks down the walls and changes the internal sugars. The vegetables taste sweeter.</p>
        <p>Consider the difference between a raw onion and a slow-cooked one: raw, it has a sharp bite and is an excellent contrast to singed meats; cooked, it has a round, sweet taste and adds lingering flavor to a light summer dish. The same is true of garlic: raw, it has fire; cooked, it adds a sweet touch of soul.</p>
        <p>The savviest deployment for summer lies in contrast: a slow-cooked onion or garlic sauce makes a wonderful counterpoint to raw or barely cooked food; a quickly prepared onion or garlic sauce is a great foil for slow-cooked food like barbecue.</p>
        <p>Heat has a similar sweetening effect on meat. Quickly seared or grilled, meat gets some caramelized flavor. Slowly cooked and basted with oil, butter or rich broth toward the end, it develops more robust caramel tones. But acidic ingredients, like those in most marinades, inhibit the caramelizing action. With some food (duck comes to mind), this can work to the summer cook's advantage. A duck steamed with tart pineapple and chilies has the sort of subtly spiced flavor that is better suited for a summer evening than a traditionally roasted and caramelized duck.</p>
        <p>The most complex flavors come not from the greatest number of ingredients but from the variety of cooking times. A long-simmered sauce can become more complex when warmed with a few additional aromatics -- minced carrots, onions or garlic -- and then more complex again when garnished with raw minced vegetables or herbs.</p>
        <p>A quick ragout, on the other hand, can be given a deeper, more rounded flavor simply by stirring in caramelized onions or mashed roasted garlic before serving.</p>
        <p>The key to summer cooking is layering flavors and textures -- it is mixing the fierce and the mellow, the raw and the cooked.</p>
        <p>Quick Meat Sauce</p>
        <p>3 tablespoons olive oil</p>
        <p>2 carrots, peeled and finely chopped</p>
        <p>1 stalk celery, finely chopped</p>
        <p>1 large onion, peeled and finely chopped</p>
        <p>1 1/2 pounds ground veal</p>
        <p>1/2 pound ground pork</p>
        <p>2 pinches Aleppo pepper or 1 pinch red pepper flakes (see note)</p>
        <p>3 cloves garlic</p>
        <p>1 bay leaf</p>
        <p>Kosher salt and freshly ground black pepper to taste</p>
        <p>1 cup dry white wine</p>
        <p>1 cup peeled, seeded and diced plum tomatoes (about 5)</p>
        <p>1 tablespoon tomato paste</p>
        <p>3 tablespoons veal demi-glace</p>
        <p>1/3 cup heavy cream</p>
        <p>1 1/2 teaspoons sage</p>
        <p>2 tablespoons chopped parsley.</p>
        <p>1. In a large deep saute pan, heat the oil and add the carrots, celery and onion. Cook, stirring often, until the vegetables are soft, about 5 minutes. Add the veal, pork, Aleppo pepper, garlic and bay leaf and season lightly with salt and pepper. Cook, breaking the chunks of meat with a spatula, until the meat is no longer pink, about 10 minutes.</p>
        <p>2. Add the wine, tomatoes and tomato paste and cook until most of the liquid has evaporated, about 20 minutes. Discard the bay leaf. Stir in the demi-glace, cream and sage and cook for 3 more minutes. Remove from the heat, season with salt and pepper and stir in the parsley. Serve over pasta with freshly grated Parmesan cheese.</p>
        <p>Yield: Sauce for 1 to 1 1/2 pounds pasta, serving 4 to 6 people.</p>
        <p>Note: Aleppo pepper is available at specialty stores or by mail from Adriana's Caravan, (800) 316-0820.</p>
        <p>Long-Cooking Meat Sauce</p>
        <p>3 tablespoons olive oil</p>
        <p>2 carrots, peeled and finely chopped</p>
        <p>1 stalk celery, finely chopped</p>
        <p>1 large onion, peeled and finely chopped</p>
        <p>1 1/2 pounds ground veal</p>
        <p>1/2 pound ground pork</p>
        <p>2 cloves garlic, minced</p>
        <p>Kosher salt and freshly ground black pepper to taste</p>
        <p>1 1/4 cups dry white wine</p>
        <p>1 1/4 cups crushed canned tomatoes</p>
        <p>1 cup beef or veal stock</p>
        <p>1 1/2 teaspoons fresh thyme leaves</p>
        <p>1/8 teaspoon freshly grated nutmeg</p>
        <p>2 tablespoons heavy cream.</p>
        <p>1. In a large deep pot set over medium-high heat, heat the oil and add the carrots, celery and onion. Cook, stirring often, until the onions begin to brown, about 10 minutes. Add the veal, pork and garlic and season lightly with salt and pepper. Cook, breaking the chunks of meat with a spatula, until lightly browned, about 10 minutes.</p>
        <p>2. Add the wine, tomatoes, stock, thyme and nutmeg. Bring to a boil, lower the heat to a bare simmer and cook, uncovered, stirring frequently, for 3 hours. Stir in the cream, season with salt and pepper and serve over pasta with freshly grated Parmesan cheese.</p>
        <p>Yield: Sauce for 1 to 1 1/2 pounds pasta, serving 4 to 6 people.</p>
        <p>Quick Onion Sauce</p>
        <p>2 medium red onions, peeled, quartered and very thinly sliced</p>
        <p>8 green or red bird chilies, seeded and minced</p>
        <p>2 stalks lemongrass, very thinly sliced</p>
        <p>8 lime leaves, thinly sliced, or an additional stalk lemongrass</p>
        <p>2 tablespoons freshly squeezed lime juice</p>
        <p>1/2teaspoon shrimp paste (see note)</p>
        <p>2 cloves garlic, peeled and minced</p>
        <p>1 shallot, peeled and very finely sliced</p>
        <p>1/4cup vegetable oil</p>
        <p>1/2teaspoon kosher salt.</p>
        <p>Combine all the ingredients in a large bowl and stir with a wooden spoon for 3 to 4 minutes. Cover the bowl and refrigerate for several hours to allow the flavors to develop. Serve as a sauce over fish or chicken, with rice on the side.</p>
        <p>Yield: 2 cups. (It may be kept covered and refrigerated for up to 2 days.)</p>
        <p>Note: Shrimp paste is available at Asian groceries or by mail from Adriana's Caravan, (800) 316-0820.</p>
        <p>Long-Cooking Onion Sauce</p>
        <p>4 pounds onions, preferably sweet varieties like Walla Walla or Vidalia (about 8 onions)</p>
        <p>2 tablespoons olive oil</p>
        <p>1 tablespoon unsalted butter</p>
        <p>1 shallot, peeled and thinly sliced</p>
        <p>2 cloves garlic, peeled and thinly sliced</p>
        <p>1/2 cup white wine</p>
        <p>1/2 teaspoon apple-cider vinegar</p>
        <p>1 tablespoon chopped sage leaves</p>
        <p>Kosher salt and freshly ground black pepper to taste.</p>
        <p>1. Peel, quarter and thinly slice the onions. In a large heavy kettle, heat the olive oil and butter over medium heat and add the onions. Cook, stirring frequently, until the onions begin to turn golden, about 1 hour. Lower the heat if the onions stick to the bottom.</p>
        <p>2. Add the shallot and garlic and continue cooking, stirring often, until the onions are a deep golden color, 20 to 30 minutes more. Add the wine and vinegar and cook until the liquid has evaporated.</p>
        <p>3. Add the sage and season with salt and pepper. Serve as a sauce with duck, pork or roasted meats.</p>
        <p>Yield: 2 cups. (It may be kept covered and refrigerated for up</p>
        <p>to 3 days.)</p>
        <p>Garlic-and-Potato Condiment</p>
        <p>4 Idaho potatoes (about 1 1/2 pounds), peeled and quartered</p>
        <p>6 cloves garlic, peeled and minced</p>
        <p>5 tablespoons freshly squeezed lemon juice</p>
        <p>2 tablespoons finely chopped parsley</p>
        <p>1/2 cup extra-virgin olive oil</p>
        <p>Kosher salt and freshly ground pepper to taste.</p>
        <p>1. Place the potatoes in a medium-size pot and just cover with cold, salted water. Bring to a boil over high heat, then lower and simmer until very tender, about 17 minutes.</p>
        <p>2. Drain the potatoes, transfer to a large bowl and set aside to cool.</p>
        <p>3. Mash together the potatoes and garlic with a fork. Beat in the lemon juice, parsley and oil until well mixed. Season with salt and pepper to taste. Spread on bread or serve as a complement to roasted meats or fried fish.</p>
        <p>Yield: 2 3/4 cups. (It may be kept covered and refrigerated for up to 2 days.)</p>
        <p>Potato Condiment With Almonds</p>
        <p>20 cloves garlic, unpeeled</p>
        <p>3/4 cup, plus 2 teaspoons, extra-virgin olive oil</p>
        <p>4 Idaho potatoes (about 1 1/2 pounds), peeled and quartered</p>
        <p>5 tablespoons slivered, toasted almonds (about 1 ounce)</p>
        <p>6 tablespoons red-wine vinegar</p>
        <p>2 tablespoons finely chopped parsley</p>
        <p>Kosher salt and freshly ground pepper to taste.</p>
        <p>1. Preheat the oven to 400 degrees. Place a large sheet of aluminum foil on the counter. Put the garlic cloves on the foil and drizzle with 2 teaspoons of oil. Toss to coat. Wrap the foil around the garlic and bake until the garlic is very soft, about 45 minutes. When cool enough to handle, squeeze out the garlic into a small bowl and set aside.</p>
        <p>2. Place the potatoes in a medium-size pot and just cover with cold, salted water. Bring to a boil over high heat, then lower and simmer until very tender, about 17 minutes.</p>
        <p>3. Drain the potatoes, transfer to a large bowl and set aside to cool.</p>
        <p>4. Mash together the potatoes, garlic and almonds with a fork. Beat in the vinegar, parsley and the remaining  3/4cup oil until well mixed. Season with salt and pepper. Spread on bread or serve as a complement to roasted meats or fried fish.</p>
        <p>Yield: 3 cups. (It may be kept covered and refrigerated for up to 2 days.)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
