<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Older Office Space For the New Economy</title>
    <meta content="21ROOT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201213"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="GRASS-ROOTS BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Office Buildings and Other Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000521T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E7DE123AF932A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1330" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Older Office Space For the New Economy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOEL KOTKIN</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vacancy rates of so-called class B urban office space have fallen to roughly 11 percent nationwide from average of nearly 20 percent in 1995, creating a niche for landlords who buy up such properties, improve them and offer them at low rents, drawing off tenants from fancier space nearby; many young companies that have arisen out of Internet boom are attracted by low rents, but also feel older building reflect their own creative, nonhierarchical and unconventional nature; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FRESH out of New York University Law School, Andrew Segal moved to Texas in the early 1990's to seek his fortune. Although he started with an inheritance of roughly $1 million, he felt that New York was too tough and expensive a place to build his own business empire.</p>
        <p>Instead, he went looking where the pickings seemed easier, moving first to Dallas, where he bought some ''see through'' office buildings left virtually vacant after the oil crisis in the early 1980's. Yet as the real estate market improved there, he had to dig deeper for new opportunities, and began buying aging office buildings along Houston's downtrodden and dangerous Main Street.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FRESH out of New York University Law School, Andrew Segal moved to Texas in the early 1990's to seek his fortune. Although he started with an inheritance of roughly $1 million, he felt that New York was too tough and expensive a place to build his own business empire.</p>
        <p>Instead, he went looking where the pickings seemed easier, moving first to Dallas, where he bought some ''see through'' office buildings left virtually vacant after the oil crisis in the early 1980's. Yet as the real estate market improved there, he had to dig deeper for new opportunities, and began buying aging office buildings along Houston's downtrodden and dangerous Main Street.</p>
        <p>That made some locals think that he was out of his mind -- or at least a very gullible outsider. ''At the time,'' Mr. Segal recalled, ''it looked like it was just another holdup on Main Street.''</p>
        <p>Now, his strategy of buying old, unwanted office buildings seems more like a stroke of genius. In the last five years, his Boxer Properties, based in  Houston, has bought some 70 of them, 17 of which are of pre-World World War II vintage, in cities that also include Baltimore, Hartford, Dallas and Tulsa, Okla., as well as  Hempstead, N.Y. Nearly all the deals have proved successful, with occupancy rates, rents and property values multiplying by two, three or more.</p>
        <p>Mr. Segal, 33, appears on the verge of becoming a king of the once-disdained niche of so-called class B urban office space. His method is simple: he buys older buildings, fixes them and puts signs on them offering space for rent. As word gets around of the improved conditions in the buildings and of the low rents, which are sometimes as little as half those offered by landlords of fancier space nearby, tenants come and stay.</p>
        <p>The entrepreneur, whose low-cost business style includes extensive traipsing from Baltimore to Tulsa and places in between on budget flights, may have seized the right niche at the right time. According to statistics from Reis Inc., a real estate information firm in New York, class B vacancy rates nationwide have dropped to roughly 11 percent from an average of nearly 20 percent in 1995. In some key urban centers, like San Francisco and Seattle, the rates are as low as 3 percent. Even in  long-distressed markets like Tulsa, Baltimore and Houston, they have dropped by as much as half.</p>
        <p>Mr. Segal credits the recovery of this niche in the last five years to broader changes in the economy -- including the explosive growth in the number of Internet, media and related businesses. These young companies may initially be attracted by the  lower rents, but they also see these older buildings -- some of them stunning examples of Art Deco or Beaux-Arts architecture -- as reflecting their image as creative, nonhierarchical and unconventional.</p>
        <p>Of course, Mr. Segal notes, the appeal of such buildings is not unconditional. To make them as functional as their more modern rivals, they often require upgraded telecommunications infrastructure and central air-conditioning systems, fresh coats of paint, and sometimes the removal of outdated features like carpeting over hardwood floors.</p>
        <p>In many cities, such structures also benefit by being in or near districts that attract the young people who are so vital to many new-economy companies. Unlike high-rise buildings, these structures -- often less than 10 stories -- were usually built to accommodate ground-level businesses that open to the street. They also tend to have more light, and therefore less of the ''concrete canyon'' coldness found in many post-1950's downtown areas.</p>
        <p>Throughout the country, districts dominated by class B buildings -- like Lower Manhattan in New York, Deep Ellum in Dallas, the Leather District of Boston and the South of Market section of San Francisco -- have first re-emerged as magnets for artists and denizens of hip clubs, then become hotbeds of Internet and other new-media activity. And with  loft and other residential spaces available nearby, they create the kind of vibrant, 24-hour-a-day, seven-day-a-week environment sought by dot-com employees.</p>
        <p>''It's where the single people are, where you go to a bar to meet them,'' Mr. Segal said. ''That's what makes it work. In Houston there are few places for people to walk around and promenade; downtown is the exception.''</p>
        <p>The movement of Web-related companies into these districts, he said, enhances their appeal for more traditional white-collar companies that he calls ''dot-com wannabes.'' In that group are advertising agencies, publishers, fashion design companies, executive recruiters and even small law firms that seek out the latest ''cool'' space to impress both clients and prospective employees with their new-economy savoir faire.</p>
        <p>OTHER pioneers include Richard Kirshenbaum, founder of Kirshenbaum Bond &amp; Partners in New York, an ad agency that prides itself on being hip. Kirshenbaum Bond moved from Midtown to Lower Manhattan more than a decade ago, in part to identify with the image of the area.</p>
        <p>''If you are in a traditional area, you say you are a traditional business,'' Mr. Kirshenbaum, 40, said in his art-filled headquarters on Hudson Street. ''It's taking risks, but we're a young agency and the area has sprouted up. It's having your own point of view and knowing your own mind.''</p>
        <p>For Mr. Segal, who tends to be a bottom-fishing King of the B's, markets like New York, San Francisco, Seattle and Boston, where class B rents can now reach $50 a square foot, have become too expensive. He prefers places like Tulsa, where he has bought seven prewar structures in the recovering downtown area; Kansas City, Mo.; and Baltimore. Space there can still be rented for as little as $10 a square foot and class B buildings bought for $1 million or less.</p>
        <p>Mr. Segal is the first to acknowledge that these markets barely exist on the radar screen of big-name speculators and real estate investment trusts. He sees that as a plus, particularly if the market has falling vacancy rates, gradually rising rents and a growing community of high-technology companies. ''I think the market will reward places that are cheaper and still offer a unique urban experience,'' he said.</p>
        <p>These markets, he added, offer him the chance to duplicate the kind of windfall he has enjoyed on Houston's Main Street, now that downtown Houston itself may be getting a bit too expensive.</p>
        <p>WITH the $525,000 he spent in 1996 to buy two 70-year-old office buildings in the city, he has made money two ways. Last year, he sold his 711 Main Street building for $2.1 million to a condominium developer. Each of the 40 lofts there, he estimated, is now worth more than the entire building was five years ago.</p>
        <p>At the other Main Street building, which he still owns, the rental income has soared as commercial tenants have flooded in. Its vacancy rate, near 80 percent in 1996, has dropped to the single digits. New Web companies like SalvageSale.com, have moved in, helping to push rents from $6 a square foot to closer to $15, a big increase since 1996 but still at least $5 cheaper than nearby class A structures.</p>
        <p>The growth of restaurants and clubs around the area, said Charlie Wilson, SalvageSale.com's president, has greatly enhanced the value of the office space -- a phenomenon seen in other cities as well.</p>
        <p>''It's different, it's cool and it has  history,'' said Mr. Wilson, 32, whose company now occupies 10,000 square feet in the building. ''If you're going to be in Houston, this is where we want to be.''</p>
        <p>GRASS-ROOTS BUSINESS Joel Kotkin is a senior fellow at the Pepperdine Institute for Public Policy. His column on the Main Street economy appears the third Sunday of each month. E-mail: grassrts@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Joel Kotkin is a senior fellow at the Pepperdine Institute for Public Policy. His column on the Main Street economy appears the third Sunday of each month. E-mail: grassrts@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
