<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On Web, Voters Reinvent Grass-Roots Activism</title>
    <meta content="Y21WEB$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201345"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wayne, Leslie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000521T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E4DE103AF932A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1825" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On Web, Voters Reinvent Grass-Roots Activism</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LESLIE WAYNE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wayne, Leslie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Election campaigns of 2000 spawn some 6,700 independent, grass-roots Web pages, which give ordinary voters with some Web-design skills a new way of engaging in political process; these Web sites are challenging the ability of the two parties and individual candidates to control their messages, direct grass-roots activism and orchestrate the rhythm and pace of campaign; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>By day, Pamela Sybrandy works as a nurse in San Diego. But in her free time, she is a cyberwarrior for Al Gore. Part of a growing band of grass-roots activists, Ms. Sybrandy has set up a Web page -- with no ties to the Democratic Party or the Gore campaign -- to promote Mr. Gore's views on family and children's issues.</p>
        <p>Until now, Ms. Sybrandy's only political involvement was to gather  bumper stickers and buttons at the local Democratic headquarters. But this year, she said, she looked at her political participation and decided to ''kick it up a notch'' and create a site (www.all4gore.com) to promote Mr. Gore in a way that gave her more clout.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>By day, Pamela Sybrandy works as a nurse in San Diego. But in her free time, she is a cyberwarrior for Al Gore. Part of a growing band of grass-roots activists, Ms. Sybrandy has set up a Web page -- with no ties to the Democratic Party or the Gore campaign -- to promote Mr. Gore's views on family and children's issues.</p>
        <p>Until now, Ms. Sybrandy's only political involvement was to gather  bumper stickers and buttons at the local Democratic headquarters. But this year, she said, she looked at her political participation and decided to ''kick it up a notch'' and create a site (www.all4gore.com) to promote Mr. Gore in a way that gave her more clout.</p>
        <p>In the 2000 election, such independent and home-grown Web pages, created by individual voters with some Web-design skills and a little spare time, are multiplying exponentially and now number about 6,700. Often rivaling the sophistication of the official Web sites of political parties and candidates, these grass-roots Web sites are a new way for ordinary voters to engage in the political process -- a high-tech version, many say, of putting a sign in a voter's front yard or a bumper sticker on a car.</p>
        <p>''It's kind of democracy at work,'' said Eddie Mahe, a Washington consultant and former deputy chairman of the Republican National Committee. ''Historically, those same things have been said in every campaign. The difference is that they used to be said in a bar or at the corner coffee shop. But now, on the Internet, everyone has a megaphone.''</p>
        <p>In their unorganized way and by their sheer numbers, grass-roots Web sites are challenging the traditional role of the two political parties and individual candidates of controlling their own messages, to direct grass-roots activism and to orchestrate the rhythm and pace of a political campaign. If the 2000 election is the one in which the Internet meets traditional campaigning, it is also one in which politicians are sorting out whether this grass-roots cyberactivism is a friend or foe.</p>
        <p>''Politicians don't know if this will be a benefit or if it is where they start losing control of their campaigns,'' said Ari Schwartz, a policy analyst at the Center for Democracy and Technology, a nonprofit organization in Washington.</p>
        <p>As of last week, 3,775 home-grown Web sites had the Bush name in them and 3,066 had Mr. Gore's name, compared with virtually none containing candidates' names in the last presidential campaign. Not all, of course, support one of the two candidates.  Some praise, some mock, some parody and others simply repeat much of what the two candidates have said or post news articles about them from other sources.</p>
        <p>So far, the Bush campaign seems to have suffered the greatest sting from parody sites, particularly over questions about whether he used drugs. The Bush campaign, in fact, tried to restrict one scathing Web site, www.gwbush.com, arguing that the site should be regulated as a political committee, but the campaign's complaint was dismissed last month by the Federal Election Commission.</p>
        <p>''It's like someone walks down the street at lunch time and yells at the top of their lungs that a presidential candidate is wrong or unattractive,'' said Robert F. Bauer, a lawyer for the Democratic Party. ''The candidates cannot demand a retraction or make a citizen's arrest. This is not different.''</p>
        <p>For the most part, however, these sites are earnest efforts at political activism and, because of that, they raise a number of tricky issues. On one hand, grass-roots Web sites represent a wellspring of new activists for candidates and parties to tap, especially when so many political observers have lamented a decline in voter participation.</p>
        <p>But this new medium also creates a series of what-if's for the parties: What if a well-meaning Web site contains information the candidate or party believes misrepresents it? What if confusion arises between official party and candidate Web sites and grass-roots ones? What if some of these Web sites contain links to groups on the far right or far left that a candidate would rather not be associated with?</p>
        <p>And, even more basic, what if these Web sites begin to shift political power away from candidates and parties and to individuals with a large electronic presence?</p>
        <p>''Until now, guilt by association was a very effective political weapon,'' said one Republican Party official. ''On the Web, heaven and hell are only two clicks away. To criticize a candidate for something on a link that is three or four sites removed from his own Web page will be problematic for every political player on the Web. They are all going to face it.''</p>
        <p>Makers of these Web sites do not see their activities as a series of what-if's, but rather as a chance to participate in politics -- in their own way, on their own schedule.</p>
        <p>''If my site was run by the Republican National Committee, they'd be saying, 'Do this' or, 'Don't say that,' '' said Travis Main, a computer technician in Eugene, Ore., who set up www.voterepublican.net. ''I wanted to be involved promoting Republican conservatives. But I didn't have the time to get involved with the parties or be an activist in that sense. The Internet gave me the opportunity to be active and work at it on my schedule.''</p>
        <p>Starting last August, Mr. Main, who works in a bank, started putting in six to seven hours a day on weekends and at nights building his Web site. Now, he has about 1,500 visits a month and he has cut his work on the site to an hour or two a day.</p>
        <p>The site has a cartoon logo of a smiling elephant cradling a baby elephant swaddled in an American flag. It contains a directory and links to conservative Republican Web sites and to a wide array of conservative publications and groups. It also posts letters from viewers and holds some discussions on conservative issues.</p>
        <p>''The thrust of our site is to provide information,'' Mr. Main said. ''There is all this information out there and voters can have a choice about what they want to gather and how they want to act on that. Before, they just had to rely on the local party or reading newspapers.''</p>
        <p>On the other side of the political spectrum is Robin Orlowski, a junior at Texas Woman's University in Denton, Tex. She runs the PioneerGrrrl Web site, which contains essays by Ms. Orlowski supporting Democratic and female candidates and attacking the Republicans. It also has links to pro-Democratic sites and anti-Bush ones.</p>
        <p>Ms. Orlowski plans to participate in more traditional campaigning this fall, but she sees her site as a way of expressing her liberal views cheaply and in the spirit of free and open debate.</p>
        <p>''These sites will increase democracy in the long run,'' Ms. Orlowski said. ''You don't have tightly scripted campaigns as the sole voice. You will have independent citizens voicing their opinions in a way they couldn't before. It's because the Internet is dirt cheap and it costs money to print campaign materials. The Internet is a great free opportunity.''</p>
        <p>And as Mr. Bush and Mr. Gore know well, it also provides an opportunity for critics to exploit their foibles. For instance, www.all gore.com, recently featured a parody of Mr. Gore saying, ''Elian can live with me.'' And anti-Bush Web sites  like www.georgybush.com feature parody songs in Spanish and English that can be put on CD's for distribution.</p>
        <p>The Gore campaign has tried to take a low-key view of the sites that make fun of Mr. Gore. ''We try to keep a good sense of humor about them,'' said Todd Webster, a campaign spokesman.</p>
        <p>Moreover, the Democratic Party has taken a page from the parody book and brought forth a number of sites mocking Republicans, among them www.MillionairesForBush .com, and has picked up some material from a Comedy Central Web site that makes fun of Senator John McCain of Arizona and linked it to  the party's own site (www. democrats.org).</p>
        <p>Even if much of the material is in jest, however, the creators of these parody Web sites say their intent is serious. ''We will play a small role in the campaign because there are many people coming to our site and who have heard what I have to say,'' said Zack Exley, creator of the gwbush.com site, which he says gets  300,000 to 500,000 visits a month. ''I am trying to make some points that have not been made in the mainstream media.''</p>
        <p>In a join-them-rather-than-fight-them effort, the Republican National Committee has decided to improve its own Web site -- it has 10 percent of the 150 staff members at its headquarters devoted to Internet campaigning -- so that voters might be more inclined to visit the official committee site (www.rnc.org) rather than to drift into unofficial sites.</p>
        <p>And the party is making banners, logos and other material available on its site for supporters to download onto their sites. In addition, the national party is sponsoring a workshop -- ''Winning in a Web World'' -- in June to help party organizers and grass-roots supporters with Web campaigning and design. The party is also putting large disclaimers on material on its Web site, so that if it is lifted by groups the party does not approve of, a message comes up saying the Republican Party does not endorse the content of any other Web site.</p>
        <p>On the Democratic side, the party is asking the Commerce Department to see whether official Web sites for federal candidates should have a separate domain suffix -- .elect or .pol -- to differentiate themselves from unofficial sites. This request was made after a grass-roots site said that it was an official Democratic site and began to collect campaign money. (The site later disappeared.)</p>
        <p>''We see the Web as the best campaign tool since the phone and the television,'' said Larry Purpuro, the  deputy chief of staff for the Republican National Committee and head of its eGOP project. ''We don't see it as a foe or a threat, but as a great opportunity. We've said, 'It's digital or die.' If we don't embrace, exploit and learn from it, we could be displaced in lots of our activities.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
