<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dining, With Water Views as Ambience</title>
    <meta content="21DINE$11" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="49" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201161"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Fisherman's Catch (Point Lookout, Ny, Restaurant)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cleawater (Massapequa, Ny, Restaurant)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pine Island Grill (Bayville, Ny)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Trumpets (East Port, Ny, Restaurant)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Beacon (Sag Harbor, Ny, Restaurant)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">La Plage (Wading River, Ny, Restaurant)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Coyote Grill (Island Park, Ny, Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Starkey, Joanne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000521T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6D9153AF932A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1755" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dining, With Water Views as Ambience</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOANNE STARKEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Starkey, Joanne</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Joanne Starkey reviews Long Island restaurants with water views: Fisherman's Catch in Point Lookout, Clearwater in Massapequa, Bayville's Pine Island Grill, Trumpets in East Port, Sag Harbor's Beacon, La Plage in Wading River and Coyote Grill in Island Park; photos; list (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SOME restaurants just say summer. On Long Island, where summer and water are nearly synonymous, it is not surprising that most of these summery spots are on or near the water. That water might be the Reynolds Channel in Island Park or Point Lookout, the Long Island Sound in Bayville or Wading River, a canal in Massapequa, Sag Harbor Cove or Moriches Bay in Eastport.</p>
        <p>Fisherman's Catch in Point Lookout is a rough and ready fish house, a casual waterfront spot that serves bountiful platters of freshly caught seafood at moderate prices. In short, it's the kind of place we all are looking for. The restaurant's owners also run the fish-packing plant, retail fish store and clam bar next door.  There, the daily catches from their own boats and others supply the restaurant.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SOME restaurants just say summer. On Long Island, where summer and water are nearly synonymous, it is not surprising that most of these summery spots are on or near the water. That water might be the Reynolds Channel in Island Park or Point Lookout, the Long Island Sound in Bayville or Wading River, a canal in Massapequa, Sag Harbor Cove or Moriches Bay in Eastport.</p>
        <p>Fisherman's Catch in Point Lookout is a rough and ready fish house, a casual waterfront spot that serves bountiful platters of freshly caught seafood at moderate prices. In short, it's the kind of place we all are looking for. The restaurant's owners also run the fish-packing plant, retail fish store and clam bar next door.  There, the daily catches from their own boats and others supply the restaurant.</p>
        <p>Fisherman's Catch, situated on Reynolds Channel, boasts its own dock (with limited space for tie-ups) and a small outdoor deck where patrons can have drinks before dinner.  Walls of windows in the rustic dining room afford great views of boats, water and spectacular sunsets.</p>
        <p>The food is just as impressive. The best openers are the thick, creamy New England clam chowder and the bisque full of lobster. Appetizers are not really necessary because a large dinner plate of fresh mixed greens, red onion and cubes of cucumber and tomato is included in the price of every entree.</p>
        <p>The freshness of the fish, combined with gentle cooking, create some memorable dishes. The roster of successes includes up-to-the-minute preparations (i.e. pan-roasted halibut encircled with an eggplant-tomato tapenade and sauteed sea scallops in a tomatoey Provencal sauce), but the hit of a recent meal was a throwback to the 1950's: fried shrimp. There were a dozen of them, lightly breaded, golden brown, crispy, greaseless treats. They arrived atop a mountain of first-class, thin French fries with a bowl of creamy, slightly sweet cole slaw on the side.</p>
        <p>Another waterfront South Shore seafood restaurant that opened last summer was Clearwater. Similarities end there. Clearwater, a canal-side spot in Massapequa, is not rough or rustic but the epitome of sleek sophistication. Its look is clean, crisp and high-tech. Images of the sea are everywhere. A back-lighted wall of brilliant blue recreates sunlight reflected on the ocean. Another wall is glass with shadows of sea creatures.  There is also a row of windows giving diners a view of the canal. During the season, a waterside porch is the most popular perch.</p>
        <p>The big news here, though, is the food. The chef and co-owner is Michael Meehan, who also owns the highly regarded Tupelo Honey in Sea Cliff. His flaky biscuits are a great introduction to the exciting regional American fare.</p>
        <p>Seafood reigns. Try the herb and potato pizza with crisp crust and toppers of cured tuna and tomato salsa. The best entrees are the pan-fried soft-shell crabs, the cedar-planked salmon served over ramps and exotic mushrooms, the steamed striped bass with a black olive relish complement and perfectly cooked catfish enhanced by pecan-studded wild rice and a luscious corn sauce dotted with crawfish.</p>
        <p>Desserts turn heads, especially the ''red sails in the sunset'': three sorbets in a sailing ship made of almond cookies with white chocolate masts and lemon meringue oars.</p>
        <p>A stunner on the North Shore is the Pine Island Grill in Bayville. The soaring three-story restaurant gives diners plenty to look at. Inside there are pale-wood mobiles of fish and other sea creatures plus a jungle of green plants. Floor-to-ceiling windows afford spectacular views of beach, the sound, Connecticut in the distance and breathtaking summer sunsets. The outdoor dining decks, edged in lofty umbrellas and nautical railings, provide the prime seating.</p>
        <p>At a recent meal, top entrees were a grilled sirloin steak with good beefy flavor, pan-seared Nile perch escorted by braised leeks, couscous and shallot-porcini butter and a memorable pasta: linguine tossed with Tuscan beans, tomato concasse and five jumbo shrimp scampi.</p>
        <p>The best openers were seared sea scallops encircling a vanilla-mango chutney and a confit of duck-sweet potato spring roll paired with a red cabbage slaw.</p>
        <p>On the opposite side of the Island is another restaurant with world-class views. At the end of a country road, overlooking Moriches Bay in Eastport, is Trumpets. The two-year-old restaurant was formerly a garage and small salt-box Colonial with a tower between them. The building now flows from one elegant dining wing, through a central tower room (with a sought-after round table) to a second wing, all taking advantage of the waterfront setting.</p>
        <p>Trumpets has the summery look down pat: creamy walls, shiny wood floors, soaring ceilings with skylights and windows everywhere. There is also a small outdoor deck with four tables and large market umbrellas.</p>
        <p>Crustaceans put on the best show at entree time. Shrimp tempura with crisp, gossamer coats are top-notch, as is a sextet of grilled shrimp with a roasted pepper vinaigrette. Even better is a sweet two-pound lobster.  For landlubbers, boneless chicken breasts topped with sauteed apples and caramelized onions are different and memorable.</p>
        <p>Begin the meal with the twin, no-filler crab cakes or with the light mushroom strudel. There are homemade desserts with chocolate mousse cake, as rich as ganache, and a yummy chocolate-macadamia nut pie receiving the most kudos.</p>
        <p>Farther east to the Hamptons is the Beacon, a Sag Harbor restaurant that opened last year and epitomizes the best of summer dining.</p>
        <p>Patrons make their way along a walk lined with bamboo trees in terra-cotta pots. They then climb a steep staircase to this lofty, breezy spot: really a long porch with a row of tables and a slightly more formal, small indoor dining room. Potted palms, bamboo roll-up shades, bistro chairs and exotic blooms add to the summery feeling.</p>
        <p>During the evening, diners can look at the sunset, stare at the water or watch the activities at the marina below: sailors moving their gear, walking their dogs or grilling their supper.</p>
        <p>The food is as summery as the milieu. Try the oysters on the half shell escorted by an addictive seaweed salad or the salad of endive, apple, butter-lettuce and blue cheese with quince-pecan vinaigrette.</p>
        <p>The No. 1 entree pick is the grilled rib-eye steak, which is full of flavor and running with juices. Among the many successful fish dishes is a lightly cooked, soy-glazed salmon crowned with a sesame-cucumber slaw that sits upon a hash of potatoes and rock shrimp.</p>
        <p>End the meal with the splendid homemade sorbets and ice creams.</p>
        <p>Homemade ice creams also top off a spectacular meal at La Plage in Wading River. La Plage (the beach in French) is literally there: across the street from a town beach with a parking lot that will fill your shoes with sand.</p>
        <p>La Plage has a look of rustic elegance. Floors are bare and wooden crates, from nearby farms, form the wine racks. But this is a white tablecloth, candlelight and fresh flowers kind of place. There is an outdoor dining deck covered with a snappy striped awning and there are sunny yellow walls within. Interesting art dots those walls and bouquets of flowers are everywhere. (I counted eight on a recent visit.) Lucky diners on the deck and in the front room, which is an enclosed porch, have eyes only for the beach, Long Island Sound and the lights of distant Connecticut.</p>
        <p>I fell in love with La Plage when it opened four years ago. It is even better today. We recently had a near-perfect meal here. High points were the inventive salads: a tower of tart apple slices, blue cheese, walnuts and mache in a sesame-sherry vinaigrette; a toss of arugula, enoki mushrooms, hearts of palm and cherry tomatoes gilded with warm, firm, baby shrimp; and a construction of tomatoes, haricots verts, chopped nicoise olives, ricotta salata and pine nuts all drizzled with white truffle oil.</p>
        <p>Tops among the entrees were a juicy baby chicken over creamy feta polenta, pan-seared halibut escorted by wild mushroom risotto and a lovely looking and lovely tasting plate of caramelized sea scallops placed atop a vibrantly green pea-coconut sauce.  They encircled a crunchy snow-crab fritter, which crowned an island of spinach. Young pea shoots finished the dish.</p>
        <p>Fresh fruit pies with homemade ice cream make great summer endings, but the restaurant's showstopper dessert is a warm chocolate banana bread pudding with a molten center paired with a scoop of that yummy homemade ice cream.</p>
        <p>Even during the hottest days of summer, diners can tire of a steady diet of salad and grilled fish. The Coyote Grill, with its Southwestern fare, offers change-of-pace food.</p>
        <p>When this Island Park restaurant made its debut a decade ago, it was a real eye-opener. Here was an adobe hacienda outlined in purple neon sporting a water view. Its look combines the best of East and West. Long Island provides the waterfront ambience. The rest is Santa Fe all the way: pale wood ceiling beams, tile floors and adobe walls dotted with cowboy artifacts and whimsical Southwestern art. A deck overlooking Reynolds Channel, with facilities for boat tie-ups, is the most popular dining area in warm weather.</p>
        <p>At a recent meal I was happy to see that the tobacco onion rings, a basket of delicious thin wisps that have been tossed with cornmeal and chili, are still on the menu and still carry the same price tag they did eight years ago ($4). They are a must-order appetizer.</p>
        <p>At entree time, try the quesadillas filled with sweet firm rock shrimp or the tasty marinated skirt steak, thinly sliced and piled atop grilled tortillas.</p>
        <p>For dessert, a great summer finale is a chewy, moist brownie topped with three scoops of ice cream, stacked vertically, with hot fudge and caramel sauces.</p>
        <p>Where to Find the Restaurants</p>
        <p>THE BEACON, 8 Water Street, Sag Harbor, (631) 725-7088</p>
        <p>COYOTE GRILL, 104 Waterview Road, Island Park, (516) 889-8009</p>
        <p>CLEARWATER, 8 Alhambra Road, Massapequa, (516) 798-4000</p>
        <p>FISHERMAN'S CATCH, 111 Bayside Drive, Point Lookout, (516) 670-9717</p>
        <p>LA PLAGE, 131 Creek Road, Wading River, (631) 744-9200</p>
        <p>PINE ISLAND GRILL, at the Crescent Beach Club, 333 Bayville Avenue, Bayville, (516) 628-3000</p>
        <p>TRUMPETS, 58 South Bay Avenue, Eastport, (631) 325-2900</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
