<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>LAZIO OPENS RACE WITH AN ATTACK ON MRS. CLINTON</title>
    <meta content="21REPU$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201385"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE RACE FOR SENATE: THE REPUBLICANS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nagourney, Adam</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lazio, Rick A (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000521T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E6DE113AF932A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1940" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>LAZIO OPENS RACE WITH AN ATTACK ON MRS. CLINTON</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM NAGOURNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nagourney, Adam</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Rep Rick A Lazio opens his campaign for Senate with a speech in West Islip charging that Hillary Rodham Clinton is a far left candidate with no real rationale for serving in New York other than as a stepping stone to some other position; says he considers himself a centrist, mainstream Republican; Clinton acknowledges the ideological divide, saying voters will get to choose between candidates with very different stands on everything from education, to health care, to future of the economy, to care for state's children and elderly; Republican leaders in New York and Wsahington line up behind Lazio's candidacy; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Representative Rick A. Lazio of Long Island came roaring into the race for senator from New York yesterday, attacking Hillary Rodham Clinton as a ''far left'' candidate who has ''no real rationale for serving here other than as a steppingstone to some other position.''</p>
        <p>''I think her ambition is the issue,'' Mr. Lazio declared in an interview before heading for the high school from which he graduated in 1976 to formally announce his candidacy in a race that has been upended by Rudolph W. Giuliani's decision to step aside because of health reasons.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Representative Rick A. Lazio of Long Island came roaring into the race for senator from New York yesterday, attacking Hillary Rodham Clinton as a ''far left'' candidate who has ''no real rationale for serving here other than as a steppingstone to some other position.''</p>
        <p>''I think her ambition is the issue,'' Mr. Lazio declared in an interview before heading for the high school from which he graduated in 1976 to formally announce his candidacy in a race that has been upended by Rudolph W. Giuliani's decision to step aside because of health reasons.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio, addressing a whooping and cheering crowd of supporters at West Islip High School, on Long Island, described the emerging contest between a little-known four-term member of Congress and the nation's first lady as a ''clear choice'' between candidates of competing ideologies and divergent backgrounds.</p>
        <p>''My opponent is a liberal and a proud one, and I respect her for that,'' said Mr. Lazio, who lives in Bay Shore. ''But make no mistake: she is no more a New Democrat than she is a New Yorker. She offers the big-government ideology that crippled New York in the 1980's. I do not believe we want to enter this new century pledging allegiance to the liberal ideas that so painfully failed us in the last century.''</p>
        <p>The remarks came as Republican leaders in New York and Washington lined up behind the candidacy of Mr. Lazio, who had suspended his campaign last year in deference to party leaders who wanted Mr. Giuliani as their candidate. Mr. Lazio announced a two-day state fly-around, an aggressive come-out-of-the-box approach intended to discourage any other Republicans who might be thinking about challenging him. And Michael Long, the state Conservative Party leader, was said to be preparing to endorse Mr. Lazio, as Joseph DioGuardi, a former Westchester County congressman who had been seeking the Conservative Party nomination, told friends that he would quit the race to make way for Mr. Lazio.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton's press secretary, Howard Wolfson, assailed Mr. Lazio for his attacks on Mrs. Clinton in the interview. ''I'm shocked by the approach they are taking,'' Mr. Wolfson said. ''They are so overwhelmed by their hatred for her. I guess you have to run a negative campaign when you're a Gingrich Republican with a record that's too extreme for New York.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton, at an appearance yesterday afternoon, took a softer line, but made it clear that she, too, saw this as a contest of ideologies. ''If Congressman Lazio is the Republican nominee,'' she said, ''there will be a clear difference between us on a number of issues because we've taken very different stands on everything from education, to health care, to the future of the economy, to how we take care of our children as well as our elderly citizens.''</p>
        <p>The tenor of Mr. Lazio's comments in both the interview and the formal  announcement speech suggested that the campaign, with the change in candidate, was going to be harsh and fast-paced, with a particular emphasis on Mrs. Clinton's attempt to run for office in a state to which she just moved five months ago, and on what Mr. Lazio described as her liberal ideology. Mrs. Clinton's advisers have moved to portray Mr. Lazio as extreme and conservative, noting that he supported many of the initiatives of former House Speaker Newt Gingrich, as they tried to discredit his candidacy.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio, 42, said he considered himself ''a centrist, a mainstream Republican.''</p>
        <p>''We're conservative, right-of-center on budget and tax issues, national security issues,'' he said. ''And I think we're realistic on social issues.''</p>
        <p>He described his Democratic opponent as ''far left,'' adding: ''She's part of the discredited philosophy that helped lead New York to ruin during the Cuomo years. I think we've turned the corner, and we don't want to go back to those failed days.''</p>
        <p>In the interview, Mr. Lazio jumped at almost every opportunity to criticize Mrs. Clinton. He responded vigorously when asked if he would make an issue out of the fact that Mrs. Clinton did not live in New York before this year, a subject that Mr.  Giuliani, as mayor of New York City, frequently raised.</p>
        <p>''I'm the real thing,'' he said. ''I don't have to try to be someone else. I was born here. I went to school here. I fished in these waters. I clammed in its bays. I graduated from our schools. My children were born in New York State. I've lived here my whole life. There will be no question of my commitment to this state.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio's announcement speech was scattered with references to his own New York roots and indirect jabs at his opponent. ''You can tell from my accent that I am a lifelong New Yorker,'' Mr. Lazio declared, grinning broadly as the audience responded with laughter and applause. ''You see, I don't have to fake it. New York isn't just a place I represent -- it is my home. And I've never needed an exploratory committee to decide where I want to live.''</p>
        <p>At another point, borrowing from what had been another of Mr. Giuliani's refrains, he said, ''I can't call on Air Force One whenever I need a ride.''</p>
        <p>By contrast, he said in the interview, Mrs. Clinton is hurt both by the fact that she has only recently lived in the state where she wants to serve, and because of the cloistered life she has lived as a first lady.</p>
        <p>''You don't know New York if you have bodyguards around you all the time,'' he said. ''You've got to know what it's like to ride the subways, to drive your own car, to buy your own gas, to buy groceries here.</p>
        <p>''I think people can see through who Hillary Clinton is, and they will have a chance to know Rick Lazio as the real deal,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The exchanges between the campaigns yesterday suggested that expectations aside, a Lazio-Clinton race could prove to be far harsher than a race between Mrs. Clinton and Mr. Giuliani, and not necessarily by choice. Mr. Lazio is under pressure to establish himself quickly as a credible and tough challenger to Mrs. Clinton, for the sake of party leaders as well as contributors from across the nation who had financed Mr. Giuliani's challenge to Mrs. Clinton and are in danger of drifting away in the next few days.</p>
        <p>And Mr. Lazio, because he is relatively unknown, is likely to find it a lot less complicated to attack Mrs. Clinton than Mr. Giuliani had. The mayor always had to be on guard about being portrayed as unyielding or rash, particularly as Mrs. Clinton sought to suggest that his temperament left him unsuited to serve in the Senate.</p>
        <p>For Mrs. Clinton, the question is not whether to attack, but when. That said, her aides acknowledged that Mr. Lazio might prove to be a more elusive target than Mr. Giuliani, both because he is a more obscure candidate and because he makes what many Republicans described as a pleasing first impression.</p>
        <p>The immediate struggle is a race to see which side succeeds in defining Mr. Lazio first over the next few weeks.</p>
        <p>Even before Mr. Lazio announced, Mrs. Clinton's aides had researched his record and were preparing to paint him as a Republican partisan who would vote against New York interests in Congress.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio has spent much of the last two weeks talking with New York and national Republicans, and that was apparent yesterday. He dismissed suggestions by Mrs. Clinton's aides that he was too partisan as ''laughable,'' adding: ''They're going to be talking about the old failed model of, 'Oh yeah, this guy is too this, or too that.' ''</p>
        <p>On one issue over which the two candidates have some disagreement -- abortion -- Mr. Lazio described Mrs. Clinton as extreme because she opposes a ban on some forms of late-term abortion. ''I'm for a woman's right to choose, but I think it's not unlimited,'' Mr. Lazio said. ''I favor the ban on partial birth. I think Mrs. Clinton takes the position to the extreme. I think I reflect where New Yorkers are and where America is. Not criminalizing abortion, but also not allowing a horrific procedure that even Ed Koch and Senator Moynihan condemn. She is on the fringes of this issue.'' Mr. Lazio also said  yesterday that he opposed any public financing of abortions.</p>
        <p>In his speech, Mr. Lazio presented himself as an ideological underdog against a candidate of the left. ''This is an important race. It seems as though everyone throughout our great nation is watching us,'' he said. ''And every possible liberal group from outside our state has lined up with our Democratic opponent. Well, I say, bring them on. From Washington, from Hollywood, from Arkansas.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio's announcement came as his campaign sprang almost overnight into full life. Workers at his headquarters answered the phone ''Lazio 2000'' early yesterday, and Mr. Lazio's Web site urged voters to contribute money.</p>
        <p>Newly hired staff members flew up from Washington, with a notable representation from the presidential campaigns of Lamar Alexander, the former governor of Tennessee, and Senator John S. McCain of Arizona. Mr. Lazio's media adviser, Michael Murphy, performed the same role for Mr. Alexander in 1996.</p>
        <p>The new Lazio campaign staff members struggled through a chaotic morning as they grappled with questions like where was Mr. Lazio's headquarters located (Bay Shore), and what was the area code (631), from an onslaught of news media that abandoned Mr. Giuliani at New York City Hall for Mr. Lazio's headquarters on Long Island with startling speed.</p>
        <p>Across New York State, Republican leaders fell in line with Gov. George E. Pataki and the state Republican chairman, William D. Powers, and proclaimed not only their support for Mr. Lazio, but also their belief that he would prove to be an extremely formidable opponent to Mrs. Clinton, notwithstanding the obvious obstacles he faces. (Some Republicans went so far as to suggest privately that he was a better candidate than Mr. Giuliani would have ever been.)</p>
        <p>''The race at the end of the day is going to be about who best can serve New York,'' said Zenia Mucha, the chief political aide to Mr. Pataki, ''and based on his record in Congress, it's clearly going to be him.'' Drawing a contrast between Mr. Lazio and Mrs. Clinton, she said he ''understands what it means to be a New Yorker. She's in the process of learning. His basic philosophy is a smaller role of government for the people. Her basic philosophy is that government has all the answers.''</p>
        <p>Representative Peter F. King of Long Island withdrew from seeking the Republican nomination. He said yesterday morning that he did not want to cause any division within the Republican Party.</p>
        <p>Republicans emphasized repeatedly that Mr. Lazio was more closely in tune with Republican positions on issues than Mr. Giuliani was.</p>
        <p>''Personally speaking, I am a little more comfortable with Rick Lazio,'' said Stephen J. Minarik, the Monroe County Republican chairman. ''He is more in line with the party.''</p>
        <p>THE RACE FOR SENATE: THE REPUBLICANS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
