<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Jordan's Long Road To the Free-Trade Club</title>
    <meta content="21WORL$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201264"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE BUSINESS WORLD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Trade Organization</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Foreign Investments</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Jordan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Middle East</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Egypt</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Saudi Arabia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Kuwait</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">United Arab Emirates</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Abdullah Ii (King)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/World Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Jordan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Kuwait</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Saudi Arabia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Arab Emirates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Egypt</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/United Arab Emirates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Kuwait</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Saudi Arabia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Egypt</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Jordan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Investments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000521T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E2DA123AF932A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1372" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Jordan's Long Road To the Free-Trade Club</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM A. ORME Jr.</byline>
      <dateline>AMMAN, Jordan</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jordan's new king, Abdullah II, has made economic growth his focus and set course to attract quick influx of foreign capital through privatization sales and high-technology industry development; King Abdullah realized that Jordan would have to accept strict adherence to international trade rules to achieve goal; in April, Jordan joined World Trade Organization as group's 136th member but only its seventh Arab member; Egypt, United Arab Emirates and several North African countries are members, bu many of Jordan's trading partners, including Iraq, Saudi Arabia and Kuwait, are not; photos, graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MOHAMMED A. HALAIQAH'S trip to Seattle last November was to have been the culmination of his career. As Jordan's most experienced trade negotiator, he had spent five years arduously preparing for his country's entry into the World Trade Organization.</p>
        <p>After a thorough and painful overhaul of its tariffs and investment rules, putting domestic industries like pharmaceuticals at risk, Jordan was finally poised to become the W.T.O.'s next full member. As the only country scheduled to join the group at its Seattle summit meeting, it hoped to attract worldwide publicity -- and American investment in the high-technology industries it sees as the key to its future.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MOHAMMED A. HALAIQAH'S trip to Seattle last November was to have been the culmination of his career. As Jordan's most experienced trade negotiator, he had spent five years arduously preparing for his country's entry into the World Trade Organization.</p>
        <p>After a thorough and painful overhaul of its tariffs and investment rules, putting domestic industries like pharmaceuticals at risk, Jordan was finally poised to become the W.T.O.'s next full member. As the only country scheduled to join the group at its Seattle summit meeting, it hoped to attract worldwide publicity -- and American investment in the high-technology industries it sees as the key to its future.</p>
        <p>It wasn't to be. Mr. Halaiqah (pronounced ha-LYE-kah) was stunned to find himself trapped in a hotel lobby as the police fought protesters with tear gas and rubber bullets.</p>
        <p>''We were expecting something, but we didn't expect it to be so fierce,'' he said. ''We were literally besieged in the hotel.''</p>
        <p>The chaos outside and policy clashes inside the meeting forced Jordan off the suddenly truncated Seattle agenda.</p>
        <p>''Waiting for that big moment, we felt that Jordan was the victim of the contradictory interests of these different groups,'' said Mr. Halaiqah, now Jordan's minister of industry and trade.</p>
        <p>Last month, at its Geneva headquarters, the W.T.O. ratified Jordan's entry, making it the 136th member and just the seventh Arab state to join. While Egypt, the United Arab Emirates and several North African nations are members, many Jordanian trading partners, including Iraq, Saudi Arabia, Syria and Kuwait, are not.</p>
        <p>Jordan won some important concessions: Agricultural subsidies can be maintained at their current high level for a 10-year transition period, and majority ownership of retailers is still reserved for local investors.</p>
        <p>But most barriers to foreign investments  and products must be phased out, exposing many Jordanian companies to international competition for the first time. For an economy that still depends on potash, used in fertilizer and chemicals, from the Dead Sea for the bulk of its export income, exploiting the  opportunities of W.T.O. membership will be a challenge.</p>
        <p>W.T.O. membership was granted almost a year after Jordan's new king, Abdullah II, summoned Mr. Halaiqah for a briefing on the effort to join the W.T.O. King Hussein, Abdullah's father, had died two months earlier, and the new monarch was determined to make economic growth his focus.</p>
        <p>The king was convinced that Jordan needed to open up quickly. Per capita income had been declining. The Persian Gulf war in 1991 disrupted the flow of money sent home by Jordanians living and working in the gulf states, and sanctions against Iraq -- Jordan's biggest trading partner -- reduced trade to a trickle.</p>
        <p>As the king saw it, Jordan's only alternative -- a quick foreign capital influx from privatization sales and high-technology industrial development -- would require strict adherence to international trade rules.</p>
        <p>Mr. Halaiqah told King Abdullah during their April 1999 meeting that after more than four years of talks, Jordan was still far from complying with W.T.O. demands. After the Seattle assembly, he warned, the organization would begin a new round of global trade liberalization, raising membership hurdles higher.</p>
        <p>Another reason to move quickly: ''There was a lot of sympathy for Jordan after the death of His Majesty King Hussein, and I thought that we should take advantage of that,'' Mr. Halaiqah said.</p>
        <p>So King Abdullah gave Mr. Halaiqah an ambitious order: Get Jordan into the W.T.O.  in time for Seattle. For his part, the young king promised to ram a set of new trade and investment laws through the balky legislature. They had only six months.</p>
        <p>As Jordanian officials concede, it would have been hard to find a country that was a less likely candidate for such a rapid turnaround. Fuzzy law and lax enforcement had made Jordan a capital of counterfeiting and patent piracy. Software, books, videos, cassette tapes -- all were produced and sold  without copyright permission or royalty payments, often for export to neighbors. Media and computer industry lobbies in Washington and Brussels put Jordan near the top of their lists of intellectual property violators. Governments friendly to Jordan warned that without drastic changes, W.T.O. entry would not even be considered.</p>
        <p>Most problematic were prescription drugs. By estimates of Jordan's own pharmaceutical industry, at least 15 percent of its patented drug output was manufactured without the patent holders' consent. Foreign analysts said the proportion was far higher. American drug companies calculated that Jordanian piracy cost them $25 million to $50 million a year.</p>
        <p>''The pharmaceutical companies here were living in cuckoo-land, thinking that you could keep on stealing and stay in business,'' said Bassem I. Awadallah, the chief economic adviser to King Abdullah.</p>
        <p>BUT with more than 4,000 employees and $140 million in export sales, the drug companies were one of this small economy's few growing sources of skilled jobs and foreign currency. Mazen S. Darwazah, the president of the Jordanian Association of Pharmaceuticals Manufacturers, says few of these companies are prepared to compete under W.T.O. rules, which make patent infringement grounds for costly trade sanctions. ''Half of them will close down, and the families of 2,000 breadwinners will be out on the street,'' he predicted.</p>
        <p>Yet as Mr. Darwazah acknowledged, his own company, Hikma Pharmaceuticals, is a potential model. Specializing in generic drugs on which the patents have expired, and with modern production facilities, Hikma exports to 30 countries from plants in sites including Eatontown, N.J.</p>
        <p>''We have recognized that in order for us to survive, we need a niche,'' he said. ''The world is run by the big corporations, whether we like it or not.''</p>
        <p>But few companies have the capital or technological sophistication to manage this transition, he said. And many Jordanians cannot afford imported medicines. ''If we make Jordan a safe haven for intellectual property rights, we know that health care prices will rise dramatically,'' Mr. Darwazah said.</p>
        <p>A few months ago, Jordan became one of the few Middle Eastern nations to be removed from the United States Commerce Department's watch lists of intellectual property violators. Its new patent protections are lauded by former critics in the computer and pharmaceutical industries. In  March, dozens of American executives traveled to a Dead Sea resort to hear King Abdullah itemize incentives for software and telecommunications investors. Jordan offers high-technology companies a significant but underemployed pool of English-speaking engineers and technicians.</p>
        <p>With W.T.O. membership in hand, Jordan is now negotiating free-trade pacts with Europe, having already reached agreements with other Arab states. Jordan's main goal now is a free-trade deal with the United States, an advantage already enjoyed by Israel and the Palestinian Authority.</p>
        <p>Jordanian officials know from their Seattle experience that any free-trade proposal will meet resistance. Mr. Halaiqah is still irked by the contentions of American  demonstrators that they were defending  poor countries like his against the predations of the global trading system -- a system Jordan had labored to join.</p>
        <p>''I understand the fears of environmentalists, of labor, but they should do their homework,'' he said. ''No country has benefited more from international trade than the United States. These people cannot speak on behalf of the world, and certainly not on behalf of developing countries.''</p>
        <p>THE BUSINESS WORLD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
