<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Getting the Express Buses Back Into the Fast Lane</title>
    <meta content="21BUS.$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201267"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: STATEN ISLAND UP CLOSE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Buses</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Delays (Transportation)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Commuting</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'grady, Jim</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gentile, Vincent</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Delays (Transportation)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Buses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Commuting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transportation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000521T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E1DA123AF932A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="567" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Getting the Express Buses Back Into the Fast Lane</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JIM O'GRADY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">O'grady, Jim</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York State Sen Vincent Gentile supports recent proposal by Tri-State Transportation Campaign to unclog Gowanus Expressway and Staten Island Expressway by building 'guided busways' to move express buses on railroad-like tracks down highway medians; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Express bus service to Manhattan is speeding up. Ridership increased 60 percent citywide in the last two years, mostly on trips to and from Staten Island.</p>
        <p>But the rate of travel of these buses is slowing down. This is especially true in the high-occupancy-vehicle lanes of the Gowanus Expressway, which are set aside for express buses and cars carrying two or more passengers but which sometimes barely move faster than the regular rush-hour crawl. The express buses also creep along the Staten Island Expressway, which has no HOV lanes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Express bus service to Manhattan is speeding up. Ridership increased 60 percent citywide in the last two years, mostly on trips to and from Staten Island.</p>
        <p>But the rate of travel of these buses is slowing down. This is especially true in the high-occupancy-vehicle lanes of the Gowanus Expressway, which are set aside for express buses and cars carrying two or more passengers but which sometimes barely move faster than the regular rush-hour crawl. The express buses also creep along the Staten Island Expressway, which has no HOV lanes.</p>
        <p>If as a bus rider, ''I saw that, I would say, 'What's the point of being on this bus?' '' said State Senator Vincent Gentile, whose district covers neighborhoods in the boroughs on both sides of the Verrazano-Narrows Bridge, which links the two roads. As a result, he said, he supports a recent proposal by the Tri-State Transportation Campaign, an influential environmental group, to try a novel idea to unclog the expressways.</p>
        <p>The group says the State Department of Transportation should build a ''guided busway'' to move buses on railroad-like tracks down highway medians. A spokeswoman for the group, Kristen Fountain, said that even regular city buses could carry equipment that attached them to the tracks, allowing drivers to control speed without steering. The idea recalls the way trolleys moved relatively freely and widely spaced down the middle of crowded city streets.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gentile, who called himself a champion of the idea, said the most likely place to first try a guided busway would be the median of the Staten Island Expressway.</p>
        <p>The reason for the choice is that the state agency is already planning to put two new lanes on the median of that expressway. The agency is also preparing a report for late fall on how to use the new lanes, said Alex Dudley, an agency spokesman.</p>
        <p>''There is a strong possibility,'' he added, ''that the report will recommend making bus-only lanes in both directions.''</p>
        <p>As for the guided-busway idea, Mr. Dudley said that sensors that were embedded in the roadway and that interacted with buses -- a new technology -- could do the same thing as a track at less expense. That sounds good to Mr. Gentile. ''If that's what they want to do,'' he said, ''I support it 100 percent.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Fountain said tracks might be better than sensors because they would keep cars away from the buses. A 1999 study by Mr. Dudley's agency, for example, reported that cars made up 80 percent of the traffic in the Gowanus HOV lanes while carrying only 15 percent of the passengers. ''Cars are the problem,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dudley worried that displacing cars from lanes used only by buses might paralyze the other traffic lanes. But Ms. Fountain and Mr. Gentile said that reliable express bus service would draw commuters from their cars.</p>
        <p>''Once people see that,'' Mr. Gentile said, ''you're going to have a revolution in the way people get to work.''</p>
        <p>JIM O'GRADY</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: STATEN ISLAND UP CLOSE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
