<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="21FSUM$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201380"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000521T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEEDF113AF932A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="770" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>3-16</p>
        <p>Broad Chinese Support For Trade Normalization  The vast majority of influential Chinese agree with the Clinton administration's position that Congress should vote for normal trade relations with China because it would strengthen reformist forces there and ensure its participation in the World Trade Organization.</p>
        <p>1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>3-16</p>
        <p>Broad Chinese Support For Trade Normalization  The vast majority of influential Chinese agree with the Clinton administration's position that Congress should vote for normal trade relations with China because it would strengthen reformist forces there and ensure its participation in the World Trade Organization.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Response to Taiwan Leader  Only two hours after Taiwan's new president Chen Shui-bian made his inaugural address, authorities in Beijing released a surprisingly temperate response, charging him with a lack of sincerity but not repeating the dire threats and invective of recent weeks.</p>
        <p>16</p>
        <p>Challenges for Peru President  Now that his opponent in the runoff presidential election has dropped out of the race, President of Peru Alberto K. Fujimori faces the possibility of unending protest marches, criticism from Washington and other foreign capitals, and perhaps even economic sanctions.</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>South African to Visit U.S.  President Thabo Mbeki of South Africa, after provoking controversy among AIDS researchers around the world, is embarking on his first state visit to the United States since succeeding Nelson Mandela as president last year, and activists and those who treat AIDS are pondering how to greet him.</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>A Son for the Blairs  Cherie Blair, the wife of Prime Minister Tony Blair, gave birth to a baby boy. Hours later mother, father and son left the London hospital for a quiet weekend at 10 Downing Street. The fourth child for the Blairs, Leo, is the first baby born to a serving prime minister in 152 years.</p>
        <p>8</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>20-33</p>
        <p>Death Penalty's Hiatus Likely to Go On in Illinois  Gov. George Ryan of Illinois, who has imposed a moratorium on executions in the state, says he would need a ''100 percent guarantee'' against any mistaken convictions before he would restore the death penalty.</p>
        <p>20</p>
        <p>Quiet Leadership in Washington  If all continues to go well, the nation's capital will regain home-rule prerogatives, confirming the stewardship of Mayor Anthony A. Williams, an unlikely politician as bland in his style as the paint on the municipal walls.</p>
        <p>20</p>
        <p>Unused Insurance Aid for Poor  Hundreds of millions of dollars set aside by the federal government to help provide health insurance to poor people remains unused because states have not claimed the money, the Department of Health and Human Services has found.</p>
        <p>22</p>
        <p>Study to Monitor Cancer Care  Responding to a call to improve cancer care, a leading cancer organization says it will work with other groups to develop a national system to monitor how well each cancer patient is treated.</p>
        <p>22</p>
        <p>1981 Murder Case Revived  Federal prosecutors in Los Angeles have unveiled an indictment that alleges that a former nightclub mogul, his bodyguard and a pornography actor killed four people nearly two decades ago.</p>
        <p>33</p>
        <p>N.R.A. to Battle Gore  The National Rifle Association has declared political war on Vice President Al Gore, using speeches at its convention in Charlotte, N.C., to accuse Mr. Gore of trying to ''disarm the country'' and to urge gun owners to work against his election.</p>
        <p>28</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>35-42</p>
        <p>Congressman Opens Race With Attack on Mr. Clinton  Representative Rick A. Lazio of Long Island roared into the race for senator from New York, attacking Hillary Rodham Clinton as a ''far left'' candidate who has ''no real rationale for serving here other than as a steppingstone to some other position.''</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>New York Feels Ad Strike  A strike of 135,000 members of the Screen Actors Guild and the American Federation of Television and Radio Artists against the advertising industry is making itself felt in New York. The central issue the in strike is how to pay actors for their work in commercials. About one-third of all national advertising is produced in New York, and the metropolitan region is home to about 55,000 members of the unions.</p>
        <p>37</p>
        <p>Fresh Air Fund</p>
        <p>38</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>43-44</p>
        <p>Jean-Pierre Rampal  The Frenchman who popularized the flute as a solo instrument became one of classical music's brightest stars. He was 78.</p>
        <p>44</p>
        <p>Robert Burr  A stage actor who played many of Shakespeare's most famous roles, he was 78.</p>
        <p>44</p>
        <p>Chess</p>
        <p>43</p>
        <p>Weather</p>
        <p>45</p>
        <p>Cong. Vote</p>
        <p>38</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
