<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bad Traffic Is a No-Brainer For Bronx Science Officials</title>
    <meta content="21TRAF" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201256"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: BEDFORD PARK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Traffic Signals and Signs</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blumenstein, Stanley</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Critchell, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Signs and Symbols</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Traffic Signals and Signs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000521T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE2DB123AF932A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="500" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bad Traffic Is a No-Brainer For Bronx Science Officials</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID CRITCHELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Critchell, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York City Transportation Department, heeding complaints from Bronx High School of Science officials and parents about dangers from speeding traffic and local construction, approves request for traffic light and installs stop sign; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Parents and school officials at the Bronx High School of Science are concerned that the dangers from  speeding traffic and construction on 205th Street between Goulden and Paul Avenues -- a stretch where  several accidents have occurred recently -- will only become worse if nothing is done.</p>
        <p>Four students from Bronx Science have been hit by passing cars in three accidents in the current academic year, school officials said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Parents and school officials at the Bronx High School of Science are concerned that the dangers from  speeding traffic and construction on 205th Street between Goulden and Paul Avenues -- a stretch where  several accidents have occurred recently -- will only become worse if nothing is done.</p>
        <p>Four students from Bronx Science have been hit by passing cars in three accidents in the current academic year, school officials said.</p>
        <p>Though no students were killed or seriously hurt in those accidents, parents and school officials warned that it was only a matter of time before that happened.</p>
        <p>According to Stanley Blumenstein, the principal, buses line the north side of 205th Street to pick up many of the 2,700 students at the end of the day. The buses block the visibility of passing cars, which then have little time to react when students emerge from behind or between the buses.</p>
        <p>Nearby construction work on two bridges that span subway yards east of the school has created traffic bottlenecks on 205th Street and further aggravated the dangers, school officials said. The construction began two years ago, and is expected to be completed in a year, city officials said.</p>
        <p>The problem is also made worse by the considerable pedestrian traffic from nearby Herbert H. Lehman College and along the Jerome Reservoir, which is adjacent to Goulden Avenue.</p>
        <p>''This is a disaster waiting to happen, and there's a lot that could be done to avoid it,'' said Mr. Blumenstein, who has asked the city to place school zone signs and crossing guards at the school during morning and afternoon hours.</p>
        <p>''This is an issue that cannot be put on the back burner,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But a partial solution may be near, said June Eisland, the local councilwoman. The city's Department of Transportation has approved her request for a traffic light at 205th Street and Goulden Avenue. Now, that intersection has one stop sign, on 205th Street.</p>
        <p>''Quite frankly, Goulden Avenue has been a thoroughfare, and a traffic light will be a major step in protecting the safety of the students and the other pedestrians,'' Ms. Eisland said.</p>
        <p>Michelle Medley, a spokeswoman for the Transportation Department, said the light would be installed in October. But Mr. Blumenstein and Ms. Eisland said that they would like to see the traffic light installed in September, for the start of the school year.</p>
        <p>''You can't put a price on the safety of these children,'' Mr. Blumenstein said.</p>
        <p>DAVID CRITCHELL</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: BEDFORD PARK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
