<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Using Oceans to Promote Riverhead</title>
    <meta content="21AQUA$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201166"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Aquariums</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Riverhead (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Atlantis Marine World (Riverhead, Ny)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tagliaferro, Linda</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Aquariums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000521T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DEFD9153AF932A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1182" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Using Oceans to Promote Riverhead</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LINDA TAGLIAFERRO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tagliaferro, Linda</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Atlantis Marine World, new aquarium and research facility in Riverhead, Long Island, slated to open June 15, whose theme is lost continent of Atlantis; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE ruins and rubble of an entire city lay strewn across East Main Street in Riverhead, but officials seemed unconcerned. On the contrary, they were delighted: the broken columns and splintered walls were part of the Atlantis Marine World, a new aquarium and research facility whose theme is the fabled lost continent of Atlantis. The official opening is scheduled for June 15.</p>
        <p>Built on a 3.2-acre site in downtown Riverhead, the 42,000-square-foot aquarium has more than 80 exhibits, including a 120,000-gallon tank where nurse sharks, white tips, browns and tiger sharks swim together.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE ruins and rubble of an entire city lay strewn across East Main Street in Riverhead, but officials seemed unconcerned. On the contrary, they were delighted: the broken columns and splintered walls were part of the Atlantis Marine World, a new aquarium and research facility whose theme is the fabled lost continent of Atlantis. The official opening is scheduled for June 15.</p>
        <p>Built on a 3.2-acre site in downtown Riverhead, the 42,000-square-foot aquarium has more than 80 exhibits, including a 120,000-gallon tank where nurse sharks, white tips, browns and tiger sharks swim together.</p>
        <p>Entering through a columned facade, visitors are first surrounded by an ample space with a Long Island environment. An artificial North Shore bluff and a South Shore dune are divided by a bridge and frame this opening exhibit. As visitors walk across the wooden planks, a 22-foot waterfall comes into sight, and fish swim below.</p>
        <p>Then, with a backdrop of Atlantean columns, visitors enter what appear to be the ruins of an underwater city. Overhead, a mural by Eric Henn depicts a giant squid in combat with a sperm whale. Columns in the shape of seahorses intersperse fissured stone walls that house tanks brimming with sea creatures.</p>
        <p>Numerous tanks contain denizens of Long Island's waters. Joseph Yaiullo, the curator, explained: ''In the summer, the water temperature in Long Island is 70 to 80 degrees, and in wintertime, it's 35 to 40 degrees. There aren't many places in the world with that dynamic a range, so we have a really diverse marine environment, and we're showing much of that in our aquarium.''</p>
        <p>He said, for example, that tropical fish can be found off Long Island in the summer because they travel with the Gulf Stream from Florida.</p>
        <p>Even more exotic offerings are red-bellied Amazonian piranhas and yellow, blue or green Lake Malawi cichlids from Africa. An octopus gracefully drifts inside a cylindrical tank built into one of the columns, and several ''touch tanks'' offer visitors the opportunity to get personal with horseshoe crabs, starfish and even stingrays.</p>
        <p>The highlight is the 12-foot high, 40-foot wide shark tank, with six large windows that offer underwater views of its residents. Volunteer divers will swim with the sharks on a regular basis, and a communication system lets them speak with visitors.</p>
        <p>The Riverhead project had several false starts. Michael Davidson, director of marketing for the aquarium, said: ''In the early 1990's, Riverhead officials were looking for a project to help revitalize their downtown area. They identified a potential site and purchased it.''</p>
        <p>Then officials invited the Okeanos Foundation, which ran marine rescue, rehabilitation and release programs on Long Island, to move its operations from Hampton Bays to Riverhead and build an aquarium. ''The not-for-profit group struggled mightily to raise the money,'' Mr. Davidson explained, ''but ultimately went out of business.''</p>
        <p>In 1996 the Riverhead Foundation for Marine Research and Preservation took over the mission of the Okeanos Foundation, also trying to raise funds for an aquarium and also failing. But town officials were not willing to give up on their dream, and they sought new proposals.</p>
        <p>Jim Bissett, owner of the Bissett nursery in Holtsville, had been involved with the Okeanos Foundation and the Riverhead Foundation, and together with Joe Petrocelli, owner of J. Petrocelli Contracting in Ronkonkoma, submitted a project.</p>
        <p>One reason their proposal was accepted, Mr. Davidson explained, was the fact that the aquarium will house the Riverhead Foundation, giving it 8,000 square feet. ''We're making an outright grant of $90,000 per year to them, as well as trying to raise money for them through sponsorships of all our exhibits,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The town was also receptive to Mr. Bissett's and Mr. Petrocelli's plan to build the aquarium as a profit-making venture.</p>
        <p>Construction began in May 1999, but plans for the development started in 1997. At that time, Mr. Bissett asked Mr. Yaiullo, a marine scientist and a resident of Aquebogue, to become the curator. Mr. Yaiullo worked as senior aquarist at the New York Aquarium in Brooklyn for eight years before leaving for the Long Island venture.</p>
        <p>Mr. Yaiullo used his expertise in working with coral reefs to develop a live exhibit in Riverhead. He had previously set up a living coral reef tank at the New York Aquarium, but on a considerably smaller scale. ''That tank was about 1,400 gallons, but our tank at Atlantis Marine World will be 16,000 gallons,'' Mr. Yaiullo said.</p>
        <p>The Riverhead reef grew for over a year in Mr. Yaiullo's basement. ''It's a colony of animals, and you work with them as you would with plants,'' he explained. ''You break off a colony from propagated coral reefs from places like Indonesia and Palau, transplant it, and the colony begins to grow by reproducing asexually. It keeps making clones of itself.''</p>
        <p>To keep the reef alive and growing, spectrally correct lighting was installed to duplicate sunlight, and nutritional supplements are regularly added to the water. ''It's initially labor intensive,'' Mr. Yaiullo said, ''but once the reef settles in, it becomes almost self-sufficient.''</p>
        <p>Although the aquarium is directed at entertainment, it also promises to educate. ''Because this is a privately funded aquarium,'' Mr. Davidson said, ''there have been questions about how committed we are to education, so we partnered with Cornell Cooperative Extension Marine Division, and they are running all of our educational programs.''</p>
        <p>Plans for the future include a 1,000-seat stadium with dolphin shows and a tropical rain forest exhibit where visitors can snorkel in an artificial lagoon. The projected date for Phase II is 2002. Phase III additions could be in place by 2004.</p>
        <p>The aquarium is expected to have a positive effect on Riverhead's economy. ''There is a direct impact of about $5 million to $6 million dollars,'' Mr. Davidson said, ''and indirectly there are the salaries, the materials we are buying, the power we are using and more.''</p>
        <p>''A number of years ago, it was the dream of Joseph Janoski, a former supervisor for the town, to turn Riverhead into the Mystic of Long Island,'' he said, ''and we think that the opening of the aquarium is going to make it happen.''</p>
        <p>Atlantis Marine World, at 469 East Main Street in Riverhead, is open every day, except for Christmas. Summer hours are 9 a.m. to 8 p.m. except Wednesday, when the closing hour is 6 p.m. From Sept. 5 to May 1, closing is 6 p.m. Admission is $11.50 plus tax for adults, $10 plus tax for those 62 and over, $9 plus tax for children 3 to 11. Children 2 and under are free.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
