<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On Broadway, an Awning Gap</title>
    <meta content="21APOS$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201103"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="POSTINGS: DEBATE OVER HAUGHWOUT BUILDING IN SOHO, THE PARTHENON OF NEW YORK'S IRON AGE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Haughwout Building (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Awnings</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Corcoran Group</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dunlap, David W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000521T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E2DF143AF932A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="508" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On Broadway, an Awning Gap</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID W. DUNLAP</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dunlap, David W</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Plan by Corcoran Group to install awnings over second and third floor windows of its offices in landmark Haughwout Building in SoHo is encountering neighborhood resistance; photos (Postings column) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''Desecrate'' was the word used by a community group known as the SoHo Alliance to describe the suggestion that awnings might be installed in the sumptuously detailed upper windows of the cast-iron Haughwout Building, celebrated as the Parthenon of New York's iron age.</p>
        <p>But there is a historical paradox that owners and tenants are learning to use to commercial advantage: some landmark buildings, Haughwout included, once had more architectural appendages and appurtenances than they do today. For by-gone authenticity, this argument goes, why not bring back an awning here or a marquee there? (Of course, it will happen to carry the name of the business behind it.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''Desecrate'' was the word used by a community group known as the SoHo Alliance to describe the suggestion that awnings might be installed in the sumptuously detailed upper windows of the cast-iron Haughwout Building, celebrated as the Parthenon of New York's iron age.</p>
        <p>But there is a historical paradox that owners and tenants are learning to use to commercial advantage: some landmark buildings, Haughwout included, once had more architectural appendages and appurtenances than they do today. For by-gone authenticity, this argument goes, why not bring back an awning here or a marquee there? (Of course, it will happen to carry the name of the business behind it.)</p>
        <p>''If you're sticking with what's historically appropriate for a building, you'd have awnings,'' said Pamela Liebman, chief executive of the Corcoran Group, which plans to open a SoHo office next month on two floors of the Haughwout Building, at Broadway and Broome Street.</p>
        <p>Corcoran proposed navy blue awnings over its second-  and third-floor windows, with its name in white on the awning skirts. However, having run into opposition from community leaders and preservationists and an objection from the Landmarks Preservation Commission, Corcoran is rethinking its plan.</p>
        <p>''We're really looking forward to becoming an active part of the SoHo community,'' Ms. Liebman said, ''which is why it's very important to work out with Landmarks what would be an appropriate presentation for the outside.''</p>
        <p>Last month, the commission approved a renovation of the Cartier store at Fifth Avenue and 52nd Street that includes awnings in the upper floors. It has also approved a plan to recreate the marquee at the Paramount Building, at Broadway and 43rd Street, over the entrance of what is now the World Wrestling Federation store and restaurant.</p>
        <p>Still, the Haughwout Building (some say HOW-itt, others HOW-wowt) may be a special case. Evoking the rhythmic, deeply sculptural facade of the the 16th-century Marciana Library in Venice by Jacopo Sansovino, the former china and silver store was completed in 1857 to designs by John P. Gaynor.</p>
        <p>''There are basic proportions to beauty,'' said Carl Rosenstein, a member of the landmarks committee of the SoHo Alliance. ''Palladian buildings do not have awnings on them. We see the application purely as one for commercial gain, as a way to advertise the Corcoran name.''</p>
        <p>Moreover, said Peg Breen, president of the New York Landmarks Conservancy, the appearance of awnings on two of the middle floors ''would look like mushroom growth out of a beautiful tree trunk.''</p>
        <p>DAVID W. DUNLAP</p>
        <p>POSTINGS: DEBATE OVER HAUGHWOUT BUILDING IN SOHO, THE PARTHENON OF NEW YORK'S IRON AGE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
