<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>They Couldn't Resist: Oh, One Last Thing . . .</title>
    <meta content="21WORD$26" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201287"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="WORD FOR WORD/POISON-PEN WILLS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wills and Estates</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stryker, Jeff</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wills and Estates</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000521T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E4DB133AF932A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1155" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>They Couldn't Resist: Oh, One Last Thing . . .</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JEFF STRYKER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stryker, Jeff</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Word for Word column excerpts spiteful passages from some memorable wills; drawing (M)2</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DEATH puts a pretty effective end to most human endeavors. But it will no longer stop us from e-mailing our friends and relatives, thanks to a new Web site, www.FinalThoughts.com. The site archives e-mail messages to be dispatched when subscribers shuffle off their mortal coils. A ''guardian angel'' notifies FinalThoughts.com of the subscriber's demise; the intended recipients receive e-mail notes to visit the Web site for a message.</p>
        <p>Given the backgrounds available for subscribers' messages -- clouds, angels, flowers or hearts -- it isn't surprising that the founder of FinalThoughts, Todd Krim, says, ''I hope no one uses the site for any spiteful or vindictive messages.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DEATH puts a pretty effective end to most human endeavors. But it will no longer stop us from e-mailing our friends and relatives, thanks to a new Web site, www.FinalThoughts.com. The site archives e-mail messages to be dispatched when subscribers shuffle off their mortal coils. A ''guardian angel'' notifies FinalThoughts.com of the subscriber's demise; the intended recipients receive e-mail notes to visit the Web site for a message.</p>
        <p>Given the backgrounds available for subscribers' messages -- clouds, angels, flowers or hearts -- it isn't surprising that the founder of FinalThoughts, Todd Krim, says, ''I hope no one uses the site for any spiteful or vindictive messages.''</p>
        <p>Hmmm. If the following excerpts from memorable wills are any guide, Mr. Krim may want to consider some other backgrounds -- daggers, perhaps -- when offering the chance to get in a final zinger from beyond the grave.</p>
        <p>JEFF STRYKER</p>
        <p>Take That</p>
        <p>I give nothing to my Lord Saye, and I do make him this legacy willingly, because I know that he will faithfully distribute it unto the poor.</p>
        <p>I give to the Lieutenant-General Cromwell one of my words . . . which he must want, seeing that he hath never kept any of his own.</p>
        <p>-- Philip, fifth Earl of Pembroke, 17th century</p>
        <p>To Sir Robert Walpole I leave my political opinions, never doubting he can well turn them into cash, who has always found such an excellent market in which to change his own.</p>
        <p>My cast-off habit of swearing oaths I give to Sir Leopold D., in consideration that no oaths have ever been able to bind him yet.</p>
        <p>-- Edward Wortley Montagu, 1716</p>
        <p>Family Matters</p>
        <p>Seeing that I had the misfortune to be married to the aforesaid Elizabeth, who, ever since our union, has tormented me in every possible way; that not content with making game of all my remonstrances, she has done all she could to render my life miserable; that Heaven seems to have sent her into the world solely to drive me out of it; that the strength of Samson, the genius of Homer, the prudence of Augustus, the skill of Pyrrhus, the patience of Job, the philosophy of Socrates, the subtlety of Hannibal, the vigilance of Hermogenes, would not suffice to subdue the perversity of her character . . . weighing seriously all these considerations . . . I bequeath, to my said wife Elizabeth, the sum of one shilling.</p>
        <p>-- John George, 1791</p>
        <p>To the worst of women, Claude Charlotte de Grammont, unfortunately my wife, guilty as she is of all crimes, I leave five-and-forty brass halfpence, which will buy a pullet for her supper. A better gift than her father can make her; for I have known when, having not the money, neither had he the credit for such a purchase; he being the worst of men, and his wife being the worst of women. . . . Had I ever known their characters I had never married their daughter, and made myself unhappy.</p>
        <p>-- Henry, Earl of Stafford, 17th century</p>
        <p>I leave my silver tankard to the eldest son of Old John, as the representative of the family. I would have left it to Old John himself, but he would melt it down and make temperance medals and that would be a  sacrilege. . . .</p>
        <p>I leave Parson Chavasse (Maggy's husband) the snuff box I got from the Sarnia Militia, as a small token of gratitude for the service he has done my family in taking a sister that no man of taste would have taken.</p>
        <p>-- William Dunlop, Canada, 1842</p>
        <p>To my monkey, my dear and amusing Jacko, [I leave] the sum of 10 pounds sterling per annum. . . . To my faithful dog Shock, and my well-beloved cat Tibb, a pension of 5 pounds sterling. . . . On the death of all three the sum appropriated to this purpose shall become the property of my daughter Gertrude, to whom I give this preference among my children, because of the large family she has and the difficulty she finds in bringing them up.</p>
        <p>-- Mr. Garland, 1828</p>
        <p>Before anything else is to be done 50 cents [is] to be paid to my son-in-law to enable him to buy for himself a good stout rope with which to hang himself, and thus rid mankind of one of the most infamous scoundrels that ever roamed this broad land or dwelt outside of a penitentiary.</p>
        <p>-- Garvey B. White, 1908</p>
        <p>Final Disposal</p>
        <p>[I want to be] composited for a fertiliser to contribute to the growth of an American elm, to be planted in some rural thoroughfare, that the weary wayfarer may rest, and innocent children may play beneath its umbrageous branches rendered luxuriant by my remains.</p>
        <p>-- S. Sanborn, 1871</p>
        <p>My head [is] to be separated from my body immediately after my death; the latter to be buried in a grave; the former, duly macerated and prepared, to be brought to the theater where I have served all my life, and to be employed to represent the skull of Yorick in the play ''Hamlet.''</p>
        <p>-- John Reed, gas lighter at the Walnut Street Theater in Philadelphia for 44 years,  in a possibly apocryphal 19th-century will</p>
        <p>Lawyers</p>
        <p>To employ an attorney I ne'er was  inclined.</p>
        <p>They are pests to society, sharks of mankind.</p>
        <p>To avoid that base tribe my own will I now draw,</p>
        <p>May I ever escape coming under their paw.</p>
        <p>-- William Ruffell, England, 1803</p>
        <p>I hereby direct my executor to lay out five guineas in purchase of a picture of the viper biting the benevolent hand of the person who saved him from perishing in the snow. . . . and in memory of me, present it to Edward Bearcroft, Esq., a King's Counsel, whereby he may have frequent opportunities for contemplating on it.</p>
        <p>This I direct to be presented to him in lieu of a legacy of 3,000 pounds which I had, by a former will, now revoked and burnt, left him.</p>
        <p>-- John Aylett, 1781</p>
        <p>I never liked lawyers as a class and to keep away from them and steer clear of their inveigling schemes and grasping machination -- ever an active ingredient in their diabolical profession -- has been my constant life-long effort. . . .</p>
        <p>The incontrovertible facts in my case are these -- there never was a better, all-round individual ever set foot upon the regions of this broad state than myself.</p>
        <p>-- Joseph H. Melchoir, Seattle, circa 1900</p>
        <p>Sources: ''Last Will and Testament,'' by Frank Thomas (St. Martin's, 1972); ''The Last Caprice,'' by Robert S. Menchin (Simon &amp; Schuster, 1963); ''Humor in or of Wills (Vanderbilt Law Review, 1958); and ''Some Jolly Testators'' (Temple Law Quarterly, 1934).</p>
        <p>WORD FOR WORD/POISON-PEN WILLS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
