<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From Political Peak, Giuliani Journeys to a Personal Crisis</title>
    <meta content="21RECO$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201384"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE RACE FOR SENATE: BOWING OUT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hanover, Donna</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barry, Dan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kershaw, Sarah</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000521T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E6DE113AF932A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2383" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From Political Peak, Giuliani Journeys to a Personal Crisis</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAN BARRY with SARAH KERSHAW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kershaw, Sarah; Barry, Dan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mayor Rudolph W Giuliani confronts personal crises with his health and family and the abandonment of a campaign for Senate only months after riding crest of his political career; friends and advisers say events have revealed more clearly qualities in Giuliani that were always there: warmth, conviviality and a spiritual and reflective nature; photo (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The year began with Rudolph W. Giuliani on top and in charge. There he was, powerful mayor of New York City, confident Republican in ascendance, ringing in 2000 for the glittering Times Square throng below and for millions watching across the world. The moment was his, just as the year promised to be.</p>
        <p>Now, less than five months later, the promises of the new year have been broken. And a very different Rudolph Giuliani has returned from his perch to ponder matters that transcend politics.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The year began with Rudolph W. Giuliani on top and in charge. There he was, powerful mayor of New York City, confident Republican in ascendance, ringing in 2000 for the glittering Times Square throng below and for millions watching across the world. The moment was his, just as the year promised to be.</p>
        <p>Now, less than five months later, the promises of the new year have been broken. And a very different Rudolph Giuliani has returned from his perch to ponder matters that transcend politics.</p>
        <p>On Friday, the mayor made a breathtaking political announcement to cap several recent revelations about his health and his life. With less than two weeks until the Republican State Convention, he was dropping out of the race against Hillary Rodham Clinton for the United States Senate. He had decided to focus instead on overcoming the prostate cancer that was diagnosed less than a month ago.</p>
        <p>''You realize you're not a superman,'' the 55-year-old mayor said, ''and you're just a human being.''</p>
        <p>The very public moment reflected the culmination of a series of private, often agonizing meetings that Mr. Giuliani has held with advisers from his distant and recent past: the friends from his adolescent days at Bishop Loughlin Memorial High School in Brooklyn, the aides he has known since entering the hurly-burly world of New York City politics, and, finally, the oncologists he now has no choice but to hear.</p>
        <p>The settings changed from day to day: his private office at City Hall one night, Gracie Mansion the next. The topics varied as well: what to pick from the various options for treatment, what to tell state Republicans waiting for his decision about the Senate race, what to do about his deteriorating marriage.</p>
        <p>One element never changed: the dynamic of those discussions. Mr. Giuliani would wonder aloud -- sometimes jokingly, sometimes somberly -- about the decisions before him, decisions he later said were the most difficult he had ever faced. And the friends and advisers would respond with their analyses, the wisest being always careful not to tell him what they thought he ought to do. By now they know better, several said. Nobody tells Rudy what to do.</p>
        <p>''The way it works is that anybody who would blurt out his bottom-line opinion would not be deemed by him to be worth consulting,'' one adviser said.</p>
        <p>These advisers -- almost entirely men -- have gone through this process many times before, but usually the issue before them was the city budget, or some other vexing political matter. Never before had they been a part of their friend's journey toward self-discovery.</p>
        <p>''He wasn't his feisty self on this one,'' one close adviser recalled. ''I think that at a time like this you feel very much alone. This was a guy all of a sudden alone, out there, and he started talking to people.''</p>
        <p>Msgr. Alan J. Placa, a friend of the mayor's for 40 years and vice chancellor of the Roman Catholic Diocese of Rockville Centre, on Long Island, agreed. ''All of a sudden, those three things came crashing down at once,'' he said. ''His health fails, his family life is shaken, he has to make a decision as to how he will relate to the body politic, to society. It's been a dramatically challenging time.''</p>
        <p>In the end, one adviser said, matters of health, of politics, of love and of leadership all came down to a single, elemental question: Who are you, Rudy?</p>
        <p>It is a question whose answer never before seemed in doubt. Even as he irritated state Republicans with his laid-back, undeclared candidacy, Mr. Giuliani seemed, at least in public, to be confidently marching toward an inevitable Election Day showdown with Mrs. Clinton. Signs of his enthusiasm for the campaign were everywhere; one Sunday in February, he appeared on five television programs to promote his mayoral record as evidence of his senatorial worth.</p>
        <p>One adviser said Mr. Giuliani's approach reflected a specific strategy: ''We really felt we were ahead, so why start a campaign earlier than you have to?''</p>
        <p>Another sensed in the mayor a subtle reluctance: ''I never quite saw the all-out lust for the office that I'd seen in the mayoral runs.''</p>
        <p>As mayor, Mr. Giuliani continued on with the style that has framed his seven-year tenure. Most famously, he released the minor arrest record of an unarmed black man who had been shot and killed by a police officer, then dismissed the victim as no altar boy. (In recent days, the mayor has expressed some regret for his handling of the matter.)</p>
        <p>All along, as the city was later to learn, the mayor's private life was in turmoil as well.</p>
        <p>For years, his marriage to Donna Hanover, a television reporter and actress, had cast a chill over Gracie Mansion; Ms. Hanover recently indicated that the mayor's close relationship to his ubiquitous communications director, Cristyne Lategano-Nicholas, had upset the marriage. In May 1999, Ms. Lategano-Nicholas left City Hall. That same month, the mayor and Ms. Hanover spent an evening dancing at a wedding reception at Gracie Mansion.</p>
        <p>Joannie Danielides, a spokeswoman for Ms. Hanover, said their dancing that night reflected a time of reconciliation. In the weeks that followed, she said, ''they had lots of private moments, family dinners, celebrating birthdays, barbecues.''</p>
        <p>At some point that spring, however, Mr. Giuliani met Judith Nathan, 45, a divorced pharmaceutical sales manager. Manos Zacharioudakis, a friend of Ms. Nathan's, recalled how, about that time, she proudly showed him a photograph of herself and her teenage daughter with the mayor, taken at a function where she told Mr. Zacharioudakis that she had met the mayor for the first time.</p>
        <p>By the summer, Mr. Giuliani was seeing Ms. Nathan more frequently: at Coopers Classic Cars and Cigar Bar, a bar in Midtown Manhattan where they watched Yankees games and sipped Diet Cokes; in Southampton, Long Island, where Ms. Nathan owns a condominium; even in City Hall. Ms. Nathan effectively became a member of the mayor's entourage; aides later said that she was alternately described as a member of the mayor's security detail and as a good friend of one of the mayor's aides who also lives on the Upper East Side.</p>
        <p>The level to which Ms. Hanover was aware of this relationship is unclear. Eleven days ago, she cryptically said the mayor ''chose another path'' last fall. But her spokeswoman, Ms. Danielides, said Ms. Hanover was not aware of Ms. Nathan until very recently.</p>
        <p>Through February, March and into early April, Mr. Giuliani deftly juggled the challenges of his public and private lives. He taunted Mrs. Clinton almost daily, but never delivered a speech laying out his vision for the Senate. And he felt confident enough to bring Ms. Nathan to public events, including the Inner Circle, an annual dinner attended by hundreds of reporters, politicians and consultants.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Ms. Hanover was signaling that a frost had returned to the mayoral mansion. In March she told a Daily News reporter that she would remain in New York if her husband was elected to the Senate, and answered a question regarding any regrets about living in Gracie Mansion by saying, ''Why don't we move on to something else?''</p>
        <p>In mid-April, Mr. Giuliani had an annual checkup, making sure that he was tested for prostate cancer, the disease that killed his father, Harold, in 1981. He later acknowledged that although the test was routine, it preyed on his mind, and made him think ''about what's important in life.''</p>
        <p>His life went on. He proposed a $36.7 billion budget for the city. He embraced his old friend, former Deputy Mayor Peter Powers, and others at the funeral of Kathy Reilly, a much-loved City Hall aide who had died of cancer. He refused to comment on reports that his wife had accepted a role in a play called ''The Vagina Monologues.''</p>
        <p>Then came the sea change in the lives of Rudolph Giuliani and those around him. On April 27, he announced that he had prostate cancer. In public he conveyed his customary self-assurance, making a joke or two; his private moments were another matter. ''It was very, very hard,'' one close adviser said. ''It hit him very hard because of the fact that his father had it.''</p>
        <p>Elliot Cuker, the owner of Coopers Classic Cars and Cigar bar and a close friend of the mayor's, declined to comment for this story, but he recently told New York 1 News that the mayor had wept while telling him of the diagnosis. The detail reflected the bond that had developed between the mayor and Mr. Cuker, a flamboyant, part-time actor who favors bow ties; Mr. Giuliani has said Mr. Cuker taught him how to use acting techniques to discover ''your own feelings about things.'' Even so, other friends of the mayor thought that Mr. Cuker's sharing of a private moment was counterproductive to the image that the mayor wanted to convey.</p>
        <p>In the days immediately after the announcement, Mr. Giuliani canceled several political obligations to concentrate on his treatment options, a matter that he later said he first approached as though it were just another bureaucratic problem. But he quickly discovered that grappling with the dimensions of a life-threatening disease could be confusing and emotionally exhausting.</p>
        <p>His political aides continued to solicit money and to engage the Clinton campaign in debate, although some began to feel as though they were running a campaign without a candidate. Meanwhile, several aides said, Mr. Giuliani was seeking out skilled, objective doctors, while also trying to find a treatment regimen that would magically meet his physical and political needs: one that would give him the best chance at survival, carry the fewest possible side effects, and allow him to wage an all-out, statewide campaign.</p>
        <p>''Every time you start fiddling with one set of variables -- suppose I do this, suppose I do that -- the other set of variables is moving along with you,'' Monsignor Placa said. ''In this case, each thing changed the other.''</p>
        <p>Then came what one adviser called ''the one-week interruption.''</p>
        <p>An ever-escalating series of revelations in early May reached its peak  when the mayor, struggling with his composure, publicly expressed his intentions to seek a separation from Ms. Hanover and to rely more heavily on Ms. Nathan. A few hours later, in front of their Gracie Mansion home, Ms. Hanover responded with angry accusations about a marriage turned upside down by her husband's involvement first with a close aide (Ms. Lategano-Nicholas) and now by his choice to take another path (Ms. Nathan).</p>
        <p>None of the many aides and advisers said they could explain the mayor's motivation for handling this personal matter in such a painfully public forum. Some chalked it up to love; others thought it reflected a marriage lacking in communication. One sought to shift the focus to Ms. Hanover, saying, ''She was getting advice, spin, from somebody to portray herself as a victim.'' Nobody thought it benefited the mayor's ambitions for the Senate.</p>
        <p>The mayor's consultations with friends continued.</p>
        <p>''The way it actually works is, he muses and says out loud what's on his mind,'' one adviser said. ''And then he bounces off you various aspects of his thinking.''</p>
        <p>Another adviser agreed. ''He'll talk about the options, and people  will ask questions,'' he said. ''I never told him whether to run or not to run or what to do on his treatment. But we would go over the political effects, the side effects.''</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, there were periods of restlessness, of questions about the careers of those around the mayor. Some had financial interests in whether the mayor pursued the Senate seat. Others had emotional capital invested in such a race; for months they had been girding for a battle that suddenly seemed in question. Throughout, Mr. Giuliani kept his own counsel.</p>
        <p>Monsignor Placa said Mr. Giuliani drove out to Long Island last week for a talk over dinner. He said he had listened to the mayor as a friend, not as a counselor, and he declined to discuss any conversations about Mr. Giuliani's marriage -- other than to say that the marital difficulties played a big role in the mayor's eventual decision to drop out of the Senate race.</p>
        <p>Depending on where they stood in the concentric rings of advisers that surround the mayor, people came to see their friend in new and different ways. One described the mayor in these moments as more relaxed and more open, as if the veneer of his public persona had been peeled away. Others said he was the same gregarious Rudy Giuliani they had always known.</p>
        <p>''Some of the media are saying they see a different Giuliani,'' said Guy V. Molinari, the Staten Island borough president, who is also grappling with prostate cancer. ''But there's a very warm, genuine side of Rudy Giuliani. I've seen it so often that I've thought to myself many times, 'I wish everybody could see this Rudy Giuliani.' ''</p>
        <p>A few hours after the mayor's news conference on Friday, Monsignor Placa said the moment had revealed something deeper than the convivial, compassionate side of Mr. Giuliani: a spiritual, reflective side that he has always had.</p>
        <p>''This has become a defining moment for him,'' he said, adding, ''He's found some spiritual meaning to all this.</p>
        <p>''He needs the peace he asked for today.''</p>
        <p>It is a peace that Rudolph Giuliani did not appear to need on New Year's Eve, as he led a city in celebration. Judith Nathan was near his side, Donna Hanover was watching the festivities from another vantage point in Times Square, and the new year seemed rich with promise.</p>
        <p>THE RACE FOR SENATE: BOWING OUT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
