<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Wading Into Depths of Memory and Repression</title>
    <meta content="21OEST$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="41" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201034"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nazi Policies Toward Jews and Minorities</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Austria</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mauthausen (Austria)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Vienna Philharmonic</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Oestreich, James R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Beethoven, Ludwig Van (1770-1827)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Austria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Austria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nazi Policies Toward Jews and Minorities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000521T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E0D71E3BF932A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2078" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Wading Into Depths of Memory and Repression</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES R. OESTREICH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Oestreich, James R</byline>
      <dateline>VIENNA</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vienna Philharmonic, performing Beethoven's Ninth Symphony in quarry of former concentration camp in Mauthausen, Austria, in tribute to victims of Nazis, brings home Austria's past to younger generation and raises anew questions about the uses and misuses of music; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CITY of Mozart, Beethoven, Schubert, Brahms, sundry Strausses, Mahler, Schoenberg, Berg and Webern. City of Freud, Adler and Reich. A burnished nostalgia crosses paths with a studied forgetfulness, and myth lurks at every turn.</p>
        <p>When the Vienna Philharmonic performed Beethoven's Ninth Symphony recently in the quarry of a former Nazi concentration camp in Mauthausen, Austria, 120 miles to the west, it knowingly waded into deep waters of memory and repression, meaning and association, hope and delusion. And all of that is to reckon without the late-breaking international fracas over Jorg Haider and the Freedom Party, as the orchestra did through most of its four years of planning.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CITY of Mozart, Beethoven, Schubert, Brahms, sundry Strausses, Mahler, Schoenberg, Berg and Webern. City of Freud, Adler and Reich. A burnished nostalgia crosses paths with a studied forgetfulness, and myth lurks at every turn.</p>
        <p>When the Vienna Philharmonic performed Beethoven's Ninth Symphony recently in the quarry of a former Nazi concentration camp in Mauthausen, Austria, 120 miles to the west, it knowingly waded into deep waters of memory and repression, meaning and association, hope and delusion. And all of that is to reckon without the late-breaking international fracas over Jorg Haider and the Freedom Party, as the orchestra did through most of its four years of planning.</p>
        <p>Seizing on the symbolism of the year 2000, the event was intended as a Janus-headed look backward, with remorse and a hope for healing, and forward, with resolve and a hope for renewal. Crucial to each point was a frank acknowledgment of a shameful past, the orchestra's and the nation's as a whole, something that has been slower to emerge here than in Germany. Austria likes to portray itself as the first victim of Nazi Germany, pointing to the Anschluss of 1938, despite its widespread embrace of annexation to the Third Reich. As has often been noted, Austrians figured among SS forces in concentration camps all out of proportion to their percentage of the Reich's Germanic population.</p>
        <p>Inevitably, the concert raised questions about the uses and abuses of music. Although some saw the orchestra's venture as misguided, many considered it a tool for good. Still, any confusion of aesthetics with morality, the cherished notion that at least the loftiest music is invariably a force for human edification and communication, must fall before even the most cursory reflection on the place of music in the Third Reich.</p>
        <p>Some of these themes have, coincidentally, taken on added resonance with publication of Richard Newman's new book, ''Alma Rose: Vienna to Auschwitz,'' the story of a noted violinist who went on to direct a women's orchestra at Auschwitz-Birkenau. To a lesser extent, it also tells the story of her father, Arnold Rose, the leader of the celebrated Rose Quartet through several transformations, a revered concertmaster of the Vienna Philharmonic and of its parent Vienna State Opera Orchestra for 57 years, and a brother-in-law of Mahler. The book encapsulates the plunge from dizzying heights of Viennese culture to fathomless depths of Nazi depredation. And through it all, there is every reason to believe, the Vienna players performed Beethoven brilliantly.</p>
        <p>''My Beethoven,'' Arnold Rose, a thoroughly assimilated Romanian-born Jew who identified himself completely with Austrian culture, liked to call the composer. ''To go to a better world, take the Beethoven piano sonatas and play them through,'' he advised his son, Alfred, who had fled to Cincinnati, from his own exile in London. The elder Rose's unstinting service to Beethoven, to the orchestra and to society availed him nothing. He was summarily dismissed from the orchestra at the time of the Anschluss. A dozen or so other Jewish members quickly followed.</p>
        <p>Alma Rose saw her father safely to London, then, against advice from friends, traveled to the Netherlands, where she worked to support herself and her father, never to return. Arnold Rose sank into loneliness and despair. The Vienna Philharmonic offered to reinstate him as concertmaster in January 1946, but he was no longer in any position to accept. He died in that year, at 82.</p>
        <p>With this context in mind, it is eerie to return to a familiar EMI recording of Beethoven's Ninth Symphony by the Vienna Philharmonic and the Vienna Singverein, which also performed at Mauthausen, from 1947. The conductor, Herbert von Karajan, and the soprano soloist, Elisabeth Schwarzkopf, it later emerged, had both been members of the Nazi party. So had half the members of the orchestra, in the estimate of Werner Resel, a cellist now in the Philharmonic who, as its president in 1996, set the Mauthausen project in motion.</p>
        <p>In early 1946, Mr. Newman writes in a similar vein, Arnold Rose reported ''an unsubstantiated claim from Vienna that 56 Nazis remained in the Vienna Philharmonic, as opposed to six in the Berlin Philharmonic.'' During that year the Vienna Philharmonic sought permission from American military authorities to tour France and was turned down. The Americans branded it a ''Nazi orchestra,'' a term that continues to haunt it.</p>
        <p>Karajan's recorded Ninth of the next year is rousing, to say the least. (Does a listener hear or only imagine an almost militaristic aggression at times?) The orchestra, of course, plays brilliantly, though the amateur Singverein in no sense rivals it, as that chorus's latter-day counterpart did in a recent performance of the work here in the Vienna Musikverein. In the years that followed, the classical-music world, which had retreated into an ivory tower of its own by midcentury, proved as adept as Austria in overlooking, excusing and ultimately forgetting unpleasant historic facts.</p>
        <p>Alma Rose, meanwhile, trapped in the occupied Netherlands, failed in an attempt to escape to Switzerland. Arrested and imprisoned in France, she was eventually sent to Auschwitz, where she took over a scrappy little women's band and, by all accounts, turned it into a crack orchestra, the pride of Maria Mandel, the SS commandant of the women's camp at Birkenau. The Nazi murderers, there is every reason to believe, appreciated the orchestra's playing just as much as their victims did.</p>
        <p>In addition to presenting concerts, the orchestra played marches for forced-labor contingents leaving the camp in the morning and returning at night. Mr. Newman casts doubt on reports that the orchestra entertained as trainloads of new prisoners arrived, with many being immediately ''selected'' for death in the gas chambers.</p>
        <p>Alma Rose was a stern taskmaster, believing that only by maintaining the highest musical standards could the orchestra insure its survival and that of its members. Yet she appears to have acquitted herself with whatever dignity and humanity the circumstances allowed: more so than depicted in Fania Fenelon's 1977 book about the orchestra, ''Playing for Time,'' and the CBS film of the same name. The orchestra members, in any case, received preferential treatment and did buy time. Most, like Fenelon, survived. Alma Rose herself died in the camp in 1944, at 37, apparently from botulism.</p>
        <p>What role, then, can music, so obviously ambiguous and amoral in its meanings and so debased by some of its makers and users, or the Vienna Philharmonic, so compromised in its integrity, play in the quest for a brighter future? A crucial one, in the view of Leon Zelman, who first presented the idea for the Mauthausen event to Mr. Resel and the Philharmonic: that of remembrance.</p>
        <p>''People don't understand that the tragedy in Europe did not begin with Mauthausen and Auschwitz,'' Mr. Zelman said. ''It began with words, with hatred, with annihilation. The young generation in Austria after us must be reminded, and music has a power to translate. It helps us to remember.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Zelman, 73, directs the Jewish Welcome Service of Vienna, which invites refugees to revisit the city they once fled. Born in Poland, he himself passed through Auschwitz and other camps on his way to Mauthausen: actually one of its many satellite camps in Austria, Ebensee, from which he was liberated 55 years ago this month. He remained in Vienna after the war and eventually developed friendships with members of the Philharmonic, including Mr. Resel and Clemens Hellsberg, a violinist and the orchestra's current president and archivist, who himself did much to lay bare the orchestra's Nazi past in his 1992 history, ''Demokratie der Konige'' (''Democracy of Kings''), not yet available in English.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zelman has no particular connection to music. The references to music in his touching memoir of 1998, ''After Survival,'' are mainly to the melancholy songs his mother sang before her disappearance from the Lodz ghetto in Poland to an unknown but certain death. He chose Beethoven's Ninth Symphony, with its concluding chorus based on Schiller's ''Ode to Joy,'' he said, ''because it represents the idea of Mauthausen, the vision we had that when we survived, it would be in a world of freedom.''</p>
        <p>Around 105,000 prisoners died at Mauthausen in unspeakably brutal conditions: not only Jews but also non-Jews from Eastern Europe and elsewhere, homosexuals, Communists and ''antisocials.'' Many others besides Mr. Zelman survived, and opposition to the Mauthausen event arose primarily from them, not from Mr. Haider's Freedom Party. (But Mr. Zelman is hardly sanguine on that score; he is obviously still shaken by the shouts of ''Heil Haider!'' and the Nazi salutes he encountered at a rally in St. Stephen's Square last December, before the election.)</p>
        <p>Some survivors opposed the very idea of presenting a musical event on what, they insisted, should be preserved as holy ground. Some protested the nature of the music: the triumphal ''Ode to Joy'' in a place of such sorrows. Some objected to the participation of the Vienna Philharmonic, with its tainted past.</p>
        <p>BUT Mr. Zelman finds nothing of that past in the current orchestra. He said he was gratified at its unanimous acceptance of his proposal and its readiness to waive fees.</p>
        <p>For Beethoven, said Simon Rattle, who conducted the Mauthausen performance, joy was always hard-won and thus aptly symbolic of this occasion. In the case of the Ninth Symphony, the music historian Richard Taruskin suggested in a 1989 essay, ''Resisting the Ninth,'' the joy of the finale has to be pried from the sublimity that characterizes the first three movements.</p>
        <p>Edmund Burke ''contrasted the smallness, the lightness and the pleasurableness of the Beautiful with the vastness, the obscurity, the painfulness of the Sublime,'' Mr. Taruskin writes. ''All the adjectives Burke applies to the 'great' -- vast, rugged, negligent, dark, gloomy, solid, massive -- suit its first three movements to perfection, even as the adjectives applied to 'beauty' -- small, smooth, polished, light, delicate -- seem altogether alien to it.'' In the same senses the occasion and the place, in the quarry of Mauthausen, were truly sublime.</p>
        <p>''Having music here is a very good thing,'' said Thomas Quasthoff, the baritone soloist in the Beethoven Ninth, who pointed to a personal meaning in the occasion, since, physically deformed by his mother's use of Thalidomide during pregnancy, he would have been among the first slain in Nazi times. ''But is it necessary to have so many speakers? The music is important. Speakers don't change anything.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Zelman is surely right that remembrance can no longer be entrusted merely to survivors, most of whom will soon be gone. There must be a way for future generations to connect to the events of the Holocaust on a visceral level, and this is indeed a function music can serve.</p>
        <p>''It helps open our hearts,'' Mr. Zelman said. And it brings to bear its tremendous power of association, through which the memories of musical experiences fuse viscerally with extramusical circumstances.</p>
        <p>''This sort of thing is important, because it gives people something to attach to,'' said Wolfgang K. Aulitzky, the director of the medical program of the American Austrian Foundation. ''The Vienna Philharmonic is accomplishing something the Austrian government should have done long ago, making Austrians aware of their history. They should do this concert every year.''</p>
        <p>Back to that notion of joy: to judge from one visit, the Mauthausen quarry is steadily filled with joyous sounds, the songs of birds. They must have seemed a cruel mockery to prisoners at the time, but from this vantage point they seem to speak of natural renewal. Having learned to destroy more efficiently than nature, can humans settle for less when it comes to repairing the damage? Hope and resolve, if not joy, may be the only appropriate responses.</p>
        <p>Beethoven's Ninth Symphony ''still awakens in us longings for what we can no longer believe in, but wish we could,'' Mr. Taruskin writes, going on to elaborate on a phrase coined by the musicologist Joseph Kerman. ''We are still in the valley of the Ninth. And so there's hope.''</p>
        <p>MUSIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
