<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Shifting Sands Into Works of Art</title>
    <meta content="21CTSAN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201204"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000521T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E1D6153AF932A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1560" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Shifting Sands Into Works of Art</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAWRENCE DOWNES</byline>
      <dateline>SOUTHAMPTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>YOU there, playing in the sand, may be perfectly content with your plastic pail and little shovel. But watch how Jeff Muhs does it.</p>
        <p>One recent morning he walked up the beach to where the sand rose to a smooth, damp escarpment above the burbling surf, his eyes hidden by wraparound shades and his lank hair rippling in the Atlantic breeze. Keeping his right hand in the pocket of his baggy fatigue pants, he used his left to start scratching in the sand with a long, skinny stick. He made a few light, swooping curves, like misaligned parentheses. Dragging the stick more forcefully, he walked around the curved marks, enclosing them within a kidney-shaped line. Then, using that line as a guide, he and a friend began to dig.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>YOU there, playing in the sand, may be perfectly content with your plastic pail and little shovel. But watch how Jeff Muhs does it.</p>
        <p>One recent morning he walked up the beach to where the sand rose to a smooth, damp escarpment above the burbling surf, his eyes hidden by wraparound shades and his lank hair rippling in the Atlantic breeze. Keeping his right hand in the pocket of his baggy fatigue pants, he used his left to start scratching in the sand with a long, skinny stick. He made a few light, swooping curves, like misaligned parentheses. Dragging the stick more forcefully, he walked around the curved marks, enclosing them within a kidney-shaped line. Then, using that line as a guide, he and a friend began to dig.</p>
        <p>There was a woman under the sand, and Mr. Muhs (pronounced MEESE), a 33-year-old Southampton painter and sculptor, was there to get her out. He and a fellow artist, Michael Perez, 40, had graciously agreed -- on short notice and ridiculously early in the year -- to demonstrate the summertime art of sand sculpture.</p>
        <p>Mr. Muhs was not about to mold a row of castle turrets using an overturned plastic bucket, though one suspects he could have -- he is a full-time artist, a School of Visual Arts graduate who has won international awards for his wood sculptures. Instead, to show what wonders could be worked in moist sand, he had chosen to carve a sleeping female nude, using only the stick and shovel, a soupspoon, a brush and his and Mr. Perez's bare hands and feet.</p>
        <p>Mr. Muhs had created sculptures on the beach before, for the annual sand castle contest in East Hampton. He is known locally as one of the best sand sculptors around, but in the world of competitive sand sculpturing, Mr. Muhs is only a dabbler.</p>
        <p>The East Hampton contest is among hundreds held every year around the globe. The phenomenon is growing rapidly, attracting crowds and a corps of professionals who compete -- frequently for cash and prizes -- on an informal circuit of beaches from France to Texas to China.</p>
        <p>Like other states, New York, New Jersey and Connecticut have several prominent sand-sculpture contests that are open to amateurs. East Hampton's contest, a benefit for local community projects, is one, as is the huge annual contest in Belmar, N.J., which draws thousands of participants. Organizers of Belmar's contest, in fact, invite master sand sculptors to give tips and classes for prospective contestants.</p>
        <p>Some may find it strange that yet another form of child's play has morphed into a quasi sport. But sand sculpture contests -- not entirely a guy thing, but mostly -- are at least more of a spectator event than pro bowling or bass fishing.</p>
        <p>The ambition and kitschy creativity at these contests can reach astonishing levels. Take the Castelli di Mare competition in Jesolo, a Italian resort north of Venice. Last year's winner, John Gowdy, 43, a fire captain from Atlantic City, took five days to create a tableau he called ''Fireman, Giver of Life.'' In it, a firefighter in authentic Italian protective gear (Mr. Gowdy did research locally) emerges from the strewn bricks and boards of a burning building, cradling an infant he is about to hand to a woman with streaming hair.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Gowdy explained in an interview from his home in Absecon, N.J., (where he had just returned from a competition in Myrtle Beach, S.C.), competitive sculptors pack wet sand into giant molds. Mr. Gowdy uses plastic cylinders made from wading pools, bound with clamps. Using hand tools, they tamp the sand until it becomes nearly as hard as rock, easy to carve with tools like masonry trowels and pallette knives.</p>
        <p>And it can be piled to amazing heights. ''I've gotten up 30 feet to build a castle,'' Mr. Gowdy said. But ''they start to get a little dangerous when you get up that high. I think the world record is up to 60, 70 feet.''</p>
        <p>Chuck Feld, another expert (he competed against Mr. Gowdy at Myrtle Beach), said the crowds at contests were routinely dumbfounded by the miracle of hard-packed sand. ''People are in awe that we're up 8, 10, 12 feet,'' said Mr. Feld, 51, a horticulturist and 20-year sand sculptor. Both Mr. Gowdy and Mr. Feld said a large part of sand sculpturing's appeal came from working while being watched. ''It's definitely what I call a performance art,'' Mr. Gowdy said. ''While you're actively carving these things, the crowd is oohing and ahhing.''</p>
        <p>Though neither man mentioned the thrill of creation, Mr. Muhs did bring it to mind when he brought a woman to life on the sands at Southampton. After the outline of her body was marked, Mr. Muhs and Mr. Perez worked quickly, digging a trench around it about two feet deep. The shape inside the trench looked like New Jersey. As Mr. Perez kept the shovel flying, Mr. Muhs sat with his feet in the trench and used both hands to push and drag away gobs of sand until the Garden State became -- a torso. Three minutes had passed. More sand flew, and a forearm and head emerged. Straddling the shape, Mr. Muhs began to smooth out planes and angles, never hesitating.</p>
        <p>''The stuff I'm doing now would take days if I were carving wood, weeks if it was a block of marble,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The method of taking away existing sand, rather than piling and packing it, makes Mr. Muhs a rarity among sand sculptors and extremely vulnerable to the perils of gravity and the wind. It took Mr. Muhs only seven minutes to transform a slab of beach into a rough but recognizable woman. As he ran his hands up and down his sculpture, there came a moment of startling transformation, when Mr. Muhs suddenly looked not like a guy messing with a pile of sand, but like a masseur. Twelve minutes on, Mr. Perez was doing his part, shaping the woman's behind, lower legs and long, straight hair. A rapt Mr. Muhs used his fingers and the end of his stick to smooth and trace the breasts, chin, nose and brow.</p>
        <p>''I'm trying to get the planes right, the height of different parts,'' he said. ''Eventually I start to get one part that's close, and then the rest just falls into place.''</p>
        <p>After 40 minutes, Mr. Muhs took out the spoon, to carve out the space under her bent arm. ''This is one of the trickiest parts,'' he said. ''Sometimes it works, sometimes it falls apart.'' It worked.</p>
        <p>''Now I can start getting into muscle groups,'' Mr. Muhs said. He brought out the brush, and as he gently moved it along her side, rough sand suddenly became skin. But at the hour mark, disaster: the woman's right leg collapsed between the ankle and hip. Mr. Muhs thought about it for a moment, then told Mr. Perez to shovel more sand over her lower half. ''We'll make it look like a blanket,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But the tension was building. ''We're losing stability, because the sun is drying out the sand,'' Mr. Perez explained. Mr. Muhs sped on, adding layer after layer of detail, as Mr. Perez lay on his stomach, delicately smoothing away the footprints in the trench. It was a race against the sun.</p>
        <p>The race was lost an hour and 20 minutes after it began. Mr. Muhs was brushing her right arm, and it collapsed. He was stoic, calling attention to a new, accidental beauty: what was briefly a living woman was now the ruin of a classical statue. ''Any other subject'' -- a castle, for instance -- ''might not hold that beauty,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Muhs stood silently apart for several moments, gazing intently at his damaged creation. Then he walked with Mr. Perez back up to the road, to get some lunch.</p>
        <p>A small sampling of events and locations.</p>
        <p>Hither Hills State Park, Montauk, Fridays June 30 to Labor Day. (631) 668-2554</p>
        <p>Belmar Sand Castle Contest, 18th Avenue Beach, Belmar, N.J., July 5. (732) 681-3700</p>
        <p>Sand Sculpting by the Sea, Coney Island,  July 29. (718) 266-4653</p>
        <p>East Hampton Sandcastle Contest, East Hampton, Aug. 5 (rain date Aug. 6). (631) 324-6250 www.peconic.net/sandcastle</p>
        <p>Great American Sand Sculpture Competition, Walnut Beach, Milford, Conn., Aug. 26. (203) 878-6647</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
