<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Happy Caterers, Many Frantic Customers</title>
    <meta content="21CATE$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201173"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parties (Social)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Catering</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Saslow, Linda</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parties (Social)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000521T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E5D8153AF932A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1269" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Happy Caterers, Many Frantic Customers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LINDA SASLOW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Saslow, Linda</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on sharp increase in requests for catering services on Long Island as summer party season approaches; caterers note some clients are being locked out as bookings rise; list (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NOBODY is likely to go hungry this summer in the Hamptons, but that is small consolation to hosts and hostesses with many mouths to feed.</p>
        <p>''I've never seen a year like this,'' said Brent Newsom, a Bridgehampton caterer. By the end of April, business at Brent Newsom Caterers was up about 80 percent from last year, he said, with every Saturday in July and August booked, as well as the whole month of September and the latter part of June.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NOBODY is likely to go hungry this summer in the Hamptons, but that is small consolation to hosts and hostesses with many mouths to feed.</p>
        <p>''I've never seen a year like this,'' said Brent Newsom, a Bridgehampton caterer. By the end of April, business at Brent Newsom Caterers was up about 80 percent from last year, he said, with every Saturday in July and August booked, as well as the whole month of September and the latter part of June.</p>
        <p>''People have been calling earlier to book their parties,'' Mr. Newsom said. ''They smell the scent of panic in the air and are beating each other to death for dates. We're selling dates for parties the way houses sell in Silicon Valley: on who wants to bid the highest for the date.''</p>
        <p>As early as February, Cheryl Stair, chef and partner of Art of Eating in Amagansett, called regular clients to warn them they had better choose their dates for summer events, or risk being shut out.</p>
        <p>''Weekends have booked up early this year, which has created a longer summer season that now stretches from May right through the last weekend in October,'' she said.</p>
        <p>By January several clients had locked in their dates with Christopher Robbins, a caterer who owns Robbins Wolfe Eventeurs in Bridgehampton. By last month, more than half the Saturdays through the summer were booked, he said, either with several large parties or up to 10 smaller ones.</p>
        <p>Last-minute party planners may be hard-pressed to find a free Saturday in July or August. And forget about June and September.</p>
        <p>''This year people seem to want the biggest and most important wedding, benefit, cocktail party or corporate function,'' Mr. Newsom said. ''The weddings and benefits this summer are crawling all over each other, and some benefits have changed their dates because they were competing with another big one.''</p>
        <p>Michael Castino, owner and chef of Pacific East in Amagansett, said, ''I've had to turn people away, and even when I suggest other places, they're also often already booked.''</p>
        <p>With so many weekend dates filled, Charlotte Sasso, co-owner of Stuart's Seafood Caterers in Amagansett, has been encouraging clients to plan parties during the week.</p>
        <p>''I try to suggest something different,'' she said. ''How about a Thursday or a Monday? Thursday is a great day because it's the start of the weekend. Some people are receptive; others insist on Saturdays.''</p>
        <p>Even if the caterer is available, there are still the challenges of finding entertainment, rental items, a tent, valet parking and other services, which are also tight.</p>
        <p>''The busy season is wonderful for us,'' said John Kowalenko, co-owner of Art of Eating, ''but for people planning an event this year, they'll be fortunate to have all their needs met.''</p>
        <p>Surprisingly, September is the first month to fill up, said Ms. Stair, mostly with weddings. ''The weekend after Labor Day is going to be insane,'' she said. ''We've already turned away about 50 couples.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Newsom's September calendar is also filled with weddings. ''September in the Hamptons has turned into the nuptial capital of the Western world,'' he said. ''Every bride wants to be married in the Hamptons in September. It used to be that at the end of August, everybody went home and the crush of summer people was over. But now the crush of September people is just as big.''</p>
        <p>Why the boom? Many attribute it largely to the strong economy and the flourishing stock market, and caterers were pleasantly relieved by the nonreaction to the recent dip in the market. ''There was not a whimper,'' Mr. Newsom said, ''not even a sniggle of a call asking to cut back on anything.''</p>
        <p>Aside from the economy, the millennium has also contributed to an unusually busy season.</p>
        <p>''There was a lot of romance in the air on New Year's Eve because of the millennium,'' Mr. Kowalenko said. ''There were more engagements than we can ever remember in the past because so many people wanted to be married in the year 2000. This has created a great need for wedding dates this year.''</p>
        <p>The fact that this is an election year has also added benefit parties to the Hamptons calendar, added Jim McManus, executive director of Party Rental Ltd. in East Hampton. ''There are many fundraisers for political causes, competing for the limited time and resources of the caterers,'' he said. ''This is contributing to the gridlock.''</p>
        <p>For caterers, gridlock also means that many of the same people will be going to more than one party on any given night, Mr. Robbins said. ''If more than one party is on our books for the same night, we ask the clients if they know each other and if there are any of the same guests,'' he said. ''Then we have to be sure not to serve the same menu.''</p>
        <p>Caterered events this summer range from formal sit-down dinners for 700 to home parties with a Caribbean or Hawaiian theme to casual clambakes on the beach. Of the growing popularity of clam bakes, Ms. Sasso said: ''While there is an element of the Hamptons that is 'see and be seen,' there's another side that is 'kick off your sneakers and have fun.' People love to wear shorts and lobster bibs with butter slothered all over their chins.''</p>
        <p>At the other end of the spectrum, some parties are more sophisticated and stylized.</p>
        <p>''Everybody in the Hamptons wants to make a statement,'' Mr. McManus said. ''People have high-quality taste and many are looking to upgrade and spend more money on details like tablecloths, china and even chairs. We now have to offer choices, including more than 30 different patterns of china, a new line of embroidery for monogramming on napkins and chairs in 28 different colors. We're taking it up a notch.''</p>
        <p>Then there are the clients who want caviar and lobster on a hamburger budget, said Greg Deger, general manager of Red Horse Catering in East Hampton. ''We can't give them foie gras and truffles for $20 per person,'' he said, ''but we find a way to work out something that works for everybody.''</p>
        <p>For Red Horse Catering, one of the highlights will be the wedding of Jodi Della Femina, a daughter of the restaurateur Jerry Della Femina, and John Kim, whose family is Korean. Mr. Della Femina is also the owner of Red Horse Catering.</p>
        <p>Planning a wedding between an Italian bride and a Korean groom has kept the caterers busy, Mr. Deger said.</p>
        <p>''We've been working for eight months to create a wedding that brings the two nationalities together,'' he said. ''There will be a traditional Korean ceremony on the beach, followed by a Korean cocktail hour, then a family-style Italian dinner.''</p>
        <p>Summarizing the pre-season frenzy, Ms. Stair said, ''We're all dancing as fast as we can.''</p>
        <p>On the Side</p>
        <p>It takes more than shrimp and chardonnay to make a summer cull of parties work. Here are other details on the checklist of one of the Hampotons' busiest caterers, Art of Eating Catering and Event Planning.</p>
        <p>Renting more than 20 locations in excess of $200,000 for parties and weddings.</p>
        <p>Donating more than $75,000 in products and services to more than $20 charities.</p>
        <p>Interviewing more than 250 people for jobs as waiters, bartenders, and other positions.</p>
        <p>Making more than 10,000 cups of coffee.</p>
        <p>Ordering more than 100,000 glasses; 12,000 plates; 40,000 knives, forks and spoons from rental companies, as well as 20,000 napkins.</p>
        <p>Going through more than 150,000 beverage napkins, 16,000 liters of soda and juice and 10,000 pounds of ice.</p>
        <p>Using 1,500 gallons of gasoline, 6,000 pounds of propane and 5,000 trash bag.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
