<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Way We Live Now: 5-21-00: ShopTalk; Very Early Admission</title>
    <meta content="WLN131046" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201011"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education (Pre-School)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Admissions Standards</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hartocollis, Anemona</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barron, Marlene</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rosenberg, Jean</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Admissions Standards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education (Pre-School)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000521T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E2DC1E3BF932A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="717" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Way We Live Now: 5-21-00: ShopTalk; Very Early Admission</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Anemona Hartocollis</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hartocollis, Anemona</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Shop Talk column features discussion between preschool directors Marlene Barron and Jean Rosenberg on nursery school admissions interview; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>This is the season when many parents begin the perilous journey of getting their toddlers into the right preschool and face the possibility of their social and intellectual rejection. As applications for the fall of 2001 loom, two of New York City's veteran preschool directors, Marlene Barron, head of the West Side Montessori School, and Jean Rosenberg, founder and director of the Chelsea Day School, offer an inside view of the dreaded admissions interview.</p>
        <p>Barron: We had a 2-year-old program, and we got rid of it because we were turning down families with children we had interviewed at 18 months, and I just could not do that, ethically. I could not live with myself. I could not deal that ego blow to a family.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>This is the season when many parents begin the perilous journey of getting their toddlers into the right preschool and face the possibility of their social and intellectual rejection. As applications for the fall of 2001 loom, two of New York City's veteran preschool directors, Marlene Barron, head of the West Side Montessori School, and Jean Rosenberg, founder and director of the Chelsea Day School, offer an inside view of the dreaded admissions interview.</p>
        <p>Barron: We had a 2-year-old program, and we got rid of it because we were turning down families with children we had interviewed at 18 months, and I just could not do that, ethically. I could not live with myself. I could not deal that ego blow to a family.</p>
        <p>Rosenberg: I had a Japanese family who applied, and they didn't get in. The day after the letters went out, this woman arrived in my office. She came to me while I was greeting my kids and broke down in tears and said, ''What did I do wrong?'' Culturally, it was probably devastating to her to stand in front of an authority figure and say that. Those kinds of things break my heart, they kill me, every year.</p>
        <p>Barron: Parents have the mistaken idea that there's one thing their child does that means he's in, or there's one thing their child does that means he's out. There's no such one thing.</p>
        <p>Rosenberg: I tell my families, ''You're coming to have a visit -- I'm not screening your child.''</p>
        <p>Barron: We want people who are not trying to sort of act their way into it.</p>
        <p>We had a family one year, and Mom comes in and is interviewed and her whole posture was around ethnicity. She's really interested in families that have different ethnic backgrounds -- racial backgrounds, I mean -- because she knows that's important here. And hers is a white family. The interviewer at that point was white. And we felt that it was an oversell. We did not accept the child. The following year she applied again, and this time we gave her a black interviewer. Little did she know, it was a very wealthy black interviewer. And then she started going on about -- well, trashing, in a subtle way -- rich people. You know, she likes the school because there's an economic mix. She kept trying to give the right answer, and it was artificial. Why couldn't she have just been herself? What was her point in all this? And though we laughed about it behind the scenes, this woman wasn't comfortable in her own skin.</p>
        <p>Rosenberg: And unfortunately that impacts on her child.</p>
        <p>Barron: That's right. The child was fine, perfectly acceptable. But we felt</p>
        <p>this family would always be trying to second-guess. And it wasn't needed.</p>
        <p>There is no school that just does six items with a child, six test kind of items, and says, O.K., this makes or breaks it.</p>
        <p>Rosenberg: Kids are being trained to pass these tests, so that the test doesn't mean anything after a while. If everybody's taking a course to take the test, it doesn't work anymore. So the rules are going to be different.</p>
        <p>Barron: Everything is subjective. We're all looking through our own eyes, our own history. There is no perfect. There's no perfect husband, there's no perfect wife, there's no perfect apartment, there's no perfect restaurant. Everything is a matter of negotiation and making some sort of adjustments. And parents have to think about that in a school. That notion of perfect -- we've got to get rid of it.</p>
        <p>Rosenberg: Yeah, life does not begin and end in the place that you go to school.</p>
        <p>Barron: And they won't have perfect children, either. No child is perfect. Children are an ongoing process.</p>
        <p>Moderated by Anemona Hartocollis</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
