<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Those Who Opt to Shop</title>
    <meta content="21SHOP" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201297"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Home Furnishings</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Seasons and Months</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fischler, Marcelle S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Home Furnishings</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Seasons and Months</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000521T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E7D9133AF932A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1288" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Those Who Opt to Shop</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by MARCELLE S. FISCHLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fischler, Marcelle S</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article describes several summer fashions and furnishings available at Long Island stores; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LIGHT MY FIRE</p>
        <p>Cool summer evenings on the deck never seemed so cozy or smelled so sweet. The chiminea, a patio fireplace made of terracotta clay, adds atmosphere, extra poolside warmth and a touch of whimsy. Place a scoop of sand and a small stack of firewood in the mouth of 3-foot high fish-shaped chiminea and smoke curls out of its tail. The elephant version has a smokestack trunk. Though not a primary heat source, fragrant woods provide the ultimate aromatherapy. The outdoor fireplaces also come shaped like traditional potbelly stoves or as oversized genie bottles set on a trivet. $175 each. Treasure Island, Wainscott Village, Wainscott, 631-537-0073.</p>
        <p>ON A ROLL</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LIGHT MY FIRE</p>
        <p>Cool summer evenings on the deck never seemed so cozy or smelled so sweet. The chiminea, a patio fireplace made of terracotta clay, adds atmosphere, extra poolside warmth and a touch of whimsy. Place a scoop of sand and a small stack of firewood in the mouth of 3-foot high fish-shaped chiminea and smoke curls out of its tail. The elephant version has a smokestack trunk. Though not a primary heat source, fragrant woods provide the ultimate aromatherapy. The outdoor fireplaces also come shaped like traditional potbelly stoves or as oversized genie bottles set on a trivet. $175 each. Treasure Island, Wainscott Village, Wainscott, 631-537-0073.</p>
        <p>ON A ROLL</p>
        <p>This summer, the chichi way to drive to Main Beach, navigate Newtown Lane, is via Zappy, the stand-up push electric scooter. Environmentally friendly, the grownup riding toy rolls along at 13 mph, has a retractable steering column, folds down to just over three feet long, fits easily in the trunk and is so quiet you could run it inside the house. Or try a battery-powered 18-speed bicycle. Pedaling is optional, said John Swanson, presidetn of the new store, a franchise of the California company Zap World. ''If you don't feel like getting exercise, you hit the juice, the little trigger on the handlebar and it activates the motor,'' he said. Electric scooter, $600; bicycles $700 to $1,500; ZapHampton, Main Street on the Circle, East Hampton. 631-907-9500.</p>
        <p>CUSHIONS WITH AN EDGE</p>
        <p>Tee shirts wit cutesy one-liners don't cut it in the Hamptons. But the buzz on the street translates perfectly to pillow talk. ''You are leaving on Sunday, aren't you?'' reads one 12 by 10-inch cushion. ''Guests of guests may not bring guests'' warns another. And if truth be told, ''You never know how many friends you have until you own a home in the Hamptons.'' ''Everybody has a suggestion,'' said Paul Levitt, owner of ''A Little of What you Fancy'' Some of the snappiest sayings came from his clientele. And he's open to putting new catchy thoughts on future navy, maroon and green pillows. For the year-rounders, try ''God Bless Everyone, Even the Summer People.'' For the rider, ''Horse Lovers are Stable People.'' The sayings are embroidered in gold thread; cushion covers are washable and the pillow inside slips out. Pillows, $29.95.  ''A Little of What You Fancy'' 19 Newtown Lane, East Hampton. 631-324-3113.</p>
        <p>COLLECTOR'S ITEM</p>
        <p>The shells are from Florida, not Montauk. But the 25 by 26-inch seashell planter covered in a beachcomber's collection of pink, beige and white seashells is large enough to hold a seven-foot palm tree. Treated for outdoor use (since when aren't seashells waterproof?), it's the ultimate decorative urn for a waterfront terrace. Come fall, it can be moved inside to stand next to its matching seashell- decked mirror. Planter, $1,500; mirro, $2,500. Devonshire, the English Garden Shop, Main Street, Bridgehampton, 631-537-2661.</p>
        <p>CHRIPING BONNETS</p>
        <p>Hats are no longer just for blocking the sun. The wide-brimmed country bonnet with a Victorian feel has a green ribbon topped with a pink rose. A more rumpled-looking khaki topper is fitted with fishing hooks and tackle. Two woven straw hats look crisp but they hardly provide UV protection. Made of fiberglass that looks like ceramic, the ock hats simply hang on a hook, where they double as birdhouses. A conversation piece for a patio wall and for feeding the bluejays. $85 each.  Devonshire, the English Garden Shop, Main Street Bridgehampton. 631-537-2661.</p>
        <p>FANCY BASKETS</p>
        <p>In the Hamptons, wicker baskets aren't just wicker baskets. Shaped to hold a bottle of East End merlot, a bucketful of chocolate-dipped strawberries or a fresh-baked loaf of seven-grain bread, natural wicker totes are trimmed in blue and nautically inspired with hand-painted tile inlays of lighthouses and sailboats. Wine bottle holder, $21; bread basket, $23.75; 8-inch round, $21.  Hamptons Accents, Inc. 31 Main Street, Southampton 631-287-1747.</p>
        <p>LOUNGING AROUND</p>
        <p>Guest room taken? this double- wide, adjustable white wicker chaise is comfortable enough to spend the night. Or just to lounge with your honey and savor the sun after dipping in the pool. Plus, there's no need to worry about getting the fabric wet. The plush cushion comes covered in the softest sailboat blue terry cloth fabric. There are matching decorative pillows trimmed with sailor's rope ($54.95) and terry cloth beach balls in a rainbow of pastels. ($69.95) Chaise by Lloyd Flanders, $1,609.95.  Hildreth's Department Store, 51 Main Street, Southampton. 631-283-2300.</p>
        <p>SUMMER CASHMERE</p>
        <p>It's the luxe lifestyle as much as the fabric. In the Hamptons, cashmere and hot summer nights mix. ''It's the most heavenly thing you can wear,'' said Margaret Dictenberg, owner of the Cashmere Hampton boutique, holding up a fringed powder pink Venus stole made from cashmere silk so lightweight</p>
        <p>RUFFLED COVERS</p>
        <p>Headed for a day at the beach? A ruffle-bottomed peasant skirt is the cover-up of the moment, worn over a bikini with a tight-fitting short-sleeve teeshirt. For dinner, the three-quarter-length skirt gets topped with a tube or halter and a closed-toe, open-backed sandal with a one- inch heel. Available in pastel shades of sage, orange, purple and pink, the skirt is this year's answer to go last year's go-anywhere, be-anything sarong. Skirt by Martin Kidman, $275.  Scoop, 47 Newtown Lane, East Hampton, 631-329-8080.</p>
        <p>BANDANNA TOPPINGS  Technically, it's not much more than two bandannas attached by a silky matching bra strap (but forget the bra). On a hot summer day, the handkerchief cami, available in a traditional bandanna pattern in pink, blue or white, may replace the halter as this sumemr's casual top. Wear it with Theary capris - white or denim cropped jeans - suggest Anna Runyan of Scoop, preferably without a waist, just fringed top and bottom. Or with a Dolce and Gabbana, mini bandanna skirt, trimmed with a slim band of plastic pink flowers near the hem. Handkerchief top, $95; skirt, $258; fringed denim capris, $155.  Scoop, 47 Newtown Lane, East Hampton 631-329-8080.</p>
        <p>IN PRINT</p>
        <p>The jeweler Cartier filled a long narrow space along East Hampton's Main Street last summer. Now Georgina, a women's apparel shop with locations in Manhasset and Cedarhusrt, has taken over the shop, filling the racks with different, but still pricey, gems: the Palm Beach -inspired floral print bikinis from the fashion forward collections of designer Michael Kors. ''Not of our clientele for the summer vacations here or is here for the entire summer and we are capturing the Manhattan clients who are here as well,'' said the manager, Christine Follenius. Collections for pool, garden parties and soirees include shoes, bags and accessories as well as clothes. The Kors Line, designed exclusively for Long Island, comes in shade of ''pool'' (aqua), lemon and lime. The bikini is $295; matching sarong $395.  Georgina, Main street, East Hampton 631-907-0670.</p>
        <p>HAUTE COOLER</p>
        <p>To quench one's thirst, a cooler with a plastic water bottle on top ususally does the trick. But for a Tuscan-inspired summer soiree, a free-standing heavy ceramic cooler, adorned with an image of plump grapes, rests on a metal base and can be filled with wine. Press the spigot and the liquid pours from one tier to another, first into one bowl, then another. ''We're trying to cover all the aspects of the growing Hamptonians'', said Anni Nevruzian of Hamptons Accents, who carries an eclectic mix of indoor/outdoor furniture and accessories. Cooler, $189.  Hamptons Accent Inc, 31 Main Street, Southampton. 631-287-1747.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
