<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Way We Live Now: 5-21-00: Questions for David Ruggerio; The Cook, The Thief</title>
    <meta content="WLN131103" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201012"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Le Chantilly (NYC Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ruggerio, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schrambling, Regina</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000521T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E2DC1E3BF932A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1195" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Way We Live Now: 5-21-00: Questions for David Ruggerio; The Cook, The Thief</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Regina Schrambling</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schrambling, Regina</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with David Ruggerio, chefs</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Q: You were arrested two years ago, when you were chef at Le Chantilly, for some rather extreme financial improprieties. Some of the stuff your restaurant was trying to get away with was so egregious that it could have been motivated only by absolute desperation. What in the world was going on there?</p>
        <p>Le Chantilly was making money, but it was laden, from a prior business partner, with huge tax debt. We were under constant threats, the I.R.S. was coming down threatening every day to padlock the place.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Q: You were arrested two years ago, when you were chef at Le Chantilly, for some rather extreme financial improprieties. Some of the stuff your restaurant was trying to get away with was so egregious that it could have been motivated only by absolute desperation. What in the world was going on there?</p>
        <p>Le Chantilly was making money, but it was laden, from a prior business partner, with huge tax debt. We were under constant threats, the I.R.S. was coming down threatening every day to padlock the place.</p>
        <p>So it was all just to keep the restaurant afloat? Not for personal gain?</p>
        <p>If anyone had profited $1 from this, no would be walking the street today. What it was -- the credit card processor forwards money to the restaurant. If it's MasterCard or Visa it's usually 48 hours, if it's American Express it's 72 hours. So they were floating the credits and getting the money faster, then repaying them. And then not repaying them. It got bigger and bigger. I mean, a dollar's a big thing. This got gargantuan.</p>
        <p>But you have said that it was going on for a year or so before you even found out. How is that possible? How could your life get so out of control that you wouldn't notice huge fraud in your own restaurant?</p>
        <p>I worked at some very established older French restaurants in the beginning of my career, and what those chefs did was, they stood behind the stove. But when I was in charge of a restaurant, that wasn't enough anymore. People kept saying to me, ''Write a book.'' The next thing I know we're talking about a PBS series in conjunction with the book. That's when things started getting out of hand. The next thing I know I'm involved with five restaurants and I have hundreds of employees. And at the same time my partnership falls apart in a horrible breakup. Now I'm all by myself, I have five restaurants, I have a book coming out and a PBS series coming out and a 42-city tour -- and we're going to start shooting a prime-time series, seven days a week. At some point, I don't care who you are, you're going to lose track of what's going on. I mean, I never professed to be the businessman of the year. I'm not trying to make excuses here, but I was way over my head.</p>
        <p>So how did you first become aware of what was actually going on?</p>
        <p>We were in bankruptcy and I was soliciting investment people. Any money person wants to see detailed record books, but it was obvious there were huge errors. Something was definitely wrong. It was a nightmare -- like you're in a building and it's crumbling and you're trying to hold everything up. I started taking funds from the restaurant and charging back the credits to the company. And then about two weeks after we started doing that, it just came tumbling down.</p>
        <p>Does it seem unfair that you got caught while you were trying to pay the money back, not while the crime was actually being committed?</p>
        <p>I didn't do the right thing, let's be honest. When I found out what was happening, I should have gone right away to the authorities and laid it out on the line. It was my vanity, my ego, my stupidity. I thought that I would be able to pay without it getting public. Rather than just come clean and blow the whistle, I tried to protect what I had.</p>
        <p>Once you were busted, you participated with the investigation and pleaded guilty to attempted theft. So you have to pay restitution, and you had to perform community service -- and you're not allowed to own a restaurant. But you are back in business as a chef. Did your new employers have qualms about hiring you?</p>
        <p>Of course they had qualms. And I had fears, because I didn't know how the press, the public would react. These were dear friends of mine and I didn't want to jeopardize them.</p>
        <p>You landed at Steak au Poivre, right? What have you been doing since then?</p>
        <p>As that was winding down I got involved at Asta Sera. And then shortly after that, I started working at Brasserie Bit. And now I'm also with Chat and Chew. Every day I go between the three of them.</p>
        <p>And you have a TV series starting ON WHATTK?, and the book CALLED WHAT TK?, which you did a year ago, just came out. Don't you worry that you're just falling back into the same pattern that got you into such trouble in the first place?</p>
        <p>If I had the choice I'd rather sit in one and just do the best job I possibly could. But I have the responsibility to pay back the restitution. Some people said, ''Ah, here he goes again.'' It's not that at all, it really isn't.</p>
        <p>Lately, it seems cooking has become a major spectator sport. How do you think it happened?</p>
        <p>It's a combination of things. In general, people go to a restaurant and that's their night out instead of running to the theater. And the restaurants have accommodated and become theater. The food itself became more dramatic, ingredients became much more exotic. And there are more forums for the chefs. The Food Network put them in the public's eye, and there are so many magazines, so many publishers. It's been growing over the last 8 to 10 years to the point where we have a very well known chef ON? ''Who Wants to Be a Millionaire.''</p>
        <p>You used to be at the top of that sport. Do you ever miss the old days? Before everything fell apart?</p>
        <p>Listen, I let a lot of friends down, I let a lot of my family down, I let down a lot of people that I didn't know. So I'm not looking to get back where I was. I don't deserve to get back where I was. You know, when I was a chef and I did very well, people would say, ''Oh, he's a very good chef.'' Then I went on PBS and Food Network, and people said, ''Oh, Ruggerio, he's an entertainer.'' And now they say, ''Oh, that's the guy who banged out the credit cards.'' I really, in my heart, I want to go back. Not to the entertainer -- I have to go back to the beginning, where I was a good cook. ''That's what he is. He's a good chef.'' If I ever get back to that I'd be very happy.</p>
        <p>Regina Schrambling</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
