<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Homeless Animals Face Homelessness Yet Again</title>
    <meta content="21DOGS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201262"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: MANHATTAN VALLEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dogs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cats</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sentient Creatures (Orgn)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Besbroda, Chitra</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Siegal, Nina</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dogs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cats</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000521T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E5DA123AF932A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="463" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Homeless Animals Face Homelessness Yet Again</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NINA SIEGAL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Siegal, Nina</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Chitra Besbroda, who runs Sentient Creatures, animal rescue service in Manhattan, says abused and abandoned dogs and cats will be homeless again unless she can find new quarters before lease ends in September; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Peggy came to her, at 10 weeks old, she had cigarette burns all over her body. ''She was this big,'' said Chitra Besbroda, cupping her small hands together. ''It was a willful act of cruelty.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Besbroda runs an animal rescue service, called Sentient Creatures, in a storefront on West 106th Street. As she has with  3,500 abandoned and abused animals over the last 27 years, Ms. Besbroda took in the puppy, tended her infected wounds, fed her, and saw her grow to a healthy 8-month-old.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Peggy came to her, at 10 weeks old, she had cigarette burns all over her body. ''She was this big,'' said Chitra Besbroda, cupping her small hands together. ''It was a willful act of cruelty.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Besbroda runs an animal rescue service, called Sentient Creatures, in a storefront on West 106th Street. As she has with  3,500 abandoned and abused animals over the last 27 years, Ms. Besbroda took in the puppy, tended her infected wounds, fed her, and saw her grow to a healthy 8-month-old.</p>
        <p>But now Peggy is one of 12 dogs and 11 cats that will lose their home once when Ms. Besbroda's lease ends in September. Unless she can find a new shelter near her Upper West Side home by then, these creatures will be homeless again.</p>
        <p>Ms. Besbroda rescued her first dog, Teddy, from an abandoned Harlem building in 1973, and then began to care for strays in her apartment or in the lots where they lived. She also coordinated adoptions of the animals. In 1997, she finally raised enough money to rent her 300-square-foot storefront near Columbus Avenue, but a few months after she moved in, she was threatened with eviction after neighbors complained about the barking dogs.</p>
        <p>She fought the case in court and won, but her landlord did not renew her lease, which will expire this fall. The landlord could not be reached for comment, and the building manager declined to comment.</p>
        <p>Finding another lease has not been easy, because many landlords do not allow pets, and because her nonprofit organization is financed by charitable donations and she has little money.</p>
        <p>By day, Ms. Besbroda is a clinical social worker at Public School 811 on the Upper West Side. When she is not working, she is searching vacant lots in Harlem for mistreated animals, collecting money for her rescue work or running the shelter with the help of two assistants.</p>
        <p>She estimates that it costs $5,000 a month to house, feed and care for the animals. But she is trying to raise at least $1 million to buy a brownstone in which she could house a shelter and an animal clinic.</p>
        <p>''My heart is broken,'' Ms. Besbroda said. ''This space is not just a refuge for the dogs, it's a refuge for me too. Sometimes, when the weather is bad, I come here and sleep on the floor with the dogs because they're afraid. In the morning I come down here and read the paper, with all the dogs around me.''</p>
        <p>NINA SIEGAL</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: MANHATTAN VALLEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
