<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bringing Down Houses, From 'Mony Mony' to Opera</title>
    <meta content="21GURE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="41" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201033"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tucker, Richard, Award</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Turay, Gregory</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gurewitsch, Matthew</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000521T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE1D71E3BF932A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1953" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bringing Down Houses, From 'Mony Mony' to Opera</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW GUREWITSCH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gurewitsch, Matthew</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article profiles lyric tenor Gregory Turay, latest winner of Richard Tucker Award for classical singing; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I WAS basically a product of the pop generation,'' said the lyric tenor Gregory Turay, 27, the latest winner of the Richard Tucker Award, the fanciest American prize an American classical singer can win. Back in his teens, as a rocker with his father's band Time Trax, he would bring the house down with Tommy James's ''Mony Mony.''</p>
        <p>Look at him now, hair slicked back in the style of his more recent idol Jussi Bjoerling, singing impeccable Schubert and Schumann and Faure and Britten in lyric tones that tug gently at the heartstrings. Or as the final singer in a master class with the veteran Italian tenor Carlo Bergonzi early this month at the Kaye Playhouse, giving his all to the smitten Nemorino's love song from the first act of Donizetti's ''Elisir d'Amore'': for the first time during the evening, Mr. Bergonzi treats a young singer as a colleague rather than a novice, not dwelling on the rudiments but going straight for the fine points.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I WAS basically a product of the pop generation,'' said the lyric tenor Gregory Turay, 27, the latest winner of the Richard Tucker Award, the fanciest American prize an American classical singer can win. Back in his teens, as a rocker with his father's band Time Trax, he would bring the house down with Tommy James's ''Mony Mony.''</p>
        <p>Look at him now, hair slicked back in the style of his more recent idol Jussi Bjoerling, singing impeccable Schubert and Schumann and Faure and Britten in lyric tones that tug gently at the heartstrings. Or as the final singer in a master class with the veteran Italian tenor Carlo Bergonzi early this month at the Kaye Playhouse, giving his all to the smitten Nemorino's love song from the first act of Donizetti's ''Elisir d'Amore'': for the first time during the evening, Mr. Bergonzi treats a young singer as a colleague rather than a novice, not dwelling on the rudiments but going straight for the fine points.</p>
        <p>Last fall, the big thing in Mr. Turay's future was the premiere of William Bolcom's setting of Arthur Miller's blue-collar classic, ''A View From the Bridge,'' at the Lyric Opera of Chicago. Mr. Turay took the part of the illegal immigrant Rodolpho, a blond, starry-eyed Sicilian who was already a tenor in the play: no unalloyed blessing. ''You know what they're callin' him now?'' asks his resentful host. ''Paper Doll they're callin' him, Canary. He's like a weird. He comes out on the pier, one-two-three, it's a regular free show.'' (Read ''freak''?)</p>
        <p>Mr. Turay's colleagues in Chicago were a good deal more supportive. His first stab at Rodolpho's aria ''New York lights'' in rehearsal brought a rousing ovation from the rest of the cast. ''Get used to it,'' said the baritone Kim Josephson, who led the applause. ''He's going to bring the house down every night.'' And he did.</p>
        <p>By a quirk of scheduling not uncommon at so early a stage in a promising career, Mr. Turay's first major American encore has had to wait until tonight, in a concert performance of Bizet's seldom-heard ''Pecheurs de Perles'' with the Washington Concert Opera. Just added to his calendar is his San Francisco Opera debut next month, as Don Ottavio in ''Don Giovanni.'' Then he pretty much vanishes again, for a summer of study in Europe (punctuated by a Salzburg Festival debut in Mozart's ''Waisenhaus'' Mass). In the fall, important American engagements start proliferating: Mendelssohn's ''Elijah'' with the Handel and Haydn Society of Boston, and Mozart's ''Cosi Fan Tutte'' at the Detroit Opera and the Metropolitan. Then, in February, comes the coronation: the Richard Tucker Gala in Avery Fisher Hall.</p>
        <p>In the meantime, Mr. Turay has been getting to know firsthand the extremes of opera-house practice, European style. His debut with the Welsh National Opera, as Ferrando in a new ''Cosi Fan Tutte,'' exemplified the made-to-order ensemble approach: six weeks of sometimes bewildering rehearsal, followed by more than a dozen shows in seven cities. From there, it was off to Berlin for a hit-and-run debut in ''Zauberflote'' at the Deutsche Oper. Six hours of rehearsal (not bad in the circumstances), three performances in eight days, three casts, three conductors, dialogue (not much) in a language Mr. Turay does not speak.</p>
        <p>''That was scary,'' he said during a recent break back home in New York. ''I didn't meet my Paminas until intermission. I didn't meet the Sarastros until intermission. There were lots of transitions I'd never rehearsed. The assistant said: 'Don't worry. You're blindfolded. The supers will whisper to you and lead you around.' Whisper in German!</p>
        <p>''During the overture, I was sitting on the stage, wrapped in my costume with my heart racing, wondering, 'Why am I here?' I think I was having an anxiety attack. But in one way it was great. Six weeks of rehearsal, especially of a piece you've done before, can get boring. I'm a quick study. I'd prefer two weeks.''</p>
        <p>MR. TURAY spent his childhood at the stable his family owned and ran in Raymond, Wis.; when his mother died, his father, an accountant, relocated the family in Greendale. Though the younger Mr. Turay has no doubt that music is the career he was meant to have, it is not at all what he was bargaining for when he enrolled at the University of Kentucky.</p>
        <p>''I went to college to play baseball,'' he disclosed with a ghost of a smile, as quizzical as it was impish. ''I was a jock.'' A jock planning to major in business. Walking in unannounced to say he wanted to minor in voice, he was startled to learn that even the chorus required an audition.</p>
        <p>Since he had nothing prepared, the chairman of the voice faculty suggested the notoriously unsingable ''Star-Spangled Banner,'' and Mr. Turay complied. Next the chairman requested ''Silent Night,'' of which Mr. Turay managed one verse before blanking on the words. The next thing the young slugger knew, he was being offered a scholarship to major in voice. As he saw it then, maybe musicals would be the ticket. But his teacher Everett McCorvey introduced him to opera and the ''whole classical experience,'' in Mr. Turay's words, and he was on his way. Now it is his wife, Courtney Turay, who maintains the show-biz connection. She spent last summer in Fort Atkinson, Wis., as Magnolia in ''Show Boat.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Turay still relies on Mr. McCorvey, who, to judge by his star pupil's progress, has been doing an outstanding job. In 1995, at 23, Mr. Turay was named a winner of the Metropolitan Opera National Council Auditions, the youngest ever. In the fall of 1996, he entered the Met's young-artists program for three years of intensive study of languages and repertory and master classes with the likes of Mr. Bergonzi and Renata Scotto, interspersed with carefully monitored performances at the Met and elsewhere.</p>
        <p>In 1996, he won the Young Concert Artists auditions, which afforded him expert career guidance and management services, already superseded by the heavy artillery of Columbia Artists Management. The list of his prizes -- an ARIA, a Tucker, a George London, a D'Angelo -- is growing unwieldy.</p>
        <p>Young as he is in his profession, Mr. Turay is already a favorite at the Opera Theater of St. Louis, where he made his operatic debut in 1995.</p>
        <p>''I was on the panel of the Metropolitan national council auditions at Butler University, in Indianapolis, in Clowes Memorial Hall, that great big barn,'' said Charles MacKay, the company's general director. ''This fresh-faced 21-year-old walked out to sing the aria from the garden scene in 'Faust,' and I thought, 'Oh, sure.'</p>
        <p>''Then out came this voice of pure gold. It was the closest thing to Jussi Bjoerling I'd ever heard: so impeccably phrased, so poised, such a mature account of the aria. I was dumbstruck. Fortunately we had one role uncast: a tenor role, Clotarco, in Haydn's 'Armida.' I offered it to him then and there, and he accepted.'' Though the opera is obscure, Mr. Turay considered the part ideal for the occasion, including as it does some ensembles to get you out on the stage and an aria (just one) to get you noticed.</p>
        <p>Mr. Turay returned three seasons in a row, as the protagonist in Monteverdi's ''Orfeo,'' as Ernesto in ''Don Pasquale'' and, last summer, as Nadir in ''Les Pecheurs de Perles.'' In 1996, he was the serenading Fenton in Verdi's ''Falstaff'' at Wolf Trap in Virginia. To date, Mr. Turay's assignments at the Met have ranged from supporting roles in ''Ariadne auf Naxos,''  ''The Makropulos Case,''  ''Romeo et Juliette,''  ''Lucia di Lammermoor'' and ''Moses und Aron'' to the florid Don Ottavio. Like many singers, Mr. Turay classifies Mozart, along with Bellini and Donizetti, as ''medicine for the voice.''</p>
        <p>''I'm no fan of Janacek,'' he said, with the experience not only of the Met ''Makropulos'' but also of ''The Excursions of Mr. Broucek'' at the Spoleto Festival in Charleston, S.C., under his belt. ''He writes for instruments.''  ''Moses und Aron,'' he declared with like candor, was ''no fun.''</p>
        <p>The heavyweights of the tenor repertory are nowhere on Mr. Turay's immediately foreseeable agenda. His concert rendition of the throbbing verismo chestnut known as ''Il Lamento di Federico'' from Cilea's otherwise forgotten ''Arlesiana'' once won him an ovation that knocked the breath out of him, an experience he shows no sign of forgetting.</p>
        <p>But it has not turned his head. Even the lighter roles of Verdi and Puccini -- the Duke in ''Rigoletto,'' Alfredo in ''La Traviata'' and Rodolfo in ''La Boheme'' -- as well as Gounod's Romeo, all of which he has been offered, will have to wait. For now, Mr. Turay plans to stick with truly lyric repertory. Serious time abroad, with daily practice in the foreign languages he already articulates with more finesse than many natives, also remains a priority.</p>
        <p>The question is where, in the long run, the fast track will take him. By voice and temperament, Mr. Turay is at least as suited to the concert stage as to the opera house. In Brahms's ''Liebeslieder Waltzes'' in James Levine's Met Chamber Ensemble series at Weill Recital Hall a year and a half ago, his contributions as a member of the quartet were as expressive and gracious as his natural, deeply affectionate solos.</p>
        <p>Shortly after the Brahms, Mr. Levine took Mr. Turay along for Haydn's ''Creation'' with the Boston Symphony, and once again, the young artist proved exceptional, holding his own in a trio with the soprano Renee Fleming and the bass Rene Pape, both at the top of their eloquent form. As a recitalist, Mr. Turay is impressive, too; his unobtrusive yet telling gestures lend an extra dimension to the poetry of music and text.</p>
        <p>''I worry sometimes that it might look contrived,'' he said, ''but my personality is such, I can't just stand and sing.'' Frederica von Stade tells the story that at the start of her career, as she rose on cue at Carnegie Hall, Marilyn Horne leaned her way with a fierce stage whisper: ''Keep your face in the light. Keep your face in the light.'' Mr. Turay seems to do so by instinct. ''You have to communicate what's in your soul,'' he says simply. What counts in the end is the light that shines within.</p>
        <p>''Strive for perfection,'' the rising star likes to say. ''Settle for excellence.'' So far, he has seldom been inclined to settle. His own critiques are apt to be more exacting than the critics', and also more constructive. His models are the acknowledged pantheon: Pavarotti in his glory years (''for the voice and the beauty of the technique''), Nicolai Gedda, Giuseppe di Stefano, Beniamino Gigli.</p>
        <p>But above all, Bjoerling. Presented with a Bjoerling rarity not in his collection -- a lyric passage from a live ''Trovatore'' at the Royal Opera House, Covent Garden, ravishingly yet naturally sculptured, complete with trill -- Mr. Turay breathed deep.</p>
        <p>''When was that, 1939?'' he asked. ''So he was 28. There's no sliding, and the tone has such a shimmer. There's such classiness. I'll never sing that well.''</p>
        <p>MUSIC Matthew Gurewitsch writes about the arts for The Wall Street Journal and other publications.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Matthew Gurewitsch writes about the arts for The Wall Street Journal and other publications.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
