<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>East End Cola Guys vs. 'Them'</title>
    <meta content="21COLA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201175"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Soft Drinks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Long Island Beverage (Co)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Franco, Joe</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Karafian, Kenf</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hubel, Joy Alter</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soft Drinks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000521T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E3D8153AF932A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="817" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>East End Cola Guys vs. 'Them'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOY ALTER HUBEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hubel, Joy Alter</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of Long Island Beverage, whose owners, Joe Franco and brother-in-law Ken Karafian, have been waging war with cola giants for 15 years with their own brand, Island Cola; business, which is expanding to East End with new varieties, supplies soda systems strictly to fountain services in bars and restaurants; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AS Memorial Day nears and most mortgage-paying mortals are hoping to slow down for the season, Joe Franco is just revving up. ''I feel like a kid getting ready for his first race, and I can hardly wait to start running,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But this race will go to the fizziest.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AS Memorial Day nears and most mortgage-paying mortals are hoping to slow down for the season, Joe Franco is just revving up. ''I feel like a kid getting ready for his first race, and I can hardly wait to start running,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But this race will go to the fizziest.</p>
        <p>Mr. Franco and a partner, his brother-in-law Ken Karafian, own Long Island Beverage, which has battled the cola Goliaths with its own brand, Island Cola, for 15 years. The fight heats up in summer, when 65 percent of the money is made.</p>
        <p>This is a familiar battle, the local guy struggling against the behemoths from out of town. The Corner Bookshop takes on Borders; Village Pharmacy against Genovese; and now, Joe versus Coke.</p>
        <p>This year, Long Island Beverage fights the cola wars on a widening front. It recently entered the East End market with a varied arsenal of brand-name knockoffs, including Orange Rush, High-P (with a pink hue), BMW (which stands for black magic wonder) and Mountain Due.</p>
        <p>Despite his effervescence, Mr. Franco admits that soft drinks can be a hard sell, and sometimes wishes he had chosen another industry. The struggle to overcome brand loyalty, and the restrictions the large companies place on the stores that are their customers, can be daunting.</p>
        <p>But the small soda makers is still in the game. In five years it hopes to triple its business, which has reached $1.5 million in annual sales. Mr. Franco, once a regional sales manager for 7-Up, and Mr. Karafian, who worked in the nuclear power industry as an engineer, hatched their business plan in 1985, while on vacation in St. Martin.</p>
        <p>Their marketing objective was to supply soda systems strictly to the fountain services of bars and restaurants on Long Island. The fountain market, they reasoned, would be a niche where they were confident they could compete with Pepsi or Coke.</p>
        <p>''It's 80 percent water, 20 percent syrup,'' Mr. Franco said of the standard recipe. ''I figured that would level the playing field for us.''</p>
        <p>They hired a chemist in New Jersey to create some formulas and got to work, though Mr. Franco prefers to think of it as play. ''Our middle name is 'cup of fun,' '' he said.</p>
        <p>No wonder, considering that their idea was incubated beneath the bliss-inducing rays of a Caribbean sun.</p>
        <p>''This Rastafarian came by, overheard us talking about it, and said we should name ourselves Island Cola,'' Mr. Franco said. To the two Long Islanders, the idea seemed inspired.</p>
        <p>''We started out like Cheech and Chong, with a business plan, one dollar and a '78 Chevette,'' said Mr. Franco, who is 45.</p>
        <p>The Chevette has been replaced by a fleet of two service and three delivery vehicles, but it is still parked outside their 3,000-square-foot factory as a reminder of their humble beginnings. Their logo, a silhouette of a soda-chugging Rastafarian, recalls the Caribbean roots of the venture.</p>
        <p>Mr. Franco says Long Island Beverage had a competitive edge over some of better-advertised companies in its personal virtues. ''I can get to you right away,'' said Mr. Franco, who drives the Long Island Expressway seven days a week, from Elmont to Montauk, correcting delivery problems or quirks in his customers' fountain systems.</p>
        <p>Mr. Franco says the basis of good fountain soda is good water: clean, cold and well filtered. If it's not clean, the flavor will be corrupted; if it's not cold, it won't fizz.</p>
        <p>His soda systems, he said, have a filtration system that is attached to the water pipe, a tank or box of syrup, and canister of dry ice. All things being equal, and all equipment working properly, Long Island Beverage says its products are every bit as good as those of Big Soda.</p>
        <p>Are they? The question was put to a panel of teenage soda sippers: Billy Kempe, 14; Justine Taormino, 16, and Sarah Horney, 16. Alas, all three agreed that in the blind taste test, Island Cola came in second, to Pepsi.</p>
        <p>Not that it mattered. In the end the panelists were definitely pro-Joe. They especially liked the Rastafarian logo, and they gave a thumbs up on a new radio ad featuring background reggae. As summer heats up, they will be glad to lift another glass to toast Mr. Franco and Island Cola.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
