<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Vacation Abroad Always Includes Longing for Home</title>
    <meta content="21PLAC$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201073"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Paris (France)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Italy</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">London (Eng)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schembari, James</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England/London</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France/Paris</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000521T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE6D9163AF932A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="784" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Vacation Abroad Always Includes Longing for Home</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES SCHEMBARI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schembari, James</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>James Schembari, extolling beauty of Paris, Tuscany and London in summer, describes his longing for his suburban Connecticut home, backyard and neighbors (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOUR years ago my family and I spent part of the summer in Italy, hopping from one breathtaking Tuscan village to another. Two years ago we ogled Versailles and stood before the ''Mona Lisa'' at the Louvre. This year it will be the Tower of London and Hamlet at Shakespeare's Globe Theater along the Thames.</p>
        <p>While I have enjoyed my summer vacations, I always depart the New York airports troubled. The wonders of Europe are inviting, I muse, but summer in Connecticut is a glorious event, and who in their right mind would ever want to leave it?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOUR years ago my family and I spent part of the summer in Italy, hopping from one breathtaking Tuscan village to another. Two years ago we ogled Versailles and stood before the ''Mona Lisa'' at the Louvre. This year it will be the Tower of London and Hamlet at Shakespeare's Globe Theater along the Thames.</p>
        <p>While I have enjoyed my summer vacations, I always depart the New York airports troubled. The wonders of Europe are inviting, I muse, but summer in Connecticut is a glorious event, and who in their right mind would ever want to leave it?</p>
        <p>I'm sure the French feel that way about Paris, but, then, why does it always empty out in August? I bet I know where they're going.</p>
        <p>The fall rightfully gets a lot of attention around here, but Connecticut, with its combination of a gorgeous coast and New England countryside, offers a landscape that was made for summer escapes. But the best of summer is simpler than that. The highlight is our own backyards.</p>
        <p>For me, summer starts the day I get off the train from my job in the city and my children, with no homework tying them to the house, ride their bikes to the station and rush up to greet me when I step onto the platform. They shout, ''Dad!'' and every man getting off the train turns his head, hoping that shout is for him. Throughout the summer, those kind of shouts are often for me.</p>
        <p>I walk home with them, then we all sit on the backyard deck and eat dinner. Afterward, my wife, Christine, and I sit back, talk, maybe even have a drink, and watch the kids play in the yard. Sometimes we all go for a bike ride or a family walk with the dog, stopping to chat with our neighbors who are out doing the same thing. Sometimes we'll pile into the minivan and head for the town beach and stay until the sun goes down. Those relaxed summer evenings seem to last longer than the days.</p>
        <p>The next morning I head back to Manhattan, knowing that waiting for me at the end of the day is another mini-vacation. I could work every day during the summer and by September still feel like I had gone someplace wonderful.</p>
        <p>All of this must sound incredibly common, but I wait all year for the chance to wallow in suburbia. That's why when we start talking about going away for a summer vacation, my heart sinks. I'd love to go, but I don't want to leave.</p>
        <p>Can't we go away during the winter? Unfortunately, summer is the only time available to have an extended vacation with the children, who are all in school the rest of the year, the only time to bring them to interesting places, show them different cultures. We tend to do this every two years, partly because we couldn't afford to do it more, mostly because I couldn't bear to go away every year.</p>
        <p>The year we went to Paris, we watched the Bastille Day parade on the Champs-Elysees. The location was grand, but the parade was tedious. We all got bored and cranky as we sat on the hot pavement. Back home, dozens of our friends were getting ready for a neighborhood camp-out that weekend at Hammonasset Beach State Park in Madison. We couldn't make it because we were away.</p>
        <p>I don't want for a moment to insinuate that I would rather have been in Madison than in Paris. That would sound ridiculous and you would think me a rube. Let's just say that this year we have scheduled our trip to London after the annual camp-out.</p>
        <p>I am looking forward to London. I hear they have summer there, too, and it can be quite nice. This trip, as we did with Paris, we are cutting our costs by swapping houses with another family. That means other people will be enjoying my Connecticut summer, taking advantage of the suburban splendor I worked so hard to create. It wouldn't surprise me if they refused to leave.</p>
        <p>Two years ago the French family who stayed in our house were just leaving when we returned from Paris in late July. They asked how things had gone at their house and told us what a marvelous time they had at ours. They said they had bicycled to the beach, cooked out on our deck and went on day trips around the state.</p>
        <p>Which was exactly the kind of summer I was planning to have as soon as they got their luggage out of my house.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
