<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fight Already On for a House Seat That Could Prove Decisive</title>
    <meta content="21DIST$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="40" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000523T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201388"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE RACE FOR SENATE: THE CONGRESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">House of Representatives (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lambert, Bruce</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bishop, David A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Israel, Steven J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">McGown, Peter</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lazio, Rick A (Repr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000521T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE5DE113AF932A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="724" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fight Already On for a House Seat That Could Prove Decisive</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRUCE LAMBERT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lambert, Bruce</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>As Rep Rick A Lazio suits up to become Republican candidate for US Senate, politicians in his Long Island district are already fighting to succeed him in House; two Democrats, Suffolk County Legislature minority leader David A Bishop and Huntington Town Board majority leader Steven J Israel, are competing for their party's nomination and Republican forces are rallying behind town of Islip supervisor Peter McGowan; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As Representative Rick A. Lazio suits up to become the Republican candidate for the United States Senate, politicians back home in his Long Island district are already fighting to succeed him in the House of Representatives.</p>
        <p>Both major parties are expected to focus on the Second Congressional District seat that Mr. Lazio is vacating as one that could flip either way in the November election. The outcome there will help decide which side captures the majority in the House for the next two years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As Representative Rick A. Lazio suits up to become the Republican candidate for the United States Senate, politicians back home in his Long Island district are already fighting to succeed him in the House of Representatives.</p>
        <p>Both major parties are expected to focus on the Second Congressional District seat that Mr. Lazio is vacating as one that could flip either way in the November election. The outcome there will help decide which side captures the majority in the House for the next two years.</p>
        <p>''There will be war for this seat, and it will transcend Long Island because control of the House is very much at stake,'' said Alan Eysen, a political consultant who has worked for Republicans and Democrats.</p>
        <p>Two Democrats -- the Suffolk County Legislature's minority leader, David A. Bishop, and the Huntington Town Board's majority leader, Steven J. Israel -- are competing for their party's nomination.</p>
        <p>On the Republican side, the party's Suffolk County chairman, Anthony Apollaro, is trying to rally his forces behind the popular supervisor of the town of Islip, Peter McGowan.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio's decision to run for the Senate makes his Congressional district one of the few open seats in the nation. Although the Second District has a roughly 2-to-1 Republican edge in voter enrollment, for 18 years it elected a Democrat, Thomas Downey, until Mr. Lazio defeated him in 1992.</p>
        <p>''Long Islanders are a bunch of ticket splitters, especially in Suffolk,'' said Michael D. Dawidziak, a political consultant and longtime adviser to Mr. Lazio.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio's district encompasses the middle-class South Shore communities of Babylon, where Democrats are the strongest, and Islip, which is staunchly Republican. It also includes part of Huntington, which is a swing area, and a small part of Smithtown. About 85 percent of the residents are white, but Hispanics are a growing minority, at 10 percent.</p>
        <p>The sudden scramble for the Second District seat was prompted by Rudolph W. Giuliani's withdrawal from the Senate race on Friday. For months, Mr. Lazio had put his own senatorial ambitions on hold as Mr. Giuliani geared up a major campaign and raised millions of dollars.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Lazio first explored running for the Senate, Mr. Bishop and Mr. Israel began maneuvering to succeed him. When he deferred to Mr. Giuliani, they pulled back. And now that Mr. Lazio is moving on, they are pouncing.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bishop claimed the support of the party's leaders in the towns of Babylon and Islip, which make up most of the district. But Mr. Israel said he was prepared to mount a primary challenge.</p>
        <p>Both Democrats are considered strong contenders.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bishop, 35, is a lawyer who once was an intern for Senator Charles E. Schumer when he was a United States representative. Since 1993, Mr. Bishop has served in the Suffolk Legislature from the 14th District, a 2-to-1 Republican stronghold that is in the heart of the Congressional district. He points to his record of bipartisan cooperation in the County Legislature and says his main issues are the economy, education and the environment. He has a reputation as a dogged door-to-door campaigner.</p>
        <p>Mr. Israel, 42, was an aide to Richard Ottinger, the former congressman. In 1993 he won a seat on the Huntington board and in later elections helped bring on two more Democrats to form a majority. He points to his record of bipartisan cooperation with the Republican town supervisor, Frank P. Petrone, in cutting taxes and rectifying finances. He calls himself a progressive on social issues and stresses child care and the environment. He is considered a gifted speaker and fund-raiser.</p>
        <p>Among the Republicans, one stands above the rest. ''They've got a 900-pound gorilla, and that's Pete McGowan,'' Mr. Dawidziak said. As an eight-year incumbent at the helm of a major town in the Congressional district, Mr. McGowan would be the most formidable Republican candidate, most party leaders agree.</p>
        <p>But there is no shortage of other names being mentioned. They include two assemblymen, Philip M. Boyle and Thomas F. Barraga; two Islip Town Board members, Pamela Greene and Christopher Bodkin; a county legislator, Angie Carpenter; a Suffolk prosecutor, Pierce Cohalan; and a planning official who once ran against Mr. Downey, Harold Withers.</p>
        <p>THE RACE FOR SENATE: THE CONGRESS  Correction:  May 23, 2000, Tuesday  An article on Sunday about the coming election for the House seat that is being vacated on Long Island by Representative Rick A. Lazio referred incorrectly in some copies to the job held by a possible candidate, Pierce Cohalan. He is an assistant district attorney. It is his father, Peter F. Cohalan, who is a State Supreme Court justice.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 23, 2000, Tuesday</p>
        <p>An article on Sunday about the coming election for the House seat that is being vacated on Long Island by Representative Rick A. Lazio referred incorrectly in some copies to the job held by a possible candidate, Pierce Cohalan. He is an assistant district attorney. It is his father, Peter F. Cohalan, who is a State Supreme Court justice.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
