<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Markets, But From Where?</title>
    <meta content="LTR020627" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201341"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Grant, Stephen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shiller, Robert J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000521T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E2DF103AF932A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="335" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Markets, But From Where?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Stephen Grant, letter, responds to Robert J Shiller's April 30 suggestion that one antidote to overvalue stock market is increase in number and variety of securities and the markets that trade them (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Robert J. Shiller, the Yale professor and author, says one antidote to what he sees as an overvalued United States stock market is to increase the number and varieties of securities, and the markets that trade them (''Wealthy Market? Yes. Healthy? Wise? No,'' April 30).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Robert J. Shiller, the Yale professor and author, says one antidote to what he sees as an overvalued United States stock market is to increase the number and varieties of securities, and the markets that trade them (''Wealthy Market? Yes. Healthy? Wise? No,'' April 30).</p>
        <p>To increase financial stability and personal security, Professor Shiller proposes markets that would trade new financial instruments linked to the national income of countries, future income of occupation groups and the value of single-family homes.</p>
        <p>There are several fundamental problems with his approach. To begin with, financial markets require sufficient volume in both demand (buyers) and supply (sellers) for a similar product (shares of stock, government debt, soybeans). None of the derivatives Professor Shiller proposed meet these basic tests.</p>
        <p>Also, the future income of even a seemingly homogenous group of workers like physicians varies far too widely based on employment status (group practice versus solo), specialty, age, location, etc. Single-family homes are notoriously dissimilar and illiquid. And the future national income remains an academic concept too often buffeted by political winds.</p>
        <p>Additionally, no securities markets exist or are likely to be naturally created for the proposed derivatives. So it would fall upon the government to create them. Investors would be expected to trade unproven derivatives on a market created and supported by government.</p>
        <p>I realize that Professor Shiller has become the savant of this latest market crisis, but wasn't the last market crisis -- Long-Term Capital's undoing -- caused by illiquid and unproven derivatives?</p>
        <p>STEPHEN GRANT  Aiken, S.C., April 30</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
