<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Body, as Mannequin, Reinterpreted</title>
    <meta content="21SEM.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201134"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ART REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Jersey City Museum</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Semmel, Joan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schwabsky, Barry</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000521T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E4DA143AF932A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="946" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Body, as Mannequin, Reinterpreted</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARRY SCHWABSKY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schwabsky, Barry</byline>
      <dateline>JERSEY CITY</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Barry Schwabsky reviews recent works by Joan Semmel on view at Jersey City Museum; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN the 1970's, Joan Semmel achieved some prominence for her big, ambitious figurative paintings, which were seen as part of a new wave of feminist art. In her best-known works, the artist's nude body was seen from her own viewpoint, with her feet back near the vanishing point of the pictures' perspective. The idea was to show that the female nude need not be portrayed only from the viewpoint of the desiring or appraising male but also according to a woman's own subjectivity -- and then to put the viewer in the position of the self-witnessing artist.</p>
        <p>More recently, Ms. Semmel's career has been proceeding with much less of the attention it had received in the heyday of feminist art, although her work came in for renewed notice last year when one of her early paintings was included in an exhibition curated by the influential younger artist Robert Gober. That exhibition was followed by a one-person show at a small New York gallery, but the Jersey City Museum is offering the best opportunity in some time to catch up on her work.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN the 1970's, Joan Semmel achieved some prominence for her big, ambitious figurative paintings, which were seen as part of a new wave of feminist art. In her best-known works, the artist's nude body was seen from her own viewpoint, with her feet back near the vanishing point of the pictures' perspective. The idea was to show that the female nude need not be portrayed only from the viewpoint of the desiring or appraising male but also according to a woman's own subjectivity -- and then to put the viewer in the position of the self-witnessing artist.</p>
        <p>More recently, Ms. Semmel's career has been proceeding with much less of the attention it had received in the heyday of feminist art, although her work came in for renewed notice last year when one of her early paintings was included in an exhibition curated by the influential younger artist Robert Gober. That exhibition was followed by a one-person show at a small New York gallery, but the Jersey City Museum is offering the best opportunity in some time to catch up on her work.</p>
        <p>The 20 paintings on view here, dating from 1996 to the present, show that Ms. Semmel is still as fascinated by the body as ever, but she's approaching the subject in a more indirect way these days: by using mannequins as stand-ins.</p>
        <p>The idea is not exactly unprecedented. Around 1914 the Italian artist Giorgio de Chirico began using tailors' dummies and plaster statues as surrogate figures to give his paintings some of their eerie, enigmatic atmosphere. The device has been a surrealist staple ever since. But the stolid naturalism of Ms. Semmel's style allows her to give a distinct, personal bent to this familiar device. Here, it brings out the artificiality of our ideas of beauty and glamour -- and, because the mannequins are often broken or fragmented, as in ''Spare Parts,'' 1998, the fragility of those ideas as well.</p>
        <p>The earliest of these paintings, ''SoHo Display,'' 1996, is quite different from the ones that followed. In it, a group of unclothed mannequins are seen bunched together on the other side of a store's display window. Here Ms. Semmel seems less interested in the dummies themselves than in the glass that separates them from the outside world, but which also undermines, through the play of reflections, the viewer's ability to identify inside and outside.</p>
        <p>If ''SoHo Display'' is working with an idea of surrogacy, it is not of the mannequin as a stand-in for the human figure, but of the store window as a surrogate for the modernist ideal of the flat, unified picture plane.</p>
        <p>In the rest of the paintings, the mannequins are depicted from a viewpoint located within the same clearly depicted space -- a space that is classical, not modernist. Furthermore, the mannequins in ''SoHo Display'' were themselves highly abstracted -- they follow the shape of the torso without attempting to depict its surface, and lacked legs, hands, eyes and mouths. The mannequins Ms. Semmel depicts in the subsequent paintings are relatively realistic depictions of women (and, less often, of men). Furthermore, having articulated limbs and moveable torsos, they can be posed, allowing for hints of narrative.</p>
        <p>What the paintings gain in terms of thematic richness, they mostly lose in terms of formal resolution, and yet I can't regret the difference: they are less successful but more interesting. Still, Ms. Semmel's uncertain command of her subject even comes through in the paintings' titles, meant to be playful, which often trivialize them: ''Oy Ve,'' 1999, shows a mannequin prone, its hand raised to its forehead in a gesture that could be seen as melodramatic; a 1997 painting whose male mannequin has lost its hands is, unfortunately, ''Hands Off''; and then there's ''Busted Butt,'' 1997 -- well, you get the idea.</p>
        <p>A painter isn't judged by her way with words, though, and one could forgive these titling faux pas if the paintings were entirely convincing visually. The problem, though, is that Ms. Semmel's figures -- if that term properly applies to mannequins -- are often awkwardly integrated into the space she's created for them. For instance, I can understand her choice of a sickly yellow-green light for the atmosphere in ''Multiples,'' 1998, but it's not convincing that the mannequin has really been perceived in that light -- even despite the bright green highlight the artist has rather ostentatiously added to her forearm.</p>
        <p>Luckily, Ms. Semmel's infectious fascination with the sensuality of paint itself can sometimes be persuasive enough to outflank such difficulties. Usually that happens when she evokes the forms and surfaces of the mannequins' bodies so convincingly that she might as well be painting real people. She models the big hips of the mannequin in ''Oy Ve,'' for instance, with the kind of relish that Courbet used to lavish on his nudes. (One wonders, do they really make such voluptuous mannequins?)</p>
        <p>Posted outside the gallery in which these paintings hang is a small sign that cautions: ''This exhibition contains nudity. Parental guidance is suggested.'' There's something comical about the fact that an unclothed mannequin is considered a perilous instance of nudity -- but at best, Ms. Semmel's paintings earn their warning.</p>
        <p>THE MANNEQUIN SERIES:  Recent Work by Joan Semmel</p>
        <p>Jersey City Museum, 472 Jersey Avenue, Jersey City.</p>
        <p>Through June 3. Tuesday, Thursday, Friday and Saturday, 10:30 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Wednesday, 10:30 a.m. to 8 p.m.  (201) 547-5655.</p>
        <p>ART REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
