<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Chance to Live Like The Rockefellers, At Least in Fantasy</title>
    <meta content="21TOUR$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201078"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Kykuit (Rockefeller Mansion)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Pocantico Hills (Ny)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rockefeller Family</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ames, Lynne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mansions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000521T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE2D8163AF932A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="988" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Chance to Live Like The Rockefellers, At Least in Fantasy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYNNE AMES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ames, Lynne</byline>
      <dateline>POCANTICO HILLS</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on volunteers at Kykuit, home to four generations of Rockefellers in Pocantico Hills, NY; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ON a flawless summer day, a visitor to Kykuit can stand in the entranceway and gaze at the six-story stone house and beyond, for a vista of bluffs and water and cloud-patched sky straight out of a Hudson River School painting.</p>
        <p>This year it will be easier than ever to visit the mansion that was home to four generations of Rockefellers and perhaps engage in a few fantasies about what it would have been like to live within the walls of Kykuit, stroll its formal gardens and landscaped terraces and help fill its rooms and grounds with sculpture and paintings.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ON a flawless summer day, a visitor to Kykuit can stand in the entranceway and gaze at the six-story stone house and beyond, for a vista of bluffs and water and cloud-patched sky straight out of a Hudson River School painting.</p>
        <p>This year it will be easier than ever to visit the mansion that was home to four generations of Rockefellers and perhaps engage in a few fantasies about what it would have been like to live within the walls of Kykuit, stroll its formal gardens and landscaped terraces and help fill its rooms and grounds with sculpture and paintings.</p>
        <p>For the first time since the estate opened to the public in 1994, visitors can come without advance reservations.</p>
        <p>The number of visitors may increase to 50,000 this year, up from 45,000 last year, said Susan Greenstein, director of the Kykuit program for Historic Hudson Valley, the nonprofit educational organization that administers Kykuit's visitors' program.  And that means more demand for volunteers (last year there were 18). Although 60 paid guides are employed at Kykuit, there is a need for more people who want to be part of the Kykuit scene, if only for a few hours each week.</p>
        <p>''Volunteers play a vital role,'' said Toni McNair, manager of Kykuit programs. ''They are the core of our hospitality staff. They answer questions. They help in lots of ways. They ensure visitor satisfaction.''</p>
        <p>Although they won't be compensated in dollars, volunteers are sure to derive some satisfaction of their own. This year volunteers will be stationed in the vast entranceway, known as the forecourt, and in the Inner Gardens. (Previously, volunteers were only stationed at the visitors' center at Philipsburg Manor, where they guided tourists onto the minibuses that make the seven-minute ride to Kykuit.) They will do everything from politely suggesting to stragglers that they keep up with the guided tour to answering mundane questions like ''where's the restroom?'' to queries about the historic aspects of the property.</p>
        <p>And they will get to immerse themselves in the grandeur of the place, which should be fun for anyone with a sense of history, aesthetics and imagination.</p>
        <p>''If I lived here, I'd sit in the gardens and read all day, biographies of people I admire,'' said one volunteer, Marilyn Ruskin, who lives in Hartsdale and is an office manager for the Westchester County Department of Emergency Services. Interviewed at a recent orientation for volunteers, she said she also liked the multiplicity of china services that she saw during a walk-through of the bowels of the house. ''If I was in a blue mood, I'd use the blue dishes; another mood, another color dishes.''</p>
        <p>Ruth Viebrock, a nurse from Hawthorne, said this would be her second season volunteering for Historic Hudson Valley. ''I've been in hospitals my whole life,'' she said. ''I needed a different perspective. I really can't imagine living in this type of luxury. But if I did, I imagine I would get involved in a lot of philanthropic work. And for enjoyment -- well, the tea house would be a nice little escape.''</p>
        <p>The tea house is in the Inner Garden. Kykuit literature describes it as of Italianate design, with ceilings painted in the ''grotesque'' style Raphael used to decorate the Vatican loggias. It was said to be one of the favorite retreats of Laura Spellman Rockefeller, wife of John D. Rockefeller, who lived at Kykuit from 1908 until his death in 1937. His son, John D. Rockefeller Jr., builder of Rockefeller Center, lived there from 1937 to 1960 with his wife, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller, a founder of the Museum of Modern Art. Nelson A. Rockefeller, four-time New York governor and later vice president, lived at the mansion from 1963 to 1979 with his wife, Margueretta Fitler (Happy) Rockefeller, and their sons, Nelson Jr. and Mark.</p>
        <p>The house was built between 1906 and 1913. The architects were Chester Holmes Aldrich and William Adam Delano. The facade was rebuilt, and other changes were made by William Welles Bosworth, who also created the gardens. It draws on elements of Greek, Roman and Italian Renaissance architecture, with elaborate carvings emblematic of spring, summer and fall -- winter is omitted because the house was originally never used in that season.</p>
        <p>As imposing as the facade is, the Oceanus Fountain, with its 20-foot diameter, 35-ton bowl and 40-foot-high statue of Oceanus, father of the river gods in Roman mythology, is even more impressive. Some volunteers at the orientation gasped at the sheer size of it, then did the same when viewing some of the sculpture and paintings in the Rockefeller collection.</p>
        <p>Even Candy Scalberg, visitors' services coordinator for Kykuit and a former volunteer, who has seen the place many times, never fails to be impressed. ''My heart soars just to be here,'' she said.</p>
        <p>A more blase attitude was expressed by Liz McBride, retired from administrative work, who has volunteered at Historic Hudson Valley for four years. Speculating on what she would do if she lived there, she replied: ''Oh, I don't know. Read a lot, stroll the gardens. Knit, sew. I'd pursue my little hobbies much as I do now.''</p>
        <p>Those who wish to volunteer should call 631-3992, ext. 33. People who want more information about touring the house and grounds can call 631-8200. Reservations are required only for groups of 10 or more. Tickets for individuals are $20, less for children, students and those over 60.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
