<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rock's Original Poets, Still Howling</title>
    <meta content="21HOLD$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="39" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000604T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201018"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Poetry and Poets</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holden, Stephen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dylan, Bob</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, Patti</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reed, Lou</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kerouac, Jack (1922-69)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ginsberg, Allen (1926-97)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Burroughs, William S (1914-97)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Poetry and Poets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000521T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E4DB1E3BF932A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1584" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rock's Original Poets, Still Howling</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN HOLDEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Holden, Stephen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Stephen Holden article says Beat generation literary trilogy of Jack Kerouac, William Burroughs and Allen Ginsberg had profound impact on rock culture, setting fervent, iconoclastic tone for younger generation; says three of rock's early poets--Bob Dylan, Patti Smith and Lou Reed--are, in their 50's, still carrying on the Beats' mission of crying out from the urban wilderness; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN Allen Ginsberg, the last surviving member of the Beat trinity that included Jack Kerouac and William Burroughs, died three years ago, it was entirely appropriate that Lou Reed and Patti Smith be prominent among those participating in the ceremonies honoring Walt Whitman's greatest poetic descendant. Four decades earlier, Ginsberg had emerged on the literary scene like a bardic John the Baptist. This raving, shaggy-haired voice from the urban wilderness arrived strewing incantatory broadsides whose blunt evocations of homosexuality, drug delirium and political paranoia wafted a pungent body odor into the genteel tea party of American letters.</p>
        <p>The shock waves of Ginsberg's ''Howl,'' Kerouac's ''On the Road'' and Burroughs's ''Naked Lunch'' radiated far beyond the academy. It's clear today that as much as the Beats helped loosen the academic straitjacket constricting American literature, they had a far more profound impact on rock culture. They set the fervent, iconoclastic tone for rock's prophetic strain and enticed a younger generation of aspiring poets to inflate folk and rock music with oracular utterance. To make some crude analogies: Bob Dylan, in his early wandering-minstrel period, became the movement's Kerouac; Mr. Reed, with his urban gallows humor and fascination with drugs and outlaw sexuality, its Burroughs, and Ms. Smith, with her shamanistic fervor, its Ginsberg.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN Allen Ginsberg, the last surviving member of the Beat trinity that included Jack Kerouac and William Burroughs, died three years ago, it was entirely appropriate that Lou Reed and Patti Smith be prominent among those participating in the ceremonies honoring Walt Whitman's greatest poetic descendant. Four decades earlier, Ginsberg had emerged on the literary scene like a bardic John the Baptist. This raving, shaggy-haired voice from the urban wilderness arrived strewing incantatory broadsides whose blunt evocations of homosexuality, drug delirium and political paranoia wafted a pungent body odor into the genteel tea party of American letters.</p>
        <p>The shock waves of Ginsberg's ''Howl,'' Kerouac's ''On the Road'' and Burroughs's ''Naked Lunch'' radiated far beyond the academy. It's clear today that as much as the Beats helped loosen the academic straitjacket constricting American literature, they had a far more profound impact on rock culture. They set the fervent, iconoclastic tone for rock's prophetic strain and enticed a younger generation of aspiring poets to inflate folk and rock music with oracular utterance. To make some crude analogies: Bob Dylan, in his early wandering-minstrel period, became the movement's Kerouac; Mr. Reed, with his urban gallows humor and fascination with drugs and outlaw sexuality, its Burroughs, and Ms. Smith, with her shamanistic fervor, its Ginsberg.</p>
        <p>The hardiness of this strain of rock is evidenced by the career longevity of all three performers, now in their 50's and still going strong, although their significance in the marketplace has diminished. Largely indifferent to pop trends, they have continued doing what they've always done, amassing larger and more impressive bodies of work. Each has produced enough powerful, rough-hewn rock poetry to be a one-person subgenre.</p>
        <p>In an odd symmetry, the three have also reverted to what Ginsberg started out as: insistent voices from the urban wilderness. The genteel tea party that Ginsberg helped disperse may have broken up decades ago, but its contemporary pop equivalent is the MTV-ready candy store of boy bands and wriggling sassy-voiced cupcakes peddling Florida sunshine. With the retreat of poetry from the pop arena, the Dylans, Reeds, Smiths and their ilk have become de facto custodians of the Beat aesthetic. The more time goes by, the more they seem like vital cultural elder statesmen.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dylan's last album, ''Time Out of Mind,'' with its growling blues-inflected rants, is as thorny and indifferent to trends as any rock album to have appeared during the last decade. Mr. Reed's newest album, ''Ecstasy'' (Reprise 947425-2), and Ms. Smith's latest, ''Gung Ho'' (Arista 07822-14618-2), also find both performers doing what they do best: ranting, brooding, meditating, philosophizing and praying, in their own way doing whatever it takes to evoke the demonic and ecstatic modes of transcendence pursued by the Beats.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reed's album is a sprawling, mostly brown-and-black musical canvas devoted to relationships, in which the singer plays various high-strung, embittered men chewing over their life choices and the disappointments and compromises involved in belonging to a couple. For Mr. Reed, guitar tones and textures (often droning and abrasive) and dramatic variations on his insinuating vocal monotone are as important as poetry in creating these antiromantic vignettes, the best of which convey a nagging, corrosive feeling of adult frustration.</p>
        <p>Working with the producer Hal Wilner, an expert at innovative art-rock coloration, and his longtime guitar partner, Mike Rathke, Mr. Reed has subtly expanded the textures of his newest songs to bring in shades of bossa nova (on ''Ecstasy''); on ''Rock Minuet,'' he sandwiches his hushed vocal delivery between extremes of harsh guitar and Laurie Anderson's ethereal electric violin.</p>
        <p>''Ecstasy'' is one of several songs in which Mr. Reed forsakes his domestic scenarios to enter the mind of a sensation-seeking loner. The song's narrator, who goes by the pseudonyms St. Ivory and St. Maurice (names worthy of Jean Genet) and describes himself as ''smooth as alabaster,'' muses as though in a heroin trance on an elusive phantom lover that is more a state of mind than a person. This sly, seductive song is really about how life's highest highs don't stick.</p>
        <p>A far more savage version of the loner figure haunts ''Rock Minuet,'' the story of a patricidal sadomasochist whose ultimate kick comes from observing two men in the back of a lower Manhattan warehouse having their eyes sewn shut. Finally we have ''Like a Possum,'' the album's 18-minute cri de coeur, a crack addict's blood-chilling monologue that twists up like an avenging specter from a grinding bed of guitar fuzz and feedback. As Mr. Reed, his voice quivering with rage and desperation, shouts, ''I've got a hole in my heart the size of a truck!'' he becomes the voice of every frenzied drug and sex addict ever to stalk the docks of lower Manhattan.</p>
        <p>This latest and most extreme variation of Mr. Reed's continuing walk on the wild side contains some of his most potent pop poetry. ''The devil tried to fill me up/ But my down was high as the sky is up,'' goes one memorable couplet. ''Like a Possum'' leaves you wondering if this vision of undomesticated, drug-fueled, insatiable male energy is Mr. Reed's nightmare vision of his own life had he not chosen a different path.</p>
        <p>The path he did choose is described in the speech-song of ''Turning Time Around,'' in which the narrator is asked to define love, thinks it over, and decides it is ''turning time around.'' The quietly touching song looks back to the austere autobiographical monologues of Mr. Reed's 1980's albums ''The Blue Mask'' and ''Legendary Hearts,'' in which he first embraced an ecstatic, Zen-like asceticism.</p>
        <p>But for all the sincerity with which Mr. Reed imparts such nuggets of hard-won wisdom, his chilly, poker-faced portrayals of personal happiness are not exactly inviting. Songs like ''Turning Time Around'' suggest a man huddled in a small, safe, bare little cubicle outside of which a nightmare is howling and clamoring to get in.</p>
        <p>Ms. Smith, unlike Mr. Reed (whose songs express little trust in humanity), really believes that ''people have the power,'' as she once put it in a famous rock anthem. And some of the most rousing numbers on ''Gung Ho'' are similar invocations, beautifully underlined by the gleaming, anthemic guitars of Lenny Kaye and Oliver Ray. Songs like ''One Voice,'' ''Gone Pie,''  ''Grateful'' and the utopian ''New Party'' are exhortative communal prayers, led by Ms. Smith playing her customary role of rock priestess and shaman.</p>
        <p>The idea of anyone's presuming to be a rock priestess in this day and age may seem silly. But Ms. Smith, as much as anyone, including Mr. Dylan in his prophetic mode, has the voice and the poetic diction for the job. In her lyrics she has refined a wonderfully flexible blend of mystical, incantatory, sometimes quasi-Biblical language and stylized street-wise argot that can stretch in either direction, depending on the song.</p>
        <p>What ignites this poetry is a singing voice that hovers between a sob and a sneer, between 1960's girl-group enthusiasm and poetic speech-song. Ms. Smith conveys an intense spontaneity that is deceptive. Vocally she knows exactly how to get powerful rhetorical effects, yet she rarely sounds affected. Just when she seems about to get too far up on her high horse, as in the sneering ''New Party,'' an undertone of punkish humor insinuates itself in her singing to help lighten things up.</p>
        <p>Ms. Smith, like Mr. Reed, favors large-scale songs. And ''Gung Ho'' contains two of her finest in ''Strange Messengers'' and the title song, in both of which she presumes to play the world's moral conscience and exorcist of demons. ''Strange Messengers,'' a relentlessly pounding incantation, conjures up nightmare visions of the slave trade and its consequences in strong, almost calligraphic images of slave auctions and lynchings and the angry spirits of the tyrannized slaughtered who will not be stilled. The song turns on lines Ms. Smith intones with a pained gravity: ''Men knew it was wrong/  But they looked away.''</p>
        <p>The album's title song, an evocation of the life of Ho Chi Minh, is grander in scale and even more effective. Performed mostly in speech-song against an ominous, ticking beat overlain with hollow echoing guitars, the song portrays the uprising of the Indochinese against their colonial masters as an inevitable, slowly grinding process fraught with agony and nobility.</p>
        <p>The Vietnamese leader isn't viewed as an individual but as the collective spirit of the people. And the lyric brilliantly uses images of the revolution's turning ''wheel'' and the planting of seeds to suggest both the hard labor of the millions being exploited and the political revolution being born. Sound effects -- the ominous putter of a helicopter and gasping breaths -- heighten the intensity of a song that carries the fervor of late-60's protest music way beyond didactic singsong and into a deeper realm of historical meditation.</p>
        <p>MUSIC  Correction:  June 4, 2000, Sunday  An article on May 21 about the singers Lou Reed and Patti Smith as custodians of the Beat aesthetic misstated the order of deaths of the writers Allen Ginsberg and William S. Burroughs. Ginsberg died in April 1997; Burroughs died four months later.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 4, 2000, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article on May 21 about the singers Lou Reed and Patti Smith as custodians of the Beat aesthetic misstated the order of deaths of the writers Allen Ginsberg and William S. Burroughs. Ginsberg died in April 1997; Burroughs died four months later.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
