<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Teaching Tiny Dancers the Steps to a Dream</title>
    <meta content="21COLM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201158"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="COPING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Urban Bush Women</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">92d Street Y</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Garcia, Carolina</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lee, Felicia R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000521T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05EFD9143AF932A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="844" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Teaching Tiny Dancers the Steps to a Dream</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FELICIA R. LEE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lee, Felicia R</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Felicia R Lee Coping column on recent visit by Urban Bush Women troupe dancer Carolina Garcia to PS 146 in East Harlem, under auspices of Dance Introduction program at 92nd Street Y; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CAROLINA GARCIA, petite and imposing, stood in front of the auditorium at Public School 146 in East Harlem. Ms. Garcia, a dancer in the Urban Bush Women troupe, was full of questions for the wiggling third graders: What is culture? What is a gesture? What is your name? What is your favorite color?</p>
        <p>It was a sunny Monday. Ms. Garcia's high-energy shenanigans (she sang, she danced) were a good way to start the school week for Julie Rosenthal's class. In this patch of Manhattan, it is a big deal to go to the theater, a museum or the ballet. Dancing is something people do on MTV. The beautiful and graceful Ms. Garcia, dressed in black, brought it on home, looking and talking like a homegirl who is also a citizen of the world.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CAROLINA GARCIA, petite and imposing, stood in front of the auditorium at Public School 146 in East Harlem. Ms. Garcia, a dancer in the Urban Bush Women troupe, was full of questions for the wiggling third graders: What is culture? What is a gesture? What is your name? What is your favorite color?</p>
        <p>It was a sunny Monday. Ms. Garcia's high-energy shenanigans (she sang, she danced) were a good way to start the school week for Julie Rosenthal's class. In this patch of Manhattan, it is a big deal to go to the theater, a museum or the ballet. Dancing is something people do on MTV. The beautiful and graceful Ms. Garcia, dressed in black, brought it on home, looking and talking like a homegirl who is also a citizen of the world.</p>
        <p>She did a few dance movements, and some of the students said it reminded them of ''nasty'' dancing on television.</p>
        <p>''All over the world there are people who use their whole bodies in different ways, that represent nature or fertility and many other things,'' said Ms. Garcia, who is Cuban-American. ''You have to think many ways. You can't let television make you think one way.''</p>
        <p>The silence and wide-eyed looks meant Ms. Garcia was getting through. The students had questions, too. Was she limber? Did people recognize her when she walked down the street? And where do they dance, these Urban Bush Women?</p>
        <p>Taking it all in along with the students was Laura Silver, the principal. Ms. Silver said parents in this struggling community had the same hopes for their children as anyone else, but the idea of exposing them to the kind of dance, art and music found in grandiose buildings in mostly rich, white neighborhoods was intimidating.</p>
        <p>Many of the students enrolled in arts programs in the school have to be taught how to sit still and how to listen. They can find it amazing to settle into plush chairs in fancy rooms.</p>
        <p>''They only know movies,'' Ms. Silver said. ''And not good movies. And maybe video games.''</p>
        <p>Consider, she said, how scary it is for many students to go a place like the Metropolitan Museum of Art. Most families from the school do not even realize that the $10 admission fee is voluntary, not required.</p>
        <p>P.S. 146, which is at 106th Street and First Avenue, serves many one-parent families and children eligible for free lunches. Most are black and Latin, and some do not speak English as their first language.</p>
        <p>The school, to its credit, is clean and cheerful. It is also surprisingly quiet, given its population of 700 students. Some wore the school uniforms of yellow shirts and navy blue skirts or pants; others chose not to.</p>
        <p>So there they were with Ms. Garcia, learning that culture does not come with a price tag and that dance is something that can be composed from bits and pieces of ordinary life.</p>
        <p>The muscle that New York flexes well is the one that forms partnerships. And, not surprisingly, in this city so rich in the arts,  there are programs to bring people like Ms. Garcia into schools. She was at P.S. 146 the other day as part of a program at the 92nd Street Y called the Dance Introduction series.</p>
        <p>The 92nd St Y, on Lexington Avenue, is something of a neighbor to the school in terms of physical proximity, but probably part of another world entirely to most people in the community. The series presents professional dance companies in special school residences and performances at the Y. The program also provides classroom instruction for the students and professional development workshops for the teachers, crowned by professional dance performances.</p>
        <p>''It's a great support,'' Ms. Silver said. ''Not only is it good exposure, but for the children who go on to take dance or music lessons, it's a great way to build up self-esteem if maybe they're not doing well in another way.''</p>
        <p>Two performances were recently arranged so the students could see the Urban Bush Women at the Y. One was last Thursday, the other will be tomorrow.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Ms. Garcia told the students that ''culture is religion, it's food, it's music.''</p>
        <p>The students went up on stage. To deal with the momentary bursts of restlessness, Ms. Garcia told the students that she could turn any little gesture into a dance. Yes. Anything. The way they shook their heads. The way they sucked their thumbs. Their laughter. Their shuffling feet.</p>
        <p>Then all the people on the crowded stage closed their eyes. Ms. Garcia had them pretend they were wrapped inside a bubble. She had the children tell their name and their favorite color and accompany that information with a gesture.</p>
        <p>''You are free to express yourself inside your skin,'' Ms. Garcia said. She told them to say ''individuality.'' They said it over and over again.</p>
        <p>''I want you to close your eyes without being asleep and listen to yourself dream,'' she said.</p>
        <p>And that, of course, was the whole point.</p>
        <p>COPING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
