<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>O'Neal's Free Throws Thwart Strategy</title>
    <meta content="21LAKE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201408"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Los Angeles Lakers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Portland Trail Blazers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Spousta, Tom</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Portland Trail Blazers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Los Angeles Lakers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000521T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E5DC113AF932A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="706" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>O'Neal's Free Throws Thwart Strategy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TOM SPOUSTA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Spousta, Tom</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, May 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Los Angeles Lakers defeat Portland Trail Blazers, 109-84, to lead playoff series 1-0; photo (M)l</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Shouts of ''M.V.P.! M.V.P.!'' cascaded around Shaquille O'Neal this afternoon, only the fans were not cheering a spectacular dunk or a blocked shot by the Lakers' center.</p>
        <p>O'Neal spent most of the fourth quarter at the free-throw line with Game 1 of the National Basketball Association's Western Conference finals still undecided, a situation that usually elicits more fear than hope.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Shouts of ''M.V.P.! M.V.P.!'' cascaded around Shaquille O'Neal this afternoon, only the fans were not cheering a spectacular dunk or a blocked shot by the Lakers' center.</p>
        <p>O'Neal spent most of the fourth quarter at the free-throw line with Game 1 of the National Basketball Association's Western Conference finals still undecided, a situation that usually elicits more fear than hope.</p>
        <p>Trailing by 13 points with 5 minutes 27 seconds remaining, the Portland Trail Blazers decided to make him shoot as many free throws as possible. O'Neal responded by making 12 of 25 attempts, including seven in a row, to lift the Los Angeles Lakers to a 109-94 victory at the Staples Center.</p>
        <p>Coach Mike Dunleavy of Portland defended the strategy as playing the percentages. O'Neal, a 46.2 percent free-throw shooter during these playoffs, called the rough tactics respect for his game. But the Hack-a-Shaq plan was just another thing that backfired on the Trail Blazers.</p>
        <p>''I knew they were going to do that,'' O'Neal said. ''I started to catch a rhythm, and I've been known throughout my career to hit at least one.''</p>
        <p>O'Neal led the Lakers with 41 points and 11 rebounds. Glen Rice added 15 points and Kobe Bryant had 13. Portland was led by Scottie Pippen with 19 points and Bonzi Wells with 17, but center Arvydas Sabonis did not score against O'Neal and grabbed only one rebound.</p>
        <p>Until the final two minutes, the Trail Blazers mostly fouled O'Neal away from the ball. At that point, under N.B.A. rules, an intentional foul becomes a moot strategy because the team gets one free throw and possession. It worked briefly. Portland closed to 97-88 with 4:59 remaining, before O'Neal got hot from the line.</p>
        <p>''Obviously, if we get down in a game, that's what we're going to do,'' Dunleavy said. ''Had we scored a few more times, we would have put ourselves in position to win. He's a great player. I like Shaq a lot. He just can't make his free throws.''</p>
        <p>The Trail Blazers trailed by as many as 24 points in the first half. After climbing back to within 9 points, they scored only one field goal in the final 4:59.</p>
        <p>''I thought they were going pretty good until they started to hack Shaq,'' Lakers Coach Phil Jackson said. ''That got the crowd into it and changed the momentum of the game.</p>
        <p>''It's a tactic you have to deal with. The odds are in your favor that he will miss one, but it stopped the flow of the ballgame and helped us play defense.''</p>
        <p>All of the Lakers' weapons fired en route to a 63-42 first-half lead. O'Neal scored 12 points and Bryant had 12, but Robert Horry led the decisive rally, a 26-4 run that covered almost eight minutes of the second quarter.</p>
        <p>Horry came off the bench and scored all 12 of his points in that span. He and Rice capped the run with consecutive 3-point baskets, then stood chest to chest during a Portland timeout, ignoring the towel-waving and back-slapping along the Lakers' bench. Four and a half minutes still remained in the second quarter, but already the Lakers led by 52-30.</p>
        <p>Portland did not shoot poorly (52.8 percent) or rebound badly (12 rebounds to the Lakers' 17) in the first half. But the Trail Blazers failed to extend their defense far enough to bother the Lakers' 3-point shooters, who drilled 8 of 12 attempts.</p>
        <p>The third-quarter ejection of Rasheed Wallace hurt the Trail Blazers, too. Wallace, who finished with 11 points, was called for his second technical after the official Ron Garretson had warned Wallace to stop staring at and trying to intimidate him.</p>
        <p>''We cannot have an All-Star sitting in the locker room with the game under 10 points with five minutes to go,'' Dunleavy said. ''At some point, even if he's right and it's a bad call, he has got to understand that.''</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
