<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hampton Helps Himself as Mets Barely Hold On</title>
    <meta content="21METS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201405"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Arizona Diamondbacks</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kepner, Tyler</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rodriguez, Rich</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Arizona Diamondbacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000521T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800EFDD113AF932A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="957" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hampton Helps Himself as Mets Barely Hold On</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kepner, Tyler</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Met</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Mets' locker room emptied quickly last night. Nobody lingered for card games or a meal or to watch television. Nobody remembered to turn on the postgame victory music. It looked as if 25 players had escaped, and it's hard to blame them for wanting to flee the scene.</p>
        <p>The Mets' bullpen was given an eight-run lead after seven innings against the Arizona Diamondbacks. Three relievers then allowed seven runs before Armando Benitez struck out Erubiel Durazo looking on a 95-mile-an-hour fastball with two men on base, preserving an 8-7 victory at Shea Stadium. All this came after a 3-hour-31-minute rain delay before the game's first pitch.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Mets' locker room emptied quickly last night. Nobody lingered for card games or a meal or to watch television. Nobody remembered to turn on the postgame victory music. It looked as if 25 players had escaped, and it's hard to blame them for wanting to flee the scene.</p>
        <p>The Mets' bullpen was given an eight-run lead after seven innings against the Arizona Diamondbacks. Three relievers then allowed seven runs before Armando Benitez struck out Erubiel Durazo looking on a 95-mile-an-hour fastball with two men on base, preserving an 8-7 victory at Shea Stadium. All this came after a 3-hour-31-minute rain delay before the game's first pitch.</p>
        <p>A long day?</p>
        <p>''Oh yes,'' Benitez said. ''Right now, I can't wait to go to sleep.''</p>
        <p>The Mets used six pitchers in the game, and three of them left with injuries. The starter, Mike Hampton, departed after six shutout innings with tightness in his back. Relievers Pat Mahomes and John Franco each injured an ankle. Hampton and Mahomes said their injuries were not serious; Franco said he might need a day or two to recover.</p>
        <p>Hampton hurt himself running the bases, after going from first to third in the fourth inning. He slid into third and popped up, twisting his body to look into the outfield for the ball. He said that was when he might have hurt his back, but it did not seem to affect his pitching.</p>
        <p>Hampton allowed four hits and a walk with four strikeouts in his six innings as he continues to distance himself from an inglorious early season. Hampton (5-4) has allowed only one earned run in 23 1/3 innings over his last three starts, lowering his earned run average to 4.21, from 6.52.</p>
        <p>''I put a lot of pressure on myself to perform well, to come in and be that impact guy,'' he said. ''It just took a while to take a step back, look at the big picture and do what I do.''</p>
        <p>For Hampton, his job also includes hitting. For his second start in a row, he singled in a five-run inning, and he improved his batting average to .261 after hitting .311 last year.</p>
        <p>Arizona Manager Buck Showalter was aware of Hampton's offense, saying before the series that he had never spent as much time reviewing a pitcher's hitting ability. But the analysis accomplished nothing.</p>
        <p>With the bases loaded and one out in the fourth inning, Hampton lined a single to left field off Omar Daal, scoring two runs and giving the Mets a 3-0 lead in an inning that included two of Arizona's four errors.</p>
        <p>''Is there a better hitting pitcher in the league than Hampton?'' Showalter said. ''I don't think so. He's a slasher. He's up there and he gets it done. He helps himself so much because he's so athletic.''</p>
        <p>Dennis Cook relieved Hampton with a scoreless seventh, but Mahomes, a right-hander, twisted his ankle while landing with his front foot after throwing a pitch in the eighth. Rich Rodriguez assumed an 8-2 lead to start the ninth, with disastrous results.</p>
        <p>Rodriguez has been used mainly in blowouts, and he was pitching for the first time in a week. He had an awful first month, allowing runs in 9 of his first 10 games, and the Mets put him through waivers to see if a team would take his two-year, $1.5 million contract.</p>
        <p>Nobody claimed him, and Rodriguez improved, allowing no runs in his last three outings before yesterday. But Bernard Gilkey and Travis Lee greeted him with doubles and Danny Klassen walked. After a double play brought the Mets within an out of a victory, Rodriguez allowed two singles, making the score 8-4.</p>
        <p>''Sometimes you can't find a feel,'' he said. ''Sometimes things start to snowball, and that's what happened.''</p>
        <p>The snowball grew. Manager Bobby Valentine called on Franco, who got Andy Fox to ground softly to first. Mark Johnson, who had entered the game in the seventh after Valentine pulled several starters, fielded the ball and flipped to Franco, too late. Franco turned to plant after crossing the base and twisted his right ankle, limping to the mound.</p>
        <p>He warmed up and decided to continue, but he had trouble planting his front foot, and two more singles brought the Diamondbacks within a run. Valentine went to the mound and Franco offered to continue, but the manager called on Benitez.</p>
        <p>''I told him to do whatever he had to do,'' Franco said. ''It's not going to hurt my feelings. The win's most important.''</p>
        <p>And the Mets -- finally -- managed to get away with their third victory in a row.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>Third baseman ROBIN VENTURA did not start yesterday's game because of a sore left thigh muscle. Manager BOBBY VALENTINE said he expected Ventura to miss two or three games with the nagging injury, though Ventura did come in on a double switch in the ninth. . . . REY ORDONEZ had two hits and now has five in his last three games. Ordonez is trying to finish his swing higher, and Valentine said Ordonez now had the kind of swing that allowed him to get hits to left and right field. . . . JAY PAYTON's single in the fourth inning was his first hit in 24 at-bats.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
