<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Getting By Onstage With Help, Of Course</title>
    <meta content="21RING$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201128"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Beatles, the</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Starr, Ringo</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Woliver, Robbie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000521T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00EEDB143AF932A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="827" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Getting By Onstage With Help, Of Course</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBBIE WOLIVER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Woliver, Robbie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on former Beatle Ringo Starr, who is bringing his Connections Tour, with All-Starr Band, to State Theater in New Brunswick, NJ; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>RINGO STARR is once again getting a little help from his friends. This time its for his Connections Tour, which will arrive in New Jersey 36 years after the Fab Four first conquered America.</p>
        <p>''We're blessed we're still alive and that people want to come and see us,'' said the former Beatles drummer, who sang the classics ''Yellow Submarine'' and ''With A Little Help From My Friends.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>RINGO STARR is once again getting a little help from his friends. This time its for his Connections Tour, which will arrive in New Jersey 36 years after the Fab Four first conquered America.</p>
        <p>''We're blessed we're still alive and that people want to come and see us,'' said the former Beatles drummer, who sang the classics ''Yellow Submarine'' and ''With A Little Help From My Friends.''</p>
        <p>''I'm still living a dream come true that I've had since I was 13 years old.''</p>
        <p>Living that dream with him is a stellar crew that includes Jack Bruce, the bass player from Cream; Dave Edmunds, guitarist, keyboardist Eric Carmen of the Raspberries, drummer Simon Kirke of Bad Company and Free and the sax player Mark Rivera, a Billy Joel tour veteran. They'll have their chance to shine in concert, too.</p>
        <p>The format, Mr. Starr said, is close to the format of his last few tours -- to perform all his past hits ''and have a lot of fun.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Starr, who turns 60 in July, has often been regarded as the least of the Beatles, because he was not one of the main songwriters, nor was he a vocalist of note. But the former Richard Starkey was the most likable of the group, the one to whom most fans could relate. And now the one who is the most visible, with a surprising number of past hits to perform.</p>
        <p>By the time the Beatles broke up in December 1970, he had already released two solo albums, both considered novelty recordings. ''Sentimental Journey'' harkened back to pre-rock pop standards and ''Beaucoups of Blues'' was a collection of country music.</p>
        <p>But that was the key to Mr. Starr's success -- he appealed to a wide age and cultural demographic. And the affable singer wrapped it all in family-friendly ditties. Paul might have been called the ''cute Beatle,'' but Ringo remained the ''fun Beatle.''</p>
        <p>During the following years he enjoyed a string of chart-topping singles including ''It Don't Come Easy,'' ''Back Off Boogaloo,'' ''Photograph,'' ''You're 16,'' ''Oh My My,'' and ''Only You.''</p>
        <p>In a testament to his inventive drumming and amiable personality, he was the one his former bandmates invited to play on their solo albums (John Lennon's ''Plastic Ono Band,'' George Harrison's ''All Things Must Pass,'' and Paul McCartney's ''Tug of War'').</p>
        <p>Mr. Starr also began a successful acting career, starring in such films as ''Candy,'' ''The Magic Christian'' and Frank Zappa's ''200 Motels.''</p>
        <p>There were also a few off-beat ventures he began, like an art-deco furniture company, which closed after a short run.</p>
        <p>By the mid-70's, Mr. Starr's personal life was in turmoil. Business ventures went bust, he began drinking and his marriage to his Beatles-era wife, Maureen Cox, broke up. But he was still scoring hits with ''The No No Song,'' and ''Goodnight Vienna,'' although albums like ''Ringo's Rotogravure,'' ''Ringo the Fourth'' and ''Bad Boy'' bombed.</p>
        <p>In 1980, while filming the movie ''Caveman,'' he fell in love with his co-star, Barbara Bach, a model and former Bond girl. They were soon married. He also won over a new generation of fans when he starred in the children's series ''Shining Time Station,'' which gained him a 1988 Emmy nomination. But a bout with alcoholism kept him out of the limelight for most of the 1980's. He and Ms. Bach finally entered a rehabilitation center and in 1989, Mr. Starr returned renewed and sober.</p>
        <p>It was that same year when he embarked upon his first solo concert tour with his All Starr Band. Four years later, the band's second incarnation took place, this time including his son, Zak, on drums. The band took on one more personnel change before its present one.</p>
        <p>His most recent recordings were 1998's ''Vertical Man,'' VH1 ''Storytellers'' release and 1999's Christmas album ''I Wanna Be Santa Claus.'' A 3-CD retrospective is expected to be released next month.</p>
        <p>Along with first-rate musicianship, a Ringo Starr concert is a sing-along romp down a memory lane filled with upbeat, familiar songs.</p>
        <p>RINGO STARR AND HIS ALL-STARR BAND</p>
        <p>The State Theater, 15 Livingston Avenue, New Brunswick.</p>
        <p>Wednesday at 8 p.m.  (732) 246-7469.</p>
        <p>MUSIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
