<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Potato Salad, All Dressed Up</title>
    <meta content="21FOOD$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201123"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="IN THE KITCHEN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COOKING AND COOKBOOKS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000521T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E1DB143AF932A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1103" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Potato Salad, All Dressed Up</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FLORENCE FABRICANT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>POTATO salad may not strictly be seasonal, but like local strawberries, backyard grilling and gin and tonic, it signals summer. And its adaptable nature makes it appropriate for everything from a picnic to an elaborate dinner.</p>
        <p>Defining potato salad is cultural. Whether or not the recipe calls for a mayonnaise dressing, warm bacon, hard-cooked eggs, chunks of unpeeled potatoes, a sharp vinegar edge, grated carrot, a touch of sweetness or diced herring, often depends on the heritage of the cook. Potato salad can involve any of these variations, and more.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>POTATO salad may not strictly be seasonal, but like local strawberries, backyard grilling and gin and tonic, it signals summer. And its adaptable nature makes it appropriate for everything from a picnic to an elaborate dinner.</p>
        <p>Defining potato salad is cultural. Whether or not the recipe calls for a mayonnaise dressing, warm bacon, hard-cooked eggs, chunks of unpeeled potatoes, a sharp vinegar edge, grated carrot, a touch of sweetness or diced herring, often depends on the heritage of the cook. Potato salad can involve any of these variations, and more.</p>
        <p>Good potato salad depends on a couple of essential principles. First is that the type of potato must be suitable. A waxy, firm-textured but somewhat moist ''new'' potato is best. Storage potatoes, like the typical russet baking varieties, tend to be too dry and mealy for proper slicing and handling, and they are more likely to sop up the dressing than to be coated with it. Look for Red Bliss, Creamer, Yukon Gold and red or pale yellow-skinned new potatoes.</p>
        <p>Careful seasoning is the second critical factor. Potatoes are fairly bland and can take a good amount of salting and peppering. Also, if the salad is to be served cold, it's important to season it well because chilling will mute the flavors. A splash of vinegar on warm potatoes that have just been cooked and drained provides a nice seasoning boost.</p>
        <p>Whether to peel the potatoes is a matter of taste. If small and uniform in size, they can be left whole or  halved. Larger ones are better peeled, cut in half or quarters for cooking and sliced when done. All  pieces should be of uniform size so they cook at the same rate.</p>
        <p>A general rule of thumb when it comes to dressing is about a cup of sauce to a pound of potatoes, a little less if a vinaigrette or mixture of a somewhat thin consistency is used. Mayonnaise is classic, but its richness can be tempered with plain yogurt. The notion that mayonnaise can be unsafe to eat in warm weather has been proved incorrect when commercial mayonnaise is used. It is made with high acidity to prevent spoilage. But homemade mayonnaise requires careful handling and should be kept chilled.</p>
        <p>The list of additions suitable for potato salad is endless, but something oniony and some green herbs for color are good to add. And a dollop of sharp mustard in the dressing is never a mistake.</p>
        <p>Classic Potato Salad  Total time:  35 minutes</p>
        <p>3 pounds medium-size red or Yukon Gold potatoes, peeled and halved  Salt and freshly ground black pepper to taste</p>
        <p>1/3 cup white-wine vinegar  2 carrots, peeled and grated  2 tablespoons finely minced parsley</p>
        <p>1/3 cup finely chopped scallions  2 cups mayonnaise  2 tablespoons Dijon mustard.</p>
        <p>1. Put potatoes in saucepan with salted water to cover. Bring to simmer and cook until potatoes are just tender, about 20 minutes. Drain and slice.</p>
        <p>2. Season potatoes with salt and pepper and fold in vinegar. Fold in carrots, parsley and scallions.</p>
        <p>3. Mix mayonnaise and mustard. Fold in. Check seasonings and serve.</p>
        <p>Yield: 6 servings.</p>
        <p>Chunky Red Potato Salad  With Bacon  Total time: 45 minutes</p>
        <p>2 pounds golf ball-size Red Bliss potatoes or other red potatoes  Salt  4 ounces slab bacon, diced in  1/2-inch pieces  2 tablespoons mayonnaise  2 tablespoons Dijon mustard  2 tablespoons red-wine vinegar  3 tablespoon extra-virgin olive oil  1 tablespoon capers  1 tablespoon finely minced shallots  Freshly ground black pepper to taste  1 tablespoon finely minced parsley.</p>
        <p>1. Put potatoes in saucepan with salted water to cover. Bring to boil and simmer until tender, 15 to 20 minutes. Drain.</p>
        <p>2. Meanwhile, saute bacon in small skillet until lightly browned. Mix mayonnaise, mustard, vinegar, oil, capers and shallots together and season with salt and pepper.</p>
        <p>3. Drain bacon, reserving three tablespoons fat. Pour fat and bacon over potatoes and toss lightly. Fold in mayonnaise mixture and parsley, and serve.</p>
        <p>Yield: 4 servings.</p>
        <p>Curried Potato Salad With Mussels  Total time: 1 hour</p>
        <p>1 teaspoon black mustard seeds  1 teaspoon cumin seeds</p>
        <p>2/3 cup extra-virgin olive oil  1 tablespoon curry powder</p>
        <p>1/2 tablespoon finely minced fresh ginger  3 tablespoons shallots  1 cup dry white wine  4 dozen scrubbed, debearded mussels  1 pound small new potatoes, peeled and halved  Salt and freshly ground black pepper to taste  4 tablespoons white-wine vinegar  4 tablespoons plain yogurt  2 tablespoons finely minced cilantro leaves.</p>
        <p>1. Put heavy three-quart saucepan over medium heat. Add mustard and cumin seeds and when they start to dance around and smell toasty, add two tablespoons olive oil, curry powder, ginger and shallots. Saute until shallots are transluscent. Transfer mixture to small bowl.</p>
        <p>2. Put wine in same pan, add mussels, bring to simmer, cover and steam until mussels open, about 10 minutes. Transfer mussels to bowl. Add half a cup of strained mussel liquid to spice and shallot mixture. Reserve remaining mussel liquid for another use.</p>
        <p>3. Put potatoes in cold salted water to cover, bring to simmer and cook until just tender, about 12 minutes. Drain and transfer to bowl. Season with salt and pepper. Fold in vinegar and yogurt.</p>
        <p>4. Shuck mussels. Put in medium-size bowl and pour spice and shallot mixture over. Fold into potatoes. Season salad with salt and pepper. Fold in cilantro and serve.</p>
        <p>Yield: 6 servings.</p>
        <p>Three-Onion Potato Salad  Total time: 40 minutes</p>
        <p>Salt  1 medium-size red onion, peeled and sliced paper thin  2 pounds medium-size Yukon Gold potatoes, peeled and quartered  Freshly ground black pepper to taste</p>
        <p>1/3 cup red-wine vinegar  2 tablespoons finely minced shallots  2 tablespoons Dijon mustard</p>
        <p>2/3 cup extra-virgin olive oil  3 tablespoons finely minced chives.</p>
        <p>1. Bring pot of salted water to boil. Put onion in strainer, submerge in water, blanch 30 seconds in boiling water, remove onion and drain. Add potatoes to boiling water, lower heat and simmer until tender, about 15 minutes. Drain.</p>
        <p>2. Toss potatoes with onion, salt and pepper to taste, vinegar and shallots.</p>
        <p>3. Beat mustard and oil together. Fold into potatoes. Fold in chives. Check seasonings and serve.</p>
        <p>Yield: 4 servings.</p>
        <p>Skinny Potato Salad  Total time: 45 minutes</p>
        <p>2 pounds small Yukon Gold potatoes, quartered  Salt and freshly ground black pepper  3 tablespoons white-wine vinegar  1 cup nonfat mayonnaise  1 cup plain nonfat yogurt  3 tablespoons minced fresh dill</p>
        <p>1/4 cup finely minced scallions.</p>
        <p>1. Put potatoes in saucepan with salted water to cover, bring to simmer and cook until tender, 15 to 20 minutes. Drain and put in bowl.</p>
        <p>2. Season with salt and pepper and toss with vinegar.</p>
        <p>3. Combine mayonnaise, yogurt, dill and scallions. Fold into potatoes. Allow to cool to room temperature before serving.</p>
        <p>Yield: 4 servings.</p>
        <p>IN THE KITCHEN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
