<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Growing Up More Popular Than You Are</title>
    <meta content="BRADY" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Television" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="63" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201461"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SPOTLIGHT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shattuck, Kathryn</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Williams, Barry</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Growing Up Brady (TV Program)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Brady Bunch, The (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000521T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E3DB113AF932A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="773" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Growing Up More Popular Than You Are</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Kathryn Shattuck</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Shattuck, Kathryn</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article profiles Barry Williams, a former star of popular television series The Brady Bunch; Williams's memoir has been adapted for new NBC television program Growing Up Brady; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The question just begged to be asked. So, that thing with Marcia, uh, Maureen McCormick? It really happened?</p>
        <p>''As in anything, when you make a transfer, details change according to the need,'' said Barry Williams, a.k.a. Greg Brady.</p>
        <p>But that scene in New York, where Marcia and Greg - oops, sorry. Maureen and Barry - almost, you know, but don't. That really happened?</p>
        <p>''Well, it was filmed in the Essex House but in reality we were on the QE2.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The question just begged to be asked. So, that thing with Marcia, uh, Maureen McCormick? It really happened?</p>
        <p>''As in anything, when you make a transfer, details change according to the need,'' said Barry Williams, a.k.a. Greg Brady.</p>
        <p>But that scene in New York, where Marcia and Greg - oops, sorry. Maureen and Barry - almost, you know, but don't. That really happened?</p>
        <p>''Well, it was filmed in the Essex House but in reality we were on the QE2.''</p>
        <p>Get to the point, buster.</p>
        <p>''The reality is that yes, we sort of chased after one another throughout the five years. Did I spend every day lusting after her? No. But that scene is accurate.''</p>
        <p>Well, what would you expect from a guy who spent his formative years playing the most popular teenage brother on television? Especially when his on-screen step-sister was widely considered a major babe.</p>
        <p>Fans of ''The Brady Bunch,'' the touchstone for a generation of adolescents in the early 1970's and a cult hit since, can see for themselves on ''Growing Up rady,'' tonight at 9 on NBC.</p>
        <p>Adapted from Mr. Williams's 1992 memoir, ''Growing Up Brady: I Was a Teenage Greg,'' the movie claims to ante up the behind-the-scenes dirt on the Brady clan -- sanitized for prime time, of course.</p>
        <p>Mr. Williams was just 14 when he was propelled into the teeny-bopper stratosphere in the role of Greg Brady, the oldest of three brothers conjoined to three step-sisters through their newlywed parents. Like many before him, Mr. Williams soon learned that hcild stardom had its downside. For the next five years, his public image and his private self fused; a rigid shooting schedule and being schooled on the set didn't help. ''I found it to be quite limiting in terms of a social front,'' Mr. Williams, 45, recalled. ''I was just socially inexperienced. I knew how to be an adult, but not a child.''</p>
        <p>In the living rooms of fans around the world, Mr. Williams metamorphosed from a freckled-faced boy into an all-out hunk with groovy Afro, shaggy sideburns and bedroom eyes. He sought companionship in the arms of eager fans, solace in his on-again, off-again relationship with Ms. McCormick and a little marjuana now and again.</p>
        <p>And then in 1974, after failed negotiations caused ABC to cancel the series abruptly, Mr. Williams was left to be himself again.</p>
        <p>''It created a void,'' he said about the loss of his alter ego.</p>
        <p>Mr. Williams moved to New York, where he won the lead in the national touring company of the Broadway hit ''Pippin.'' A succession of cabaret gigs and theme-park shows followed, and the aura of Greg Brady continued to envelope him, with good luck in tow.</p>
        <p>''My down time didn't come for about three or four years later,'' he said. ''Then I sort of hit a wall.''</p>
        <p>That wall sent him back to Los Angeles to compensate for the teenage rebellion he'd never had.</p>
        <p>''It was the other part of balancing out life,'' he said. ''There was an arrogance that was attached. I didn't come in for interviews, didn't return phone calls, didn't bother showing up.''</p>
        <p>After a vegetative spell, Mr. Williams began taking intensive acting and singing courses, something that his television father, Robert Reed, who trained at the Royal Academy in London, encouraged.</p>
        <p>The result was Mr. Williams's salvation.</p>
        <p>''I got the chip on my shoulder blown off for good,'' he said. ''I stopped taking things for granted; I started appreciating things that were in front of me. I finally got what I wanted.''</p>
        <p>That now includes a year-old marriage to an investment banker, in addition to the book, a new CD, a full concert calendar and loyal fans visiting his Web site (www.barrywilliams.com). Mr. Williams says he couldn't be happier. Even if he isn't always certain which of of his personas audiences are focusing on.</p>
        <p>''The association with 'The Brady Bunch' is a profound and powerful one. It's still seen by 2.5 million people at night.''</p>
        <p>''No, I don't get tired of it,'' he said, sounding a little worn out. ''I'm thrilled that I have something that creates a common point with me and an audience. Do you think that Tony Bennett gets tired of singing 'I Left My Heart in San Francisco'?  SPOTLIGHT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
