<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>And the Moliere for Best Actor Goes to . . .</title>
    <meta content="21RIDI$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201039"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER/THE TONY AWARDS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Riding, Alan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000521T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E3D61E3BF932A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1854" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>And the Moliere for Best Actor Goes to . . .</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN RIDING</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Riding, Alan</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Theater awards are proliferating but they can do little to bring prestige or sell tickets if they are not reflective of good theater and keen audiences; some new awards noted; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT is something of a paradox,'' Conor Brady, the editor of The Irish Times, remarked a few years back, ''that a director who may have a Tony on his mantelpiece will have no corresponding award from his Irish peers.''</p>
        <p>Well, Mr. Brady soon helped fix that. In 1997, The Irish Times created the Irish Theater Awards in partnership with the country's Electricity Supply Board. And since then, peer recognition has been gradually filling mantelpieces from Dublin to Galway.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT is something of a paradox,'' Conor Brady, the editor of The Irish Times, remarked a few years back, ''that a director who may have a Tony on his mantelpiece will have no corresponding award from his Irish peers.''</p>
        <p>Well, Mr. Brady soon helped fix that. In 1997, The Irish Times created the Irish Theater Awards in partnership with the country's Electricity Supply Board. And since then, peer recognition has been gradually filling mantelpieces from Dublin to Galway.</p>
        <p>Not that Ireland's theater is necessarily the better for joining the awards game. After all, from Oscar Wilde to Sebastian Barry, the country's playwrights have fared well enough on a diet of scandal and applause. And surely no Irish actor ever needed more than an attentive audience for the muse to stir. On the other hand, since a theater award usually means a splash of publicity and a good party, no complaints. Free Champagne and a decorated mantelpiece? Even better.</p>
        <p>So is that what theater awards are all about? Sort of, because the Oscars are everyone's role model. Playwrights, directors and actors may be at the heart of the show, there to provide glamour, to excite the paparazzi, perhaps even to add a touch of class, but they are in fact only bit players. In the more serious business of selling tickets, it is the party -- the awards ceremony -- that counts. As with the Oscars, the prize, rather than any individual winner, is the real star.</p>
        <p>Yet on their own, theater awards can do little. Above all, they are no substitute for good writers, directors, actors, managers, theaters -- and keen audiences. In fact, for such prizes to be coveted, for awards ceremonies to be televised, for the competition to stir interest, a country and, above all, a city must first have a healthy and active theater life. Conversely, the paucity of prestigious theater prizes speaks alarmingly of the theater's losing battle against television and movies in much of the world.</p>
        <p>The new Irish Theater Awards have prospered, then, because the ground was already fertile. With the Gate and Abbey theaters its traditional pillars, Dublin has been a theater town for well over a century. And in the last decade, a burst of fine writing and a fresh generation of directors have injected new blood into theater there. So even though they have not created it, the theater prizes are a nice way of celebrating that renaissance. This year's best new play was ''Howie the Rookie'' by Mark O'Rowe, while the best director award went to John Breen for his production of his own play ''Alone It Stands.''</p>
        <p>Across the water in London, theater awards are as well established as the theater business itself, indeed self-confident enough to honor Irish or American or even French artists who help keep the lights bright in the West End.</p>
        <p>The Evening Standard Theater Awards, created in 1955, eight years after the Tony Awards, have as good a record as any for spotting the best. In their first year, they included a bizarre category, most controversial play. The winner? Samuel Beckett's ''Waiting for Godot.'' And in 1956, the most promising playwright? John Osborne.</p>
        <p>SINCE then, while acting and directing awards have often gone to pillars of the London stage like the actors Dame Maggie Smith and the directors Sir Richard Eyre and Deborah Warner, The Evening Standard's jury of theater critics continues to seek out new writing talent.</p>
        <p>Recent most promising playwrights include Martin McDonagh (''The Beauty Queen of Leenane'') in 1996, Conor McPherson (''The Weir'') in 1997, Mark Ravenhill (''Handbag'') in 1998 and Rebecca Gilman (''The Glory of Living'') in 1999. The 1999 awards ceremony, broadcast by Carlton Television, nonetheless had a surprise: no best play was picked, a decision widely applauded as evidence that quality matters.</p>
        <p>In 1981, the Laurence Olivier Awards were added by the Society of London Theaters, an organization that, much like the League of American Theaters and Producers (one of the sponsors of the Tony Awards), represents the theater business -- producers, proprietors and managers. While the Evening Standard Awards are given in a maximum of 10 categories, the Oliviers have 22, including two each for opera and dance. Unusually, the theater, opera and dance juries are formed by a mixture of theater professionals and members of the theatergoing public (theater lovers can apply to become jurors), which assures that popular appeal remains a key variable.</p>
        <p>One measure of this is the emphasis given by the Oliviers to musical comedies, the West End's main crowd-puller, with awards for best actor in a musical, best actress in a musical, best theater choreographer and best supporting performance in a musical, as well as the Radisson Edwardian Award for Best Musical. This year, when the ceremony was televised by BBC-2, the Royal National Theater picked up three musical prizes as well as best director for two Shakespeare productions by its own artistic director, Sir Trevor Nunn, accolades that reflect the broad range of the theater's work. (Sir Trevor also won the less glitzy Critics' Circle Theater Award for best director.)</p>
        <p>France's main theater award, the Moliere, has an even weightier name and a still stronger commercial lineage. It was created in 1987 by the Union of Theater Managers and the administrator of the Comedie Francaise, with a Paris publicist, Georges Cravenne, given the job of founding the Professional and Artistic Theater Association to promote the Molieres. Since then, winners have included the actors Jeanne Moreau, Ute Lemper and Sophie Marceau, the directors Peter Brook and Patrice Chereau and the playwright Yasmina Reza (''Art'').</p>
        <p>From the beginning, however, the award was caught in the perennial French squabble between government-subsidized theater and commercial theater, a problem it temporarily resolved by awarding a best-production Moliere in each of those categories. But some people in subsidized -- read intellectual and experimental -- theater felt that commercial theater was favored, and their resentment surfaced in 1996 when they boycotted the televised Moliere ceremony. Negotiations followed, and the distinction between subsidized and commercial theater was eliminated, replaced by prizes for best repertory play and best new creation.</p>
        <p>This year's ceremony, held on May 8 in the Opera-Comique and broadcast in prime time on the government-owned television channel France 2, went off without controversy, with top prizes spread around diplomatically. Best playwright, best adaptation of a foreign play and best comedy went to Dario Fo's ''Accidental Death of an Anarchist'' at the private Theatre la Bruyere, while best new creation, best director and best scenic design went to Ariane Mnouchkine's ''Tambours sur la Digue'' (''Drums Over the Dike''), presented at her subsidized Cartoucherie de Vincennes. The prize for best female newcomer, in turn, went to Mr. Brook's daughter, Irina, for her production of ''Resonances,'' by the young American playwright Katherine Burger.</p>
        <p>In Russia, where theatrical experimentation flourished in the early 20th century, the end of Communism has spawned intense new interest in theater despite the economic troubles plaguing most theaters. As with Ireland, the conditions were ripe for the creation of a prestigious theater award. The Golden Mask was established as a Moscow award in 1995 and became the main national award the following year. In order to embrace work done across Russia, above all in St. Petersburg, winners in a range of categories (covering music and dance as well as drama and puppetry) are chosen from participants in a Golden Mask festival, which now takes place in Moscow every spring. And while this year's award ceremony was as long-winded as some Oscar evenings, the Golden Mask now seems to have established itself as worthy of any mantelpiece.</p>
        <p>More of a puzzle is the absence of major theater awards in Germany and Italy, despite traditions that embrace the likes of Goethe and Brecht, commedia dell'arte and Pirandello. One explanation may simply be that both countries were only founded in the 19th century and, as such, are not dominated by a single city. Certainly, in Germany, most theater awards are still regional. One exception is the Bavaria Theater Prize, announced in Munich every summer, with jurors drawn from across the country and awards given to opera, drama, dance and new plays performed anywhere in Germany. With Berlin the new German capital, its two main theater awards -- the Daphne Prize and the German Theater Prize -- are also growing in stature. No German theater awards ceremony, though, has yet earned live television coverage.</p>
        <p>In Italy, scores of less important theater awards given by towns and cities across the peninsula go largely unnoticed in the rest of the country. ''In Italy, every steeple has its own teeny prize,'' Marcantonio Lucidi, a spokesman for the National Academy of Dramatic Arts, explained. ''It's a cheap form of publicity. It costs less to invite someone to your town and give them a tin statue than it does to run an ad campaign.'' Still, one prize, the Premio Ubu, created in the late 1970's by Ubu Libri, a Milan publishing house, has won some respect, if only because, unlike much of Italy's cultural life, it is thought to be above political manipulation.</p>
        <p>All too often, though, theater awards are known to those in the theater industry and few others. Poland's Schiller Prize, given annually to an eminent theater figure, does little to boost contemporary theater. Japan's Education Ministry offers an annual theater prize, but it barely merits a mention in the press. Argentina, which offers Latin America's most developed theater, has no fewer than four theater awards, too many to create a buzz. In Brazil, the Shell Prize of $1,750, sponsored by the British oil giant, has existed since 1983, but the state government of Rio de Janeiro has now stepped in with a much more lucrative theater prize -- $100,000 for the best production -- to be awarded for the first time this year.</p>
        <p>Clearly, money helps -- money for prizes, for publicity, for glitzy awards ceremonies, for television coverage. And yet for theater prizes to stir genuine excitement, theater goers must first be excited by what they have seen onstage. Or at least that is how it should be.</p>
        <p>The danger arises when awards ceremonies evolve into ends unto themselves, because once the show becomes the priority, the temptation is to have television and movie stars handing out and receiving top prizes. This may be good for the tabloids, good for the television ratings, even good for the awards, but it probably does little for theater.</p>
        <p>THEATER/THE TONY AWARDS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
