<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Decision on Knight Shows the Fine Line That Colleges Walk</title>
    <meta content="21COLL$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201382"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Assaults</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Indiana University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Knight, Bob</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mckinley, James C Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Assaults</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000521T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E7DE113AF932A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2003" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Decision on Knight Shows the Fine Line That Colleges Walk</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES C. McKINLEY Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mckinley, James C Jr</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Indiana University's handling of case of basketball coach Bob Knight underscores the extraordinary pressure put on college presidents when outstanding athletes or popular coaches get in trouble; administrators must weigh lofty moral and educational standards of their schools against students, sports fans, wealthy alumni and donors demanding success on the playing field; Indiana's decision not to dismiss Knight for his abusive behavior may seem like a capitulation to people ouside the state, but within Indiana, where many members of political power structure are Indiana alumni, the decision to give Knight one more chance makes sense; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After the president of Florida State University, Talbot D'Alemberte, dared to suggest last fall that a star wide receiver serve a jail sentence before returning to play football, some of the irate letters he received were telling.</p>
        <p>''How dare you treat Athletic Director Hart and Coach Bowden as mere subordinates,'' wrote an alumnus, Ron Lawrence. ''I will never give another penny to the university as long as you are president of the institution.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After the president of Florida State University, Talbot D'Alemberte, dared to suggest last fall that a star wide receiver serve a jail sentence before returning to play football, some of the irate letters he received were telling.</p>
        <p>''How dare you treat Athletic Director Hart and Coach Bowden as mere subordinates,'' wrote an alumnus, Ron Lawrence. ''I will never give another penny to the university as long as you are president of the institution.''</p>
        <p>When outstanding athletes or popular coaches get in trouble, college presidents like Mr. D'Alemberte face extraordinary pressure; they must weigh the lofty moral and educational standards of their schools against students, sports fans, wealthy alumni and donors demanding success on the playing field.</p>
        <p>Seldom have the contending forces -- and the potential risks to a university's reputation -- been more evident than at Indiana University last week, when the legendary basketball coach, Bob Knight, escaped dismissal even though the president, Myles Brand, and the university trustees concluded that he had a long history of abusive behavior, including choking a player and bullying a secretary.</p>
        <p>To many people outside Indiana, the decision seemed odd, a capitulation to a powerful coach with a persistent three-decade record of inappropriate words and actions. But within the state, where many members of the political power structure are alumni of Indiana University, and Mr. Knight is a celebrity whose name is more widely known than the governor's, the decision to give Mr. Knight one more chance made sense.</p>
        <p>''Within the state, more people view him as a case of the positives outweighing the negatives,'' said Murray Sperber, an English professor at Indiana who writes books on college sports and has long been a critic of Mr. Knight. ''That explains the pressures on Brand.''</p>
        <p>Many critics say Mr. Knight's case illustrates the great divide between the ideals of universities and the reality of big-time college sports: in many schools, athletics have become a potent entertainment business, with coaches and athletes who become media stars and help market schools, attracting donations and students.</p>
        <p>''College sports becomes the bridge between the elite culture of the university and the mass culture outside the university upon which the university depends,'' said Allen L. Sack, the director of the sports management program at the University of New Haven. ''In the midst, holding up that bridge, are the college presidents.''</p>
        <p>In recent years, officials at the University of Minnesota and the University of Tennessee have struggled with allegations of academic fraud by athletes, while the University of Nebraska dealt with accusations that star football players physically abused women.</p>
        <p>The University of Vermont canceled part of the hockey season earlier this year because of hazing, and Providence College expelled three basketball players last week over an assault.</p>
        <p>For his part, Mr. Brand insists that he made the decision to give Mr. Knight ''one last opportunity'' without regard to pressure from alumni and Hoosier basketball fans, who staged a demonstration on campus and flooded Mr. Brand's office with e-mail messages. Several alumni organizations also threatened to stop giving to the university, said Michael Pegram, a booster who organized the demonstration.</p>
        <p>''There may have been people who said, 'I won't give money anymore,' '' Mr. Brand said in an interview. ''All those issues have to be totally ignored in the decision-making.''</p>
        <p>In fact, Mr. Brand said he and most of the nine-member board of trustees had been leaning toward dismissing Mr. Knight until the basketball coach posted an apology on the internet on May 13. That night, Mr. Brand met at his home with Mr. Knight and his wife.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brand said he told Mr. Knight that the trustees were on the verge of voting to dismiss him. But during a three-and-a-half-hour conversation, he said, Mr. Knight persuaded him to recommend penalities instead. For the first time, Mr. Knight accepted responsibility for his past actions and promised to rein in his temper, Mr. Brand said.</p>
        <p>The Coach Draws Up His Survival Plan</p>
        <p>Mr. Brand said he believed that the university had been culpable as well. For 29 years, he said, officials had either ignored Mr. Knight's abusive behavior or let him off with light sanctions, setting ''implicit rules'' that Mr. Knight could behave as he wanted.</p>
        <p>The following day, Mr. Brand recommended to the trustees that Mr. Knight be given one last chance. The coach was fined $30,000, suspended for three games and ordered to abide by a strict code of conduct or face dismissal.</p>
        <p>''Whatever sanction I gave him would not have been enough,'' Mr. Brand said. ''The meat of the issue were the directives about how he's expected to behave in the future and if he doesn't, he doesn't have a second chance anymore.''</p>
        <p>''The easy decision to make was to terminate Bob Knight,'' Mr. Brand added. ''I knew there was a groundswell of interest outside the state to terminate him.''</p>
        <p>Even inside the state, opinion was divided. Trustees said they had received hundreds of letters.</p>
        <p>''Nobody was down the middle,''  John Walda, the board president, said. ''It was either 'This was a witch hunt begun by the media and you should ignore it,' or 'It's about time, you should get rid of Coach Knight.' ''</p>
        <p>Another trustee, Ray Richardson, a former state legislator, said the decision was a no-win situation politically for the board. A poll by The Indianapolis Star last month showed about 55 percent of state residents thought Knight should remain as coach and about 39 percent said he should not.</p>
        <p>''There is a huge segment of Hoosiers that feel that he's done some nasty things, but they weren't necessarily ready to fire him,'' Mr. Richardson said. ''I was trying to figure out what would please the people in the middle.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Richardson said he had been prepared to vote to dismiss Mr. Knight, but changed his mind after Mr. Brand told the board of Mr. Knight's sincere promise to change. ''Knight's never had an incentive to control himself,'' Mr. Richardson said.</p>
        <p>Some faculty members, however, said the trustees' decision had irreparably damaged Indiana University's reputation. ''It sends the message that athletics are more important than academics, that marketing and revenue streams mean more than scholarships,'' said Dave Pisoni, a psychology professor.</p>
        <p>Angry Mail Bombards School and Prosecutor</p>
        <p>At Florida State University, the pressure on Mr. D'Alamberte to keep the football team's star receiver, Peter Warrick, on the field was more overt. One donor threatened to withdraw a $1 million contribution, university officials said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Warrick had been charged with another football player and a department store cashier in a $600 shoplifting scheme. Mr. Warrick's lawyer, John Kenny, along with the football coach, Bobby Bowden, and athletic director, Dave Hart Jr., had worked out a plea agreement with the Tallahassee prosecutor, Willie Meggs. Mr. Warrick would plead guilty to a misdemeanor, and he would serve 30 days in jail after the football season.</p>
        <p>But Mr. D'Alamberte said it was university policy, set after two previous cases involving players convicted of crimes, that Mr. Warrick must pay his debt to society before returning to football.</p>
        <p>''I'd had that policy and I thought I made it clear to everyone all along that was going to be my policy,'' Mr. D'Alemberte said in an interview. ''A lot of people got outraged, in part because it looked as if everything had been worked out and I was stepping in.''</p>
        <p>His office immediately received more than 600 letters and e-mail messages, denouncing him as well as supporting him.</p>
        <p>''There were two or three major donors who were sending me messages that they were not going to give the gift they had promised,'' he said. ''The best thing for a university president to do is to stake out a ground that he feels comfortable with and stay there.''</p>
        <p>Worried alumni and other Seminole football fans also bombarded the prosecutor, himself an alumnus, with angry mail. They lobbied sympathetic state legislators to use their influence. ''I had hundreds of phone calls,'' said State Senator Jim King of Jacksonville, also a graduate of Florida State. ''I thought the phone would never stop ringing.''</p>
        <p>In the end, Mr. Warrick's lawyer brokered a new deal. Instead of jail time, Mr. Warrick was allowed to do community service -- picking up trash for 30 days -- after admitting his guilt. Mr. D'Alamberte permitted Mr. Warrick to rejoin the football team before doing the community service, reasoning that the punishment was much less severe than jail time. ''The line I have drawn looks at the result produced by the criminal justice system,'' he said. ''The judgment here is 'This has been pretty minor.' ''</p>
        <p>The Seminoles went on to win the national championship at the Sugar Bowl, in large part because of Warrick's outstanding play.</p>
        <p>Of course, university officials respond in varying ways when coaches and athletes face possible suspension or dismissal. The facts vary, and so do the outside pressures.</p>
        <p>Two Smaller Schools Take Strong Action</p>
        <p>Last week, Providence College, a small Roman Catholic school in Rhode Island with a well-respected Big East basketball program, came down hard on members of the basketball team for their role in an assault last month. Three players projected as starters next season were expelled. ''An assault on a student goes to the very heart of who we are,'' the college president, the Rev. Philip A. Smith, said. ''This is not a basketball issue for me.''</p>
        <p>In some cases, elected officials have even urged universities to take strong action. The University of Vermont canceled the remainder of the hockey season last January after Gov. Howard Dean intervened in the wake of a hazing scandal.</p>
        <p>A former member of the team had alleged in a lawsuit that he had been degraded during hazing. Among other things, he said he had been forced to wear women's panties and to parade naked at a party while holding the genitals of other freshman players.</p>
        <p>University officials had investigated the allegations last fall, but had had difficulty penetrating a wall of silence among the hockey players, said the president, Dr. Judith Ramaley. The coach, Mike Gilligan, had planned to suspend each player for one game on a rotating basis.</p>
        <p>''I was outraged at what had gone on,'' Governor Dean said in an interview last week. ''My concern was that the university didn't appear to be taking any action.''</p>
        <p>Governor Dean made a rare appearance before the board of trustees, where he is an ex officio member, and made his feelings known. University officials then asked the state attorney general to investigate the allegations. Under oath, several hockey players admitted they had not told the truth earlier and provided details. Dr. Ramaley then canceled the rest of the season.</p>
        <p>Although hockey is the most popular college sport in the state, Dr. Ramaley said she had not been pressured by fans or alumni to go easy on the players. Indeed most Vermont alumni seemed to support canceling the season, she said. The problem had been getting to the bottom of the charges. ''We learned to our shock the students had lied,'' Dr. Ramaley said. ''We ended up making a statement about character.''</p>
        <p>In the end, Indiana's decision to keep Mr. Knight on may have also been about character, critics say. Mr. Knight's flamboyant and volatile style has kept him and his teams in the public eye for years.</p>
        <p>''He's a media star of heroic proportions,'' Dr. Sack said. ''You are messing with an American institution, who stands for all that popular culture and mass culture holds in high regard.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
