<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hill Has Many Reasons To Stay With Detroit</title>
    <meta content="21NBAA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201360"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL: NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Detroit Pistons</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hill, Grant</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wise, Mike</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Detroit Pistons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000521T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE2DA103AF932A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1525" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hill Has Many Reasons To Stay With Detroit</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIKE WISE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wise, Mike</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Basketball Notebook article focuses on whether Grant Hill will remain with Detroit Pistons; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Grant Hill has been visiting team employees at the Palace of Auburn Hills, talking often with Joe Dumars, a Pistons executive and former teammate, and enjoying life in Detroit while he recovers from foot surgery.</p>
        <p>None of this guarantees that Hill, an All-Star forward, will remain a Piston in the off-season. But the notion that he is fed up with the franchise and wants to relocate soon is hardly accurate.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Grant Hill has been visiting team employees at the Palace of Auburn Hills, talking often with Joe Dumars, a Pistons executive and former teammate, and enjoying life in Detroit while he recovers from foot surgery.</p>
        <p>None of this guarantees that Hill, an All-Star forward, will remain a Piston in the off-season. But the notion that he is fed up with the franchise and wants to relocate soon is hardly accurate.</p>
        <p>Lon Babby, Hill's agent, has said Hill plans to visit other teams when he exercises a clause in his contract to become a free agent in less than two months. Unless his feelings about leaving change quickly, Hill will most likely sign a one-year deal with Detroit for $9 million.</p>
        <p>After the 2000-1 season, he will have seven years of experience, which could help him secure a deal worth more than $100 million from the organization and about $95 million from another team. If Hill does not sign, he can now qualify for only an $83 million deal from Detroit and about a $76 million deal elsewhere, based on his six years of experience.</p>
        <p>Hill, who along with Shaquille O'Neal has taken over Michael Jordan's endorsement throne, has often said money is one of the smallest considerations in his decision. He desperately wants to play on an elite team. He is also proud enough not to want to have the lasting image of the Hill era in Detroit of an injured All-Star kicking his foot in frustration during a first-round sweep by Miami.</p>
        <p>He believes in Dumars's ability to find the right people. The outside possibility that the Pistons can lure Jalen Rose home to Michigan and away from Indiana has also piqued Hill's interest.</p>
        <p>In February 1998, with the Pistons in turmoil after the firing of Coach Doug Collins, Hill told a confidant he could see himself playing in New York. Who knows if the Knicks, if unsatisfied with their performance in the playoffs, would try to upgrade by trying to move either Latrell Sprewell or Allan Houston for the right player?</p>
        <p>Hill is one of the top four commodities in the National Basketball Association, in the class of O'Neal, Kobe Bryant and Tim Duncan. Unless the Pistons' hand is forced, the idea that they would accept anything less than one of the top 10 players in the league for Hill is disrespecting the intelligence of their front office.</p>
        <p>You wonder if salivating executives from other teams have not contributed mightily to the Hill-is-unhappy rumors spreading throughout the league. If he stays, it is not as if his value will go down or he is an aging veteran trying to find a championship team before it is too late. The feeling is, Hill will give Detroit one more season to build a bona fide contender. But not any longer.</p>
        <p>Postseason Frenzy</p>
        <p>A Western Conference general manager recently heard an intriguing rumor: that Sonics point guard Gary Payton, fed up with playing for Seattle, was going to issue a trade demand Friday night on TNT. ''And if Duncan bolts for Orlando, all of a sudden, we're in good shape,'' the general manager said, speaking on condition of anonymity.</p>
        <p>Payton did not go on the air and ask to be traded, just as Tim Duncan was not about to leave San Antonio and sign with the Orlando Magic. But such is the climate this time of year, when every eliminated team starts to wonder how it can make itself better.</p>
        <p>Some other scuttlebutt is making the rounds.</p>
        <p>Isiah Thomas is supposedly coveted by every team with a vacant head-coaching position. That may be stretching the truth.</p>
        <p>Actually, Byron Scott now appears to be Atlanta's No. 1 candidate, and that is if he does not wind up in Indiana. Thomas would like to coach the Pacers, but that will probably not happen if Larry Bird remains with the team in some capacity. Bird prefers Rick Carlisle, his longtime friend and Pacers assistant, to take over.</p>
        <p>Carlisle, by the way, has an in for the Vancouver job. He was on Chuck Daly's staff in New Jersey. Daly was recently hired by the Grizzlies as a consultant. (Read: Dick Versace needs help hiring a coach.)</p>
        <p>Thomas's best bet may be with the Nets, who want a marquee name.</p>
        <p>That does not explain why Kenny Smith, studio analyst for TNT, said the Nets were interested in talking to him. At any rate, as Thomas or Doc Rivers could tell Smith, why get genuine coaching experience on a bench when you can increase your profile taking other coaches apart on TV?</p>
        <p>Payton may move from Seattle, but not unless another team will give up comparable value. The Knicks will not tear up their team to acquire Payton, no matter how badly they appear to need an elite point guard.</p>
        <p>''We value him so highly, it's hard for me to envision we could get back what he means to us,'' said Wally Walker, Seattle's general manager. ''We'll always listen, but our respect for Gary's talent level would prevent us from probably doing anything.''</p>
        <p>Orlando's John Gabriel was not selected executive of the year by his peers last week because the Magic did not make the playoffs this season. Beyond having enough salary cap room to sign two free agents to the maximum contracts, the Magic has a good chance of securing the Nos. 3, 10 and 13 picks in today's draft lottery.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Michael Jordan has got to be hoping for a good bounce of the Ping-Pong balls in the lottery hopper. If the Washington Wizards receive one of the top three picks, they get to keep it while giving Chicago an unconditional first-round pick next season. If they fall below No. 3, the pick reverts to Chicago this season.</p>
        <p>Interestingly, Chris Webber, eight years after he was drafted, will be responsible for the maneuvering of at least two of the top seven picks. The Magic's first pick is courtesy of Golden State, which gave up the pick when it traded Webber for Anfernee Hardaway on draft day 1992.</p>
        <p>What is more, Washington's pick is tied into their acquiring Webber in 1994. That is the same pick the Warriors held the Wizards hostage over when Jordan tried to hire Rod Higgins at the end of January.</p>
        <p>Talk about a time-release bomb. The Wizards and the Warriors are still suffering from their Webber association.</p>
        <p>Depending on where it drafts, the Magic is high on Iowa State's Marcus Pfizer, whose scoring savvy dwarfs any other offensive-minded player in college basketball.</p>
        <p>A Riley-Rider Combo</p>
        <p>No matter how far Pat Riley takes Miami this season, the Heat need some sort of offensive upgrade next season. Having tried to acquire players like Mitch Richmond and Latrell Sprewell, Riley and Randy Pfund, the Heat general manager, understand the need for more point production.</p>
        <p>That is where America's No. 1 trouble-making basketball player comes in. Imagine, Isaiah Rider cloaked in Miami red and black.</p>
        <p>''I would consider it, with certain conditions,'' Riley said recently, regarding the possibility of acquiring the oft-troubled but incredibly talented shooting guard. ''You just never know. I believe people can change and somewhere they really do see the light and they see their career passing right in front of them. I don't know. We'll come to that point.''</p>
        <p>Riley said acquiring a player like Rider, whose penchant for being tardy and whose play to the beat of his own drum are among his litany of transgressions, would depend on how well a player like Rider adapted to playing for him.</p>
        <p>''I'm all for giving players opportunities, but when they come here they know there are no compromises there,'' Riley said. ''And especially with somebody who has his track record.''</p>
        <p>Riley said a bigger problem than Rider's fitting in might be changing people's perceptions. ''A guy like that, he's on call all the time,'' Riley said. ''He's on notice all the time. That even creates even more pressure. He can't even then be an innocent human being, so if he does something innocently wrong, he's measured. That's what he's created for himself. Those players have to be above and beyond reproach now. They have to at least have to try to be.''</p>
        <p>Riley has a reputation for getting malcontents to buy into his system, but you wonder if he might not be going too far with Rider, who was released from the Atlanta Hawks earlier this season after a series of team violations.</p>
        <p>''You can't control the injury factor, but you can control the personality factor,'' Riley said. ''You don't let anybody get into the way of that. You're always going to have conflict. There's an ongoing tension in this league between coaches and players. It's always going to be there. Because my job -- and this is going to sound cliche -- my job is to get those guys to do the things they don't want to do in order to achieve what it is we all said we want.''</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL: NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
