<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Americans Keep It Interesting</title>
    <meta content="12SOCC$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/12/sports/12SOCC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238222"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SOCCER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Cup (Soccer)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Costa Rica</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Barbados</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yannis, Alex</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Barbados</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Costa Rica</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Costa Rica</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Barbados</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Cup (Soccer)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001012T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E3D7173FF931A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="688" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Americans Keep It Interesting</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEX YANNIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Yannis, Alex</byline>
      <dateline>COLUMBUS, Ohio, Oct. 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>United States and Costa Rica play to scoreless tie in world cup qualifying match; US might need victory in Barbados next month to advance to regional final (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The United States played to a scoreless tie against Costa Rica in a frantic World Cup qualifying game here tonight and now might need a victory in Barbados next month in the last game of the group to advance to the regional final.</p>
        <p>Two teams from among Costa Rica, Guatemala and the United States will advance. Costa Rica, which leads the group with 11 points, is scheduled to play Guatemala, which now trails the United States by 1 point.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The United States played to a scoreless tie against Costa Rica in a frantic World Cup qualifying game here tonight and now might need a victory in Barbados next month in the last game of the group to advance to the regional final.</p>
        <p>Two teams from among Costa Rica, Guatemala and the United States will advance. Costa Rica, which leads the group with 11 points, is scheduled to play Guatemala, which now trails the United States by 1 point.</p>
        <p>The Americans played with their suspended coach, Bruce Arena, in a booth in the stands, without their suspended captain and playmaker, Claudio Reyna, and several other key players because of suspensions and injuries.</p>
        <p>With so many regulars missing the game, the Americans reached into their depth chart and came up with a combination of players that was not good enough for a victory against a quick and skillful Costa Rica team that has always given problems to the Americans.</p>
        <p>''We have good depth, but Costa Rica is a good team,'' Arena said after the game. ''I feel confident with the Olympians, especially Wolff.''</p>
        <p>Josh Wolff, Chris Albright, Jeff Agoos and Ben Olsen were four Olympians the Americans used in the game. Except for Agoos, who acted as the captain in place of Reyna, the other three were used as substitutes in the last 20 minutes in the game, when the Americans seemed to need fresh legs. Wolff had a goal disallowed for offside three minutes into injury time, to the disappointment of the large segment in the sellout crowd of 24,430 at Crew Stadium.</p>
        <p>The game was evenly played for the most part. A number of chances were created by each team, but they failed to finish.</p>
        <p>Joe-Max Moore and Cobi Jones had the best chances for the Americans in the first half, but Moore's blistering shot was knocked away by the goalkeeper, Alvaro Messen, in the 23rd minute, and the shot by Jones sailed wide left five minutes later. Moore also had a good chance in the second half, but his header missed the target in the 56th minute. ''It's an unfortunate result for us,'' Jones said, ''because I thought we played well enough for a victory.''</p>
        <p>Paulo Wanchope had the best chance for Costa Rica. It came a minute before intermission, but Kasey Keller reacted well to smother Wanchope's low shot from the top of the penalty area. Wanchope and Hernan Medford, the two strikers, caused some problems for the American defenders, who had Carlos Lliamosa marking Wanchope on the right and Agoos marking Medford on the left.</p>
        <p>Costa Rica has been a thorn on the Americans' side in World Cup qualifying. The Americans have lost just five games in World Cup qualifying since the 1982 World Cup, and all the losses have come to Costa Rica.</p>
        <p>It was the 2-1 loss in Costa Rica last July that led to the suspension of Arena and Reyna for their tirade with the Jamaican referee for awarding Costa Rica a questionable penalty kick in injury time that provided the margin of victory for Costa Rica.</p>
        <p>Arena served the first of his three-game suspension by FIFA, by sitting in a booth in the stands during the game, but he relayed messages to the bench, which was ran by his assistant, Dave Sarachan.</p>
        <p>''I'm not happy we didn't win, but I'm happy with the way we played,'' Sarachan said. ''We pressed for a goal and we had our chances, but guys passed up a shot in favor of a pass a couple times.''</p>
        <p>It all means that the Americans will need their best players for the game in Barbados Nov. 15, even though Barbados is the weakest team in the group.</p>
        <p>SOCCER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
