<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Delicate Dance of the Interventionist and the Reluctant Internationalist</title>
    <meta content="Y12POL$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/12/politics/12POLI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238251"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: FOREIGN POLICY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sanger, David E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Issues/Foreign Policy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001012T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE7D6173FF931A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1382" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Delicate Dance of the Interventionist and the Reluctant Internationalist</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID E. SANGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sanger, David E</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Analysis of foreign policy issues raised in presidential debate between Vice Pres Al Gore and Gov George W Bush; both candidates seem to see little electoral advantage in fighting over issue, with each politely warning of foreign entanglements they might avoid; Gore portrays self as interventionist Democrat; Bush seems reluctant internationalist (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For the better part of a year now, Vice President Al Gore and Gov. George W. Bush have gingerly stepped around much detailed discussion of how America should exercise its unchallenged economic, diplomatic and military power around the world.</p>
        <p>When they were finally forced to face off on that question in their presidential debate tonight, it seemed as if each had calculated that there was little electoral advantage in fighting over foreign policy. Indeed, rather than talk about how to exert American might -- the subtext of the famous Nixon-Kennedy debates in 1960 and so many of the cold-war-era debates that followed -- they spent much of the time politely warning of the foreign entanglements they might avoid.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For the better part of a year now, Vice President Al Gore and Gov. George W. Bush have gingerly stepped around much detailed discussion of how America should exercise its unchallenged economic, diplomatic and military power around the world.</p>
        <p>When they were finally forced to face off on that question in their presidential debate tonight, it seemed as if each had calculated that there was little electoral advantage in fighting over foreign policy. Indeed, rather than talk about how to exert American might -- the subtext of the famous Nixon-Kennedy debates in 1960 and so many of the cold-war-era debates that followed -- they spent much of the time politely warning of the foreign entanglements they might avoid.</p>
        <p>And yet there were some significant distinctions -- often buried in quick asides meant to hint, but never exactly state, how each man might run the country differently from the other.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore portrayed himself as the interventionist Democrat, the man who would be driven largely by ''a question of values'' and who would consider an act of genocide enough of a challenge to American interests to consider sending troops abroad. He stopped short, however, of saying the Clinton administration should have done so to stop the genocide in Rwanda six years ago.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush was the reluctant internationalist, the man who allowed that ''we've got to do a lot of work in Africa to promote democracy and trade'' and then insisted that America should keeps its troops out of Africa and Haiti, or anyplace else where the mission sniffed of ''nation-building.'' He never defined that phrase, but he made clear that he thought the purpose of the American military was to fight wars, not rebuild countries.</p>
        <p>And in Mr. Bush's world view, America's traditional allies mattered far more than remote, poor or strategically inconsequential nations. ''There's got to be priorities,'' he said, ticking off the Middle East, Europe, the Far East and ''our own hemisphere,'' a list that conspicuously omitted Africa and many of the world's poorest nations.</p>
        <p>''I'm not so sure the role of the United States is to go around the world and say, 'This is the way it's got to be,' '' Mr. Bush said, sounding much like the Democrats sounded in the aftermath of the Vietnam War. Later he added, ''I just don't think it's the role of the United States to walk into a country, say, ' We do it this way; so should you.' ''</p>
        <p>That left Mr. Gore free to sound more like the Republicans of two decades ago -- certain that America's role is to make others in the world exercise their long-suppressed desire to ''be like us more.'' He described himself, as he did in an interview last week, as a nation-builder and proud of it.</p>
        <p>Once again, he invoked President Harry S. Truman's use of the Marshall Plan to rebuild Europe, seeming to suggest that it was the kind of role Mr. Bush would have opposed.</p>
        <p>''We were nation-building,'' Mr. Gore said. ''And it was economic, but it was also military.''</p>
        <p>This all seemed like an academic argument, more suited for International Relations 101. But it got interesting as soon as it got specific.</p>
        <p>Pressed by the moderator, Jim Lehrer, about when they would have committed troops and when they would have backed off, Mr. Gore and Mr. Bush politely quibbled. But these  were quibbles with a deeper message that suggested significantly different standards of when American intervention makes sense.</p>
        <p>Lebanon, where American marines died in a huge car-bomb blast? ''I thought that was a mistake,'' Mr. Gore said.</p>
        <p>Grenada, where President Ronald Reagan, in the name of saving American medical students, made a clumsy but successful stand against a tiny government that seemed to be defying American wishes and influence? ''I supported that,'' he said, along with the Bush administration's ouster of Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega, Panama's dictator. But he had second thoughts about Somalia, a decision of ''the Bush-Quayle administration,'' he said, unable to avoid reference to one of the Republican Party's less admired vice presidents.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush, treading carefully, had problems with Somalia, too, not the mission his father began but the one President Clinton finished.</p>
        <p>''Started off as a humanitarian mission and then changed into a nation-building mission,'' he insisted, ''and that's where the mission went wrong.''</p>
        <p>But he supported almost every other intervention -- ''Some of them I've got a conflict of interest on,'' he said, to laughter, in a reference to his father's decisions -- raising the question of when he in fact would decide to keep his forces at home.</p>
        <p>Later, pressed about where he might pull back American forces, which he said were overcommitted, Mr. Bush had a hard time. He would keep them in Korea, he said, and in Europe. But he also said he would hand off peacekeeping to other, regional players; he cited Australia's role last year in East Timor as a superb example of where someone else provided the troops while the Pentagon gave advice and a bit of logistical help. He said he would like to withdraw American troops from the Balkans, but not immediately. The only place he named from which he would withdraw troops at once was Haiti, where there are only a handful.</p>
        <p>Governor Bush may have left viewers with the incorrect impression that the United States is alone in maintaining ground troops to keep the peace in Bosnia and Kosovo.</p>
        <p>''I'd very much like to get our troops out of there,'' he said. ''I recognize we can't do it now; nor do I advocate an immediate withdrawal. That would be an abrogation of our agreement with NATO. No one is suggesting that. But I think it ought to be one of our priorities to work with our European friends to convince them to put troops on the ground.''</p>
        <p>But many other nations -- and not just the NATO allies -- have ground troops currently committed to the Balkans. Of the 20,000 troops now assigned to the Bosnia peacekeeping mission, 4,600 are American. In Kosovo, the total mission of 40,000 troops has 6,000 Americans.</p>
        <p>The dynamic of the interventionist Mr. Gore and the more reluctant Mr. Bush also played out beyond the military realm.</p>
        <p>As on other foreign policy issues, the two men gingerly approached the question of when America should put up its own money, or the International Monetary Fund's, to stop financial crises. Here, Mr. Bush was more specific.</p>
        <p>''I think the I.M.F. has got a role in the world,'' the governor said, ''but I don't want to see the I.M.F. out there as a way to say to world bankers, 'If you make a bad loan, we'll bail you out.' ''</p>
        <p>Yet that is exactly what the I.M.F. and the United States Treasury did in Mexico, an intervention that was supported by Mr. Bush, whose home state, Texas, would have borne the brunt of a more severe Mexican economic collapse.</p>
        <p>Without noting that Mr. Gore had been the architect of much of the Clinton administration's Russia policy, Mr. Bush charged that the administration had blindly lent to corrupt regimes. ''We went into Russia,'' he said. ''We said, 'Here's some I.M.F. money,'  and it ended up in Viktor Chernomyrdin's pocket.''</p>
        <p>He referred to the former Russian prime minister, who was Mr. Gore's counterpart in long negotiations over Russian reforms.</p>
        <p>Numerous studies of the I.M.F. bailouts of Russia have failed to prove that Mr. Chernomyrdin benefited directly, though the enterprises that he made a fortune running were certainly helped.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore was clearly on the defensive, and said he was uncomfortable with the I.M.F. ''I've seen them make some calls that I thought were highly questionable,'' he said, without giving specifics.</p>
        <p>And then he went on to decry corruption -- hardly a controversial position -- before insisting that providing aid was also a way of extending American influence.</p>
        <p>''We have a fundamental choice to make,'' he said. ''Are we going to step up to the plate as a nation the way we did after World War II?''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush chose not to answer, at least directly.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: FOREIGN POLICY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
