<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Promising Start for Hampton and the Mets</title>
    <meta content="12METS$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/12/sports/12METS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238262"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL: 2000 PLAYOFFS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">St Louis Cardinals</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kepner, Tyler</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/St Louis Cardinals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001012T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E4D6173FF931A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1194" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Promising Start for Hampton and the Mets</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kepner, Tyler</byline>
      <dateline>ST. LOUIS, Oct. 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Mets defeat St Louis Cardinals, 6-2, and take 1 game to none lead in National League championship series; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mike Hampton made these the first words of his postgame news conference tonight: ''It wasn't pretty.'' His manager, Bobby Valentine, opened with these: ''His performance was fabulous.''</p>
        <p>Hampton is a perfectionist, and his seven shutout innings looked fine to the Mets, who rode them to a 6-2 victory over the St. Louis Cardinals in the first game of the National League Championship Series. But Hampton knew he had better stuff in his last start, a loss at San Francisco in the first game of the last playoff round.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mike Hampton made these the first words of his postgame news conference tonight: ''It wasn't pretty.'' His manager, Bobby Valentine, opened with these: ''His performance was fabulous.''</p>
        <p>Hampton is a perfectionist, and his seven shutout innings looked fine to the Mets, who rode them to a 6-2 victory over the St. Louis Cardinals in the first game of the National League Championship Series. But Hampton knew he had better stuff in his last start, a loss at San Francisco in the first game of the last playoff round.</p>
        <p>One bad pitch cost him the game that day, but over all, he felt his command was better, his pitches sharper. He encountered plenty of trouble tonight, but escaped every time. It was a maximum-effort performance, he explained, and it was draining.</p>
        <p>''There was only one inning when I retired the side in order,'' Hampton said, ''so there were always people on base, and every pitch had some meaning behind it.''</p>
        <p>Hampton, who lost in the division series and did not have a victory in three postseason starts for Houston, allowed six hits and walked four. John Franco followed with a scoreless inning. Before the Cardinals scored a pair of unearned in the ninth, the Mets had tossed 26 consecutive scoreless innings.</p>
        <p>Hampton held the Cardinals hitless in seven at-bats with runners in scoring position. His counterpart, the 20-game winner Darryl Kile, pitched well over seven innings, but was burned by the top of the Mets' batting order. Mike Piazza drove in the first run with a double, Edgardo Alfonzo scored a run and drove in another, and Timo Perez figured in both of the first two rallies.</p>
        <p>Even in the best-pitched games, said Al Leiter, who starts Game 2 for the Mets Thursday, there are one or two moments when a pitcher gets in trouble. The difference in October, Leiter said, is which pitchers work out of it. ''Certainly Mike had his moments,'' Leiter said, ''but really what it is is mental toughness and making quality pitches when he had to, and he did that.''</p>
        <p>The most crucial pitch for Hampton was his last one, to Jim Edmonds with two outs and two runners on in the seventh. Hampton threw a cutter away, and Edmonds bashed it to left, trotting to first and tracking the flight of the ball and Benny Agbayani's uncertain pursuit of it.</p>
        <p>The wind blowing his way, Agbayani retreated tentatively to the warning track, camping himself under the ball. With his glove about shoulder-high, Agbayani cradled it. The Mets' 3-0 lead was preserved, and disaster was averted.</p>
        <p>''I think everybody took a deep breath after that catch,'' Agbayani said. ''Some of the guys in the dugout said, 'You made us nervous there.' ''</p>
        <p>That was the Cardinals' last, best chance against Hampton. If Shawon Dunston had reached base off John Franco with a runner on and two outs in the eighth, Mark McGwire would have come to bat as the potential tying run. But Franco retired Dunston on a fly out, and the Mets broke the game open after that.</p>
        <p>They scored three runs in the ninth off reliever Mike James, who allowed a homer to Todd Zeile, a single to Agbayani and a two-run homer to Jay Payton.</p>
        <p>Many of the 52,255 fans left Busch Stadium then, but James stayed in and ran a fastball up and in on Mike Bordick, striking the Mets' shortstop on his right thumb. Bordick reacted immediately, snapping his hand in pain, and Kurt Abbott replaced him.</p>
        <p>Bordick suffered a contusion of his right thumb, and although X-rays were negative, he was uncertain if he would play on Thursday.</p>
        <p>In their three division series victories, the Mets scored in seven innings. Perez had a hit in four of those rallies, and he was involved in the first two tonight. The rookie leadoff hitter is a force, and the Mets readily acknowledge the difference he makes.</p>
        <p>''We didn't have a prototypical leadoff hitter, and we do in Timo,'' said Agbayani, who was displaced at the top of the order by Perez. ''He gets on base, has some power, and you've got one of the best clutch hitters in baseball hitting second. If Timo gets on, you know Fonzie's going to make something happen.''</p>
        <p>That was the pattern in the Giants' series, and it continued tonight. Perez led off the game with a double to the right-field corner, and with Alfonzo batting, Kile's fastball skipped away from the catcher, allowing Perez to go to third. Then Alfonzo walked, and Piazza came to bat.</p>
        <p>Piazza has made a habit of hitting well against the best pitchers, and he came in with a .344 career average against Kile. On the first pitch, Piazza pulled a curveball inside the third-base line for a double, bringing in Perez with the game's first run.</p>
        <p>Robin Ventura then lined to left field, deep enough to score Alfonzo on a sacrifice to put the Mets ahead by 2-0. Piazza was still on second as Zeile, who also hits Kile well, came to bat. But Zeile struck out looking on a pitch he thought was inside, and Agbayani grounded out, ending the inning.</p>
        <p>Hampton nearly surrendered the lead in the bottom of the inning, and he said he was conscious of the Cardinals' big first inning in Game 1 of their division series, when they battered Atlanta's Greg Maddux for six runs, propelling them to a sweep.</p>
        <p>With two outs, Eric Davis, a nemesis of Hampton batting cleanup to take advantage of the matchup, singled, then Will Clark walked. The bases were loaded for Carlos Hernandez, and Hampton went with his best pitch, a sinker.</p>
        <p>''I didn't want to leave a ball over the plate; I didn't want to give in,'' Hampton said. ''I wanted to stay aggressive.''</p>
        <p>It worked, as Hernandez grounded into a fielder's choice, ending the inning and sending Hampton on his way to that elusive first postseason victory.</p>
        <p>''It's good to finally win a game,'' Hampton said. ''I'm not going to downplay that. But it's really about having a quality start, giving the team a chance to win.''</p>
        <p>Ugly or fabulous, great stuff or not, Hampton did that tonight, and the Mets are three victories from the World Series.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL: 2000 PLAYOFFS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
