<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Relentless Steps, Nasdaq Slides Back Near Low of Year</title>
    <meta content="12RPLAC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238175"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001012T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E2DA173FF931A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="300" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Relentless Steps, Nasdaq Slides Back Near Low of Year</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Nasdaq stock market continued its plunge and has now returned to the lows of six months ago, when panic briefly gripped investors. This time the fall has been a bit less abrupt, but it has been even more relentless as one technology company after another has warned investors that growth is slowing.</p>
        <p>''Technology stocks are now guilty until proven innocent,'' said Thomas M. Galvin, the chief investment officer of Credit Suisse First Boston.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Nasdaq stock market continued its plunge and has now returned to the lows of six months ago, when panic briefly gripped investors. This time the fall has been a bit less abrupt, but it has been even more relentless as one technology company after another has warned investors that growth is slowing.</p>
        <p>''Technology stocks are now guilty until proven innocent,'' said Thomas M. Galvin, the chief investment officer of Credit Suisse First Boston.</p>
        <p>The Nasdaq composite index fell 72.05 points, or 2.2 percent, to 3,168.49, leaving it barely above its low close for this year of 3,164.55, reached on May 23. The index has declined in 13 of the last 15 sessions -- a record matched only twice in the last 15 years, during the 1987 crash and during the summer of 1994, when most of the declines were small.</p>
        <p>This time, the declines have been large by historical standards but small by the standards of the April plunge. The index has dropped 18.7 percent in the last 15 sessions. That is not nearly as much as the 33.1 percent fall the index endured during a similar period that ended April 14. During that stretch, the Nasdaq fell 7 percent or more on three days.</p>
        <p>This time, there has been no single day when the index fell by as much as 3.5 percent, and individual investors do not seem to have panicked. But the investors who are buying have not offset the selling pressure from other investors, which has been concentrated in stocks of companies that have warned that growth prospects were less than investors had grown accustomed to.  Business Day, Page C1.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
