<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The 'Makeup' Debate</title>
    <meta content="12THU1$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/12/opinion/12THU1.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238225"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001012T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E3D7173FF931A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="787" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The 'Makeup' Debate</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial holds Gov George W Bush may have gained more than Vice Pres Al Gore from kinder, gentler atmosphere of second presidential debate; notes he strove to look smarter and Gore to be less off-putting; sees Gore gambling that he will gain in long run with voters inclined toward him on issues but troubled by his officious manner</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Like two students dutifully taking a makeup exam, Vice President Al Gore and Gov. George W. Bush tried earnestly and politely last night in their second debate to make a better impression on Americans than they did the first time. Their goals were obvious. Mr. Bush wanted to look smarter, and Mr. Gore, chastened by criticism over the last week, wanted to be less off-putting. Both succeeded, but at first blush the Texan may have gained more from the kinder, gentler atmosphere. Mr. Bush thrived in the low-intensity environment, appearing markedly more confident and sure-footed than he had in the past. But Mr. Gore could get a payoff in the days ahead. He had clearly made a bet that by abandoning his bullying tactics of the first debate, he might gain in the long run with voters inclined toward him on issues but troubled by his officious manner.</p>
        <p>In the foreign policy sphere Mr. Gore was, as ever, more in command of the details. But Mr. Bush came across as solid and better briefed on the issues than he was last week. Indeed, the governor's misgivings about using American troops on ''nation-building'' missions framed the discussion. His cautious approach gave Mr. Gore a chance to promote his more muscular, interventionist view to deal with genocide and other humanitarian crises. He described the nation-building feared by Mr. Bush as within the tradition of American foreign policy since the days of the Marshall Plan in Europe after World War II.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Like two students dutifully taking a makeup exam, Vice President Al Gore and Gov. George W. Bush tried earnestly and politely last night in their second debate to make a better impression on Americans than they did the first time. Their goals were obvious. Mr. Bush wanted to look smarter, and Mr. Gore, chastened by criticism over the last week, wanted to be less off-putting. Both succeeded, but at first blush the Texan may have gained more from the kinder, gentler atmosphere. Mr. Bush thrived in the low-intensity environment, appearing markedly more confident and sure-footed than he had in the past. But Mr. Gore could get a payoff in the days ahead. He had clearly made a bet that by abandoning his bullying tactics of the first debate, he might gain in the long run with voters inclined toward him on issues but troubled by his officious manner.</p>
        <p>In the foreign policy sphere Mr. Gore was, as ever, more in command of the details. But Mr. Bush came across as solid and better briefed on the issues than he was last week. Indeed, the governor's misgivings about using American troops on ''nation-building'' missions framed the discussion. His cautious approach gave Mr. Gore a chance to promote his more muscular, interventionist view to deal with genocide and other humanitarian crises. He described the nation-building feared by Mr. Bush as within the tradition of American foreign policy since the days of the Marshall Plan in Europe after World War II.</p>
        <p>The exchanges came in a relatively informal setting at Wake Forest University in Winston-Salem, N.C. Mr. Bush had sought a more casual venue as a better showcase for his personal charm, and indeed he seemed to grow in confidence as the debate wore on. ''Seems like we're having a great love fest here tonight,'' he remarked, almost as if amused at the way Mr. Gore seemed to be on good behavior -- ''defanged,'' as some commentators put it. The vice president, conscious of the need to avoid being overbearing or committing trivial errors, at times did not look like his normal self, and it changed the chemistry of the encounter. Only at the end did he address the subject explicitly. Mr. Bush, in answer to a question about his opponent's credibility, repeated the charge that Mr. Gore had engaged in exaggerations and falsehoods. The vice president parried the accusation, acknowledging that he had gotten ''some of the details'' wrong about a student's having to stand for lack of desks but that his larger contention about overcrowded classrooms remained correct. As to the overarching question of his reliability, Mr. Gore insisted that even if he got details wrong, ''if I'm elected president, I'll work my heart out to get the big things right for the American people.''</p>
        <p>The shift of emphasis toward more discussion of foreign policy issues was obviously dictated by events. Except for a general criticism that the Clinton administration had been too quick to intervene in Haiti and other places, Mr. Bush did not level major criticisms at Mr. Gore. He noted, however, that the coalition against Saddam Hussein of Iraq had unraveled since the end of the gulf war, prompting Mr. Gore to observe dryly that it was the administration of President Bush, the governor's father, that had left Mr. Hussein in power.</p>
        <p>The candidates' polite demeanor lifted somewhat when they sparred over health care and the environment. Mr. Gore charged that Texas was either 49th or 50th in extending health care to uninsured women and children, failing to take advantage of the federal child health insurance program. Noting the governor's claims to be compassionate, the vice president sharply declared that he was not challenging Mr. Bush's ''heart'' so much as his priorities. Mr. Bush fired back that on the Clinton-Gore watch the number of uninsured Americans had increased, and that the vice president ''can make any excuse he wants.''</p>
        <p>The debate occurred at a moment of almost exquisite closeness in the presidential contest. Several recent polls have shown Mr. Bush slightly ahead of Mr. Gore, his best showing since before the Democratic convention in Los Angeles in August. A lot will depend on the public's final impressions of the debate last night, rather than on the flash polls and post-debate spin. Last week many voters thought Mr. Gore had ''won'' on substance but lost on style. The underlying truth is that while most Americans have made up their minds about the candidates and their positions, enough voters are uncertain about the measure of these two men to keep the race unpredictable. It may stay that way until the very end.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
