<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tensions Ease in a Blur of Runs</title>
    <meta content="12YANK$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/12/sports/12YANK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238244"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL: 2000 PLAYOFFS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Seattle Mariners</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olney, Buster</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Seattle Mariners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001012T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02EFD7173FF931A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1227" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tensions Ease in a Blur of Runs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olney, Buster</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Yankees defeat Seattle Mariners, 7-1, to tie American League championship series at 1-1; photos; graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The tension in the dugout was at high tide again, and Yankees Manager Joe Torre tried a small joke. ''Are you guys trying?'' he asked Derek Jeter after the Yankees' streak of scoreless innings reached 20 yesterday.</p>
        <p>Yes, they were trying. Sometimes you are trying so hard that you squeeze the bat handle, Paul O'Neill explained, and the fans are yelling and reminding you that you need to try even harder. Soon you are so rigid that the act of hitting a baseball -- something you have done since childhood -- is like driving a stick shift for the first time, the gears grinding.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The tension in the dugout was at high tide again, and Yankees Manager Joe Torre tried a small joke. ''Are you guys trying?'' he asked Derek Jeter after the Yankees' streak of scoreless innings reached 20 yesterday.</p>
        <p>Yes, they were trying. Sometimes you are trying so hard that you squeeze the bat handle, Paul O'Neill explained, and the fans are yelling and reminding you that you need to try even harder. Soon you are so rigid that the act of hitting a baseball -- something you have done since childhood -- is like driving a stick shift for the first time, the gears grinding.</p>
        <p>Yes, they were trying, losing by a run to Seattle in the eighth inning. But after Bernie Williams singled home the tying run in the bottom of the eighth, the Yankees finally relaxed and then exploded to beat the Mariners, 7-1, in Game 2 of the American League Championship Series. All their runs came in that one inning.</p>
        <p>Orlando Hernandez threw another masterly game, allowing one run in eight innings and improving his career postseason record to 7-0.</p>
        <p>The four-of-seven-game series is now tied at 1-1, and the Yankees departed Yankee Stadium last night feeling as if they had rescued themselves from inevitable defeat.</p>
        <p>The next three games will be played in Seattle, and had there been a 2-0 deficit after two games, the Yankees' reign would have been in serious jeopardy.</p>
        <p>''I just sense that we relieved a lot of pressure today,'' said Torre, whose Yankees teams have won the last two World Series.</p>
        <p>Torre said something along those lines after the Yankees clinched the division title in Baltimore on Sept. 29, and after they won a playoff game five days later to snap an eight-game losing streak, and after the Yankees finally eliminated Oakland on Sunday. The tension keeps rising and the Yankees have almost gone under several times, but they keep struggling, seemingly dog-paddling their way to the next game.</p>
        <p>They scored six runs in the first inning against Oakland on Sunday but only one more the rest of the game, then were shut out by Seattle on Tuesday, when the Yankees struck out 13 times and Torre felt compelled to pinch-hit for the former All-Star O'Neill.</p>
        <p>After that game, O'Neill poked his head inside Torre's office as he departed the Stadium. ''Am I playing tomorrow?'' O'Neill asked.</p>
        <p>''Yeah, you're playing tomorrow,'' Torre replied forcefully.</p>
        <p>Torre did adjust his lineup to account for O'Neill's slump, dropping him to seventh in the batting order, switching David Justice to third and Jorge Posada to sixth, and right away, the Yankees threatened. Chuck Knoblauch led off the first inning with a walk, and after Seattle second baseman Mark McLemore botched a potential double-play ball, John Halama, the Mariners' starter, walked Justice to load the bases.</p>
        <p>But Bernie Williams, the Yankees' cleanup hitter, topped the ball two feet in front of the plate, and Seattle catcher Dan Wilson retrieved it, stepped on home and threw to first for a double play. Tino Martinez grounded out to end the inning without any runs, and the fans booed loudly, their heroes absorbing their frustration.</p>
        <p>It got worse. Scott Brosius beat out an infield hit to open the third and was immediately picked off, falling awkwardly. The Yankees had runners on first and second and two out in the fifth, and Justice grounded out. They advanced another runner into scoring position with two out in the sixth but failed to score.</p>
        <p>They were fortunate that Hernandez was pitching. Seattle scored a run in the third on a two-out single by Stan Javier, but El Duque allowed only five other hits and struck out seven, at ease on the October stage.</p>
        <p>When Martinez reached second with two outs in the sixth, O'Neill came to bat with the tying run in scoring position, but with only 13 hits in his last 82 at-bats, including one extra-base hit. Fans in right field, for whom O'Neill has been an icon, rose, and the rest of the Yankees faithful followed, chanting his name.</p>
        <p>O'Neill pulled a slow dribbler to the right side. He pumped his arms and legs, moving down the line in tight strides. First baseman John Olerud led Halama with the throw, and Halama and O'Neill both stomped on the bag at virtually the same instant. Out, signaled the umpire Wally Bell.</p>
        <p>O'Neill slammed his helmet to the ground with both hands, turned and charged the umpire. ''Sometimes you get caught up in these games,'' O'Neill said later.</p>
        <p>An inning later, the Yankees caught up to Seattle. After the Mariners' left-hander Arthur Rhodes took over for the Yankees eighth, his manager, Lou Piniella, decided not to make one other switch he thought about -- replacing the defensively challenged Al Martin in left.</p>
        <p>Justice led off for the Yankees. He hits left-handers well, and he smashed a high drive to left-center, the ball thumping high against the wall, maybe a foot or so from carrying over. It was a good start, and yet at the moment, it seemed like just another example of how the Yankees' offense was fated: so close to a home run, so close to tying the game.</p>
        <p>Williams came to bat, looking to punch the ball to the right side and advance Justice to third. But Rhodes knew this and began jamming the right-handed-hitting Williams with fastballs. The count reached three and two, and Williams changed his approach.</p>
        <p>''I was like, 'Forget this, I'm just going to try to hit the ball any way I can,' '' Williams said.</p>
        <p>Rhodes spun a breaking ball and Williams fouled it off, barely, and fouled off two more pitches. On the eighth pitch of the at-bat, Williams rifled a line drive toward second; Justice hesitated, unsure whether the ball would carry over McLemore's head, and when it did, he scored easily, and the top two decks of the old ballpark began quivering, the fans moving them.</p>
        <p>The burden of tying the game was gone, and the Yankees relaxed. Martinez hit a liner to left, and off the bat, it appeared Martin would be able to make the catch easily. Martin hesitated, however, staggered forward, reached down, and the ball went in and out of his glove for a single.</p>
        <p>The rest of the inning fell into place for the Yankees. Posada singled off McLemore's glove to score Williams with the go-ahead run; O'Neill hit a sacrifice fly, actually clapping his hands in relief; Luis Sojo singled; Jose Vizcaino doubled; Knoblauch singled; and Jeter slammed a homer, the hardest ball he has hit in a month and just the second Yankees homer in 88 innings, dating to the regular season.</p>
        <p>The Yankees had not had a hit with runners in scoring position in 25 innings, and in the eighth inning yesterday, they had four in a row.</p>
        <p>Are they trying? Yes. But they are resigned to the reality that nothing will come easy for them.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL: 2000 PLAYOFFS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
