<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cutting The Web Down to Size; New Tools Let You Get the Information You Want (as Long as Your Computer Doesn't Crash)</title>
    <meta content="12TOOL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Circuits" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238071"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Privacy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer Security</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Guernsey, Lisa</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Circuits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Privacy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001012T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E1DE163FF931A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1927" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cutting The Web Down to Size; New Tools Let You Get the Information You Want (as Long as Your Computer Doesn't Crash)</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LISA GUERNSEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Guernsey, Lisa</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Novel devices designed to streamline Web browsing may constitute threat to privacy as well as delivering convenience; new companies offer free services and software to accomplish this, as battle for attention of Internet users continues; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE average Web surfer opens the Netscape or Internet Explorer browser, punches in a Web address, comes to a Web page, then clicks from page to page. When lost, the person tries to maneuver through an array of bookmarks or, more often than not, resorts to the Back button.</p>
        <p>In 1994, that page-turning process seemed revolutionary. Today, it not only sounds run-of-the-mill but is also considered by many new Internet companies to be, well, ridiculous. Why should a person who wants a few headlines have to open a full page of information? Why should anyone have to click on link after link to get to the right information? And how many people really go back to all those Web sites they bookmark?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE average Web surfer opens the Netscape or Internet Explorer browser, punches in a Web address, comes to a Web page, then clicks from page to page. When lost, the person tries to maneuver through an array of bookmarks or, more often than not, resorts to the Back button.</p>
        <p>In 1994, that page-turning process seemed revolutionary. Today, it not only sounds run-of-the-mill but is also considered by many new Internet companies to be, well, ridiculous. Why should a person who wants a few headlines have to open a full page of information? Why should anyone have to click on link after link to get to the right information? And how many people really go back to all those Web sites they bookmark?</p>
        <p>Convinced that Web users are hungry for a better way, at least a dozen new companies are offering free services and software that they say will streamline browsing and ultimately change the way people experience the Internet. But before everyone applauds the arrival of these next-generation services, observers have a few warnings. The new tools, they say, may also lead to new annoyances, especially technical glitches, and new risks to consumers' privacy.</p>
        <p>''Your options are now richer and more various,'' said Keith Dawson, an Internet consultant who edits and publishes an online newsletter called Tasty Bits from the Technology Front. ''But from a privacy point of view, there are now more threats, more potential for the leakage of personal information.''</p>
        <p>Among the new tools, the most radical enable people to disregard the standard Web browser altogether by downloading colorful, Internet-based taskbars that are displayed on the computer desktop. Two of the services now available are Snippets and EntryPoint, which use a long, horizontal bar that sits at the bottom of your screen. Another is DoDots, which features small square windows that hover on your desktop wherever you choose to put them. They enable users to view bits of data, like the current weather or local traffic reports, without opening a full Web page.</p>
        <p>Other programs work within the format of the standard Web browser but tweak it. A company called NeoPlanet offers people the chance to alter their Internet Explorer browsers by dressing them up with color and patterns while also adding buttons for their favorite sports and shopping sites, weather reports and news headlines. Another service, called HotBar.com, offers similar options for both Netscape and Internet Explorer browsers.</p>
        <p>And a third species of service lets people set up their own personalized gates to the Web, a la My Yahoo, but with the option of gathering headlines or bits of data from whatever sites the users choose. That means users do not have to select sites from among those that have deals with Yahoo or other major Internet portals.</p>
        <p>''It's not up to us to go out and figure out what you want to see,'' said William A. Chen, founder and chief executive of OnePage, one of the personalization companies. ''That's not our job.''</p>
        <p>In addition to OnePage, other customization services include Octopus, which invites the surfer to add a new button to the browser that can be used to clip sections of Web pages at will, and ClickMarks, which seeks to provide personalized portals for wireless devices as well as for computer desktops.</p>
        <p>Not to be outdone, the developers of Internet Explorer and Netscape are unveiling new browsing tools, too. Netscape 6, which is available in beta versions, includes tabs on the left side of the browser that can be customized to include pieces of Web content. Microsoft's latest version of Internet Explorer, 5.5, allows people to create buttons that link to frequently used Web sites, like company intranets or school lunch menus. The browser has also been designed to encourage developers to create taskbars that display headlines or stock quotations even as new Web pages are opened.</p>
        <p>Amid the cacophony, one thing rings clear: the battle continues to rage for the attention of the Internet user. ''Everyone and his brother wants to have more of your eyeball space,'' said Paul Hagen, an analyst at Forrester Research. If a company can persuade surfers to rely on its service, to scan the service constantly for quick hits of updated and personalized information, that company has the best shot of turning traffic into advertising and e-commerce revenue.</p>
        <p>Of course, some would argue that this is not a new mission. In the early days of the Web, a company called Pointcast offered users a non-Web toolbar that included streaming news feeds. About the same time, America Online started to feature some personalization, like ZIP-code-specific data on weather reports. And officials for My Yahoo and My Excite, some of the earliest iterations of personalized Web-clipping programs, say that Web users are still signing up for their services in droves.</p>
        <p>But the developers of the new options say they offer more time savings and flexibility. Imagine, for example, that you simply want to know how cold it is outside. If you have a Snippets taskbar and an always-on Internet connection, you can simply glance at the bar's weather icon, where the local temperature is displayed and updated continually, even when you are working offline in an application like Microsoft Word.</p>
        <p>''This is empowering you to get the information you want,'' said Dennis Moulton, vice president for business development and marketing for Snippets Software, which is also creating products tailored to company intranets or customer-based Web sites. Without such a service, he said, a Web surfer often has to dig deep into a Web site to find one piece of information.</p>
        <p>Or suppose you want to glance at the day's feature stories on nonsyndicated news sites like Salon and Slate. By customizing your own Web view using OnePage, you can get hyperlinked headlines from all three in one spot. And you can retrieve those Web clippings from any computer with an Internet connection, not just the one that includes the downloaded software.</p>
        <p>In the short term, however, the drawbacks of the services could outweigh their benefits, Internet analysts say. To get those handy personalized features, for example, users will often have to divulge details about themselves. Snippets asks for the user's sex, ZIP code, job interests and e-mail address. DoDots collects data about how often a user turns to its services, how long is spent with the services and what information is sought.</p>
        <p>In both cases, the companies tell their customers how they use the data, and some people may be willing to sacrifice some privacy for convenience. But privacy advocates point to past cases, like that involving  Amazon.com, in which the company changed course in midstream and decided to distribute its customers' personal data if they bought products from other vendors at the Amazon site.</p>
        <p>With the stand-alone programs like DoDots or Snippets, there may also be the potential for security breaches. Mr. Dawson warns that the people who download these programs have essentially opened a new gateway for information to travel into and out of their computers.</p>
        <p>But the nuisance of the downloading process may turn off most people. Setting up customized Web-clipping services can be tedious and slow, especially using a dial-up connection. And many Internet users may not know how to hunt for those ''.exe'' files that install many of the browser applications. Besides, once they go through the trouble, they may find that the new software comes back to haunt them. The computer may start up more slowly than ever. Or it may start crashing inexplicably.</p>
        <p>The source of the instability is often hard to pin down, but it usually comes from a conflict between the new software and the software already on the machine, according to Dave Methvin, founder of PCPitstop.com, a Web site that offers computer tuneups. Sometimes, too, the addition of yet another application taps too much of the computer's memory, triggering shutdowns. Either way, the result is a pain in the P.C.</p>
        <p>Users should ask themselves this question, Mr. Methwin said: ''Is the benefit it offers me really worth the reduction in systems resources and stability?''</p>
        <p>Once a user has determined that a piece of software has become an unwelcome guest, the next challenge is to get rid of it. In HotBar.com, for example, a user might eventually figure out that by right-clicking on the word Hotbar, the Hotbar panel goes away. But the fix is only temporary; each time Internet Explorer is opened, Hotbar comes back. Like most software, the program must be completely uninstalled before it is truly gone. (To do that in Windows, go to the Add/Remove Program section of your computer's Control Panel.)</p>
        <p>Bob Rankin, the co-editor of Tourbus, an online newsletter about the Web, is not convinced that most Internet users are so desperate for new navigation tools that they will tolerate the annoyances, let alone change their browsing habits.</p>
        <p>''My experience is that, unless it is fantastically useful,'' he said, ''I either forget that it is there or stop using it after a few weeks.''</p>
        <p>What works for him instead? Simply getting an e-mail message with news headlines and worthwhile Web links, he said. ''Plain text in e-mail,'' he said, ''will rule the roost for a while.''</p>
        <p>Site-Seeing: Metabrowsers</p>
        <p>If you are not inclined to set up a customized portal or download a personalization taskbar, there are other tools that are designed to streamline your Web browsing. They are sometimes called metabrowsers because they provide information about the information you are viewing.</p>
        <p>For example, you may be reading a Web page that mentions a jazz band that interests you. Click on the band's name (even if it is not hyperlinked) and these tools will open up a window on your screen offering related links, news articles and, of course, online shops that sell the band's music. Many of these applications also work outside the Web browser, with Microsoft Word documents or e-mail messages, if you are using a Windows-based machine.</p>
        <p>But be warned: These are software programs, not just Web sites. You must download them to your computer, and in some cases they may destabilize your system. If crashes occur, try uninstalling the program to determine if it is the culprit.</p>
        <p>ALEXA: www.alexa.com -- As you browse the Web, related links pop up in the Alexa toolbar. One tab provides statistics about the site you are viewing, like third-party ratings and reviews.</p>
        <p>FLYSWAT: www.flyswat.com -- Press the Alt key while clicking on any word in any document and a tiny window will open with links to related news and shopping sites. Words that are already hyperlinked by Flyswat -- underlined in yellow -- require a single click.</p>
        <p>GURUNET: www.gurunet.com -- Point to a word on the screen in any document, press the Alt key and click the mouse button to pull up definitions, related news and stock quotes. A Web-based version is also available that works more like a search engine and does not require downloading.</p>
        <p>NANO: www.nano.com -- Highlight a word in a Web page, hit the right-click button on your mouse, and open a box with links to related news articles, online shops and encyclopedia entries.</p>
        <p>ZAPPER: www.zapper.com -- Click on a word and Zapper will use the surrounding context to figure out what additional information you seek.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
