<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lonely People Aren't Nice; Just Ask One</title>
    <meta content="12AUGU" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/12/arts/12AUGU.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238078"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Atlantic Theater Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brantley, Ben</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Donaghy, Tom</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pepe, Neil</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Steenburgen, Mary</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Beginning of August, The (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001012T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE5DD163FF931A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="898" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lonely People Aren't Nice; Just Ask One</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN BRANTLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brantley, Ben</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ben Brantley reviews Atlantic Theater Company production of Tom Donaghy play The Beginning of August, directed by Neil Pepe and starring Mary Steenburgen; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Playing a less than merry widow in ''The Beginning of August,'' the somber screwball comedy by Tom Donaghy now at the Atlantic Theater Company, Mary Steenburgen has that grown-up waif look that makes sane people run for cover. She's Little Orphan Annie with cleavage, a manicure and an aggressive air of neediness. The words ''dangerously vulnerable'' come to mind, as long as it's understood that the danger in this instance is to others.</p>
        <p>Ms. Steenburgen, who won an Academy Award as a prurience-proof stripper in ''Melvin and Howard'' (1980), became a film star providing skewed variations on goofy innocence. When she first appears in a tight macrame dress in ''The Beginning of August,'' a preachy play that has terrific, tantalizing promise for its first 10 minutes, she looks both wide-eyed and wild-eyed, eager and bitter.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Playing a less than merry widow in ''The Beginning of August,'' the somber screwball comedy by Tom Donaghy now at the Atlantic Theater Company, Mary Steenburgen has that grown-up waif look that makes sane people run for cover. She's Little Orphan Annie with cleavage, a manicure and an aggressive air of neediness. The words ''dangerously vulnerable'' come to mind, as long as it's understood that the danger in this instance is to others.</p>
        <p>Ms. Steenburgen, who won an Academy Award as a prurience-proof stripper in ''Melvin and Howard'' (1980), became a film star providing skewed variations on goofy innocence. When she first appears in a tight macrame dress in ''The Beginning of August,'' a preachy play that has terrific, tantalizing promise for its first 10 minutes, she looks both wide-eyed and wild-eyed, eager and bitter.</p>
        <p>There's a thrill of satisfaction in seeing a familiar persona so resourcefully reinvented. It's a bit like watching Goldie Hawn turn her trademark gamine allure into monstrous egotism in ''The First Wives Club.'' That dithery naivete is still there, but it seems somehow to have grown fangs.</p>
        <p>When Ms. Steenburgen's character is told that she seems like a nice person, she answers quickly, ''I'm not; I'm mean,'' adding without apology, ''Lonely people are never nice.'' Since everyone is lonely in Mr. Donaghy's new play, which opened last night under Neil Pepe's direction, you can easily compute the niceness quotient here. Fey and winsome these characters may be, with enough quirks to fill a season of sitcoms, but they are also very desperate.</p>
        <p>Looking for sourness and disenchantment within the cute and eccentric is a specialty of Mr. Donaghy, the talented and exasperating young author of ''Northeast Local'' and ''Minutes from the Blue Route.'' Like many playwrights of his generation, including Nicky Silver and David Greenspan, he portrays fractured families that are not so much dysfunctional as beyond functioning at all. You can't go home again in these fretful comedies because home, in its mythic sense, has ceased to exist.</p>
        <p>''The Beginning of August'' might be a manifesto for this school of theater, so painstakingly does it chart its ideas. At its center is yet another detonated domestic group. Pam (Mary McCann) has inexplicably fled from her new home, leaving her infant child in the care of her anal-retentive husband, Jackie (Garret Dillahunt), who calls in his stepmother, Joyce (Ms. Steenburgen), whom he never really liked, to look after the baby.</p>
        <p>Providing sexual complications are Ben (Jason Ritter), the Pam-worshiping young house painter, and Ted (Ray Anthony Thomas), a neighbor who looks after Jackie's lawn, among other things. There is also the unseen old woman who lives next door, a flashlight-wielding specter hungry for human contact and a cautionary vision of what the others might easily turn into.</p>
        <p>Everyone has pointed value in a symbolic map of solitary souls, with explanatory monologues to match. Ms. Steenburgen, for example, delivers a rant about the problems of holidays in this age of divorce, screaming, ''Everybody has to drive to too many houses.''</p>
        <p>Ms. McCann speaks forlornly of Pam's nervous breakdown in a supermarket parking lot, overwhelmed by a list of domestic items signifying nothing. And Jackie is saddled with an unfortunate climactic speech to the baby about a future in which things may be better. Emblems of disconnected lives are everywhere, from the tiny recorders in which characters tape messages for one another to the taunting catalogs of household accessories.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pepe and his worthy ensemble have gone for a comically exaggerated naturalism, which matches Scott Pask's ironically cheerful suburban backyard set, and this was probably a mistake. The approach doesn't make sense of the play's shifts between barbed dialogue and thematic monologues. It also underscores the impression that the people onstage are visual aids in a hipster's sermon.</p>
        <p>This is especially disappointing because there are intriguing glimmers of character in Joyce, a recent widow who suddenly finds herself without the sustaining social life she knew as part of a couple. Ms. Steenburgen, whose strength has always been in droll understatement, doesn't rise convincingly to Joyce's confrontational eruptions.</p>
        <p>But in the evening's early moments Ms. Steenburgen manages to sketch a provocative study of a woman suddenly deprived of the only role she has ever learned to play. Joyce's social reflexes have obviously become disjointed, and the resulting self-consciousness feels poisonous.</p>
        <p>Performers famous for eccentric charm in their youth can become self-parodies as they get older. Some, however, are cannily able to subvert that charm to enriching effect. Ms. Steenburgen is clearly capable of such unsettling sabotage. Let's hope she gets more complete opportunities to achieve it.</p>
        <p>THE BEGINNING OF AUGUST</p>
        <p>By Tom Donaghy; directed by Neil Pepe; sets by Scott Pask; lighting by Christopher Akerlind; costumes by Ilona Somogyi; sound by Janet Kalas; composer, David Carbonara; production stage manager, Darcy Stephens; production manager, Kurt Gardner; general manager, Andrew Loose. Presented by the Atlantic Theater Company, Mr. Pepe, artistic director; Hilary Hinckle, managing director. At 336 West 20th Street, Chelsea.</p>
        <p>WITH: Mary Steenburgen (Joyce), Garret Dillahunt (Jackie), Jason Ritter (Ben), Ray Anthony Thomas (Ted) and Mary McCann (Pam).</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
