<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE MARKETS: Market Place; Nasdaq Continues Its Relentless Falloff</title>
    <meta content="Y12PLA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/12/technology/12PLAC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238132"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nasdaq Composite Index</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nasdaq Stock Market</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Norris, Floyd</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Market Place</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nasdaq Composite Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001012T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E4DF173FF931A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="877" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE MARKETS: Market Place; Nasdaq Continues Its Relentless Falloff</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FLOYD NORRIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Norris, Floyd</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Nasdaq stock market, enduring its most persistent selling pressure in more than six years, has returned to lows of six months ago; this time fall has been a bit less abrupt, but it has been even more relentless as one technology company after another has warned investors that growth is slowing; Nasdaq composite index falls 72.05 points, or 2.2 percent, to 3,168.49, leaving it barely above its low close for 2000 on May 22; graph; photo (Market Place column) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Nasdaq stock market, enduring its most persistent selling pressure in more than six years, has now returned to the lows of six months ago, when panic briefly gripped investors. This time the fall has been a bit less abrupt, but it has been even more relentless as one technology company after another has warned investors that growth is slowing.</p>
        <p>''Technology stocks are now guilty until proven innocent,'' commented Thomas M. Galvin, the chief investment officer of Credit Suisse First Boston. He noted that investors who earlier this year focused on growth possibilities are now concentrating on fears that growth is slowing along with the economy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Nasdaq stock market, enduring its most persistent selling pressure in more than six years, has now returned to the lows of six months ago, when panic briefly gripped investors. This time the fall has been a bit less abrupt, but it has been even more relentless as one technology company after another has warned investors that growth is slowing.</p>
        <p>''Technology stocks are now guilty until proven innocent,'' commented Thomas M. Galvin, the chief investment officer of Credit Suisse First Boston. He noted that investors who earlier this year focused on growth possibilities are now concentrating on fears that growth is slowing along with the economy.</p>
        <p>The Nasdaq composite index fell 72.05 points, or 2.2 percent, to 3,168.49 yesterday, leaving it barely above its low close for this year of 3,164.55, reached May 23. The index has shown declines during 13 of the last 15 sessions -- a record matched only twice in the last 15 years, during the 1987 crash and during the summer of 1994, when most of the declines were small.</p>
        <p>This time, the declines have been large by historical standards, but small by the standards of the April plunge. The index has dropped 18.7 percent in the last 15 trading days. That is not nearly as much as the 33.1 percent fall the index endured during a similar period that ended April 14. During that stretch, the Nasdaq fell 7 percent or more on three days, producing front-page news that panicked some traders, as well as a spate of margin calls that forced some traders to sell.</p>
        <p>This time, by contrast, there has been no single day when the index fell by as much as 3.5 percent, and individual investors do not seem to have panicked. Indeed, one online brokerage firm, Ameritrade, reports that its customers have been doing more buying than selling over the stretch.</p>
        <p>But that buying has not been enough to offset the selling pressure from other investors, which has concentrated in stocks of companies that have warned that growth prospects were less than investors had grown accustomed to.</p>
        <p>''The revenues are just not growing as fast as they were, although they are still growing at a good rate,'' said William Rhodes, the chief investment strategist at the Williams Capital Group. Many of those stocks were trading at very high earnings multiples that are hard to justify if growth is slowing.</p>
        <p>Yahoo was one of yesterday's casualties, falling $17.31, to $65.38, even though it met investor expectations for third-quarter profits. But it warned that growth in its advertising revenue was being held down by financial problems affecting many Internet companies that had advertised heavily on Yahoo sites.</p>
        <p>In the last 15 sessions, Yahoo has fallen 40 percent, as has Dell Computer, but some other companies have done much worse, with Apple Computer off 68 percent, Intel down 44 percent and CMGI, a company that invests in Internet companies, off 47 percent.</p>
        <p>During the April sell-off, many of the worst performers were young Internet companies whose shares had been bid to giddy heights long before they provided evidence they could ever earn money. Most of those stocks never came back, but the more solid technology companies bounced back. Now many of them are suffering again, partly because of worries that growth is slowing.</p>
        <p>But concentrating on such companies gives a distorted view of the overall stock market. For most of 1998 and 1999, many stocks lagged behind as technology stocks soared and bolstered the major market indexes. This year, many of the technology stocks have come back down, but a lot of other stocks have held their own. Indeed, while the Value Line index -- which gives equal weight to every stock -- has fallen 5.7 percent over the last 15 days, it is still up 4.2 percent since the end of last year, indicating that the average stock has risen this year despite the big falls of some stocks. The Nasdaq composite is down 22 percent since the end of last year.</p>
        <p>Utilities have been especially strong -- the Standard &amp; Poor's utility index is up 44.5 percent this year, and financial stocks have also held their own.</p>
        <p>Many investors, and many mutual funds, entered this year with their largest investments in some of the stocks that have done the worst. Janus Capital, the mutual fund company, made headlines in January when it bought an entire secondary offering of Healtheon WebMD, since renamed webMD, paying $62 a share, or $930 million, for 15 million shares. Yesterday, with the stock under $10 a share, Janus disclosed that it had sold most of the shares.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
