<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Concern for Mourning Overshadows Preseason Opener</title>
    <meta content="12NETS$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/12/sports/12NETS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238180"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Miami Heat</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Robbins, Liz</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mourning, Alonzo</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Miami Heat</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Transplants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001012T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E5D9173FF931A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="753" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Concern for Mourning Overshadows Preseason Opener</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIZ ROBBINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Robbins, Liz</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., Oct. 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Miami Heat players , preparing for preseason opener, express concern for center Alonzo Mourning, who is suffering from kidney ailment; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The day felt strangely empty to the Miami Heat players, the game, in the end, a little more meaningless than a typical preseason game.</p>
        <p>When the Heat went to work against the Nets tonight in Continental Arena, it was without their All-Star center, Alonzo Mourning.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The day felt strangely empty to the Miami Heat players, the game, in the end, a little more meaningless than a typical preseason game.</p>
        <p>When the Heat went to work against the Nets tonight in Continental Arena, it was without their All-Star center, Alonzo Mourning.</p>
        <p>He was back in Miami seeing doctors about his kidney ailment, which was discovered during a team physical a week ago, trying to determine whether he would need a kidney transplant, dialysis or other treatment. The Heat has released little information about his condition.</p>
        <p>Mourning's absence tonight was a sobering reminder of vulnerability, even as the Nets celebrated their first preseason victory, 88-82. It came in the coaching debut of Byron Scott, a former Lakers player, who beat his onetime coach, Pat Riley, now coach of the Heat.</p>
        <p>Both teams were missing marquee players -- the Nets were without forward Keith Van Horn (strained left knee) -- and players wearing new uniforms excelled instead.</p>
        <p>Miami forward Brian Grant, a free-agent acquisition, had 29 points and 11 rebounds in 36 minutes.</p>
        <p>The top overall draft pick, Kenyon Martin of the Nets, started at power forward, and after Grant blocked his first shot, he struggled early with three first-half fouls. But Martin surged in the end, getting all of his 11 points and his three rebounds in the second half, playing 24 minutes. Point guard Stephon Marbury led the Nets in scoring with 18 points, and Kendall Gill shot 7 of 10 for 14 points.</p>
        <p>The training-camp hopeful Stephen Jackson made a strong bid to earn one of two available roster spots. Jackson, 22, who did not attend college but played in the Continental Basketball Association and Venezuela before joining the Nets, scored 12 first-half points and finished with 14. Miami center Todd Fuller, backing up Duane Causwell, who started for Mourning, had 12 points, 7 rebounds and 3 blocks.</p>
        <p>Without Mourning, it seemed as if the gaping hole in the middle of the paint extended to the hearts of the Heat coaches and players, who spoke before the game about being burdened by the uncertainty of Mourning's condition.</p>
        <p>''That's the hard thing,'' the 7-foot Causwell said. ''We don't know what we're getting ready for; we're getting ready for a whole year without Alonzo, or a whole preseason, or just a few games. It makes you reflect. There's more to this game. Hopefully, it's not serious.''</p>
        <p>Point guard Tim Hardaway said he would miss Mourning's on-court chatter for as long as he was out. But tonight he and his teammates were missing something more intangible than Mourning's points and blocks. ''His being,'' Hardaway said softly.</p>
        <p>On Tuesday, Mourning made a surprise visit to the Heat practice in Miami and infused the team with his signature cheeriness, refusing to take sympathy, instead riding an exercise bike, breaking a sweat as he did only 10 days ago with the United States Olympic team.</p>
        <p>''Alonzo is the type of guy who does not try to show his weakness,'' Causwell said. ''He was upbeat, but at the same time, you could tell it was really bothering him.''</p>
        <p>Riley did not want to elaborate on his ailing center, disturbed about the different reports speculating on his condition. ''He wants to make a statement himself, and when he looks at the camera, that's when he will be sure,'' Riley said.</p>
        <p>As for the impact of his absence, Riley was also guarded. ''I'm not thinking about that,'' he said. ''I'm trying to be optimistic just like Alonzo is. But he's more optimistic than all of us.''</p>
        <p>Miami's players were shocked by the suddenness of the news. ''I was with him the whole Olympics, and I didn't even dream of this happening,'' Hardaway said.</p>
        <p>The United States Olympic Committee conducts physicals for its athletes, but does not take blood tests. Mourning's blood was tested as part of the Heat's physical.</p>
        <p>''I haven't thought about anything basketball wise,'' forward Dan Majerle said. ''We're just more worried about Zo getting healthy. We don't know a lot about it. Once we get that settled and find out exactly what's going on, then we'll start thinking about the team.''</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
