<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Safeway Recalls Taco Shells After Test Questions Corn Origin</title>
    <meta content="Y12TAC$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/12/business/12TACO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238160"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Grain</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recalls and Bans of Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Corn</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bacteria</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Food Contamination and Poisoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Genetic Engineering</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Genetically Engineered Food Alert (Orgn)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Safeway Stores Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Misson Foods</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Environmental Protection Agency</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Kraft Foods</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Taco Bell</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pollack, Andrew</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Food Contamination and Poisoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Genetic Engineering</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corn</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Grain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food Contamination and Poisoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recalls and Bans of Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bacteria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vegetables</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001012T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E3DC173FF931A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="485" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Safeway Recalls Taco Shells After Test Questions Corn Origin</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW POLLACK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pollack, Andrew</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Coalition known as Genetically Engineered Food Alert has found unapproved corn in house-brand taco shells sold by Safeway supermarket chain; Safeway, without confirming discovery, immediately says it will remove taco shells from its shelves and offer refunds to customers who have already purchased them; it also says it will halt sales of taco shells sold under brand of Mission Foods, company that manufactured Safeway brand shells; new discovery, if confirmed, would indicate that contamination of food supply extends beyond Taco Bell brand taco shells recently recalled from groceries by Kraft Foods; corn, which contains bacterial toxin that kills insects, was approved by Environmental Protection Agency for use as animal feed but not for human consumption because of concerns that toxin could cause allergic reactions (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The unapproved genetically engineered corn connected with a nationwide recall of taco shells has been found in a second brand of shells as well, a coalition of biotechnology food critics said last night.</p>
        <p>The coalition, Genetically Engineered Food Alert, said it had found the unapproved corn in house-brand taco shells sold by the Safeway supermarket chain. Safeway, without confirming the discovery, immediately said it would remove the taco shells from its shelves and offer refunds to customers who have already purchased them. It also said it would halt sales of taco shells sold under the brand of Mission Foods, the company that manufactured the Safeway brand shells.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The unapproved genetically engineered corn connected with a nationwide recall of taco shells has been found in a second brand of shells as well, a coalition of biotechnology food critics said last night.</p>
        <p>The coalition, Genetically Engineered Food Alert, said it had found the unapproved corn in house-brand taco shells sold by the Safeway supermarket chain. Safeway, without confirming the discovery, immediately said it would remove the taco shells from its shelves and offer refunds to customers who have already purchased them. It also said it would halt sales of taco shells sold under the brand of Mission Foods, the company that manufactured the Safeway brand shells.</p>
        <p>The new discovery, if confirmed, would indicate that the contamination of the food supply extends beyond the Taco Bell brand taco shells recently recalled from groceries by Kraft Foods, a subsidiary of Philip Morris, after they were found to contain genetically engineered StarLink corn.</p>
        <p>The corn, which contains a bacterial toxin that kills insects, was approved by the Environmental Protection Agency for use as animal feed but not for human consumption because of concerns that the toxin could cause allergic reactions.</p>
        <p>There could be a connection between the two incidents of contamination. Mission Foods, the Safeway supplier, is owned by the same Mexican company, Gruma S.A., that owns Azteca Milling. Azteca's mill in Plainview, Tex., was determined to be the source of the corn flour used in the Kraft Tacos and the mill is also a supplier to Mission Foods.</p>
        <p>The report of further contamination could put more pressure on the Food and Drug Administration, which has said it will begin testing other foods made with corn.</p>
        <p>Larry Bohlen, director of health and environment programs at Friends of the Earth, a member of the coalition, said the Safeway taco shells tested were purchased at a supermarket in the suburbs of Washington. He said it was the only one of 14 corn-based foods tested to be found to contain the StarLink gene.</p>
        <p>The tests were conducted for the coalition by Genetic ID, a testing company in Fairfield, Iowa, that was started by a prominent critic of bioengineered foods. Genetic ID has defended the objectivity of its tests, and its initial findings about the Kraft taco shells were confirmed by Kraft and by the F.D.A.</p>
        <p>No one has determined how the StarLink corn got into the Kraft taco shells. There is speculation that farmers sold the corn for human food rather than for animal feed to get a higher price. It could also have been an inadvertent mix-up.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
