<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TRANSACTIONS</title>
    <meta content="12TRAN$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238266"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001012T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E2D6173FF931A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="538" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TRANSACTIONS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sports transactions</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AUTO RACING</p>
        <p>NASCAR--Fined Tim Boatwright, Scotty Pease and Alan Tully $2,000, Ralph Bryant $1,500 and Donnie Richeson and Ricky Pearson $500 and placed them on probation until Dec. 31 for an altercation in the pit area during the Bumper to Bumper All Pro 300 Busch Series race at Lowe's Motor Speedway on Oct. 7.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
        <p>American League  ANAHEIM ANGELS--Claimed LHP Mark Lukasiewicz off waivers from the Toronto Blue Jays.  OAKLAND ATHLETICS--Sent RHP Jon Ratliff and RHP Scott Service outright to Sacramento of the PCL. Announced OF Bo Porter has been claimed off waivers by the Texas Rangers.  TAMPA BAY DEVIL RAYS--Activated LHP Wilson Alvarez, RHP Juan Guzman and RHP Ryan Rupe from the 60-day disabled list. Sent LHP Trevor Enders, RHP Tony Fiore and RHP Dave Eiland outright to Durham of the International League.  TEXAS RANGERS--Sent LHP Corey Lee, LHP Juan Moreno and C B.J. Waszgis outright to Oklahoma of the PCL.</p>
        <p>National League  FLORIDA MARLINS--Announced C Sandy Martinez has declined an outright assignment to Calgary of the PCL and elected to become a free agent.  LOS ANGELES DODGERS--Named Maury Wills organizational baserunning and bunting coordinator. Agreed to terms with RHP Mike Fetters on a two-year contract.  PITTSBURGH PIRATES--Released RHP Brad Clontz. Sent OF Adam Hyzde, RHP Matt Skrmetta, RHP Brian Smith and INF John Wehner outright to Nashville of the PCL.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AUTO RACING</p>
        <p>NASCAR--Fined Tim Boatwright, Scotty Pease and Alan Tully $2,000, Ralph Bryant $1,500 and Donnie Richeson and Ricky Pearson $500 and placed them on probation until Dec. 31 for an altercation in the pit area during the Bumper to Bumper All Pro 300 Busch Series race at Lowe's Motor Speedway on Oct. 7.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
        <p>American League  ANAHEIM ANGELS--Claimed LHP Mark Lukasiewicz off waivers from the Toronto Blue Jays.  OAKLAND ATHLETICS--Sent RHP Jon Ratliff and RHP Scott Service outright to Sacramento of the PCL. Announced OF Bo Porter has been claimed off waivers by the Texas Rangers.  TAMPA BAY DEVIL RAYS--Activated LHP Wilson Alvarez, RHP Juan Guzman and RHP Ryan Rupe from the 60-day disabled list. Sent LHP Trevor Enders, RHP Tony Fiore and RHP Dave Eiland outright to Durham of the International League.  TEXAS RANGERS--Sent LHP Corey Lee, LHP Juan Moreno and C B.J. Waszgis outright to Oklahoma of the PCL.</p>
        <p>National League  FLORIDA MARLINS--Announced C Sandy Martinez has declined an outright assignment to Calgary of the PCL and elected to become a free agent.  LOS ANGELES DODGERS--Named Maury Wills organizational baserunning and bunting coordinator. Agreed to terms with RHP Mike Fetters on a two-year contract.  PITTSBURGH PIRATES--Released RHP Brad Clontz. Sent OF Adam Hyzde, RHP Matt Skrmetta, RHP Brian Smith and INF John Wehner outright to Nashville of the PCL.</p>
        <p>BASKETBALL</p>
        <p>National Basketball Association  DETROIT PISTONS--Waived C Matt Fish.  Women's National Basketball Association  LOS ANGELES SPARKS--Acquired C Rhonda Mapp and G E.C. Hill from Charlotte and F Latasha Byears from Sacramento; sent G-F Allison Feaster and C Clarisse Machanguana to Charlotte and F LaKeisha Frett to Sacramento.</p>
        <p>FOOTBALL</p>
        <p>National Football League  KANSAS CITY CHIEFS--Released PK Pete Stoyanovich. Signed PK Todd Peterson to a two-year contract.  MIAMI DOLPHINS--Signed LB Michael Hamilton. Placed LB Scott Galyon on injured reserve.  NEW ENGLAND PATRIOTS--Signed S Andre Dixon to the practice squad. Released TE Chris Fontenot.  PITTSBURGH STEELERS--Released DL Ernie Brown from the practice squad. Signed OL T.J. Washington to the practice squad.  SAN DIEGO CHARGERS--Signed TE Terrence McCaskey to the practice squad.  SAN FRANCISCO 49ERS--Claimed DT Nate Hobgood-Chittick off waivers from St. Louis.</p>
        <p>SOCCER</p>
        <p>Major League Soccer  SAN JOSE EARTHQUAKES--Announced the retirement of D Ryan Tinsley.  TAMPA BAY MUTINY--Named Drew Cloud director of corporate partnerships.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
