<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>WORLD BRIEFING</title>
    <meta content="Y12BRI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/12/world/12BRIE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238107"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001012T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E6D8163FF931A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="2058" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>WORLD BRIEFING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by Terence Neilan</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ASIA</p>
        <p>MYANMAR: U.N. ENVOY MEETS ACTIVIST  The United Nations special envoy to Myanmar met the pro-democracy activist Daw Aung San Suu Kyi at her home in Yangon, the capital, ending more than two weeks of isolation for the Nobel Peace Prize laureate, who is under house arrest. The envoy, Razali Ismail of Malaysia, spent two hours at her residence, accompanied by local United Nations officials. Ms. Aung San Suu Kyi has been confined to her home with her telephone cut since Sept. 22.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ASIA</p>
        <p>MYANMAR: U.N. ENVOY MEETS ACTIVIST  The United Nations special envoy to Myanmar met the pro-democracy activist Daw Aung San Suu Kyi at her home in Yangon, the capital, ending more than two weeks of isolation for the Nobel Peace Prize laureate, who is under house arrest. The envoy, Razali Ismail of Malaysia, spent two hours at her residence, accompanied by local United Nations officials. Ms. Aung San Suu Kyi has been confined to her home with her telephone cut since Sept. 22.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>PHILIPPINES: CARDINAL URGES PRESIDENT TO QUIT  Cardinal Jaime Sin and a council of 75 Catholic priests urged President Joseph Estrada to resign, saying a payoff scandal had destroyed public trust in his leadership. The presidential palace rejected the call, saying the embattled former movie actor, accused of receiving $8.7 million from gambling lords, would not step down. Demonstrators rallied outside the Senate depicting Mr. Estrada as ''The Godfather,'' above. In 1986 the cardinal helped lead a revolt that toppled Ferdinand E. Marcos.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>PAKISTAN: RIGHTS SITUATION ASSAILED  Human rights conditions in Pakistan have deteriorated since the military took power a year ago, the New York-based Human Rights Watch said. Its report said political activities have been suppressed, and that opponents of the military regime have been subjected to prolonged detention without being charged.</p>
        <p>Barry Bearak (NYT)</p>
        <p>BANGLADESH: FLOODS RECEDE  Floods that have killed more than 130 people and left another two million homeless have begun to recede, allowing many people to return to their homes, officials announced. The rains, which started on Sept. 26, have swept away more than 675 miles of road and done major damage to rice crops.</p>
        <p>Barry Bearak (NYT)</p>
        <p>EAST TIMOR: REQUEST FOR MILITIA CHIEF DENIED  East Timor asked Indonesia to hand over the pro-Jakarta militia leader Eurico Guterres for questioning about massacres in the territory last year. But Indonesia quickly rejected the request, saying Mr. Guterres, 27, would remain under arrest in Jakarta in connection with separate investigations. A spokesman for the United Nations, which administers East Timor, said warrants had been issued for Mr. Guterres's arrest in the slaying of scores of civilians in two attacks before the territory's independence vote in August 1999.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>JAPAN: 6 HELD IN NUCLEAR ACCIDENT  Six former top officials of a nuclear fuel reprocessing plant were arrested for an accident last year that killed two people and exposed hundreds to radiation. The suspects face charges of negligence resulting in death in the Sept. 30, 1999, accident at the plant 70 miles northeast of Tokyo. The six men could each get up to five years in prison or be fined $4,630, a police official said.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>MIDDLE EAST</p>
        <p>IRAQ: MORE SUPPLIES FLOWN IN  Turkish and Syrian planes landed in Baghdad with aid and medical supplies to offset the effects of United Nations sanctions. It was the second time this week that both a Turkish and Syrian plane had landed at the recently reopened Saddam International Airport, airport officials said.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>AFRICA</p>
        <p>NIGERIA: ISLAMIC CODE SHELVED  The northern state of Kaduna, torn by sectarian riots this year, said it had shelved plans to adopt the strict Islamic Shariah penal code. Gov. Muhammad Ahmed Makarfi cited the cosmopolitan nature of the state as a reason for the move. His announcement is expected to defuse the anxiety of non-Muslims, but could also anger Shariah's ardent backers. Hundreds of people died in Christian-Muslim fighting in Kaduna city last February and May over reported plans to introduce the law.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>SOMALIA: PARLIAMENT MEMBERS ATTACKED  About 100 members of the new Parliament came under heavy fire from militiamen as they flew into Mogadishu in a step toward restoring central government after almost a decade of anarchy. One gunman was killed and nine people were wounded when the legislators' convoy was attacked outside a hotel. The legislators, none of whom were hurt, arrived from Djibouti, where the 245-member Parliament was set up in August as part of a peace conference bringing together representatives from Somalia's rival clans.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>THE AMERICAS</p>
        <p>PERU: FUJIMORI AGREES TO REFORMS  President Alberto Fujimori and the opposition have agreed to key judicial reforms, ending a deadlock in talks over re-establishing democratic institutions in preparation for new presidential and congressional elections next year. The accord does away with a system under which the president appoints provisional judges whom he can hire and fire any time, allowing for manipulation from the executive branch.</p>
        <p>Clifford Krauss (NYT)</p>
        <p>ARGENTINA: 4 QUIT GOVERNING COALITION  Four members of the lower house of Congress said they would leave the government coalition because of their  disagreement with President Fernando de la Rua's economic policies, making it tougher for the government to enact its legislative program. The Alianza has been splintering since the resignation last week of Vice President Carlos Alvarez, leader of the social democratic Frepaso party, which is joined in the government with the centrist Radical Party.</p>
        <p>Clifford Krauss (NYT)</p>
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>TURKEY: GREEK ARMY RETURNS  More than 75 years after they left Turkey as a defeated army, Greek troops returned, joining NATO exercises on Turkish territory for the first time. About 30 Greek soldiers jumped off Spanish and Italian helicopters ferrying them from ships in the Bay of Doganbey. The landing site is only 25 miles southwest of the Aegean port city of Izmir, which Greek troops occupied in 1919 as part of a disastrous campaign to seize Asia Minor from the Ottoman Empire.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>ITALY: ILLEGAL IMMIGRANTS STRANDED  About 500 illegal immigrants, mostly Kurds fleeing Iraq, were left stranded on a ship off Italy when the crew abandoned their passengers to avoid arrest. The coast guard guided the vessel, which left Izmir, Turkey, a week ago, to safety in the southern town of Otranto. The interior minister, Enzo Bianco, said Europe should organize a joint police force to safeguard its borders.</p>
        <p>Alessandra Stanley (NYT)</p>
        <p>RUSSIA: SOLDIERS SLAIN  Officials said Chechen rebels had killed four Russian soldiers and wounded eight others in attacks on Tuesday in the regional capital, Grozny, and in two other areas. Three died in Grozny when guerrillas attacked an armored personnel carrier with grenades. But a rebel commander told The Associated Press that 20 Russians had died in an ambush of a three-vehicle convoy in southeast Chechnya. Both sides have regularly exaggerated the other's losses, and it was not possible to determine which, if either, was correct.</p>
        <p>Michael Wines (NYT)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
