<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Garden Q.&amp; A.</title>
    <meta content="12QNA.$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/12/living/12QNA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238066"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001012T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E7DE163FF931A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="684" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Garden Q.&amp; A.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Dora Galitzki</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>New York's Flying Geraniums</p>
        <p>Q. Every time I visit New York from New Jersey, I marvel at the huge pots of flowers hanging on the lampposts all around the city. The geraniums look as if they were flying. I bought what I thought had the same characteristics: leaves and flowers on long curly stems. Not the same thing at all. What variety are the city geraniums, and why are they so prolific?</p>
        <p>A. These are the container-planted ivy geraniums that also make Americans traveling in Europe so envious. Members of the Balcon series (ask for them by name or you'll get something else), they have a wild, trailing growth habit. They are covered in flowers and practically deadhead themselves, as the petals quickly drop off once the flower fades.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>New York's Flying Geraniums</p>
        <p>Q. Every time I visit New York from New Jersey, I marvel at the huge pots of flowers hanging on the lampposts all around the city. The geraniums look as if they were flying. I bought what I thought had the same characteristics: leaves and flowers on long curly stems. Not the same thing at all. What variety are the city geraniums, and why are they so prolific?</p>
        <p>A. These are the container-planted ivy geraniums that also make Americans traveling in Europe so envious. Members of the Balcon series (ask for them by name or you'll get something else), they have a wild, trailing growth habit. They are covered in flowers and practically deadhead themselves, as the petals quickly drop off once the flower fades.</p>
        <p>If you like to pinch back, these geraniums could take it every hour on the hour. Or you can just pinch them back when they get too far out of shape for your taste. Either way, full sun and weekly fertilizing will reward you amply.</p>
        <p>The four members of the series are Balcon Royale (scarlet), Princess Balcon (light orchid), King of Balcon (light coral pink) and Balcon Pink Star (pink with a white eye).</p>
        <p>Garden centers with the healthy attitude that convent neatness and manicured shapes aren't everything should carry them next spring; otherwise, ask to have them ordered.</p>
        <p>Flies to Euonymus's Flame</p>
        <p>Q.  I have a set of three Euonymus Manhattan shrubs, just like the ones I see in Central Park, and they have grown fairly tall, about five feet. They get a lot of sun and have a lot of flowers in late summer. For about three or four weeks, hundreds of flies swarm the shrubs, landing on the flowers. (There are also some bees, but mostly flies.) I would like to plant more euonymus, in shadier spots, and so would my neighbors. I have tried to research the shrub but found nothing about flies. I can't believe this happens all over Central Park.</p>
        <p>A.  The flies are there at the request of the euonymus, which views them not as pests but as pollinators, and there isn't much you can or should do about it. Many plants, including favorites like hollies, hawthorns and willows, attract flies rather than bees, moths or other insects. Most flowering plants have more than one pollinator, just in case. One type may get preferential treatment -- bees, for example, may be lured with bright colors and sweet aromas -- but being pollinated is more important to the plant than how it is done.</p>
        <p>In general, and there are lots of exceptions to the rule, flies are major pollinators if the flowers are white, pale yellow or greenish; if they are more wide open than tubular; and if their aroma is more musky than sweet.</p>
        <p>With everything else that happens in Central Park, who would notice a few extra flies?</p>
        <p>Morning Glories' Proclivities</p>
        <p>Q.  I was tempted to grow morning glories in a hanging basket, but was afraid they wouldn't flower if there was no place for them to climb. Would it work?</p>
        <p>A.  They're going to be a bit confused and frustrated, but they will flower anyway. Climbing vines like morning glories are simply trying to get up where the sun shines and the pollinators fly. They evolved amid taller competition and developed a drive to climb in order to get their share of the good things in life and produce seed.</p>
        <p>Don't be surprised if a few stems find the wires the basket hangs from. The rest will entwine each other looking for support. And your morning glories may end up looking like a tangle of yarn after three cats have finished with it.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
