<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="12FSUM$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238184"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001012T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E0D9173FF931A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1280" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-10</p>
        <p>Clinton Is Set to Ease Sanctions on Yugoslavia  President Clinton is expected to announce today that he is lifting many of the trade and economic sanctions against Yugoslavia that were designed to speed the fall of Slobodan Milosevic. Officials said the ban on American flights and an embargo on oil to the country would be ended immediately. But sanctions intended to keep Mr. Milosevic and his family's political allies from sending assets overseas will be kept in place.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-10</p>
        <p>Clinton Is Set to Ease Sanctions on Yugoslavia  President Clinton is expected to announce today that he is lifting many of the trade and economic sanctions against Yugoslavia that were designed to speed the fall of Slobodan Milosevic. Officials said the ban on American flights and an embargo on oil to the country would be ended immediately. But sanctions intended to keep Mr. Milosevic and his family's political allies from sending assets overseas will be kept in place.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Barak Warning on Terror  Prime Minister Ehud Barak warned that renewed terrorism by Islamic militants could follow the recent riots and gun battles. His statement followed the release of 20 members of Islamic fundamentalist groups from Palestinian jails. As clashes continued, Secretary General Kofi Annan said Israeli and Palestinian leaders had agreed to three-way talks led by the United States.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Bill to Aid Victims of Terror  The Senate passed legislation to let victims of terrorism collect court-awarded damages from countries that sponsor terrorist activity.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>East European Health Study  At least 50 million children in Eastern Europe and the former Soviet Union live in poverty and are exposed to tuberculosis levels associated with the third world, the European Children's Trust reported, urging the West to ease debt burdens.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Russia Nobelist Derides Budget  Zhores Ivanovich Alferov, the first Russian since 1978 to win a Nobel Prize for science, told Parliament that the Kremlin was not spending enough on research.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Albright to Visit North Korea  Secretary of State Madeleine K. Albright said she would visit North Korea. She would be the highest-ranking American to visit the Communist nation since the Korean War.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A5</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-12</p>
        <p>National Book Award Nominees  The novelists Susan Sontag and Joyce Carol Oates and the historian Jacques Barzun are among the 20 finalists in categories that include fiction, nonfiction and poetry.</p>
        <p>E10</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A12-26</p>
        <p>Gore and Bush Meet In 2nd Campaign Debate  Vice President Al Gore and Gov. George W. Bush, seated side-by-side, agreed more than they disagreed in a subdued and generally cordial debate on foreign policy and domestic matters like racial profiling, gun control and same-sex marriage.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Court Strikes Fairness Rules  A federal appeals court ordered the repeal of two rules that required radio and television stations to provide free reply time for opponents of political candidates endorsed by the stations and for people whose integrity is attacked. Last week, the F.C.C. temporarily suspended the rules.</p>
        <p>A15</p>
        <p>Flaws in Aircraft Wiring  A team of experts assembled after the T.W.A. Flight 800 crash found flaws in airplane wiring, some from age and some from damage during maintenance. The team is developing new maintenance techniques and a circuit breaker to reduce the chance of fires or explosions.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Hearing on Disabilities Act  The Supreme Court heard arguments on whether Congress acted within its constitutional authority 10 years ago when it made states liable for damages for violating the Americans With Disabilities Act. The decision will hinge on whether the court believes the law to be a valid exercise of Congress's authority to enforce the 14th Amendment's equal protection guarantee.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Dispute Over H.M.O. Financing  Congress is rushing to provide additional money to H.M.O.'s to keep them in the Medicare program, even as politicians daily denounce the abuses of H.M.O.'s on the campaign trail. President Clinton said the increase in payments to managed care plans was excessive.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>Subpoenas for Drug Makers  The F.T.C. announced plans to subpoena records from 90 pharmaceutical companies to see whether drug industry strategies were keeping lower-cost generic drugs from patients or harming consumers.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>New Strike in Los Angeles  More than 42,000 county employees -- mostly clerical and service workers -- went on strike, affecting jails, libraries, beaches, clinics and other offices in a dispute over wages and contract talks. Transit workers went on strike nearly a month ago.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-10</p>
        <p>New Jersey Police Leaders Balked at Ending Profiling  Senior commanders in the State Police rejected aggressive measures to end racial profiling in 1996, though internal audits showed it was widespread, records show, and they pursued a strategy of withholding data from federal civil rights prosecutors. State officials did not publicly acknowledge profiling until 1999.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Assessing Anti-Drug Tactic  The New York Police Department quietly suspended Operation Condor for the first 10 days of October to evaluate the effectiveness of the expensive and often criticized overtime program, which supporters say has cut crime with extra drug sweeps and quality-of-life patrols.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Rent Aid for the Homeless  The Giuliani administration, seeking to comply with a court order, proposed rent subsidies for homeless families to ease pressure on the emergency shelter system. The plan, which requires state approval, focuses on people with jobs or who are trying to move from welfare to work.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Ad Prompts Role Reversals  A new ad for Hillary Rodham Clinton that criticizes Rick A. Lazio for missing votes in Congress to campaign in New York for the Senate resembles one run by Senator Alfonse M. D'Amato against Representative Charles E. Schumer in 1998, a race Mr. Schumer won. Many players from 1998 are involved in this race, though they are taking opposite tacks on Mrs. Clinton's ad.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>The Manhattan Institute said Mrs. Clinton's tax cut plan was less beneficial for New Yorkers than Mr. Lazio's because hers did not properly compensate for the higher salaries and cost of living in New York.</p>
        <p>B6</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>A27</p>
        <p>CIRCUITS</p>
        <p>G1-12</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-8</p>
        <p>Yankees and Mets Win  The Yanks beat Seattle, 7-1, in Game 2 and the Mets beat St. Louis, 6-2, in the opener of the four-of-seven-game league championship series.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-22</p>
        <p>Bid to Expand Carrier Access  The F.C.C. was said to be considering issuing rules today that would move toward forcing commercial landlords to open their buildings to most any communications carrier that wanted access to their tenants.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Decline and Fall of Tech Stocks  The Nasdaq fell 72.05 points, or 2.2 percent, to 3,168.49, leaving it barely above its low close for this year of 3,164.55, reached May 23. The index has now shown declines during 13 of the last 15 sessions.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>The Dow fell 110.61 points, or 1.05 percent, to 10,413.79, and the S.&amp; P. 500 lost 22.43 points, or 1.62 percent, to 1,364.99.</p>
        <p>C12</p>
        <p>Judge Orders Ford Recall  A California judge ordered Ford to recall and repair nearly two million cars and trucks after concluding that it had knowingly installed defective ignition systems in as many as 22 million vehicles nationwide and had then concealed the defects.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>2 Americans Win Nobel Prize  James J. Heckman of the University of Chicago and Daniel L. McFadden of the University of California at Berkeley received the Nobel Memorial Prize in Economic Science.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>World Business</p>
        <p>W1-8</p>
        <p>HOUSE &amp; HOME</p>
        <p>F1-18</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A28-29</p>
        <p>Editorials: The ''makeup'' debate; rebuilding Yugoslavia; meaningful patients' rights legislation.  Columns: Bob Herbert, William Safire.</p>
        <p>Bridge</p>
        <p>E9  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E11  Crossword</p>
        <p>E10  Weather</p>
        <p>B9  Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
