<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No Detail About Debate Is Too Minor for Negotiation</title>
    <meta content="Y12VIE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/12/politics/12VIEW.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238202"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE STAGING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marks, Peter</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001012T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE3D8173FF931A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="915" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No Detail About Debate Is Too Minor for Negotiation</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER MARKS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Marks, Peter</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Presidential campaigns, seeking to meticulously control and refine way candidates are perceived, set exacting ground rules for second televised debate between Vice Pres Al Gore and Gov George W Bush; rules also reduce potential for gaffes (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When it comes to the clash of candidates on national television, no detail, it seems, is too minor for negotiation, no risk too small to eliminate. Not even the seemingly innocuous issue of the precise moment at which the debaters' microphones were to be switched on.</p>
        <p>The moment agreed upon by the campaigns for last night's debate in Winston-Salem, N.C., was 9:01 and 30 seconds, Eastern time, on the button. And since Gov. George W. Bush and Vice President Al Gore were to take their seats onstage at exactly 8:58 p.m., that meant anything they might say to each other in the three and a half minutes before the debate could not be heard by television viewers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When it comes to the clash of candidates on national television, no detail, it seems, is too minor for negotiation, no risk too small to eliminate. Not even the seemingly innocuous issue of the precise moment at which the debaters' microphones were to be switched on.</p>
        <p>The moment agreed upon by the campaigns for last night's debate in Winston-Salem, N.C., was 9:01 and 30 seconds, Eastern time, on the button. And since Gov. George W. Bush and Vice President Al Gore were to take their seats onstage at exactly 8:58 p.m., that meant anything they might say to each other in the three and a half minutes before the debate could not be heard by television viewers.</p>
        <p>Which is precisely what happened. The proceedings followed the script to the letter. The candidates strode onstage precisely at 8:58 and waited for their cues.</p>
        <p>Exacting ground rules like this are a measure of how meticulously the campaigns want to control and refine the way their standard bearers are perceived in these crucial face-offs.</p>
        <p>And at the same time, it is a way to reduce the potential for gaffes. And not just obvious ones, like the vulgar aside about a reporter that Mr. Bush made to his running mate (and an open microphone). As last week's debate in Boston demonstrated, any small mannerism or affectation, whether an audible sigh or sniffle, or a dusting of rouge on a candidate's cheeks, was potential grist for interpretation and criticism by voters and political analysts.</p>
        <p>John Scardino, a spokesman for the Commission on Presidential Debates, the bipartisan panel that oversees the encounters, said the microphone rule was a matter of privacy.</p>
        <p>''The effort was to protect the confidentiality of any private conversations the candidates might have,'' Mr. Scardino said.</p>
        <p>There was no such interlude in the first presidential debate in Boston. Spokesmen for the campaigns and the Commission on Presidential Debates confirmed that the microphones were already on when Mr. Bush and Mr. Gore walked to their lecterns at the University of Massachusetts on Oct. 3. Although the broadcast networks begin their coverage of all the debates at 9 p.m., Eastern time, cable channels like C-Span start up in the hall at 8:30 p.m.</p>
        <p>Spokesmen for Mr. Bush and Mr. Gore differed yesterday over when the microphone policy was to take effect. Ari Fleischer, a spokesman for the Bush campaign, said it was supposed to have been put into effect before the Boston debate. But Mark Fabiani, Mr. Gore's deputy campaign manager, said the agreement that ''the mikes do not go live until production time'' was negotiated this week.</p>
        <p>The campaigns themselves have gone to great lengths to try to protect the candidates. Some network television journalists said that before the first debate, there had been intense lobbying by the campaigns over how much freedom the networks would have with camera angles.</p>
        <p>Several people involved in the negotiations said the Bush and Gore campaigns had sought, for example, to bar the networks from showing a candidate's reaction while his opponent spoke. A senior Bush adviser said the two campaigns agreed early in the negotiations that only one image should be broadcast, but the adviser added that the agreement was not binding on the networks.</p>
        <p>The networks, in fact, dismissed the idea out of hand.</p>
        <p>''The networks came back and said, 'You don't tell us how to cover it,' '' said Steve Scully, political editor of C-Span, who attended the commission meetings on the coverage plans.</p>
        <p>Network officials say that under the debate guidelines, the bipartisan commission has authority over the lighting in the debate hall and the audio transmission of the proceedings. The networks are responsible for the video. For each debate, one network is designated as the ''pool'' for the event, which means that its cameras in the hall feed the debate to all of networks, said Barbara Levin, a spokeswoman for NBC, which was the pool last night. Each network could then broadcast the camera shots as it wished, showing both candidates on a split screen, for example.</p>
        <p>The commission also decided that for the North Carolina debate, it would supply to the pool network only one audio transmission, mixing the sound from all the microphones on the stage. In Boston, it provided three transmissions: the ''mixed'' feed, and one each from the microphones of Mr. Gore and Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>Mr. Scardino, the commission spokesman, said the change was intended to simplify the transmission arrangement and would not affect viewers' ability to hear extraneous sounds, like an off-camera sigh.</p>
        <p>Commission and network officials say the microphones were also turned off before the start of the debate last week between the vice-presidential contenders, Dick Cheney and Senator Joseph I. Lieberman. But at the end of the debate, they remained on, said Mr. Scully of C-Span.</p>
        <p>Viewers of that network, he said, could hear Mr. Lieberman tell Mr. Cheney that he thought the debate went rapidly. Mr. Scully added that they could also hear Mr. Cheney reply that he had not even worn a watch, a reference, perhaps, to a moment in the 1992 debates, when President George Bush sneaked a highly visible peek at his.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE STAGING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
