<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hate-Crime Charges Filed In Vandalism of Synagogue</title>
    <meta content="12HATE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/12/nyregion/12HATE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238242"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Arson</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hate Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Synagogues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Conservative Synagogue Adath Israel (Riverdale, NY)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gootman, Elissa</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Alfaqih, Mohammed</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Assi, Mazin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hate Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Arson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Synagogues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001012T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901EFD7173FF931A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="734" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hate-Crime Charges Filed In Vandalism of Synagogue</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELISSA GOOTMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gootman, Elissa</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bronx prosecutors file hate-crime charges against three young men in connection with vandalism of Conservative Synagogue Adath Israel; Mayor Rudolph W Giulini calls incident an 'attempted firebombing'; Mohammed Alfaqih and Mazin Assi are charged with attempted arson and related charges, and a 15-year-old boy will be tried as a juvenile (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bronx prosecutors filed hate-crime charges against three young men yesterday in connection with the vandalism of a Riverdale synagogue on Sunday. The suspects are believed to be the first charged under the state's new bias-crimes act, which took effect Sunday and provides for stronger penalties.</p>
        <p>The young men, all from nearby Yonkers, are accused of throwing a bottle of vodka at the front door of Conservative Synagogue Adath Israel of Riverdale, at West 250th Street and the Henry Hudson Parkway, on Sunday morning.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Bronx prosecutors filed hate-crime charges against three young men yesterday in connection with the vandalism of a Riverdale synagogue on Sunday. The suspects are believed to be the first charged under the state's new bias-crimes act, which took effect Sunday and provides for stronger penalties.</p>
        <p>The young men, all from nearby Yonkers, are accused of throwing a bottle of vodka at the front door of Conservative Synagogue Adath Israel of Riverdale, at West 250th Street and the Henry Hudson Parkway, on Sunday morning.</p>
        <p>Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani said yesterday that a bottle containing ''very, very cheap high-octane vodka'' and a burned wick were found near the synagogue's glass front door, which was shattered. Pieces of a second bottle and two pieces of a rock were also found nearby, he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani called the incident an ''attempted firebombing,'' but it was not clear yesterday whether the vodka could have been ignited. There was no fire, and police officials had previously said the liquid in the bottle was not incendiary.</p>
        <p>Two of the suspects -- identified by the police as Mohammed Alfaqih, 17, and Mazin Assi, 21 -- were charged with attempted arson, criminal mischief and related charges. They are being held without bail, said Steven Reed, a spokesman for the Bronx district attorney's office. A 15-year-old boy whose name was not released by the police because of his age will be tried as a juvenile. A fourth young man, a companion of the three, was not charged and was to be released pending further investigation, officials said.</p>
        <p>All four were questioned Tuesday night and were arrested yesterday, the police said.</p>
        <p>The vandalism was discovered at 9 a.m. Sunday, only hours before the start of Yom Kippur, the most solemn Jewish holy day.</p>
        <p>The Bronx district attorney, Robert T. Johnson, said the case might be the first to be prosecuted under the state's new anti-bias statute, which took effect at 12:01 a.m. Sunday. ''It is our position that this is a hate crime,'' Mr. Johnson said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The Hate Crimes Act of 2000, which was signed into law on July 10, strengthens the penalties for crimes that are motivated by bias.</p>
        <p>All the suspects are of Arab descent, the police said, but authorities have found no evidence that they are tied to an organized group. ''I just think it was misguided bigotry,'' the first deputy police commissioner, Joseph P. Dunne, said at a news conference.</p>
        <p>The mayor added, ''I don't think there is any evidence at this point of a connection to any real group or directed activity.''</p>
        <p>The authorities said that the police were able to find the suspects because two patrol officers had spotted them parked near the synagogue at 2:45 a.m. Sunday and recorded the car's license plate number.</p>
        <p>One of the officers, Sgt. Richard Neillands, said at the news conference they questioned the suspects after they noticed the car parked about 80 feet south of the synagogue.</p>
        <p>When the officers asked what they were doing, the young men said they were lost. Sergeant Neillands said that seemed suspicious because the car's registration indicated that the young men lived nearby.</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani praised the officers' work as an example of the aggressive policing that has received what he called unfair criticism. ''Sometimes people wonder why we stop and frisk and do some of the things we do,'' the mayor said. ''Reasonable suspicion is why we do it.''</p>
        <p>Gov. George E. Pataki said yesterday the new anti-bias law was a ''powerful new tool to ensure that those responsible for this despicable attack are held accountable for their actions.''</p>
        <p>He said, ''These acts are so inherently destructive to society that they deserve special consideration under the law.''</p>
        <p>The director of the New York regional office of the Anti-Defamation League, Howie Katz, said yesterday that he thought that using the anti-bias law in this case would be appropriate.</p>
        <p>''The intent of the perpetrators to burn a house of worship, to burn a synagogue, is intended not only to damage property but to send a message to the members of that congregation and to the members of that community that they were targeted just because of who they are,'' Mr. Katz said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
