<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Strike Shuts Many Los Angeles Agencies</title>
    <meta content="Y12STR$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/12/national/12STRI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238134"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Government Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Los Angeles County (Calif)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Service Employees International Union</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Purdum, Todd S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/Los Angeles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Government Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001012T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E3DF173FF931A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="994" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Strike Shuts Many Los Angeles Agencies</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TODD S. PURDUM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Purdum, Todd S</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, Oct. 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Over 42,000 Los Angeles County, Calif, workers, mostly clerical and service workers, begin general strike in dispute about wages and new contract; Service Employees International Union and county resume talks; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Couples needing marriage licenses, parents needing birth certificates and homeowners needing a deed recorded were all out of luck today in Los Angeles County as more than 42,000 county employees -- mostly clerical and service workers -- began a general strike at dawn in jails, libraries, beaches, health clinics and other departments in a dispute about wages and a new contract.</p>
        <p>The countywide job action further complicated life in the nation's second-largest city, which was already grappling with a 26-day-old subway and bus strike that left nearly half a million commuters scrambling to get to work in car pools, gypsy cabs and other ad hoc conveyances as negotiations between the Metropolitan Transportation Authority and striking drivers dragged on.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Couples needing marriage licenses, parents needing birth certificates and homeowners needing a deed recorded were all out of luck today in Los Angeles County as more than 42,000 county employees -- mostly clerical and service workers -- began a general strike at dawn in jails, libraries, beaches, health clinics and other departments in a dispute about wages and a new contract.</p>
        <p>The countywide job action further complicated life in the nation's second-largest city, which was already grappling with a 26-day-old subway and bus strike that left nearly half a million commuters scrambling to get to work in car pools, gypsy cabs and other ad hoc conveyances as negotiations between the Metropolitan Transportation Authority and striking drivers dragged on.</p>
        <p>The 42,000 county workers on strike represent about half the county's overall public employee work force. But the worst potential effects of the strike were apparently avoided after a judge on Tuesday ordered some 5,000 nurses and other medical workers deemed essential to emergency services to report to their jobs as usual at six hospitals and 42 health clinics.</p>
        <p>County and union officials said there were mixed reports about compliance, however, and the emergency room and trauma center at the giant Los Angeles County-U.S.C. Medical Center was closed, with ambulance patients diverted to other area hospitals.</p>
        <p>Negotiators for the striking union, Local 660 of the Service Employees International Union, and the county resumed talks at noon today, but reported little progress. The union  seeks a 15.5 percent wage increase over three years for its employees, who earn an average annual salary of $29,000, while the county is offering a raise of 9 percent.</p>
        <p>''This is a very complicated negotiation,'' Mark Tarnawsky, a union spokesman, said. ''There are 20 different bargaining units negotiating separate agreements, each with their own side issues. We've told our members that it could go on for a while.''</p>
        <p>County officials, concerned about just that prospect, said they would return to court on Thursday seeking an order that election workers in the registrar-recorder's office return to work to prepare for the Nov. 7 general election. The deadline for new voter registration by mail was Tuesday, and stacks of mail piled up outside the registrar's office in Norwalk today.</p>
        <p>Already, the department has been working double shifts, seven days a week, to record the new voters and prepare voter rolls, ballots and voting machines, said a county spokeswoman, Judy Hammond.</p>
        <p>''I don't think there's ever been a strike of this magnitude in the throes of an election,'' she said. ''We feel our election preparations are really in jeopardy.''</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, transit officials made what they called their ''last, best and final offer'' to striking bus drivers and subway operators on Tuesday night and gave the union leadership until Thursday morning to accept it or face the prospect of the Transportation Authority's sending copies of the offer directly to 4,300 members' homes in an effort to persuade them to end the strike.</p>
        <p>Officials did not disclose the terms of the offer, and a spokesman for the United Transportation Union would say only that union negotiators were preparing a response.</p>
        <p>For more than three weeks, the drivers union and transit officials have wrangled about wages, work rules and overtime. Even the intervention of state mediators has failed to resolve the strike.</p>
        <p>The county workers' strike touched a huge range of government activities in a jurisdiction with 10 million residents over a 4,000-square mile region, three-fifths the area of Connecticut, and the nation's most populous county. Welfare workers, marriage and property clerks, coroner's office workers, librarians and beach and sewer maintenance crews were among the employees who joined the strike and picketed under rainy morning skies in about 250 locations, union officials said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Hammond, the county spokeswoman, said local school cafeterias had been pressed into service making hot meals for county jail inmates, in place of the striking county food-service workers. She said that neighboring Orange County had agreed to process deed recordings for real estate transactions scheduled to close today. ''We're directing everyone who needs a marriage license and can't wait to go to another county,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Outside the Kenneth Hahn Hall of Administration, the main county office building in downtown Los Angeles, several dozen picketing union members carried green and blue placards proclaiming, ''On Strike for Our Fair Share,'' and tooted whistles at passing cars. Drivers often honked in solidarity.</p>
        <p>But 60 percent of the workers earn less than $32,000 a year, and several strikers said they could not afford to be without a paycheck for long.</p>
        <p>''This is a real hardship,'' said Patrice Littleton, a supervisor in the court services unit of the mental health department, which transports mental patients to court appearances. ''I'm in it for the long haul. I can't afford it, but I have to, to get a bigger paycheck.''</p>
        <p>Paul Larisch, a health inspector who tests for rabies and other animal diseases and earns about $2,400 a month, said: ''A 9 percent raise is too little. We have a lot of single mothers and single fathers who just can't make a go of it and send their kids to school on that.''</p>
        <p>Jose Galindo and Leo Egland, mail deliverers in the county's internal mail service, said they did not expect to be handing out any checks by the next payday, which is Friday.</p>
        <p>''We've got to do this,'' Mr. Egland said as the pair marched up and down the sidewalk.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
