<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Changing Course, Giuliani Proposes Rent Subsidies for Homeless Families</title>
    <meta content="12HOME" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/12/nyregion/12HOME.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238163"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Homeless Persons</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bernstein, Nina</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Homeless Persons</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001012T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03EEDC173FF931A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1336" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Changing Course, Giuliani Proposes Rent Subsidies for Homeless Families</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NINA BERNSTEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bernstein, Nina</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Giuliani administration proposes rent subsidies for homeless families, in striking departure from its previous policies; effort is to resolve bottlenecks in city's emergency shelter system; proposed subsidies are part of pilot project for more than 500 homeless families, and are offered to comply with court order that was violated this summer when 500 families were left to sleep on floors and benches of Emergency Assistance Unit in Bronx; proposed subsidies are also sign that city is taking fresh look at problem of homeless families in booming economy with sharply rising rents; it is also acknowledgement that poor people crowding city's shelters increasingly include working poor; new proposal, which requires state approval, would be aimed at homeless people who have jobs or are trying to move from welfare to work; Mayor Giuliani has vetoed similar rental assistance programs in past, contending they encourage dependency on government (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a striking departure from its previous policies, the Giuliani administration is proposing rent subsidies for homeless families in an effort to resolve bottlenecks in the city's emergency shelter system.</p>
        <p>The proposed subsidies, which are part of a pilot project for more than 500 homeless families, were offered to comply with a court order. But they are also a sign that in a booming economy with sharply rising rents, the city is taking a fresh look at the problem of homeless families. And it acknowledges that the people crowding the city's shelters increasingly include the working poor.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a striking departure from its previous policies, the Giuliani administration is proposing rent subsidies for homeless families in an effort to resolve bottlenecks in the city's emergency shelter system.</p>
        <p>The proposed subsidies, which are part of a pilot project for more than 500 homeless families, were offered to comply with a court order. But they are also a sign that in a booming economy with sharply rising rents, the city is taking a fresh look at the problem of homeless families. And it acknowledges that the people crowding the city's shelters increasingly include the working poor.</p>
        <p>Some rental supplements have been provided by the state since 1990, but those are limited to certain welfare households facing eviction. The new proposal, which would require state approval and is part of remedial plan the city submitted in court last week, would be aimed at homeless people who have jobs or are trying to move from welfare to work.</p>
        <p>Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani has opposed and even vetoed similar rental assistance programs in the past, contending that they encourage dependency on government and would make the city's emergency shelter system a magnet for families seeking subsidized apartments. Earlier this year, the mayor lost a bid to overturn the right to shelter established in the city through class-action lawsuits two decades ago.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Giuliani has been trying to burnish and perhaps soften his mayoral legacy since he withdrew from the Senate race in May. And the administration was confronted with a crisis this summer when more than 500 families were left to sleep on the floors and benches of the Emergency Assistance Unit in the Bronx, the city's sole portal to shelters for families with children. That practice, which violates a longstanding court order, had been common until a year ago, when the City Council banned it and the Department of Homeless Services made new efforts to comply.</p>
        <p>''When the people started sleeping on the floor, we went and tried to get additional relief,'' said Leonard Koerner, the city's chief assistant corporation counsel, who is handling the case. ''This will make more permanent housing available.''</p>
        <p>At the same time, Mr. Koerner noted: ''There is a fear that this is going to create an additional problem, because there are more families than housing. You have all these families out there doubled up.''</p>
        <p>He added, ''I have no idea what the long-term solution is.''</p>
        <p>Debra Sproles, the spokeswoman for the city's Human Resources Administration, said she did not expect the program to have a magnet effect, but added that because the program would begin as a six-month pilot project, ''we have time to see what's going to happen.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Sproles stressed that the Human Resources Administration considered the program consistent with, not a departure from, its efforts to move people from welfare to self-sufficiency. Though details are still being worked out, she added, the pilot would include about 550 families now in the shelter system. Each family could get up to $600 a month in rental assistance in a combination of state, city and possibly federal money. The average subsidy, she said, is expected to be $300 to $400 and would last for two years.</p>
        <p>Apart from the administration's new proposal, four nonprofit groups are also to begin offering rental assistance programs next month for about 200 households. Those programs would draw from $3 million in city money that was budgeted by the City Council. In previous years, the administration either vetoed or left unspent money appropriated by the Council for that purpose.</p>
        <p>City officials have said that they do not track how many parents applying for shelter have jobs. But Barbara Cutler, the court-appointed special master who oversees the city's operation of the family shelter system under a longstanding court decree, said they were common. She added that the court was now focusing on problems in the application process that make it hard for working parents to keep their jobs and keep children in school.</p>
        <p>''There are people that are real, live, hard-working citizens who still operate every day from the E.A.U.,'' Ms. Cutler said, referring to the Emergency Assistance Unit. ''We have as a society to look at this again. We have to look at what the elements of being homeless really are.''</p>
        <p>Families who have waited night after night recently for temporary shelter in the Bronx unit office have included a nurse's aide employed for seven years on the midnight shift at Coney Island Hospital in Brooklyn, and her two children; and a public schoolteacher who said she moved back here from Seattle with her 16-year-old son in response to the city's teacher shortage.</p>
        <p>On a weeknight last month, the teacher called a reporter at 11:32 p.m. from the Bronx office and left a telephone message, describing her situation after 11 days of bouncing between overnight or short-lived shelter placements and the intake center, sometimes not getting a bed until after 3 a.m.</p>
        <p>''I'm just letting you know how discouraged I am that at 5:30 I have to get up, and at 8:21 I have to be fresh for 61 New York City public schoolchildren,'' the teacher said. ''It doesn't seem as though they anticipated the time when working people would be homeless.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Koerner told Justice Helen E. Freedman of New York State Supreme Court last month that the city planned an ''aggressive program,'' including rent subsidies, to help move families more swiftly from temporary shelters to permanent housing.</p>
        <p>Advocates for the homeless called the Giuliani administration's proposal a step in the right direction. They and the mayor's opponents on the City Council have long championed modest rent subsidies, combined with social services, as a more cost-effective way to help homeless people than the expansion of temporary shelter beds, which they say cost $3,000 a month for a family.</p>
        <p>''I have been preaching the gospel of rental assistance for nearly 12 years now,'' said Mary Brosnahan, director of the Coalition for the Homeless, which pioneered a similar rental subsidy program with money from law firms and churches in the late 1980's. ''It's a huge victory, practical and moral.''</p>
        <p>Steven Banks, counsel to the coalition and to the Homeless Rights Project of the Legal Aid Society, whose contempt motions last month prompted the remedial plan, was more cautious.</p>
        <p>''After seven years of resisting the notion that additional housing provided by the city is part of the solution to homelessness, it's a welcome first step,'' Mr. Banks said. ''But it's not enough to make the current crisis, which has built up over years, go away.''</p>
        <p>In its legal papers, the city in part blamed unexpected demand for the recurrence of the old problem of families left in the Bronx office overnight, saying that the number of families seeking shelter was 9 percent higher between April 1 and Sept. 30 than during the same period last year.</p>
        <p>But lawyers for the homeless dispute those figures, contending that the problem is not more demand, but an increase in ''churning'' -- multiple applications required of families who are wrongly found ineligible, shuttled between one-night placements and forced to reapply.</p>
        <p>''The families that are caught up in these desperate circumstances now are including increasing numbers of working families and families fleeing from domestic violence,'' Mr. Banks said.</p>
        <p>Both sides agree that since the court began examining the problem last month, crowding has eased, but Ms. Cutler said churning remained a concern.</p>
        <p>In the last fiscal year, through June 30, there were 20,841 applications and reapplications made by families seeking shelter, according to the mayor's management report. The shelter system now houses 5,337 families, including 9,563 children.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
