<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Women Who've Been There</title>
    <meta content="12BOOK$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/12/arts/12BOOK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238097"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MAKING BOOKS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arnold, Martin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Burana, Lily</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gray, Amy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Columns/Making Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001012T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E2DA163FF931A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1148" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Women Who've Been There</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Martin Arnold</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Arnold, Martin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Making Books column notes that publishers are busy signing up first-person nonfiction books about unusual endeavours undertaken by young women; several books discussed; photos of authors Lily Burana and Amy Gray (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Some see it as the fastest growing fancy in the trade. Publishers are busy signing up first-person nonfiction books that are not exactly adventure yarns, like tales of mountain climbing, but journalistic accounts of someone unusual doing something unusual. Many of the authors are young women, at a moment when more and more novels of love and emotion are being written by men. Could it be that it's the women who are from Mars, and the men who are from Venus?</p>
        <p>An exaggeration? Possibly. But  from some of the books in the works, an inference can be drawn that it's the young women who are bursting out, adventurous and audacious, while men are retreating.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Some see it as the fastest growing fancy in the trade. Publishers are busy signing up first-person nonfiction books that are not exactly adventure yarns, like tales of mountain climbing, but journalistic accounts of someone unusual doing something unusual. Many of the authors are young women, at a moment when more and more novels of love and emotion are being written by men. Could it be that it's the women who are from Mars, and the men who are from Venus?</p>
        <p>An exaggeration? Possibly. But  from some of the books in the works, an inference can be drawn that it's the young women who are bursting out, adventurous and audacious, while men are retreating.</p>
        <p>Last month, for instance, Villard published a book about a woman's sojourn in the world of women's professional boxing: ''When the bell goes, I square up and march to meet her. . . . I put a jab straight through her guard. . . . I circle a little, feeling not like the circus cat I was with Leslie but like a hell-eyed shark scenting meat.'' The writer was Kate Sekules, an editor at Food &amp; Wine magazine who found herself drawn to the gyms of SoHo and later Gleason's Gym, that boxing temple of world champions. She retired from the ring after two losses, but she insists, ''The first one, I was robbed.''</p>
        <p>''This isn't a trendy women's book thing; I'm hoping it gets noticed as a good piece of writing,'' she told me. ''It's quite a serious endeavor to step into a ring. I can really take a punch, it turns out.''</p>
        <p>Also in the works are first-person accounts of a young female private investigator, a photojournalist, a stripper and a topless dancer. Bruce Tracy, the editorial director of Villard, said: ''The general idea of the memoir has been overplayed, or is tired out in the market. What's interesting is unconventional lives, living out fantasies the rest of us wonder about.''</p>
        <p>Why so many women? ''This wasn't by design,'' he said. ''Maybe it's because women are choosing to write them now, or women are choosing to acquire and edit them. I'm stumped, but I'm very enthusiastic.''</p>
        <p>Kate Niedzwiecki, who edited the boxing book and is editing those about the private investigator and the photojournalist, said that the rush of books by young women writing about their idiosyncratic lives was in essence about their freeing themselves. ''It's part of the fruition of the women's movement,'' she said. ''The voices of these nontraditional women are so strong and smart, often witty, and their books really take the reader on a journey.''</p>
        <p>''Shutterbabe'' (Villard) is about the journalistic and sexual adventures of Deborah Copaken Kogan, starting in 1989 when she was 22 and the lone woman among a group of Afghan rebels. It will be published in January. Then there's a book that could be described as ''Harriet the Spy'' (Louise Fitzhugh's popular 1964 girl book) meets ''Sex and the City.'' It is being written for Villard by Amy Gray, who works as a private eye for an agency that investigates white-collar crime. The book will be titled ''Spy Girl.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Gray, who will be 26 next week, described her job as ''fantasy fulfillment.'' She came to detective work from book publishing. ''I decided to stop thinking about other people's lives and to live,'' she said. ''I think that's a big part of what these books are about. I'm actually investigating these things. They'll only be as much sex in it as there is in real life, only a thread about dating, but I hope it is funny and has all the wistfulness and drama and heartbreak of mid-20's life.'' A television show is in development.</p>
        <p>Such books by women doing unconventional things are certainly not new. There was, for instance, Louise Rafkin's ''Other People's Dirt'' (Algonquin, 1998), a cleaning lady's scrub-and-tell: ''Prozac is Manhattan popcorn,'' she discovered while peeking into medicine cabinets. More seriously was Lauralee Summer's ''Learning Joy: A Memoir'' (Simon &amp; Schuster), the true story of a homeless girl who was admitted to Harvard on a full scholarship in 1994.</p>
        <p>There is daring and grit in these books by women doing the unorthodox at a time when so many men seem to be bleating. Lily Burana spent six years working as a topless dancer. ''To settle my feelings before I got married, I decided to work in clubs around the country,'' she said, in a ''have body, will travel'' trip.</p>
        <p>She said: ''A journey to the center of my navel it's not. People like to get lost in the details of topless dancing, but not in the real story of what it's like. All the little rituals we go through to maintain our sanity. It's more about performance than about your body. What you actually wear looks very small, but it works as armor and is as good as cast iron.'' Her book, ''Strip City,'' is to be published by Talk/Miramax Books.</p>
        <p>Elisabeth Eaves, who has a master's degree in international affairs from Columbia and who has been a reporter for Reuters in London, started working as a stripper -- not a topless dancer, it's a different art --  before she went to graduate school. She explained: ''It's about money and flexibility. If you are a student or a single mother, you can't work many hours.'' Strippers do peep shows, perform on stages or tables at clubs, do bachelor parties. Her book, ''Private Dancer'' (Knopf), is about five women, herself included, who have worked as strippers and why.</p>
        <p>Strippers are as diverse as athletes. ''One of the things I want to show is the diversity of the women who do it and the many reasons they do it,'' she said. ''Many of them don't think of themselves as exploited or victimized, and that runs counter to the stereotyping.''</p>
        <p>Do the customers get carried away and start groping? ''When I started, I was surprised about how polite they are,'' Ms. Eaves said. ''They seem to know what they are there for,'' a show, nothing more, ''and they leave when they get it.''</p>
        <p>What may be different, and what is perhaps reflected in these books, is that women now seem to be holding onto their fantasies, trying them out. Every boy and most girls probably had secretly thought of being a spy or at least a private detective, but the girls weren't encouraged. Now it's their time. Ms. Burana, the former topless dancer, said: ''It's not a Hemingway thing. Women are doing exciting things now we couldn't or didn't do before. As females we are deciding what to disclose, so let's hear about it.''</p>
        <p>MAKING BOOKS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
