<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bordick Not Sure In Game 2</title>
    <meta content="12SIDE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/12/sports/12SIDE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238253"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL: 2000 PLAYOFFS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">St Louis Cardinals</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Curry, Jack</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bordick, Mike</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">James, Mike</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/St Louis Cardinals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001012T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE6D6173FF931A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="588" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bordick Not Sure In Game 2</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Curry, Jack</byline>
      <dateline>ST. LOUIS, Oct. 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Mets shortstop Mike Bordick's status for game 2 of NLCS against St Louis Cardinals is uncertain after being hit on thumb by pitch from Cardinals relief pitcher Mike James (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Mets had just clubbed two homers off Mike James in an ugly ninth inning tonight when Mike Bordick sauntered to the plate. The setting was too blatant for a reliever to throw at a batter. It would look too obvious. It would look as if it were retaliation for the homers. James hit Bordick anyway.</p>
        <p>Bordick was drilled on the right thumb with a pitch and he twisted away from the plate and shook his hand in pain. The mild-mannered Bordick glared at James and Manager Bobby Valentine joined in staring down the St. Louis reliever after coming out to check on Bordick's conditions. James did not look up.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Mets had just clubbed two homers off Mike James in an ugly ninth inning tonight when Mike Bordick sauntered to the plate. The setting was too blatant for a reliever to throw at a batter. It would look too obvious. It would look as if it were retaliation for the homers. James hit Bordick anyway.</p>
        <p>Bordick was drilled on the right thumb with a pitch and he twisted away from the plate and shook his hand in pain. The mild-mannered Bordick glared at James and Manager Bobby Valentine joined in staring down the St. Louis reliever after coming out to check on Bordick's conditions. James did not look up.</p>
        <p>''Any time you get hit in the hand, it's scary,'' Bordick said.</p>
        <p>Even though the Mets defeated the Cardinals, 6-2, in Game 1 of the National League Championship Series, it could get a little more uncomfortable for them if Bordick cannot play in Game 2. Although X-rays on Bordick's thumb were negative, he said the thumb was still stiff and he was unsure if he could play.</p>
        <p>''It's a bruise,'' Bordick said. ''We're going to do everything we can to move it around. If it's a bruise, you can play through bruises. Hopefully, I'll play tomorrow.''</p>
        <p>Catcher Mike Piazza sprained his right big toe in the ninth inning, but he is expected to start on Thursday night. Bordick said he had no idea whether James was throwing at him, and he speculated that James would have hit him on the first pitch instead of the second pitch if he had been intent on plunking him. But General Manager Steve Phillips was not so coy, and insisted that the pitch was intentional.</p>
        <p>''I think he did'' throw at him,  Phillips said. ''It's just baseball.''</p>
        <p>When Phillips was asked if that bothered him, he said, ''Anger is part of baseball.'' When Phillips was asked if the Mets had to retaliate because that is also part of baseball, he smiled and said, ''That's not part of baseball.''</p>
        <p>Valentine was sarcastic when asked about James's 1-1 pitch, which followed Jay Payton's two-run homer. Todd Zeile led off the inning with a homer off James.</p>
        <p>''You mean, do I think they took the smallest guy in our lineup, and decided to throw at him? I doubt it,'' Valentine said. Referring to Manager Tony La Russa, he added: ''I have never thought of Tony's team to do anything like that. I am not going to start that now.''</p>
        <p>The Mets lost right fielder Derek Bell to a sprained right ankle in Game 1 of the division series against the Giants and he is finished for the season. They do not think Bordick's injury is as severe.</p>
        <p>''It's swollen,'' Phillips said. ''We'll keep ice on it and see how he feels tomorrow.''</p>
        <p>Timo Perez, who doubled to start the game and later scored, has filled in admirably for Bell. Losing Bordick would be a more difficult situation because the Mets would probably start Kurt Abbott, who batted .217 this season and is not as consistent defensively.</p>
        <p>Bordick played for La Russa in Oakland and La Russa has said that Bordick is tied as being among his favorite players. So it is doubtful that La Russa would have called for the pitch from the dugout. But James could have made the choice on his own. He breezed by reporters and declined to answer questions.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL: 2000 PLAYOFFS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
