<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Plan, a Smoke Cloud and 3 Were Gone</title>
    <meta content="12KIDN$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/12/world/12KIDN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238194"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hostages</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Lebanon</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iran</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Jerusalem</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hezbollah</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kifner, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iran</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Lebanon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iran</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel/Jerusalem</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Lebanon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hostages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001012T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802EED9173FF931A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1046" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Plan, a Smoke Cloud and 3 Were Gone</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN KIFNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kifner, John</byline>
      <dateline>SHABAA, Lebanon, Oct. 9</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Kidnapping of three Israeli soldiers at Lebanese border by Hezbollah guerrillas described; marks new role for Hezbollah, reportedly developed with Iranian guidance, of working for Muslim liberation of Jerusalem; map; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Everything seemed routine to the Indian peacekeepers at the lonely United Nations post perched on a rocky outcrop overlooking the Israeli border fence snaking through the foothills of Mount Hermon. Very routine.</p>
        <p>It was Saturday, and as usual an Israeli patrol below drove down its looping maintenance road on its twice-daily tour to check the fence and an old border gate that had been used during Israel's 20-year occupation of southern Lebanon.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Everything seemed routine to the Indian peacekeepers at the lonely United Nations post perched on a rocky outcrop overlooking the Israeli border fence snaking through the foothills of Mount Hermon. Very routine.</p>
        <p>It was Saturday, and as usual an Israeli patrol below drove down its looping maintenance road on its twice-daily tour to check the fence and an old border gate that had been used during Israel's 20-year occupation of southern Lebanon.</p>
        <p>And, as they had in the months since Israel withdrew in May, Hezbollah guerrillas lounged nearby at their own watch point, clad casually in jogging suits and plastic sandals, no weapons visible.</p>
        <p>They had a cargo container as their office and marked their presence with flapping flags and big signs with their belligerent symbol, a raised assault rifle.</p>
        <p>''It was a normal thing,'' said Maj. Rajendra K. Bansiwal, standing atop the United Nations observation tower, three ladders high.</p>
        <p>Despite security alerts by Israeli commanders, based on reports of Hezbollah's kidnapping plans, three Israeli Army sergeants from an engineering unit made the regular check on schedule, without escorts. Two got out to look at the old gate, secured by a thick chain.</p>
        <p>There were two big explosions by the Lebanese side of the fence. Eight anti-tank rockets screamed overhead, exploding on the Israeli side and setting grass fires. Smoke from homemade grenades obscured the Hezbollah squad racing through the blown-up gate toward the dazed Israeli soldiers. ''All of a sudden there was smoke,'' Major Bansiwal said. ''Nothing could be seen. At the same time, there was heavy fire on the Israelis.''</p>
        <p>From 1:40 that afternoon to 2:25, some 313 rounds of mortar and rocket fire were leveled at seven Israeli positions across the border, according to United Nations logs. The launchers are easily transportable; broken down, they can be carried in the trunk of a car or on foot. They vanished.</p>
        <p>When the smoke cleared, the three Israeli soldiers were gone too, seized by the guerrillas to exchange for 19 Shiite Muslim fighters long held in Israeli jails, including two who had themselves been abducted from their homes by Israeli commandos.</p>
        <p>The latest abduction marks a new role for Hezbollah, one developed with Iranian guidance, according to Hezbollah officials and a leading Lebanese expert on Islamic fundamentalism.</p>
        <p>This summer, with their guerrilla war in the south successfully over, leaders of Hezbollah -- the Iranian-backed Lebanese Shiite militia whose name means the Party of God -- were uncertain what their new aims should be, said Nizar Hamzi of the American University of Beirut. So Sheik Hassan Nasrallah, the Hezbollah political leader, went to Tehran to seek the counsel of Ayatollah Ali Khamenei, the supreme leader of Iran and a religious guide for Shiite Muslims.</p>
        <p>Do not get bogged down in parliamentary politics, the ayatollah advised them, according to Dr. Hamzi; your role is to work for the Muslim liberation of Jerusalem.</p>
        <p>It seemed a far-off goal, but the current Palestinian uprising has drastically changed matters. ''Hezbollah has not given up on jihad,'' or holy war, Dr. Hamzi said. ''They see themselves as examples and role models who can train, advise and give expertise.''</p>
        <p>Sheik Nasrallah made that clear when he announced the capture of the three Israelis in a two-hour television address, saying the operation had been carried out ''in support of our brothers in Palestine.''</p>
        <p>Hezbollah's deputy secretary general, Sheik Naim Qassem, made the same point at a news conference for foreign journalists. Planning for the operation went on for months, he said, adding, ''We used this timing to be in harmony with the intifada.''</p>
        <p>The planning was evident. On Saturday hundreds of Palestinians demonstrated at the Ramieh gate, many miles from here, diverting the army's attention. Hezbollah helped provide buses for the Palestinians' unusual outing to the gate from their camps near Beirut.</p>
        <p>Almost simultaneously with the abduction, Hezbollah fighters abandoned all their other border posts, United Nations officials said. With the artillery barrage, it was half an hour before the Israelis realized that the three soldiers had disappeared.</p>
        <p>''One would have to call it a smooth operation, very professional,'' said a senior United Nations official in the area.</p>
        <p>A walk through the abandoned Hezbollah camp here, where much of the guerrillas' equipment remains intact, shows how skilled it was. A cheap red metal desk sits hidden from the road by a mound of earth, with a white telephone, its receiver dangling from its curly wire. In an opened drawer are two electric switch boxes with big ''on'' buttons.</p>
        <p>About 20 yards in front of the desk is a nondescript office chair by a tree, with a clear view of the road and the gate.</p>
        <p>Two sets of wires from the electric boxes run toward the gate, stopping short, burnt out, on a small bluff on the Lebanese side of the border, at a mass of torn-up dirt. A demolition expert said bombs had been set off at that spot, near the road, presumably intended to cause disorientation rather than damage.</p>
        <p>Communication wire from the phone led back to the Hezbollah cargo-container headquarters, now destroyed by Israeli fire. Hidden in the dirt outcroppings behind the headquarters were two places where four sets of Soviet-made Sagger anti-tank missiles were launched electronically. Their metal suitcase containers were set up as launching pads.</p>
        <p>A swift set of explosions apparently disoriented the three Israelis, and an immediate burst of artillery fire covered their abduction. By the time the Israelis responded with helicopter gunships, the captives had been carried off through Shabaa, only a kilometer away.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
