<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Surf the Palace at Versailles. Donations Accepted.</title>
    <meta content="12VERS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Circuits" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/12/technology/12VERS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238065"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SCREEN GRAB"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Versailles (France)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">France</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pollak, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Circuits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France/Versailles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001012T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E0DF163FF931A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="823" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Surf the Palace at Versailles. Donations Accepted.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL POLLAK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pollak, Michael</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>December 1999 brought freakish storm to Versailles, France, causing $32.6 million damages to horticulture, rooves and windows at the Palace; official Web site for Versailles offers data and exquisite illustrations and seeks donations for restoring the damaged architectural treasure; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT was once the center of French political and social life, a 700-room, gilt-and-glass birdcage strategically expanded by Louis XIV to concentrate the nobility where he could keep an eye on them. It housed queens and mistresses, played a large part in the revolution and was the place where two wars officially ended.</p>
        <p>And now it needs help.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT was once the center of French political and social life, a 700-room, gilt-and-glass birdcage strategically expanded by Louis XIV to concentrate the nobility where he could keep an eye on them. It housed queens and mistresses, played a large part in the revolution and was the place where two wars officially ended.</p>
        <p>And now it needs help.</p>
        <p>The official, exquisitely illustrated Web site for Versailles (www .chateauversailles.fr) is a royal feast. Even the data page under ''Versailles Today'' is fascinating: 27 miles of trellises, 200,000 trees, 210,000 flowers planted every year, 50 fountains with 620 nozzles, 26 acres of roof, 67 staircases, 2,100 sculptures and 6,000 paintings.</p>
        <p>But 10,000 of those trees, including Marie Antoinette's 1783 tulip tree and a Corsican pine planted for Napoleon in 1810, were uprooted by 100-mile-an-hour winds, which also damaged roofs and windows, in a freakish storm last year on Dec. 25 and 26.</p>
        <p>The French Ministry of Culture, which estimated the damage at 238 million francs ($32.6 million), is using the Web site to ask for donations ($154 will replant one tree). The appeal is accompanied by pictures of the storm's aftermath, described by an official as resembling the World War I battlefield of Verdun.</p>
        <p>The Versailles site, which is available in French, English and Spanish, began in 1998, and half of its 3,800 daily users are English-speaking, a site official said.</p>
        <p>It has all the expected online tourism information: maps, transportation schedules, fees, hours, concerts, sound-and-light shows and special exhibitions. But the site's home page also offers a quick immersion in Versailles's grandeur, with three, 360-degree moving panoramas of the chateau's courtyard, the Hall of Mirrors and the king's bedchamber. The latter is swathed in brocades and equipped with cushions for the roughly 100 officials who typically jammed into the bedroom to attend the king's rising and retiring. The panorama also offers a view from his windows.</p>
        <p>Throughout the site, the art allows zoom-in examination. One page lists Louis XV's recipe for chocolate; it is illustrated by Charpentier's painting of the family of the Duke of Penthievre, all with chocolate cups in hand.</p>
        <p>There are descriptions of the royal dinners, a day in the life of the Sun King, Louis XIV, and tips on being a winning courtier. (Wealth, perseverance, strong will and skill were all required. ''Depending on the king's whim, however,'' the site says, ''greatest favor would probably go to the best hunter or billiard player.'')</p>
        <p>The Places section covers the history of the chateau, starting with the hunting lodge built in 1623 by Louis XIII. It was his son, the Sun King, who had his architect embellish the palace, which became the official residence of the French Court in 1682.</p>
        <p>There are illustrated histories of the Grand Trianon and the Petit Trianon, the palaces within the palace, and the peasant village where Marie Antoinette played at being a shepherdess. There are descriptions of the gardens, fountains and 120 miles of channels and aqueducts that kept the water flowing.</p>
        <p>Personal profiles include Louis XIV (who became king at age 5); Louis XV, who fathered 10 children by age 27; Madame de Pompadour, Louis XV's mistress, whose support for the arts benefited the Sevres porcelain works and Voltaire, among others; and the Marquis de Lafayette, who rejected a position at court for a military career and support for American independence. (Returning from the surrender at Yorktown a hero, he danced a quadrille with Marie Antoinette at the Petit Trianon.)</p>
        <p>The profiles offer unusual anecdotal glimpses of French history. At the peak of his power, before his disastrous Russian invasion, Napoleon envisioned living at Versailles and had the Grand Trianon and the Petit Trianon refurbished for his and his family's use.</p>
        <p>Versailles was used as a hospital during the Franco-Prussian War, and for a few months served as the residence of the victorious king of Prussia, who proclaimed the founding of the German Empire in the Hall of Mirrors in January 1871. (France signed a peace treaty with Bismarck there, a favor that was returned in 1919, when Germany signed the Treaty of Versailles in the hall.)</p>
        <p>Charles De Gaulle, the site notes, referred to Versailles 40 times in his memoirs. De Gaulle had the Grand Trianon restored, and he preferred to entertain distinguished guests there rather than at his official residence, the Elysee Palace, the former home of Madame de Pompadour. ''The home of a queen seems more dignified than that of a favorite,'' he is quoted as saying.</p>
        <p>For those who want more French culture online, two other major English-language sites are www .smartweb.fr/orsay, for the Musee d'Orsay, which is in a converted railway station and covers art from 1848 to 1914; and www.louvre.fr /louvrea.htm, the official site for the Louvre.</p>
        <p>SCREEN GRAB</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
