<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Spin in Spotlight for Pettitte and Martinez</title>
    <meta content="25YANK$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/25/sports/25YANK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233720"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Detroit Tigers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Robbins, Liz</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Detroit Tigers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000925T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E6D6143AF936A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1093" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Spin in Spotlight for Pettitte and Martinez</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIZ ROBBINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Robbins, Liz</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Yankees defeat Detroit Tigers, 6-3; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two Yankees did the tango in the spotlight all afternoon yesterday against the Detroit Tigers.</p>
        <p>Pitcher Andy Pettitte percolated with emotion as he sought his 19th victory and 100th career victory, forgetting the struggles of last season when he was nearly traded before the trading deadline. Tino Martinez, a slugger who has struggled this year, was merely looking for a hit.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Two Yankees did the tango in the spotlight all afternoon yesterday against the Detroit Tigers.</p>
        <p>Pitcher Andy Pettitte percolated with emotion as he sought his 19th victory and 100th career victory, forgetting the struggles of last season when he was nearly traded before the trading deadline. Tino Martinez, a slugger who has struggled this year, was merely looking for a hit.</p>
        <p>Manager Joe Torre had faith in both, and yesterday they rewarded him.</p>
        <p>Martinez blasted out of a 1-for-33 slump with two two-run home runs that lifted the Yankees to a 6-3 triumph over Detroit, helping Pettitte reach the century mark in his six-year career with the Yankees.</p>
        <p>Pettitte struck out five batters through seven and a third innings, and he picked off a runner in the fifth. In the seventh, he speared a speeding-bullet line drive and then spun around on his knees, whipping the ball across his body to Martinez. He slammed his glove on his leg when the first-base umpire, Jerry Meals, ruled Martinez was off the bag to prevent a double play, showing how important this victory was to Pettitte, if not the team.</p>
        <p>''I was a little more emotional for this one,'' said Pettitte (19-8), who has one start left in the regular season. ''You try to get keyed up for certain things, try to turn it up a little bit. There was more emphasis going for the 100th.''</p>
        <p>For the first time in nearly two weeks, the Yankees have won two in a row, distancing themselves from their six-game losing streak and shaving their number to clinch the American League East to three after Toronto lost yesterday.</p>
        <p>''Andy was terrific today,'' Torre said. ''I don't think the priority for him was win the 100th win, he wanted to help us win a pennant. It was a good game for him, for us, because we put two wins back to back.''</p>
        <p>The 41,415 fans watching the final regular-season day game at Yankee Stadium gave two standing ovations: when Pettitte came out of the game for reliever Jeff Nelson with a 4-3 lead and one out in the eighth inning, and when Martinez ran out to the field in the top of the ninth after his eighth-inning heroics.</p>
        <p>With two outs and a full count, and with Jorge Posada on second, Martinez crushed a two-run home run to the upper deck off reliever C. J. Nitkowski that gave the Yankees a three-run cushion.</p>
        <p>Three outs later, Martinez caught a soft liner to end the game and conveyed the souvenir to Pettitte through the closer Mariano Rivera, who came in for the ninth to earn his 36th save. In his third start since Sept. 9, Pettitte finally secured No. 100.</p>
        <p>''I feel like I'm a pretty good pitcher, and I feel like I play for a really good team with a really good bullpen and it makes me look a little bit better,'' Pettitte said. ''I may not dominate like some pitchers do.''</p>
        <p>Maybe not, but Pettitte's 88 victories from 1996, when he went 21-8, to this year are the third most in the major leagues during the five-year span.</p>
        <p>''He doesn't get a whole lot of attention paid to him, but he certainly has been consistent,'' Torre said. ''For a year, he was spotty, and you look up and he still wins ballgames.''</p>
        <p>After starting the season 7-8 last year (he finished 14-11), Pettitte knew Torre had to persuade management to keep him. ''I wouldn't be here if it wasn't for him,'' Pettitte said. ''They were set on getting rid of me. I wouldn't have been able to have done what I've done if not for him.''</p>
        <p>Torre has supported Martinez, too, dropping him to seventh in the batting order, but keeping him in the lineup through his 0-for-28 streak. In his first four years Martinez has been with the Yankees, he has had no fewer than 25 home runs a season, with 44 in 1997 and 28 each of the past two seasons.</p>
        <p>''I don't forget what he's done in the past,'' Torre said. ''I told him, 'You're going to play every day. When we clinch this thing, then we'll rest.' He has been a big part of what we've done here since I've been here.''</p>
        <p>Martinez got his 15th home run of the season in the second inning. Bernie Williams had already led off with a solo shot that marked a career-best 30 home runs.</p>
        <p>After Posada singled to right, Martinez delivered his home run a few rows back of the right-field wall for a 3-0 Yankees lead. ''Early in the season, I think I was trying too hard to hit home runs and I was overswinging for a while there,'' Martinez said.</p>
        <p>Pettitte was also trying too hard at times yesterday. Perfect through two and two-thirds innings, he gave up a walk to Shane Halter, who scored, despite stumbling, on Jose Macias' triple. The Yankees got another run in the sixth when Derek Jeter singled to lead off the inning and scored on a wild pitch. But with a 4-1 lead, Pettite fell into trouble in the seventh.</p>
        <p>With one out, Pettitte snared a liner from Brad Ausmus. On the double-play attempt, Martinez said his foot was on the bag at first, but the umpire did not see it. Pettitte gave up a single and then a triple to Halter that made the score 4-3. But Martinez ensured Pettitte's 100th victory.</p>
        <p>''At least we righted the ship, and we're playing with a lot more confidence right now,'' Torre said.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>ROGER CLEMENS has a circular multicolored bruise on the back of his right hamstring and he was sore, as expected, yesterday. Clemens was hit by a ground ball in the third inning of Saturday's game, which could affect his push-off leg in his delivery. Manager JOE TORRE will not make a decision on whether to rest Clemens for his final regular-season start until today or tomorrow.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
