<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Better Nursing Home Care</title>
    <meta content="25MON3$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/25/opinion/25MON3.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233667"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nursing Homes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nursing Homes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Aged</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000925T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E3DA143AF936A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="545" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Better Nursing Home Care</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial says Pres Clinton is right to focus debate on nursing home reform on often indigent older women who make up most of nursing home population (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When President Clinton walked into a room filled with the old people who live at the Washington Home, in the District of Columbia, on a recent Saturday, Alice Gavin, who is 105, stood up. It was, she thought, the respectful thing to do, and Mr. Clinton was about to deliver his weekly radio address, proposing a package of federal grants, punishments and rewards to try to improve the quality of care in the nation's nursing homes. He called for a billion dollars in new federal grants to hire more health care workers and better train them so each resident would have at least two hours of individual care each day.</p>
        <p>His announcement came as a surprise. The Clinton administration has a record of toughening the standards and inspections of nursing homes, and it recently issued a report that showed what anyone in health care has long known -- good care is a function of the number of people available and trained to give it. The fewer nurses and nurses' aides on staff, the less individual attention the 1.6 million frail elderly residents get, the more bedsores, malnutrition, abnormal weight loss and depression they suffer, and, in all probability, the faster they die. There are no federal requirements for staff-patient ratios, but 54 percent of homes, the report found, are understaffed to the point that residents do not get the minimal two hours of care by nurses' aides per day necessary to keep them from being endangered.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When President Clinton walked into a room filled with the old people who live at the Washington Home, in the District of Columbia, on a recent Saturday, Alice Gavin, who is 105, stood up. It was, she thought, the respectful thing to do, and Mr. Clinton was about to deliver his weekly radio address, proposing a package of federal grants, punishments and rewards to try to improve the quality of care in the nation's nursing homes. He called for a billion dollars in new federal grants to hire more health care workers and better train them so each resident would have at least two hours of individual care each day.</p>
        <p>His announcement came as a surprise. The Clinton administration has a record of toughening the standards and inspections of nursing homes, and it recently issued a report that showed what anyone in health care has long known -- good care is a function of the number of people available and trained to give it. The fewer nurses and nurses' aides on staff, the less individual attention the 1.6 million frail elderly residents get, the more bedsores, malnutrition, abnormal weight loss and depression they suffer, and, in all probability, the faster they die. There are no federal requirements for staff-patient ratios, but 54 percent of homes, the report found, are understaffed to the point that residents do not get the minimal two hours of care by nurses' aides per day necessary to keep them from being endangered.</p>
        <p>The president could have let that study by the Health Care Financing Administration simply feed the bipartisan interest in passing some kind of nursing home support bill before this session of Congress ends. He has chosen instead to try to shape that debate, and he has focused on the single most important element for the welfare of the vulnerable, often indigent older women who make up most of the nursing home population. He is right to do so. Congress, which spends $39 billion a year on nursing home care, seems inclined to restore some of the Medicare funds it cut three years ago, in part because six of the nation's largest for-profit nursing home chains have gone bankrupt as those cuts have taken effect in the last year.</p>
        <p>Restoring the Medicare money might improve the financial health of those chains, and if Congress also restored the Medicare funds cut from home health care, more older Americans might be able to remain in their own homes. That is desirable. Most people do not need or want to be in nursing homes.</p>
        <p>But none of that touches the issue of inadequate staff. The study reported that good care requires 4.5 hours per resident per day. Congress needs to mandate staff ratios and be willing to help pay for them. Enough staff to meet the standard of two hours of care a day is a worthwhile start. Congress should also instruct the Health Care Financing Administration to arrive at meaningful long-term staff ratios within two years to ensure quality care for all the residents of nursing homes. Miss Gavin still bathes and dresses and feeds herself, but most residents of nursing homes need a lot more help than she does.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
