<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>If Cell Phones Were Sport, A Platinum Medal for Aussies</title>
    <meta content="25CELL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/25/technology/25CELL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233636"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Summer Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cellular Telephones</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sydney (Australia)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Australia</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Samsung Electronics Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Telstra Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Landler, Mark</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia/Sydney</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cellular Telephones</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000925T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901EED6173AF936A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1109" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>If Cell Phones Were Sport, A Platinum Medal for Aussies</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARK LANDLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Landler, Mark</byline>
      <dateline>SYDNEY, Australia, Sept. 24</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Cellular phone use is at record level at Sydney Olympics; Samsung Electronics, Olympics sponsor, has flooded area, where wireless penetration was already heavy, with 15,000 free phones; Telstra, Australia's publicly traded but still state-controled phone company, has upgraded digital network and installed galaxy of microcells in enormous Olympic stadium to handle heavy call volume; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Yakking on a cellular phone is not yet an Olympic sport, even at an Olympics that has featured the debut of trampoline jumping. But after a week of record-breaking mobile chatter, Sydney can lay reasonable claim to being the first wireless Olympics.</p>
        <p>Mobile telephones can be found are everywhere at these Games -- in the hands of spectators, officials, athletes, even visitors, who are taking advantage of agreements on roaming use to bring their phones from overseas.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Yakking on a cellular phone is not yet an Olympic sport, even at an Olympics that has featured the debut of trampoline jumping. But after a week of record-breaking mobile chatter, Sydney can lay reasonable claim to being the first wireless Olympics.</p>
        <p>Mobile telephones can be found are everywhere at these Games -- in the hands of spectators, officials, athletes, even visitors, who are taking advantage of agreements on roaming use to bring their phones from overseas.</p>
        <p>With 8.5 million subscribing to cellular service -- more than 40 percent of the population -- Australia is already one of the world's concentrated wireless markets. The high penetration has been magnified by Samsung Electronics, an Olympics sponsor, which has flooded Sydney with 15,000 free phones.</p>
        <p>''Aussies love their mobiles,'' said Michelle Mazzarella, a city transit employee, who took her phone to a soccer match to receive minute-by-minute updates on Australia's swimming champion, Ian Thorpe.</p>
        <p>Claude Comley, a software designer, stood in Sydney's teeming railroad station the other day, with a frazzled look and a phone cradled in his shoulder. He was trying to meet a friend to head for the Olympic stadium.</p>
        <p>''She's coming in on a train, and she's probably in a tunnel,'' Mr. Comley said as he punched up her number for the umpteenth time.</p>
        <p>Many of these calls are flowing over the newly upgraded digital network of Telstra, Australia's publicly traded but still state-controlled phone company, which has prompted company executives to strain for superlatives.</p>
        <p>''For telecommunications, these Games have produced the largest concentration of demand for services at any singular event ever,'' said Brian Pilbeam, general manager of Olympics services for Telstra.</p>
        <p>Verifying such claims is tricky, but Telstra's numbers are impressive by any measure. The company connected 500,000 mobile calls in Olympic Park on the first day of the Games. About 125,000 of those were made inside Stadium Australia, which was packed with 110,000 people for the opening ceremony.</p>
        <p>Telstra experienced huge spikes in use at dramatic moments, like when the Olympic torch was lighted and when the athletes entered the stadium. Plenty of those calls were made by the athletes themselves, some of whom were too busy racking up long-distance charges to wave to the crowd.</p>
        <p>Telstra said it was fairly simple to equip smaller arenas, like the Aquatic Center, with an adequate cellular network. The engineering challenge was how to equip the enormous Olympic stadium.</p>
        <p>The company installed a galaxy of microcells -- many hidden in lampposts -- that shower a signal over the audience in much smaller segments than a typical macrocell. This allows slices of the radio spectrum to be reused more efficiently, expanding its capacity beyond that of a normal network.</p>
        <p>''We believe it's the densest cellular network in any structure in the world,'' said Anthony Goonan, regional manager of Telstra's mobile division. He said the network's only potential rival had been at the Stade de France in suburban Paris, where the World Cup soccer final was played in 1998.</p>
        <p>Mr. Goonan carried three phones around the stadium throughout the opening ceremony, testing Telstra's service against those of its rivals, Optus and Vodafone. They are allowed to lease capacity on Telstra's network inside the stadium, but must complete calls on their own networks.</p>
        <p>''Our objective was for people to get through the first time, most of the time,'' Mr. Goonan said. ''The congestion levels were quite low, and we didn't have any complaints from customers about poor service.''</p>
        <p>Not surprisingly, Mr. Goonan said he had more trouble making calls on the two other services. Although Telstra has the biggest market share here, at 50 percent, it is waging a fierce battle against Optus and Vodafone.</p>
        <p>With its revenue under attack, Telstra announced steep rate increases earlier in the month on land-line local and long-distance calls. The company, which has been part-privately owned since 1997, also said it would lay off 10,000 workers.</p>
        <p>For Telstra, the Olympics are a chance to redirect attention from its business fortunes to its technical prowess. The company has invested $50 million to upgrade its mobile network throughout Sydney for the Olympics. And the bells and whistles go beyond Stadium Australia.</p>
        <p>Throughout the park, Telstra has engineered the network so that it can increase the capacity in segments to follow a crowd of people and their cellular calls. If that does not meet demand, it has stashed mobile cells behind buildings that can be rolled out to increase capacity.</p>
        <p>For all these precautions, Telstra cannot guarantee that calls will not connect at peak moments.</p>
        <p>''Mobile service is one of the most visible contributions we're making to the Games, but also the most vulnerable,'' Mr. Pilbeam said. ''There will be massive spikes in usage that no network in the world can handle.''</p>
        <p>It is not just the number of people talking on cellular phones that makes these Games seem to some like a wireless convention with athletic events thrown in. It is also the pervasive presence of Samsung, the  Korean conglomerate, which hopes to use Sydney to vault itself into the major leagues of mobile phones.</p>
        <p>Samsung began making cellular telephones in 1989, but only began exporting them to the United States in 1997. It is fourth in the industry, after Nokia, Ericsson and Motorola, with 6.2 percent of the global market.</p>
        <p>''We need the powerful marketing tool of the Olympics to catch up, because we're a latecomer,'' said Jay Kim, a Samsung spokesman.</p>
        <p>Perhaps hoping to make up in hype what it lacks in history, Samsung donated about 15,000 phones to the Sydney Olympic committee, which in turn lent or leased them to athletes, volunteers and the news media.</p>
        <p>The company also erected a cavernous tent pavilion in Olympic Park to promote the Samsung name. A slick showroom features its latest gadgets, including a phone so tiny that one wears it -- Dick Tracy-like -- on the wrist.</p>
        <p>Just in case anyone misses the message, Samsung has hired performers, dressed in zoot suits and wraparound sunglasses, to march through public places around Sydney in tight formation, chattering on their phones.</p>
        <p>No word yet on whether team cellular will become an Olympic event.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
