<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Navarro May Fulfill A Brother's Failed Quest</title>
    <meta content="25BOXI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="S" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233611"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SYDNEY 2000: BOXING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Summer Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Morocco</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sydney (Australia)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pennington, Bill</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Navarro, Jose</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mesbahi, Hicham</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004/Boxing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Morocco</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia/Sydney</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Morocco</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000925T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E0D7173AF936A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="989" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Navarro May Fulfill A Brother's Failed Quest</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL PENNINGTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pennington, Bill</byline>
      <dateline>SYDNEY, Australia, Sept. 24</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>American flyweight Jose Navarro scores second-round victory over Hicham Mesbahi of Morocco to advance in boxing competition at Summer Olympics; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A soundtrack came with the American flyweight Jose Navarro's second-round victory today in the Olympic boxing tournament. It was loud, passionate and mostly in Spanish, and it came from Navarro's older brother, Carlos, who stood ringside yelling instructions and encouragement that filled the small converted hall that serves as Sydney's boxing arena.</p>
        <p>Navarro was losing a tight fight with Hicham Mesbahi of Morocco and needed a final-round rally. Carlos was doing everything in his power to make sure his brother pulled through.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A soundtrack came with the American flyweight Jose Navarro's second-round victory today in the Olympic boxing tournament. It was loud, passionate and mostly in Spanish, and it came from Navarro's older brother, Carlos, who stood ringside yelling instructions and encouragement that filled the small converted hall that serves as Sydney's boxing arena.</p>
        <p>Navarro was losing a tight fight with Hicham Mesbahi of Morocco and needed a final-round rally. Carlos was doing everything in his power to make sure his brother pulled through.</p>
        <p>When Navarro was declared the winner, 12-9 on points, Mesbahi threw himself facefirst to the canvas and later left the ring sobbing.</p>
        <p>''They stole a victory and everyone who watched the fight knows it,'' said Mesbahi, who was ahead by 7-6 heading into the fourth and final round when Navarro quickly grabbed the lead with a series of left-hand jabs and combinations. Mesbahi appeared to counterpunch successfully later in the round, but he did not receive any points to close the gap.</p>
        <p>There may be only one gold medal awarded in this division this week, but there are two Navarros chasing it. And if Jose wins it, Carlos gets to keep it.</p>
        <p>''I could hear him,'' Jose said with a laugh after the fight. ''Everybody in the place could hear him. He knows we're in this together.''</p>
        <p>It was supposed to be the other way around, Jose in the grandstand, cheering for Carlos at the Olympics.</p>
        <p>In the two-bedroom house in South Central Los Angeles that Navarro shared with his parents and 11 brothers and sisters, Carlos, five years his senior, was always going to be the family's Olympian. Or at least the first one.</p>
        <p>Carlos Navarro was the top-rated American amateur featherweight for most of the early 1990's and a seasoned fighter with international experience.</p>
        <p>''I was ranked No. 1 for three straight years heading into the 1996 Olympic trials,'' Carlos Navarro said last week. ''Everybody knew I was going to the Atlanta Olympics. I guess I got big-headed because I lost in the trials to Floyd Mayweather, who ended up winning a bronze medal.''</p>
        <p>Navarro, who was 15 years old at the time, remembers sitting with his older brother in the locker room after his Olympic trials defeat.</p>
        <p>''He was just staring down at the floor,'' Navarro said. ''What was there to say? So I told him I still had a chance at the Olympics. If I could win a gold medal, it would be for him and me. He was always there from the beginning, helping me in boxing. I told him, why should all our hard work go to waste?''</p>
        <p>The brothers sat next to each other as Jose told this story last week.</p>
        <p>''He's fighting for both of us,'' Carlos added as his brothers nodded in agreement. ''And if he wins a gold medal, he's going to give it to me. Right, Jose?''</p>
        <p>Jose smiled.</p>
        <p>''That's right,'' he said. ''I am.''</p>
        <p>Carlos, along with his eldest sister, Esperanza, and their father, Carlos Sr., are in Sydney with help from Oscar De La Hoya, the star boxer and a former Olympic champion. The family raised money for years -- ''Tons of aluminum cans recycled,'' Carlos said -- but was still short when it came to the air fare to Australia.</p>
        <p>The Navarro home isn't too far from De La Hoya's old neighborhood, and Carlos and Jose had occasionally trained in the same gym as De La Hoya.</p>
        <p>''Last year, he said he wanted to help me out,'' Jose said of De La Hoya. ''He's helped a lot of people like me in our community. I wanted my family to be able to come to Sydney, so I said O.K. It's a nice gesture.''</p>
        <p>As the son of Mexican immigrants living in Los Angeles, and with boyish good looks, Navarro, who graduated from high school with a 3.8 grade-point average, has been compared to De La Hoya and been called the next Golden Boy.</p>
        <p>''It's way too early for that,'' Navarro said. ''I'm just getting started.''</p>
        <p>Carlos has begun a professional career -- his record is 22-1 -- and Jose concedes he will most likely turn pro, too. He dreams of earning enough money to build his parents a new home outside Los Angeles, though he is not sure he could move.</p>
        <p>''In a way, I like it there with all the noise -- the helicopters overhead, the police sirens, the gunshots,'' he said. ''I know that might sound funny, but I'm so used to it. But I'd like to do something for my family; they did so much for me.''</p>
        <p>Carlos Sr. bought and sold used cars, funneling extra income into vitamins for his boxing sons and boxing equipment for the backyard. His wife sewed the robes they wore in the ring.</p>
        <p>''The income wasn't always constant,'' said Jose, who began competitive boxing when he was 5 years old. ''But for the number of children we had in that little house, they did great. And that backyard got a lot of use. We had a punching bag out there, a speed bag. It was like a little gym.''</p>
        <p>PUNCH LINES</p>
        <p>The American RICARDO WILLIAMS JR. advanced to the quarterfinals of the light-welterweight division with a commanding victory over OLUSEGUN AJOSE of Nigeria. The fight was stopped in the third round because Williams had built a 21-6 lead. But the United States light-heavyweight OLANDA ANDERSON lost his second-round fight with RUDOLF KRAJ of the Czech Republic, 13-12. Anderson had a bye in the first round, something United States Coach TOM MUSTIN felt hurt Anderson.</p>
        <p>SYDNEY 2000: BOXING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
