<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Monday Morning Quarterback</title>
    <meta content="25QB.$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/25/sports/A34661-2000Sep25.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233733"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="COLLEGE FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Drape, Joe</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000925T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E3D6143AF936A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="934" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Monday Morning Quarterback</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE DRAPE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Drape, Joe</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Highlights and lowlights from weekend college football games; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Highlights and lowlights from the weekend.</p>
        <p>IT WASN'T HIS FAULT. . .  Wisconsin tailback Michael Bennett gained a career-high 293 yards on a taxing 48 carries.</p>
        <p>IT WAS THE SHOES -- But the No. 17 Badgers were still upset by Northwestern, 47-44, in double overtime perhaps because of the absence of their No. 1 receiver Chris Chambers and All-America cornerback Jamar Fletcher, who were among the last of 26 players who served N.C.A.A suspensions for accepting discounts at a shoe store outside Madison, Wis.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Highlights and lowlights from the weekend.</p>
        <p>IT WASN'T HIS FAULT. . .  Wisconsin tailback Michael Bennett gained a career-high 293 yards on a taxing 48 carries.</p>
        <p>IT WAS THE SHOES -- But the No. 17 Badgers were still upset by Northwestern, 47-44, in double overtime perhaps because of the absence of their No. 1 receiver Chris Chambers and All-America cornerback Jamar Fletcher, who were among the last of 26 players who served N.C.A.A suspensions for accepting discounts at a shoe store outside Madison, Wis.</p>
        <p>FROM THE BENCH TO THE POSTGAME SHOW -- Arkansas's third-string tailback Alvin Ray rumbled 32 yards to set up the winning touchdown with 64 seconds left in the Razorbacks' 28-21 victory over Alabama. ''The line opened up and there was a big hole,'' said Ray, who got the ball after injuries to Arkansas' top two backs. ''I felt a defender on me, but I just kept my legs pumping and ran.''</p>
        <p>FROM THE TRAINER'S ROOM TO THE POSTGAME SHOW -- Michigan quarterback Drew Henson came off the bench to lead the No. 9 Wolverines to a 35-31 come-from-behind victory over No. 24 ranked Illinois. It was the ballyhooed passer's first appearance since breaking a bone in his right foot shortly before the season began. The Illini were up by 21-7 in the second half when Henson, 8 of 17 for 141 yards, led four scoring drives including his 8-yard run and 57-yard touchdown pass to David Terrell.</p>
        <p>HIGHLIGHTS FROM SIGNAL CALLERS NOT NAMED BREES, VICK, CROUCH OR WEINKE -- Woodrow Dantzler ran for 220 yards and two touchdowns and completed 15 of 24 passes for 154 yards and another score as No. 7 Clemson beat Virginia, 31-10.</p>
        <p>-- Jesse Palmer accounted for five touchdowns, four of them rushing, to tie a school record, as No. 3 Florida beat Kentucky for the 14th consecutive time, 59-31.</p>
        <p>-- Jonathan Beasley scored a school-record five touchdowns as No. 5 Kansas State beat North Texas, 55-10.</p>
        <p>-- Rashaan Matthews threw four touchdowns to Darnerien McCants in the second half, and five over all, as Delaware State beat Liberty, 42-25.</p>
        <p>YES, I HAVE A PLAN -- ''You know how demanding our program is and how much we expect out of our kids. It's just great to give them evidence. For a year and a half, I have been waiting to give them evidence that there is a method to the madness and a reason for all the things we try to do,'' Northwestern Coach Randy Walker after a 47-44 upset of Wisconsin that lifted the Wildcats to 3-1, 1-0 in the Big Ten.</p>
        <p>HIS EYES SAID YES -- ''I knew it was a touchdown, you knew it was a touchdown, everybody does. The ref knew it too because he looked at me like he was sorry,'' said U.C.L.A. receiver Freddie Mitchell about what he believed was his apparent touchdown reception in the third quarter of the Bruins' 29-10 loss to Oregon. Instead, the official waved it off as out of bounds.</p>
        <p>COLLEGE FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
