<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Compressed Data; In Time for Fall Season, NBCi Piles On the Features</title>
    <meta content="25NBCI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/25/technology/25NBCI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233608"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nbc Internet (Nbci)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">General Electric Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Broadcasting Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hansell, Saul</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000925T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E1D7173AF936A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="430" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Compressed Data; In Time for Fall Season, NBCi Piles On the Features</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAUL HANSELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hansell, Saul</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>NBC Internet, company partly owned by General Electric's NBC network, is set to introduce its new flagship NBCicom site; site brings together under one name features from jumble of brands company built and bought; has been adding features and technology in bid to compete with bigger Internet portals (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Maybe it is because they are used to a new season in the fall. But the Internet services that are tied to big television networks seem to be picking this month to showcase new versions of their sites.</p>
        <p>Two weeks ago, Walt Disney's Go.com, which incorporates sites related to its ABC and ESPN networks, introduced a complete redesign. And today, NBC Internet, a company partly owned by General Electric's NBC network, will introduce its new flagship NBCi.com. The site brings together under one name the features from a jumble of brands the company built and bought, including Snap, Xoom and NBC.com. (The MSNBC news site and the CNBC financial news site are separate.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Maybe it is because they are used to a new season in the fall. But the Internet services that are tied to big television networks seem to be picking this month to showcase new versions of their sites.</p>
        <p>Two weeks ago, Walt Disney's Go.com, which incorporates sites related to its ABC and ESPN networks, introduced a complete redesign. And today, NBC Internet, a company partly owned by General Electric's NBC network, will introduce its new flagship NBCi.com. The site brings together under one name the features from a jumble of brands the company built and bought, including Snap, Xoom and NBC.com. (The MSNBC news site and the CNBC financial news site are separate.)</p>
        <p>While neither Go.com nor the NBCi sites have been able to keep pace with the growth of the very largest Internet portals -- America Online, Yahoo and Microsoft's MSN -- they are coping in very different ways.</p>
        <p>Go is trying to squeeze more from less. It has stripped down the site to little more than a search engine while increasing the size and number of advertisements.</p>
        <p>NBCi, by contrast, continues to add features and technology in order to try to beat the bigger portals at their own game.</p>
        <p>''People spend a lot of time on Yahoo,'' said Edmond Sanctis, NBCi's president, noting that the more pages seen, the more ads sold. ''We got a lot of people to try us as a search engine, but we never got people to stay. We want to go from an average of 3 or 4 pages per visit to 8 pages.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, most of the site's new initiatives appear to be copied from Yahoo.com. Its advertising urges users to customize NBCi to their personal taste, much as the popular My Yahoo feature does.</p>
        <p>And just as Yahoo offers free Internet access through Kmart, NBCi is making a similar offer through Montgomery Ward. NBCi has also introduced a free software program that lets users search the Web even when they are not on its site. And yes, Yahoo also has its own search software.</p>
        <p>To be sure, NBCi says its products will be different and better than the competition. Its personalization software, for example, will aim to learn as much about each user as possible so that searches are more fruitful. A user in Britain, say, would get a different result to a search on ''football'' than someone in Boston.</p>
        <p>SAUL HANSELL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
