<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An industry group revamps its awards in an effort to improve the way women are portrayed.</title>
    <meta content="25ADCO$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/25/business/25ADCO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233614"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shoes and Boots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nike Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Advertising Women of New York</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Elliott, Stuart</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Advertising (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shoes and Boots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000925T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E7D6173AF936A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1058" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An industry group revamps its awards in an effort to improve the way women are portrayed.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Stuart Elliott</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Elliott, Stuart</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Nike television commercial that is widely viewed as making light of violence toward women reignites debate over images of women in advertising; comes as Advertising Women of New York prepares for annual event to spur industry to improve portrayal of women in campaigns (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE firestorm last week over a Nike commercial during the Summer Olympics, in which a female runner escapes a masked madman wielding a chainsaw, has reignited a debate about images of women in advertising. The spot, intended as a spoof of so-called slasher movies, was widely castigated as making light of violence toward women and was soon pulled off the air by NBC.</p>
        <p>That outcry still reverberates, as the Advertising Women of New York prepares for its annual event to encourage Madison Avenue to improve the portrayal of women in campaigns. The event, called the Good, the Bad and the Ugly Awards, is scheduled to be held tonight.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE firestorm last week over a Nike commercial during the Summer Olympics, in which a female runner escapes a masked madman wielding a chainsaw, has reignited a debate about images of women in advertising. The spot, intended as a spoof of so-called slasher movies, was widely castigated as making light of violence toward women and was soon pulled off the air by NBC.</p>
        <p>That outcry still reverberates, as the Advertising Women of New York prepares for its annual event to encourage Madison Avenue to improve the portrayal of women in campaigns. The event, called the Good, the Bad and the Ugly Awards, is scheduled to be held tonight.</p>
        <p>The fourth presentation of the organization's honors and dishonors has been revamped from previous years to try to make the event less of a novelty that powerful and influential executives -- particularly male executives -- have found ''easy to dismiss,'' said Alison Burns, one of the three co-chairwomen of the awards, and the president of Fallon New York, part of the Fallon Worldwide unit of the Publicis Groupe S.A.</p>
        <p>For instance, for the first time, men were recruited to serve as judges, and a men's magazine, Maxim, was signed as a sponsor.</p>
        <p>''We needed to elevate the status of the awards because it's important they really effect change in advertising toward women,'' said Cindy Gallop, another co-chairwoman of the event and the president of the New York office of Bartle Bogle Hegarty, which is 49 percent-owned by the B Com3  Group.</p>
        <p>''To really effect change, we have to talk to men, because the creative departments are still heavily male,'' Ms. Gallop said. ''Women sitting around talking to each other will never get anything to happen.''</p>
        <p>Two of the nine judges are men. One is John Hegarty, chairman at Bartle Bogle. The other is Jamie Barrett, executive creative director at Fallon New York.</p>
        <p>''It's very enlightened to include men,'' Mr. Barrett said.</p>
        <p>''I'm one of many creative directors out there who are very much on the hunt for great female creatives,'' he added. ''It's very frustrating not to have a diversity of voice.''</p>
        <p>In the past, said his colleague, Ms. Burns, the awards ceremony was ''a ladies-who-lunch, Midtown-hotel event.'' Rescheduling it as an evening event and moving it to the Puck Building in Lower Manhattan will help ''make people realize it's not 'your mother's awards show,' '' she said.</p>
        <p>Another way to change perceptions, said Mary Warlick, another judge, was to cast a wider net in considering ads deemed patronizing, insulting or annoying.</p>
        <p>''You could pull a lot of ads with busty women out of mechanics' magazines to attack, and they'd be what you'd expect,'' said Ms. Warlick, who is the executive director of the One Club for Art and Copy in New York.</p>
        <p>''That's why it's important to look at ads from larger advertisers that are not sending out the appropriate messages,'' she added.</p>
        <p>For example, one ad the judges declared ''bad'' is for the Jell-O brand, sold by the Kraft Foods unit of Philip Morris, the nation's fourth-largest marketer. The commercial, by Young &amp; Rubicam Advertising in New York, shows a girl rushing to fix Jell-O pudding for a cute new neighbor, a boy playing baseball, as the comedian Bill Cosby declares, ''They say the way to a man's heart is through his stomach.''</p>
        <p>But wait, there's more. When the girl presents the pudding to her budding beau, two other girls turn up with similar treats for him.</p>
        <p>''This boy hasn't done anything but bounce a ball and move in next door, and all of a sudden there are three Graces delivering votives to him,'' Ms. Warlick said ruefully.</p>
        <p>Another judge, Jane Talcott, is a senior partner and group creative director at Y.&amp; R. Advertising; judges excused themselves from evaluating their agencies' work.</p>
        <p>''I'm not embarrassed for Y.&amp; R.,'' Ms. Talcott said. ''Obviously, in any year, a big agency is going to take some hits.''</p>
        <p>Y.&amp; R. Advertising took another hit for a commercial for another big marketer, Colgate-Palmolive. The spot, for the Palmolive Spring Sensations line of dishwashing liquids, shows two women dancing around a kitchen as flowers fall from the ceiling; they chirp lines like ''Springtime every time you do dishes!''</p>
        <p>Perhaps Mel Brooks could include a song titled ''Springtime for Dishes'' in the coming Broadway version of his 1968 film ''The Producers.''</p>
        <p>Other major advertisers and agencies to be chastised tonight include Bristol-Myers Squibb, for a commercial for Clairol Herbal Essences by the the Kaplan Thaler Group in New York, part of B Com3, which will get the Grand Ugly Award, and Volkswagen of America, for a commercial for the Audi A8 by McKinney &amp; Silver in Raleigh, N.C., part of MarchFirst.</p>
        <p>The top award for campaigns praised for positive portrayals of women, called the Grand Good, will be shared by two World Wide Web sites and their agencies. One honored pair is Nordstrom and the Fallon Minneapolis office, for ads for Nordstromshoes.com, and the other is Women.com and Citron Haligman Bedecarre in San Francisco.</p>
        <p>The decision by organizers of the event to ask Maxim to become a sponsor -- along with Business Week magazine, part of McGraw-Hill, Reebok International and Women.com -- may raise some eyebrows (or even hackles) because of its reputation as the leader of the ''beer and babes'' category of the men's magazine market.</p>
        <p>''I'd urge women to read the magazine before they make a formal judgment,'' Ms. Gallop said. ''It has an enormous sense of humor.''</p>
        <p>''Maxim is supporting us,'' she added, ''because they know that to build their business as a mainstream men's magazine, they need the 'girlfriend vote.' ''</p>
        <p>Lance J. O. Ford, general manager at Maxim in New York, published by Dennis Maxim Inc., echoed Ms. Gallop by describing what he termed ''the 'girlfriend test.' ''</p>
        <p>''If you're lucky enough for a girl to come back to your apartment, and Maxim is on the coffee table, what does she think of you?'' Mr. Ford asked. ''If she thinks you're a pig and walks out, we've failed.''</p>
        <p>Hmmmm. Sounds like the basis for another Nike commercial.</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
