<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Peru Spy Chief Flies to Panama Looking for Asylum</title>
    <meta content="Y25PER$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/25/world/25PERU.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233686"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Asylum (Political)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Panama-International Relations-Peru</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bribery</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Peru</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Panama</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Montesinos, Vladimiro</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fujimori, Alberto K (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rohter, Larry</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Panama</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Peru</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Peru</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Panama</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bribery</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Asylum (Political)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000925T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E0D9143AF936A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1100" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Peru Spy Chief Flies to Panama Looking for Asylum</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LARRY ROHTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rohter, Larry</byline>
      <dateline>LIMA, Peru, Sept. 24</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vladimiro Montesinos, disgraced spy chief who was until recently Peru's second most powerful figure, flies to Panama to request asylum in wake of bribery scandal that threatened to topple Pres Alberto K Fujimori; flight appears to be result of diplomatic intervention by US, other Latin American countries and Organization of American States; all have exerted pressure on Fujimori to introduce more democracy and have urged all sides to avoid violence; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The disgraced spy chief who until recently was Peru's second most powerful figure slipped out of the country today, flying to Panama to request asylum in the wake of a bribery scandal that threatened to topple his boss, President Alberto K. Fujimori.</p>
        <p>The ousted intelligence chief, Vladimiro Montesinos, boarded a private jet accompanied by bodyguards and took off from a military air base here just after midnight.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The disgraced spy chief who until recently was Peru's second most powerful figure slipped out of the country today, flying to Panama to request asylum in the wake of a bribery scandal that threatened to topple his boss, President Alberto K. Fujimori.</p>
        <p>The ousted intelligence chief, Vladimiro Montesinos, boarded a private jet accompanied by bodyguards and took off from a military air base here just after midnight.</p>
        <p>The flight, unthinkable until a bribery scandal involving Mr. Montesinos broke 10 days ago, appeared to be a result of diplomatic intervention by the United States, other Latin American countries and the Organization of American States. All have put pressure on Mr. Fujimori to introduce more democracy and urged all sides in Peru to avoid violence after Mr. Fujimori's stunning announcement last week that he would hold new elections in which he would not run, and also ''deactivate'' Mr. Montesinos's widely feared National Intelligence Service.</p>
        <p>Peruvian officials refused to discuss the circumstances of Mr. Montesinos's departure.</p>
        <p>Mr. Montesinos, 55, a cashiered former army captain, has been Mr. Fujimori's most trusted aide, so powerful that the two men are known here as ''the Siamese twins.''</p>
        <p>But that relationship and Mr. Fujimori's hold on power were jeopardized on Sept. 14 with the broadcast of a videotape that showed Mr. Montesinos paying $15,000 to an opposition member of Congress, apparently to get him to go over to the government side.</p>
        <p>Two days later, Mr. Fujimori, after a decade of increasingly authoritarian rule that culminated in May with what many outsiders and Peruvians considered fraudulent re-election to a third term, announced a new vote, but without specifying a date.</p>
        <p>Mr. Montesinos immediately dropped out of sight, and for a week it was unclear whether he was defying the president with the backing of the military or relying on Mr. Fujimori to protect him from opposition demands that he be arrested and tried on corruption charges.</p>
        <p>At first Panama and Brazil were reported to have received and rejected Peruvian requests that they grant asylum to Mr. Montesinos.</p>
        <p>For decades Panama has been a favorite place of exile for deposed leaders from all over the world, ranging from the shah of Iran to, more recently, Gen. Raoul Cedras of Haiti and former President Abdala Bucaram of Ecuador.</p>
        <p>Panamanian officials said the first  solicitation on behalf of Mr. Montesinos came on Friday from Peru's prime minister, Federico Salas. After an emergency session of the Panamanian cabinet on Saturday, though, Alfredo Castillero, a Foreign Ministry official, said Panama had rejected the asylum request to show that it was ''against authoritarianism, fraud, irregularity and corruption, not just at the national level but internationally.''</p>
        <p>But after considerable pressure from abroad, Panama reversed course. Harmodio Arias, the country's deputy foreign minister, said today that the presidents of five South American countries, the Organization of American States and ''high-level functionaries of the United States,'' among them Under Secretary of State Thomas Pickering, had all urged Panama to take Mr. Montesinos, to ''facilitate the democratic process in Peru.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Arias took pains to make it clear that while Panama had agreed to allow Mr. Montesinos to land there, it had not yet granted him political asylum. A formal request is under study, the Panamanian official said.</p>
        <p>At observances here today to commemorate Armed Forces Day, Mr. Fujimori made no explicit reference to Mr. Montesinos, referring merely to what he called ''a week of political decisions of the greatest importance for our nation.''</p>
        <p>But he twice singled out the National Intelligence Service, which Mr. Montesinos controlled for the last decade, praising the agency for its role in helping to liquidate two left-wing guerrilla movements.</p>
        <p>''I have never navigated in calm waters, and that is a story known to all my countrymen,'' Mr. Fujimori, wearing his red and white presidential sash, said in an effort to play down the importance of the crisis. He added, ''It can never be said of me that I am a man or a president who circumstance has paralyzed or forced to buckle.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Fujimori's speech followed ceremonies in which the commanders of all three branches of the military and the head of the national police made their first public demonstration of support for the president since the crisis erupted.</p>
        <p>In his remarks, Gen. Jose Villanueva Ruesta, the armed forces chief, pledged that the military would fulfill ''our constitutional responsbility to guarantee the independence, sovereignty and integrity of the fatherland.''</p>
        <p>But doubts remain here about the ultimate allegiances of the military high command. A majority of the top brass graduated in the same class as Mr. Montesinos, two more are related to him by marriage and most of them are said to owe their appointments to him.</p>
        <p>By law, all members of Mr. Montesinos's class are to retire at the end of the year, including General Villanueva. The officer who would normally succeed him based on seniority, Gen. Carlos Tafur, was forced to step down last week, an action that military analysts here said could pave the way for the appointment of one of a pair of Montesinos loyalists as military commander.</p>
        <p>On Friday Mr. Fujimori sent a bill to Congress that would formally abolish the SIN, as the spy agency is known here, within 15 days of being signed into law. He met another key opposition demand later that day, promising to announce the formal dismissal of Mr. Montesinos no later than Monday.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, Mr. Montesinos's departure was greeted with mixed feelings by the political opposition. A group of members of Peru's Congress released a letter today condemning the arrangement to let him leave the country, saying he had no legal ground to seek asylum abroad, since he was facing well-founded criminal charges and not political persecution.</p>
        <p>But with Mr. Montesinos out of the picture, it now becomes easier for the Fujimori government to negotiate with the opposition over new elections. Opposition parties vowed to boycott a ''national dialogue'' sponsored by the Organization of American States until Mr. Montesinos was fired, arguing that his control of the electoral commission made a clean and fair vote impossible.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
