<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Police Arrest 25 in Connection With Indonesia Bombings</title>
    <meta content="Y25IND$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/25/world/25INDO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233660"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Indonesia-International Relations-US</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Indonesia</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United States Foreign Service</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sims, Calvin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Indonesia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Indonesia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000925T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E2DC143AF936A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="894" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Police Arrest 25 in Connection With Indonesia Bombings</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CALVIN SIMS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sims, Calvin</byline>
      <dateline>JAKARTA, Indonesia, Sept. 24</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Indonesian police arrest 25 people in connection with recent series of bombings in Jakarta, including one that killed 15 people at stock exchange; say suspects admitted carrying out bombings and indicated next target was American Embassy (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Indonesian police said today that they had arrested 25 people in connection with a recent series of bombings in Jakarta, including one that killed 15 people at the stock exchange. The police said that the suspects admitted carrying out the bombings and indicated that their next target was to be the American Embassy.</p>
        <p>They said the suspects were arrested in Jakarta on Friday and Saturday based on tips and information gathered by police investigators. One suspect, armed with a grenade, indicated after he was picked up that he had been on his way to attack the  American Embassy and a nearby crowded department store, they said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Indonesian police said today that they had arrested 25 people in connection with a recent series of bombings in Jakarta, including one that killed 15 people at the stock exchange. The police said that the suspects admitted carrying out the bombings and indicated that their next target was to be the American Embassy.</p>
        <p>They said the suspects were arrested in Jakarta on Friday and Saturday based on tips and information gathered by police investigators. One suspect, armed with a grenade, indicated after he was picked up that he had been on his way to attack the  American Embassy and a nearby crowded department store, they said.</p>
        <p>''The suspects have all admitted to being involved in recent bomb attacks, and one of them said that he intended to blow up the United States Embassy,'' said Superintendent Nur Usman, a spokesman for the Jakarta police.</p>
        <p>American Embassy officials said they were aware of the arrests but declined to comment on them. Last week, the State Department warned United States citizens that American companies and interests in Indonesia might be the target of such attacks.</p>
        <p>In the last week, there have been numerous anti-American demonstrations across Indonesia, during which American flags were burned. The protests followed a visit by Defense Secretary William S. Cohen, who warned Indonesia that it could face economic sanctions if it does not disband violent militia groups that are accused of killing three United Nations aid workers on the divided island of Timor. The militias are linked to the Indonesian military.</p>
        <p>The police spokesman said three of the people detained are believed to be the ringleaders, while the others  either knew about the plot or played minor roles. Mr. Nur declined to provide any details on the suspects or a motive for the bombing campaign, which included attacks on the Indonesian attorney general's office, the Philippine ambassador's residence and the Malaysian Embassy.</p>
        <p>Although the investigation is continuing, Mr. Usman said there was so far no indication that the suspects were connected with the military or the police. There had been widespread speculation that the blasts were the work of disaffected members of the armed forces loyal to former President Suharto.</p>
        <p>The bombings have coincided with major developments in the government's corruption case against Mr. Suharto, the former longtime dictator, and law enforcement officials have said attacks were meant to derail President Abdurrahman Wahid's democratic reforms.</p>
        <p>The arrests brought a sigh of relief to residents of this bustling capital city of 11 million people, who had grown apprehensive in recent weeks as the government appeared helpless to solve the bomb attacks. Last week, the president, frustrated that not a single arrest had been made in the case, replaced the national police chief and ordered the arrest of Mr. Suharto's son, whom police questioned, then released for lack of evidence.</p>
        <p>With Mr. Suharto's trial scheduled to resume this week, Jakarta had been bracing for perhaps another round of bomb attacks. Mr. Suharto's lawyers contend that he is too sick after three strokes to attend his trial.</p>
        <p>In a related development, the Indonesian government, facing mounting pressure from other nations to contain the violence on Timor, began an ambitious campaign this weekend to disarm the militia groups that are accused of killing the three United Nations aid workers in West Timor early this month.</p>
        <p>The police in West Timor, which is controlled by Indonesia, said that by this evening the militias had surrendered 34 automatic rifles, 9 grenade launchers, about 1,000 homemade guns and an equal number of rounds of ammunition. The government has said it will use force to disarm the militias if they do not hand over all their weapons by Tuesday.</p>
        <p>The militias, which are infamous for decapitating their prey, went on a rampage in East Timor last year after the territory voted to secede from Indonesian rule. The vicious gangs continue to cause havoc on both sides of the border.</p>
        <p>''So far, it appears that the militias are being very cooperative in turning over their arms,'' said Simatupang, the police superintendent in the West Timor border town of Atambua, where the three aid workers were killed. Mr. Simatupang said in a telephone interview that since Saturday at least 18 militia groups had brought weapons to the Atambua police station and that he expected more would be turned in.</p>
        <p>But almost no one expects the  crackdown to bring an end to the violence. Authorities have conducted several campaigns to disarm the militias in the past, collecting hundreds of weapons. But the gangs, which are friendly with the military, continue to resurface with guns.</p>
        <p>Moreover, the situation has become critical along the West Timor border, where 120,000 refugees from East Timor are trapped in refugee camps with food supplies running out.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
