<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Noncandidate Clinton's Steady Refrain: I Believe in Fund-Raising</title>
    <meta content="Y25DON$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/25/politics/25DONA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233657"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE MONEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">California</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lacey, Marc</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000925T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E4DC143AF936A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1072" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Noncandidate Clinton's Steady Refrain: I Believe in Fund-Raising</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARC LACEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lacey, Marc</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, Sept. 24</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Clinton's attends 139th and 140th fund-raisers of year in California; has raised approximately $90 million for Democrats thus far in year; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Clinton's 139th fund-raiser of the year came and went this afternoon just as all the ones before it. There was socializing in the backyard of a fancy house. There was a mouthwatering menu served to elegantly dressed guests. Then there was the presidential pitch.</p>
        <p>By the time Mr. Clinton's 20-vehicle motorcade pulled down the long spiral driveway en route to political fund-raiser No. 140, Representative Lois Capps, Democrat of California, had netted $200,000 for her re-election bid.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Clinton's 139th fund-raiser of the year came and went this afternoon just as all the ones before it. There was socializing in the backyard of a fancy house. There was a mouthwatering menu served to elegantly dressed guests. Then there was the presidential pitch.</p>
        <p>By the time Mr. Clinton's 20-vehicle motorcade pulled down the long spiral driveway en route to political fund-raiser No. 140, Representative Lois Capps, Democrat of California, had netted $200,000 for her re-election bid.</p>
        <p>''In my lifetime, we have never had a chance like this to build the future of our dreams for our children,'' Mr. Clinton said, rattling off one of the numerous lines that are now indelibly etched in his head.</p>
        <p>He had delivered much the same remarks the day before at a luncheon in Fremont, Calif., for the Democratic National Committee; at a barbecue in San Jose for the Congressional candidate Mike Honda; and at an evening gala in Los Angeles for the Democratic Congressional Campaign Committee, the group trying to take back the House for the Democrats.</p>
        <p>His words were only slightly different from the ones he used later in the day at a fund-raiser for the California League of Conservation Voters. And the president will undoubtedly offer the same message at a fund-raiser for the New Mexico Democratic Party in Santa Fe on Monday afternoon.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton frequently says this election will be the first one in more than two decades in which his name is not on the ballot. But that in no way means the president is sitting this election out.</p>
        <p>He may not be attending campaign rallies or dropping by diners or union halls, but he is engaged in an unabashed fund-raising frenzy, one with all the intensity of the money-raising efforts of Candidate Clinton in 1992 and 1996.</p>
        <p>''I believe in raising money,'' the president told several hundred people at a reception in Livonia, Mich., on Wednesday night. ''I believe people ought to contribute.''</p>
        <p>Days before, at a fund-raiser in Philadelphia for Hillary Rodham Clinton's bid for a Senate seat from New York, the president displayed his knowledge of the arcana of campaign giving.</p>
        <p>''In order to maximize her impact between now and the election day,'' he said, ''she has to raise more money for her campaign -- in $1,000 and $2,000 contributions; if nobody has given to her at all before, they can give $2,000 -- and for the Democratic committee, more money in so-called hard money. I think all of you know that there's a limit under our federal laws how much soft money can be spent, unless there's a matching amount of hard money. And we need a lot of contributions at a more modest, but generous, level.''</p>
        <p>This year alone, Mr. Clinton has raised around $90 million for the Democratic cause, money that has been routed to the national party, to individual senators and representatives, to governors and state legislators. By Election Day, his take will probably have shot well past $100 million; there are many more presidential fund-raising events in the works.</p>
        <p>As he does with many fund-raising trips, Mr. Clinton mixed a modest amount of presidential business with his campaign duties, a tactic that allows the White House to bill some of the trip to the taxpayers.</p>
        <p>The White House does not keep a tally of the number of fund-raisers Mr. Clinton attends, but Mark Knoller, a reporter for CBS Radio, has logged them one by one since January. Mr. Clinton acknowledged Mr. Knoller's count several times this weekend.</p>
        <p>''You might ask yourself why, in the last year of my presidency, when things are going so well, I would do what is now 138 events,'' Mr. Clinton said Saturday night here at a musical tribute to House Democrats. ''You might say, well, maybe he did a few for Hillary, he had to do that, but why did he do the others?''</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton then answered his own question.</p>
        <p>''This is a strange time in my life,'' he said. ''It's the first time in 26 years I haven't been on the ballot. My party has a new leader. My family has a new candidate. I'm kind of trading in the title of commander in chief for cheerleader in chief. But I like it.''</p>
        <p>He also acknowledges, however, that the heavy fund-raising schedule takes its toll on him personally.</p>
        <p>''The cumulative impact of it -- it's hard,'' he said aboard Air Force One last week, looking exhausted on the flight home from a long day of fund-raisers in Michigan. ''It's a lot of wear and tear, but I like seeing all these people.''</p>
        <p>And they like seeing him. The crowds are always enthusiastic, and the candidates he helps are effusive in their praise.</p>
        <p>Ms. Capps told her guests: ''With all of the demands on the president's time, I am so grateful that he is with me today to support my re-election campaign. Make no mistake, I can use his generosity and yours.''</p>
        <p>At the Michigan fund-raiser, State Attorney General Jennifer Granholm introduced the president with a David Letterman-style list of the top 10 reasons the president has excelled.</p>
        <p>''Mo' money. Mo' money. Mo' money,'' she said, saluting his fund-raising prowess.</p>
        <p>''No one can get people to part with their cash like Bill Clinton,'' agreed Marshall Wittmann, a senior fellow with the Hudson Institute, a research organization in Washington. ''He'll probably play this role for many years to come.''</p>
        <p>But for now, Mr. Clinton has his sights set no farther than Nov. 7, the day voters will decide on the fate of his wife and vice president -- to mention just two elections the president cares about.</p>
        <p>''I have worked harder in this election, I think, than in any election I've been in,'' Mr. Clinton said.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE MONEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
