<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Venus Williams Headed for Gold</title>
    <meta content="25TENN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233708"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SYDNEY 2000: TENNIS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rhoden, William C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Williams, Venus</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dementieva, Elena</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004/Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000925T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E1D7143AF936A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="709" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Venus Williams Headed for Gold</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM C. RHODEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rhoden, William C</byline>
      <dateline>SYDNEY, Australia, Monday, Sept. 25</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Venus Williams (US) and Elena Dementieva (Russia) advance to finals of Olympic women's singles tennis championship (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Venus Williams has not lost a tennis match since the quarterfinals of the French Open in June, to Arantxa Sanchez-Vicario. Williams roared through Wimbledon, stormed through the United States Open and brought a 26-match winning streak to these Olympics.</p>
        <p>Her streak reached 31 today after she defeated Monica Seles, 6-1, 4-6, 6-3, in an all-American semifinal match. The second-seeded Williams needed 1 hour 22 minutes to beat Seles, seeded third. With the victory, she clinched at least a silver medal.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Venus Williams has not lost a tennis match since the quarterfinals of the French Open in June, to Arantxa Sanchez-Vicario. Williams roared through Wimbledon, stormed through the United States Open and brought a 26-match winning streak to these Olympics.</p>
        <p>Her streak reached 31 today after she defeated Monica Seles, 6-1, 4-6, 6-3, in an all-American semifinal match. The second-seeded Williams needed 1 hour 22 minutes to beat Seles, seeded third. With the victory, she clinched at least a silver medal.</p>
        <p>In the final, Williams will meet 10th-seeded Elena Dementieva of Russia, who defeated unseeded Australian Jelena Dokic, 2-6, 6-4, 6-4.</p>
        <p>Williams, going to the net more than in her previous matches at Sydney, forced Seles to rush her shots and often hit while off balance.</p>
        <p>After winning the first set in 18 minutes, Williams led by 4-2 in the second set but began to struggle with her serve, double-faulting five times in the next two games. Williams regained her serve in the final set, however. She served three consecutive aces for a 3-1 lead, then saved two break points with big serves to go ahead by 5-3.</p>
        <p>''To serve like she did in the first set, at 170 kilometers an hour, she was too good,'' said Seles, who is 0-5 against Williams. ''It's discouraging.''</p>
        <p>Williams, who remained in contention for the gold in doubles with her sister Serena, had advanced to the singles semifinal with a 3-6, 6-2, 6-4 victory over Sanchez-Vicario.</p>
        <p>Sanchez-Vicario thought Seles might have problems with Williams. ''The game right now is very powerful and you have to be very fit physically and take the chances you have,'' she said. ''The young players don't give you many chances.''</p>
        <p>Going into this semifinal, Seles had never defeated Williams, who found that statistic troubling. ''I know I never had a victory against some people for three or four matches and it's not that much fun,'' Williams said. ''Both of us play pretty similar. Larger serves, larger ground strokes, a lot of fight, a lot of determination.''</p>
        <p>Going into the match with Seles, Williams had the longest winning streak of the year and the longest in women's tennis since Martina Hingis won 37 straight in 1997. The longest streak over all is Martina Navratilova's 74 consecutive match victories.</p>
        <p>Billie Jean King, the United States coach, said that the greatest challenge for any coach would be putting new vistas in front of Williams.</p>
        <p>Williams may have already found one, however: keeping her streak alive. After today's victory, Williams admitted that the streak was something she had on her mind.</p>
        <p>''These last two matches I've thought about it a little bit more,'' Williams said. ''Thirty-one wins is pretty nice. For it to continue going would be perfect, but all good things come to an end.''</p>
        <p>Williams, who turned 20 in June when her streak began, said her goal was consistency.</p>
        <p>''I'm trying my best to get the No. 1 ranking,'' she said. ''And when I get there I don't want to just be a flash in the pan. Right now is an important time for me to improve and be consistent at all times so I can prepare myself for a top position.''</p>
        <p>On Sunday, Williams defeated Sanchez-Vicario in what some said was the best match in the last four Olympic tournaments. Williams called the match a civil war. She survived 14 double faults to defeat the Spaniard.</p>
        <p>Williams served well when it mattered and made great shots. She hit roaring winners when she had to, reached would-be winners when she had to.</p>
        <p>Williams said the Olympic gold would be a cherished prize in a special year. ''During my streak, I've taken two Grand Slams, and I haven't lost a match,'' she said. ''The Olympic gold would be pretty super, but it's a long way from now.''</p>
        <p>SYDNEY 2000: TENNIS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
