<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Some See Politics in Oil Release</title>
    <meta content="25OIL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/25/politics/25OIL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233671"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE ENERGY ISSUE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Strategic Petroleum Reserve</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Heating Oil</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kelley, Tina</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Banerjee, Neela</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Heating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000925T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E2DA143AF936A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1657" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Some See Politics in Oil Release</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TINA KELLEY with NEELA BANERJEE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kelley, Tina; Banerjee, Neela</byline>
      <dateline>HOOKSETT, N.H., Sept. 24</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Many residents of New Hampshire feel use of oil from Strategic Petroleum Reserve is necessary and practical in light of soaring oil prices and tight winter supplies, but also that it was politically motivated; few say decision will sway their vote; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The first twinges of orange and red had already appeared in the woods when Arleigh Greene and John Noone gathered with their wives, children and some friends today for what they called a wood party.</p>
        <p>The men traded off a chain saw and an ax while the women and children tossed split logs into the bucket of a bulldozer, ready to dump the load into a truck.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The first twinges of orange and red had already appeared in the woods when Arleigh Greene and John Noone gathered with their wives, children and some friends today for what they called a wood party.</p>
        <p>The men traded off a chain saw and an ax while the women and children tossed split logs into the bucket of a bulldozer, ready to dump the load into a truck.</p>
        <p>Concerned about the rising cost and limited supply of heating oil, they were hoping to store a larger supply of firewood this year than last.</p>
        <p>''I'm scared of not getting deliveries,'' said Mr. Greene, a used-truck dealer from Hampton Falls, N.H., who heats his house with oil and wood, about eight cords a winter. ''I want to keep the house warm so the pipes don't freeze.''</p>
        <p>Even though he has heard that some local fuel suppliers are already running low on oil, Mr. Greene scoffed at President Clinton's decision to release 30 million barrels of oil from the Strategic Petroleum Reserve, which was established in 1975 after the Arab oil embargo.</p>
        <p>''I'm totally against it,'' he said, adding that he supported Gov. George W. Bush for president. ''I think it's terrible and 100 percent political. There's no doubt in my mind. I'm for everything that makes it easier for the poor, and especially the elderly. But they had a chance to do this a year ago and they didn't.''</p>
        <p>He went on to quarter a section of oak with three well-placed chops.</p>
        <p>In a state where the presidential race is too close to call and where most residents heat their homes with oil, strong opinions like Mr. Greene's are not difficult to find.</p>
        <p>Of more than two dozen people interviewed today about Mr. Clinton's move, nearly all had a firm opinion. But few said the decision would sway their vote.</p>
        <p>Like Mr. Greene, many voters here called it pure politics when, so close to Election Day, Vice President Al Gore said last week that oil from the reserve should be used to increase supply and reduce prices, and Mr. Clinton followed through, ordering the release of 30 million barrels of the 570 million barrels of crude oil in the national reserve.</p>
        <p>But many considered the use of the reserves as a necessary and practical measure.</p>
        <p>Michael Blake, an air traffic controller from Amherst, N.H., said he expected to pay $500 more this year for heating oil but was more worried about his mother-in-law, who was on a fixed income.</p>
        <p>He welcomed the release of the oil, but complained that it had taken too long for the government to act.</p>
        <p>''It's a ready resource,'' Mr. Blake said of the oil reserve. ''They don't think there's a big enough threat out there that they need to retain that much.</p>
        <p>''The move was not politically motivated,'' he added as he sat in the Mall of New Hampshire in Manchester.</p>
        <p>''I think a lot of people in the Northeast and Midwest suffered,'' he said, ''and the new oil is a good thing. Being good for voters, you call that political? I don't think it's totally political.''</p>
        <p>The Clinton administration insisted that despite the political windfall that Mr. Gore might receive from the decision, the move was triggered by growing concern about the high prices of crude oil and heating oil and the exceedingly low supplies of heating fuel in the Northeast.</p>
        <p>''The main objective was to ensure that we had adequate stocks for this winter -- especially in New England,'' Energy Secretary Bill Richardson said today on the NBC News program ''Meet the Press.'' ''This is about disruption of supply, this is to increase supply. We are not trying to manipulate prices.''</p>
        <p>Over the last few months, the White House had staked great credibility on reining in the price of crude and with it, products such as gasoline, diesel and heating oil.</p>
        <p>Although it convinced the Organization of Petroleum Exporting Countries this year to increase crude supplies, the price of oil remained high. By tapping the reserve, the administration was able to deliver on its lingering promise of cheaper oil, at least in the short run.</p>
        <p>Crude prices plummeted on news of the promised increase in supply. The price of heating oil declined on Friday as well, to 95.48 cents a gallon. Last year at this time, heating oil was about 60 cents a gallon.</p>
        <p>New Hampshire consumers have reason to be concerned about a possible oil shortage. In New England, there are only 6 million barrels of heating oil in commercial inventories, compared with 16.3 million barrels last year, according to the American Petroleum Institute. The six million barrels is less than a 10-day supply under normal usage.</p>
        <p>Further complicating matters, there are no refineries in the Northeast or pipelines in the area, which means deliveries of heating oil by barge and truck can be disrupted when they are needed most, such as during winter storms.</p>
        <p>If the weather turns cold suddenly, the release from the reserves, which should be available to consumers, after refining, by early December, will not be able to shield the Northeast from price spikes or possibly crippling shortages.</p>
        <p>Even if there were political motivations behind opening the reserves, as Republicans contend, it did nothing to budge undecided voters off their fences.</p>
        <p>''I don't agree with Clinton, because now we have a tighter noose around our neck,'' said Walter Fleming, a retired auditor from Merrimack, N.H., who was sitting on a bench in the Mall of New Hampshire.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fleming said he did not believe that using the reserves was politically motivated, or effective in lowering prices in the long run. He would much rather see conservation efforts in place.</p>
        <p>''With these big vehicles and S.U.V.'s, no one seems to care,'' he said. ''No one seems to care until they have a crisis. It could really help this country if people used small cars.''</p>
        <p>Sam King, a wrecker operator from Goffstown, N.H., said he feared that opening the reserves would endanger national security.</p>
        <p>''It's just a bad idea,'' Mr. King said. ''What if you ever need that and it's not in there? I think Clinton should sit with OPEC and see what they could do, before his term is up.''</p>
        <p>Like many other New Hampshire residents, Sue Gray of West Lebanon was able to lock in a fixed price for heating oil by paying for most of the winter's supply in advance.</p>
        <p>Ms. Gray said she thought that opening the reserves was a good idea, but would prefer to see the resulting benefits spread directly to the people who need it most, like those who make under $50,000 a year.</p>
        <p>''This may lower prices by a nickel or dime, where if it could be targeted, it could go to the people who really need it,'' she said, sitting in the mall's food court.</p>
        <p>She added that, as a Gore supporter, she did not care if Mr. Clinton's decision had been politically motivated. And she did not think it was.</p>
        <p>Outside of the Puritan Back Room, a crowded family restaurant in Manchester, Tammie Lambert of Merrimack, N.H., said she was dreading her next oil delivery, which she expected to cost over $400, when she is used to paying $175. The last price she heard for oil was $1.41 a gallon.</p>
        <p>''I'm going to croak,'' said Ms. Lambert, who works in the accounting department of Associated Grocers, as her daughter and her husband waited for her near their van. ''It used to be if you paid in 10 days, you'd get 10 cents off, and it would be like 69 cents a gallon. We could pay in 10 days. Now it's going to take us the whole 30 days. We're trying to put money away for it.''</p>
        <p>Nearby in the restaurant's parking lot, Kris Payton, a medical technician from Hooksett, N.H., said her family had just bought a more efficient furnace.</p>
        <p>''We're trying to squeeze everything,'' Ms. Payton said. ''We've heard oil is supposed to be real high this year.''</p>
        <p>She planned to keep the house at 68 degrees. Mr. Clinton's decision swayed her slightly towards the Democrats, she said, but she wondered why he waited so long to free up the reserve supply.</p>
        <p>George Blushiy of Manchester, N.H., was sweeping in front of a carwash on Daniel Webster Highway in Manchester. A Bush supporter, Mr. Blushiy called the decision to open the reserves an election-year ploy, but seemed to put more faith in the law of supply and demand than in any political tactics.</p>
        <p>''Everything is going to go up,'' he said. ''When it's time for the leaf-peepers to come up here, you watch, gas is going to go up 15 cents a gallon.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE ENERGY ISSUE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
