<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Patents; Trademarks gain attention as passports to the Internet and for a critical vote ahead in Congress.</title>
    <meta content="25PATE$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/25/technology/25PATE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233634"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trademarks and Trade Names</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Patent and Trademark Office</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chartrand, Sabra</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Columns/Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trademarks and Trade Names</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000925T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507EED6173AF936A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1015" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Patents; Trademarks gain attention as passports to the Internet and for a critical vote ahead in Congress.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Sabra Chartrand</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chartrand, Sabra</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Trademark experts and owners are pressing Congress to approve international trademark accord backed by Patent and Trademark Office and Clinton administration; are worrried that Congress does not grasp importance of brands; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN the world of intellectual property, the business of trademarks exists in the shadow of patents. Patent owners are inventors, while trademark owners are simply people who control brand names, slogans and logos.</p>
        <p>Trademark experts -- lawyers, lobbyists and others -- think few people understand that establishing and protecting brand names is a critical part of the economic success of many patented devices or systems, and that trademarks are increasingly important to companies competing in the global, digital marketplace.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN the world of intellectual property, the business of trademarks exists in the shadow of patents. Patent owners are inventors, while trademark owners are simply people who control brand names, slogans and logos.</p>
        <p>Trademark experts -- lawyers, lobbyists and others -- think few people understand that establishing and protecting brand names is a critical part of the economic success of many patented devices or systems, and that trademarks are increasingly important to companies competing in the global, digital marketplace.</p>
        <p>Some big trademark owners are particularly worried that Congress does not grasp the importance of brands. While Congress recently extended the life span of patents to conform with standards in Europe and Japan, it has not acted to adopt similar changes to trademark law contained in a 1989 international agreement known among specialists as the Madrid protocol.</p>
        <p>That agreement which updates an international trademark treaty negotiated in 1891, allows anyone to apply for or to renew a trademark anywhere in the world by submitting one form in one country. The amendment took effect in many nations in 1995, but not in the United States because of a dispute whether the European Union should have a vote as well as each of its 15 member nations.</p>
        <p>Last week, a phalanx of officials from the International Trademark Association went to Capitol Hill to try to persuade Congress to adopt the trademark agreement. The United States Patent and Trademark Office supports it, as does the Clinton administration. The dispute over voting rights is resolved. The trademark association officials said there was no opposition in Congress to the Madrid protocol, but they still were not sure the vote would occur. Evidently, trademark law is not a front-burner issue.</p>
        <p>So they took to the hallways of Congress, seeking to ensure that their bill was not lost in a last-minute flurry of voting on sexier legislation. Indeed, the vote is now scheduled this week.</p>
        <p>''We need to strike while the iron is hot and make sure it moves before the end of this session,'' said Michael Heltzer, the trademark association's government relations manager, just before the officials left for Capitol Hill.</p>
        <p>The International Trademark Association was established in 1878 as the United States Trademark Association and changed its name 10 years ago to reflect its global membership. Lately, the issues that most concern trademark owners -- such as the counterfeiting of designer handbags, or determining the rights to Internet domain names -- have become increasingly international. For this reason, inducing the United States to join the 48 countries already signed onto the Madrid protocol is the group's top priority.</p>
        <p>''Now we'll have a centralized way to submit one application, pay one fee in one currency and get quicker action,'' said Kimbley Muller, the trademark association's president and senior counsel for intellectual property at Shell Oil. He said the new regulations are more important for midsize and small businesses than for companies like Shell.</p>
        <p>''If I get a trademark approved and then I change my address, I only have to send one letter instead of 180 letters around the world,'' he continued. ''Big companies like Shell can afford those administration costs, but for a small company, that could be a life-or-death difference in their worldwide business.''</p>
        <p>If the bill passes, the trademark association would be able to focus more attention on counterfeiting and domain-name disputes, issues important to some of its largest members. Both affect brands that are worth hundreds of millions of dollars to their owners.</p>
        <p>''For Warner Brothers, first and foremost, the concern is for the cartoon characters we protect around the world through trademark and copyright,'' said Nils Montan, a vice president and senior counsel for intellectual property of the studio. ''We have thousands and thousands of registrations, from Bugs Bunny to Fred Flintstone and now to Harry Potter. We spend a lot of time, effort and money in the registration process around the world.''</p>
        <p>Secure trademarks are increasingly important because they are becoming the key to obtaining easily recognizable Internet addresses. The Internet Corporation for Assigned Names and Numbers in December began arbitrating disputes over the ownership of Internet addresses based on trademarked brands. About 1,000 cases have been heard, and 75 percent have been won by trademark owners.</p>
        <p>Controlling a brand name is ''more important when you go into cyberspace because there's no salesperson there, nobody to reassure you,'' Mr. Muller said. ''All you have is the name.''</p>
        <p>If the United States adopts the new standards, the next goal will be to sign up as many smaller countries as possible, said Alan Drewsen, the trademark group's executive director.</p>
        <p>''In many jurisdictions, they're just beginning to appreciate the value of intellectual property,'' he said. ''We have to educate officials in those countries to understand how it affects their own economic development, both for local businesses and for their attractiveness to foreign investment.''</p>
        <p>If the trademark association was wooing Congress in hopes of winning a vote on the Madrid protocol, it may soon be back to battling over a perennial issue -- funds for the Patent and Trademark Office. Congress has taken a chunk of the agency's income every year for the last several years, leaving it with a budget deficit.</p>
        <p>''They don't have enough trademark examiners, the examiners are not getting training, then you have something like the Madrid protocol which is not in the budget, so they have to divert funds,'' Mr. Drewsen said. ''So we've made this a priority till it gets straightened out.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
