<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>High-Speed Web Access Creeping Along</title>
    <meta content="25DSL.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/25/technology/25DSL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233709"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Verizon Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blair, Jayson</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000925T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE1D7143AF936A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1027" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>High-Speed Web Access Creeping Along</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAYSON BLAIR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Blair, Jayson</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Verizon's high Internet digital service, or DSL, is beset with problems; many Silocon Alley executives regard service's sluggish response to demand as one of greatest short-term threats they face competing with top technology companies in other regions (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Kevin Newman knew that his small Chelsea advertising company could not be competitive while relying on slow-speed computer modems. The company designs Web pages that often include streaming video and animated graphics. But its dial-up modems, which received data over regular telephone lines, were so slow that it often took minutes to get online access to some of the Web pages his employees had created.</p>
        <p>So last year, Mr. Newman ordered four high-speed Internet digital subscriber lines, or D.S.L.'s, from Bell Atlantic for his ad agency, the William H. Brown Company. Sometimes, he wishes he had not. ''There would be days I would come in when I had no phone lines and no Internet access at all,'' he said last week.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Kevin Newman knew that his small Chelsea advertising company could not be competitive while relying on slow-speed computer modems. The company designs Web pages that often include streaming video and animated graphics. But its dial-up modems, which received data over regular telephone lines, were so slow that it often took minutes to get online access to some of the Web pages his employees had created.</p>
        <p>So last year, Mr. Newman ordered four high-speed Internet digital subscriber lines, or D.S.L.'s, from Bell Atlantic for his ad agency, the William H. Brown Company. Sometimes, he wishes he had not. ''There would be days I would come in when I had no phone lines and no Internet access at all,'' he said last week.</p>
        <p>That happened after he waited nearly 10 weeks for installation after placing the order. Once the high-bandwidth lines were in place, he added, the service crashed often and there were software malfunctions, and it was often difficult to reach a Bell Atlantic technician.</p>
        <p>Mr. Newman, who is the company's president, is not alone in his frustration with the D.S.L. service from Bell Atlantic, which recently merged with GTE to become to Verizon Communications.</p>
        <p>In dozens of interviews, Silicon Alley executives listed things like Manhattan's high rents and onerous city taxes as the greatest long-term obstacles to the growth of high-technology businesses in the city. But when asked what was the greatest short-term threat to their ability to compete with top technology companies in other regions, the executives uniformly placed what they called Verizon's sluggish response to demand  and its attempts to frustrate D.S.L. competitors at the top of their lists.</p>
        <p>Andrew Brust, vice chairman of the New York Software Industry Association, a trade group, said, ''The time it takes to get a data line and the effort it takes to keep it working is really important to New York and the growth of Silicon Alley.''</p>
        <p>Technology industries are driving  the economies of several regions, from Silicon Valley in California to the Route 128 corridor outside Boston to Montgomery County, Md., where biotechnology firms have clustered.</p>
        <p>Executives of Silicon Alley businesses believe that one of the main factors in recruiting and retaining good companies is being able to assure them that they and their employees can get high-speed Internet connections at home and at work. But it has not been easy guaranteeing that with Verizon, one of the largest local providers of high-speed Internet connections.</p>
        <p>Jack Hidary, president of EarthWeb, one of the first Silicon Alley companies, said he considered Verizon's problems with its D.S.L. service to be an impediment to the industry's expansion in the metropolitan region. Mr. Hidary said it was ''insane'' that Time Warner Cable's  high-speed Internet service, called Road Runner, is doing so well competing against Verizon D.S.L. Cable modems can be faster than D.S.L., but the connections are generally less secure and their speed can be less reliable, which is why small businesses often choose D.S.L.</p>
        <p>''We are not seeing what we need when it comes to the whole process of wiring the city up for high-speed, secure access,'' Mr. Hidary added, referring to D.S.L. ''Road Runner is simply taking over because you can get an appointment faster.''</p>
        <p>Cable modems use the same type of wire that brings cable television programming into a building. In general, cable downloading speeds average about 20 times as fast as a standard 56 kilobits-per-second telephone modem, while D.S.L. lines run about 11 times as fast as a 56k connection. But cable modems run on shared lines that can slow significantly if many people in the same area have the service.</p>
        <p>Silicon Alley business executives  said Verizon's missteps started around 1996, during D.S.L.'s infancy, when the company did not offer  D.S.L. service in New York at the same time it was offering it in other parts of the country. At the time, one Verizon official compared it to testing a show on the road before taking it to Broadway. They say the show never really opened on Broadway because Verizon did not invest the money needed to upgrade its network and wiring or to train its sales and installation workers.</p>
        <p>Verizon officials acknowledge that there have been problems with D.S.L., which they attribute to New York's complicated and aged wiring and the difficulties of being at the forefront of a new industry.</p>
        <p>''This industry is only two years old'' in New York City, said Larry Plumb, a spokesman for Verizon. ''It is moving very fast, and you have a lot of demands, with a lot of people trying to work together.''</p>
        <p>But some industry leaders, including the New York Software Industry Association and the New York New Media Association, a trade group, have claimed that Verizon problems go beyond the complicated nature of the D.S.L. business. They complained  that Verizon's decision to delay  D.S.L. service in New York and the way it treated competing D.S.L. providers have slowed the growth of D.S.L. service in the city.</p>
        <p>And they also charge that Verizon made it difficult for the other providers to flourish, because it ran its own D.S.L. service over telephone wires that were already installed, but forced competitors to put in their own lines, driving up those companies' costs and the costs to consumers. Verizon officials have denied trying to stifle competition.</p>
        <p>Under pressure from the Federal Communications Commission and the New York State Public Service Commission, Verizon promised in May to open up its network of existing lines to D.S.L. competitors, a move that regulators say will lower costs and reduce installation delays.</p>
        <p>Mr. Plumb, the Verizon spokesman, said D.S.L. service should improve. ''It is difficult in New York because of the existing infrastructure,'' he said. ''In other parts of the country, it is not quite as hard.''</p>
        <p>On that point, at least, Verizon and its critics are in agreement.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
