<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Victory for Schumacher, a First for Indy</title>
    <meta content="25PRIX" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/25/sports/25PRIX.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233676"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="AUTO RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Grand Prix (Auto Race)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Spurgeon, Brad</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schumacher, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/San Marino</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Wheel Spin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Race</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000925T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E7D9143AF936A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="956" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Victory for Schumacher, a First for Indy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRAD SPURGEON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Spurgeon, Brad</byline>
      <dateline>INDIANAPOLIS, Sept. 24</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Michael Schumacher wins US Grand Prix auto race; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Michael Schumacher won the U.S. Grand Prix today, making racing history as the winner of the inaugural Formula One race at the Indianapolis Motor Speedway and as the second most successful driver in Formula One history, with 42 career victories.</p>
        <p>The victory lifts him and his Ferrari team back into the lead in the drivers' and constructors' championship standings with only two races left in the season. Schumacher is trying to become the first Ferrari driver to win the world title since Jody Scheckter did it in 1979.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Michael Schumacher won the U.S. Grand Prix today, making racing history as the winner of the inaugural Formula One race at the Indianapolis Motor Speedway and as the second most successful driver in Formula One history, with 42 career victories.</p>
        <p>The victory lifts him and his Ferrari team back into the lead in the drivers' and constructors' championship standings with only two races left in the season. Schumacher is trying to become the first Ferrari driver to win the world title since Jody Scheckter did it in 1979.</p>
        <p>''It's something really, really nice,'' Schumacher said. ''It's the first time we've been here, and I guess none of us expected to have such a great welcome from the American fans.''</p>
        <p>It was the first Formula One race in the United States since 1991. Before more than 200,000 fans -- a Formula One attendance record -- the race started on a damp track with most cars running on rain tires.</p>
        <p>Schumacher, 31, started from the pole position, with David Coulthard, in a McLaren, starting in second place, and Mika Hakkinen, in the other McLaren, in third.</p>
        <p>Coulthard charged off the line before the other cars moved and he took the lead from Schumacher by the first corner. Hakkinen and Rubens Barrichello, who started fourth, maintained their positions.</p>
        <p>Schumacher pushed Coulthard to the limit, and while the race stewards investigated whether or not the Scot had jumped the green light to start the race, Schumacher managed to pass him at the end of the long straightaway at the beginning of Lap 7 to gain the lead. The cars touched lightly going into the corner, angering Schumacher.</p>
        <p>''I passed him on the outside in Turn 1 and basically was by and went really wide to make sure that he cannot touch me at all,'' Schumacher said, ''and I would say he didn't take the tightest line to avoid me touching.''</p>
        <p>Coulthard was then ordered to serve a 10-second penalty in the pits for having jump-started the race.</p>
        <p>''I knew I jumped the start,'' Coulthard said. ''You set a rhythm of when you expect the lights to change. Obviously, you're trying to anticipate. It seemed to me that they were a bit longer than normal, but rules are rules.''</p>
        <p>Between Laps 6 and 9, most of the drivers switched to dry-weather tires, but not Schumacher. The German stayed out on wet-weather tires and built his lead. After establishing a 43.5-second edge on Hakkinen through 15 laps, Schumacher finally made the switch to dry-weather tires. He returned to the track 10 seconds ahead of the Finn.</p>
        <p>Hakkinen started to increase his speed, gaining time on the Ferrari. By Lap 26, Hakkinen was only four seconds behind Schumacher and it looked as if the race was anything but decided. But flames suddenly began to shoot from the back of the McLaren, forcing Hakkinen out of the race.</p>
        <p>''It looks like the engine just failed,'' Hakkinen said. ''I think I could have won it. I was gaining in every segment. I was really good. We have two races to go and it's going to be a fight to the end.''</p>
        <p>Schumacher proceeded to have a rather routine race until he spun out with five laps left and drove across the infield grass.</p>
        <p>''I was a bit too far inside and I touched the grass,'' he said. ''I wasn't going really flat out, just cruising and making sure nothing goes wrong. You lose a bit of concentration. You just drive around like you do in a road car. Once it went, I wasn't prepared to catch it. I was concerned for that, but some people asked me to make a bit of a show this weekend, so I hope that was good enough.''</p>
        <p>He spun the car back on the track to maintain a 14.2-second lead on Barrichello.</p>
        <p>Schumacher covered the 73 laps of the 2.6-mile track in 1 hour 36 minutes 30.883 seconds for an average speed of 118.203 miles an hour.</p>
        <p>It was his seventh victory this season and Ferrari's seventh at a U.S. Grand Prix. Ferrari regained the lead in the constructors' championship over McLaren, 143-133. McLaren started the race leading the series by 4 points. Schumacher leads Hakkinen, 88-80, in the drivers' championship after starting the day 2 points behind.</p>
        <p>Schumacher's 42 career victories put him one in front of the late Ayrton Senna and nine behind the career leader Alain Prost. Senna died at the San Marino Grand Prix at Imola in an accident in 1994.</p>
        <p>Barrichello, in the other Ferrari, finished second, 12.1 seconds behind Schumacher, while Heinz-Harald Frentzen was third. Jacques Villeneuve was fourth and Coulthard fifth. Ricardo Zonta, Villeneuve's teammate, finished sixth.</p>
        <p>Villeneuve was the only driver in the series to have raced in the Indianapolis 500, which the Canadian driver won in 1995. He finished fourth after a tough battle with Frentzen. With only seven laps left, Villeneuve spun off the track while trying to overtake Frentzen, but he recovered to maintain his position.</p>
        <p>''I was really wanting to get him,'' Villeneuve said. ''The problem is when I went next to him, I lost track of where I was. I just braked whenever, and it was way too late.''</p>
        <p>AUTO RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
