<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lazio Extols Agreement To Ban Use Of Soft Money</title>
    <meta content="25LAZI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/25/nyregion/25LAZI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233677"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Archibold, Randal C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lazio, Rick A (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000925T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E7D9143AF936A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1058" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lazio Extols Agreement To Ban Use Of Soft Money</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RANDAL C. ARCHIBOLD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Archibold, Randal C</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Rep Rick A Lazio, buoyed by an agreement with Hillary Rodham Clinton aimed at curbing campaign fund-raising by outside organizations, presses his case on television and on campaign trail that he should be credited with deal; acknowledges that agreement is fragile and depended on good will and influence of candidates and their supporters; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Representative Rick A. Lazio, buoyed by an agreement with Hillary Rodham Clinton aimed at curbing campaign fund-raising by outside organizations, pressed his case yesterday on television and on the stump that he should be credited with the deal.</p>
        <p>But even he acknowledged that the  agreement was fragile and depended on the good will and influence of the candidates and their supporters. At least one group has already expressed concerns about the deal.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Representative Rick A. Lazio, buoyed by an agreement with Hillary Rodham Clinton aimed at curbing campaign fund-raising by outside organizations, pressed his case yesterday on television and on the stump that he should be credited with the deal.</p>
        <p>But even he acknowledged that the  agreement was fragile and depended on the good will and influence of the candidates and their supporters. At least one group has already expressed concerns about the deal.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio, the Republican Senate nominee, appeared on the ABC-TV Sunday news program ''This Week,'' with Sam Donaldson and Cokie Roberts, and played up the agreement at two campaign stops. He is expected to campaign today with Senator John McCain of Arizona, who is one of the leading proponents of campaign finance reform.</p>
        <p>The tentative agreement between the two Senate candidates prohibits political parties from using unregulated, unlimited contributions known as soft money for advertising. Soft money, critics contend, enables candidates to skirt legal limits on fund-raising. The agreement also requires each candidate to ask independent groups to refrain from broadcasting issue ads, and both Mr. Lazio and Mrs. Clinton said they had done so.</p>
        <p>But there were indications yesterday that outside groups not connected to political parties had their own reservations, which could jeopardize the deal. Although the National Abortion and Reproductive Rights Action League agreed to pull a planned television commercial, its director said the group, which endorsed Mrs. Clinton months ago, would await a decision of its board later this week before deciding whether to comply.</p>
        <p>Kelli Conlin, the executive director of the New York affiliate of the group, said that although Mrs. Clinton had asked the group to refrain, the decision would be up to the organization's national board.</p>
        <p>''We're forced to do advertising, and without advertising our message becomes very small and muted,'' Ms. Conlin said. ''We're hesitating to go along with this. We feel we have a responsibility to pro-choice people to inform them.''</p>
        <p>Dan McLagan, a spokesman for Mr. Lazio, said he doubted that Mrs. Clinton was forceful enough with the group, though the deal still stood.</p>
        <p>''It doesn't pass the political sniff test to say that Hillary Clinton couldn't stop Naral from spending soft money on her behalf if she wanted to,'' Mr. McLagan said.</p>
        <p>On Saturday, when Mrs. Clinton offered a compromise to a broader ban Mr. Lazio had sought, she promised that she would urge all these outside groups to stay out of the race. But she drew a distinction between these independent groups and organizations established by Lazio supporters to defeat her.</p>
        <p>And she suggested on Saturday that if a group on one side violated the agreement, then the other side could do so proportionately.</p>
        <p>Asked about that possibility yesterday, Mr. Lazio noted that there was no written agreement between the two candidates, something he wanted earlier last week.</p>
        <p>In the television interview with Mr. Donaldson, Mr. Lazio said the agreement would not have been reached ''unless my campaign showed leadership in not raising soft money, not spending soft money, and frankly, holding the Clinton campaign's feet to the fire on this.''</p>
        <p>A spokesman for Mrs. Clinton, who had no public events yesterday, said it was she who initiated the proposal and criticized Mr. Lazio for helping his party raise soft money for Congressional candidates. (Mr. Lazio said last week that his role in such fund-raisers had no bearing on this race, because he had not raised any soft money for his Senate campaign.)</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton first offered a ban on soft money to Mr. Lazio in May, but Mr. Lazio rejected it as a ''gimmick'' until last month, when he pledged to abide by such an agreement only if Mrs. Clinton first pledged the same. He pressed the issue at their first debate, held on Sept. 13, and again last week.</p>
        <p>On the campaign trail yesterday afternoon, about seven abortion- rights advocates, holding up signs questioning his commitment to abortion rights, followed Mr. Lazio at his appearance at a Korean cultural festival in Queens.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio has said he would uphold the Supreme Court's landmark Roe v. Wade decision legalizing abortion, but Mrs. Clinton and Naral have pressed him about whether he would reject a Supreme Court nominee who opposed abortion. Mr. Lazio, on ''This Week,'' appeared to answer that he would not, but then reiterated his position that he would not rely on a nominee's abortion views as the sole criterion for the high court.</p>
        <p>''Would you vote against a nominee who clearly was going to try to overturn Roe-Wade?'' Mr. Lazio was asked.</p>
        <p>He replied: ''No, I wouldn't. Let me say, first of all, I ----''</p>
        <p>''You wouldn't?''</p>
        <p>''I am going to question that nominee very closely,'' Mr. Lazio said. ''What I am going to do is, I'm going to say: 'Who is the most experienced jurist? Who's got the right temperament? Who's got a respect for precedent? I'm not going to establish a litmus test right now.''</p>
        <p>In the interview, Mr. Lazio also sought to put some distance between himself and Gov. George W. Bush of Texas, the Republican presidential nominee, who according to most polls is behind Vice President Al Gore in New York State.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio said he disagreed with Mr. Bush's suggestion that the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge in Alaska be open to oil drilling as a way to ease an expected increase in home heating oil prices this winter.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio and Mr. Bush have campaigned together only once, at a Conservative Party luncheon on July 14 in Manhattan. Mr. Lazio campaigned upstate when Mr. Bush last visited the state, on Thursday, for a talk show appearance in New York City.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
