<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Mets Have Found A Successor to Mora</title>
    <meta content="25BASE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/25/sports/25BASE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233718"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perez, Timo</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Curry, Jack</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Philadelphia Phillies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000925T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E7D6143AF936A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="906" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Mets Have Found A Successor to Mora</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jack Curry</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Curry, Jack</byline>
      <dateline>PHILADELPHIA</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses play of rookie New York Mets outfielder Timo Perez (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A grumpy Derek Bell tossed his bat about 15 feet across the clubhouse and into his empty locker, temporarily interrupting the solitude of a peaceful morning. Bell had noticed that his name was not in the lineup for yesterday's game with the Phillies, so he pouted.</p>
        <p>About 10 feet away from Bell, Timo Perez, who has played in 1,140 fewer major league games than Bell, hovered over a palm-size videocassette recorder and studied his at-bats. Nothing could have diverted Perez's attention. Not even Bell's flying bat. Perez is still trying to make a positive impression with the Mets, to prove that he has considerable value in October.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A grumpy Derek Bell tossed his bat about 15 feet across the clubhouse and into his empty locker, temporarily interrupting the solitude of a peaceful morning. Bell had noticed that his name was not in the lineup for yesterday's game with the Phillies, so he pouted.</p>
        <p>About 10 feet away from Bell, Timo Perez, who has played in 1,140 fewer major league games than Bell, hovered over a palm-size videocassette recorder and studied his at-bats. Nothing could have diverted Perez's attention. Not even Bell's flying bat. Perez is still trying to make a positive impression with the Mets, to prove that he has considerable value in October.</p>
        <p>The Mets should be sold on Perez by now, after his solid imitation of Melvin Mora. Mora was never more valuable to the Mets than he was in the 1999 postseason, which was basically when his major league career started and why fans started adoring him.</p>
        <p>Perez, whose career has essentially just begun, could be the same type of intriguing weapon.</p>
        <p>Perez can bunt, he can squeeze out infield hits, he can pinch-run, he can pinch-hit and he can even smack an inside-the-park homer, which is what he did yesterday to help the Mets edge the Phillies, 3-2. It was Perez's first career homer and he will take the ball back home to the Dominican Republic. After the postseason, that is.</p>
        <p>''He looks like he knows about the game,'' Edgardo Alfonzo raved. ''He has all the talent.''</p>
        <p>The Mets are making this interesting again. After Glendon Rusch pitched as if he deserves to be the fourth starter in the postseason, after Todd Zeile hit a two-run homer and after Armando Benitez survived a sticky ninth, the Mets won for the fourth time in the last five games. The Mets are slowly showing that they might be past a disastrous three weeks that muddied another September.</p>
        <p>Very few good things have happened to the Mets in September. Perez is one of them. He got his first major league hit on Sept. 1, started his first game on Sept. 2 and surely clinched a spot on the postseason roster this weekend with three hits and three runs scored in the last two days. Perez gives the Mets another leadoff batter, someone who can play each outfield spot and a pest who also brings excitement.</p>
        <p>''He's a spark plug,'' Rusch said. ''He can do it all. He can bunt, he can work the count. He definitely adds some juice at the top of the lineup.''</p>
        <p>Sometimes, teams get lucky. The Mets signed Perez as a minor league free agent for less than $100,000 last March and were so enamored of the Japanese League refugee that they started him at Class A Port St. Lucie. Perez moved up to Class AAA Norfolk and surprised the Mets by hitting .357 in 72 games to earn a promotion to the major leagues.</p>
        <p>Now the 23-year-old is batting .257 in 20 games with the Mets and is a much better option than Joe McEwing or Bubba Trammell as a postseason reserve.</p>
        <p>''He's taking this all in stride,'' Mets Manager Bobby Valentine said. ''He's confident in his abilities. He had the pressure-cooker stuff of playing in Japan. That's not the minor leagues.''</p>
        <p>Perez, who follows the classy Alfonzo the way a 5-year-old trails his 10-year-old brother, speaks Japanese fluently, keeps a can of Lysol in his locker to clean his cleats and has a glove that seems half as tall as his 5-foot-9-inch frame.</p>
        <p>''Little by little, I'm gaining more confidence,'' Perez said through an interpreter. ''In the beginning, I was nervous. I'm playing more, so I'm feeling more confident.''</p>
        <p>After taking two steps forward and unsuccessfully trying to slap a chopper over the third baseman's head in the first inning, Perez took a conventional approach in the third. He smacked a liner to center field that fooled Doug Glanville, who stopped when he realized the ball would drop in front of him and slipped as it bounced off the artificial turf.</p>
        <p>Once Glanville stumbled, everyone who bothered to show up at gray Veterans Stadium for the Phillies' last home game of the season knew this had become a race. As the ball trickled to the fence, Perez motored toward second, his eyes peeking to center and then shifting to the third-base coach, Cookie Rojas.</p>
        <p>''Once I stepped on second,'' Perez said, ''I thought about a homer.''</p>
        <p>There are thrilling moments in baseball, but the pursuit of an inside-the-park home run is baseball's version of hockey's penalty shot. It takes a few seconds, it is about one player trying to score and it can have a climactic ending.</p>
        <p>As Perez zoomed past third, shortstop Jimmy Rollins received the relay throw from Glanville, double-pumped as he tried to pull it out of his glove, and threw high to the plate. Perez slid in safely, popped up, clapped his hands, and looked like a player who belongs.</p>
        <p>''I feel pretty good,'' Perez said. ''Hopefully, I'll be on that roster.''</p>
        <p>ON BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
