<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Decatur Journal; City Winces in the Glare of the Spotlight on Tires</title>
    <meta content="Y25DEC$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/25/national/25DECA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233655"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tires</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recalls and Bans of Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobile Safety Features and Defects</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Defective Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recalls and Bans of Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Decatur (Ill)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bridgestone Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Firestone</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ford Motor Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barboza, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Illinois</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Illinois</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Defective Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Safety Features and Defects</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recalls and Bans of Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tires</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000925T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903EFDD143AF936A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1025" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Decatur Journal; City Winces in the Glare of the Spotlight on Tires</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID BARBOZA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barboza, David</byline>
      <dateline>DECATUR, Ill.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>People in Decatur, Ill, home of Bridgestone/Firestone plant that produced bulk of tires blamed for more than 100 deaths and 400 injuries, say unflattering coverage of story is a blow to civic pride and could hurt efforts to attract business; local press strikes back at what it sees as a drive-by-shooting by national media; map; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For residents here, no news would definitely be good news.</p>
        <p>Six years ago, they had their first encounter with the national news media when workers at the city's three biggest employers went on strike. A year later, the Archer Daniels Midland Company got caught up in a global price-fixing scandal.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For residents here, no news would definitely be good news.</p>
        <p>Six years ago, they had their first encounter with the national news media when workers at the city's three biggest employers went on strike. A year later, the Archer Daniels Midland Company got caught up in a global price-fixing scandal.</p>
        <p>And last November, reporters descended when the Rev. Jesse Jackson marched through the streets to protest the expulsion of six black high school students who had gotten into a fight.</p>
        <p>Now the national spotlight has turned to the city's Bridgestone/ Firestone plant, which produced the bulk of the faulty tires blamed for more than 100 deaths and about 400 injuries.</p>
        <p>People here call their city of 89,000 residents the Pride of the Prairie. Still, all the bad news can be a bit demoralizing.</p>
        <p>''Per capita, we seem to be generating more news than other big cities,'' Mayor Terry Howley says. ''And it's not nice. Some have suggested: Why would anyone want to live here in this snake pit?''</p>
        <p>Of course, no one here doubts Decatur is a fine place to live. But the mayor and other residents say the unflattering coverage is a blow to civic pride and could hurt efforts to attract business.</p>
        <p>Angered at the slant of coverage, the local press has struck back. Recently, an editorial in The Decatur Herald &amp; Review said national news organizations had committed the journalistic equivalent of a drive-by shooting.</p>
        <p>''A further scan of national publications brought out all the stereotypical adjectives used to modify the proper noun Decatur,'' the editorial read. ''They seem to trip off the keyboards of people who have spent all of one afternoon in Decatur -- 'small, troubled city,' 'a once-proud factory town,' 'gritty, blue-collar community' -- anyway, you get the idea.''</p>
        <p>The national coverage has clearly upset Decatur, in central Illinois  amid some of the most fertile farmland in the nation.</p>
        <p>In the 1920's, the A. E. Staley Manufacturing Company, the giant food processor, transformed agriculture when it helped introduce large-scale farming of soybeans, now one of the world's major food staples. That earned Decatur the title Soybean Capital of the World.</p>
        <p>Staley's soybean processing plants -- giant steel skyscrapers that still foul the air with the smell of crushed and cooked soybeans -- eventually lured the Archer Daniels Midland Company from Minneapolis, which has since surpassed Staley as a grain processing giant and now has its headquarters here.</p>
        <p>This is also where George Halas founded the Chicago Bears football team (originally the Decatur Staleys) and where heavy industry has erected many a plant. Caterpillar, the giant construction equipment maker, and Bridgestone/Firestone, the big tire manufacturer, a subsidiary of Bridgestone Corporation, have manufacturing plants here.</p>
        <p>As a result, day and night, this city turns out tires, tractors and mining equipment. During harvest, railroad cars parade to the city delivering  bushels of corn and soybeans to be processed into a variety of products, including vegetable oil and the sweeteners and additives that go into soft drinks and detergents.</p>
        <p>That the city owes its success to farming and manufacturing is evident in the names of a local radio station (WSOY) and some of the biggest financial institutions (Soy Capital Bank, Union Planters Bank and the Earthmovers Credit Union).</p>
        <p>The city is so old-fashioned that it still has no Starbucks and no Borders or Barnes &amp; Noble. And Walgreens goes head-to-head with Huck's Convenience Stores.</p>
        <p>''This is just a little small town,'' said Karen Holliday, the owner of Grandma's, a popular eatery near the Firestone plant on the northeast side of town. ''I wouldn't want to live anywhere else.''</p>
        <p>Residents say they are proud of their working-class ethic and the small-town flavor. And some say the bad press is just another fact of life they have learned to cope with.</p>
        <p>''People here are used to getting the raw end of the deal because they're blue-collar,'' said Chris Anderson, who moved to Decatur from Champaign, Ill., and now is a disc jockey at WSOY. ''They're working people. So I don't think they think twice about it.''</p>
        <p>It was a shock to people at Firestone, though, when a camera crew from the NBC News program ''Dateline'' appeared on the scene.</p>
        <p>''I was driving and my wife called me in the car and said the folks from 'Dateline' were at our house,'' Chuck Hilton, a Firestone employee, told the local paper. ''They just showed up at the house.''</p>
        <p>Of course, residents have not exactly turned their backs on the press. Everyone seems to have an opinion. And plenty of time to share it.</p>
        <p>''At A.D.M., that was just too high up, not the working people,'' Ms. Holliday said, taking a break from making biscuits. ''Jesse Jackson? He needs to let the locals take care of it. And Firestone? There was talk about sabotage but I don't think the guys would do that. They would be jeopardizing their jobs.''</p>
        <p>Most people in Decatur have been generally supportive of the workers at the Firestone plant, which Bridgestone has hinted could be shuttered. Many here -- including the Firestone workers -- do not even believe the Decatur plant was primarily at fault.</p>
        <p>Now, the city of Decatur is trying to do its best to turn the tide. It is promoting its Forbes ranking as the No. 1 best small-town metropolitan area and circulating buttons that boast: ''Decatur Downright Delightful.''</p>
        <p>''We're trying to accentuate the positive,'' Mayor Howley says. ''For every bad story there are 10 good ones here.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
