<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>METRO BRIEFING</title>
    <meta content="25MBRF$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233706"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000925T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E2D7143AF936A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1129" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>METRO BRIEFING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by Anthony Ramirez</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NEW YORK</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: HIGH-TECH PARKING METERS -- The city's Department of Transportation is expanding its program for high-tech parking meters. Known as Muni Meters and resembling small vending machines, they can replace as many as 10 old-fashioned parking meters. For drivers, the new meters mean more parking space because cars do not have to be spaced as far apart to accommodate meter wiring. The department plans to put Muni Meters, first introduced in August 1998, in the theater district next month. About 1,800 regular meters have been replaced by 173 Muni meters in all boroughs except Staten Island; an additional 1,000 regular meters are to be replaced by June 2001.</p>
        <p>(NYT)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: PRAISE FOR KERIK -- Suggesting a thaw in its cool relations with the New York Police Department, a prominent organization of minority law enforcement officers offered praise yesterday for Bernard B. Kerik, the new police commissioner. Lt. Eric Adams, left, a co-founder of 100 Blacks in Law Enforcement Who Care, issued a report card of Mr. Kerik's first 30 days in office, giving him an overall grade of B. Lieutenant Adams noted Mr. Kerik's promotion of minority officers and his willingness to meet with minority residents and church congregations. The group had been sharply critical of Howard Safir, Mr. Kerik's predecessor.</p>
        <p>C. J. Chivers (NYT)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NEW YORK</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: HIGH-TECH PARKING METERS -- The city's Department of Transportation is expanding its program for high-tech parking meters. Known as Muni Meters and resembling small vending machines, they can replace as many as 10 old-fashioned parking meters. For drivers, the new meters mean more parking space because cars do not have to be spaced as far apart to accommodate meter wiring. The department plans to put Muni Meters, first introduced in August 1998, in the theater district next month. About 1,800 regular meters have been replaced by 173 Muni meters in all boroughs except Staten Island; an additional 1,000 regular meters are to be replaced by June 2001.</p>
        <p>(NYT)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: PRAISE FOR KERIK -- Suggesting a thaw in its cool relations with the New York Police Department, a prominent organization of minority law enforcement officers offered praise yesterday for Bernard B. Kerik, the new police commissioner. Lt. Eric Adams, left, a co-founder of 100 Blacks in Law Enforcement Who Care, issued a report card of Mr. Kerik's first 30 days in office, giving him an overall grade of B. Lieutenant Adams noted Mr. Kerik's promotion of minority officers and his willingness to meet with minority residents and church congregations. The group had been sharply critical of Howard Safir, Mr. Kerik's predecessor.</p>
        <p>C. J. Chivers (NYT)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: CLUB DEATH RULED OVERDOSE -- The death of a student who collapsed at a Chelsea nightclub in July resulted from an overdose of the drug Ecstasy, the city's medical examiner has ruled. The student, James Wiest, 21, who was visiting New York from Johns Hopkins University in Baltimore, had been at the club Twilo when he lost consciousness and died a few hours later. Mr. Wiest was the second young person in recent years whose death has been linked to the club, a former warehouse at 530 West 27th Street that the city has been trying to shut down.</p>
        <p>Eun Lee Koh (NYT)</p>
        <p>PURCHASE: CHARTER SCHOOL APPLICATIONS -- Thirty-seven groups have applied for permission to open charter schools in New York State next fall, the Charter Schools Institute of the State University of New York in Purchase said yesterday. The SUNY trustees can grant up to 50 charters. So far, the trustees have approved 17 schools, 15 of which are in operation. Of the 37 most recent applications, 20 are resubmissions from previous applicants who were turned down or who withdrew their requests. The applications cover plans for eight schools in New York City, six in Westchester County and four on Long Island.</p>
        <p>Edward Wyatt (NYT)</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY</p>
        <p>TRENTON: PLANT THREATENS WETLANDS -- Growing as high as 10 feet, the fast-spreading purple loosestrife plant is threatening New Jersey wetlands, biologists say. They estimate that it has taken over thousands of acres in central and northern New Jersey. State environmental officials are trying to keep it in check by spraying herbicides and releasing European beetles that eat its leaves. Eradicating the plant is especially difficult because it is a prodigious seed producer.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>TRENTON: FEDERAL REPORT ON TROOPERS DUE -- Better training, improved paperwork and computer-collected statistics on motor vehicle stops will show that New Jersey is working to reform the state police, the authorities say. The first report card from a court-ordered federal monitor is expected Wednesday, and state officials predict favorable marks. In December, the Justice Department agreed to a legal settlement that included the appointment of an independent civilian monitor for the state police. New Jersey has five years to comply with the consent decree.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>CONNECTICUT</p>
        <p>HARTFORD: STATE GIRDING FOR FLU SEASON -- The state's hospitals may be ill prepared to handle the upcoming flu season, doctors say. Dr. Steven Wolf, director of New Britain General Hospital's emergency department, said the state's nursing shortage had grown worse in the last year, making it harder for hospitals to handle a big influx of flu patients this winter. In addition, delivery of this year's influenza vaccine to doctors' offices and pharmacies has been delayed because of manufacturing problems. Last year, many hospitals were near capacity and occasionally had to divert ambulances to other hospitals.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>MERIDEN: EXPLOSION SHUTS INTERSTATE -- Two people were injured in an explosion involving a tanker truck that shut down Interstate 91 in Meriden last night. The state police said the accident happened between Exits 15 and 16 just after 6 p.m. A southbound car crossed into the northbound lanes and into the path of the tanker, the police told WTNH-TV. The tanker, carrying more than 8,000 gallons of fuel, flipped, caught fire and exploded, the police said. The driver of the car was taken to St. Francis Hospital and Medical Center in Hartford, where he was being treated for multiple injuries. The driver of the truck was taken to MidState Medical Center in Meriden, the police said.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>MERIDEN: SCOUT DONATIONS DOWN -- The Connecticut Yankee Council of the Boy Scouts of America says it has lost about $50,000 in donations because of the uproar over the organization's exclusion of gays. Doug Krofina, executive director of the council, which oversees 20,000 scouts in southern Connecticut, said the United Way in Branford and in Westport-Weston, and one corporate donor he declined to identify, have cut their financing. Connecticut's Commission on Human Rights and Opportunities tried to drop the Scouts from its employee contribution campaign, but the Scouts sued and won.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>CALENDAR  Today</p>
        <p>BIERENBAUM TRIAL -- Jury selection is scheduled in State Supreme Court in Manhattan in the murder case against Dr. Robert Bierenbaum, accused of killing his wife, Gail Katz-Bierenbaum, who disappeared in 1985.</p>
        <p>HEARING IN PAINTING DEFACEMENT -- A pretrial hearing is scheduled in State Supreme Court in Brooklyn for Dennis Heiner, accused of throwing paint on ''The Holy Virgin Mary,'' a painting at the center of a dispute last year between the Brooklyn Museum of Art and Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani.</p>
        <p>HEARING SET IN 1979 MURDER CASE -- A pretrial hearing is set for State Supreme Court in Brooklyn for Madeline Carmichael and her son Gregory Carmichael in the 1979 beating death of her 3-year-old daughter, whose body was found in a closet last year.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
