<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Giant Step After a Leap of Faith</title>
    <meta content="25GEOR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/25/sports/25GEOR.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233699"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Jets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Tampa Bay Buccaneers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">George, Thomas</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Tampa Bay Buccaneers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000925T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E4D7143AF936A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1022" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Giant Step After a Leap of Faith</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Thomas George</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">George, Thomas</byline>
      <dateline>TAMPA, Fla.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses New York Jets victory over Tampa Bay Buccaneers; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After the Jets had gained everything they needed in the final 1 minute 54 seconds yesterday -- a Curtis Martin touchdown reception, a Tampa Bay turnover, Wayne Chrebet's winning catch and another Tampa Bay turnover -- their sideline turned into a sea of green and white, jumping, bouncing and back-slapping. If only you could have seen all of the Jets' faces on that sideline after the rookie John Abraham stripped the ball from Tampa Bay quarterback Shaun King and Bryan Cox recovered it at the Tampa Bay 13 with 44 seconds left.</p>
        <p>Each and every Jet -- in his eyes and in his celebration -- had the look, the amazement, the wonder, the glee of a 6-year-old at Disney World.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After the Jets had gained everything they needed in the final 1 minute 54 seconds yesterday -- a Curtis Martin touchdown reception, a Tampa Bay turnover, Wayne Chrebet's winning catch and another Tampa Bay turnover -- their sideline turned into a sea of green and white, jumping, bouncing and back-slapping. If only you could have seen all of the Jets' faces on that sideline after the rookie John Abraham stripped the ball from Tampa Bay quarterback Shaun King and Bryan Cox recovered it at the Tampa Bay 13 with 44 seconds left.</p>
        <p>Each and every Jet -- in his eyes and in his celebration -- had the look, the amazement, the wonder, the glee of a 6-year-old at Disney World.</p>
        <p>''You got to play the game!'' Bernie Parmalee yelled to no one and to everyone.</p>
        <p>''The best team always wins!'' Aaron Glenn yelled.</p>
        <p>''Hey, 19 who?'' Victor Green yelled. ''I don't want to hear nothing else about Keyshawn Johnson!''</p>
        <p>After the Jets had spun and turned this game upside down, winning by 21-17, Johnson found a few of his ex-teammates, offered a hug, a whisper in the ear, and then scurried off the field. Inside the Tampa Bay locker room, he was subdued. For a man who has plenty of answers, this game, this bizarre loss, left his old Jets -- not his new Bucs -- with a 4-0 record and left him nearly speechless.</p>
        <p>We are not, however, speaking of the impossible here -- Keyshawn did talk. Johnson was asked about the game's start: ''I didn't feel good about it going out in the first place,'' he said. ''It was rainy; I felt a little out of sync.''</p>
        <p>About losing to the Jets: ''It will help the people in New York and the tabloids,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Was he down about Chrebet's catching the winning score? ''No, that's good,'' he said. ''There's more drama for your paper. When the ball was caught, I said, 'We left somebody open!' I didn't know it was him.''</p>
        <p>How frustrated was he with his one-catch, 1-yard performance?</p>
        <p>''I'm not frustrated at all,'' Johnson said. ''I've been in this position before.''</p>
        <p>And he crawled out.</p>
        <p>It was the Jets who did the clawing, scratching and fighting at Raymond James Stadium before a numbed crowd of 65,619. The Tampa Bay Buccaneers, the Super Bowl-caliber Buccaneers, led this game, 17-6, late in the fourth quarter and were victims of another Jet resurrection.</p>
        <p>The Jets won their season opener with a late rally at Green Bay.</p>
        <p>They won the next week against New England with a shocking fourth quarter, rallying from a 12-point deficit in the final 6:25.</p>
        <p>They handled Buffalo last week, but some in Tampa Bay viewed the Jets as lucky, with so many Bills turnovers and mistakes that fell right into the Jets' hands.</p>
        <p>It would take more than luck to beat the Bucs here in this place. Tampa Bay knew that.</p>
        <p>And saw it happen.</p>
        <p>''Things were happening to us that just don't happen,'' said Ronde Barber, the Bucs cornerback whose interception and 37-yard return for a touchdown in the final minutes of the third quarter made it a 17-6 game. ''We bit on that toss to Martin and left Chrebet open in the end zone. We turned the ball over. We gave up a fourth-quarter lead. That just doesn't happen to us here.''</p>
        <p>Not against the Tampa Bay defense. But it did. The Jets did it with 15 points against that defense in the final 1:54.</p>
        <p>''No one gave us much of a chance here,'' Glenn said in the joyous Jets locker room. ''Everyone thought they had the better team. When you have a comeback win like that and you beat a team that is supposed to be great, what does that make you?''</p>
        <p>Good question.</p>
        <p>We know the Jets are unbeaten through one quarter of the season. They have beaten good teams and exhibited remarkable resolve. The Jets play defense. They matched Tampa Bay's defensive intensity, keeping the game close, allowing the offense to win it in the end.</p>
        <p>They are reminding everyone that football is not an individual sport.</p>
        <p>Al Groh, the Jets' coach, could not help but emphasize that point.</p>
        <p>''The power of 46 flashlights can be pretty powerful sometimes,'' Groh said, referring to Johnson's calling Chrebet a flashlight and himself a star.</p>
        <p>The Jets can move forward now. They have stared down two ghosts -- New England Coach Bill Belichick and Johnson, two who were once their own -- and did not blink. Both were overwhelmed by the power of the Jets' new bond and determination.</p>
        <p>''In a sense, it's a good thing for us and for Keyshawn to get this game over with,'' Parmalee said. ''Now we both can keep things in perspective and go on and have good seasons. We put the ball in our playmakers' hands at the end and won it in a game where so much looked so dim. It shows us that we have an amazing team. And to beat them, it shows we have a talented team. I don't know how it gets much better than this.''</p>
        <p>Easy, Glenn said.</p>
        <p>''The Super Bowl is as good as it gets,'' he said. ''This is a baby step.''</p>
        <p>Maybe a baby step for some. But for the Jets, for Groh, this was a leap of faith: that trading Johnson would not crumble his team; that he could take his team out of Bill Parcells's and Belichick's shadows. That the rookie head coach could, indeed, lead and win. That the Jets' players would make it all work and create new heroes. Those are not baby steps.</p>
        <p>Those are huge footprints left here.</p>
        <p>ON PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
