<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Media Talk; Network Newscasts Court Hispanic Viewers</title>
    <meta content="25ABC.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/25/business/25ABC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233610"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Spanish Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hispanic-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Broadcasting Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cbs Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Abc Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rutenberg, Jim</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hispanic-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Spanish Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Language and Languages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000925T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E1D7173AF936A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="513" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Media Talk; Network Newscasts Court Hispanic Viewers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JIM RUTENBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rutenberg, Jim</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Television networks weigh steps to court growing audience for 6:30 evening newscasts on Spanish-language networks; ABC will offer Spanish-language audio track for its show; NBC and CBS consider similar services (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For years, network executives have bemoaned the fact that the audiences of their flagship 6:30 p.m. newscasts have slowly dwindled.</p>
        <p>With a variety of cable television and Internet outlets now offering the news of the day, at any time of day, people are less compelled to watch the evening news shows on CBS, NBC or ABC.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For years, network executives have bemoaned the fact that the audiences of their flagship 6:30 p.m. newscasts have slowly dwindled.</p>
        <p>With a variety of cable television and Internet outlets now offering the news of the day, at any time of day, people are less compelled to watch the evening news shows on CBS, NBC or ABC.</p>
        <p>But one audience for general news is actually expanding: the growing Hispanic population. Indeed, the combined audience for the 6:30 p.m. evening newscast on Univision and Telemundo, the two major Spanish-language TV networks, has increased by more than 40 percent, from an average of 1.4 million in 1993 to nearly 2 million in 2000. During the same period, the three network newscasts have lost nearly 30 percent of their household audience.</p>
        <p>So the broadcast news executives are starting to take notice.</p>
        <p>Beginning next Monday, ABC will begin running a Spanish-language audio track for ''World News Tonight.'' It will be offered each night in 33 major TV markets over SAP, or secondary audio program, which is available on television sets equipped with stereo sound. Though many viewers probably do not even know they have it, the system, which runs alternative audio tracks for programs when provided, is activated with the push of a button on the remote control or TV set.</p>
        <p>NBC executives said they were considering offering a similar service during ''NBC Nightly News,'' with Tom Brokaw. CBS said that it was planning to provide an SAP translation of the presidential campaign debates and that it was seriously considering offering SAP audio tracks for other CBS newscasts.</p>
        <p>Though it seems like an attempt to simply draw a larger audience, the decision to offer the translation, said Paul Slavin, the ''World News Tonight'' executive producer, was made on principle.</p>
        <p>''It's pure gut,'' Mr. Slavin said. ''It is a large population, which I don't think is particularly well served by any of the broadcast networks.''</p>
        <p>Should Telemundo or Univision worry? Their executives said they did not think so.</p>
        <p>''It's one thing to take a story and put it in a different language,'' said Stephanie Pillersdorf, a Univision spokeswoman. ''It's another thing to pick topics that are relevant to your audience. Our only target audience is U.S. Hispanics. That's why we're different.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Slavin said he would strive to insert more segments on issues that are relevant to Hispanics while he is at it.</p>
        <p>Actually, a study released last week by the National Association of Hispanic Journalists found that the number of news segments focusing on Hispanics or Hispanic-related issues increased 35 percent on CBS, ABC and NBC from 1998 to 1999. But those segments still represented only 1.2 percent of the total shown that year.</p>
        <p>A big reason for that increase? The Elian Gonzalez story.</p>
        <p>JIM RUTENBERG</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
