<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Copperbelt Is Test Site For Politics In Zambia</title>
    <meta content="Y25ZAM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/25/world/25ZAMB.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000926T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233641"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Copper, Brass and Bronze</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Zambia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Luanshya (Zambia)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cauvin, Henri E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Zambia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Zambia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Copper, Brass and Bronze</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Metals and Minerals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000925T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E7DE143AF936A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="843" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Copperbelt Is Test Site For Politics In Zambia</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HENRI E. CAUVIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cauvin, Henri E</byline>
      <dateline>LUANSHYA, Zambia, Sept. 24</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Politicking likely to frame campaign for presidential election in Zambia in 2001 is centering on towns like Luanshya, located in country's eroded copper belt, which has suffered more than most at hands of copper's cascading fortunes and government's lamentable efforts fo manage nation's most precious natural resource; copper remains Zambia's most important commodity and its greatest hope for improving economy saddled by enormous debt, high inflation and unemployment; map; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a nation that has seen its hopes for prosperity fade like the luster of a rusting coin, this struggling town in the country's Copperbelt has suffered more than most at the hands of copper's cascading fortunes and government's lamentable efforts to manage the nation's most precious natural resource.</p>
        <p>So it is hardly happenstance that the politicking likely to frame the campaign for presidential elections next year is centering on this eroded expanse of industrial promise. Copper has always been the biggest export for this country of 10 million and, despite the industry's struggles, it remains Zambia's most important commodity and its greatest hope for improving an economy saddled with enormous debt, high inflation and unemployment.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a nation that has seen its hopes for prosperity fade like the luster of a rusting coin, this struggling town in the country's Copperbelt has suffered more than most at the hands of copper's cascading fortunes and government's lamentable efforts to manage the nation's most precious natural resource.</p>
        <p>So it is hardly happenstance that the politicking likely to frame the campaign for presidential elections next year is centering on this eroded expanse of industrial promise. Copper has always been the biggest export for this country of 10 million and, despite the industry's struggles, it remains Zambia's most important commodity and its greatest hope for improving an economy saddled with enormous debt, high inflation and unemployment.</p>
        <p>The first volley in the presidential campaign by Ben Mwila, a wealthy former cabinet minister, will be fired here on Tuesday, when he hopes a special election will put his month-old Republican Party on the political map. Winning even a few of the seven seats the party is contesting could help Mr. Mwila, who was expelled in July from the governing party he helped found, the Movement for Multiparty Democracy.</p>
        <p>Whether the Republican Party -- so new that it is still planning its inaugural convention -- can tap the discontent of this impoverished country and turn it into a political platform will become clear within months. The desperation that has settled over this town and others around it will certainly remain for years, even if Mr. Mwila succeeds in winning power from President Frederick Chibila.</p>
        <p>In his campaign, Mr. Mwila has won the support of other disaffected leaders of the ruling party. Simon Kachimba was a stalwart of the ruling group for many years, first as a council member and then as mayor of Luanshya. Last year, he said, he was forced out after he won re-election against the ruling party's chosen candidate for the mayoralty. Now, he is running as the Republican candidate for the parliamentary seat held by Mr. Mwila, who lost it when he was forced out of the ruling party in July. The maneuvering is all part of an apparent effort by Mr. Chibila, who won election in 1991 and 1996 and is constitutionally barred from a third term, to guarantee that his successor is firmly in his mold.</p>
        <p>With the presidency and 130 of the 150 seats in Parliament held by the governing Movement for Multiparty Democracy, the party is loathe to cede its tight grip on power. And, says its national secretary, Michael Sata, it won't. ''We're winning all of our seats,'' Mr. Sata said in an interview. ''They have no manifesto, they have no plan, they have no original ideas,'' he said of the Republicans.</p>
        <p>Hundreds of people showed up Thursday for a rally by Mr. Mwila in Kalulushi, a township near here, listening intently but applauding sparingly and resisting invitations to join in crowd chant or singing. ''They are waiting to see what he has to offer,'' said Donald Chola, a businessman in the Copperbelt who attended the rally.''People are still assessing him. They want to hear from him. They want to hear what new ideas he has.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Mwila railed against cronyism and corruption in government and then promised to devote more money to building homes and cutting the costs of raw agricultural supplies. His party, he said, is about empowering people. ''This is the time to redeem yourself and redeem your economy,'' he said.</p>
        <p>In a drive around Luanshya and the mining compound that once was its economic engine, it is possible to see much to redeem: a shuttered library, an empty market, one dormant mining shaft after another. Bumpy dirt roads are pocked by patches of pavement as well as bustling bottle shops, as the people here call the neighborhood liquor stores.</p>
        <p>''This is what my voters have resorted to, just drinking,'' Mr. Kachimba said as he left a grocery store that sells little else besides beer. ''You find Zambian bars are flooded in the morning.''</p>
        <p>Even by the standards of the Copperbelt, Luanshya is suffering, he said. Like the rest of the country's mines, Luanshya's were nationalized more than three decades ago on the heels of independence from Britain.</p>
        <p>After years of government mismanagement, Luanshya's mines were among the first to be returned to private hands in 1997. Little has changed. Where thousands of people once worked, clutches of men stand idle. Where once children bathed at home, crumbling infrastructure now leaves them to splash in the waste water still pumped out of the mothballed mine shafts.</p>
        <p>Correction:  September 26, 2000, Tuesday  Because of an editing error, an article yesterday about presidential candidates in Zambia who are testing their political messages on voters in the Copperbelt, the country's industrial section, misspelled the surname of the incumbent president.  He is Frederick Chiluba, not Chibila.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: September 26, 2000, Tuesday</p>
        <p>Because of an editing error, an article yesterday about presidential candidates in Zambia who are testing their political messages on voters in the Copperbelt, the country's industrial section, misspelled the surname of the incumbent president.  He is Frederick Chiluba, not Chibila.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
