<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; Redskins Get Thumbs Up From Snyder</title>
    <meta content="25ANDE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/25/sports/25ANDE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233719"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Washington Redskins</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Anderson, Dave</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Snyder, Daniel</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Dave Anderson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Washington Redskins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000925T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E7D6143AF936A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="983" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; Redskins Get Thumbs Up From Snyder</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE ANDERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Anderson, Dave</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dave Anderson on new Washingtin Redskins owner Daniel M Snyder discusses his hands-on approach and willingness to spend millions of dollars; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE way Daniel Snyder peered down from the Redskin owner's suite at Giants Stadium last night, you expected him to give a thumbs-up or a thumbs-down, the way Roman emperors did in the Coliseum when they pardoned or condemned a gladiator.</p>
        <p>And after an embarrassing thumbs-down loss to the Cowboys last Monday night, the Redskins earned a thumbs-up pardon from Snyder with a 16-6 victory that lifted their record to 2-2 while deflating the Giants to 3-1.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE way Daniel Snyder peered down from the Redskin owner's suite at Giants Stadium last night, you expected him to give a thumbs-up or a thumbs-down, the way Roman emperors did in the Coliseum when they pardoned or condemned a gladiator.</p>
        <p>And after an embarrassing thumbs-down loss to the Cowboys last Monday night, the Redskins earned a thumbs-up pardon from Snyder with a 16-6 victory that lifted their record to 2-2 while deflating the Giants to 3-1.</p>
        <p>As the Redskins, one by one, filed into their locker room, Snyder was there to greet them with a word or a smile. When he wasn't clapping, he was shaking or slapping hands with each of the players and coaches.</p>
        <p>The atmosphere in the Redskins' locker room had to be more congenial than it was after the loss to the Cowboys. During the week Coach Norv Turner was asked if Snyder had been growling because the Redskins had not yet lived up to expectations.</p>
        <p>''We communicate on a regular basis,'' Turner said with a laugh. ''When we're struggling, he wants to know the answer to the same questions the media asks.''</p>
        <p>With his demanding manner, his signing of running back Stephen Davis to a nine-year, $90 million contract extension, and his $40 million collection of free agents, which includes Deion Sanders, Bruce Smith and Jeff George, Snyder has upstaged the Cowboys' Jerry Jones as pro football's rebel owner with a cause: to win the Super Bowl.</p>
        <p>Snyder, the marketing zillionaire who bought the Redskins for $800 million, has inspired a National Football League inside joke: ''He's making Jerry Jones look like Art Rooney,'' the Steelers' longtime benevolent owner.</p>
        <p>Then again, Daniel M. Snyder is just the latest in a long loud line of Redskin owners established by George Preston Marshall, embraced by Edward Bennett Williams and enhanced by Jack Kent Cooke.</p>
        <p>Note that each of those previous owners went by three names, as Franklin Delano Roosevelt or Lyndon Baines Johnson did as president. Must be a Washington thing. Snyder uses just an initial, though he makes it known that he expects to be addressed by all underlings as Mr. Snyder.</p>
        <p>To purge the memory of Cooke's reign, he sold the name of the Redskins' stadium (built by and named for his predecessor) to Federal Express and turned it into a huge orange-and-purple FedEx poster.</p>
        <p>Somewhere Cooke must be steaming about that, although his ego was such that he's probably still steaming over having left this world. At lunch once with the Washington sports columnist Morrie Siegel, Cooke casually said, ''If I die . . .  ,'' prompting Siegel to blurt, ''What do you mean, 'If?' '' Cooke calmly replied, ''My dear Morrie, I don't intend to die.''</p>
        <p>In 1997, apparently to his surprise, Cooke did die. He was 84.</p>
        <p>For all Cooke's bluster, his Redskins, with Joe Gibbs as coach and Bobby Beathard as general manager, won three Super Bowls with three different quarterbacks (Joe Theisman, Doug Williams and Mark Rypien).</p>
        <p>Marshall's teams won two N.F.L. championships, in 1937 (the Redskins' first year in Washington after having deserted Boston) and in 1942 when Marshall himself chalked ''73-0'' on the blackboard before the championship game and the Redskins avenged the Bears' rout by that score for the 1940 title.</p>
        <p>Marshall, who owned a chain of laundries and was married to the Hollywood actress Corinne Griffith, often suggested plays to his coaches, but more than anything else, he was pro football's first show-biz club owner. Back when nobody feared being politically incorrect, Marshall formed the Redskins' marching band, which wore feathered headresses and played ''Hail to the Redskins,'' a District of Columbia takeoff on ''Hail to the Chief.''</p>
        <p>Whenever the Redskins played the Giants at the old Polo Grounds, the band took the Sunday train from Washington to Penn Station, then marched and tootled up Eighth Avenue to Columbus Circle before going to the game.</p>
        <p>After the legendary passer Sammy Baugh retired, the Redskins skidded in the standings and in esteem. As other teams signed more and more African-American players, Marshall signed none. Not until 1962 did he surrender to sociological and political pressure, obtaining the future Hall of Fame running back Bobby Mitchell in a trade with the Browns.</p>
        <p>Four decades later, Mitchell remains the Redskins' constant through the Marshall-Williams-Cooke-Snyder regimes.</p>
        <p>Now the Redskins' assistant general manager, Mitchell joined their front office in 1969 when Williams, the celebrated trial attorney, revived the franchise by secretly persuading Vince Lombardi to resign as the Packers' general manager and move to the nation's capital as coach and overall boss.</p>
        <p>Williams lured Lombardi with 5 percent of the Redskin stock, then a bonanza of about $500,000. And under Lombardi the Redskins, who had not been over .500 since 1955, jumped to 7-5-2, but just before the 1970 season, Lombardi died of cancer.</p>
        <p>Williams's next trophy coach was George Allen, who had what Williams called an unlimited expense account, but the owner soon was complaining that Allen had already ''exceeded'' it. And in 1974 Cooke, who had owned the Los Angeles Lakers and Kings as well as the Chrysler Building, moved in as the Redskins owner, turning his suite at R.F.K. Stadium into a Sunday hangout for politicians and celebrities.</p>
        <p>But now Daniel Snyder is in that Redskin owners' box, and next Sunday against the Tampa Bay Bucs at FedEx Field, his thumbs will be under surveillance again.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
