<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Media Talk; 'Big Brother' Has Not Been Voted Off CBS</title>
    <meta content="25BRO.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/25/business/25BRO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233609"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Endemol Entertainment Holdings</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cbs Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carter, Bill</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Big Brother (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000925T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E1D7173AF936A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="346" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Media Talk; 'Big Brother' Has Not Been Voted Off CBS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL CARTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Carter, Bill</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Big Brother, CBS reality series, is set to wind up its run; CBS is reportedly close to accord with Endemol, show's production company, on renewal accord that would give it more hands-on control of future versions; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''Big Brother,'' the CBS reality series that did not become a hit, winds up its run on Friday, hoping to light some last-minute ratings sparks.</p>
        <p>But regardless of how well the show does this week, the series is close to winning a second life on CBS. Executives from both the network and the show's production company, Endemol, said a renewal announcement awaits only some last details.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''Big Brother,'' the CBS reality series that did not become a hit, winds up its run on Friday, hoping to light some last-minute ratings sparks.</p>
        <p>But regardless of how well the show does this week, the series is close to winning a second life on CBS. Executives from both the network and the show's production company, Endemol, said a renewal announcement awaits only some last details.</p>
        <p>Probably the biggest is over control of things like casting and daily production, elements that CBS executives believe Endemol fell short on largely because it misread both American television and American culture. CBS will want more hands-on control of future versions of the show.</p>
        <p>Even Endemol executives have conceded that the American version of the show played out in ways radically different from previous European versions, all of which were far bigger ratings successes.</p>
        <p>Officially, CBS said it was satisfied with the ratings, which, while never spectacular, always improved the network's previous summer showing, especially among young viewers.</p>
        <p>Unofficially, many CBS executives  expressed disappointment with the show -- but never so much that a second edition was threatened. A new session could be ready as soon as February, Endemol executives said.</p>
        <p>For now, ''Big Brother'' may only be summer programming for CBS -- unless threatened strikes by Hollywood writers and actors come to pass.</p>
        <p>In that case, CBS may want ''Big Brother'' available to fill scheduling holes.</p>
        <p>''Big Brother'' will eliminate one of the four remaining house guests on Wednesday and collect votes from the audience on Thursday and Friday to choose among the final three.</p>
        <p>Friday's finale will be a live show, with the third-place finisher announced first. Then the host, Julie Chen, will enter the house and sit down with the last two contestants before she tells them who gets the first prize of $500,000. Second place is worth $100,000, and third $50,000.</p>
        <p>BILL CARTER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
