<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New York Jails Pose Biggest Test For Health Firm With Mixed Past</title>
    <meta content="25JAIL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/25/nyregion/25JAIL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233670"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Privatization</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Prison Health Services</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lipton, Eric</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Privatization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000925T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E3DA143AF936A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="2183" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New York Jails Pose Biggest Test For Health Firm With Mixed Past</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC LIPTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lipton, Eric</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Prison Health Services, part of corporation that delivers health care to 175,000 inmates in 27 states, prepares to take on contract of nearly $100 million a year to care for prisoners in New York City jails even though it has been accused of failing occasionally to deliver quality care; has grown enormously in recent years by aggressively pursuing share of nation's estimated $4.5-billion-a-year inmate health care market; it has largely succeeded in cutting prison health costs for governments it serves, and it has been dogged along way by allegations of severe staffing problems, poor or unstable management and substandard care; company executive admit occasional failure to live up to expectations, but say problems in some states represent only small fraction of its 125 contracts; company's performance in New York City will receive extraordinary scrutiny as it tries to improve what some already consider seriously troubled system of inmate medical care; map; chart (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was founded 22 years ago by a registered nurse who was disturbed by the slipshod medical care he witnessed at a county jail outside Philadelphia, and who was intrigued by the possibility of making a dollar if he set up his own business to improve it.</p>
        <p>Today, Prison Health Services is the central component of a $400 million-a-year corporation, one that delivers everything from dental work to cardiac care to 175,000 inmates in 27 states and Washington, D.C.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was founded 22 years ago by a registered nurse who was disturbed by the slipshod medical care he witnessed at a county jail outside Philadelphia, and who was intrigued by the possibility of making a dollar if he set up his own business to improve it.</p>
        <p>Today, Prison Health Services is the central component of a $400 million-a-year corporation, one that delivers everything from dental work to cardiac care to 175,000 inmates in 27 states and Washington, D.C.</p>
        <p>Now the company that one executive calls the ''H.M.O. Behind Bars'' is moving to take on the greatest challenge in its history: a contract of nearly $100 million a year to care for 13,000 prisoners on Rikers Island and in other New York City jails. But as it does, some officials and others who have monitored the company's performance say it has occasionally failed to deliver quality care.</p>
        <p>The Tennessee-based company has grown enormously in recent years as it aggressively pursued a share of the nation's estimated $4.5 billion-a-year inmate health care market. And it has largely succeeded in cutting prison health costs for the governments it serves.</p>
        <p>But along the way, in Pennsylvania, Georgia, Florida, Maine and Washington, among others, it has been dogged at times by allegations of severe staffing problems, poor or unstable management and substandard care.</p>
        <p>For example, in recent months in Cumberland County, Me., where the company is being replaced by local authorities, Prison Health Services routinely failed to provide inmates with prescribed medications or dental care, and nurses were sometimes asked to work 24-hour shifts, according to a sheriff's office report issued this month. And in Philadelphia, prisoners with serious injuries or life-threatening conditions sometimes waited months for care or were denied it entirely, according to a physician who inspected Prison Health's clinics from 1993 to 1998 as part of a longstanding lawsuit against the city jails.</p>
        <p>''It was very difficult to go back, time after time, and find that the physicians were still not doing the work they were supposed to do,'' said Dr. Robert L. Cohen, a former medical director at Rikers Island who led the Philadelphia inspections.</p>
        <p>The company's executives do not dispute that they have, at times, failed to live up to expectations. But they said that those troubled sites  represented only a tiny share of the company's roughly 125 contracts, and they noted that there was no shortage of state and local governments who were pleased with their performance, including the states of Kansas and Indiana and Alameda County in the Oakland, Calif., region.</p>
        <p>''There will be complications, there will be bumps in the road,'' said Lawrence H. Pomeroy, a senior vice president at Prison Health. The company and its corporate parent, America Service Group, which is traded on the Nasdaq, are based in Brentwood, Tenn. ''The objective is to prevent as many as possible when they occur, and to respond and correct them quickly.''</p>
        <p>Certainly, P.H.S.'s performance in New York -- it is scheduled to start work Jan, 1, assuming final negotiations are successful -- will receive extraordinary scrutiny here as it tries to improve what some already consider a seriously troubled system of inmate medical care.</p>
        <p>Three years ago, in an effort to cut costs, the city hired St. Barnabas Medical Center in the Bronx to handle all but the most severe inmate medical cases, paying the hospital a set fee per prisoner. While the city saved money, inmate complaints increased threefold after St. Barnabas took over, and the Manhattan district attorney opened a criminal investigation into problems with the care given to more than a dozen prisoners, including four who died. St. Barnabas has defended its performance, criticizing the city's oversight and the poor condition of the medical system it inherited.</p>
        <p>The challenges in delivering prison care in New York City are enormous: it has the nation's second-largest urban jail system (after Los Angeles), with an inmate population that turns over quickly and one with a complex range of ailments in numbers that are much higher than in the population at large. The company's duties will include hiring the doctors, nurses and other staff members who will assess the health of inmates as they arrive and treat all but the most acute medical or mental health problems that arise.</p>
        <p>City officials acknowledged Prison Health's mixed reviews but said they were confident that the company could live up to their high expectations for the care to be provided at the Manhattan Detention Center and at clinics on Rikers Island and the Vernon C. Bain barge.</p>
        <p>''It is a corporation that is willing to put its money where its mouth is,'' said Ernesto Marrero, executive director of Correctional Health Services, the city unit that oversees care in jails. He said the company had proved as much with the recent efforts to improve its performance in Philadelphia. ''What we want here is a way to more effectively provide and improve the quality of care.''</p>
        <p>Advocates for the city's prison inmates promise they will monitor Prison Health's performance in New York intensely.</p>
        <p>''There have been very serious failures in care in New York City over the last two and a half years,'' said John Boston, director of the Prisoners' Rights Project for the Legal Aid Society of New York City. ''Let's hope they will correct these problems and not repeat them.''</p>
        <p>Prison Health's struggle to deliver first-rate care dates back to the first years after it was set up by Doyle H. Moore, the onetime nurse who had worked at the Delaware County, Pa., jail, and a partner. Indeed, one of the early complaints about the care the company provided -- an inmate with leukemia in Broward County, Fla., was given little more than Tylenol -- resulted in a lawsuit that is still cited by lawyers for prisoners.</p>
        <p>Ruling on that 1982 incident, the United States Court of Appeals held that Prison Health's ''intentional failure to provide service'' violated the Constitution's protections against cruel and unusual punishments.</p>
        <p>But if that case was an extreme example of medical neglect, there have been a regular string of problems at prisons large and small. The company has been the subject of criticism in Philadelphia, in Georgia and in Pinellas County, Fla.</p>
        <p>In Georgia, the company was fined about $250,000 shortly after it took over the 30,000-inmate state prison system in 1995 because of difficulties it had in hiring personnel, said William P. Kissel, director of health services for Georgia's Department of Corrections.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kissel said he believed the company submitted a bid price that was too low, making it difficult for the state's expectations to be met. Ultimately, it was felt that the company moved to address the problems. But in 1997, the state nonetheless decided to resume control of medical care for its inmates, and terminated its contract with Prison Health.</p>
        <p>Prison Health also failed to win a new contract in Pinellas County -- where it cared for 2,600 inmates from the St. Petersburg and Clearwater areas between 1992 and 1995 -- after local officials concluded that its management was inadequate and that it had failed to maintain inmate medical records properly and to conduct timely inmate evaluations, said Marianne Pasha, a Pinellas County sheriff's office spokeswoman.</p>
        <p>The company also was said to be partly responsible for the death in 1994 of a 46-year-old female inmate who had pleaded for but not received one of her heart medications, county officials said.</p>
        <p>''There would be one fix put in, but then something else would require fixing,'' Ms. Pasha said. ''Things required constant attention and monitoring by us. It was less than satisfactory.''</p>
        <p>In Philadelphia, where it has worked since 1993 and now cares for about 7,000 inmates in five jails, P.H.S. has come closest to running a jail system like the one in New York City.</p>
        <p>When the company first arrived in Philadelphia, there were signs that it had succeeded in improving care, said Dr. Cohen, who handled the monitoring. But during return visits over the next several years, he documented dozens of cases of inmates who he said had received improper or deficient care by P.H.S. staff, largely because of insufficient access to specialty care.</p>
        <p>In one example, according to a 1998 inspection report, it took five months after the diagnosis of an aneurysm in a 36-year-old inmate for a decision to be made about treatment. At that point a doctor called the condition ''a time bomb,'' but even then, approval for needed surgery was denied, because the Prison Health medical director for Philadelphia said the inmate's release was imminent.</p>
        <p>Many of the problems in Philadelphia, Dr. Cohen reported, had to do with the Prison Health medical staff. He noted that there was frequent turnover of doctors and administrators and a ''simultaneous tendency to maintain nonperforming or malperforming physicians on staff for extended periods of time.''</p>
        <p>Philadelphia officials disputed many of Dr. Cohen's findings, saying that Prison Health had established a ''stable and viable'' inmate health care system and that Dr. Cohen frequently misread inmate medical records. But the company's executives agreed there were problems, and ultimately administrators assigned to the Philadelphia project were replaced and a new team of executives took over.</p>
        <p>''There are always things to improve in any contract, and Philadelphia certainly had its share or more,'' said Mr. Pomeroy, Prison Health's senior vice president. ''It was a troubled contract that needed more resources, more attention and more accountability.''</p>
        <p>A 1999 inspection report suggests that Prison Health was successful in improving the quality of care in the Philadelphia prison system as it found more qualified medical personnel and better treatment of chronic diseases and other conditions. Press M. Grooms, deputy commissioner of the Philadelphia prison system, noted that the city recently expanded and extended Prison Health's contract.</p>
        <p>Most recently, Prison Health has encountered difficulties even with one of its smallest contracts: the 370-inmate jail in Cumberland County, Me.</p>
        <p>At times in the last year, there have been so many vacancies in the Prison Health staff that no nurse has been available to distribute medications or a nurse has been asked to work a 24-hour shift, said Sheriff Mark N. Dion. Supervision in the jail pharmacy was so lax, Sheriff Dion said, that he called in the federal Drug Enforcement Administration to do an audit. The company shifted administrators four times, he said, but was never able to correct shortcomings.</p>
        <p>''At the corporate level, they just could not get the chain of command in place,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pomeroy agreed that Prison Health had had difficulty recruiting and retaining staff for the Cumberland contract, from which the company is now withdrawing. But he said part of the problem was that the jail population was about 40 percent higher than the number Prison Health had been told it would have to handle.</p>
        <p>To be sure, there are clearly any number of satisfied Prison Health customers, small and large, at different sites around the United States. In Indiana, all of the state's prisons won accreditation from a national correctional health group three years after Prison Health arrived, in 1997. During that same time, the state and company claim, Prison Health helped avoid about $25 million in projected inmate medical costs, in large part by reducing treatment outside of the 20,000-inmate prisons.</p>
        <p>''They have helped us to improve quality and to take a more businesslike approach to the delivery of medical services,'' said Robert J. Ohlemiller, a deputy commissioner at the Indiana Department of Correction.</p>
        <p>In Kansas, where the company has worked since 1991, handling about 8,300 inmates, a court order mandating improvements has been lifted and the state's prisons also have won accreditation, officials said.</p>
        <p>Several government officials, doctors and other inmate health experts who have observed Prison Health operations said that the key to the company's success in New York City will be aggressive oversight by city officials and others.</p>
        <p>Even some of the company's critics, like David Rudovksy, a professor at the University of Pennsylvania Law School and an inmate rights lawyer, said they believed Prison Health Services was more than capable of providing quality care.</p>
        <p>''It is not a company I would say 'If you go with Prison Health Services, forget it, it is not going to happen,' '' Mr. Rudovksy said. ''They are established, credible, and I think they want to provide adequate care. But you can see around the country, if nobody is watching from the outside it is easy to let things slip as of course it costs less money that way.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
