<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TRANSACTIONS</title>
    <meta content="25TRAN$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233732"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000925T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE4D6143AF936A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="713" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TRANSACTIONS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
        <p>Pioneer League  MISSOULA OSPREY--Announced the extension of their player development contract with the Arizona Diamondbacks through the 2004 season.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
        <p>Pioneer League  MISSOULA OSPREY--Announced the extension of their player development contract with the Arizona Diamondbacks through the 2004 season.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
        <p>National Hockey League  COLUMBUS BLUE JACKETS--Signed D Tyler Sloan. Reassigned G Greg Gardner, D Jonas Junkka and C Reggie Savage to Syracuse of the AHL. Released D Jeff Ware. Assigned RW Matt Davidson, LW Sean Selmser, RW Scott Hollis, LW Mathieu Darche and C Jeff Williams to Syracuse.  DALLAS STARS--Assigned C Gregor Baumgartner, C Eric Houde, LW Brad Lauer, LW Steve Gainey, LW Michael Christian, RW John Purves, RW David Ling, D Evgueni Tsybouk, D Jeff Tory, D Pat Neaton, D Jeff McKercher and G Chad Alban to Utah of the IHL and G Doug Teskey to Fort Wayne of the UHL.  EDMONTON OILERS--Agreed to terms with LW Ryan Smyth on a three-year contract.  FLORIDA PANTHERS--Reassigned C Eric Boguniecki to Louisville of the AHL.  LOS ANGELS KINGS--Reassigned RW Scott Thomas to Manitoba of the IHL. Reassigned D Joe Corvo, D Michael Pudlick, LW David Hymovitz, RW Kevin Baker, RW Nate Miller and RW Jason Podollan to Lowell of the AHL.  OTTAWA SENATORS--Assigned G Mathieu Chouinard, LW Derek King, F Konstantin Gorovikov and F Chris Neil to Grand Rapids of the IHL.  PITTSBURGH PENGUINS--Signed F Kip Miller and G Jean-Sebastien Aubin. Assigned G Craig Hillier, G Joel Laing, G Brant Nicklin, G Mark Scally, D Brendan Buckley, D Sven Butenschon, D Trent Cull, D Andrew Ference, D Chris Kelleher, D Kevin Magnuson, D Mark Moore, D Chris Newans, D Doug Schmidt, D John Slaney, D Jean-Philippe Soucy, F Eric Bellerose, F Greg Crozier, F Jan Fadrny, F Dylan Gyori, F Quinn Hancock, F Alexie Kolkunov, F Tom Kostopoulos, F Jason MacDonald, F Alexandre Matthiew, F Eric Meloche, F Steven Parsons, F Toby Peterson, F Alexei Podalinski, F Boris Protsenko, F Joel Scherban, F Martin Sonnenerg, F Darcy Verot and F Alexander Zevakhin to Wilkes-Barre-Scranton of the AHL.  WASHINGTON CAPITALS--Signed D Ryan Vanvuskirk to a three-year contract.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
