<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE MARKETS: Market Place; Janus Capital Executive Quits Amid Turmoil</title>
    <meta content="Y10PLA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221467"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Janus Capital Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Craig, Jim</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcgeehan, Patrick</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Market Place (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Market Place</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000810T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DEEDA163FF933A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1036" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE MARKETS: Market Place; Janus Capital Executive Quits Amid Turmoil</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICK McGEEHAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mcgeehan, Patrick</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Market Place column on resignation of Jim Craig, No. 2 executive at Janus Capital Corp, amid public feud between successful mutual funds company and parent organization; he insists resignation is not related to feud (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When executives of the phenomenally successful Janus family of mutual funds started feuding publicly with the management of their parent company last year, some investors feared the dispute would drive out top talent. Yesterday, Jim Craig, the No. 2 executive at Janus Capital, said he would leave but insisted that his resignation was unrelated to the feud.</p>
        <p>Mr. Craig, who played critical roles in building the Janus Capital Corporation from a small money-management operation in Denver into the fifth-biggest mutual fund company in the country, said he had resigned to manage money for a charitable foundation that his wife will run. Since he turned over the reins of the flagship Janus Fund at the end of 1999, Mr. Craig, 44, had been overseeing the company's funds as chief investment officer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When executives of the phenomenally successful Janus family of mutual funds started feuding publicly with the management of their parent company last year, some investors feared the dispute would drive out top talent. Yesterday, Jim Craig, the No. 2 executive at Janus Capital, said he would leave but insisted that his resignation was unrelated to the feud.</p>
        <p>Mr. Craig, who played critical roles in building the Janus Capital Corporation from a small money-management operation in Denver into the fifth-biggest mutual fund company in the country, said he had resigned to manage money for a charitable foundation that his wife will run. Since he turned over the reins of the flagship Janus Fund at the end of 1999, Mr. Craig, 44, had been overseeing the company's funds as chief investment officer.</p>
        <p>He and other Janus officials repeatedly stated yesterday that his leaving should not affect management of the $308 billion in Janus's 23 mutual funds and its institutional and private accounts. ''I feel very confident there will be nary a ripple in the operations at Janus,'' Mr. Craig said.</p>
        <p>Investors apparently were less certain as shares of Stilwell Financial Inc. fell $3.50, to $44.50. That was the biggest one-day drop since Stilwell was formed a month ago when Kansas City Southern Industries, the railroad company based in Kansas City, Mo., spun off Janus with three other subsidiaries.</p>
        <p>Thomas Bailey, the founder and chief executive of Janus, and other Janus managers had pressed the railroad to spin off Janus separately. But the railroad executives rejected that idea in a bitter battle that at one point led them to spell out in financial documents how they thought they could fire Mr. Bailey. For the most part, Mr. Craig stayed out of the matter.</p>
        <p>''This has nothing at all to do with Stilwell,'' he said in an interview. ''That's kind of a sideshow.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bailey, who sold most of Janus to Kansas City Southern in 1984, remains entrenched at Janus, and a company spokeswoman said he had no plans to leave any time soon. Mr. Craig, who was Mr. Bailey's designated successor as chief executive, said he did not expect the company to name anybody to take his place.</p>
        <p>He said he would sell his stock in Janus, which is not publicly traded, back to the company. He declined to say how much he owned, but one analyst estimated his stake at about 1 percent. Stilwell owns 80 percent of Janus, Mr. Bailey owns about 12 percent and other Janus employees own the rest.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for Stilwell said the parent company had the ''utmost confidence in Tom Bailey'' and the rest of the Janus management team. ''We believe Janus has appropriate management in place to continue to produce returns for the shareholders of the Janus family of funds,'' the spokesman said.</p>
        <p>Guy Moszkowski, an analyst at Salomon Smith Barney, said he did not take Mr. Craig's resignation as a sign of continuing management turmoil at Stilwell. He continues to recommend that investors buy the stock, whose price he said had been depressed by concerns about Janus's concentration on aggressive growth stocks and the ''animosity and tension between Janus and the parent company.''</p>
        <p>''It's not a huge event,'' Mr. Moszkowski said. ''If Jim Craig were departing to start his own money management shop and potentially taking a lot of the talent and a lot of the assets with him, you'd have a real cause for worry.''</p>
        <p>But Jon Zeschin, a former fund company executive who is a consultant in Denver, said there was no way to separate Mr. Craig's decision from the hostility created by the infighting over the spinoff.</p>
        <p>''I have to believe that there certainly are some issues there,'' Mr. Zeschin said. ''It seems rather abrupt.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Zeschin said he would have expected the managers of Janus and Stilwell to plan a more gradual transition that would not come as such a surprise to shareholders. The suddenness of the departure, coming when the performance of Janus funds has cooled considerably, inevitably will lead people to wonder, ''Is Jim Craig getting out now because things aren't going so well?'' he said.</p>
        <p>Until the Nasdaq stock market plummeted in April, Janus funds had been shocking the industry with their performance across the board. Investors took notice and flooded the company with cash, prompting the closing of several Janus funds to new investors. To satisfy all the demand, Janus created funds, including its first ''value'' fund, which invests in companies its managers think are underpriced.</p>
        <p>The Janus Fund, which Mr. Craig managed for 13 years through the end of 1999, has swollen to $48 billion. It had an average annual gain of 19 percent while he ran it, but so far this year it has posted a slim loss.</p>
        <p>''The regulation of the flow of the money into the firm is the biggest issue,'' Mr. Craig said. He said neither he nor anyone else at Janus had second thoughts about the company's philosophy of loading up on stocks of the companies they think will dominate the fastest-growing industries.</p>
        <p>That approach made Janus one of the biggest owners of the Finnish cellular phone maker Nokia, as well as Cisco Systems and Sun Microsystems. Those stocks were major holdings of several of its funds, making it difficult for investors to own more than one Janus fund without having a heavy exposure to a handful of companies.</p>
        <p>Mr. Craig said he planned to use a similar investing style in managing money for the Craig Family Foundation, though he probably will buy stocks of companies that are too small for a giant Janus Fund to bother with.</p>
        <p>''I'm a stock jockey and never really aspired to be the M.B.A.-C.E.O. type,'' he said. ''Essentially, I'm trading working at Janus for going to work for my wife.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
