<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Artist vs. Artist, Vision vs. Vision; 2 Groups Battle for Control of City-Owned Cultural Center</title>
    <meta content="10CULT$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221539"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Clemente Soto Velez Cultural Center (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Richardson, Lynda</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000810T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01EED7163FF933A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1818" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Artist vs. Artist, Vision vs. Vision; 2 Groups Battle for Control of City-Owned Cultural Center</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYNDA RICHARDSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Richardson, Lynda</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Performing artists and visual artists battle over control of Clemente Soto Velez Cultural Center on Lower East Side of Manhattan; both groups have decided to fight city's efforts to shut down center independently; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Talk about ugly. The performing artists and the visual artists are barely speaking to one another. Two mediation sessions have collapsed. Accusations have ricocheted off the peeling walls of the building where the artists pursue their muses. In the bathrooms and hallways, the graffiti reads: ''Corruption. Scandal. Violence.''</p>
        <p>In the arts world, passions can run pretty deep. But passions have carved a Grand Canyon-size divide among warring factions of artists fighting for control of the Clemente Soto Velez Cultural Center on the Lower East Side. And the fight could end up in a death grip, with all the artists being kicked out of the castlelike building.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Talk about ugly. The performing artists and the visual artists are barely speaking to one another. Two mediation sessions have collapsed. Accusations have ricocheted off the peeling walls of the building where the artists pursue their muses. In the bathrooms and hallways, the graffiti reads: ''Corruption. Scandal. Violence.''</p>
        <p>In the arts world, passions can run pretty deep. But passions have carved a Grand Canyon-size divide among warring factions of artists fighting for control of the Clemente Soto Velez Cultural Center on the Lower East Side. And the fight could end up in a death grip, with all the artists being kicked out of the castlelike building.</p>
        <p>One might think that the two sides -- visual artists versus a cadre of mostly theatrical groups -- should stick together to stave off the city's efforts to sell their building, on a scruffy corner of Suffolk and Rivington Streets. Although the city-owned building is one of the last bastions of affordable working space for artists in downtown Manhattan, it has gone on the auction block four times since 1996.</p>
        <p>Instead of uniting to prevent the sale, though, the two groups have assembled their own lawyers and public relations machines to promote their separate crusades to claim the imposing Dutch neo-Gothic former schoolhouse where poor immigrants were once taught how to be good citizens.</p>
        <p>Artistic and organizational strife is not unusual at fledgling arts and nonprofit groups. But in New York City, with its severe shortage of space and financing for artists, competition and infighting are often magnified.</p>
        <p>Call it cultural Darwinism. Only the fittest organization survives.</p>
        <p>Performing arts groups and visual artists have coexisted at the Clemente Soto Velez Cultural Center since it was founded in 1994. The building was a symbol of a community of artists from several disciplines sharing turf. (Well, that was the promise, anyway.)</p>
        <p>Now the two sides are prepared to go to court next week when three leaders of the visual artists' group will face eviction for refusing to pay rent to the cultural center for more than a year.</p>
        <p>The center is made up of 10 mostly Latino theater, dance and film groups. The artists say that they lacked basic services like heat, and that toilets froze in the winter. The building's monthly lease is held by the nonprofit organization of performing groups, but the visual artists have submitted a competing plan to City Hall to acquire the building. In the end, both sides could lose out if the city decides to sell the building to the highest bidder.</p>
        <p>''Everybody is cutting their nose off to spite themselves,'' said Theodore S. Berger, the executive director of the New York Foundation for the Arts. ''The animosity is terrible. It has become so bitter because everybody really wants to make this last stand. Instead of making a stand together so everyone can live together, they are fighting each other. It's like a civil war.''</p>
        <p>Last year, the Clemente Soto Velez center was spared the fate of another Hispanic cultural center in the neighborhood, the Charas/El Bohio at Avenue B and Ninth Street, which was sold to a private developer.</p>
        <p>Both sides in the Soto Velez center contend that their own private lobbying persuaded the city to withdraw the building from auction, arguing that it was an important community resource. The Department of Citywide Administrative Services is not actively considering a sale, but is making no promises.</p>
        <p>On a recent night, salsa music filled the five-story building as the center's directors staged a sampling of skits, dance and poetry recitals to an audience of lawyers whose firm has agreed to represent them free.</p>
        <p>''We are here at your service,'' said Orlando Plaza, the center's 32-year-old executive director, before introducing the actors and dancers. ''I grew up in the neighborhood. Gentrification, hopefully, stops here. What we are trying to create here is culture, live culture.''</p>
        <p>Three nights later, as part of a $25-a-plate fund-raiser to pay their own legal bills, a group of mostly white visual artists, called the Artists Alliance, climbed the iron latticework stairwell and transformed the fourth floor into an exhibition of their paintings and sculptures. As South American and techno music played, sushi, chicken, and rice and beans were served.</p>
        <p>''We simply want to have management that works,'' said Shelly McGuinness, an artist originally from Cleveland who is co-president of the Artists Alliance.</p>
        <p>Ms. McGuinness and about half of the 60 visual artists in the building have been on rent strike for more than a year. Their monthly rents are $1 a square foot a month ($240 to $600) for studios carved out of old classrooms. The artists figure they have paid more than $1 million in rent over six years, but have received little in return. The monthly rent for the entire building is $2,200, and part of the dispute is over where the money has gone.</p>
        <p>In an absurdist twist, one of the visual artists refusing to pay rent is Paul S. Clay, the set designer for the rock opera ''Rent,'' which is about efforts to evict young bohemian squatters from a Manhattan loft. Sitting on a silvery rococo love seat in his $600-a-month corner studio, Mr. Clay, a 39-year-old with bleached blond hair and Buddy Holly glasses, said the center's directors did not seem to value the work of visual artists. ''They consider the art studios as a means of making money for the other cultural artists,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Tensions flared last summer when the visual artists produced a detailed plan to buy the building from the city shortly after their rent strike began. They proposed renaming the building -- Clemente Soto Velez was a Puerto Rican poet and independence fighter -- Public Space 160, a move that enraged the center's leadership.</p>
        <p>The center's directors say the artists are middle-class carpetbaggers with powerful connections and are after the building at a time when real estate prices in the neighborhood are skyrocketing.</p>
        <p>''If this goes,'' Mr. Plaza said, ''there will be such an absence of artistic Latino culture on the Lower East Side, it will be pathetic. They have no right to tell us how to run our organization. They have only one right, and that is to pay their occupancy fees.''</p>
        <p>Nothing has helped end the icy standoff, not even the recent resignation of the center's president, Edgardo Vega Yunque, a Puerto Rican novelist and 60's firebrand who is the stepfather of the singer Suzanne Vega.</p>
        <p>It was Mr. Vega, in fact, who had warmly invited the visual artists into the building shortly after he started the center. He even had suggested the formation of the Artists Alliance so the members could be more effective in getting medical benefits, insurance and art supplies. He also saw the alliance as a way to draw the artists out of their self-absorption and into community work.</p>
        <p>But the visual artists now accuse Mr. Vega of misappropriating the center's assets for his personal benefit and letting the century-old building fall into disrepair.</p>
        <p>''It feels like sending a kid to college, then to law school, then having them turn around and sue you,'' Mr. Vega, 64, said with a sigh. He has retreated to his apartment in Williamsburg, Brooklyn, to finish a collection of short stories, ''At a Place of Remembrances on an Island Called Regret.''</p>
        <p>The center's directors insist that they are trying to rectify problems of poor management, but they admit to feeling under siege.</p>
        <p>Mr. Plaza feels that the use of terms like ''corrupt'' and ''raising standards'' by the mostly white artists are patronizing and racist code words. And, he added, the studio artists traditionally have not made the same type of contribution to the community as the center's resident performing artist companies. In performances and workshops, he said, the bilingual children's theater alone served more than 65,000 children last year.</p>
        <p>''What have they done?'' snapped Marilyn Aguirre-Molina, a co-chairwoman of the center's board and a professor of public health at Columbia University. ''When you compare what they have done to what we have done, there's no comparison.''</p>
        <p>Members of the Artists Alliance said they put together a plan to acquire the building because they feared it was on the verge of being sold. The plan entails a three- to five-year lease, followed by the purchase of the building through grants and loans. The group wants it to be an artists' cooperative in which all organizations in the building would have proportional representation on the board. The studio artists are not currently represented.</p>
        <p>''We are a group of smart people,'' said Mark Power, an artist in a paint-speckled baseball cap who makes sculptures out of found objects. ''We can't allow a group of corrupt people to maintain the building.''</p>
        <p>Miguel Trelles, co-president of the Artists Alliance, said his group was not interested in evicting anyone, but simply wanted a democratic partnership. ''It's been like taxation without representation,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Trelles, though, is dismissed by the Clemente Soto Velez Cultural Center's directors as a Latino front for an overwhelmingly white group. He bristles at the center's recent use of ethnic politics. ''All of a sudden it drapes itself in the Puerto Rican flag,'' he said.</p>
        <p>To some observers, the tempest inside the cultural center portends an ominous sign for the arts institution as a whole.</p>
        <p>Carlos Garcia, the executive director of the Charas cultural center, recalls how the Artists Alliance joined protests to save his embattled building last summer, but not the leadership at the cultural center, which took a nonpartisan position.</p>
        <p>Mr. Garcia, who is known as Chino, said that the two sides at Clemente Soto Velez might want to rethink their priorities, as there might be little time left before the city sold the building. ''They have to discuss how to save each other,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
