<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Talks, Exhibitions, Tours and a Festival</title>
    <meta content="10CAL.$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221398"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="CALENDAR"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000810T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02EFD81F3CF933A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="602" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Talks, Exhibitions, Tours and a Festival</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Home Hazards  Park Slope Food Co-op, 782 Union Street (between Sixth and Seventh Avenues);  (718) 622-0560.</p>
        <p>A discussion on environmental hazards found in the home, including lead, asbestos, mold, chemicals and carbon monoxide, will take place tonight at 7:30. No charge for admission.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Home Hazards  Park Slope Food Co-op, 782 Union Street (between Sixth and Seventh Avenues);  (718) 622-0560.</p>
        <p>A discussion on environmental hazards found in the home, including lead, asbestos, mold, chemicals and carbon monoxide, will take place tonight at 7:30. No charge for admission.</p>
        <p>An Architect's Work  BookHampton, 20 Main Street, East Hampton; (631) 324-4939.</p>
        <p>On Saturday at 5:30 p.m., John Pawson, a British architect, whose projects include an airport lounge for Cathay Pacific Airlines, the Calvin Klein flagship store in New York and a house in the Hamptons for Martha Stewart, will speak about his work. No charge.</p>
        <p>Stone Works  Neuberger Museum of Art, State University College at Purchase, N.Y., 735 Anderson Hill Road, (Exit 8E on the Cross Westchester Expressway); (914) 251-6100.</p>
        <p>''Women of Stone,'' a two-part exhibition, opens Sunday with an installation by Barbara Segal, which will feature a domestic setting made of marble. Her sculpture will depict a cloth-covered table and a chair, and framed portraits of family members, all in chiseled, carved and colored stone. It will continue through Oct. 29.</p>
        <p>The second part of the exhibition, which will run from Nov. 12 to Jan. 14, 2001, is an installation about the Israeli-Arab conflicts in the Middle East, by Harriet Feigenbaum, a sculptor. Her work will evoke ruins and classical architecture.</p>
        <p>Open Tuesday through Friday, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m.; Saturday and Sunday, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. Admission: $4; students and those 62 and older, $2; children under 12, no charge.</p>
        <p>A Garden Tour  Blithewold Mansion, Gardens and Arboretum, 101 Ferry Road, Bristol, R.I.; (401) 253-2707.</p>
        <p>Seven private gardens in Westport, Mass., will be open for a self-guided tour on Aug. 18 and 19, from 10 a.m. to 4 p.m. The gardens will include a cottage garden overlooking the Westport River; a plant collector's garden, which mixes Japanese and English design elements, and the garden at an artist's retreat, which is decorated with sculptures.</p>
        <p>Tickets, in advance, $25 (members, $20); on the day of the tour, if available, $30, at Partner's Village Store and Kitchen, 999 Main Road in Westport.</p>
        <p>A Quilt Festival  New England Quilt Museum, 18 Shattuck Street, Lowell, Mass.; (978) 452-4207.</p>
        <p>''The Spirit of a Milltown: N.E.Q.M. Quilts,'' an exhibition from the museum's permanent collection of 25 quilts, which starts today and continues through Oct. 15, will be the centerpiece of a quilt festival in Lowell.</p>
        <p>The exhibition at the quilt museum will include antique works like an 1890's Amish quilt using the log cabin pattern, and a 1935 quilt by Nina Shrock called ''Butterflies.'' Open Tuesday through Saturday, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. Admission: $4; $3 for students and those ages 60 and older.</p>
        <p>Other events in the quilt festival are a show of more than 200 quilts, as well as sales of fabrics and sewing supplies, from Aug. 17 to 20, at the Paul Tsongas Arena, and an antique quilt show and sale at Lowell Memorial Auditorium, from Aug. 17 to 20.</p>
        <p>There will also be exhibitions of contemporary quilts. The Brush Art Gallery and Studios will feature 42 brightly colored abstract and narrative contemporary quilts, beginning Sunday through Oct. 22. Another show, Aug. 19 to Dec. 31, features quilts made from reproduction fabrics at the American Textile History Museum.</p>
        <p>A schedule of quilt festival events, with locations, hours and admission fees, is available by calling the museum, or by visiting its Web site, www.nequiltmuseum.org.</p>
        <p>CALENDAR</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
