<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With California Stops, Bush Presses Bid for Clinton Voters</title>
    <meta content="Y10BUS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221444"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: POLITICAL MEMO"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">California</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bruni, Frank</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000810T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E3DC163FF933A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1065" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With California Stops, Bush Presses Bid for Clinton Voters</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANK BRUNI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bruni, Frank</byline>
      <dateline>SAN LUIS OBISPO, Calif., Aug. 9</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gov George W Bush again campaigns in California, in counties with relatively large percentages of moveable, malleable centrist voters; seeks to lure swing voters who tilted Democratic in last two presidential elections; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Making his seventh campaign trip to California since he won the state's Republican primary early this year, Gov. George W. Bush today spoke a little Spanish, described his education and tax proposals as efforts to help less affluent Americans and headed straight for counties with relatively large percentages of moveable, malleable voters in the center of the political spectrum.</p>
        <p>It was more than a glimpse into how Mr. Bush, the Republican presidential nominee, planned to challenge, or at least seem to challenge, Vice President Al Gore for California's 54 electoral votes. It also illuminated the Bush campaign's strategy from this point forward: to select the places that, and seduce the people who, tilted Democratic in the last two presidential elections but could be made to lean in the other direction this time around.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Making his seventh campaign trip to California since he won the state's Republican primary early this year, Gov. George W. Bush today spoke a little Spanish, described his education and tax proposals as efforts to help less affluent Americans and headed straight for counties with relatively large percentages of moveable, malleable voters in the center of the political spectrum.</p>
        <p>It was more than a glimpse into how Mr. Bush, the Republican presidential nominee, planned to challenge, or at least seem to challenge, Vice President Al Gore for California's 54 electoral votes. It also illuminated the Bush campaign's strategy from this point forward: to select the places that, and seduce the people who, tilted Democratic in the last two presidential elections but could be made to lean in the other direction this time around.</p>
        <p>''El sueno Americano es para todos,'' Mr. Bush said at the train station in Oxnard, north of Los Angeles, where he began a ride on the rails up the California coast. The Texas governor was saying that the American dream is for everybody.</p>
        <p>But he was speaking primarily to the broad, deep pool of swing voters in Ventura County and elsewhere around the country. And he was telling them -- as much with the accent as the content of his words -- that they should feel comfortable voting for him.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush has been doing that since the beginning of his campaign, but his trip to the West Coast this week, like the journeys he took in and out of the Republican National Convention, represents an especially pointed, carefully aimed restating of his message.</p>
        <p>California, where Mr. Bush planned to spend today and Thursday, and Oregon and Washington, where he was scheduled to travel later this week, are states where President Clinton prevailed in 1992 and 1996, but where demographic information and some early polling suggest that Mr. Bush stands a good, decent or at least plausible chance of victory. His itinerary this week reflects the Bush campaign's desire to look beyond the typical chain of Midwestern states that teeter between Democrats and Republicans and put new places into serious play.</p>
        <p>These places have in common an opportunity-rich supply of ''weakly linked Republicans, weakly linked Democrats and independent voters whose allegiances are up for grabs,'' said Karl Rove, the Bush campaign's chief strategist. And what the Bush campaign is doing is issuing a variety of invitations to these fickle political consumers.</p>
        <p>Over the weekend, as Mr. Bush rode the rails through Pennsylvania, Ohio, Michigan and Illinois, he repeatedly praised the hard work of members of labor unions, made a point of having a former Democrat introduce him at one event and, at that same event, rendered a blunt, broad statement about just how big he wanted to spread his tent.</p>
        <p>''This is a campaign that welcomes Democrats,'' Mr. Bush said on Saturday in Durand, Mich., southwest of Flint. ''Our message speaks to working people from all walks of life.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush has found another way to express that sentiment this week: on Thursday through Saturday, he will campaign with Senator John McCain at his side. In the Republican primaries, Mr. McCain proved to be a powerful lure for moderate Republicans, independents and moderate Democrats, a centrist band of voters prevalent on the West Coast.</p>
        <p>''McCain is reassuring to swing and independent voters,'' Mr. Rove said. ''Bush ultimately has to make the sale, but McCain helps.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore, too, is reaching hard for the center, as his selection of Senator Joseph I. Lieberman of Connecticut to be his running mate demonstrated. Mr. Bush spoke publicly for the first time today about that choice, and heartily praised it.</p>
        <p>''I think he's man of integrity,'' Mr. Bush said on the tarmac at the naval air station in Point Mugu, where his campaign plane landed late this morning after a flight from Austin, Tex.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Bush was asked whether Mr. Lieberman's reputation for moral rectitude would make it more difficult for Republicans to link Mr. Gore to President Clinton's behavior in office, Mr. Bush implied that it would not.</p>
        <p>''The race is between Al Gore and me,'' he said, directing the spotlight away from Mr. Lieberman and toward Mr. Gore.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush also suggested that Mr. Gore would have to do more to separate himself from the president than choose a running mate who had harshly criticized Mr. Clinton.</p>
        <p>''If Vice President Gore wants to say, 'I'm different from President Clinton,' let him explain how,'' Mr. Bush said.</p>
        <p>''I'm saying we'll set a new tone in Washington,'' he added, referring to himself and his own running mate, Dick Cheney, the former defense secretary.</p>
        <p>Later, in an interview with Fox television news, Mr. Bush fielded a question about whether anti-Semitism might hurt the Gore-Lieberman ticket by saying, ''I believe America has grown beyond that.''</p>
        <p>''There's going to be some people,'' Mr. Bush added, ''who are going to criticize Senator Lieberman because of his religion, and if they're in my campaign, I'll just ask them to leave.'' Mr. Lieberman is the first Jew on a major party's presidential ticket.</p>
        <p>In setting out for California this morning, Mr. Bush was trying both to end several days during which he ceded the news media spotlight to Mr. Gore and Mr. Lieberman and to crash, or at least pre-empt, Mr. Gore's imminent party here. The Democratic National Convention takes place Monday through Thursday in Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's desire to get at least some time on local television news broadcasts here was evident in the choreography of his event. Toward the end of the rally in Oxnard, someone released dozens of white doves into the air. Later in the day, Mr. Bush took a walking tour through Guadalupe, a tiny, dusty town whose Hispanic residents swarmed around him, seemingly in disbelief that a presidential candidate had come their way.</p>
        <p>In all his planned events this week, Mr. Bush will appeal strongly to swing voters by appearing in places where Republicans do not always go, tallying endorsements that Republicans do not always get and framing his proposals in populist terms, with so-called average Americans on hand to help him make his case.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: POLITICAL MEMO</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
