<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="10DIGE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221466"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000810T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902EFDA163FF933A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1121" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Phone Strike Drags On As Contract Talks Continue  As Verizon Communications prepares to enter its fifth day of bargaining with its striking unions, the question arises: Has Verizon gotten more with this strike than it bargained for?</p>
        <p>As the walkout by 86,000 workers of Verizon, the nation's largest telecommunications employer, has developed into one of the most unruly strikes in years, doubts are growing over the company's preparation for the contract talks and its handling of the strike. [Page C8.]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Phone Strike Drags On As Contract Talks Continue  As Verizon Communications prepares to enter its fifth day of bargaining with its striking unions, the question arises: Has Verizon gotten more with this strike than it bargained for?</p>
        <p>As the walkout by 86,000 workers of Verizon, the nation's largest telecommunications employer, has developed into one of the most unruly strikes in years, doubts are growing over the company's preparation for the contract talks and its handling of the strike. [Page C8.]</p>
        <p>'Dot-Com' Merger Excites Investors  Phone.com and Software.com, two relatively small, money-losing software companies, announced they were merging, and investors responded by adding $2.6 billion to their combined market values. The ''.com'' suffix in both companies' names is somewhat misleading, as neither does business through its Web site. [C20.]</p>
        <p>DNA Used to Make Tiny Motors  A team of researchers at Bell Laboratories and Oxford University has fashioned molecular-sized motors out of the chemical that stores the genetic code, portending a possible role for DNA beyond biology. The development is part of an effort, still in its infancy, to harness DNA as a structural and electronic material that might one day be used to make ultra-tiny computers or mechanical devices, like a robot that could cruise through the bloodstream to repair an injury. [C5.]</p>
        <p>Ex-Broker Accused of Murder Plot  Stuart Winkler, a former top executive for a small brokerage company in New Jersey who is awaiting trial on charges that he bilked investors of $100 million, was accused of hiring a fellow prisoner to kill the judge who has kept him behind bars since April. [B3.]</p>
        <p>ABC to Reprimand Correspondent  ABC News executives said they would reprimand John Stossel, the news correspondent, for a report challenging the assumed benefits of organic food that was based in part on evidence that did not exist. The producer of the segment, David W. Fitzpatrick, is to be suspended without pay for one month. [C20.]</p>
        <p>Advanced Micro Readies New Chip  Advanced Micro Devices plans to release details of its new 64-bit processor today, a chip that is intended to compete head on with Intel's forthcoming Itanium. Advanced Micro said it expected the new chip to help it gain sales in the workstation and server market. [C20.]</p>
        <p>Barclays in Talks to Buy Lender  Britain's third largest bank, Barclays, said it was negotiating to acquire Woolwich, a leading British mortgage lender, for about $:5.5 billion or $8.3 billion. Barclays, which only a few years ago was one of Britain's most troubled banks, has been on a tear over the last year under its chief executive, Matthew Barrett, who took the bank's top job about 10 months ago. [C3.]</p>
        <p>Carmakers to Add Stability Systems  Ford Motor said it would offer computerized stability systems as an option on all of its sport utility vehicles and pickups by the 2005 model year to reduce the frequency of rollovers. General Motors responded by saying that the Cadillac Escalade full-sized sport utility vehicle will be equipped with the stability system as standard equipment this autumn. [C4.]</p>
        <p>Report Suggests Brazilian Recovery  Brazil's economy grew 3.92 percent in the second quarter compared with the period a year earlier, the government said in a report, signaling that the recovery from a currency crisis in early 1999 was accelerating. [C3.]</p>
        <p>Tracking Who Is Getting Richer  The rich are getting richer, and the poor are getting poorer, right? It will be a familiar refrain this election year. But what if increasing inequality is mostly a myth -- an artifact of misleading data and changing lifestyles? What if just about everyone is getting richer? Virginia Postrel: Economic Scene. [C2.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
