<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Woods Decides to Play A Week Before a Major</title>
    <meta content="10GOLF$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/10/sports/10GOLF.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221431"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Buick Open (Golf)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brown, Clifton</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Woods, Tiger</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000810T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E4DD163FF933A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="872" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Woods Decides to Play A Week Before a Major</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFTON BROWN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brown, Clifton</byline>
      <dateline>GRAND BLANC, Mich., Aug. 9</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses outlook for Buick Open golf championship; Tiger Woods will compete (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tiger Woods is taking a different approach this week, but he wants the same results.</p>
        <p>Instead of practicing in private before the P.G.A. Championship next week, Woods returns to action Thursday in the Buick Open at Warwick Hills Golf and Country Club. It is the first time since the 1998 P.G.A. Championship that Woods has played the week before a major championship. And considering his recent domination, Woods's departure from the norm is an interesting decision.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Tiger Woods is taking a different approach this week, but he wants the same results.</p>
        <p>Instead of practicing in private before the P.G.A. Championship next week, Woods returns to action Thursday in the Buick Open at Warwick Hills Golf and Country Club. It is the first time since the 1998 P.G.A. Championship that Woods has played the week before a major championship. And considering his recent domination, Woods's departure from the norm is an interesting decision.</p>
        <p>He did not play the week before this year's United States Open, and he won by 15 strokes. He did not play the week before last month's British Open, and he won by eight strokes.</p>
        <p>Why prepare differently for the P.G.A. Championship, where Woods will try to win his third consecutive major? There are several reasons behind Woods's decision to play this week. One, he likes the golf course. Two, he wanted to play at least once between the British Open and the P.G.A. Championship, so he could adjust to tournament conditions.</p>
        <p>That Woods has a sponsorship agreement with Buick did not guarantee his appearance, because the contract does not require him to play all Buick events, or even a certain number of Buick events. But when Woods decided to play this week, tournament sponsors were understandably thrilled. For the tournament, getting the world's No. 1 player was like getting a Christmas present in August.</p>
        <p>Woods will step on the first tee Thursday and hope to pick up where he left off in St. Andrews, Scotland. ''I came here to win this tournament,'' said Woods, who has already won six times this year, and three of his last four starts. ''I'm looking forward to getting back into competition.''</p>
        <p>The field this week features five of the top 10 players in the world ranking: Woods, Davis Love III, Phil Mickelson, Hal Sutton and Vijay Singh. Among those taking the week off are David Duval, who is still bothered by a back injury, and Ernie Els, the world's No. 2-ranked player who is resting after his victory Sunday in The International.</p>
        <p>Woods's presence makes the Buick Open a huge event here in the Detroit-Flint area, as evidenced by the crowds that followed him all day. Fans were watching at 7 a.m. when Woods teed off in the pro-am. They were watching this afternoon when he hit balls on the driving range. And they will be watching Thursday morning, when Woods hopes to send a buzz through the locker room by posting a low first-round score.</p>
        <p>It has reached the point where his name on the leader board can be an intimidating presence that works to his advantage. While Woods does not openly acknowledge his ability to rattle opponents, he is not opposed to the idea. ''The only way to increase the intimidation factor, if it does exist, is to play well and to win tournaments,'' Woods said. ''Simple as that. And fortunately, I have won my share of tournaments.''</p>
        <p>Singh, who won the Buick Open in 1997, was looking forward to this week's challenge, but he cautioned against worrying too much about Woods.</p>
        <p>''I think too many players are getting caught up in what Tiger is doing,'' said Singh, this year's Masters champion. ''If you're playing with Tiger and you start thinking about how well he's playing, it can get into your head. I think that showed a little at the U.S. Open. He was the only guy who was under par, and he won by 15 strokes.''</p>
        <p>If Woods wins the P.G.A. Championship next week, he would become the first player to win three majors in one year since Ben Hogan in 1953. Woods traveled to Louisville, Ky., on Tuesday to play at the Valhalla Golf Club, the site of next week's P.G.A. Championship and a course that Woods was unfamiliar with. He left with a positive first impression.</p>
        <p>''You're going to have to use your driver quite a bit next week, so this course is wonderful preparation,'' he said. ''Valhalla is a typical Jack Nicklaus course, where he gives you room off the tee but makes it a little more challenging around the greens. You have to hit precise shots.''</p>
        <p>For Woods, hitting precise shots has not been a problem, and after a two-week break, he felt rejuvenated for a coming hectic schedule. Woods will play three consecutive events: the Buick Open, the P.G.A. Championship and the WGC-NEC Invitational in Akron (Aug. 24 to Aug. 27). But for Woods, returning to work meant another chance to win. He scoffed at the notion that he would ever tire of golf.</p>
        <p>''I don't think I've ever seen anyone love a job and get burned out,'' Woods said. ''As you get better and learn, you start to love it even more.''</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
