<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lieberman's Political Life an Open Book</title>
    <meta content="Y10AUT$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221470"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE CONNECTICUT SENATOR"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vice Presidents and Vice Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mitchell, Alison</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lieberman, Joseph I (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bailey, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/Joseph I Lieberman</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vice Presidents and Vice Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000810T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E7D9163FF933A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1263" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lieberman's Political Life an Open Book</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALISON MITCHELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mitchell, Alison</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Aug. 9</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>College thesis Sen Joseph I Lieberman wrote on Connecticut political boss John Bailey, which he later turned into two books, also led him to summer job at Democratic National Committee, which Bailey headed; Lieberman has written five books that give insight into his range of interests, ways of thinking and forces that shaped his life (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If politics is the art of seeing your opportunities and taking them, Joseph I. Lieberman seized his first opportunity by writing a book.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Lieberman, the son of a liquor store owner, was a senior at Yale University with a desire to run for office, he wrote his college thesis on the quintessential political boss John Bailey of Connecticut.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If politics is the art of seeing your opportunities and taking them, Joseph I. Lieberman seized his first opportunity by writing a book.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Lieberman, the son of a liquor store owner, was a senior at Yale University with a desire to run for office, he wrote his college thesis on the quintessential political boss John Bailey of Connecticut.</p>
        <p>''I could see that there was no better way to learn about the history and intricacies of Connecticut's government than to study John Bailey,'' Mr. Lieberman wrote more than three decades later in his memoir, ''In Praise of Public Life.'' ''The hours I spent interviewing him that winter were priceless, my own private course in political science.''</p>
        <p>The admiring thesis turned into two books, ''The Power Broker,'' published in 1966 and a reworked version, ''The Legacy,'' updated and published in 1981. But, as importantly, the thesis led Mr. Lieberman to a ringside seat in politics, a summer job at the Democratic National Committee, which Mr. Bailey headed during the presidencies of John F. Kennedy and Lyndon B. Johnson.</p>
        <p>Across his career in politics, Senator Lieberman of Connecticut, the  Democratic vice-presidential nominee, has written five books that give insight into his range of interests, his ways of thinking and the forces that have shaped his life.</p>
        <p>His second book, ''The Scorpion and the Tarantula,'' was an account of what he called a ''disastrous failure of statecraft'' in the dawn of the nuclear age.</p>
        <p>As Connecticut's attorney general, he wrote ''Child Support in America,'' a handbook on how to bring in delinquent child support payments.</p>
        <p>This year, having received national attention with his condemnation of President Clinton for his affair with a White House intern, Mr. Lieberman published his memoir in defense of government service in an age of cynicism. Some reviewers  saw the book as a bid for the attention of Al Gore.</p>
        <p>In most of his books, Mr. Lieberman details history. But he went beyond history in ''The Scorpion and the Tarantula'' to argue that if the United States had openly recognized a Soviet sphere of influence in Eastern Europe, it might have helped reduce Soviet suspicions enough to achieve international control of atomic energy after World War II.</p>
        <p>Such a step, he wrote, ''would have amounted to the acknowledgment of reality,'' a reality ''which was a fact of American foreign policy in the years that follow even if it was never articulated as such. The passivity of the United States in both the Hungarian uprising of 1956 and the Czechoslovakian tremors of 1968 makes it clear that American diplomats have accepted the fact that Eastern Europe is a Soviet sphere of influence.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Lieberman can also delve into the personal. In his last book -- the only one written with a co-author, Michael D'Orso -- he tells of the collapse of his first marriage to Betty Haas, whom he met when they were both interns in the office of  Senator Abraham A. Ribicoff, Democrat of Connecticut.</p>
        <p>''There was no single reason our marriage failed,'' he wrote. ''Some of it had to do with the different directions in which our personalities and careers developed. Some of it was related to the fact that I had become much more religiously observant than I was when we met and married. And there is no doubt that some of it was caused by the demands my political career put on our private life. That is surely one of the great costs and risks of public life.''</p>
        <p>From the start of his career, Mr. Lieberman was fascinated with politics. It shows in the way he wrote of Mr. Bailey. Suspicious of machine bosses, he called Mr. Bailey ''a mysterious figure of merciless, manipulative genius. He was not totally evil, but then again he was not a philosopher king either.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Lieberman came to admire Mr. Bailey for his choice of candidates, his love of politics and the unity he brought to the state Democratic Party. ''Bailey's organization evidently did not feed on the corruption which seemed to be necessary fuel for the traditional American political machine,'' he wrote in ''The Power Broker.''</p>
        <p>But it is his memoir, ''In Praise of Public Life,'' that is the most revealing -- coincidentally because of the way that it allows Mr. Lieberman to be compared to another son of Yale, Gov. George W. Bush of Texas, the Republican presidential nominee.</p>
        <p>At times the two men can sound uncannily alike. Like Mr. Bush, Mr. Lieberman says his service in state government taught him bipartisan consensus. And, like Mr. Bush, Mr. Lieberman condemns attack politics, ''the kind of negative campaigning and mudslinging that leaves both winners and losers dirtied and degraded in the public eye.''</p>
        <p>But take a closer look at ''In Praise of Public Life,'' and it is as if Mr. Lieberman and Mr. Bush have actually lived in parallel universes.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lieberman writes of being inspired by the Rev. William Sloane Coffin, the Yale chaplain and renowned antiwar protester, to lead a group of classmates to Mississippi to help register black voters for a mock election in the state in 1963.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush, by contrast, has recalled Mr. Coffin telling him that the better man had won when Mr. Bush's father lost a Senate race in Texas. To Mr. Bush, Mr. Coffin became another kind of symbol, of an Eastern intellectual elite opposed to traditional values. The Texas governor's suspicion of figures like Mr. Coffin led Mr. Bush to a political philosophy that considered the 1960's a time of irresponsible ideas and rebellions.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush last week largely attributed the practice of attack politics to Mr. Clinton, but Mr. Lieberman dated it back 30 years and gave both parties a share in the blame.</p>
        <p>''These three decades have seen an unprecedented parade of betrayals of the public's trust,'' Mr. Lieberman wrote in his memoir.</p>
        <p>He described a political landscape that stretched ''from the deception that lay behind the Vietnam War, to the shock of the Watergate scandal'' and through the Iran-contra hearings, a chain of poisonous hearings like the Senate confirmation hearing of Clarence Thomas to a seat on the Supreme Court, and ''the earth- shaking impeachment experience of 1998 and 1999.''</p>
        <p>Writing books can be risky in politics. Republicans have used Mr. Gore's book, ''Earth in the Balance,'' as fodder for criticism of the Democratic nominee.</p>
        <p>So far, however, Republicans say they have focused on only one particular passage of Mr. Lieberman's books, a condemnation of the kind of opposition research which pries into candidates' personal lives. It is likely to be thrown back at him if the campaign turns nasty.</p>
        <p>''As far as I am concerned this kind of digging does nothing but demean our politics and defame the people who are its targets,'' Mr. Lieberman wrote. ''There is nothing wrong with going after your opponent's voting record or any other evidence of negligence in his public life, but digging into his bank account, his phone records, his medical history, his sexual life and literally his garbage when these things have nothing to do with the performance of his public duties -- past, present or future -- is wrong.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE CONNECTICUT SENATOR</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
