<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lebanese Security Force Moves Into South</title>
    <meta content="Y10LEB$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/10/world/10LEBA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221435"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Lebanon</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hezbollah</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kifner, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Lebanon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Lebanon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000810T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E1DD163FF933A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1080" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lebanese Security Force Moves Into South</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN KIFNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kifner, John</byline>
      <dateline>MERJ 'UYUN, Lebanon, Aug. 9</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lebanese government forces roll into southern Lebanon for first time in 22 years, over two months after Israel ended costly occupation; military and government officials say mixed force of 500 soliders and 500 special police troops will act as internal security force, not border guards, keeping order among Christians and Muslims and barring feuding between Shiite Hezbollah guerrillas and people who fought for Israel's proxy army; Hezbollah has vowed not to interfere with authorities, but its fighters continue to maintain checkpoints along some remote back roads near border; map; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lebanese government forces rolled into southern Lebanon before dawn today for the first time in 22 years.</p>
        <p>The long-awaited deployment took place two months and two weeks after Israel withdrew from its costly occupation, but military and government officials immediately made clear that they had no intention of deploying Lebanese troops along the border with Israel.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Lebanese government forces rolled into southern Lebanon before dawn today for the first time in 22 years.</p>
        <p>The long-awaited deployment took place two months and two weeks after Israel withdrew from its costly occupation, but military and government officials immediately made clear that they had no intention of deploying Lebanese troops along the border with Israel.</p>
        <p>Instead, the mixed force of 500 soldiers and 500 special police troops will act as an internal security force, keeping order among a population of Christians and Shiite Muslims and preventing old scores from being settled between the Shiite Hezbollah guerrillas and people who fought for Israel's proxy militia.</p>
        <p>To emphasize the point, the task force is commanded not by the army, but by Col. Nazih Abu Nader, of the Internal Security Forces, who reports directly to the interior minister, Michel Murr.</p>
        <p>Mr. Murr and other Lebanese officials have repeatedly said that the border is the responsibility of United Nations peacekeepers and that Lebanon does not want to serve as Israel's border guard.</p>
        <p>Privately, the government is said to be worried that the close proximity of the border posts, sometimes only a few yards apart, might lead to incidents or that Lebanon might be held responsible if Palestinian or Islamic guerrillas struck into Israel.</p>
        <p>''This is not a defensive force,'' said Gen. Elias Farhat, the army spokesman. ''The task is maintaining law and order.''</p>
        <p>The deployment of the Lebanese contingent was dependent on the United Nations peacekeepers' taking up border positions last weekend and has been the subject of weeks of haggling among Lebanon, the United Nations and Israel, beginning with exactly where the border was.</p>
        <p>Finally, after a telephone call from Damascus, which calls the shots in Lebanon, President Emile Lahoud gave the go-ahead on Friday.</p>
        <p>Hezbollah, the de facto force on the ground for more than two months, has pledged not to interfere with the government authorities. Its forces, with a hard core of about 500 fighters, have reverted to civilian clothes and are not carrying weapons in public, although they are planning to keep them hidden away.</p>
        <p>But a drive along some of the remote back roads near the border found Hezbollah fighters in casual clothes with binoculars and walkie-talkies still maintaining checkpoints and observation posts.</p>
        <p>Indeed, at Border Post 14, near the village of Rumaysh, where a United Nations detail from Nepal was originally posted, the only force visible on the Lebanese side consisted of five young Hezbollah guerrillas lounging in an old guard post.</p>
        <p>One of them, a tall, bearded young man in a baseball cap and track suit, showed the way up a road to what had been a major crossing point into Israel, now a tangled wreck of corrugated metal and old beams. Just ahead of where the pale blue United Nations flag still flew near an abandoned pile of sandbags, an Israeli backhoe was busily digging for a new border fence.</p>
        <p>Both the Hezbollah men and United Nations officials said the Nepalese had left at the request of the Lebanese government, which did not want United Nations forces at the old crossing points. There was no further explanation of the reasoning behind the order.</p>
        <p>The deployment, when it finally came, was made up of mostly gray-clad Internal Security police and military police officers, who spent the day in their new barracks.</p>
        <p>The main body is to be based at an old army barracks here in Merj 'Uyun, a mainly Christian town that had been the headquarters of the South Lebanon Army, Israel's proxy militia. About a third were sent to Bint Jubail, a predominantly Shiite town farther south, where one main street is marked by a sculpture of a hand grenade.</p>
        <p>''The main impact of the deployment is psychological,'' a senior United Nations official said. ''It's a really badly needed reassurance for these people who have been alone too long.'' a</p>
        <p>Qulayah, the Christian village next to Merj 'Uyun, was almost deserted today. It had supplied many of the officers and troops for the S.L.A. and, consequently, many of the 6,000 refugees who scrambled across the border when Israel abruptly pulled out on May 24.</p>
        <p>But Hezbollah has acted in a remarkably restrained and disciplined  manner, and there has been little in the way of reprisals. The Christian areas, in particular, where bloodletting could have revived the passions of the 15-year civil war, have been left alone.</p>
        <p>In the main square of Merj 'Uyun, framed by picturesque stone buildings and the distinctive cross atop a Greek Orthodox Church, people waited for the army, barracked just down the road, to arrive.</p>
        <p>''How are they deployed? We haven't seen anything yet,'' said George Mandalek, 67, who mentioned his children in Detroit and Oklahoma City. ''Well, I welcome the army anyway. We went through a lot of troubled times.</p>
        <p>''Nobody expected it to be like this,'' he said of the quiet that has prevailed here since late May. ''That's why those who went left. They were afraid. The liberation was very calm. To be honest, nobody expected it.''</p>
        <p>Adid Maalouf, 80, a retired soldier, agreed. ''There has never been a more genteel atmosphere,'' he said. ''We went through times when everything was turned upside down. But now everything is calm.</p>
        <p>''This is a chance in a lifetime to live in safety,'' he added. ''If you had been here when they hit us from all these hills and the Israeli shelling from over there was random. It was very hard times.''</p>
        <p>But Jean Mandalek, George's twin brother, took a dimmer view.</p>
        <p>''Nobody goes back to the root of the problem,'' he said. ''The Palestinians came here, they massacred and burned. Then the Israelis came and did the same. Since May, what has the government done?</p>
        <p>''The people here, how can they live, what will they do?'' he asked.  ''Nothing has happened.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
