<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Footlights</title>
    <meta content="10FOOT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221389"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000810T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E1D91F3CF933A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="443" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Footlights</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Footlights column on cultural events coming up in New York areas; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NEWS</p>
        <p>Finale</p>
        <p>The Marlboro Music School and Festival will wrap up its 50th season with a three-concert finale by some of the 75 musicians who ventured to Vermont for the experience for seven weeks this summer. Beginning tomorrow the flutist Paula Robison, the violinist Ida Levin, the French horn player David Jolley and others are to be heard in works by Dvorak, Ravel and Hayden as well as Adolf Busch, a founder of the festival, and Thomas Ades, its resident composer. On Saturday, a performance of Schoenberg's ''Pierrot Lunaire'' will feature the pianist Mitsuko Uchida, who is completing her first year as artistic director with Richard Goode, her fellow keyboardist. In the spirit of giving back, most of today's senior Marlboro artists are returning participants, including Mr. Goode, 57, who first attended the festival when he was 15, and Ms. Uchida, now 52, who first attended in her 20's.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NEWS</p>
        <p>Finale</p>
        <p>The Marlboro Music School and Festival will wrap up its 50th season with a three-concert finale by some of the 75 musicians who ventured to Vermont for the experience for seven weeks this summer. Beginning tomorrow the flutist Paula Robison, the violinist Ida Levin, the French horn player David Jolley and others are to be heard in works by Dvorak, Ravel and Hayden as well as Adolf Busch, a founder of the festival, and Thomas Ades, its resident composer. On Saturday, a performance of Schoenberg's ''Pierrot Lunaire'' will feature the pianist Mitsuko Uchida, who is completing her first year as artistic director with Richard Goode, her fellow keyboardist. In the spirit of giving back, most of today's senior Marlboro artists are returning participants, including Mr. Goode, 57, who first attended the festival when he was 15, and Ms. Uchida, now 52, who first attended in her 20's.</p>
        <p>Moon Over Manhattan</p>
        <p>Well, it's a marvelous night for -- you get the idea. And so did the people at the Hudson River Park Trust, whose Moondance series beckoned New Yorkers to tango, swing and shimmy their way along Pier 25, at North Moore Street, under a vast expanse of sky. The footloose can put on their dancing shoes for the series' final offering on Sunday at 6:30 p.m. with mood-altering music by Pasion, a predominately female band whose backgrounds span classical, jazz and Latin music. Information: (212) 533-7275.</p>
        <p>Bigger Men</p>
        <p>They Might Be Giants, the ever evolving wiseacres of alternative rock, have tapped their inventive streak yet again. The industrious duo of Johns (Flansburgh and Linnell), who also recorded the theme for the Fox hit ''Malcolm in the Middle,'' have added an eight-piece brass orchestra to their usual accordion-laden band. The 12-man ensemble will perform old hits as well as new music from their forthcoming CD on Saturday at the John Harms Center for the Arts, 30 North Van Brunt St. in Englewood, N.J.  The Giants move on to the Celebrate Brooklyn festival in Prospect Park on Aug. 19. Information: (201) 567-3600.</p>
        <p>Fleet Feet</p>
        <p>The dance portion of Central Park Summerstage will close with the Montreal-based ensemble O Vertigo, whose experimental style is dominated by flights of the fantastic. The work ''La Vie Qui Bat,'' to be presented tomorrow night in its United States premiere, was choreographed by the company's director, Ginette Laurin, and relies on the composer Steve Reich's ''Drumming'' for its foundation. The result, she said, is ''dance polarized between order and chaos, between urban and tribal.'' The free performance begins at 8:30.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
