<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In America; Smiles All Around</title>
    <meta content="10HERB" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221414"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/Bob Herbert</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000810T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E3DF163FF933A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="784" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In America; Smiles All Around</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BOB HERBERT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It's a clever strategy.</p>
        <p>Newt Gingrich is gone. And the others -- the Strom Thurmonds, the Trent Lotts, the Tom DeLays, the Dick Armeys -- are all wearing camouflage outfits and hiding in the tall grass. They will stay there at least until November.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It's a clever strategy.</p>
        <p>Newt Gingrich is gone. And the others -- the Strom Thurmonds, the Trent Lotts, the Tom DeLays, the Dick Armeys -- are all wearing camouflage outfits and hiding in the tall grass. They will stay there at least until November.</p>
        <p>What we see on television is the perfect front man, George W., a happy-go-lucky guy who hasn't a harsh word to say about anyone, and the avuncular Dick Cheney. They are meant to epitomize mainstream America, and to deflect (via images that could have been crafted by Norman Rockwell) any suggestion that the G.O.P. is extreme.</p>
        <p>Now comes Al Gore with his brand new running buddy, Joe Lieberman. At the moment they are sprinting away from Bill Clinton. No sex, please, we're religious. But their real mission is to convince voters that they are closer to the so-called mainstream than Mr. Bush and Mr. Cheney, and that the reality of the G.O.P. is something other than moderate, tolerant, inclusive and kind.</p>
        <p>This is not easy without the delightfully unabashed mean-spiritedness we've come to associate with the G.O.P. (Mr. Gingrich once told a group of young Republicans, ''I think one of the great problems we have in the Republican Party is that we don't encourage you to be nasty.'' Tom DeLay has characterized the Environmental Protection Agency as the ''Gestapo of the government.'')</p>
        <p>George W. may need a cheat sheet when it comes to naming world leaders, but he was smart enough to recognize the need to put a friendlier face on his party.</p>
        <p>But is a friendly face enough?</p>
        <p>The biggest decision Mr. Bush and Mr. Gore have had to make so far was picking a running mate, and a comparison of their choices is instructive.</p>
        <p>By today's standards, Joe Lieberman is pretty moderate. He supports the Clinton administration's budget and trade policies, favors a cut in the capital gains tax, is pro-choice on abortion, feels strongly about protecting the environment, voted for the Clinton administration's welfare reform legislation, is willing to experiment with school vouchers, and has taken a harsh stand against what he views as excessive sex and violence in the entertainment industry.</p>
        <p>Dick Cheney is another story. His avuncular persona is one thing. But his political views are something else. The Republican Party can't find a smile wide enough to conceal those aspects of his Congressional voting record that were way outside the American mainstream. At times he was more extreme than the guys now hiding in the high grass.</p>
        <p>In 1988 Dick Armey and Tom DeLay were part of the overwhelming majority to vote for the AIDS Federal Policy Act, which was the first major bill to provide funds for AIDS testing and counseling. Dick Cheney was one of only 13 House members to vote against it.</p>
        <p>In 1984 and 1987 he voted against funding the Older Americans Act, which offered nutrition and other services to the elderly. He voted repeatedly against funding for Head Start. (Now that the national spotlight is on him, he says he will support Head Start.) He voted against subsidizing school lunches for poor children. He voted against aid to college students. He voted against fair housing legislation. He was one of only eight members of the House to vote against the Clean Water Act in 1987, and was one of only 21 to vote against the Safe Water Drinking Act in 1986.</p>
        <p>He is far outside the mainstream on abortion. He has consistently opposed abortion even in cases of rape and incest, and even when the life of the mother is at stake. That, to most Americans, is extreme.</p>
        <p>And then there was the legislation to ban plastic guns, which could not be detected by airport security. Even the National Rifle Association supported that measure. But not Mr. Cheney. He was one of only four members of the house to vote against the ban. You will not find many Americans of any political persuasion who would support that position.</p>
        <p>Dick Cheney is way out there.</p>
        <p>But he's got a nice, quiet, steady way about him. He doesn't look like an extremist.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore and Mr. Lieberman believe their views are in sync with the real American mainstream. But they will have a tough time trying to unmask this year's happy-face Republicans.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
