<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Political Memo; Levy Is Sparring With an Old Ally Over Direction of the City Schools</title>
    <meta content="10LEVY" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221440"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goodnough, Abby</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mills, Richard P (Comr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Levy, Harold O (Chancellor)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000810T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E6DC163FF933A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1405" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Political Memo; Levy Is Sparring With an Old Ally Over Direction of the City Schools</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ABBY GOODNOUGH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Goodnough, Abby</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lawsuit filed by state education commissioner, Richard P Mills, to block Schools Chancellor Harold O Levy, an old ally, from hiring uncertified teachers to work in New York City's failing schools startles many people in education circles, but such conflicts are inevitable if both officials are doing their jobs to the utmost; city's schools have a specific set of problems, and they do not always jobe with what the state mandates; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In his efforts to raise standards for school districts throughout New York State, Richard P. Mills, the state's education commissioner, had no stronger ally than Harold O. Levy.</p>
        <p>Mr. Levy worked closely with Mr. Mills for three years as a member of the State Board of Regents, helping shape ambitious new instructional requirements until he resigned in January to become New York City's schools chancellor. But last week, Mr. Mills sued Mr. Levy for violating one of the very policies Mr. Levy helped create: a ban on hiring uncertified teachers to work in failing schools.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In his efforts to raise standards for school districts throughout New York State, Richard P. Mills, the state's education commissioner, had no stronger ally than Harold O. Levy.</p>
        <p>Mr. Levy worked closely with Mr. Mills for three years as a member of the State Board of Regents, helping shape ambitious new instructional requirements until he resigned in January to become New York City's schools chancellor. But last week, Mr. Mills sued Mr. Levy for violating one of the very policies Mr. Levy helped create: a ban on hiring uncertified teachers to work in failing schools.</p>
        <p>News of the lawsuit startled many people in education circles. Why, they wondered, would Mr. Mills take such a hostile action against his former colleague and philosophical sidekick? But others see such conflict as unavoidable now that Mr. Levy is no longer Mr. Mills's fellow policy maker, but the chief executive of New York City's enormously complex school system. The lawsuit, they said, is the first sign of an inevitable shift in the two men's relationship.</p>
        <p>''No matter who is commissioner and who is schools chancellor, they are going to be on a collision course if they are both doing their jobs to the utmost,'' said Meryl Tisch, a Board of Regents member from Manhattan. ''The city schools have a specific set of problems, and they don't always jibe with what the state mandates.''</p>
        <p>Now that Mr. Levy is on the other side of the fence, he faces the daunting task of bringing the city's 1,100 public schools in line with the tough new standards he championed as a state regent. In doing so, he must balance the competing interests of state education officials and an array of local constituencies -- not least the powerful teachers' union, whose support he needs much more as a chancellor than he did as a regent. As Mr. Levy prepares for his first full school year as chancellor, he is realizing just how complicated the new state requirements are when applied to a school system as huge, political and beleaguered as New York City's.</p>
        <p>''While Mills makes broad pronouncements of policy, Chancellor Levy now has to deal with day-to-day realities,'' said Steven Sanders, chairman of the Assembly Education Committee. ''He now realizes that what you see as the best of all worlds when you're crafting policy 155 miles away from New York City is not necessarily possible.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Mills, who is known for his stubborn streak, has relentlessly pushed for higher standards since he came to New York in 1995. From his point of view, the disproportionate number of uncertified teachers working in New York City's failing schools is the biggest obstacle to their improvement. The state closely monitors these 99 schools, known as SURR schools or ''schools under registration review.'' But while both the state and the city have poured money into them for years, most have remained at the bottom of the heap in terms of test scores.</p>
        <p>The Board of Regents adopted a new policy in 1998 prohibiting failing schools from hiring uncertified teachers after September 1999. But Mr. Levy's predecessor, Rudy Crew, decided he could not comply. Out of desperation, he hired nearly 600 unlicensed teachers to work in those schools last fall. About 1,200 of the 6,150 teachers working in the SURR schools, or 20 percent, were uncertified last year.</p>
        <p>In his lawsuit, Mr. Mills is demanding that Mr. Levy not only replace the unlicensed teachers hired last year, but also fill any additional vacancies with certified teachers. Mr. Levy has prepared several responses to the problem, including an alternative certification program that will put 350 people with little or no teaching experience in the schools this fall and pay for them to get the equivalent of a master's degree.</p>
        <p>But board officials are anticipating as many as 1,000 vacancies in the 99 schools this fall. With so many jobs to fill, Mr. Levy repeatedly refused to promise Mr. Mills that he would hire only certified teachers. Hence the lawsuit, which Mr. Mills told Mr. Levy about only minutes before he notified reporters.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mills -- who, like Mr. Levy, says the rift is not personal -- has been careful not to recommend a specific plan. But people close to Mr. Mills have asked why Mr. Levy does not simply force senior teachers to transfer into the failing schools or put any certified teachers hired this fall in those schools.</p>
        <p>''This is something Harold can do but has chosen not to do,'' said Carl T. Hayden, chancellor of the Board of Regents. ''Harold has landed in the middle of a culture that has longstanding rules of engagement, and all of the players there are asking him to work within those rules. Those are rules that we do not necessarily respect.''</p>
        <p>Foremost among those ''players'' is the United Federation of Teachers, the union representing the city's 78,000 teachers. Because of the union's wealth and influence, chancellors rarely defy its wishes. In this case, Randi Weingarten, the union president, has warned that she will not tolerate any involuntary transfer of experienced teachers into the 99 failing schools.</p>
        <p>But pressure from the union, which could take the form of a lawsuit or even a strike, is apparently not the only factor in Mr. Levy's refusal to take drastic measures. His aides say that he is philosophically opposed to the idea of forcing teachers to work in troubled schools, especially at a time when the school system is struggling to attract new teachers and retain older ones who are nearing retirement age.</p>
        <p>''Historically the board has lost certified teachers to the suburbs when it has attempted involuntarily to require new teachers to teach in undesirable locations,'' Mr. Levy wrote in the memo. ''I view this road as folly.''</p>
        <p>William C. Thompson Jr., president of the Board of Education, said he would urge Mr. Levy to appeal the suit -- a move that would further jeopardize his relationship with Mr. Mills.</p>
        <p>Even if the immediate problem is resolved, Mr. Levy will have to work wonders to ensure that city schools meet other requirements that he helped create as a regent. The ban on uncertified teachers will extend to all schools in 2003, posing a huge challenge for a city whose teaching force includes 11,000 uncertified teachers, or 14 percent of the total.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, all of the city's 1.1 million students -- including special education and bilingual students -- are now required to pass rigorous Regents exams to graduate. And in the latest accountability measure imposed by Mr. Mills and the Board of Regents, every school in the state will soon be publicly graded based on its students' scores on the new statewide tests, and rewarded or punished according to where it ranks.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hayden of the Board of Regents indicated that Mr. Levy would not be granted a reprieve on any of those requirements. He said that in his short tenure as chancellor, Mr. Levy had already come up with innovative solutions to several seemingly intractable problems and that he could certainly come up with more.</p>
        <p>''He has really asked for a rethinking of many of the ways in which business gets done,'' Mr. Hayden said. ''This just happens to be an issue where he's not ready to do that, and for the life of me, I don't understand why.''</p>
        <p>For his part, Mr. Levy refused to discuss how he would handle the suit. But he said that since becoming chancellor, he had a new perspective on the standards movement.</p>
        <p>''I realize now how extraordinarily difficult it is to meet the mandates the Regents have put in place,'' Mr. Levy said. ''You need to run a system like this to understand just how hard the burden is. But that's not a reason not to do it.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
