<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Buchanan Coup Attempt</title>
    <meta content="10THU2$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221474"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Reform Party</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Buchanan, Patrick J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000810T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E5D9163FF933A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="538" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Buchanan Coup Attempt</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial deplores Patrick Buchanan's apparent seizure of Reform Party machinery, saying he has little to offer as presidential candidate; notes takeover is aimed at getting over $12 million in federal campaign funds due to party; holds his policies run counter to libertarian streak of many party members</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Eight years after the establishment of the Reform Party by Ross Perot, the party's machinery has apparently been seized -- or disabled -- by Patrick Buchanan, longtime scold on the Republican right. As a presidential candidate, Mr. Buchanan has little to offer the American public except the politics of resentment. But if he gets the Reform Party's presidential nomination this week, his tirades against free trade, affirmative action and abortion may draw votes away from Gov. George W. Bush, unless they help Mr. Bush by making him seem more moderate. In any case, it is enough to make one nostalgic for Mr. Perot, the eccentric Texas billionaire who founded the party.</p>
        <p>Despite Mr. Perot's comical behavior, the Reform Party has drawn support from a wide range of well-intentioned Americans who wanted to elevate the tone of politics. For them it is especially unfortunate that Mr. Buchanan's takeover attempts have been less about issues than about getting his hands on the more than $12 million in federal campaign funds due the party because of Mr. Perot's past showings on the ballot.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Eight years after the establishment of the Reform Party by Ross Perot, the party's machinery has apparently been seized -- or disabled -- by Patrick Buchanan, longtime scold on the Republican right. As a presidential candidate, Mr. Buchanan has little to offer the American public except the politics of resentment. But if he gets the Reform Party's presidential nomination this week, his tirades against free trade, affirmative action and abortion may draw votes away from Gov. George W. Bush, unless they help Mr. Bush by making him seem more moderate. In any case, it is enough to make one nostalgic for Mr. Perot, the eccentric Texas billionaire who founded the party.</p>
        <p>Despite Mr. Perot's comical behavior, the Reform Party has drawn support from a wide range of well-intentioned Americans who wanted to elevate the tone of politics. For them it is especially unfortunate that Mr. Buchanan's takeover attempts have been less about issues than about getting his hands on the more than $12 million in federal campaign funds due the party because of Mr. Perot's past showings on the ballot.</p>
        <p>Today the party opens its convention in Long Beach, Calif., where Mr. Buchanan says he expects to be nominated after working hard all year to take over the party organization state by state. Anti-Buchanan members are charging fraud, and contend that if they cannot stop his selection at the convention they will break off and form a separate Reform Party with its own nominee. A court battle over who gets the $12 million is considered likely.</p>
        <p>The high-water mark of Mr. Perot's candidacy occurred in the spring of 1992, when it seemed plausible that he could actually beat President Bush and the Democratic challenger, Gov. Bill Clinton of Arkansas. But Mr. Perot's odd tactical reversals -- dropping out of the race suddenly and, just as suddenly, jumping back in -- and his paranoid-sounding charges of conspiracies against him and his family did him in. Nevertheless, he brought a certain truth-telling to the 1992 campaign, warning of the dangers of federal deficits, the power of special interests and what he said was declining American competitiveness abroad. In his 1996 race he was far less credible as a candidate.</p>
        <p>The only policy that Mr. Buchanan has picked up from the old Perot campaign is opposition to trade agreements. His moralizing and demands for anti-abortion laws run counter to the libertarian streak of many Reform Party members, including Gov. Jesse Ventura of Minnesota.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Buchanan walked out of the Republican Party last fall, Governor Bush lamented his loss to the G.O.P. In fact, the party was fortunate to be rid of his nasty brand of nativism and his divisive rants about cultural war and the ''Israeli lobby.'' In these generally prosperous economic times, it is fair enough for Mr. Buchanan to try to call attention to the problems of those not benefiting from the boom. But it is doubtful that his flame-throwing attacks on his ever-changing list of foreign and domestic enemies will elevate the race this year. The Reform Party would do better to nominate a candidate appealing to idealism rather than the paranoid fringe.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
