<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Population Trends Heighten West's Fire Woes</title>
    <meta content="Y10FIR$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221456"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fires and Firemen</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forest and Brush Fires</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Montana</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Bitterroot River Valley (Mont)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Forest Service (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Milloy, Ross E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kitchens, Bobby</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Montana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Rockies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Montana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forest and Brush Fires</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000810T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03EFDB163FF933A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1124" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Population Trends Heighten West's Fire Woes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROSS E. MILLOY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Milloy, Ross E</byline>
      <dateline>HAMILTON, Mont., Aug. 9</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Forest Service official Bobby Kitchens says population migration to heavily wooded areas and Service's policy of trying to save people and buildings first make fighting forest fires even harder in nation's worst fire season in 50 years; says saving houses and buildings diverts resources from fire containment, leading to bigger fires with more destruction; problem is particularly apparent in Montana's Bitterroot River Valley, which may be most vulnerable part of state to forest fires; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After a steep hike to the top of a hill overlooking Dixon Creek near here, Bobby Kitchens pointed today to a mound of rubble surrounded by blackened trees, smoking stumps and, everywhere, a two-inch layer of gray soot.</p>
        <p>''This was one beautiful home, someone's dream home, with one beautiful view,'' Mr. Kitchens said, sweeping an arm across the Stygian panorama left by forest fires that swept through this area on Sunday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After a steep hike to the top of a hill overlooking Dixon Creek near here, Bobby Kitchens pointed today to a mound of rubble surrounded by blackened trees, smoking stumps and, everywhere, a two-inch layer of gray soot.</p>
        <p>''This was one beautiful home, someone's dream home, with one beautiful view,'' Mr. Kitchens said, sweeping an arm across the Stygian panorama left by forest fires that swept through this area on Sunday.</p>
        <p>A thick fog of smoke still lingered in the air, and, stretching into the misty horizon, all that could be seen on the rolling hills below were darkened tree stalks, many still smoldering.</p>
        <p>The house Mr. Kitchens, a Forest Service information officer, was pointing out had been reduced to ashen remnants of someone's lost mountain lifestyle: twisted tin, stones from a toppled chimney, a half-melted refrigerator, some charred mattress springs and a scorched television set.</p>
        <p>In the midst of what officials are calling the nation's worst fire season in more than 50 years -- with 70 major fires now consuming over a million acres of forests in a dozen Western states -- Forest Service officials are having to answer a lot of questions about the dimension of this summer's fires, Mr. Kitchens said.</p>
        <p>''A lot of people say, 'Why don't you just put out those fires?' '' he said. ''Frankly, it's just not that simple.''</p>
        <p>Trends in population migration and the Forest Service's own policies add to the difficulty of combating the fires, Mr. Kitchens said.</p>
        <p>One problem, he said, is what the agency calls ''human interface.''</p>
        <p>''We've got too many people moving into heavily wooded areas like this,'' he said. ''There's no way we can save a home like this, positioned at the top of hill, surrounded by all these trees. It's just not going to happen. When humans interface with the natural environment in a remote setting, you're going to have problems.''</p>
        <p>''I've been fighting fires for 37 years, and I see a definite trend,'' Mr. Kitchens said. ''It used to be we'd never see a house or structure when we were on a fire, but these days it's rare that you have a fire where you're not trying to save buildings and people.''</p>
        <p>The official policy of the Forest Service, he said, is to protect people and structures first and then worry about putting out the fire.</p>
        <p>''Saving houses and buildings diverts resources away from containing the fires,'' he said, ''so you ultimately get bigger fires with more destruction.''</p>
        <p>And in no place is that problem more apparent than here in the Bitterroot River Valley of Montana.</p>
        <p>In terms of property damage, the valley may be the most vulnerable part of the state to forest fires. Ravalli County, where Hamilton rests, is the fastest-growing county in Montana, having grown 40 percent in the last eight years. There are now 35,000 people living in the dry Ponderosa pine forests in the valley bottom.</p>
        <p>And that is where the fires burn the hottest, said Bill Armold, a planner for Ravalli County.</p>
        <p>''People have come here because it's the last best place,'' Mr. Armold said. ''It's an unspoiled picturesque mountain valley with views, a river and wilderness.''</p>
        <p>One of those people is Lisa Wissenbach, who was canning tomatoes on Sunday when a city official told her it was time to evacuate the home she and her husband had built in the community of Pinesdale near here.</p>
        <p>Today, Ms. Wissenbach was still staying at a junior high school in Hamilton with her five children, waiting to hear if her home would survive the fires moving near Pinesdale today.</p>
        <p>''It never occurred to me that this might happen,'' she said. ''We even let the fire insurance lapse when my husband was changing jobs, and now, with the fires on, the company won't reinstate us.''</p>
        <p>Elizabeth and Bob Sporer had read a lot of magazines about the Bitterroot Valley and fallen in love with it before they had even seen it, said Mr. Sporer, a retired heavy equipment operator from El Cajon, Calif.</p>
        <p>''It was a place to get out of the rat race,'' he said.</p>
        <p>On Sunday the Sporers were forced to evacuate their dream home when the fires turned their way. They have heard their home is still standing, though two nearby homes and most of the trees have burned.</p>
        <p>''Our neighbors got in and said everything in their home is black with ash and dirt from the fire,'' Mr. Sporer said. ''And I just got new bedroom furniture. But at least the house is still standing.''</p>
        <p>He shook his head emphatically when asked whether the charred landscape would force him from his mountain refuge.</p>
        <p>''It doesn't discourage me that much,'' he said. ''I'll have to cut down some burned trees. But things will grow back. It'll green up, if we ever get any rain.''</p>
        <p>Another part of the growing fire problem is a contradiction that has not been addressed, Forest Service officials say.</p>
        <p>Western ecosystems are adapted to periodic, low intensity fires that clean out accumulated debris and thin the trees. But for decades the policy has been to suppress all fires, and people have built their homes  amidst a dangerous accumulation of fuels.</p>
        <p>''People think the more trees you have the healthier the forest, but actually, it's just the opposite,'' said Jerry Williams, director of fire and aviation management for the Northern region of the Forest Service in Missoula, Mont.</p>
        <p>''A healthy forest has 60 to 70 trees per acre,'' Mr. Williams said. ''Instead, we have 600 to 700 trees per acre here and it's the driest period ever recorded in some places. These places are very vulnerable to high intensity fire.''</p>
        <p>As fire officials here noted that single-digit humidity, high temperatures and an extended drought had conspired to create almost textbook conditions for more fires, they were warning local residents today to brace themselves for new and intense incoming dry lightening storms.</p>
        <p>''We cannot guarantee that we can protect every structure,'' said Jack Sept, chief of external affairs at the National Interagency Fire Center. ''That's the cold truth.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
