<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nervous About Using Napster? Used CD's Are Bargains Online</title>
    <meta content="10SHOP$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Circuits" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221365"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ONLINE SHOPPER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Compact Discs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mirapaul, Matthew</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Columns/Online Shopper</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Circuits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electronics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000810T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E4D6113CF933A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1207" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nervous About Using Napster? Used CD's Are Bargains Online</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW MIRAPAUL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mirapaul, Matthew</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on buying and selling used compact discs on line; some services discussed; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TRADING in your compact discs can be a humiliating experience. As you stand at the counter, trying to recover some cash for a musical experiment gone awry or a summer hit that started to sound silly in the fall, you often learn that your $16.98 investment is now worth a couple of bucks -- or nothing at all.</p>
        <p>Andy Grundy, president and a founder of Spun.com, a used-CD shop on the Web, knows the feeling. ''I've walked into stores with a stack of 10 CD's and they're like, 'I'll take these 2,' '' Mr. Grundy said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TRADING in your compact discs can be a humiliating experience. As you stand at the counter, trying to recover some cash for a musical experiment gone awry or a summer hit that started to sound silly in the fall, you often learn that your $16.98 investment is now worth a couple of bucks -- or nothing at all.</p>
        <p>Andy Grundy, president and a founder of Spun.com, a used-CD shop on the Web, knows the feeling. ''I've walked into stores with a stack of 10 CD's and they're like, 'I'll take these 2,' '' Mr. Grundy said.</p>
        <p>By selling discs on the Internet, he said, online customers, can avoid ''the clerk with a pierced nose who laughs at you and seems to be saying, 'You bought this?' ''</p>
        <p>I'm not ashamed to admit that my large, eclectic collection consists mainly of previously owned titles acquired at local shops. But in recent months, I've started buying most of my used CD's over the Web.</p>
        <p>Used CD's can provide a cost-effective alternative for those who feel new disc prices are too high but are uncomfortable with the intangibility and questionable legality of free song downloads through sites like Napster.</p>
        <p>The online selection at sites like  Spun.com, SecondSpin.com and smaller operations like UsedMusicExchange.com tended to be better than what I found at the neighborhood stores, and because I rarely rush to pick up a new release, I'm willing to wait until a CD comes available.</p>
        <p>Buying used CD's online is no different than buying new discs: search for the CD's you want, toss them in a virtual shopping cart and pay with your credit card.</p>
        <p>Some online stores also sell new CD's and used movies and computer games. Several sites augment album entries with song lists and audio clips, but to make sure I am getting the latest reissue (the one with all the bonus tracks) and a sufficient price break, I usually open another browser window and crosscheck the entries against those on sites that sell new CD's. This method is reliable but not fail-safe.</p>
        <p>A disc of Debussy piano music that arrived last week from Spun.com was a live recording from a performance in Italy instead of the major-label classic that I expected. The company will pay for the return.</p>
        <p>I conducted an informal check of five used-CD sites by shopping for six popular but slightly dated releases -- ''Play'' by Moby, ''Supernatural'' by Carlos Santana, ''On How Life Is'' by Macy Gray, ''Fly'' by the Dixie Chicks, ''Human Clay'' by Creed and ''Appalachian Journey'' by Yo Yo Ma, Edgar Meyer and Mark O'Connor -- and found the potential savings to be considerable.</p>
        <p>Buying the same discs new, at discounted prices, from Amazon.com would cost $71.94. Including shipping and handling fees, the lowest total would have been $49.44, from SecondSpin.com for the used CD's.</p>
        <p>I have rarely received a defective disc, only 2 of the 150 I've ordered in two years, and all the used-CD sites guarantee their merchandise. But availability can be an issue, if not an outright disappointment.</p>
        <p>Spun.com was the only site with all six discs in stock, for $53.94. Most of the sites had half the titles on hand, and SecondSpin.com had one. But inventories changed daily, and several sites offered a notification feature that sent an e-mail message when a desired title arrived.</p>
        <p>I also tested the stores with five obscure titles, including ''Too Tired to Sleep'' by Dirk Hamilton and ''Bricolage'' by Amon Tobin, and five just-released titles, including ''The Marshall Mathers LP'' by Eminem  and ''Anarchy'' by Busta Rhymes. Once again, Spun.com's shelves were full when the others were empty. Mr. Grundy said used copies of current titles usually sell quickly.</p>
        <p>So much for buying CD's, what about selling. Like everyone else, I have acquired my share of turkeys. And as I discovered last week, using the Internet to trade discs can be more complicated than buying them. Determining the value of your castoff discs required some effort, and it might take several weeks to receive compensation in cash or virtual credit.</p>
        <p>Nor was there any guarantee that your undesirable CD's would be accepted. When I asked Todd Ramcke, general manager of UsedMusicExchange.com in Glendale, Calif., via an e-mail message how much he would pay for a Mahler symphony and another disc of classical music, he replied, ''Sorry, but both of the CD's you want to trade us are of no value to us. Try SecondSpin.com.''</p>
        <p>Even in cyberspace, my rejects had been cruelly rejected. In a subsequent phone interview, Mr. Ramcke apologetically confessed, ''Classical stuff we just don't sell at all.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Grundy said most Spun.com customers sell discs at the same time they buy. The company sends a postage-paid mailer for trade-in discs along with the order. SwapIt.com ships a postage-paid container when you register online, or you can print out a mailing label from its site.</p>
        <p>SecondSpin.com and the CD Exchange (www.thecdexchange.com) require you to pay the freight, although the CD Exchange lets you cut costs by keeping the jewel-box containers.</p>
        <p>When it comes to trade-ins, online stores can be just as picky as real-world shops. The discs are expected to be playable, and the cover and liner notes must be intact. Recordable CD's are out, as are designated as being for promotional purposes.  (CashForCDs.com buys promo copies.) SecondSpin.com deducts 50 cents for cracked or broken cases.</p>
        <p>Determining the value of trade-ins takes work. The CD Exchange lets you type in a list of discs and returns a quote, but most sites ask you to search for titles and add them to a trade-in cart. When a title can't be found, you can sometimes use the number on a disc's universal product code.</p>
        <p>I also sought trade-in quotes for a half-dozen discs, a mix of mainstream and offbeat titles. Despite my best efforts, I had trouble getting prices for the nonhit CD's -- or they weren't accepted at all.</p>
        <p>Of the sites that would take all six discs, Spun.com and SwapIt.com offered the best deals: about $30. Except for Spun.com, which offered an immediate credit, the others asked me to send in the CD's, whose value would be verified, and then would send a check or issue a credit, a process that generally takes two weeks.</p>
        <p>For comparison, I took the same six discs to the local branch of Djangos, a national chain store that sells used CD's but does not accept trade-ins through its Web site (www .djangomusic.com). The clerk examined the CD's and offered me $13. He was overruled by a manager who was monitoring the transaction and upped the offer to $18 in cash or $24 in store credit.</p>
        <p>I could do better online, so I turned down the offer. The clerk looked puzzled, and maybe a little hurt. But I'll still shop there. I found a musical cast recording of ''Babes in Arms'' for just $7.95.</p>
        <p>What a steal.</p>
        <p>ONLINE SHOPPER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
