<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Real Winner In Zimbabwe</title>
    <meta content="28RIEF$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210974"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Results</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Zimbabwe</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rieff, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mugabe, Robert (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Zimbabwe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Zimbabwe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Results</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000628T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E2DF1130F93BA15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="707" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Real Winner In Zimbabwe</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By David Rieff</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rieff, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>David Rieff Op-Ed article reports that Zimbabwe election, while deeply flawed by thuggery of Mugabe forces, still represents some of best news from sub-Saharan Africa in recent memory; cites success of opposition, and gives much of credit to civil society groups that trained 24,000 local poll watchers (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Even though the democratic forces lost -- and may have had the election stolen from them, at that -- the result of this week's voting in Zimbabwe represents some of the best news from sub-Saharan Africa in recent memory. What it has shown, as the Movement for Democratic Change came close to winning a parliamentary majority in the face of violence and intimidation, is the strength of the popular desire for a fair and decent government.</p>
        <p>This was an election that President Robert Mugabe and his ruling party were committed to winning at any cost. Some opposition party candidates were killed. The so-called war veterans -- men who were little more than bands of thugs loyal to Mr. Mugabe -- were deployed to make a show of force and to help curry the votes of impoverished farmers through an attempted expropriation of white-owned land. Moreover, United Nations officials were prevented from acting as monitors. European Union observers have refused to certify the vote as free and fair, blaming the government and its security forces for the widespread irregularities.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Even though the democratic forces lost -- and may have had the election stolen from them, at that -- the result of this week's voting in Zimbabwe represents some of the best news from sub-Saharan Africa in recent memory. What it has shown, as the Movement for Democratic Change came close to winning a parliamentary majority in the face of violence and intimidation, is the strength of the popular desire for a fair and decent government.</p>
        <p>This was an election that President Robert Mugabe and his ruling party were committed to winning at any cost. Some opposition party candidates were killed. The so-called war veterans -- men who were little more than bands of thugs loyal to Mr. Mugabe -- were deployed to make a show of force and to help curry the votes of impoverished farmers through an attempted expropriation of white-owned land. Moreover, United Nations officials were prevented from acting as monitors. European Union observers have refused to certify the vote as free and fair, blaming the government and its security forces for the widespread irregularities.</p>
        <p>Even under these circumstances, the opposition party won handily in the cities and made powerful inroads in rural areas, which have been Mr. Mugabe's base of support since independence. Much of the credit for this moral victory goes to the civil society groups that trained 24,000 local poll watchers.</p>
        <p>This election in Zimbabwe is a salutary reminder that the situation in sub-Saharan Africa, though desperate, is not hopeless. All across the continent, the desire for reform continues to grow, even though too many African leaders seem determined to rule tyrannically and destructively.</p>
        <p>Zimbabwe itself has exemplified both the promise and tragedy of post-colonial Africa. Mr. Mugabe has been gradually transformed from an idealistic guerrilla commander fighting for an end to white rule into a tyrant.</p>
        <p>Because of the deep wounds from colonialism, both Zimbabweans and foreigners have been reluctant to face the truth about him, and he has been a master at turning attention away from his own destructive conduct by harking back to the evils of colonial days. As the president of the opposition party, Morgan Tsvangirai, has put it, Mr. Mugabe specialized in the ''unethical use of legitimacy of the past in order to rationalize the plundering of the present.''</p>
        <p>By now, Mr. Mugabe's indifference to the welfare of his citizens has been matched only by his willingness to shed blood or provoke political crises.</p>
        <p>Soon after he came to power, he used troops trained by North Korea to unleash a campaign of terror in the province of Matabeleland that some human rights activists have described as genocidal. More recently, he has embroiled his country in a war in the Democratic Republic of the Congo that benefits business and mining interests linked to him and his close associates. At home, he has presided over the ruination of the economy and the evisceration of basic services from public health to road maintenance.</p>
        <p>Unfortunately, the fact that Mr. Mugabe has managed, however tenuously, to hold onto power means that the next few months will be dangerous. Before the election, the opposition activists worried that, as one put it, ''we will need a landslide victory to handle Mugabe and his thugs.''</p>
        <p>They didn't get one, or, at least, if they did, voting irregularities make the question of how people really voted all but moot. What is clear is that the people of Zimbabwe have done their part to try to rid themselves of Mr. Mugabe. Will the rest of the world now help them, as it did the people of Eastern Europe in 1989? It can do so by offering aid to the independent media, supporting democratic political parties and taking a hard line with the Mugabe regime in international forums.</p>
        <p>Or will it abandon them to a dictatorial government's determination to stay entrenched, as it abandoned Chinese freedom fighters in the aftermath of the Tiananmen Square uprising?</p>
        <p>David Rieff is the author of ''Slaughterhouse: Bosnia and the Failure of the West.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">David Rieff is the author of ''Slaughterhouse: Bosnia and the Failure of the West.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
