<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Draft 2000</title>
    <meta content="Y29NEXT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210867"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000628T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E1D91230F93BA15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1238" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Draft 2000</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIKE WISE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Another young phenom, a few good big men and a projected No. 2 pick who wants to play for the Vancouver Grizzlies.</p>
        <p>BY MIKE WISE</p>
        <p>TOP 10  1. New Jersey  KENYON MARTIN  The Nets need size and Martin is the closest thing to an impact players in the draft.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Another young phenom, a few good big men and a projected No. 2 pick who wants to play for the Vancouver Grizzlies.</p>
        <p>BY MIKE WISE</p>
        <p>TOP 10  1. New Jersey  KENYON MARTIN  The Nets need size and Martin is the closest thing to an impact players in the draft.</p>
        <p>2. Vancouver  STROMILE SWIFT  Unlike Steve Francis, he's not complaining about going to Canada. Three months ago, Swift was not a lottery selection.</p>
        <p>3. Clippers  MARCUS FIZER  An N.B.A. body at 6 feet 6 inches with legs the circumference of maple trees. He can score from anywhere.</p>
        <p>4. Chicago  DARIUS MILES  Bulls fans are running out of patience, but his development may be worth the wait.</p>
        <p>5. Orlando  MIKE MILLER  South Dakota's last hoop commodity: Eric Piatkowski.</p>
        <p>6. Atlanta  DERMARR JOHNSON  Cincinnati shooting guard can flat-out score.</p>
        <p>7. Chicago  CHRIS MIHM  Jerry Krause gets the capable center he wanted.</p>
        <p>8. Cleveland  JOEL PRZYBILLA  Skilled around the basket, he's not as big a project as everyone thinks.</p>
        <p>9. Houston  ETAN THOMAS  Good shot-blocker.</p>
        <p>10. Orlando  COURTNEY ALEXANDER  Nation's leading scorer could go as high as No. 6.</p>
        <p>KID II Darius Miles, the 6-9, 18-year-old prodigy from East St. Louis High school (Ill.), will become the 14th player in the modern era to go directly from high school to the pros - and the 10th player since Kevin Garnett to skip college since 1995. Michael Jordan, who picked Miles to play with on his summer-camp team in Santa Barbara, Calif., said he would take Miles if he had the first pick. ''I finally saw it in the paper and my mom put it in the scrapbook,'' Miles said. His idols? ''Kevin Garnett and Chris Webber. I love those guys. I was a big Fab Five fan when I was a kid. Even when C. Webb called the timeout and lost the title, I still loved him,'' Miles was 12 years old when he watched the Michigan-North Carolina title game in 1993.</p>
        <p>BULL MARKET Chicago has 6 picks among the first 34. Orlando owns the Nos. 5, 10 and 13 picks. The Clippers, have Nos. 3, 18 and 30.</p>
        <p>THE BIG THREE It's not a great big-man draft but three centers have emerged as lottery picks. At 7 feet, Texas' Chris Mihm is more skilled than rugged and teams are concerned about his toughness. Polite, well-spoken, he did not wear two diamond-studded earrings to the news media availability session yesterday - as Florida's Mike Miller did. Doesn't matter if you grew up in South Dakota, like Miller, the more hip-hop you appear, the better your chance of going higher, Minnesota's 7-1 sophomore Joel Przybilla comes from the same Gopher lineage as Randy Breuer and Kevin McHale. lakovos (Jake) Tsadalidas is the strongest of them all at 7-2, 282. Rugged down low he is the rare draftee who can score with his back to the basket. Whoever drafts Tsakalidis may have to pay a portion or all of a $1 million buyout to AEK, his club team in Greece.</p>
        <p>N.C.A.A. BAD BOYS In a draft littered with 6-foot-and-under point guards, Michigan's 6-6 freshman Jamal Crawford may be plucked before Michigan State's Mateen Cleaves. Crawford played only 17 games this season because the N.C.A.A. ruled that he accepted money from a Seattle businessman while in high school. He tried to make himself eligible for the draft last season, but his letter reached the N.B.A. offices after the early-entry deadline. Erick Barkley may not go until late in the first round. He, too, drew the ire of N.C.A.A. investigators this season. Przybilla was not exactly on his way to becoming a four-year letter-winner, either. He did not understand why Minnesota Coach Dan Monson, who was brought in to clean up the program after Clem Haskins, insisted he go to class.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
