<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Naive Detective Packing Goofy Malapropisms</title>
    <meta content="28TRIX" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210894"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Watson, Emily</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holden, Stephen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rudolph, Alan</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Trixie (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews/By Stephen Holden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000628T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E2DE1030F93BA15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="966" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Naive Detective Packing Goofy Malapropisms</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN HOLDEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Holden, Stephen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Stephen Holden reviews movie Trixie, written and directed by Alan Rudolph; Emily Watson stars; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Few filmmakers are as generous toward actors as Alan Rudolph. That's why they flock to be in his films, even though the chances of a box office hit are next to nil. Like his actor-friendly mentor, Robert Altman, Mr. Rudolph is a maverick who has always gone his own way, strewing behind him a filmography (now 17 movies), the bulk of which might be described as ambitious failures.</p>
        <p>''Trixie,'' this director's latest experiment in combining genres, tantalizingly (and accurately) bills itself as a ''screwball film noir.'' But with its off-kilter mixture of menace and cornball humor attached to a sketchy, sluggishly paced story whose holes are left gaping, it is unlikely to break the pattern.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Few filmmakers are as generous toward actors as Alan Rudolph. That's why they flock to be in his films, even though the chances of a box office hit are next to nil. Like his actor-friendly mentor, Robert Altman, Mr. Rudolph is a maverick who has always gone his own way, strewing behind him a filmography (now 17 movies), the bulk of which might be described as ambitious failures.</p>
        <p>''Trixie,'' this director's latest experiment in combining genres, tantalizingly (and accurately) bills itself as a ''screwball film noir.'' But with its off-kilter mixture of menace and cornball humor attached to a sketchy, sluggishly paced story whose holes are left gaping, it is unlikely to break the pattern.</p>
        <p>The sad thing is that there is enough to admire about ''Trixie'' to make you wish it were much, much better, but not enough for the movie to be called even a qualified success. Still, ''Trixie'' is a comeback of sorts; it isn't half as frustrating as the surreal sludge Mr. Rudolph left behind last year with his impenetrable film adaptation of Kurt Vonnegut's ''Breakfast of Champions.''</p>
        <p>''Trixie'' is above all a showcase for Emily Watson, who appears in almost every scene as the title character, a saucer-eyed, virginal amateur sleuth from Chicago (Ms. Watson lays on an extra-thick Midwestern accent) investigating a murder in a lakeside casino resort somewhere in the Far West. If Trixie is a much less meaty part than Ms. Watson's roles in ''Breaking the Waves'' and ''Hilary and Jackie,'' it still allows her ample space for flexing her talent, starting with that accent. And underneath the character's wary, prudish exterior lurks an erotic spark waiting to ignite.</p>
        <p>With her carefully exaggerated accent, this squeaky-clean character often seems like a first cousin of Frances McDormand's intrepid, unfailingly polite police investigator in ''Fargo,'' the far superior Coen brothers film to which ''Trixie'' bears a sometimes uncomfortable resemblance. In much the same way that the Coens fetishized their heroine's squareness to throw us off balance by gently mocking her decency, Ms. Watson's Trixie is given to naively spouting slogans using the wrong words. ''You've got to grab the bull by the tail and look it in the eye,'' she blurts. Or ''That's the truth, the hole in the truth and nothing but the truth.''</p>
        <p>Giving the character one or two goofy malapropisms might have been a refreshing touch. But the screenplay (written by Mr. Rudolph from a story he concocted with John Binder) makes the mistake of basing much of its humor on Trixie's continual verbal stumbling, and the joke is quickly beaten to death.</p>
        <p>Trixie's adventures begin in the casino where while working as an undercover detective she attracts the lustful attention of Dex Lang (Dermot Mulroney), a bar-hopping Don Juan who works as a gofer for Red Rafferty (Will Patton) a sleazy local developer. In the movie's best scene, Trixie winds up with Dex on Red's boat, along with Red's drunken, pill-popping girlfriend, a pathetically inept pop-country singer named Dawn Sloane (Lesley Ann Warren). Also aboard is Drummond Avery (Nick Nolte), a hard-drinking senator who is Red's partner in several kinds of mischief. In a scene rumbling with undercurrents of violence and sex, Trixie tussles with Red and is ordered off the boat.</p>
        <p>The story darkens after Dawn disappears and is discovered by Trixie, beaten up, hysterical and in possession, she claims, of a sexually incriminating videotape. Soon afterward, she is found dead beneath her hotel window. Determined to solve the case, Trixie stalks the senator to an exclusive restaurant where, sozzled on martinis, he delivers a rambling, incoherent monologue about presidential hanky-panky. Only a director as fond of actors as Mr. Rudolph would have allowed Mr. Nolte the room to deliver a scenery-chewing rant that for all its dramatic heat, also stops the movie cold.</p>
        <p>Skulking around the outskirts of the story are Kirk Stans (Nathan Lane), a lounge impressionist with a shady past, and Ruby Pearli (Brittany Murphy), a reckless barfly and ex-lover of Dex.</p>
        <p>Despite its occasional flashes of brilliance (every Rudolph film has them), this unsavory stew never comes to a boil. The biggest problem is the screwball side of the equation.  From its forced malapropisms to sudden, clumsy lurches into farce, the movie's humor feels like a painfully self-conscious exercise in genre bending. It turns out that the kind of ironic playfulness that comes so naturally to younger filmmakers nowadays is just not Mr. Rudolph's forte. Even when ''Trixie'' is being ''light,'' the weight of the director's heavy hand keeps the lid on any genuine levity.</p>
        <p>''Trixie'' is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It contains sexual situations, profanity and some mild violence.</p>
        <p>TRIXIE</p>
        <p>Directed by Alan Rudolph; written by Mr. Rudolph, based on a story written by him and John Binder; director of photography, Jan Kiesser; edited by Michael Ruscio; music by Mark Isham and Roger Neill; production designers, Richard Paris and Linda Del Rosario; produced by Robert Altman; released by Sony Pictures Classics. Running time: 117 minutes. This film is rated R.</p>
        <p>WITH: Emily Watson (Trixie Zurbo), Dermot Mulroney (Dex Lang), Nick Nolte (Senator Drummond Avery), Nathan Lane (Kirk Stans), Brittany Murphy (Ruby Pearli), Lesley Ann Warren (Dawn Sloane) and Will Patton (Red Rafferty).</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
