<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Miranda's Value in the Trenches</title>
    <meta content="28TURO$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210926"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Miranda V Arizona (US Supreme Court 1966 Decision)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Self-Incrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fifth Amendment (US Constitution)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Supreme Court (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Turow, Scott</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Constitutional Amendments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000628T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CEFDA1030F93BA15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="922" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Miranda's Value in the Trenches</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Scott Turow</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Turow, Scott</byline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Scott Turow Op-Ed article welcomes Supreme Court's affirmation of Miranda, 34-year old constitutional mandate that requires police to advise suspects of their right to remain silent (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I was delighted by the Supreme Court's decision on Monday to uphold Miranda, the 34-year old constitutional mandate that requires the police to advise anyone arrested of the right to remain silent. Miranda retains an almost sacramental value; it is a vivid emblem of central ideas about the law. But the truth is that by now, Miranda has little practical impact on the interaction between suspects and cops.</p>
        <p>To whatever degree Miranda ever impeded law enforcement, its effect abated a long time time ago. I have been practicing criminal law for nearly 22 years now, eight years as a federal prosecutor and 14 years in private practice. In that time, I have been involved in exactly one case where the result was changed after a confession was declared inadmissible under Miranda, and that matter involved a juvenile who, in addition to not being told his rights, did not enjoy the benefit of a number of other safeguards applied in Illinois to the questioning of minors.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I was delighted by the Supreme Court's decision on Monday to uphold Miranda, the 34-year old constitutional mandate that requires the police to advise anyone arrested of the right to remain silent. Miranda retains an almost sacramental value; it is a vivid emblem of central ideas about the law. But the truth is that by now, Miranda has little practical impact on the interaction between suspects and cops.</p>
        <p>To whatever degree Miranda ever impeded law enforcement, its effect abated a long time time ago. I have been practicing criminal law for nearly 22 years now, eight years as a federal prosecutor and 14 years in private practice. In that time, I have been involved in exactly one case where the result was changed after a confession was declared inadmissible under Miranda, and that matter involved a juvenile who, in addition to not being told his rights, did not enjoy the benefit of a number of other safeguards applied in Illinois to the questioning of minors.</p>
        <p>Nor is my experience idiosyncratic. After a couple of hours of computer research, I could not find a single reported decision in Illinois in the last 12 months in which a confession was suppressed or a conviction reversed because of a Miranda violation.</p>
        <p>To a great extent, as the court recognized on Monday in Dickerson v. United States, courts and cops have accommodated themselves to the rule. The more conservative justices who ascended to the Supreme Court after the Warren years have narrowed the decision's grand mandate, refining, for example, what amounts to interrogation for Miranda purposes, or sometimes allowing subsequent statements to be admitted even if a defendant initially claimed his Miranda rights.</p>
        <p>As for the police, the court is right when it says that law enforcement practices have adjusted to Miranda's strictures. As a prosecutor, I never noted that federal agents much resented Miranda, even though some, like those in the Internal Revenue Service, were required to give warning when simply questioning someone.</p>
        <p>In eight years, I never had a statement excluded from evidence because of the Miranda rule. The agents accepted the standard and often applied it skillfully. I remember a veteran F.B.I. agent dispensing the Miranda warnings to a suspect before we took him before a grand jury, a practice required by the Justice Department. As one of my colleagues commented, the warning sounded so avuncular, you just about expected the agent to put his arm around the prospective defendant's shoulders.</p>
        <p>Granted, the federal agents with whom I worked were most often investigating white-collar crime, while most of the objections to Miranda have come from urban police, whose confrontations with suspects are often far more spontaneous. They are frequently faced with sorting out on the fly whether they intend to let a suspect go, which determines whether the Miranda warnings are required.</p>
        <p>In the last decade, I've talked to enough people arrested in Chicago who said they were not read their rights during their initial interrogation that I wonder if some cops have reached a different accommodation with Miranda.</p>
        <p>While I resent these kinds of tactics, I don't think many of these defendants, if given the Miranda warnings, would have shut up or asked for a lawyer. As the Supreme Court noted, Miranda by now is part of our national culture, well understood by anyone who has ever watched TV. Confronted with an accusation, most people can't resist the impulse to explain, probably fearing that remaining silent would make them look guilty.</p>
        <p>So if Miranda makes little difference in the daily world of law enforcement, why is it so heartening to see it still standing? Because Miranda is an expression of some fundamental concepts about the law we all should hold dear. One is equality before the law. Miranda, in essence, says that despite the vast disparities in education and income in our society, everyone in a confrontation with the state will possess the same critical knowledge about how the system works.</p>
        <p>Second, the fact that some cops resent giving warnings has always been evidence in my mind of the warnings' value. Miranda's requirements are, in the most stereotypical police view, the intrusive work of nosy outsiders from the world of the law, people sitting in the serene comfort of their cushy offices and judicial chambers, telling the police how to handle things on the dangerous streets.</p>
        <p>But cops should recognize that no matter how noisy their protests, or how much they chafe, they are always going to be subject to civilian authority. Catching bad guys is important, but it is not the only thing this society values; we also care about certain minimal standards of decency in the government's treatment of citizens and limits on the authority of the state.</p>
        <p>The requirement to recite Miranda is an important reminder to the police that the war on lawlessness is always subject to the guidance of the law. This week's decision, by a court that is not perceived as particularly hostile to law enforcement, is a needed reaffirmation of that message.</p>
        <p>Scott Turow is the author of ''Presumed Innocent'' and ''Personal Injuries.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Scott Turow is the author of ''Presumed Innocent'' and ''Personal Injuries.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
