<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lazio Accuses Mrs. Clinton Of Waging Fear Campaign</title>
    <meta content="28HILL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210970"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bumiller, Elisabeth</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lazio, Rick A (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000628T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE5DF1130F93BA15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1062" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lazio Accuses Mrs. Clinton Of Waging Fear Campaign</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELISABETH BUMILLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bumiller, Elisabeth</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Representative Rick A Lazio accuses Hillary Rodham Clinton of waging campaign based on fear and warns that her latest television commercials attacking his record will backfire; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Representative Rick A. Lazio last night accused Hillary Rodham Clinton of waging a campaign based on fear and warned that her latest television commercials attacking his record would backfire.</p>
        <p>''I know what these attack ads are all about,'' Mr. Lazio said at a sparsely attended fund-raiser at the Sheraton Hotel in Midtown Manhattan. ''They're about fear.'' He added, ''If these attacks continue, my opponent will learn this about New York: Bend the truth, and you will face the consequences. New Yorkers will not elect a person they cannot trust.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Representative Rick A. Lazio last night accused Hillary Rodham Clinton of waging a campaign based on fear and warned that her latest television commercials attacking his record would backfire.</p>
        <p>''I know what these attack ads are all about,'' Mr. Lazio said at a sparsely attended fund-raiser at the Sheraton Hotel in Midtown Manhattan. ''They're about fear.'' He added, ''If these attacks continue, my opponent will learn this about New York: Bend the truth, and you will face the consequences. New Yorkers will not elect a person they cannot trust.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio's escalating attacks came in response to Mrs. Clinton's intensified criticism in recent weeks, both for his votes in Congress and his positions on gun control, abortion and education financing. Mrs. Clinton has also released a series of television advertisements attacking Mr. Lazio for what she says is his opposition to legislation on hate crimes and health care.</p>
        <p>''I am sorry to say that my opponent is now on her fifth negative attack ad,'' Mr. Lazio said as the crowd booed to show their distaste for the first lady. ''That makes five negative attack ads over the last 10 days.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio added that the advertisements were designed ''to fool New Yorkers, to drag New Yorkers down.'' Then he invoked the name of the New York senator whom he and Mrs. Clinton are seeking to replace: ''You know, Pat Moynihan never needed to use attack ads like that.''</p>
        <p>Next he addressed his opponent: ''Maybe, Mrs. Clinton, we shouldn't expect you to know that. Because you've never seen a New York campaign. You've never lived here through a New York campaign.''</p>
        <p>His predecessor in the race, Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani, picked up where the congressman had left off. ''I mean it really is hard when you step back from this to completely assess the arrogance of all this,'' Mr. Giuliani said. ''Never having lived here, never having held public office and, 'I want to be your senator?' I mean, we have to demand more than that, don't we?'' The mayor also retooled one of his favorite insults from his days as Mrs. Clinton's opponent, aiming again at one of Chappaqua's newest residents. ''I think what they should do is put Rick and Hillary in an automobile at La Guardia Airport and figure out who can actually get home on their own,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Karen Dunn, a spokeswoman for Mrs. Clinton's campaign, responded:  ''Rick Lazio couldn't get through his announcement speech without attacking Hillary Clinton. It's clear that things haven't changed much. What New Yorkers will really learn in this race is that Rick Lazio has a voting record he can't defend.''</p>
        <p>Republican officials said the Sheraton fund-raiser and another one for Mr. Lazio were expected to raise $1.7 million. Nonetheless, the ballroom at the Sheraton was only a quarter full at best, and many Republicans were asking last night whose idea it was to rent such a large space.</p>
        <p>Earlier in the day, Mrs. Clinton gave a detailed response to Mr. Lazio's contention that the Clinton administration is to blame for federal gasoline taxes that have caused higher prices at the pumps. She argued that New York stands to lose millions of dollars in revenue for highway construction if those taxes are suspended or repealed, as Mr. Lazio urged by calling for the 18.3 cents per gallon federal tax to be lifted.</p>
        <p>''Here in Buffalo it's gone up 50 cents since last year and oil company profits have gone up almost as much as 500 percent,'' Mrs. Clinton said. ''Prices are out of control for consumers and profits are out of line for the oil companies.''</p>
        <p>Gas prices in New York average about $1.68 per gallon for regular, a 41 percent increase over this period last year and among the highest ever registered.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio, on a campaign swing in upstate New York that also included the Buffalo area, asked on Monday for a six-month suspension of the 18.3 cents per gallon federal tax, and suggested that part of it, a 4.3 cents per gallon tax enacted seven years ago, be eliminated. He repeated his case at an Eastchester gas station yesterday, accusing Mrs. Clinton of being tardy on the issue and out of touch with average New York customers.</p>
        <p>Mayor Giuliani joined the fray at a Manhattan gas station, saying the Clinton administration had not applied sufficient pressure on oil-producing nations to increase oil output. He said a survey of 80 city gas stations by the Department of Consumer Affairs found an average price of $1.78 a gallon for regular.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton agreed that prices were high and that oil-producing nations should be pressured to increase their output, She said people should consider other solutions advocated by Vice President Al Gore, including expanding the use of alternative technology to reduce the nation's dependency on foreign oil.</p>
        <p>But Mrs. Clinton argued that the gas tax ''is one of the few exceptions where we get more money back than we send to Washington.''</p>
        <p>''Here's what New York pays in the gas tax: over $300 million dollars a year,'' she said, holding up her charts. ''I got that figure from my opponent's press release. And the amount that New York State gets back from Washington in highway funding is $477 million a year. So our surplus is almost $177 million a year.'' Another chart laid out individual oil company profits that she called excessive.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio, she added, does not understand the impact that his proposal ''would have on the jobs in construction projects that we need to improve transportation, especially here in western New York, especially in Buffalo.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton earlier spoke at a luncheon in Buffalo for the TAP, a political action committee that raises money for women who are running for state or local office and who support abortion rights. She said ''the humanization of politics'' means it is a misnomer to call issues like education, child care and abortion rights ''women's issues.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
