<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In the Boom, Desperately Seeking Bean Counters</title>
    <meta content="Y28ACC$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210905"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MANAGEMENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accounting and Accountants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hiring and Promotion</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Winter, Greg</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Accounting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accounting and Accountants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hiring and Promotion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000628T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE5DC1030F93BA15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1193" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In the Boom, Desperately Seeking Bean Counters</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GREG WINTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Winter, Greg</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Many of nation's largest accounting firms and associations, competing for smallest pool of college graduates of accounting programs in more than a decade, have begun grooming talent at secondary schools, latest battlefield in industrywide recruitment war; with scholarships and internships in hand, they are hoping to resuscitate field that is rapidly losing conscripts to technology fields and glamour of being entrepreneur; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When jobs are plentiful but applicants scarce, where do accountants go to drum up enthusiasm for a profession whose very name evokes images of numbers-crunching nerds with penholders in their shirt pockets?</p>
        <p>As it turns out, they now go to the one place where hostility to all things uncool burns hottest: high schools.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When jobs are plentiful but applicants scarce, where do accountants go to drum up enthusiasm for a profession whose very name evokes images of numbers-crunching nerds with penholders in their shirt pockets?</p>
        <p>As it turns out, they now go to the one place where hostility to all things uncool burns hottest: high schools.</p>
        <p>Competing for the smallest pool of college graduates of accounting programs in more than a decade, many of the nation's largest accounting firms and associations have begun grooming talent at secondary schools, the latest battlefield in an industrywide recruitment war. With scholarships and internships in hand, they are hoping to resuscitate a field that is rapidly losing conscripts to the wonders of technology and the glamour of being an entrepreneur.</p>
        <p>''We're making big investments in the development of a high school pipeline,'' said James Hayes, a partner at PricewaterhouseCoopers who sends recruiters to roughly 3,000 schools a year to scout promising students. ''High school may almost be too late, and at some point we have to start looking at middle schools.''</p>
        <p>Which is not to say that the Big Five accounting firms -- Arthur Andersen, Deloitte &amp; Touche, Ernst &amp; Young, KPMG and PricewaterhouseCoopers -- have stopped their hiring efforts on college campuses. In fact, driven by a boom in business, they are crafting ever-wilder ways of grabbing college students' attention and winning their loyalty. Ernst &amp; Young now sends its interns to Disney World, while Arthur Andersen sponsors a national tax Olympics every year that awards the winning school $20,000 in scholarships.</p>
        <p>But a 23 percent drop in enrollment in college accounting programs since 1996 -- meaning that about 10,000 fewer accounting graduates come into the workplace -- has persuaded many in the industry to focus on still younger students, before they are whisked away by more scintillating majors. Their goal is not to pluck recruits fresh from high school, but to plant the corporate flag and push college-bound students into the field.</p>
        <p>''One objective is to get them exposed to careers in accounting,'' said Allen Boston, a recruiter with Ernst &amp; Young who offers college scholarships to high school students from 15 states. ''The other is to get them to know Ernst &amp; Young.''</p>
        <p>Leading the charge is the profession's primary association, the American Institute of Certified Public Accountants, which will send an accounting curriculum to about 10,000 high schools this fall.</p>
        <p>As much public relations as instruction, the institute's lessons promote accounting across the disciplines, from physics to social studies. History becomes a class on how sleuthing accountants caught Al Capone; chemistry becomes a chance to set the price of an electric car; and so on. Anything, in fact, to topple the stereotype of the humorless drone in a back room.</p>
        <p>Some high school students are buying it. Lindsey Whitneck, who graduated from Bristol Central High School in Connecticut this month, says distaste for her course work had soured her on going to college. But after taking classes with one of the accounting curriculum's designers, she took an after-school bookkeeping job last fall and has now enrolled in Central Connecticut State University to major in accounting.</p>
        <p>''It's like accounting saved me,'' Ms. Whitneck said, although she added: ''Everyone in my family thinks it's only a bunch of numbers on paper. They just don't understand.''</p>
        <p>To be sure, such converts remain rare, college professors say. The profession holds a certain appeal in tough times; when jobs are scarce, a certified public accountant is nearly assured employment. In an economy that promises young people fun and riches elsewhere, however, the profession must redouble its recruiting.</p>
        <p>College students ''don't want to dedicate themselves to the work it takes to get a technical degree,'' said Sally Jones, an accounting professor at the University of Virginia, where accounting majors have dropped more than 50 percent since 1992, despite rising applications to the business school.</p>
        <p>''There's such a demand for business students that they are going to work in start-ups, finance, everything but accounting,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Making matters worse, almost all states now require an extra year of college courses before students can take exams to get a license in accounting. The new rules, adopted at the accounting institute's urging in the late 1980's, only recently went into effect.</p>
        <p>''The timing was unfortunate,'' said Bea Sanders, the institute's academic director. ''Ten years ago, no one imagined that there would be a whole new economy drawing on the pool.''</p>
        <p>The number of first-time takers of C.P.A. exams has fallen 13 percent since 1992, the institute says. And with fewer accountants to choose from, many firms have taken to raiding one another for talent or simply buying smaller practices.</p>
        <p>''There's just nobody left to employ,'' lamented Kim Fantaci, director of the National Association of Certified Public Accounting Firms, an association of 47 small to midsize practices.</p>
        <p>Not surprisingly, the shortage has been a boon to salaries. In an April survey of 70 academic disciplines at more than 120 schools, the National Association of Colleges and Employers reported an 8.8 percent increase in starting pay -- now about $37,000 -- for accounting graduates, second only to the gain for information-systems majors.</p>
        <p>But accounting salaries still lag behind those in high technology, and firms have proved reluctant to offer stock options, the holy grail of job seekers these days.</p>
        <p>''People feel that they are covering their bets better by getting a broader business degree,'' said Jane Rubin, an accreditation specialist at the International Association for Management Education.</p>
        <p>Ms. Rubin supports efforts to arouse teenagers' curiosity, though she thinks programs so far are insufficient. ''There's going to have to be a much more comprehensive master P.R. plan than even what's been envisioned so far,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Maybe so, but the Big Five firms still stand to benefit from the early exposure of their profession to young people. ''Eventually these kids are going to be adults with businesses who are going to use their services,'' said Ms. Sanders, the accounting institute's academic director.</p>
        <p>The firms themselves have no illusions about their high-school expeditions. Easily distracted, convinced their careers are eons away, teenagers are moving targets, difficult to track through college and beyond, they acknowledge.</p>
        <p>But, they add, they have no choice but to take aim at them.</p>
        <p>''As difficult as it is, given the number of high schools that are out there, we need to do more,'' said William Nickey, New York recruiting director for Deloitte &amp; Touche. ''Even if the economy slows down, we're always going to need more accountants than we're currently producing.''</p>
        <p>MANAGEMENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
