<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'Tutti Frutti' Indeed! (Alop-Bam-Boom, Too)</title>
    <meta content="28RICH$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210885"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="POP REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Little Richard (Richard Penniman)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ratliff, Ben</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000628T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901EFDF1030F93BA15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="624" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'Tutti Frutti' Indeed! (Alop-Bam-Boom, Too)</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN RATLIFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ratliff, Ben</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ben Ratliff reviews performance by singer Little Richard (Richard Penniman) and his band at B B King Blues club (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''I am the beautiful Little Richard,'' said Richard Penniman, with the utmost assuredness, opening his eyes wide and grinning. ''I know you've seen me on television, but now I'm in person so you know I ain't lying.'' He spotted a professional photographer in the audience fiddling with a camera. ''You're a picture-maker,'' he said. ''I can see it in your eyes. Would you mind getting up and going? I'm almost 70 years old. They've been doing that to me forever, and I never did make a dime from those pictures.'' He waited until his request was honored.</p>
        <p>''Now,'' he continued, ''I want all the ladies to say 'whooo!' Only real ladies -- no imitations, no false vibrations. If you ain't a real lady, shaddup.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''I am the beautiful Little Richard,'' said Richard Penniman, with the utmost assuredness, opening his eyes wide and grinning. ''I know you've seen me on television, but now I'm in person so you know I ain't lying.'' He spotted a professional photographer in the audience fiddling with a camera. ''You're a picture-maker,'' he said. ''I can see it in your eyes. Would you mind getting up and going? I'm almost 70 years old. They've been doing that to me forever, and I never did make a dime from those pictures.'' He waited until his request was honored.</p>
        <p>''Now,'' he continued, ''I want all the ladies to say 'whooo!' Only real ladies -- no imitations, no false vibrations. If you ain't a real lady, shaddup.''</p>
        <p>This was Little Richard, outfitted entirely in blue -- navy polka-dots on a dark mesh shirt, azure pants -- warming up his crowd at the B. B. King Blues club on Monday night.  But ''warming up'' doesn't quite capture it; ''barbecuing'' is more the word.</p>
        <p>For 90 minutes, his band pumped out a roadhouse mixture of funk and rock 'n' roll, pure eighth-note battering to match Little Richard's driving right hand on the piano. The shape of it was wild overkill: two drummers, two bassists, two saxophonists, at times two electric guitars.</p>
        <p>Almost -- not quite, but almost -- as energized as its leader, this band could be easily manipulated; most of the songs were played as chorus after chorus of the same basic idea, without bridges or a lot of chord changes, so it was easy for Little Richard to stop on a dime and start up something new.</p>
        <p>There were the songs, enacted like speed trials, some of them only one or two choruses long -- and there was the free-ranging commentary, both during and between numbers. The show resembled a party, and from the stage Little Richard mingled with his guests. There was ''Blueberry Hill,'' during which the audience started to sing along.  (''That sounds so good, it's like singin' with Mitch Miller!''); ''Boney Maronie'' (''I'm gonna scream like a white lady!''); ''It Hurts Me Too'' (''I love that little part of that song -- it makes my big toe shoot up in my boot! Shaddup! I'm gonna play it again!'').</p>
        <p>Then came ''Goodnight Irene'' (''The God of Abraham is the god of the world!''); ''Tutti Frutti'' (''I used to be a dishwasher, and I was the most beautiful dishwasher in the world. I used to have to put my beautiful arm down in those tall pots and scrub the food off them.''); ''I Saw Her Standing There'' (''I still sing the songs in the same keys, you know!'') and ''After Hours'' (''You remember Count Basie? I remember growing up in Macon, Ga., and seeing Andy Kirk, Cootie Williams, Hot Lips Page . . . '')</p>
        <p>It was a slow process, but Little Richard's voice got looser and began to thud more confidently into the high notes; the belted phrasing of his lyrics picked up the assertiveness of his early records. By the time he got to ''Lucille,'' he demanded entirely blue lighting and he went for the song's jugular, lodging a wild scream in the girl's name. Even at its peak this wasn't memorable music, per se; but as a performance, it was to be savored.</p>
        <p>POP REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
