<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Stevenson Is Talkative, Except About Erving</title>
    <meta content="28WIMB$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210954"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TENNIS: NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wimbledon Tennis Tournament</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Roberts, Selena</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stevenson, Alexandra</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wimbledon Tennis Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000628T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E2D71030F93BA15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="676" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Stevenson Is Talkative, Except About Erving</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SELENA ROBERTS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Roberts, Selena</byline>
      <dateline>WIMBLEDON, England, June 27</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Wimbledon notebook column discusses Alexandra Stevenson's first round victory (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A loquacious Alexandra Stevenson floated off the court after her first-round victory today, ready to discuss anything from race to politics to her favorite actress, Julia Roberts.</p>
        <p>The only one-word response came when she was asked if the trauma Julius Erving was experiencing in coping with the disappearance of his son Corey would encourage her to call him. One year ago, while Stevenson was on her way to becoming the first female qualifier to reach the Wimbledon semifinals, it was disclosed that Erving was her biological father and that she has no relationship with him.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A loquacious Alexandra Stevenson floated off the court after her first-round victory today, ready to discuss anything from race to politics to her favorite actress, Julia Roberts.</p>
        <p>The only one-word response came when she was asked if the trauma Julius Erving was experiencing in coping with the disappearance of his son Corey would encourage her to call him. One year ago, while Stevenson was on her way to becoming the first female qualifier to reach the Wimbledon semifinals, it was disclosed that Erving was her biological father and that she has no relationship with him.</p>
        <p>''No,'' Stevenson said about the possibility of contacting him now.</p>
        <p>To everything else, there were ample answers in a giddy dialogue that followed her 7-5, 7-6 (3) victory against the Hungarian Rita Kuti Kis, No. 51 in the WTA ranking. First up, racism on the tour.</p>
        <p>''I think that it's naive to think there is no racism in the world,'' said Stevenson, ranked 46th. ''The tour is part of the world. You're going to get it wherever you go.</p>
        <p>''Being multicultural, being pink, being blue, being whatever, there are different cultures out there. You have to face it. It's made me tougher.''</p>
        <p>There was some question as to whether Stevenson's decision to play in South Carolina -- in a tournament Serena and Venus Williams boycotted because of the Confederate flag controversy -- had disrupted her friendship with the two sisters. Stevenson said no, and did add that she spoke to the governor while in South Carolina to voice her opinion.</p>
        <p>''I think it helped because the house voted it down right after I went in and talked about it,'' Stevenson said. ''The governor wrote me a letter saying: 'Thank you. I think you helped.'</p>
        <p>''I think they realized if a 19-year-old could go into the state and tell them it's wrong, discuss it with them, approach it in a positive way, they realize their mistake. It should come down. Serena had a different approach, but that's not going to ruin our friendship.''</p>
        <p>Same Old Stories</p>
        <p>Nathalie Tauziat's tell-all book, ''The Underside of Women's Tennis,'' isn't rattling too many on the tour. Her assertions that the Williams sisters are aloof, that Martina Hingis is too quick too speak, that the marketing of the tour is focused too much on Anna Kournikova is nothing new.</p>
        <p>''I think she could have told a lot more,'' Lindsay Davenport said, igniting laughter in the interview room. ''I think all these players could write a much better book.</p>
        <p>''I don't think she said anything all that outrageous or something that the players were like, 'Oh, my gosh, I don't believe she said that.' ''</p>
        <p>Boycott Support</p>
        <p>Wayne Ferreira and Neville Godwin of South Africa accused Wimbledon officials of ''rigging'' the seedings to favor certain players.</p>
        <p>The South Africans sided with the three Spaniards who withdrew from Wimbledon over the weekend, complaining about a seeding system that gives preference to grass-court players. Ferreira and Godwin, who won their first-round matches today, applauded Alex Corretja, Albert Costa and Juan Carlos Ferrero for taking a stand.</p>
        <p>Wimbledon seeds players according to their ability on grass. But the Wimbledon chairman, Tim Phillips, said on Sunday that the All England Club may change its system next year and waived fines against the Spaniards.</p>
        <p>Ferreira pointed out the advantage players like Tim Henman and Richard Krajicek have by being seeded despite ATP rankings lower than No. 16.</p>
        <p>''Even the way they have done it stinks,'' Ferreira said, pointing to seeded treatment of the adopted Briton Greg Rusedski (who was upset Monday by Vince Spadea) and the homegrown Henman, who were both drawn away from Pete Sampras and Andre Agassi. ''They have put Rusedski at 14 so he won't have to play Sampras or Agassi in the Round of 16, and Henman at eight so he won't meet them until the quarterfinals at least. They can argue what they like. That's rigging the draw.'' (AP)</p>
        <p>TENNIS: NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
