<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>World Briefing</title>
    <meta content="Y28BRI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210913"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000628T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E0DB1030F93BA15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1704" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>World Briefing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by Terence Neilan</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>NORTHERN IRELAND: TROOP BUILDUP  Some 2,000 British troops are being flown in to increase security levels after the Parades Commission ruled that members of the militant Protestant Orange Order cannot follow a march path through a Catholic neighborhood after services at Drumcree parish next month. Similar increases were made in recent years before the so-called marching season, which has set off rioting across the province.</p>
        <p>Warren Hoge (NYT)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>NORTHERN IRELAND: TROOP BUILDUP  Some 2,000 British troops are being flown in to increase security levels after the Parades Commission ruled that members of the militant Protestant Orange Order cannot follow a march path through a Catholic neighborhood after services at Drumcree parish next month. Similar increases were made in recent years before the so-called marching season, which has set off rioting across the province.</p>
        <p>Warren Hoge (NYT)</p>
        <p>BRITAIN: ROYAL SUGGESTION  A member of Prime Minister Tony Blair's cabinet has suggested that the royal family be moved out of Buckingham Palace and rehoused in a modern building. Cabinet Office Minister Mo Mowlam told a magazine that ''if people want a monarch of the new century, they should have a palace of the new century.'' Distancing Mr. Blair from the comment, a Downing Street spokesman said, ''The Queen lives in Buckingham Palace, and I don't think she's intending to move and the prime minister doesn't think she should.''</p>
        <p>Warren Hoge (NYT)</p>
        <p>RUSSIA: YELTSIN AIDE CLEARED  Prosecutors said they had no evidence that former President Boris N. Yeltsin's senior aide and close friend, Pavel Borodin, took bribes in awarding a huge contract to restore the Kremlin to the Swiss company Mabetex. The chief Russian investigator in the case told the Interfax news service that although the Swiss have given him 10 huge files, none contain any evidence that the bribes took place.</p>
        <p>Michael Wines (NYT)</p>
        <p>KOSOVO: U.N. RESUMES WORK  The United Nations high commissioner for refugees said it would resume operations in the Serb-dominated northern part of Kosovo, including in the divided town of Mitrovica, after the Serbian leadership apologized for the violence last Wednesday and said it supported the arrest of the perpetrators. Nine ethnic Albanian families have been forced from their homes in northern Mitrovica in the last week and more than 20 foreign aid workers have been threatened by the Serb population, the agency said.</p>
        <p>Carlotta Gall (NYT)</p>
        <p>ASIA</p>
        <p>KAZAKHSTAN: PRESIDENT'S NEW POWERS  Kazakhstan's autocratic president, Nursultan Nazarbayev, won new powers that would prolong his influence even should he retire as scheduled when his term ends in 2006. Under legislation passed after three hours of debate. Mr. Nazarbayev was granted a permanent seat on the Kazakh Security Council and the right to address the population and major state bodies at will. Mr. Nazarbayev, who ran Kazakhstan when it was a Soviet republic, has dominated the country since a 1995 referendum expanded his powers.</p>
        <p>Michael Wines (NYT)</p>
        <p>CHINA: CRITICISM FOR BRITAIN  China condemned Britain for letting former President Lee Teng-hui of Taiwan visit Britain, calling him a troublemaker who continues to work for Taiwan's independence from the mainland. Mr. Lee left yesterday for his first trip abroad since stepping down last month after 12 years as president. The reason given for the trip was to attend the high school graduation of a granddaughter.</p>
        <p>Erik Eckholm (NYT)</p>
        <p>KOREAS: TALKS STUMBLE  Red Cross talks between North and South Korea to reunite families separated by the Korean War stumbled because of disagreements over the repatriation of Communist spies held in the South. Officials began a four-day session, but the talks adjourned in 80 minutes and will not resume until tomorrow as North Korea insisted that South Korea repatriate convicted North Korean spies before reunions of separated families take place.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>MIDDLE EAST</p>
        <p>ISRAEL: REFORM PRAYERS  Led by a female cantor, left, Reform Jews prayed near the Western Wall, Judaism's holiest site, without being heckled -- a rare occurrence. The police set up two rows of steel barricades about 150 yards from the wall. They guarded the perimeter, anticipating a demonstration by rigorously observant Jews, who oppose the concept of men and women praying together and a woman chanting the service.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>IRAN: TEHRAN PROTEST  About 1,000 demonstrators burned tires and blocked a main road in a Tehran suburb to protest what they say is a lack of basic amenities, witnesses said. The protesters, who were demanding an end to cuts in water and other services, began their protest in the morning and dispersed peacefully when the police moved in, the witnesses said.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>THE AMERICAS</p>
        <p>CANADA: NEW U.S. ENVOY  The new ambassador to the United States will be Michael Kergin, Prime Minister Jean Chretien's top foreign policy adviser. Mr. Kergin, who replaces Raymond A. J, Chretien, was Canada's ambassador to Cuba from 1986 to 1989 and later directed the security intelligence branch of the foreign ministry.</p>
        <p>James Brooke (NYT)</p>
        <p>AFRICA</p>
        <p>SUDAN: NEW PARTY  The Islamist leader Hassan Turabi formed his own party a day after he was replaced as head of the ruling National Congress Party. Thousands of supporters gathered outside his Khartoum house to celebrate the founding of his Popular National Congress Party.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>RWANDA: EX-PREMIER APPEALS  Former Prime Minister Jean Kambanda began an appeal against his conviction at the United Nations international criminal tribunal for involvement in Rwanda's 1994 blood bath. Mr. Kambanda was sentenced to life imprisonment in September 1998 after confessing to a role in the killing frenzy, in which Hutu killed 800,000 mainly Tutsi civilians. Mr. Kambanda said he wanted to retract his confession and plea agreement, saying he had not been properly advised by his lawyer.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
