<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Airlines Are Faulted on Candor and Promises</title>
    <meta content="Y28AIRL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210946"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Delays (Transportation)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Traffic Control</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Transportation Department</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mead, Kenneth</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wald, Matthew L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Delays (Transportation)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Traffic Control</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transportation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000628T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E7D71030F93BA15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="506" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Airlines Are Faulted on Candor and Promises</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wald, Matthew L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 27</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Transportation Department report charges that airlines, required to inform passengers about delays, often blame air traffic control even if real reason is bad weather, crew shortage or maintenance problem; inspector general Kenneth Mead sees room for improvement on airlines' promise to offer consumers lowest fare (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Airlines, required to tell their passengers if a flight will be delayed, often blame air traffic control, even if the real reason is bad weather, a shortage of crew members or maintenance problems, the Transportation Department said in a report today.</p>
        <p>The report, intended to gauge how well the airlines are meeting their customer service commitments, was ordered by Congress last fall and issued by the department's inspector general.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Airlines, required to tell their passengers if a flight will be delayed, often blame air traffic control, even if the real reason is bad weather, a shortage of crew members or maintenance problems, the Transportation Department said in a report today.</p>
        <p>The report, intended to gauge how well the airlines are meeting their customer service commitments, was ordered by Congress last fall and issued by the department's inspector general.</p>
        <p>The report said there was ''major room for improvement in the accuracy, reliability and timeliness of the airlines' communications to customers about the status of flights.'' In general, the inspector general found, the airlines were making a ''clear and genuine'' effort to keep their promises but that the results were mixed. The airlines ''have a ways to go to restore customer confidence,'' the report said.</p>
        <p>The airlines agreed to improve service last year to stave off legislation that would have required such action. The House and Senate held hearings on the issue because of growing complaints about overbooking, lost baggage and delays, including an incident in Detroit last year,  when hundreds of Northwest Airlines passengers were stuck on snowbound planes for up to eight hours.</p>
        <p>The inspector general, Kenneth Mead, said there was still room for improvement on the airlines' promise to offer shoppers the lowest fare for which they are eligible. In some cases, the report said, telephone ticket agents did not ask callers if they were willing to adjust their itineraries to get a cheaper fare.</p>
        <p>The airlines promised to use their best efforts to return misrouted bags within 24 hours, but the report found that the carriers cannot agree on what 24 hours means. Some started the clock when a passenger filed a missing bag claim, while others started it only when the bag finally arrived at the destination airport.</p>
        <p>The airlines, at a news briefing earlier today, said they had generally improved. American Airlines said it was providing more leg room on all domestic flights by removing some seats; Continental said it had set up Service Planning Centers at hub airports to help re-book passengers or find them hotel reservations. Delta said it was installing automated ticketing kiosks to cut waiting time, and United said it was providing ''mobile workstations'' to help reduce lines when passengers rush to rebook.</p>
        <p>But Senator Ron Wyden, Democrat of Oregon, said the report was evidence that Congress should have made the improvements mandatory, and said he would introduce legislation. ''This is hard, independent evidence that there is a big gap between what the airlines have promised the passengers and what they have actually delivered,'' Mr. Wyden said.</p>
        <p>''The passenger is not being given straight information,'' he said, referring to announcements on flight delays. And if ticket agents do not offer the lowest fare, he said, ''this suggests to me that the airlines are not making it a particularly high priority for their personnel.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
