<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Smackdown: Viacom Wins USA's Wrestling</title>
    <meta content="Y28TUB$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210960"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wrestling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television and Radio Programming</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">World Wrestling Federation Entertainment Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Usa Networks Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Viacom Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">TNN (Cable Channel)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carter, Bill</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Redstone, Sumner M</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Raw Is War (TV Program)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Live Wire (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wrestling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000628T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E4D61030F93BA15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="889" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Smackdown: Viacom Wins USA's Wrestling</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL CARTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Carter, Bill</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Hourlong wrestling shows produced by World Wrestling Federation Entertainment Inc, most popular weekly programs on cable television, will leave USA cable network in fall and move to cable channels owned by Viacom as result of decision in Delaware court; decision, which awards rights of WWF programs to Viacom based on higher bid that court said USA had not matched as required by its contract, is widely seen as serious blow to USA Networks Inc, which had sued to try to prevent Viacom from buying away five hours of wrestling shows carried on USA; Viacom chairman Sumner M Redstone says Viacom plans to revamp TNN programming in coming television season, and wrestling will be biggest part of that improvement; wrestling shows Raw Is War and Live Wire will shift to TNN (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The most popular weekly programs on cable television, hourlong wrestling shows produced by World Wrestling Federation Entertainment Inc., will leave the USA cable network in the fall and move to cable channels owned by Viacom as a result of a decision yesterday in a Delaware court.</p>
        <p>The decision, which awarded the rights to W.W.F. programs to Viacom based on a higher bid that the court said USA had not matched as required by its contract, was widely seen as a serious blow to USA Networks Inc., which had sued to try to prevent Viacom from buying away the five hours of wrestling shows carried on USA.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The most popular weekly programs on cable television, hourlong wrestling shows produced by World Wrestling Federation Entertainment Inc., will leave the USA cable network in the fall and move to cable channels owned by Viacom as a result of a decision yesterday in a Delaware court.</p>
        <p>The decision, which awarded the rights to W.W.F. programs to Viacom based on a higher bid that the court said USA had not matched as required by its contract, was widely seen as a serious blow to USA Networks Inc., which had sued to try to prevent Viacom from buying away the five hours of wrestling shows carried on USA.</p>
        <p>Sumner M. Redstone, the chairman of Viacom, said, ''This is a much more important victory for us than most people know.'' In particular, he said, the shift will benefit the TNN cable channel, which was previously owned by CBS and is now part of Viacom's MTV Networks. The channel, once known as The Nashville Network, had mainly been known for programming oriented to country music fans.</p>
        <p>Viacom plans to revamp TNN programming in the coming television season, and wrestling will be the biggest part of that improvement, Mr. Redstone said.</p>
        <p>Among other W.W.F. programs, two Monday night wrestling shows, ''Raw Is War'' and ''Live Wire,'' which are routinely watched more than any other shows on cable television, will shift to TNN.</p>
        <p>''That will surely mean a big increase in the distribution of the channel,'' Mr. Redstone said. ''TNN has not been in the same class as other MTV networks, and now it clearly will be. As a result of this and other programming we plan for that channel, TNN will become a much more valuable asset for Viacom.''</p>
        <p>The loss of wrestling may have the opposite effect on USA, though the channel's executives took pains yesterday to try to play down the effect on the channel. In a statement, Stephen Chao, the president of USA Cable, said, ''We would have preferred a different decision, but, as we said, the loss of the W.W.F. will have a negligible effect on our ratings and a positive effect on our profits.''</p>
        <p>USA executives had previously tried to argue that wrestling was not all that important to the USA channel because other programming could replace it and because it was never as profitable as its ratings would seem to indicate since the wrestling company itself took most of the advertising revenue.</p>
        <p>Neither Mr. Chao, nor Barry Diller, the chairman of USA Networks, nor any other USA executive would comment further, said Ron Sado, a USA spokesman.</p>
        <p>But one executive involved in the lawsuit noted that USA executives had testified that W.W.F. programming was highly profitable and amounted to a crown jewel in the schedule because it brought more viewers to other USA programs.</p>
        <p>USA executives have not said what programs will replace wrestling, though the channel had previously announced a lineup of potential new shows including a comedy about warring neighbors and a drama about female bounty hunters.</p>
        <p>The court case centered on USA's contention that it did not have to match every aspect of a Viacom offer to satisfy a clause in its contract that allowed its deal with the wrestling company to continue as long as it matched any new offer.</p>
        <p>Specifically, USA argued that it should not have to match promises like promotion on radio and billboards and sale to international television channels and an agreement not to pre-empt the wrestling shows regularly, as USA Network had done with programs like the Westminster Kennel Club Dog Show. The decision by Chancellor William B. Chandler III of Delaware Chancery Court found that USA was obligated to match on those points, though not on some others, like carrying a new package of football games being produced by the wrestling company.</p>
        <p>Viacom plans to carry games of the new eight-team football league, XFL, on TNN on Sunday afternoons as well as on one of its broadcast outlets, the UPN network, on Sunday nights. It will also shift one of the W.W.F. wrestling shows, ''Sunday Night Heat,'' to MTV, where it will have a younger, more rock-music-oriented format.</p>
        <p>In addition, Viacom has promised to stage W.W.F. events at its theme parks and to stage pay-per-view wrestling events at its theaters in Canada.</p>
        <p>The decision against USA comes at a time of transition in part of its ownership. USA Networks is 45 percent owned by the Seagram Company, which is being acquired by the French media company Vivendi. An  executive close to the deal said yesterday that the loss of the wrestling programming was unlikely to affect the Seagram-Vivendi deal.</p>
        <p>Mr. Redstone, who has had previous battles with Mr. Diller, most notably a financial battle over the Paramount studio in 1994, which Mr. Redstone also won, said, ''I don't feel badly about winning against my friend Barry Diller.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
