<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Chasing Trump Or the Pink Dog Of Patience</title>
    <meta content="28MYJO$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Workplace" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Job Market" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210870"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MY JOB"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Subpoenas</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Serving by Irving (Co)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rapp, Ellen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Botwinick, Irving</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000628T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFD81230F93BA15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="683" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Chasing Trump Or the Pink Dog Of Patience</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By IRVING BOTWINICK; Written with Ellen Rapp.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Botwinick, Irving; Rapp, Ellen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>My Job column focuses on Irving Botwinick, president of Serving by Irving, process-serving firm in New York City; Botwinick comments; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I used to manage a law firm. They were sending work to servers who were so inept -- one literally couldn't find the Empire State Building. I said to a lawyer: ''This is a joke. Let me get my license and I'll serve those papers for you.'' In 1977, Serving by Irving was born.</p>
        <p>Lawyers love us. They know that if a case is ever haunting them years later, they can come back to the same reliable servers that were here before. My guys have done everything -- served celebrities, had their lives threatened. One of my guys, Big Bob, once served a guy on a nude beach. The slogan I coined for the company is: ''If they're alive, we'll serve them. If they're dead, we'll tell you where they're buried.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I used to manage a law firm. They were sending work to servers who were so inept -- one literally couldn't find the Empire State Building. I said to a lawyer: ''This is a joke. Let me get my license and I'll serve those papers for you.'' In 1977, Serving by Irving was born.</p>
        <p>Lawyers love us. They know that if a case is ever haunting them years later, they can come back to the same reliable servers that were here before. My guys have done everything -- served celebrities, had their lives threatened. One of my guys, Big Bob, once served a guy on a nude beach. The slogan I coined for the company is: ''If they're alive, we'll serve them. If they're dead, we'll tell you where they're buried.''</p>
        <p>I don't serve papers myself anymore, but I used to have fun doing it. Another guy and I once had to serve Donald Trump's bodyguards for a divorce deposition. We ran down the street to this tuxedo place at 4 p.m., then showed up at a party at the Plaza. Ivana got us on the list. We hung out having hors d'oeuvres, caviar until Trump and his bodyguards came in. Our people have served Donald Trump many times.</p>
        <p>We don't have voicemail and never will. You call this office and you get a human being. If a lawyer is on trial, he doesn't want to have to start pushing buttons. He wants me, he gets me. Now I have walkie-talkies, so we can get answers to the lawyers much faster. We work with a lot of huge corporate law firms and even if they have four months to serve a client, they want it done this afternoon. They don't care about cost.</p>
        <p>You can't always do it as fast as a lawyer wants. I'll say, ''Sir, we can't just bust this guy's door down -- he's not under arrest.'' We have to hide under a tree, stake him out, whatever. And sometimes a guy just disappears. If I can't find him, nobody can.</p>
        <p>Now I have a staff of 20, including 15 process servers. Some have been with me 15 years or more. Bob was with me from the beginning -- 23 years. Process serving is usually a transient position. But our servers make this their career. Bob now has a house, two cars, a boat, but when he met me he was living in a basement in Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>I look for people who are creative, street-smart. People who can lie well, but are also honest. They also have to have a lot of patience. We often have to do stakeouts. You can spend hours outside a house, waiting for the lady with the pink dog to come out.</p>
        <p>We don't want people who have done this work before. We want to train them our way. One woman who works for me is a professional singer; one guy used to be a doorman. My P.R. firm has been working on some new ads for The New York Law Journal. I'll go around with a photographer and he'll get me in all kinds of scenes. Dressed as a Hasidic Jew on the Lower East Side. In Central Park with a horse and buggy. Outside a hospital serving doctors. Lawyers love my ads.</p>
        <p>I once tried to set up a franchise with offices in D.C., Westchester, Philly, New Jersey. It didn't work out, though. I could pay people to teach this stuff, but they're not me. No one can really do what I do.</p>
        <p>I'm getting a private investigator license soon, so we'll be expanding to do investigation as well. It'll triple our revenues. We've worked with a lot of the same firms from the beginning. We've also seen law firms come and go. I'm still here. One lawyer said to me once, ''Irving, you still answer the phone!'' I said, ''Yeah. That's what I do.''</p>
        <p>MY JOB</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
