<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TRANSACTIONS</title>
    <meta content="28TRAN$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211055"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000628T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07EFDB1130F93BA15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="960" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TRANSACTIONS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AUTO RACING</p>
        <p>NASCAR--Fined crew chief Joe Garone $50,000 for using an illegal liquid brake cooling device during Save Mart 350. Deducted 50 driver points from Scott Pruett and 50 owner points from Cal Wells.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AUTO RACING</p>
        <p>NASCAR--Fined crew chief Joe Garone $50,000 for using an illegal liquid brake cooling device during Save Mart 350. Deducted 50 driver points from Scott Pruett and 50 owner points from Cal Wells.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
        <p>American League  BALTIMORE ORIOLES--Signed 3B Tripper Johnson, RHP Richard Bartlett, C Thomas Arko, 1B Doug Gredvig, OF Brandon Littleton, RHP Jayme Sperring, C Michael Russell, C Kristopher Wilken, RHP Ryan Keefer, LHP Brian Forystek, OF Thomas Joyce, LHP Joel Crump, SS Shayne Ridley, RHP Aaron Bouie, SS Jose Rodriguez and RHP Dan Marchetti.  BOSTON RED SOX--Placed OF Trot Nixon on the 15-day disabled list. Recalled 1B-DH Morgan Burkhart from Pawtucket of the International League.  CLEVELAND INDIANS--Activated RHP Paul Shuey from the 15-day disabled list. Designated LHP Alan Newman for assignment.  OAKLAND ATHLETICS--Activated LHP Mike Magnante from the 15-day disabled list. Optioned LHP Rich Sauveur to Triple-A Sacramento of the PCL.</p>
        <p>National League  LOS ANGELES DODGERS--Waived RHP Orel Hershiser.  SAN DIEGO PADRES--Activated RHP Steve Montgomery from 15-day disabled list. Optioned RHP Brandon Kolb to Las Vegas of PCL.</p>
        <p>BASKETBALL</p>
        <p>MIAMI HEAT--Acquired F-C Chris Gatling and a 2000 second-round draft pick from Denver for G Voshon Lenard and F Mark Strickland.  MILWAUKEE BUCKS--Traded F Robert Traylor and F J.R. Reid to the Cleveland Cavaliers and G Vinny Del Negro to the Golden State Warriors. Cleveland sent G Bob Sura to Golden State and Golden State sent F Jason Caffey and F Billy Owens to Milwaukee.  NETS--Named Byron Scott coach.</p>
        <p>FOOTBALL</p>
        <p>JETS--Waived RB Leon Johnson.  SAN DIEGO CHARGERS--Signed DE Jonathon Brown to a two-year contract.  SAN FRANCISCO 49ERS--Waived DB Ryan Roques.  WASHINGTON REDSKINS--Signed S Quincy Sanders to four-year contract. Released WR Cory Allen.</p>
        <p>Arena Football League  NEW JERSEY RED DOGS--Fired Frank Mattiace, coach, and Amod Field, offensive coordinator. Named Kevin Guy interim coach-general manager and announced QB coach Charlie Cocuzza will serve as offensive coordinator.  Indoor Professional Football League  IPFL--Awarded a franchise to Trenton, N.J. and announced the team nickname will be Lightning.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
        <p>National Hockey League  BOSTON BRUINS--Signed RW Lee Goren.  CHICAGO BLACKHAWKS--Re-signed D Kevin Dean.</p>
        <p>TRACK &amp; FIELD</p>
        <p>International Amateur Athletic Federation  IAAF--Suspended high jumper Javier Sotomayor until July 31, 2001, for cocaine use.</p>
        <p>COLLEGE</p>
        <p>BLOOMFIELD--Named David Vivino women's soccer coach.  CALIFORNIA--Named Ron Witmeyer assistant baseball coach.  CCNY--Named Ronaldo Salomon men's and women's tennis coach.  COASTAL CAROLINA--Named Allen Terrell director of golf and men's golf coach.  COLUMBIA--Announced the resignation of Lou Montano, wrestling coach.  CORNELL--Named Ray Wright football scouting and college personnel director.  NEBRASKA--Announced freshman RB Chris Butler would transfer to Auburn. Announced the suspension of C Kimani Ffriend and G John Robinson from the basketball team for violating team rules.  SOUTHERN UNIVERSITY--Named Sandy Pugh women's basketball coach.  TEMPLE--Named Gaye Chapman women's assistant basketball coach.  TULSA--Named Steve Gulley cross country and track and field coach.  UNLV--Signed football coach John Robinson to a contract through the 2002 season.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
