<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Success of Zimbabwe's Opposition Signifies Big Changes</title>
    <meta content="Y28ZIM$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211014"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Results</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Zimbabwe</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mugabe, Robert (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Swarns, Rachel L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Zimbabwe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Zimbabwe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Results</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000628T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E6DC1130F93BA15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1345" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Success of Zimbabwe's Opposition Signifies Big Changes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RACHEL L. SWARNS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Swarns, Rachel L</byline>
      <dateline>HARARE, Zimbabwe, June 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Zimbabwe voters, in pointed rejection of Pres Robert Mugabe, take away his party's almost unchallenged authority in parliament by electing powerful new opposition party to more than third of seats; photo; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a pointed rejection of President Robert Mugabe, voters here have taken away what was his governing party's almost unchallenged authority in Parliament by electing a powerful, new opposition party to more than a third of the seats.</p>
        <p>Counting in the closely watched election ended early today with the new party winning 57 seats in the 150-member Parliament, a share large enough to prevent Mr. Mugabe's party from unilaterally changing the constitution, as it has been able to do for more than a decade.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a pointed rejection of President Robert Mugabe, voters here have taken away what was his governing party's almost unchallenged authority in Parliament by electing a powerful, new opposition party to more than a third of the seats.</p>
        <p>Counting in the closely watched election ended early today with the new party winning 57 seats in the 150-member Parliament, a share large enough to prevent Mr. Mugabe's party from unilaterally changing the constitution, as it has been able to do for more than a decade.</p>
        <p>For years, Mr. Mugabe's party has controlled all but three seats in Parliament, giving it virtually unlimited power over lawmaking and governance. His party, the Zimbabwe African National Union-Patriotic Front, will still control a majority of seats. But analysts agree that the election this past weekend will inevitably reshape legislative politics here, introducing consultation and negotiation into a chamber that has rarely needed or allowed it.</p>
        <p>In a speech broadcast on national television tonight, Mr. Mugabe promised to deal with the new opposition as lawmakers wrestle with the nation's economic problems.</p>
        <p>''I look forward to working with the new Parliament as together we grapple with the pressing challenges of improving the livelihood of our people and developing our nation,'' he said.</p>
        <p>And as supporters of the nine-month old opposition party cheered their victory today, honking horns and dancing in impromptu sidewalk celebrations, other government officials also admitted that the world they knew had dramatically changed. After years of apathy, frustrated urban voters had finally turned their backs on a governing party that had failed to focus on the issues of joblessness, soaring inflation and government corruption.</p>
        <p>''When there are diverse voices, the government of the day is on its toes,'' said Jonathan Moyo, a spokesman for the governing party, known as ZANU-P.F. ''And there is no doubt that for the next five years we are going to be on our toes.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Mugabe's party won only 62 of the 120 contested seats, most of them in rural areas where the party's support has traditionally been strongest, the final tallies showed. (Under the Constitution, the public elects only 120 of the 150 members of Parliament. The president appoints 20 members. And local chiefs select the other 10.)</p>
        <p>The opposition party, the Movement for Democratic Change, won its seats in lopsided victories in the country's urban centers. Almost overnight, the party, known as the M.D.C., became the most powerful opposition force in Zimbabwe's history.</p>
        <p>In a news conference this morning, the party's leader, Morgan Tsvangirai, generally praised the weekend's peaceful voting. But he said his party is also carefully scrutinizing the results and is considering challenging the count in about 20 races.</p>
        <p>The races include those in which the M.D.C. had lost by a margin of 500 or less and those in which intimidation and political violence, which has claimed at least 26 lives since March, may have influenced the vote. Mr. Tsvangirai, who lost his race for Parliament, plans to challenge the result in his own district.</p>
        <p>Once that is resolved, Mr. Tsvangirai said he would turn his attention to running for president in the year 2002, facing off against Mr. Mugabe, 76, if Mr. Mugabe chooses to run again. In the meantime, he urged people to work together across party lines to rebuild trust and to improve the unraveling economy.</p>
        <p>''Zimbabweans have to learn to work together,'' said Mr. Tsvangirai, reflecting on what has been a bitter and divisive campaign, as the cameras flashed and the television cameras rolled. ''This election result means that neither ZANU-P.F. nor President Mugabe can go it alone.''</p>
        <p>It has certainly been one of the most extraordinary political campaigns in Zimbabwe.</p>
        <p>For the first time in this nation's 20-year history, opposition candidates contested all 120 parliamentary seats that are up for election, riding a wave of voter frustration and anxiety. For the first time, dozens of politicians defected from Mr. Mugabe's party to run as independent candidates, many of them men in their 30's and 40's who saw little future in a party still dominated by aging freedom fighters.</p>
        <p>And for the first time ever, the white minority, which still controls much of the economy here, woke up from years of political hibernation to bankroll the M.D.C., allowing the fledgling party to wage a successful campaign, which was critical since the party had virtually no access to government-controlled media.</p>
        <p>The unprecedented political activity owes much to growing public frustration over Mr. Mugabe's often iron-fisted style of governance, the unraveling economy and government corruption. And for many whites, the government's increasingly hostile racial rhetoric and support of the recent spate of land invasions became increasingly intolerable.</p>
        <p>In the last decade, the percentage of people living in poverty has surged to more than 60 percent from 40 percent. Wages have fallen to pre-independence levels. The government can no longer pay creditors, buy adequate fuel or supply medicines to hospitals.</p>
        <p>And by early this year, it was clear that Mr. Mugabe, who was once revered for expanding access for the entire population to schools and clinics during his first decade in power, was no longer unassailable. In February, in an astonishing rebuke to the ruling party, the nation voted against a constitutional referendum that would have expanded President Mugabe's power.</p>
        <p>And this weekend, energized by frustrations with what had virtually become a one-party state, voters turned out in heavy numbers. Election officials estimate that about 60 percent of the 5.8 million registered voters went to 120 polling stations on Saturday and Sunday, up from about 26 percent in the parliamentary elections of 1995.</p>
        <p>Voters also ousted several of Mr. Mugabe's cabinet ministers, including Emmerson Mnangagwa, the justice minister, and Dumiso Dabengwa, the home affairs minister.</p>
        <p>In their places, voters elected opposition candidates and political novices who had experienced the hardships of ordinary people. Among the newly elected is Evelyn Masaiti, 35, a high school science teacher who struggles to feed her family and was repeatedly intimidated and attacked by supporters of the governing party.</p>
        <p>Benni Tumbare Mutasa, 44, runs a local butchery and beauty salon, and can no longer afford to buy spare parts for his trucks. Tafadzwa Musekiwa, 24, is a university graduate who has been unable to find a job.</p>
        <p>''I feel over the moon,'' Mr. Musekiwa said today. ''All night yesterday, I didn't sleep.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Mugabe had campaigned heavily on the pledge that he would make good on his promise to redistribute fertile land, which is still mostly owned by the tiny white minority here. He supported the invasions of hundreds of white-owned farms by black squatters and was widely blamed for supporting the waves of political violence. He repeatedly disparaged opposition party members as puppets of the whites.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mugabe seemed more than ready tonight to reconcile. Prominent members of his party are already admitting that they will have to change their message and, perhaps, reshuffle their ranks to appeal to a younger and increasingly urban population.</p>
        <p>In his speech tonight, Mr. Mugabe said, ''There is a great expectation in our country, around the land, which is still to come to our people in a big way, and around the economy, which is going through a bad patch and for which lasting answers will have to be found.''</p>
        <p>For many ordinary people in this country, that is the message they have been longing to hear.</p>
        <p>''What is important at the end of the day is that they solve our problems, whoever is in charge,'' said Edwin Ncube, 47, an accountant, who voted for the M.D.C. this weekend.  ''All we want to see is the economy picking up, life getting better.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
