<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="28FSUM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211001"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000628T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E5DD1130F93BA15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1193" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-12</p>
        <p>House Moving to End Ban on Food Sales to Cuba  House Republican leaders agreed to end four decades of sanctions on sales of food to Cuba, but Cuban-American lawmakers managed to place severe restrictions in the bill. American farmers and agricultural businesses could sell directly to Cuba, but the federal government and American banks could not provide any financing for Cuba.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-12</p>
        <p>House Moving to End Ban on Food Sales to Cuba  House Republican leaders agreed to end four decades of sanctions on sales of food to Cuba, but Cuban-American lawmakers managed to place severe restrictions in the bill. American farmers and agricultural businesses could sell directly to Cuba, but the federal government and American banks could not provide any financing for Cuba.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>U.N. Warning on AIDS in Africa  About half of all 15-year-olds in African countries most affected by AIDS will die of the disease even if the rates of infection drop substantially in the next few years.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>New Opposition in Zimbabwe  Voters have decisively ended the dominance of President Robert Mugabe's governing party in Parliament, casting ballots for a powerful, new opposition and limiting the authority of the governing party.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Violence in Indonesia  A surge of violence, apparently fueled by anti-government agitators in Jakarta, is tearing apart the remote islands of Maluku, raising fear of widespread destabilization.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>French Effort for Europe Union  President Jacques Chirac urged Germany to join France in leading a core group of European Union countries in moving faster than others toward political and economic union.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>France disavowed the document summarizing the principles agreed to by other participants at the conference on democracy organized in Warsaw by the United States.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>Terror Suspect Held in Paris  The French police detained a terror suspect linked to the network of Osama bin Laden and to an Islamic fundamentalist cell in Canada that plotted to bomb American targets.</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>Russia Appeals to Belarus  Russian legislative leaders urged Belarus's president, Aleksandr G. Lukashenko, to let the opposition fully participate in elections.</p>
        <p>A5</p>
        <p>Assad's Son Named Candidate  Syria's Parliament chose Bashar al-Assad, son of the late Hafez al-Assad, as the sole candidate for president in a referendum set for July 10.</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A16-25</p>
        <p>House Votes to Require Groups to Disclose Spending  The House voted to require a growing number of shadowy tax-exempt groups that raise and spend unlimited amounts on political advocacy to disclose their donors and spending, opening the way for the first major change in campaign finance law in two decades.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Group Attacks Drug Plan  The drug industry, operating through Citizens for Better Medicare, a group that can legally conceal the source of its money, has accelerated its lobbying against the Clinton administration's proposal for a Medicare prescription drug benefit, which the industry contends will lead to price controls and throttle research.</p>
        <p>A22</p>
        <p>Airlines Faulted on Candor  Airlines, required to tell their passengers if a flight will be delayed, often blame air traffic control, even if that is not the reason, the Transportation Department reported.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>Growing Coastal Erosion  The Federal Emergency Management Agency reported to Congress that a quarter or more of houses within 500 feet of the United States coastline could be lost to erosion in the next 60 years, straining the federal Flood Insurance Program.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>Explaining Decision on Inquiry  Attorney General Janet Reno said at a Senate hearing that no one ever pressured her into deciding against having an outside prosecutor investigate fund-raising by President Clinton and Vice President Al Gore.</p>
        <p>A25</p>
        <p>SCIENCE/HEALTH</p>
        <p>Prescription Rules Review  The F.D.A. is considering whether many medicines -- like cholesterol-lowering medications, antibiotics and birth control pills -- should be available without a prescription. Hearings are today and tomorrow.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Pollution's Danger to Elderly  Microscopic particles of air pollutants from tailpipes, power plants and other sources are causing measurable increases in deaths and the hospitalizations of the elderly, a study of large metropolitan areas found.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-9</p>
        <p>In Black Poll, Complexity In Views on Police and Bias  Black city residents are afraid of being brutalized by the police, but they welcome and appreciate officers who keep criminals out of their neighborhoods, a poll for the New York Urban League found. At all income levels, blacks are convinced that racial discrimination limits their income and holds back job advancement. Yet they also believe that the major reason that young black men have troubled lives is not bias but the breakdown of black families and a lack of motivation.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Sentences in Louima Case  Charles Schwarz received 15 years and 8 months in prison for taking part in the Abner Louima assault and plotting to cover up his role with two other former police officers, Thomas Bruder and Thomas Wiese, who received 5-year sentences.</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>Echo of Last Year's Blackout  The breakdown of three electric feeder cables on Monday, which forced Con Edison to cut or reduce service to thousands on the Upper East Side, was the same type of failure that led to the 19-hour blackout in northern Manhattan last July.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Coming Soon to Columbus Circle  City officials today will unveil the design for Columbus Center, providing space for business, culture and residences at Columbus Circle.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-14</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-8</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>B10</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>B11</p>
        <p>Private School for Columbia  Columbia University plans to create a private school near campus in which half of the 700 or so seats would be reserved for children of the university's faculty and about 70 would be reserved for neighborhood children on full scholarship.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Suit Cites Bias in Scholarships  The A.C.L.U. accused Michigan of discriminating against minority students by awarding merit scholarships on the basis of test scores.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-28</p>
        <p>Oracle's Anti-Microsoft Effort  Oracle acknowledged that it had hired a Washington detective firm to investigate groups sympathetic to its rival Microsoft, an effort that yielded documents embarrassing to Microsoft during its antitrust battle.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>U.S. Moves Against Phone Deal  The Justice Department went to court to halt WorldCom's $115 billion acquisition of Sprint, citing concern over competition. The companies withdrew the deal from consideration by the European Commission.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>New Rules for Accounting  The S.E.C. proposed rules to tighten standards on additional services accounting firms could sell to companies whose books they audit.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Data on Growth of Prosperity  New government figures show just how far prosperity has spread across America, with stock options, two-career couples and capital gains helping to lift a record number of families to six-figure annual incomes.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Viacom Over USA Networks  A Delaware judge awarded the rights to World Wrestling Federation programs -- the most popular weekly programs on cable television -- to Viacom, based on a high bid that the court said USA Networks had not matched, as required by contract.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>DINING</p>
        <p>F1-12</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A26-27</p>
        <p>Editorials: Politicizing gas prices; after the genome announcement; New York joins the gun suits.  Columns: Paul Krugman.</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E12  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E13  Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2  Weather</p>
        <p>D8</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
