<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>What They Were Thinking About Race; The Gospel According to Tim</title>
    <meta content="MB135414" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="70" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215129"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rollins, Tim</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine/Columns/What They Were Thinking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E6DD1038F935A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="225" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>What They Were Thinking About Race; The Gospel According to Tim</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Catherine Saint Louis, Emily Nussbaum, Joshua Green, Reena Jana, Robert Mackey, Andy Young and Chris Mitchell.</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Photo of Tim Rollins, only prominent white member of Memorial Baptist Church in Harlem (What They Were Thinking About Race)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tim Rollins, Memorial Baptist Church, Harlem, New York</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Tim Rollins, Memorial Baptist Church, Harlem, New York</p>
        <p>I've been a member there five years now. I'm the only prominent white member of the church. I think there was some wariness toward me in the beginning -- a certain coldness or a certain suspicion. And, to be honest, I had to really soul search, because sometimes you'll have white folk going in there trying to pose and being self-congratulatory. But you cannot fake this feeling. I'm sure that this is the place for me, this is where I belong.</p>
        <p>There's certain points in the services at Memorial when we're all feeling something that transcends the physical five senses. In that moment, it doesn't really matter what you look like or what you talk like or where you come from. You're feeling something that is so transcendent and you feel so close to God and everyone's feeling the same thing that it gives you hope for healing between groups that have been separated by politics and history and violence. You actually feel transparent with joy. And it's that joy that I think only gospel music really expresses. People on the outside think black gospel music and white rural gospel music are so incredibly different, but they're not. The similarities are what fascinate me.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
