<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Crime Takes a Vacation (Yours); London: Don't wear a Rolex, unless it's the sidewalk-sale type</title>
    <meta content="MB012441" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215161"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Watches and Clocks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jewels and Jewelry</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">London (Eng)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cowell, Alan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England/London</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Watches and Clocks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jewels and Jewelry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E6D81138F935A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="505" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Crime Takes a Vacation (Yours); London: Don't wear a Rolex, unless it's the sidewalk-sale type</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN COWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cowell, Alan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alan Cowell travel article on recent reports of petty criminals snatching expensive watches or jewelry from tourists in tonier sections of London, Eng; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It's making headlines in Hampstead: the Rolex muggers are back.</p>
        <p>Like any other metropolis, London has its share of petty criminals, from pickpockets to purse snatchers. But of late, nothing has seemed to seize attention in the tonier parts of town as much as thieves whose stock in trade is to grapple a fancy watch or item of jewelry off the wrist of someone wealthy enough to afford the ostentation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It's making headlines in Hampstead: the Rolex muggers are back.</p>
        <p>Like any other metropolis, London has its share of petty criminals, from pickpockets to purse snatchers. But of late, nothing has seemed to seize attention in the tonier parts of town as much as thieves whose stock in trade is to grapple a fancy watch or item of jewelry off the wrist of someone wealthy enough to afford the ostentation.</p>
        <p>And nothing seems to attract the thieves as much as the high-end versions of Rolexes and other high-class timepieces: the latest to be reported missing was on the wrist of a millionaire soccer-club owner, George Reynolds, whose Rolex was said to be worth  $61,500.</p>
        <p>The police routinely advise people to avoid wearing expensive jewelry -- or at least avoid making a show of it -- particularly in such areas as Hampstead, Knightsbridge and Regent's Park, where small gangs lie in wait for people they know to be wearing expensive accouterments. Mr. Reynolds, for instance, was followed from a restaurant in Hampstead before he was accosted.</p>
        <p>Of course, among those whose budget runs more to a Swatch or Timex, there is some Schadenfreude at such assaults on the rich. But thievery makes no such social distinctions. Recently, the police warned travelers on London's subway to be alert for gangs of child pickpockets -- a throwback to ''Oliver Twist,'' without the charm of the musical. And crowded parts of the capital,  particularly Leicester Square, Piccadilly Circus and Oxford Street, are haunts of thieves acting in groups of three -- one to distract a passer-by, another to pick the pocket or purse and the third to receive the stolen item and melt into the crowd.</p>
        <p>Late at night, though, street-savvy Londoners are on the lookout not just for thieves. Especially in Soho and the West End, women in particular are advised by police to avoid curb-crawling drivers offering their vehicles as unlicensed taxis: there have been a series of sexual assaults on people who took up the offer. Young people hitting the city's all-night clubs are also advised to ensure they have enough money for a cab home from a reputable company whose drivers and cars can be traced.</p>
        <p>The patterns behind London's crime are more opaque. Last year, the Metropolitan Police changed the categories and time-scale of its crime statistics, making comparisons with previous years difficult. But some crimes such as burglary -- which do not directly affect hotel-based visitors -- seemed to be on the increase, with 127,701 incidents reported in 1999, slightly more than in 1998. Thefts of everything from automobiles to bicycles (not to mention Rolexes) also seemed to be increasing, with 415,019 cases, 22,357 involving pickpockets, reported to the police last year -- around 10 percent higher than a year earlier.</p>
        <p>ALAN COWELL is a correspondent in the London bureau of The Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">ALAN COWELL is a correspondent in the London bureau of The Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
