<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Miniature Golf's Big Man</title>
    <meta content="16PERS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215205"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="IN PERSON"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Business and Finance</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Miniature Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Dan Powell</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Harris Miniature Golf Courses Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Powell, Dan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Strauss, Robert</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE3DC1E38F935A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1678" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Miniature Golf's Big Man</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT STRAUSS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Strauss, Robert</byline>
      <dateline>WILDWOOD</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Dan Powell of Ocean City, designer whose employer, Harris Miniature Golf Courses Inc, is largest builder of miniature golf courses in New Jersey; he comments on how course designs have changed over the years; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN Dan Powell looks at miniature golf courses, there is not a windmill in sight. Alligators whose mouth eats the ball and whose tail puts it back on the course no longer exist. Dinosaurs don't lean over the roof, nor do gorillas' feet block the way to a hole-in-one.</p>
        <p>Most of these hazards appear at Club 18, a course that Mr. Powell's employers, Harris Miniature Golf Courses Inc., laid out in the 1980's. But in the last decade, Harris has changed its emphasis from creaky windmills to flowing water; from growling gorillas to neatly placed rills and bunkers made of actual sand.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN Dan Powell looks at miniature golf courses, there is not a windmill in sight. Alligators whose mouth eats the ball and whose tail puts it back on the course no longer exist. Dinosaurs don't lean over the roof, nor do gorillas' feet block the way to a hole-in-one.</p>
        <p>Most of these hazards appear at Club 18, a course that Mr. Powell's employers, Harris Miniature Golf Courses Inc., laid out in the 1980's. But in the last decade, Harris has changed its emphasis from creaky windmills to flowing water; from growling gorillas to neatly placed rills and bunkers made of actual sand.</p>
        <p>In short, Harris -- the largest builder of miniature golf courses in New Jersey -- with the help of Mr. Powell, one of its designers who lives in Ocean City, has led the game from a trifle of a novelty to a putter's version of the real Tiger Woodsian thing.</p>
        <p>''There is no question that Tiger has helped everyone in this business,'' said Mr. Powell, 38. ''But especially people who use our realistic style of courses. Windmills and dancing bears are just fine if you go to a resort and play the course one time a year. But for repeat business, people want something challenging, something that makes them have a vague sense of the feeling Tiger has when he plays.''</p>
        <p>These days, Harris builds about 40 courses a year around the country, mainly in the Northeast. It all started in the 1950's with a man by the name of Joe Harris, a local handyman who decided to get into the miniature golf business. Mr. Harris built all of the hazards by himself, selling them primarily at the Shore. Business was steady enough, though it really started doing well in the mid-1980's, at which point he needed another salesman to help out so he could  actually construct the courses.</p>
        <p>Rich Leahy applied for the job, and Mr. Harris hit it off with the young salesman. Mr. Leahy was hired on a Friday, and eager to start his new job, came in the following Monday. Unfortunately, Mr. Harris died of a heart attack over that weekend. Mr. Leahy stayed with the company, anyway. Within a few years, he had bought out Mr. Harris's  partners and, at the same time, dumped the windmill-vision of miniature golf.</p>
        <p>It was at that point that Mr. Leahy hired  Dan Powell, who was 33 at the time and had grown up in Ocean City. He had attended several colleges, ultimately studying interior design.</p>
        <p>''I wanted to come back home in the worst way,'' Mr. Powell said. ''I knew I didn't want to raise a family in California, but I knew there wouldn't be many interior design jobs. Miniature golf, well, I didn't know. But it was a shot, and it's been pretty interesting.''</p>
        <p>When Mr. Powell sets out to design a course, he first thinks first about the initial view the public will have.</p>
        <p>''More often than not, we want them to see a dramatic flow of water from the road,'' Mr. Powell said. ''It's like advertising. So most Harris courses are banked uphill from the road or entrance and, when possible, have water coming down from the highest point to the lowest.</p>
        <p>''I draw in the water system first, and make sure holes are layered in after that,'' he added. ''The best thing is to have the land sloped gently toward the road. That way, you can always see someone playing as you drive by while, at the same time, you have a good chance to bank or dogleg holes in different ways.''</p>
        <p>Sometimes he has actual boulders are trucked in and at other times a substance called Gunite, which simulates a rocky feel, is laid into the fill to produce the base for a waterfall. A big waterfall can cost up to $25,000 -- about half of what an entire 18-hole old windmill-dancing-bear-type course would cost.</p>
        <p>The grass is made from a form of polypropheline that lasts about five years under normal wear. In its entirety, a new Harris course costs from $170,000 for a small 18-hole layout to as much as $500,000 for a two-acre, 36-hole course with lots of water hazards. Harris has six three-person crews that can usually construct a course from a bare piece of property in fewer than three weeks.</p>
        <p>Mr. Powell said that the optimum size for one of Harris's courses is 25,000 to 30,000 square feet, or twice the size of the average old-style course, though Harris did lay out a new 9,000-square-foot course at Stockton and Beach Streets in Cape May in 1998.</p>
        <p>''The old obstacle courses are not going to die out in resorts, where people come with their kids, but we feel the trend is to more year-round play and for an older crowd,'' he said. In fact, Mr. Powell said the average age range for the courses he designs is 18 to 35, and the courses usually pay for themselves within two years.</p>
        <p>''I try not to duplicate any hole in any of the courses,'' said Mr. Powell, who has all his hole layouts on a graphic computer.  ''But just like in the old obstacle courses, you try to give a player more than one way to make the hole, either around a sand trap or by dividing the green with some landscaping or just having different undulations.''</p>
        <p>On the other hand, some things are forbidden on the new courses, said Mr. Powell, who plays a lot of miniature golf to make sure he knows what might or might not work. ''First, you don't put a hole at the top of a hill -- it's too hard and slows down play. One cave is enough, even if you put three holes around it, since kids seem to love them and stay too long listening to the water flow over the rocks. Sand is good for effect and landscaping, but too much makes for a lot of clean-up. And the Goldilocks rule is important -- holes shouldn't be too easy or too hard, just difficult enough to challenge and bring them back next week.''</p>
        <p>Yet more and more, said Mr. Powell as he swung an imaginary putter at the Harris-made Cape May Miniature Golf, he is able to design tougher layouts. ''The big thing now is driving ranges and par-three courses putting in miniature courses,'' said Mr. Powell, noting that there are about 50 Harris-made courses around New Jersey. ''So Dad may hit a bucket of balls while the kids play miniature golf. The layout then looks somewhat like the par-three, so maybe soon they all play that. Owners find that putting in a miniature layout brings them 10 to 30 percent more business on the driving range.''</p>
        <p>Then there is the Tiger Factor.</p>
        <p>''I can't emphasize enough how much Tiger Woods's popularity has helped even miniature golf,'' he said. ''Golf centers want to expand, so miniature golf is an easy way to do so. People in the Midwest and inland want courses. And now it's going all over the globe.''</p>
        <p>Recently, he said, Harris built courses in Bermuda, the Bahamas, Bonaire, Cancun, Canada and even in Cyprus.</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Powell said that Harris would probably eschew most European jobs, since work rules there are strict, and Harris likes to use its own crews to insure quality control.</p>
        <p>And sometimes people order a course just for the heck of it.</p>
        <p>''There was this guy in Long Island, a doctor I think,'' said Mr. Powell. ''He had us put nine holes in his back yard. He gave a lot of parties, I guess.''</p>
        <p>The Place to Work on Your Short Game</p>
        <p>WHILE the nouveau in miniature golf may be looking for sand traps and water hazards, there is still a call, at least at the Jersey Shore, for the old-style moving-windmills-dancing-bears arrangement.</p>
        <p>And nowhere is that more evident than at the miniature golf Mecca just off 18th Street at Long Beach Boulevard in North Beach Haven. There, back-to-back, windmill-to-Tiki hut are Mr. Tee's Shark Island Golf and The Beacon, competing 36-hole old-style miniature golf centers.</p>
        <p>Both courses charge only $3.50 -- or about a quarter a hole -- and since both let golfers go around as often as they like from 9 a.m. to 5 p.m., it may be the cheapest Shore entertainment short of a Skee-Ball machine with an endless ball return.</p>
        <p>Shark Island has a Tiki/South Pacific theme, and those who complete the course get a plastic shark's tooth as a souvenir. The Beacon is somewhat Victorian; it's real Beacon is a Porky-like pig seemingly calling vacationers in as they drive along Long Beach Boulevard.</p>
        <p>Each of the courses holds tournaments -- Shark Island on Wednesdays at 9 a.m. and The Beacon on Thursdays at 9 a.m. And both keep endless hours, taking their first golfers at 9 a.m. and staying open until at least 11 p.m. every night.</p>
        <p>Proving once again that the old can become new again, Shark Island has its own website (www.nealcomm.com/tees/ index.htm), where you can download discounts for the 18th Street course and its companion at the two Wacky World 18-hole courses at Bay and Engleside Avenue in Beach Haven.</p>
        <p>If golfers want to go back upscale, slightly up Bay Avenue from Wacky World at Eighth Street is the Settler's Mill Adventure Golf. It is in the '90s waterfall-and-mountain mode on the second story of a retail complex. Two other smaller courses on Long Beach Island are Hartland Golf, which beckons with its huge golf club at the entrance, at 29th Street and Long Beach Boulevard in Beach Haven, and Sand Trap Miniature Golf, 23rd Street and Long Beach Boulevard in Ship Bottom.</p>
        <p>ROBERT STRAUSS</p>
        <p>IN PERSON</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
