<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>POSTINGS: Renovated Hotel at 77th and Broadway Gets 4 More Floors; Adding 23 Rooms at the Top</title>
    <meta content="16APOS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel; Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215180"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hotels and Motels</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Broadway American Hotel</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">On the Ave (NYC Hotel)</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Luxury and Vacations/Vacation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hotels and Motels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE3D61138F935A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="548" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>POSTINGS: Renovated Hotel at 77th and Broadway Gets 4 More Floors; Adding 23 Rooms at the Top</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Broadway American Hotel at 77th Street in Manhattan is transformed into On the Ave hotel, with four new top floors; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When the old Broadway American Hotel, a 12-story, single-room-occupancy structure at 77th Street and Broadway, was being transformed into the On the Ave hotel to attract tourist guests, it got more than a facelift and an interior remodeling. It actually grew by four floors, adding 14,000 square feet of hotel space with 23 units and a 3,000-square-foot mechanical floor on the top.</p>
        <p>The new rooms and two-room suites, most of which have balconies, have views of Central Park and the Hudson River. They are in addition to the 230 rooms on the existing fifth to 12th floors, which underwent a renovation that was completed last year for the conversion to On to Ave. Rooms on the lower levels house permanent residents, whose rooms were modified on a tenant-by-tenant basis.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When the old Broadway American Hotel, a 12-story, single-room-occupancy structure at 77th Street and Broadway, was being transformed into the On the Ave hotel to attract tourist guests, it got more than a facelift and an interior remodeling. It actually grew by four floors, adding 14,000 square feet of hotel space with 23 units and a 3,000-square-foot mechanical floor on the top.</p>
        <p>The new rooms and two-room suites, most of which have balconies, have views of Central Park and the Hudson River. They are in addition to the 230 rooms on the existing fifth to 12th floors, which underwent a renovation that was completed last year for the conversion to On to Ave. Rooms on the lower levels house permanent residents, whose rooms were modified on a tenant-by-tenant basis.</p>
        <p>The addition was done ''as of right'' under zoning regulations because the structure had unused development capacity, said Ronald DeSouza, an associate at David Kenneth Specter and Associates, the architects for the renovation and addition.</p>
        <p>Mr. DeSouza said that little effort had been devoted to matching the look of the building's 1920's-era brick facade. Instead, he said, the four new floors, which are set back from the edges of the building, were intended as an ''architectural folly'' more in keeping with the tops of buildings in the area. To emphasize the views, much more glass was used in the three new hotel floors, whose curved lines are a contrast to the strictly rectangular building below.</p>
        <p>''It is a very different environment 150 feet above the sidewalk,'' Mr. DeSouza said. ''We use the old building as a podium supporting the new structure.'' To make sure that support was adequate, he added, the steel columns of the top three floors of the existing building were reinforced and the weight of the new floors transferred to the reinforced columns.</p>
        <p>The new 13th floor has nine rooms, including two suites, as does the 14th floor. The top hotel floor is smaller, with five rooms, including two suites. The mechanical floor at the very top has machinery to heat and cool the entire building and is more efficient than a system in the basement, a hotel official said.</p>
        <p>The hotel is owned by the Citylife Hotel Group,  which has converted several long-term residential hotels into ones oriented toward travelers. They include the old Allerton House at 57th Street and Lexington Avenue, which is now called Habitat. Another is the former Martha Washington Hotel at 30 East 30th Street, to be known as Thirty Thirty when it opens within a few weeks.</p>
        <p>An additional seven stories or 80,000 square feet of space can be added to the 12-story Thirty Thirty, said Kevin Maloney, one of the principals of the Citylife Hotel Group. The space could accommodate 78 suites and a new mechanical room, but Mr. Maloney said that the project was currently on hold, with no plans to build for at least several years.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
