<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>F.Y.I.</title>
    <meta content="16FYI.$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215263"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Rock and Stone</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Office Buildings and Other Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cedar Trees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Subways</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Staten Island (NYC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schneider, Daniel B</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rock and Stone</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Subways</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE3D71F38F935A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="622" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>F.Y.I.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANIEL B. SCHNEIDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schneider, Daniel B</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>FYI column answers questions about what appears to be Cyrillic message on boulder left over from construction of Staten Island Expressway in Staten Island, fate of illuminated cedar trees that used to reside in atrium beneath tower at 120 West 45th Street and why one subway line once required additional fare before exiting; drawings (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mysterious Russian</p>
        <p>Q. A trail at the base of Moses Mountain, in central Staten Island, leads to a boulder carved with a long inscription in what appears to be Cyrillic script. Does anyone know what the mysterious message says?</p>
        <p>A. The inscriptions -- there are two, and they are, in fact, carved in Cyrillic -- are easily translated by a Russian speaker, according to Bruce Kershner, author of ''Secret Places of Staten Island'' (Kendall/Hunt, 1998). Moses Mountain is a 220-foot mound of rock blasted during construction of the Staten Island Expressway, a Robert Moses project, in the 1960's. While hiking there as a youth, Mr. Kershner slipped and fell beside the rock, and may have been among the first to read the professional-looking inscriptions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mysterious Russian</p>
        <p>Q. A trail at the base of Moses Mountain, in central Staten Island, leads to a boulder carved with a long inscription in what appears to be Cyrillic script. Does anyone know what the mysterious message says?</p>
        <p>A. The inscriptions -- there are two, and they are, in fact, carved in Cyrillic -- are easily translated by a Russian speaker, according to Bruce Kershner, author of ''Secret Places of Staten Island'' (Kendall/Hunt, 1998). Moses Mountain is a 220-foot mound of rock blasted during construction of the Staten Island Expressway, a Robert Moses project, in the 1960's. While hiking there as a youth, Mr. Kershner slipped and fell beside the rock, and may have been among the first to read the professional-looking inscriptions.</p>
        <p>''The person who did them spent many, many days,'' Mr. Kershner said. ''That rock is hard.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kershner told no one of his find. Thirty years later, he rediscovered the inscriptions behind an overgrowth of thorns and brambles, sketched them and had them translated. They are signed ''Robert Dobrovalsky'' but Mr. Kershner was unable to trace the stonecutter. A rough trail was later cleared to the one-inch inscriptions, and Mr. Kershner -- hesitant to ruin the mystery -- discussed them in his book without revealing their meaning.  They are everyday proverbs: ''What you sow, so shall you reap,'' and ''Do not put off until tomorrow what you can do today.''</p>
        <p>Scared of Heights?</p>
        <p>Q. The narrow atrium beneath the tower at 120 West 45th Street is enclosed by an open gridlike structure rising about 15 stories. The rear of the grid is divided into five levels, each of which once supported a row of illuminated cedar trees. The trees, which swayed beautifully against the open sky, are now gone. Why?</p>
        <p>A. After completion of the building and atrium in 1989, the 20 red cedars died and were replaced about twice a year, according to Sandy Hahn, the properties manager for Reckson Associates, which took control of the 40-story building in 1999. The dead trees were removed that May. ''They looked pretty and it was a great idea, but the city gets the best of them,'' Ms. Hahn said. ''They were destined to fail from the beginning.''</p>
        <p>The 175-foot-tall vista of slender cedars was designed by the artist Robert Irwin, who chose the original trees. The 30-foot-wide, 80-foot-deep atrium was built because an easement protected the windows of the adjacent tower from being blocked by new construction. Within each supporting beam, an irrigation channel and a narrow trough were installed. ''In order to plant the trees in that trough, they had to really cut the root ball, down to two or three feet,'' Ms. Hahn said. New construction nearby added dust and curtailed available light, and hiring workers to weed and trim the trees at such vertiginous heights was, in Ms. Hahn's words, an awful experience. Sometimes the withered trees were even sprayed with an environmentally safe green dye to give the appearance of health.</p>
        <p>''Our horticultural people told us all the time -- trees just aren't meant to grow up in the air like that,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Paying to Leave Train</p>
        <p>Q. There was once a subway line that required passengers to pay an additional fare before exiting. Why?</p>
        <p>A. In 1953, the city acquired the Long Island Rail Road's Rockaway line, which failed in part because the wooden railroad trestle spanning Jamaica Bay was periodically destroyed by fire.</p>
        <p>The cost of the rebuilt 11-mile line, and a new, fireproof trestle, came to $56 million. Passengers exiting from the stations in the Rockaways helped foot the bill from the day the line opened in 1956 until 1975.</p>
        <p>DANIEL B. SCHNEIDER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
