<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lives; My Chinese Phase</title>
    <meta content="MB120259" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215099"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Asian-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Chinese-Americans</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Malcomson, Scott L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine/Columns/Lives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Asian-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E0DF1038F935A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1023" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lives; My Chinese Phase</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Scott L. Malcomson</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Malcomson, Scott L</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Scott L Malcomson comment on growing up in Oakland and hanging around with Chinese and other Asian friends (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Growing up in Oakland, I lived down the street from a Chinese kid named Jeff. We walked to grade school together, and when we went on to junior high I fell in with his nascent group of Chinese or quasi-Chinese friends. I say ''quasi-Chinese'' because the concept was loose. Anything Asian -- the word meant little in the early 70's -- was more or less Chinese. This looseness made perfect sense when we were 12, still just trying out the roles that we would later play. The process of becoming racial came up slowly, along with skin problems, hair under our arms, breasts: mysterious changes, all but one of them natural.</p>
        <p>I was red-haired and about as pale as chalk, but for a host of reasons I could not see myself as white, nor could I imagine straining social credibility so far as to pass myself off as black. So I identified, if that's the word, with the Chinese kids. It was sometimes an awkward fit. I could not understand Jeff's grandmother -- though he didn't always understand her Cantonese, either. And I could never quite get the uniform right: Jeff and his friends wore black or navy Derby jackets, sky-blue cords or jeans, collared shirts with the sleeves rolled up, Adidas or Tiger running shoes; my Derby was brown and my sneakers were tennies. Yet there I was, a most unlikely Asian. The girls in that circle would never have considered me a potential boyfriend, but aside from that, my friends did not seem to question my presence among them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Growing up in Oakland, I lived down the street from a Chinese kid named Jeff. We walked to grade school together, and when we went on to junior high I fell in with his nascent group of Chinese or quasi-Chinese friends. I say ''quasi-Chinese'' because the concept was loose. Anything Asian -- the word meant little in the early 70's -- was more or less Chinese. This looseness made perfect sense when we were 12, still just trying out the roles that we would later play. The process of becoming racial came up slowly, along with skin problems, hair under our arms, breasts: mysterious changes, all but one of them natural.</p>
        <p>I was red-haired and about as pale as chalk, but for a host of reasons I could not see myself as white, nor could I imagine straining social credibility so far as to pass myself off as black. So I identified, if that's the word, with the Chinese kids. It was sometimes an awkward fit. I could not understand Jeff's grandmother -- though he didn't always understand her Cantonese, either. And I could never quite get the uniform right: Jeff and his friends wore black or navy Derby jackets, sky-blue cords or jeans, collared shirts with the sleeves rolled up, Adidas or Tiger running shoes; my Derby was brown and my sneakers were tennies. Yet there I was, a most unlikely Asian. The girls in that circle would never have considered me a potential boyfriend, but aside from that, my friends did not seem to question my presence among them.</p>
        <p>Not one of us knew as much about Asian cultures as a focused adult could glean in a day at the library. We were, after all, Americans. My parents did not talk about life before Oakland, much less our heritage (whatever that might have been), and neither did my friends' parents. But among ourselves, we began referring to other kids through an elaborate system of classification: hock (black) and bock (white), f.o.b. (fresh off the boat), a.b.c. (American-born Chinese), Jap, Flip.</p>
        <p>And we idolized Bruce Lee. We imitated everything about him that we could take from his movies except his bad haircut: the walk, the moves, the stare, the cool stoicism and of course the martial arts. At that time, we all understood Chineseness -- theirs as well as mine -- as a matter of appearance, and the essence of that appearance, with Bruce as our guide, was a martial or warlike art, a defensive posture in the literal sense.</p>
        <p>But, ai-ya, defense against what? What we were interested in was the appearance or imitation of power, which in the event was the appearance of racial solidarity and the imitation of race. (My imitation was just a bit more obvious.) It was something to do; it was kind of a joke, really, a game, and then it wasn't.</p>
        <p>My memories of our little race war are shaky now. I think it began with a stabbing. Either a Chinese boy stabbed a black boy at school or the other way around. Whatever it was, the black kids and the Chinese kids squared off. We carried more than the usual complement of weapons. We gathered at recess times, grumbled, sought allies, strengthened our resolve.</p>
        <p>I felt torn. The Chinese kids were my friends, but some of the black kids had once been my friends, too, before this business of race took us over. I ended up in the principal's office to help mediate the conflict -- which, at bottom, was not about anything. The two groups, Chinese and black, had no competing interests. Therefore, mediating could only mean convincing all the parties that there was no conflict and nothing to mediate. In practice, this meant gathering many small bits of information and cycling them through enough meetings so that everyone got tired and began to question their own memories. Fortunately, we were still children and didn't know any better than to stop fighting. No one really wanted a race war. That had just been the available form into which a clash might fit.</p>
        <p>But when we reached high school, our vague set of antiwhite prejudices -- that whites were cowardly, physically unimpressive and unmanly -- grew stronger, as did our assumption that we could beat white kids in any arena. This faith in our racial superiority had almost no content beyond belief in itself. We had become a gang, but we were a gang of what a teacher of that era would have called achievers. Whether this behavior had any distant connection to China I do not know, but I doubt it. We were just staking out a place between black and white in a competitive, racial society.</p>
        <p>Day after day, our Chinese gang played mumbletypeg, throwing knives at each other's shoes to see who would flinch. But with no other gangs around, we were all dressed up with nowhere to go, jealous of a turf no one else wanted. This accounts for our perfect survival rate.</p>
        <p>Then at last we managed to concoct some small violence. One of our group acquired a tiny gun. We drove by the home of a Chinese boy whom we considered uncool because of his poor physique, average grades and f.o.b. buzz cut. We parked outside his family's bungalow and fired into the front window, then we laughed as we watched the boy, his sister and their parents scurry about the living room in fear, the glass broken. Having attacked one of our own, we moved on, uphill, to the rich white shopping district. And there on its streets, our murky hatred of whites and their money-smugness, their indifferent superiority that we did so much to imitate, briefly found a focus. We all agreed that we should shoot at their bank. So we shot at the bank, and we felt pretty good about it too.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
