<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Yoho's Trails Have Little Traffic</title>
    <meta content="YOHO.$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215070"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Walking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Yoho National Park (Canada)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Rocky Mountains</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Canada</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Crittenden, Ann</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Hiking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Walking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02E6D71238F935A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="3178" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Yoho's Trails Have Little Traffic</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANN CRITTENDEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Crittenden, Ann</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ann Crittenden travel article on two-week hiking trip through Yoho National Park, along western side of Continental Divide, in Canadian Rockies; photos; map (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE Canadian Rockies are the only place I know where the postcards don't lie. The snow-capped mountains and raging torrents of water really are as spectacular as the glossy photographs make them seem. And among its charms, the area is blessed with one of the best systems of hiking trails to be found anywhere. This is not a secret; one of the first people to explore the region and to recognize its hiking potential was Edward Whymper, the conqueror of the Matterhorn. On a trip last summer, my husband and I met more Germans, Swiss and other Europeans on the trails than Americans, drawn to the kind of civilized wilderness characteristic of Europe in the 19th century.</p>
        <p>At times we felt that we were in the era of Goethe and Wordsworth, or at least of Frederick Church and Asher Durand and other American landscape painters. Scenes: on a quiet road, suddenly surrounded by a herd of male elk, their six-  and seven-point racks bobbing gently as they slowly grazed past us; on a mountain ledge high above an emerald lake, chatting with collectors of still unidentified Cambrian fossils; in a forest of spruce and subalpine fir, motionless as a female moose and her calf warily cross the path ahead; on a highline trail looking across a valley at an explosive waterfall 1,000 feet high, with not another soul in sight. But I'm getting ahead of my story.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE Canadian Rockies are the only place I know where the postcards don't lie. The snow-capped mountains and raging torrents of water really are as spectacular as the glossy photographs make them seem. And among its charms, the area is blessed with one of the best systems of hiking trails to be found anywhere. This is not a secret; one of the first people to explore the region and to recognize its hiking potential was Edward Whymper, the conqueror of the Matterhorn. On a trip last summer, my husband and I met more Germans, Swiss and other Europeans on the trails than Americans, drawn to the kind of civilized wilderness characteristic of Europe in the 19th century.</p>
        <p>At times we felt that we were in the era of Goethe and Wordsworth, or at least of Frederick Church and Asher Durand and other American landscape painters. Scenes: on a quiet road, suddenly surrounded by a herd of male elk, their six-  and seven-point racks bobbing gently as they slowly grazed past us; on a mountain ledge high above an emerald lake, chatting with collectors of still unidentified Cambrian fossils; in a forest of spruce and subalpine fir, motionless as a female moose and her calf warily cross the path ahead; on a highline trail looking across a valley at an explosive waterfall 1,000 feet high, with not another soul in sight. But I'm getting ahead of my story.</p>
        <p>Our first priority in planning this two-week trip was to find good day hiking, allowing us to experience the mountains without carrying 40-pound packs for days or  having to endure the crowds and the bus terminal madness that now surround the grand old hotels in Banff and Lake Louise. Of the five national parks that encompass the prime wilderness of the Canadian Rockies, we discovered that the best one for our purposes would be Yoho.</p>
        <p>Banff, the first national park in Canada, including the crown jewel of Lake Louise, is known as the hiking capital of the country, with a huge network of well-maintained trails. But the park also has more than five million visitors, most of them in July and August -- too many to get away from without spending all one's time above the tree line, sleeping on rocks. Jasper, a few hours north up the magnificent Icefields Parkway, has celebrated longer trails, but not too many get-away-from-it-all day hikes. Yoho, just west of Lake Louise on the western side of the Continental Divide, has far fewer visitors (an estimated 1.8 million in 1999)and 185 miles of trails that can take you to the top of the world and down again in time for a dinner and a book in front of the fire.</p>
        <p>Before we arrived in Yoho we spent a few days in Jasper and the Lake Louise area. We liked the informal funkiness of the little town of Jasper and our log cabin (and hot tub) in the woods nearby, but we had to drive an hour or more each day to find good day hikes. We skirted the crowds at Lake Louise by staying eight miles away at Lake Moraine Lodge, luxuriously rustic in the style of Ralph Lauren. There a couple of world-class day hikes began right on the grounds, but the lake itself, an emerald gem, was surrounded by day trippers.</p>
        <p>But on our first day in Yoho we had it all: a vigorous hike with dazzling views; a glimpse into the geological forces that formed this region; and seven kinds of weather, including drizzle, sun, cloudiness and a brief hail storm. For outdoor activities in the Canadian Rockies, the key word is layers -- rainproof layers.</p>
        <p>We had joined a group put together by the Yoho-Burgess Shale Foundation for a hike up to one of the most important fossil sites in the world, now a Unesco World Heritage Site. In 1989, Stephen Jay Gould, in his book ''Wonderful Life,'' described the ''weird wonders'' found here: strange, 500-million-year-old sea creatures displaying a greater disparity than exists in the animal kingdom today. The hike is no joke -- 12 and a half miles round trip and an elevation gain of about 2,500 feet, up to an altitude of 6,700 feet -- not high by Colorado or High Sierra standards, but high enough to be aware of thin air and aging muscles.</p>
        <p>It was utterly worth it. The guide,  a geologist named Carole Augereau, gave us the rundown as we trudged up: how half a billion years ago this area was the north shore of a vast supercontinent surrounded by shallow warm seas, teeming with the earliest forms of multicellular animal life. Eons later, between 175 million and 45 million years ago, two separate collisions of continental plates (moving at their fastest at the speed of a growing fingernail) slowly pushed up the ancient ocean floors, forming the mountain spines running north-south through Canada and the United States.</p>
        <p>Thus it was that in 1886 railway workers found ''stone bugs'' buried in alpine rocks, and from 1909 to 1917 Charles D. Walcott, then head of the Smithsonian Institution and the foremost Cambrian paleontologist of his day, found such marvelous marine invertebrates as Opabinia, with its five eyes, Aysheaia, with its mouth surrounded by a ring of tentacles, and the strangest of all, Hallucigenia, an animal so bizarre that for decades no one knew which of its sides was up.</p>
        <p>To our delight, Dr. Des Collins of the Royal Ontario Museum, who has been excavating the quarry for 25 years, was at the site when we arrived. He told us that thanks to discoveries in two new quarries, in China and Greenland, as well as his own finds, there is now evidence of even more unclassified Cambrian organisms than a decade ago. ''The Cambrian world,'' he said, ''is getting stranger-looking than ever.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Collins passed around a few of that week's finds, some of which, to a lay person's eye, looked like faint scratchings on dark grey pieces of shale. A few steps away, half a dozen graduate students and volunteers were busy chipping away on stacks of muddy rocks with hammers and chisels. When I peered into the quarry to have a closer look, a handsome French scientist looked up at me and said, with deep and unmistakable pride, ''I just found a worm.''</p>
        <p>The view from Burgess Ridge was unparalleled. On our left were the massive limestone cliffs of Burgess Mountain and on our right was Mount Wapta. In the distance loomed Michael Peak, the President and the Vice President, all three covered in snow. Far below lay Emerald Lake, the largest body of water in Yoho National Park. (The explorer who gave Emerald Lake its perfect name had to rename a lake already called Emerald. Its new name: Lake Louise.)</p>
        <p>I have found that one of the principal joys of a hike is contemplating the pleasures that await its end. Daydreams of the hot shower, the cool drink, the good meal and the soft bed tend to crowd out more immediate realities, like the flora and fauna of the last few knee-crushing kilometers downhill. Toward the end of this particular 10-hour day the fantasies were vivid, for we were headed for the Emerald Lake Lodge, another sybaritic outpost. A few hours later, we were unwinding in a hot tub overlooking the mountain-ringed lake, perusing a tempting menu and building a fire in our bedroom. Ah, wilderness!</p>
        <p>The next day we took a less strenuous stroll around the lake and up into the basin behind it. We arranged for a naturalist to accompany us. A cold, snowy winter and nonexistent spring meant that the flowering alpine meadows we had hoped to see had still not appeared, even by mid-  to late July, but myriad earlier flowers were scattered around the lakeside, including the ubiquitous white globe flowers and bunchberry, wild roses, yellow columbines, bright orange western wood lilies, purple asters, tiny white and green bog orchids, and equally delicate twinflower (Linnaea borealis), a Linnaeus favorite.</p>
        <p>We also learned the secret of the mountain lakes' brilliant turquoise color: a substance called rock flour.  As the glaciers that feed these lakes move down the mountains, the rocks embedded in their base scrape against other rocks, grinding them into a fine grayish powder that washes into the lakes as the glaciers melt. This powder reflects the blue-green part of the light spectrum, giving the water a hue that would be garish if any painter tried to capture it.</p>
        <p>The next day we were eagerly anticipating another major trek, this time in the Lake O'Hara area, a uniquely beautiful place of cirque and rock basin lakes, alpine heath and larch stands, framed by the same two peaks -- Lefroy and Victoria -- that overlook Lake Louise on the other side of the great divide. So beautiful is Lake O'Hara that private vehicles are banned from the road leading into it and a quota system limits the number of daily visitors to 150 to 200. A day hiker from the town of Field, for example, has to make a reservation for one of the six available seats on the daily bus going in. You have to be at the tourist office at dawn on the morning before you want to go. Unless you are one of the first six people there, forget it.</p>
        <p>Not being savvy, we arrived at 7 a.m. one morning and lost out. The next day, seriously determined, we arrived at the still-locked office by 6 o'clock, and there were only two people ahead of us. Ten minutes later a young man from Quebec arrived, and there went the last two spaces. Literally one minute after that, an older man and his son came up, only to be told, at 6:15, that they were too late. The gentleman commented that the sight of the sun coming up over the mountains had been so magnificent that he had stopped on the highway several times to take pictures; otherwise, he said ruefully, he might have made it.</p>
        <p>''That was you?'' the man from Quebec exclaimed. ''I was right behind you.''</p>
        <p>We picked one of the most popular hikes, from Lake O'Hara up to Lake Oesa, then across a ledge around Yukness Mountain, down to the Opabin Plateau, and back in time for the 6:30 P.M. bus. Oesa (the Stoney Indian word for ice, so called because the lake is frozen nearly year round) was, as predicted, gorgeous. But on Yukness, big patches of snow still covered the trail, including one long stretch that curved up and around the mountain with a precipitous drop on one side.</p>
        <p>At this point I remembered that I really am terribly afraid of heights. I inched my way along the slippery track, digging now my toes, then my heels, into the footsteps of the fools who had preceded me. When we were finally back on solid, if not flat, ground, I literally sobbed, relieved to be alive.</p>
        <p>We began to saunter down toward the plateau. Just as I was beginning to get back into the blissful rhythm of trekking, a voice cried up at us from far below: ''A mother bear with two cubs!''</p>
        <p>The most dangerous kind of bear.</p>
        <p>We froze. ''Black or grizzly?'' my husband shouted back. We didn't hear an answer. He scanned the valley below, and sure enough, way down there, right where we were heading, were a large tawny bear and two smaller ones, moving faster than race horses on a diagonal away from the trail. They didn't look like black bears.</p>
        <p>I thought of the ordeal behind me and decided I'd rather face a grizzly than go back the way we'd come. We took a whistle out of our pack and started tooting as we came down, making noise, scanning both sides of the trail constantly, and marching briskly back to Lake O'Hara. When I looked at the hiking guide later, I realized that we'd seen nothing of one of the prettiest parts of that hike.</p>
        <p>We did get to be interviewed by the park rangers; a grizzly sighting is big news, particularly in one of the most popular hiking areas in the Canadian Rockies. It turned out they knew these bears well -- they were even tagged. But they weren't supposed to be hanging around trails those of us who are lower on the food chain like to frequent.</p>
        <p>Our final hike was more satisfying. The trail to take in Yoho is called the Iceline, and true to its name, it was still partly under snow even at the end of July. We had put it off until our last day, which turned out to be a Rocky Mountain high, clear and sunny. The first mile and a half was steadily uphill, sweetened by an almost constant view of magnificent Takakkaw Falls, which burst out of a rock cliff like a giant's broken water main. The trail climbed high on the open avalanche slopes of the President Range and onto the moraines of several glaciers, past two half-frozen glacier-fed tarns. We were dazzled by the utter stillness and vastness of the bleak alpine landscape, so close to the glaciers and snowy peaks, and so far above the Yoho Valley that we felt as if we were in the clouds looking down.</p>
        <p>There were no bears on the way down. Just crunching through tracks in the snow in shorts and T-shirt, swinging hiking poles like a cross-country skier, sliding down a snow bank to avoid any more slippery traverses, down into the forest around another pristine lake, past a raging river and more plunging falls. Yoho, by the way, is a Cree word loosely translated as ''awesome.''</p>
        <p>Along the way to 500-million-year-old fossils</p>
        <p>Getting There</p>
        <p>The gateway to the Canadian Rockies is Calgary, 130 miles east of the town of Field. Calgary is served from the New York City area by Air Canada and United Airlines. United offers one direct flight a day and connections with Air Canada.</p>
        <p>Where to Stay</p>
        <p>Rates are based on double occupancy and are given in U.S. currency.</p>
        <p>Emerald Lake Lodge, (250) 343-6321. The main lodge of hand-hewn timber and fieldstone was built in 1902 by the Canadian Pacific Railway and restored in 1986 by Canadian Rocky Mountain Resorts. Open year round, the lodge has 85 guest rooms, all with wood-burning fireplaces, in 24 chalet-style buildings. There is a hot tub and sauna, and several dining rooms. Rates in peak season range from $200 to $310.</p>
        <p>Moraine Lake Lodge. Lake Louise, Alberta. June 1 to Sept. 30: (403) 522-3733; fax (403) 522-3719; Oct. 1 to May 31: (604) 985-7474; fax (604) 985-7479. Although technically not in Yoho, Moraine Lake is close, and lovely. Rooms have wood-burning fireplaces, and the main lodge offers free afternoon tea and port and sherry after dinner. Rates range from $168 to $198 from June 1 to 15, and $235 to $293 from mid-June to October. The hotel is closed the rest of the year because of avalanches.</p>
        <p>The Lake O'Hara Lodge, (250) 343-6418, (403) 678-4110 off season, built in the early 20th century, is one of those places aficionados hate to mention for fear of drawing crowds And this late in the season, it is already virtually impossible to book for the summer. (It is also open from late January to mid-April for back country ski holidays for those hardy enough to ski in, uphill, along a 6.8-mile access road.) The lodge offers lakeshore cabins for two with private bath at $320 a couple per night, cabins suitable for four at $360 for the first two people, plus $118 for each additional adult, and small, spartan rooms with shared bath in the lodge at $236 a couple. There is a minimum stay of two nights. Rates include all meals, afternoon tea, round-trip bus fare to the highway, and all taxes and tips. The lodge has no fax machines, television, radios, or access to e-mail. There is one public telephone nearby.</p>
        <p>Kicking Horse Lodge. Box 174, Field, British Columbia V0A 1G0; (250) 343-6303; fax (250) 343-6355. Really a motel in the town of Field, the lodge has 14 comfortable units and a good Rocky Mountain restaurant. Doubles are $89.</p>
        <p>Cathedral Mountain Chalets, Box 40, Field, British Columbia. V0A  1G0; telephone and fax (250) 343-6442; in winter (403) 762-0514. Twenty log cabins with fireplaces and restaurant on the road leading up to Takakkaw Falls. Open mid-May through mid-October. Doubles range from $90 to $127.</p>
        <p>West Louise Lodge. Box 9, Lake Louise, Alberta T0L 1E0; (250) 343-6311. A large motel with 50 rooms on the Trans-Canada Highway leading into Yoho. Open mid-May to mid-October; $64 a night, with breakfast. Restaurant, indoor pool and sauna.</p>
        <p>The town of Field also has numerous clean and pleasant bed-and-breakfasts. We stayed at the Wildflower Guesthouse, (250) 343-6707, in a one-bedroom guest apartment with a kitchen for $64 a night. The Alpenglow, (250) 343-6356, has four guest rooms, at $60 a night; the Otterhead, (250) 343-6034, has three rooms with shared bath for $75 a night.</p>
        <p>For other B &amp; B suggestions, contact the Field Visitor Center, Yoho National Park, Post Office Box 99, Field, British Columbia V0A 1G0; (250) 343-6783; www.worldweb.com/ parkscanada-yoho.</p>
        <p>Just short of camping is the Whiskey Jack Hostel, (403) 762-4122, Box 1358, Banff AB T0L 0C0, Alberta. About half a mile from Takakkaw Falls, near trailheads, the hostel has a kitchen and three shared rooms sleeping 27 people, at $13 a head. Open Mid-June to mid-October.</p>
        <p>Where to Eat</p>
        <p>The restaurants at the Emerald Lake Lodge and Moraine Lake are open to outside dinner reservations, as are those at the Kicking Horse Lodge, Cathedral Mountain Chalets. and West Louise Lodge.</p>
        <p>Wherever you stay in Field, the restaurants are in plain sight. Two people can dine well for $30 or less. The Truffle Pigs Cafe and the diner-style CP Rail Bunkhouse Cafe also offer simple meals. The Yoho Bros. Trading Post prepares sandwiches in the early morning for hikers, and offers buffalo burgers for lunch.</p>
        <p>ANN CRITTENDEN</p>
        <p>ANN CRITTENDEN lives in Washington, D.C.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">ANN CRITTENDEN lives in Washington, D.C.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
