<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Talent for Dance, and for Its Documentation</title>
    <meta content="16LEIV$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215144"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Museum of Dance (Saratoga Springs, Ny)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Caras, Steven</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leivick, Laura</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803EEDA1038F935A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1525" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Talent for Dance, and for Its Documentation</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">BY LAURA LEIVICK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Leivick, Laura</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Laura Leivick reviews retrospective of works by dance photographer Steven Caras on view at National Museum of Dance in Saratoga Springs, NY; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN ''Last Bow,'' one of the best-known ballet photographs in history, no one is dancing. Shot from the first ring at the New York State Theater by Steven Caras, then a New York City Ballet dancer, it shows George Balanchine taking a curtain call in 1982, less than a year before his death. Behind the great choreographer, visible only from Mr. Caras's perch, are New York City Ballet dancers in costume, applauding.</p>
        <p>''I love the moments between dancers, between steps, in Steve's photographs,'' says the former dancer Siobhan Dunham. Ms. Dunham is now interim artistic director of the National Museum of Dance in Saratoga Springs, N.Y., where Mr. Caras's ''Last Bow'' is on permanent view. His striking one-man retrospective of 97 photographs, ''An American Mosaic,'' opened there last Sunday, coinciding with City Ballet's 35th annual residency at the Saratoga Performing Arts Center.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN ''Last Bow,'' one of the best-known ballet photographs in history, no one is dancing. Shot from the first ring at the New York State Theater by Steven Caras, then a New York City Ballet dancer, it shows George Balanchine taking a curtain call in 1982, less than a year before his death. Behind the great choreographer, visible only from Mr. Caras's perch, are New York City Ballet dancers in costume, applauding.</p>
        <p>''I love the moments between dancers, between steps, in Steve's photographs,'' says the former dancer Siobhan Dunham. Ms. Dunham is now interim artistic director of the National Museum of Dance in Saratoga Springs, N.Y., where Mr. Caras's ''Last Bow'' is on permanent view. His striking one-man retrospective of 97 photographs, ''An American Mosaic,'' opened there last Sunday, coinciding with City Ballet's 35th annual residency at the Saratoga Performing Arts Center.</p>
        <p>Mr. Caras, now 49, began taking pictures in 1977 and quickly established himself as an expert witness. Dance photography was a rare avocation when he entered the field, but during his years at City Ballet it was professionalized in ways that changed the image of dance.</p>
        <p>After Mr. Caras retired from dancing in 1983, the season following Balanchine's death, he continued to photograph the company as it evolved under Peter Martins. But his work entered a new, exuberant phase in 1990, when he left New York for Florida to begin a double career as a ballet master and photographer, first with the Miami City Ballet and then Ballet Florida in West Palm Beach.</p>
        <p>The Miami company's founding director is another City Ballet dancer, Edward Villella, a leader in the worldwide diaspora of Balanchine disciples who today run companies, stage his work and teach his aesthetic. While Mr. Caras still photographs Miami City Ballet, his home base is Marie Hale's West Palm Beach company, where maintenance of the Balanchine and Peter Martins repertory is his responsibility. Just as important, Mr. Caras has the freedom to travel, making images of the wildly varied dance scene around the country, from Mikhail Baryshnikov's White Oak Dance Project to the travesty company Les Ballets Grandiva de Russia. As both a ballet master and photographer, Mr. Caras can capitalize on what Mr. Villella calls his ''terrific eye and split-second timing.''</p>
        <p>At first, however, Mr. Caras's timing was way off. Born in New Jersey, he began ballet training in New York at 15, much too late. Until a high school drama teacher suggested ballet lessons, Mr. Caras had believed that ''people were born into ballet, like royalty'' -- ''I had no idea this was something an American person could learn,'' he said. A waitress at a pancake house suggested he try out for the Joffrey Ballet School, and Mr. Caras bluffed his way into an audition and a scholarship there.</p>
        <p>Only a remarkable natural facility can account for his getting, after a year, a scholarship to the School of American Ballet and two years later a corps de ballet contract with the New York City Ballet. His first assignment was to fill in for an injured dancer during the last two weeks of the 1969 season.</p>
        <p>''I was onstage surrounded by the most beautiful people I'd ever seen in my whole life, feeling completely unworthy to be on this planet,'' Mr. Caras recalls. ''I watched the curtain go up and felt this rush of cold air from the air-conditioned house, and I heard the music, and I thought: 'Well, I'll get through these two weeks and I'll go to college.' ''</p>
        <p>He lasted 14 years and was stage-struck every single minute. When he began taking photographs, he says: ''My territory was my world -- backstage, the dressing rooms, the wings. I had nowhere else to go, and no time to go anywhere else but there.''</p>
        <p>The City Ballet company photographer, Martha Swope, who had trained at the School of American Ballet, spotted the young dancer in the wings with his camera and asked to see his work. ''There's nothing like a dance background for a dance photographer,'' Ms. Swope says. ''Steve knows what the moment is, what's correct.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Caras recalls that Balanchine tacitly supported his dual career, keeping him on payroll as a dancer when he missed a rehearsal period to photograph the celebrated ballerina Alicia Alonso in Cuba, and refusing a request from the company ballet mistress Rosemary Dunleavy to hire him as an assistant when he was losing interest in dancing.</p>
        <p>''Mr. B. said, 'You're becoming a good photographer, a well-known photographer, why would you want to be Rosemary's baby?' '' Mr. Caras recalls. Balanchine offered to keep him on salary, suggesting that he dance only those roles he could manage along with his workload as a photographer.</p>
        <p>OVERALL, Mr. Caras's career at City Ballet followed the company fever chart: he danced in and photographed the 1981 Stravinsky Festival and the 1982 Tchaikovsky Festival, and worked with Jerome Robbins, who choreographed for him and cast him in principal parts. His photos appeared in publications including The New York Times, Time, Newsweek and Vogue, and on the cover of Dance Magazine and Ballet News.</p>
        <p>Balanchine's death in 1983 brought Mr. Caras his most difficult assignment -- and a revelation. The company ballet master John Taras, who had hoped to commission a death mask (''It was too late, or there were objections,'' Mr. Taras recalls), asked Mr. Caras to photograph the choreographer in his coffin. The photographer, who ''had never photographed Mr. B. at such close range,'' arrived at the Cathedral of Our Lady of the Sign when it opened on the day of the funeral and stayed for two hours after the photos were done, listening to the mourners who showed up before the service ''talking to him, kneeling next to him to say thank you.''</p>
        <p>''This was our audience, people that kept us working all these years,'' Mr. Caras continues. ''As usual, they knew what was going on before everybody else did. We felt very possessive, but Mr. B. belonged to everyone.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Martins, Balanchine's successor, had been friendly with Mr. Caras since his early days in the company, and the photographer's career continued seamlessly. ''Our paths didn't cross much when we were dancing,'' Mr. Martins says. ''I know Steve more as a photographer. His work is terrific.''</p>
        <p>But at the State Theater, Mr. Caras felt new pressures: requests were coming in for photographs showing the stage from center front, the audience's perspective. ''I tried sitting in the sound-and-light booth at the back of the orchestra section, where the computer boards are, which means I was shooting through a double pane of glass,'' he says. ''Though I thought the pictures weren't as sharp, the press department and the magazines and newspapers I shot for were happy. But I liked having one foot on the stage.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Caras was more at home shooting the studio portraits for the company's 40th anniversary souvenir book in 1988. Unmistakably, this was a labor of love for him. He bought vintage earrings for each woman in the corps to wear with her costume and hired hair and makeup artists to give each dancer a distinctive look. The shoot took three months. The pictures, seen in a standard 8-by-10-inch format, are handsome and colorful, but the miniature versions published 10 to a page are hard to read. The editor and critic Anita Finkel, writing in The New Dance Review, took exception to the ''overwrought hair.''</p>
        <p>Eventually, Mr. Caras was ready to move on. ''I wasn't able to shoot for me anymore,'' he says. Though documentary pictures of performance are now the gold standard, Mr. Caras also loves the dance studies and portraits that photographers like George Platt Lynes made in their studios under controlled lighting. ''I love working in the studio, taking the sensuality of a work and celebrating it on film, but dance photography didn't go there,'' he says. ''It tightened up. I could have followed Kyra Nichols around the stage with a camera for the rest of my life, but it was more of a fixation and less of a career.</p>
        <p>''And I was getting interested in teaching. I wanted to be hands-on with dancers after studying them under the microscope. Plus I was getting tired of the gray and the cold in New York, and I was seduced by the climate in South Florida.''</p>
        <p>In Florida, Mr. Caras has been able to explore color and extravagance as much as he likes. He shoots documentary pictures of dance in dress rehearsal whenever he can, ''so I can get closer and make more noise,'' he says. And he is able to experiment in the studio. Mr. Villella says the results are ''posteresque: they tell you everything you need to know.''</p>
        <p>DANCE Laura Leivick is writing a book about ballet and literature for Yale University Press.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Laura Leivick is writing a book about ballet and literature for Yale University Press.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
