<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lives; A Case Of Race Ennui</title>
    <meta content="MB133705" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="57" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215114"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jefferson, Margo</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine/Columns/Lives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901EFDE1038F935A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="875" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lives; A Case Of Race Ennui</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Margo Jefferson</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jefferson, Margo</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Margo Jefferson Lives essay on growing up as black upper-middle-class American with physician father and 'chic housewife' mother, and race as subtext (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A few years ago I found myself moderating a panel, all of whose participants were people of color. I no longer remember the topic. I do remember that each of us was supposed to make an introductory statement, and that when we got to my Chinese-American friend, he announced that he could talk about race but did not intend to. ''Race can be so boring,'' he said, and then sat back to see what would happen next.</p>
        <p>Each face in the crowd looked stricken, outraged, relieved or cautious. (The cautious ones kept glancing around to see which expression would win out before they committed themselves). But I was tickled. My friend wasn't asking any of us to ignore race; he was trying his best to provoke a discussion that just might be unpredictable.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A few years ago I found myself moderating a panel, all of whose participants were people of color. I no longer remember the topic. I do remember that each of us was supposed to make an introductory statement, and that when we got to my Chinese-American friend, he announced that he could talk about race but did not intend to. ''Race can be so boring,'' he said, and then sat back to see what would happen next.</p>
        <p>Each face in the crowd looked stricken, outraged, relieved or cautious. (The cautious ones kept glancing around to see which expression would win out before they committed themselves). But I was tickled. My friend wasn't asking any of us to ignore race; he was trying his best to provoke a discussion that just might be unpredictable.</p>
        <p>Race is no longer a biological reality. Scientists have shown that there are more differences within designated racial groups than between them. It's race history that matters now; our culture, our politics, the way our minds are formed and the oh-so-many tricks our psyches play. We know that love, sex, friendship and work don't take any one shape in our lives. Why do we coarsen and simplify race so often? Why must we so often make it boring?</p>
        <p>To bore isn't simply to be dull and monotonous; it is to drive, drill or close in relentlessly. When I was growing up it was a bore to be praised over and over for acting like any other upper-middle-class American. Speaking standardized English became ''You speak so beautifully'' or ''articulately.'' A father who was a doctor and a mother who was a chic housewife could suddenly be a cause of astonishment, delight or chilly disbelief, as in this exchange from my elementary school years:</p>
        <p>The parent of a friend: ''And what does your father do?''</p>
        <p>Me: ''He's a pediatrician.''</p>
        <p>(Pause)</p>
        <p>Parent: ''A pediatrician? Are you sure you don't mean a podiatrist?''</p>
        <p>I repeated this exchange to my mother and she explained the subtext with chagrin and reluctance.</p>
        <p>I must be prepared for such remarks, she said, but everyone wasn't so insecure or so prejudiced. Did it affect all of my relations with schoolmates, not least the child of this rude and doubting parent? No. This kind of thing came and went, like bad and good weather, like a slap or a scolding followed by ease and good times.</p>
        <p>I used to think it a luxury that the whites I knew didn't have to think so much about race. ''Consciously think about race'' is what I should have said, for race was there, knocking around in the nether regions of their minds, lurching to the surface in all kinds of ways. The part of a person that must study race consciously from childhood on -- race etiquette, race facts and fictions, race terrors, delights and grotesqueries -- is studying a second language. Nowadays, everybody seems to need one. And languages are best learned early in life.</p>
        <p>But I don't want to sound smug. This learning can overwhelm you in all kinds of ways. Your ideas can get stale and repetitive. Your vocabulary can get stunted. Your defenses can start to matter more than the freedom to think and act as you please. And then there are the scoldings and penalties when you make a mistake. How could you, how dare you shame your own people by doing something that showed them in a bad light? And how little it used to take for that light to shine! At one point I developed an unsavory habit of tidying up any public bathroom I'd been in lest the white person who came in next thought me responsible for such slovenliness.You can get away with this -- I can't,'' I would think, in scorn and despair.</p>
        <p>What a dreary little compulsion. Boring in the deepest sense, for we are wrong to think of boredom as a kind of civilized weariness. To be in the grip of boredom is to be paralyzed, stuck in a past that makes the present hopeless and the future pointless. The storytellers and the audience keep changing, but the story stays the same.</p>
        <p>It would bore me, for instance -- I would find it unbearable, in fact -- to think that anyone reading this believes that the Race Question takes up all my social and psychic time. Whole portions of my life are spent acting, thinking and dreaming in ways that have nothing to do with racial crisis; moving between white and black culture with pleasure and a sense of entitlement. And I don't always bother to call them ''black'' and ''white.'' Race is permanently stored in my memory. (In America, if it's not stored in your memory it's stored in your fantasies.) Sometimes I summon it up and arrange it in all sorts of ways. Sometimes circumstances demand a quite conventional narrative. And sometimes race is there but not there, like those galaxies that are invisible to the naked eye and can only be seen accurately when one turns the most refined equipment on them with the greatest care.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
