<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Girl Scout</title>
    <meta content="16KELLYT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215034"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kelly, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, April</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Be the One (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E3DE1F39F935A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="712" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Girl Scout</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By David Kelly</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kelly, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>David Kelly reviews book Be the One by April Smith (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BE THE ONE</p>
        <p>By April Smith.</p>
        <p>317 pp. New York: Alfred A. Knopf. $24.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BE THE ONE</p>
        <p>By April Smith.</p>
        <p>317 pp. New York: Alfred A. Knopf. $24.</p>
        <p>WHAT is it about sex? Why do people who have no trouble writing about other spectator sports -- boxing, baseball, synchronized swimming -- come a cropper when called on to describe what a man and a woman (or any other combination) do in bed?</p>
        <p>Take April Smith. The heroine of her new thriller, Cassidy Sanderson, is a 35-year-old scout for the Los Angeles Dodgers. Cassidy is the only female scout in the major leagues, and she works as hard and drinks as much as any of her colleagues. ''Be the One'' is at its best when the action is on or near a ball field. When it moves to a bedroom (or, in this case, a Bentley), watch out:</p>
        <p>''She forces herself to slow down, to savor the untying of the tie, the opening up and pushing apart of the jacket and the white dress shirt, off his shoulders like the wings of an angel, drinking from the pool between the small bones, then both of them clawing gracelessly along the pleated panels of soft hide in order to do this thing. . . . Now his fingers are enslaving as they compress the tendons of her wrists, forcing them, in the last unbinding moment, to hold their arms straight out together: a double crucifixion; throats exposed, and blood-red fists.''</p>
        <p>Jeez. Unfortunately for Cassidy but fortunately for Joe Galinis, her partner in crucifixion, she's a fool for love, ''lost in a daydream of perpetual sex.'' There's romance too: he sends her flowers with a card that says, ''Your breasts are like diamonds.'' (Is that a compliment?) Like Ana Grey, the F.B.I. agent who narrated Smith's superior first novel, ''North of Montana,'' Cassidy is feisty; unlike Ana, she's a doofus. It's hard to root for her, and not just because she works for the Dodgers. According to Smith, ''a batter has a quarter of a second to commit to the swing,'' which is approximately the amount of time Cassidy spends on her own decisions.</p>
        <p>The problems start in the Dominican Republic when Joe, a West Coast developer, and Alberto Cruz, the young phenom Cassidy is scouting, take turns driving her drunken self through a hurricane. Some kind of accident occurs. Back in Los Angeles, Cassidy is soon contending with blackmail, voodoo and money laundering -- but, in contradistinction to everyone else, including the reader, she never seems too sure where this is all heading.</p>
        <p>Smith writes perceptively about California, and persuasively about the Dominican Republic: ''Cassidy can remember shanties painted lemon yellow, women at a water pump outside the farmacia, dusty alleys hung with laundry, strange-looking mongrel dogs, which, like everything else in town, looked as if they had been put together out of spare parts.'' And she demonstrates an affinity with the outsider, whether it's Cassidy trying to impress a roomful of baseball men or Alberto taking in the splendors of an all-American mall:</p>
        <p>''Cassidy keeps them moving up escalators and down ramps, wondering what goes on in the kid's head when he sees stuff like the window of F. A. O. Schwarz -- all that whizzing and whirring, sparkle Barbies and Lego Ferris wheels -- and outside the store a huge bronze bear, big as a church. How does it feel, when work is a hundred-year-old sugar mill and home is a shack near a sewage trench with pigs in the backyard, to find yourself in a completely fabricated environment, where the trees are fake and the sun, through arched skylights, is a shy and tentative guest?''</p>
        <p>The story takes place in 1994 and 1995, so we hear some sorrowful talk about the possibility of a ''baseball family'' (the O'Malleys -- as in ''Hitler, Stalin and Walter O'Malley'') selling the team to a ''big diversified corporation'' (read Rupert Murdoch). Those were the years of the baseball strike, which Smith doesn't mention; in fact, she has big-leaguers showing up for spring training in 1995 a month before they actually did. But this is fiction, after all, and since the book also never mentions O. J. Simpson or Tommy Lasorda, she can only be commended for her reticence.</p>
        <p>David Kelly is an editor at the Book Review.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">David Kelly is an editor at the Book Review.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
