<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No One People Owns Jerusalem</title>
    <meta content="16ARMS$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000722T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215420"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Jerusalem</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Armstrong, Karen</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel/Jerusalem</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E4DD143BF935A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1107" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No One People Owns Jerusalem</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Karen Armstrong</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Armstrong, Karen</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Karen Armstrong Op-Ed article contends political expedience, today as in the past, demands pragmatic coexistence of Jews, Muslims and Christians in Jerusalem; proposes Rome, the capital of two sovereign states, as possible model for future of Jerusalem (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The most difficult issue that Ehud Barak and Yasir Arafat will have to deal with is likely to be the future status of Jerusalem. Jerusalem has become so central to the interior landscape of Jews, Christians and Muslims that politicians have a difficult time engaging in a rational debate about rights and sovereignty. Even those Israelis and Palestinians who have no religious beliefs contend that Jerusalem is ''holy'' to them, so sacred to their cultural and personal identity that it is beyond the normal give-and-take of political negotiation.</p>
        <p>Nobody could doubt Mr. Barak's commitment to peace, but he holds fast to the claim that has acquired the force of a mantra in Israeli politics: Jerusalem is the eternal and indivisible capital of the State of Israel.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The most difficult issue that Ehud Barak and Yasir Arafat will have to deal with is likely to be the future status of Jerusalem. Jerusalem has become so central to the interior landscape of Jews, Christians and Muslims that politicians have a difficult time engaging in a rational debate about rights and sovereignty. Even those Israelis and Palestinians who have no religious beliefs contend that Jerusalem is ''holy'' to them, so sacred to their cultural and personal identity that it is beyond the normal give-and-take of political negotiation.</p>
        <p>Nobody could doubt Mr. Barak's commitment to peace, but he holds fast to the claim that has acquired the force of a mantra in Israeli politics: Jerusalem is the eternal and indivisible capital of the State of Israel.</p>
        <p>This policy, however understandable, is not politically expedient. There can be no lasting peace in the Middle East unless there is a solution for Jerusalem that will satisfy not only  the Palestinians and the Arabs, but also the whole Muslim world.</p>
        <p>Jerusalem has been sacred to Muslims ever since the Prophet Muhammad began to preach in 610 A.D.; Muslims have lived and worshiped in Jerusalem as long as Anglo-Saxons have been in Britain; Jerusalem is the third-holiest city of Islam. Muslims in the Arab countries, Iran, Pakistan, central and southeast Asia and Africa may accept a compromise, but not total, permanent Israeli sovereignty.</p>
        <p>Indeed, Muslims are likely to become more intransigent. History shows that Jerusalem has always become more important to a people after they have lost it and after political catastrophe. The city only became central to Judaism after its destruction by King Nebuchadnezzar in 586 B.C., the deportation of the Jews to Babylon and the subsequent building of the Second Temple after their return. But the new cult of Jerusalem became exclusive, forbidding access to the temple not only to gentiles, but even to Israelites who had not been exiled.</p>
        <p>Similarly, after the Muslims lost Jerusalem to the Crusaders in 1099, the holy city became more crucial to Muslims than ever before. When Saladin took Jerusalem from the Crusaders in 1187, the city became far more aggressively Islamic and more wary of other faiths.</p>
        <p>The situation today is particularly explosive, because there is a clash between two peoples who have either lost or may be in the process of losing Jerusalem. Jews have returned to rule the holy city after an exile of nearly 2,000 years. After the Holocaust, Jerusalem has become even more sacred to Jewish identity. Many see Jewish Yerushalayim arising phoenix-like from the ashes of Auschwitz. Jews are, therefore, in the first flush of their reunion with the city.</p>
        <p>But Palestinians see Jerusalem, now surrounded by the towering new Jewish neighborhoods, as a symbol of their own beleaguered identity. Their exile has only just begun; as they watch their holy city slipping daily from their grasp, Palestinians feel a renewed passion for Al Quds (''the Holy''). This clash is exacerbated by the fact that, rightly or wrongly, the Muslim world feels humiliated by the West, with the loss of Jerusalem an intolerable symbol.</p>
        <p>After the Six Day War of 1967, the Arab-Israeli conflict was complicated by the emergence of a new religious Zionism and a Muslim fundamentalism that have no time for the cautious pragmatism of security politics. We cannot but recall the last Middle East summit held at Camp David, attended by President Anwar Sadat, who would be murdered in 1981 partly because he signed a peace treaty with Israel. The assassinations of Sadat and Yitzhak Rabin, both killed by fellow countrymen who were religious fundamentalists, remind us of the violence and terror that is often the result of giving politics a sacred, absolute dimension. Yet neither Sadat nor Rabin had to deal with anything as potentially dangerous as the status of Jerusalem.</p>
        <p>Once an issue like Jerusalem is elevated beyond the reach of compromise, the most extreme and immoral actions become not only possible but ''holy'' to a disaffected minority.  Great courage will be needed to cut through the prevailing rhetoric, but without it, irrational mythology will prevail over sober rationalism.</p>
        <p>Israel began as a defiantly secular state. It was made possible, against great odds, by the inspired pragmatism of Zionist leaders, who accepted anything they were offered, even if it fell lamentably short of what was required, and did not allow themselves to be boxed in by ideology. Jerusalem has not always been the ''eternal and indivisible'' capital of Israel. Theodor Herzl, who made Zionism a political force, deplored the ''musty deposits of 2000 years of inhumanity, intolerance and foulness,'' when he visited in 1898. His first impulse was to tear the Old City down.</p>
        <p>In 1947, during the discussion leading up to the partition of Palestine by the United Nations, the Zionists first proposed that they take the modern Western suburbs and cede the old city and East Jerusalem to the Arabs; then they agreed that Jerusalem would become an international zone. The priority was the creation and survival of the Jewish state, not an impracticable seizure of the holy city of Zion. After the war between Israel and the Arabs in 1948, Israel occupied West Jerusalem and agreed that Jordan should take the old city and the eastern suburbs. It is only since 1967 that Israel has claimed exclusive control of the whole city.</p>
        <p>Such exclusive policies do not work in Jerusalem. When the Byzantine Christians gained control of the city in the fourth century, they systematically dispossessed the pagan majority and permanently banned Jews from Jerusalem. Their intolerant policies alienated the local populace. When Muslim armies invaded Palestine in 634, Jews greeted them and gave practical help.</p>
        <p>When the Muslims captured Jerusalem in 638, they invited the Jews to return to the holy city and left the Christian shrines and residences undisturbed. Until the Crusades, the city had a huge Christian majority and the three religions coexisted in relative harmony. The Muslims did not allow this simply because the Koran told them to respect the People of the Book, but because it made shrewd political sense.</p>
        <p>Pragmatic coexistence has worked better in Jerusalem than rigid ideology. Is such a solution an impossible dream today? In 1871, the new kingdom of Italy appropriated the papal states and confined Pius IX to the tiny city-state of the Vatican, where he lived in high dudgeon as a self-proclaimed prisoner. Until 1937, the popes  refused to recognize the new Italy or to negotiate with it. Today, Rome is the capital of two sovereign states, which live together in peace. Could this be a model for a future Jerusalem?</p>
        <p>Karen Armstrong is the author of ''The Battle for God'' and ''Jerusalem: One City, Three Faiths.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  July 22, 2000, Saturday  An Op-Ed article on July 16 about Jerusalem misstated the date when the pope recognized the state of Italy. The Vatican signed the Lateran Treaty in 1929.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: July 22, 2000, Saturday</p>
        <p>An Op-Ed article on July 16 about Jerusalem misstated the date when the pope recognized the state of Italy. The Vatican signed the Lateran Treaty in 1929.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Karen Armstrong is the author of ''The Battle for God'' and ''Jerusalem: One City, Three Faiths.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
