<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>It's Not About Race. Or Is It? Are You Sure?</title>
    <meta content="16COLU$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215250"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="COUNTY LINES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Profanity</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Applebome, Peter</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Profanity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E6D81F38F935A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1217" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>It's Not About Race. Or Is It? Are You Sure?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER APPLEBOME</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Applebome, Peter</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Peter Applebome County Lines column on reader response to his last one, about what they would have assumed and done or not done about loud, profane rap music blasting from car at gas pump within hearing distance of his 9-year-old daughter; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHERE were we?</p>
        <p>Oh, yes. When last heard from, we were assaying suburban manners and racial mores at a gas station in Millwood with a 9-year-old daughter in the back seat of the car and high-voltage, high-profanity rap blasting out of the car at the next gas pump. The dilemma was what, if anything, to say to or do about the gentleman sharing his expletive-laden music with the world. The question posed to readers was what would you do and why would you do or not do it? Maintain your silence and chalk it up to one of life's myriad annoyances? Make a polite request to turn it down? What if the offending driver had not been a black prison guard, but rather a snotty rich white kid in his dad's Land Rover? Would a comment be more appropriate then? Is this a real issue or just white-bread squeamishness?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHERE were we?</p>
        <p>Oh, yes. When last heard from, we were assaying suburban manners and racial mores at a gas station in Millwood with a 9-year-old daughter in the back seat of the car and high-voltage, high-profanity rap blasting out of the car at the next gas pump. The dilemma was what, if anything, to say to or do about the gentleman sharing his expletive-laden music with the world. The question posed to readers was what would you do and why would you do or not do it? Maintain your silence and chalk it up to one of life's myriad annoyances? Make a polite request to turn it down? What if the offending driver had not been a black prison guard, but rather a snotty rich white kid in his dad's Land Rover? Would a comment be more appropriate then? Is this a real issue or just white-bread squeamishness?</p>
        <p>The idea was to offer something of a Rorschach test on race. What to make of the incident and the two people involved, the white suburbanite and the black man blasting out rap? The blizzard of e-mail messages I got did provide much of that. But, in the end, they provided a lot more.</p>
        <p>One could argue that the real flaw implicit in this parable was the presupposition about race. Implicit in the scenario was the notion that race was an issue, that, in fact, there is something inherently different in how one views the situation depending on whether the other driver was black or white. It is, as several readers pointed out, an unfortunate assumption, since I knew nothing about the driver other than the color of his skin, his occupation and his choice of music.</p>
        <p>But, of course, that misapprehension goes well beyond race. And what was most interesting in your e-mail was the instant assumptions and judgments many of you made about everyone involved.</p>
        <p>Linda Solomon of New Rochelle, a ''49-year-old, white professional suburban mother of two bi-racial sons,'' ignoring the fact that the issue for me had been profanity, not volume, proudly announced she plays her sons' CD's so loud it makes other cars shake. She envisioned, one guesses, a thoroughly enlightened world in which everyone blasted profane rap loud enough to induce deafness. ''If you asked me to turn down the music, I'd probably smile, say 'no,' and because I'm basically a nice person, I would refrain from calling you a jerk,'' she allowed. ''Heck, when your daughter becomes a teenager, she'll just say it for me.''</p>
        <p>One reader's mossback jerk is another's hopeless, mushy-headed liberal, like the reader who opined: ''The one impression you conveyed, more clearly than anything else, is the larded weight of your own hopelessly pathetic, tired, liberal guilt.'' The other driver, this reader deduced, was a ''lout'' and ''miscreant,'' and the writer helpfully advised: ''Explain to your daughter how hateful that type of music is and how despicable the people who both make and listen to it are.''</p>
        <p>Some of you assumed my reference to the driver as a prison guard was an attempt to render him ominous. Others assumed it portrayed him as somewhat benign. I meant neither. Several people made reference to my apparent fears of a physical confrontation -- I had none and cited none. I had used the word confrontation thinking of a possible exchange of words, not blows. Two readers said that if this is the biggest racial dilemma I face then I must live a myopic life. I never said it was.</p>
        <p>I received many thoughtful, insightful letters. Rita Stewart of Rye, along with several others, made the point that the issue was not race but rudeness. She compared the black motorist's high-volume rap with the high-volume nattering of a white woman using a cell phone at an upscale food shop.</p>
        <p>Several readers took me to task -- fairly -- for not using the occasion to teach my daughter a lesson about manners and being considerate of others.</p>
        <p>And while most people said they would not have said anything -- life's too short being the main thought -- several said I demeaned the other driver by not giving him the benefit of the doubt and expecting a reasonable response.</p>
        <p>''Prison guards have daughters, too,'' wrote Kenneth Jacobs of Mamaroneck. ''I am confident that if you had approached the man politely and said, 'Excuse me, but the song you are playing contains a lot of profanity that may be O.K. for you and me, but I'd like my daughter not to hear. Would you please lower the volume until you or I have finished pumping our gas?'the guard would have lowered the volume immediately. Even if the guard had refused, I am positive that his refusal would not have triggered a physical confrontation of the sort you imagined.''</p>
        <p>Others, noting the man's high-stress, low-status job, said that even if the music was too loud and too raunchy, he deserved to be cut some slack and his music should be seen as an understandable and harmless way to blow off steam, not an in-your-face gesture.</p>
        <p>Two of the most compelling responses came from black women. The first, Joyce Howard of the Bronx, told of coming down the steps of the Cathedral of St. John the Divine after church and being ''assaulted by the boom-boom, hip-hop noise'' coming from a black S.U.V. with a handsome young black man inside. She said she politely asked him to turn the volume down, and he dutifully complied. ''Now, my situation was different from yours, because he was not at all threatened by my gray, Afro-style hair or my black face or my grandmotherly physique. . . . You don't have these same circumstances on your side.''</p>
        <p>Mary Robinson of New Rochelle said the incident was about conduct, not color:</p>
        <p>''What would I do? Why would I do or not do it,'' she wrote. ''I would close the windows of my car, complete my business as quickly as possible, and explain to my child /grandchild how that incident was a graphic example of inconsiderate behavior, better known as bad manners. Coincidentally, I am a woman of color, the mother of a correction officer and a resident of Westchester.''</p>
        <p>If there's a clear message in all this, it's in the dangers of stereotyping. Reasonable people can easily differ on whether to take offense and what, if anything, to say. But, as several readers pointed out, whatever one decided to do or not do should be determined by one's own instincts, not by the color of the guy's skin.</p>
        <p>A final thought. I had little to lose in this exchange. I was hoping to get a reaction. But, in fact, it bothered me that people seemed to assume so much about me from their own reading or misreading of my motives and behavior.</p>
        <p>I imagine the guy in the other car would also have been bothered by the myriad assumptions made about him -- assumptions that get made all the time through the distorting mirror of race.</p>
        <p>COUNTY LINES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
