<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="16FSUM$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215503"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE4D8153BF935A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="885" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>3-10</p>
        <p>Russian Military Seeks To Increase Arms Sales  Russia's military industrial establishment is engaged in a major effort to increase arms sales to Asia, the Middle East and Africa and is expanding its share of the lucrative global arms market.</p>
        <p>1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>3-10</p>
        <p>Russian Military Seeks To Increase Arms Sales  Russia's military industrial establishment is engaged in a major effort to increase arms sales to Asia, the Middle East and Africa and is expanding its share of the lucrative global arms market.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Camp David's Delegates  While it is impossible to know what is going on at the negotiating tables inside the secluded Camp David, the contrasting teams of delegates reflect the serious intent on reaching some kind of deal. Everything will eventually come down to the leaders themselves, but the delegations offer a road map to the process.</p>
        <p>10</p>
        <p>Sri Lankan Support in Canada  Fund-raising for the Liberation Tigers of Tamil Eelam is illegal in the United States, but Canada has no such prohibition, and Canadian officials and Sri Lankan diplomats say it has become an important source of support for the Sri Lankan rebels.</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>Haitian Election Results Upheld  Haitian officials say they will stand by the results of their recent elections despite threats from international donors to suspend aid over a vote-counting method they deemed unfair and unacceptable.</p>
        <p>10</p>
        <p>Hong Kong Pollster Warned  A prominent pollster said he was warned by the head of Hong Kong University not to publish surveys critical of the Beijing-appointed chief executive of Hong Kong, Tung Chee-hwa, raising fears about academic freedom.</p>
        <p>10</p>
        <p>Canadian Tornado Kills 9  A campground tornado in Alberta, Canada, has killed nine people while leaving more than 130 injured and 400 in shelters.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>12-22</p>
        <p>Clinton Called On to Bring Star Power to Campaign  A rising tide of Democratic leaders contend that President Clinton, who is still revered by a core of the party's constituents, should play a prominent role campaigning for Vice President Al Gore, who is trailing Gov. George W. Bush in several battleground states.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Vice President Al Gore presented his own economic proposals as ''tried and true'' in a continuation of his assault on Gov. George W. Bush's record in Texas.</p>
        <p>20</p>
        <p>Tobacco Jurors Speak Out  The six jury members who punished the tobacco industry with a $144.8 billion punitive damage settlement in Florida saw the industry as dishonest and arrogant throughout the two-year trial, the jurors said.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Even if the award in the Florida class-action lawsuit is eventually reduced or thrown out, the size of the figure has stunned legal experts.</p>
        <p>19</p>
        <p>Researchers See Bias  Asian and Asian-American scientists are staying away from jobs at national weapons laboratories, saying that researchers of Asian descent have been systematically harassed and denied advancement.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Flight Delays Worsen  Last summer was the worst on record for airline delays, prompting the airlines and the Federal Aviation Administration to try to ease the burden on passengers. Yet despite those efforts, this summer is turning out to be even worse.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Philadelphia's Starring Role  Philadelphia has suffered some loss of face recently, but the city is still hard at work preparing for the Republican National Convention.</p>
        <p>12</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>23-28</p>
        <p>Senate Campaign's Intensity Drops Without Giuliani  The Senate race in New York State has become less intense, and less interesting to many voters, since Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani dropped out as Hillary Rodham Clinton's opponent. And a fog has descended over this once highest of high-flying  campaigns, leaving the candidate's  advisers discussing what to do about it -- if anything, since it remains a matter of debate in both campaigns whether all this attention was ever a good thing for either candidate.</p>
        <p>23</p>
        <p>Nightclub Owner Slain Over Bill  The owner of a popular Korean nightclub in Midtown Manhattan was shot and killed by a customer who was enraged by his bill of nearly $1,000, the police said. The customer shot the owner, Sang Dal Choi, 43, several times in the head inside the Dae Tong Ryung club, in the basement of 6 East 32nd Street.</p>
        <p>25</p>
        <p>Corzine's Record Spending  A final accounting shows that Jon Corzine spent $36.7 million, almost all of it his own money, to beat former New Jersey Governor Jim Florio and win the Democratic nomination for United States Senate.</p>
        <p>28</p>
        <p>Fresh Air Fund</p>
        <p>27</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>30-31</p>
        <p>John O. Pastore  A dominant figure in Rhode Island politics for three decades who was the first Italian-American to be elected as a Governor and to sit in the United States Senate, he was 90.</p>
        <p>30</p>
        <p>John Morgan  A dashingly dapper dandy who took it upon himself to dictate to the  proper English about proper manners, he was 41.</p>
        <p>31</p>
        <p>Ursule Molinaro  A novelist and translator whose  career spanned five decades, she was believed to have been in her 80's.</p>
        <p>31</p>
        <p>Chess</p>
        <p>30  Weather</p>
        <p>26  Cong. Vote</p>
        <p>27</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
