<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Jazz Can Take Itself Too Seriously</title>
    <meta content="16RATL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215140"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kenny G</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Armstrong, Louis (1900-71)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ratliff, Ben</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Metheny, Pat</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEFDB1038F935A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="984" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Jazz Can Take Itself Too Seriously</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN RATLIFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ratliff, Ben</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ben Ratliff column responds to guitarist Pat Metheny's June letter, posted on Web site and meant for his fans but forwarded around the world, blasting smooth jazz saxophonist Kenny G for embedding voice of Louis Armstrong within new recording of What a Wonderful World; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE most widely read piece of writing on jazz in the last few months, I would imagine, has been by the guitarist Pat Metheny. In early June, Mr. Metheny outlined his views on the smooth-jazz million-seller Kenny G within the discussion section of his own Web site,  patmethenygroup.com. (It's no longer posted there.) Mr. Metheny's letter (intended only for the fans who visit his site and written in heat-of-the-moment e-mailese) has been forwarded around the world; there was a day last month when I received it a dozen times.</p>
        <p>The letter is impressively honest and rather thoughtful. It proceeds from evenhanded assessment -- a rare response where smooth jazz is concerned -- to persecutory rage, setting up Kenny G as a defiler in the temple of jazz. ''I first heard him a number of years ago,'' Mr. Metheny wrote of Kenny G, ''playing as a sideman. . . . My impression was that he was someone who had spent a fair amount of time listening to the more pop-oriented sax players of that time, like Grover Washington or David Sanborn, but was not really an advanced player, even in that style. He had major rhythmic problems and his harmonic and melodic vocabulary was extremely limited, mostly to pentatonic-based and blues-lick derived patterns.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE most widely read piece of writing on jazz in the last few months, I would imagine, has been by the guitarist Pat Metheny. In early June, Mr. Metheny outlined his views on the smooth-jazz million-seller Kenny G within the discussion section of his own Web site,  patmethenygroup.com. (It's no longer posted there.) Mr. Metheny's letter (intended only for the fans who visit his site and written in heat-of-the-moment e-mailese) has been forwarded around the world; there was a day last month when I received it a dozen times.</p>
        <p>The letter is impressively honest and rather thoughtful. It proceeds from evenhanded assessment -- a rare response where smooth jazz is concerned -- to persecutory rage, setting up Kenny G as a defiler in the temple of jazz. ''I first heard him a number of years ago,'' Mr. Metheny wrote of Kenny G, ''playing as a sideman. . . . My impression was that he was someone who had spent a fair amount of time listening to the more pop-oriented sax players of that time, like Grover Washington or David Sanborn, but was not really an advanced player, even in that style. He had major rhythmic problems and his harmonic and melodic vocabulary was extremely limited, mostly to pentatonic-based and blues-lick derived patterns.''</p>
        <p>But Kenny G (his last name is Gorelick) had other resources. ''He did show a knack for connecting to the basest impulses of the large crowd,'' Mr. Metheny wrote, ''by deploying his most effective licks (holding long notes and playing fast runs -- never mind that there were lots of harmonic clams in them) at the key moments. . . . The other main thing I noticed was that he also, as he does to this day, plays horribly out of tune -- consistently sharp.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Metheny believes that Kenny G's music should be assessed as jazz, not as instrumental pop. ''He SHOULD be compared to John Coltrane or Wayne Shorter,'' he contended, ''on his abilities (or lack thereof) to play the soprano saxophone.''</p>
        <p>But it was what followed that got people excited. The subject was Kenny G's 1999 recording of the song ''What a Wonderful World,'' in which the voice of Louis Armstrong is embedded within the new recording by Kenny G's quartet. ''With this single move,'' Mr. Metheny wrote, ''Kenny G became one of the few people on earth I can say that I really can't use at all -- as a man, for his incredible arrogance to even consider such a thing, and as a musician, for presuming to share the stage with the single most important figure in our music.'' And then he adds a hint of personal retribution: ''Everything I said here is exactly the same as what I would say to Gorelick if I ever saw him in person. And if I ever DO see him anywhere, at any function -- he WILL get a piece of my mind.''</p>
        <p>Taking a cue from Mr. Metheny's challenge (''I am also amazed that there HASN'T already been an outcry against this among music critics -- where ARE they on this?????!?!?!?!''), I bought ''Classics in the Key of G'' to hear the offending song and listened to a Kenny G album for the first time in my life. Like Mr. Metheny, I never felt one way or the other about Mr. Gorelick; his music is ambient dandelion-fluff that I knew plenty about from being put on hold by telephone receptionists. He sells millions, yet doesn't measure up to Coltrane? I'd sooner get riled about why I can't shoot my tax returns at the moon and get them back an hour later, fully executed.</p>
        <p>When I heard ''What a Wonderful World,'' I experienced another first: I felt something from a Kenny G song. This mostly came from Armstrong. His singing is the only life in the track. But it came from the juxtaposition, too. For anyone to use Armstrong this way is horrid; the jolt you feel, whether you like the song or not, is caused by the arrogance it takes to make that hop into the land of the dead.</p>
        <p>But sometimes pop culture is horrid, and Kenny G, Louis Armstrong and Pat Metheny all belong to pop culture. Armstrong's public persona was marked by generosity; he was the least rarefied of geniuses. And ''What a Wonderful World'' itself is not sacred. It's perfect within itself, but it's merely pleasant, a big, dewy Barney smile.</p>
        <p>In selecting ''What a Wonderful World,'' Mr. Gorelick made a good choice for his own purposes. I'm afraid that it works. The last 20 years of intelligent writing about Armstrong has established that he was capable of both the freshest, freest pieces of improvisation as well as cheery schlock; and to understand him is to understand that American pop culture is nothing without both impulses. I think I'd be more upset if Kenny G sampled a really lively, rhythmic Armstrong performance. But he wouldn't. It wouldn't work. Pop may be opportunistic, but above all it's practical.</p>
        <p>If Kenny G belongs to a tradition, it isn't jazz so much as advertising, in which music has a specific function: to provoke passivity. His use of an Armstrong tune is just giving way to the flow of commerce; it has no other meaning.</p>
        <p>There's a new ad for Pop-Tarts that uses Jimi Hendrix's version of ''The Star-Spangled Banner.'' I haven't seen people get hot about that. Where would they start? The crime of appropriating a moment from Woodstock? Or of appropriating Hendrix for the sake of a Pop-Tart? Or of the equating of Hendrix with a Pop-Tart? You realize, after a while, that Hendrix isn't the point. The point is, are you hungry?</p>
        <p>MUSIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
