<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Red Dot, Meet Green: If It's Tuesday, Network!: Singapore; A Caution Signal In Venture Capital</title>
    <meta content="MB061633" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215465"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Small Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Singapore</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">First Tuesday (Co)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arnold, Wayne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Singapore</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Singapore</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Small Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E1D6143BF935A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="473" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Red Dot, Meet Green: If It's Tuesday, Network!: Singapore; A Caution Signal In Venture Capital</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WAYNE ARNOLD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Arnold, Wayne</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Caution is the watchword at First Tuesday gathering of venture capitalists and new-economy entrepreneurs at Bar in Singapore, where consultants outnumber investors, and both outnumber entrepreneurs with viable ideas; only small minority of people in Southeast Asia regularly use Internet, and they are separated by geography, language, culture and regulatory barriers; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The spring rout on the Nasdaq caught Southeast Asia's dot-com industry in an awkward adolescent stage, somewhere between finding venture capital and a public offering.</p>
        <p>Here at Bar, a minimalist hang-out where 20- and 30-somethings come after work, business cards are flying like chips in a casino. But consultants outnumber venture capitalists, who in turn outnumber the people with the ideas worth financing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The spring rout on the Nasdaq caught Southeast Asia's dot-com industry in an awkward adolescent stage, somewhere between finding venture capital and a public offering.</p>
        <p>Here at Bar, a minimalist hang-out where 20- and 30-somethings come after work, business cards are flying like chips in a casino. But consultants outnumber venture capitalists, who in turn outnumber the people with the ideas worth financing.</p>
        <p>Caution is the watchword, and one good indication is Chia Tek Yew's appointment book. Mr. Chia, chief executive of PricewaterhouseCoopers' Venture Accelerator, specializes in investing in high-technology start-ups. But these days, he said, venture capitalists are hiring his group to scrutinize the business plans of companies in which they want to invest.</p>
        <p>''They want someone to rubber-stamp them,'' said Mr. Chia, as he described how early hopes for easy riches had given way to questions about which businesses would prosper and which would die. ''The idea of spending someone else's money is gone,'' he said, adding that his own firm now insists on being a co-signer of its start-ups' checks.</p>
        <p>That, in a way, brings the region full circle. At this time last year, aspiring entrepreneurs were rare and venture capitalists willing to finance them even rarer. But government incentives and success stories from the United States changed all that, giving rise to what some say has been a gold rush of dot-com financing.</p>
        <p>Yet Southeast Asia presents its own disadvantages to potential investors. Political instability and civil strife around the region have scared off foreign investors to larger markets with more obvious Internet plays. So despite efforts to set up Southeast Asian versions of Nasdaq with easier listing requirements for high-tech start-ups, the prospects for a wildly received initial public offering are dimmer than before.</p>
        <p>Moreover, Southeast Asia as a market for online services is looking less lucrative. Only a tiny minority of the region's residents use the Internet so far, and they are spread across vast regions separated by language, culture and regulatory barriers. ''I won't look at a plan that says the company is looking at only one country or just Southeast Asia,'' Mr. Chia said.</p>
        <p>Fresh on many minds here are the travails of a local start-up called Catcha.com. Designed as a Yahoo-style search engine tailored for Southeast Asian Web surfers, the company is cutting staff after postponing plans to raise 55 million Singapore dollars ($31.5 million) in an initial public offering in May. Its 25-year-old founder has offered to work for free.</p>
        <p>WAYNE ARNOLD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
