<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lives; Learning Whiteness</title>
    <meta content="MB130021" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="45" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215103"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hispanic-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Chinese-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Conley, Dalton</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine/Columns/Lives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hispanic-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E5DE1038F935A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1365" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lives; Learning Whiteness</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Dalton Conley</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Conley, Dalton</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dalton Conley article on growing up as white child in largely minority housing project in New York City, where he and his sister had no idea they belong any kind of majority gruop; recalls enrolling in Lower East Side mini-school school where his mother had to choose between the black, Puerto Rican or Chinese class, all strictly segregated except for him (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the largely minority housing project where I grew up in the 1970's, race was not something mutable, like a freckle or a hairstyle; it defined who looked like whom, who was allowed to be in the group -- and who wasn't. But for my sister and me, as whites, race was turned inside out. We had no idea that we belonged to the majority group, the privileged one. We merely thought we didn't belong.</p>
        <p>That began to change when I started at the local public school, on the Lower East Side of Manhattan. The first day of classes, the principal called my mother and me into his office. The school was P.S. 4, a mini-school, named for its diminutive size. But the moniker reflected nothing about the size of the classes. There were three, each with about 40 students.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the largely minority housing project where I grew up in the 1970's, race was not something mutable, like a freckle or a hairstyle; it defined who looked like whom, who was allowed to be in the group -- and who wasn't. But for my sister and me, as whites, race was turned inside out. We had no idea that we belonged to the majority group, the privileged one. We merely thought we didn't belong.</p>
        <p>That began to change when I started at the local public school, on the Lower East Side of Manhattan. The first day of classes, the principal called my mother and me into his office. The school was P.S. 4, a mini-school, named for its diminutive size. But the moniker reflected nothing about the size of the classes. There were three, each with about 40 students.</p>
        <p>''We do not have a class for your son,'' the principal told my mother in a heavy Puerto Rican accent, looking down and smiling at me; I remember staring, transfixed, at his snakeskin boots, feeling as if they might slither around the floor of his office if I took my eyes off them. ''You see,'' he continued, ''there are the black and Puerto Rican classes.'' The words ''Puerto Rican'' stood out from the rest; they seemed to spring naturally from his mouth, whereas the English words dropped out like stillborns. ''And then there is the Chinese class. . . . '' He trailed off, as if he regretted the Chinese class. ''There have been many Chinese that come here now.'' They were coming from an ever-expanding Chinatown, which had crept into the other side of the school district.</p>
        <p>''So, which class do you prefer?'' he asked. ''You see, there is no white class.'' It now dawned on my mother that school desegregation did not necessarily mean classroom desegregation. ''I suppose we'll take the black class,'' she said. In this instance, the choices our race gave us were made quite explicit -- by a government institution, no less.</p>
        <p>I found myself in a crowded classroom with paint peeling from the walls and plaster falling from the ceiling. The teacher was a black woman with a slender frame but a booming voice. She normally taught fourth or fifth grade and wasn't too happy about being stuck with us first graders. She paced across the front of the room, intermittently drawing on the blackboard to illustrate what she was saying. She also compulsively brushed chalk residue off her hands and dress. As each day wore on the layer of chalk dust got progressively thicker, giving her skin a ghostlike quality, as if she were fading away -- along with our attention.</p>
        <p>As if to compensate for her weakening skin tone and our waning concentration, she grew stricter by the hour. In the mornings we could get away with whispering or fidgeting in our seats. But by 1 p.m., any peep or audible rustle meant a whack across the knuckles with a yardstick. For everybody but me.</p>
        <p>''Yo, your momma been on welfare so long,'' my classmate Earl whispered to me, ''her face is on food stamps.'' He gave a low five to the boy seated in front of him.</p>
        <p>''Up here right now, Earl,'' our teacher said. She stood, arms akimbo.</p>
        <p>Earl marched up slowly, staring at his sneakers, face down and Afro up, as if it offered protection. It didn't. She took his hands and whacked them three times with the thin edge of the ruler. I felt myself leap off the seat with each whack. I started to blink, and my cheeks began to twitch. Earl did not flinch or yelp in the least.</p>
        <p>He turned around and walked back to his desk with a stoicism that exceeded his age. When he passed by my seat, I stared down as he had in the presence of the teacher, unable to look him in the eyes. I remember catching a glimpse of his bloodied knuckles, where his brown skin parted to reveal the scarlet flesh underneath. I fantasized about being beaten myself, digging the graphite tip of my No. 2 pencil into my skin. Then I released the pressure, trying to share the sense of relief I imagined Earl felt after his punishment was over. At lunch Earl asked if he could sit next to me. I nodded. Still looking down, I tensed up and twitched, waiting for his blow. It never came. Instead, he offered me his Tater Tots. As if he could read my mind, he said, ''Aw, she's all right; don't worry about her.''</p>
        <p>Over the weeks, every kid received this form of corporal punishment, boys and girls alike. I was the only one who escaped -- and not, I knew even at the time, because I was particularly well behaved. Everyone involved took it for granted that a black teacher would never cross the racial line to strike a white student. The other kids didn't resent me for this. I even tried to get into fights in school, fights I knew I would lose; I wanted to feel the relief of being struck. But Earl, one of the largest kids there, took it upon himself to protect me. By the end of my first term, my mother noticed that I was twitching and blinking compulsively.</p>
        <p>Wanting to get to the bottom of my tics, my mother made an appointment with the principal. He wore the same gray snakeskin boots and sat on the edge of his desk, one foot swinging back and forth slowly, as if he were trying to hypnotize my mother.</p>
        <p>''Does the teacher hit Dalton?'' my mother asked.</p>
        <p>''Oh, no,'' he answered. ''In fact,'' he added, ''Dalton is the only student that is not hit.''</p>
        <p>''That must be it,'' she said. ''That's why he's twitching.''</p>
        <p>''So you want him to receive physical discipline as well, then?'' the principal asked, as if this were the logical conclusion to their conversation, as if Board of Ed. rules didn't explicitly ban corporal punishment. His boots had stopped moving and were now clamped against the side of his desk for balance as he leaned toward her.</p>
        <p>''No, no,'' she said, pushing her glasses back up the bridge of her nose. She asked whether something could be done to prevent the other kids from being struck.</p>
        <p>''No, Mrs. Conley,'' he explained in a tone that was simultaneously sympathetic and exasperated. ''The other parents had requested that their children be physically disciplined,'' he said. ''We knew that white parents spoil their kids, so she doesn't strike Dalton.''</p>
        <p>The Puerto Rican class had a Puerto Rican teacher who also hit the students, so the solution was to switch me to the Chinese class. The teacher there did not use corporal punishment. The local Asian population was still comparatively small, so the class had the added benefit of having fewer students. I transferred in during the first week of the spring semester. Half the lessons were taught in English, the other half in Chinese. I liked the friendly dynamics of the class and felt challenged by my language handicap, which compensated for the fact that by some error, I had been switched from my first-grade class into kindergarten.</p>
        <p>''When I call out your name, stand up,'' the teacher said during roll call on my first day. ''If you have an American name, tomorrow I will tell you your name in Chinese. If you have a Chinese name, tomorrow I will tell you your name in English.'' I was excited by the prospect of being renamed and merging into the group, of which I was the only ethnically non-Chinese member. Of course I didn't know then that none of the name pairs were actual translations, that there was no straightforward way to convert names from a tonal, character-based language to English.</p>
        <p>The next morning the instructor came in and started the roll call again. This time she read off two names for everyone: ''John,'' she said. He stood. ''Jiang.'' Then, ''Jaili: Julie.'' She was standing too, now. Then she got to me. ''Dalton,'' she said, sighing, almost apologetic. ''Dalton.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
