<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Octogenarians Ask: What Keeps Us Going?</title>
    <meta content="16AGIN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215203"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Longevity</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Center For Creative Retirement</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Matthews, Florence</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Matthews, Clyde</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Swirsky, Joan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Age, Chronological</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E5DC1E38F935A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1513" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Octogenarians Ask: What Keeps Us Going?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOAN SWIRSKY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Swirsky, Joan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Florence and Clyde Matthews, who established Center for Creative Retirement in 1980 at Long Island University's Southampton College and who are undertaking study of 80- to 100-year-olds to determine how aging of Long Islanders is influenced by psychological, spiritual, attitudinal and life-style factors; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN 1995, when Florence Matthews was a mere 76 and Clyde Matthews just 80, and they had been married only 55 years, they decided to conduct a study on the Island about the ingredients that go into long-lasting marriages.</p>
        <p>The couple, co-directors of the Center for Creative Retirement, which they established in 1980 at Southampton College of Long Island University, found that keeping romance alive and learning to compromise were central features in enduring and satisfying relationships.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN 1995, when Florence Matthews was a mere 76 and Clyde Matthews just 80, and they had been married only 55 years, they decided to conduct a study on the Island about the ingredients that go into long-lasting marriages.</p>
        <p>The couple, co-directors of the Center for Creative Retirement, which they established in 1980 at Southampton College of Long Island University, found that keeping romance alive and learning to compromise were central features in enduring and satisfying relationships.</p>
        <p>''When we got married,'' Mr. Matthews explained, ''the divorce rate was about 20 percent, but when we started our study, it was 50 percent. What we learned was that marriage was more important to men, but their wives didn't feel quite that way. Men should feel happier because women do so much more for their husbands than the opposite, and men live longer when they're married.''</p>
        <p>''I figured out that I said I love you 50,000 times, give or take a thousand,'' he added.</p>
        <p>Now, they are at it again: In May the Matthews became the principal investigators of a 53-question longevity study of 80- to 100-year-olds to determine how the aging of Long Islanders is influenced by psychological, spiritual, attitudinal and lifestyle factors. The survey is to be completed in September.</p>
        <p>''Despite the popular image of a frail and dependent older population,'' Mr. Matthews said, ''there is a rapidly increasing number of men and women in their 80's and 90's who are living active lives and contributing their life experiences and talents as volunteers at hospitals, cultural centers, educational institutions and other community organizations. Many are involved politically and socially and pursuing their own creative endeavors.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Matthews was a television producer ''when there were only 5,000 sets in our country,'' and the director of a successful public relations firm, which allowed him to retire in the mid-1950's. He has also written a novel (''The Ides of March Conspiracy,'' Arbor House, 1980), about how corporate and government computers violate privacy.</p>
        <p>The couple chose the Island for the survey because of its diverse cross-section of urban, suburban, semi-rural and rural populations.</p>
        <p>Deborah Y. Anderson, a professor in the graduate program of gerontology at Southampton College who is assisting in the study, cites Census Bureau figures showing that between 1960 and 1994, those 85 and older rose almost fourfold, a significantly larger increase than in any other group. By 1999 Census Bureau estimates, there are now nearly 5 million people 85 and over, and a projection of 12 million by 2010.</p>
        <p>Census data from 1996 offer a mixed picture of economic status: For the most part, the elderly have more assets than younger people, but poverty rates are relatively high for older blacks and Latinos.</p>
        <p>''A lack of money can affect creative aging,'' Dr. Anderson said. ''If you are worried about survival, it's hard to go to that higher level to find something meaningful and to maintain a sense of wonder about the world. And old-old age also brings the loss of friends and family.''</p>
        <p>Depression plagues more than 2 million of the 34 million Americans 65 and older, who also have a disproportionately high suicide rate, with white males being particularly vulnerable, according to data from the National Institute of Mental Health. Often, depression descends when people feel burdensome to their families or when they feel they no longer make a difference in the world.</p>
        <p>Much of healthy aging depends on good genes. In laboratory experiments, scientists have been able to get human cells to live much longer than normal, paving the way for new treatments for age-related diseases, cancer and the deterioration of memory. According to the Washington-based Administration on Aging, the prospect of altering the genetic code promises that in the near future, aging and infirmity might not be synonymous, and raises the possibility of extending the currently accepted limit of human life beyond the 124 years currently documented.</p>
        <p>Dr. Thomas Perls, director of the New England Centenarian Study in Boston and acting chief of gerontology at Beth Israel-Deaconess Medical Center, said: ''The average person has a remarkable set of genes that should allow life to go on into the late 80's, compressing the time of sickness until the end of life. But in this country, we're living about 10 years less than what our genes are capable of achieving because there is so much overweight, smoking, lack of exercise and horrible diets.''</p>
        <p>''But beyond 85, genetic booster rockets are needed,'' added Dr. Perls, who is also an assistant professor of medicine at the Harvard Medical School and the co-author (with Dr. Margery Silver) of ''Living to 100'' (Basic Books, 1999; www .livingto100.com). ''People who live well into the 80's and beyond are good at managing stress. They're also funny and many have a history of being thin.''</p>
        <p>Building an acronym for the British spelling of aging, he said that long life has everything to do with ''Attitude, Genes, Exercise, Interest, Nutrition and Getting rid of smoking.''</p>
        <p>Florence Matthews confirms this. ''Aging well is a tripartite thing,'' she said. ''It's a matter of genes, good living habits and a belief that things will go well or will get better. It's important not to dwell on what has gone wrong and not to wallow in adversity, which has a lot to do with staying active and involved -- and attitude, attitude, attitude.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Matthews holds a post-graduate degree in nutrition from Columbia Teacher's College and master's degrees in physiology and counseling. She developed the menu for the health spa at Gurney's Inn in Montauk and was the host of a monthly television program on nutrition and health on Long Island. Before all these second and third careers, she taught high school home economics in Valley Stream.</p>
        <p>But when she and her husband, who have two children and five grandchildren, moved to Springs, in East Hampton, 25 years ago, she said, ''it was a cultural desert in the wintertime.'' They founded the Hampton Round Table, ''to attract people who were interested in cultural affairs and the world at large.''</p>
        <p>''You don't suddenly get to be 80 and start to socialize! It starts much earlier.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Anderson reinforced this view. ''The old life map,'' she said, ''was that you retired at 65 and sat in a rocking chair and disengaged from life around you. Today, creative aging involves calling on core characteristics, like optimism, that probably existed in youth and are magnified in old age. Even people with chronic medical conditions who maintain friendships and are open to new ideas and keep as active as they can find the spark.''</p>
        <p>Volunteering, she added, is ''one way for older people who have developed skills and talents over a lifetime to share the wealth of their experience with others.'' Of the 45 million Americans who volunteer, about a third are elderly, the Administration on Aging reports.</p>
        <p>Exercise is also important. The Matthews are walkers and swimmers who gave up tennis only a few years ago because they both hurt their tennis arms. '''I interviewed a woman who was 99 who said she got plenty of exercise by tap dancing,'' Mr. Matthews said.</p>
        <p>Another key factor is a sense of spirituality, Mr. Matthews said. ''Belief is a longevity tool that enables you to transcend obstacles,'' he added, ''and it has a very beneficial effect on your immune system, your attitudes and thoughts.''</p>
        <p>On average, women live about eight years longer than men. While the reasons for this are not known, Christopher L. Hayes, a professor of gerontology and psychology at Southampton College, said his research on women over 85 shows that ''in addition to good genes, what is striking is their ability to adapt, to roll with the punches, to make lemonade out of lemons.''</p>
        <p>Many women who are housebound with illnesses or disabilities ''are genuinely happy and have a good quality of life,'' he added. ''They seem to be able to verbalize their needs to friends and physicians, maintain friendships, envision and plan for the future and to be their own best advocates. Their disabilities don't run their lives; they run their lives.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Hayes also cited the increasing use of computers that ''allow elderly women and men to keep in touch with the world.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Matthews agrees. ''I couldn't imagine myself going into the new millennium without a computer,'' she said of the computer and printer she bought last year. ''Curiosity is very important. People have to realize that it's great to be 80 or older and alive and doing things. My message is: Don't be afraid.''</p>
        <p>Long Island residents over 80 who wish to take part in the survey can contact county departments that assist older people: in Nassau, (516) 571-5902; in Suffolk, (631) 853-8200. Information is also available at a toll-free number, (877) 651-0400.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
