<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>FOOTLIGHTS</title>
    <meta content="16FOOT$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215251"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Garden Conservancy</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hershenson, Roberta</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E6D81F38F935A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="833" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>FOOTLIGHTS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERTA HERSHENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hershenson, Roberta</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Garden Conservancy of Cold Spring, NY, is set to begin annual Open Days Program, during which more than 400 private suburban, farm and estate gardens in 26 states, including several in Westchester County, NY, will be open to public; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>How Others' Gardens Grow</p>
        <p>When luscious summer skies compete with museum walls, nature's own art has an added appeal. A happy blend of the natural and fabricated is the garden, where design receives a boost or a boot from the unpredictable elements.</p>
        <p>The Garden Conservancy, based in Cold Spring, does not promise the viewing conditions of a gallery, but its Open Days Program may offer diversions from another sun-besotted Sunday by the pool. Curious about what others have done with begonias and day lilies? Risk an attack of petal envy in the private garden of a stranger. People really proud of their gardens will offer you a look and may even provide a glass of iced tea.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>How Others' Gardens Grow</p>
        <p>When luscious summer skies compete with museum walls, nature's own art has an added appeal. A happy blend of the natural and fabricated is the garden, where design receives a boost or a boot from the unpredictable elements.</p>
        <p>The Garden Conservancy, based in Cold Spring, does not promise the viewing conditions of a gallery, but its Open Days Program may offer diversions from another sun-besotted Sunday by the pool. Curious about what others have done with begonias and day lilies? Risk an attack of petal envy in the private garden of a stranger. People really proud of their gardens will offer you a look and may even provide a glass of iced tea.</p>
        <p>Open Days, a program spanning 26 states and more than 400 private gardens, started six years ago in New York and Connecticut.  Gardens available for viewing vary from suburban plots (''small but completely beautiful and amazing,'' Stephanie Werskey, a spokeswoman, said) to expansive farm or estate gardens.</p>
        <p>And don't think that all are the work of professional designers. Do-it-yourselfers abound.</p>
        <p>Next Sunday three private gardens will be available for viewing in Westchester. These include a five-acre contoured swath in Cortlandt Manor, a Mount Kisco perennial and wildflower plot with a woodland gazebo and a 55-acre estate featuring cranes, peacocks and more than 2,000 plant species.  Admission to each garden is $4 a person.</p>
        <p>On Sept. 10 four more gardens will be on view. The Westchester season will end Oct. 15 at Cobamong Pond in Armonk, an estate garden with a lakeside path.</p>
        <p>To receive the Garden Conservancy directory, which includes garden locations and dates nationwide, call (888) 842-2442. Requests can also be mailed to the conservancy at Post Office Box 219, Cold Spring, N.Y. 10516. Include a check for $14.95 plus $3.50 for shipping and handling. Descriptions, driving directions and viewing hours are given, but there are no garden reviews.  ''We try not to rate them,'' Ms. Wersky said. ''It's such a personal thing, where one person's fancy can be someone else's folly.''</p>
        <p>Dancing the Landscape Away</p>
        <p>Tie down the lawn chairs; the dancers are coming. Sometimes a tree is just a tree, and sometimes it is a choreographic statement.  As for your own rolling lawn, have you considered its aesthetic potential?</p>
        <p>Dancers at Wave Hill, the New York City-owned, 28-acre public garden in the northwest Bronx, leave no stone wall unclimbed as they plumb the landscape for ideas. With the Hudson River and Palisades as backdrop, four dancers will perform on the grounds next Sunday and July 30 at 5 p.m. and July 26 at 6:30 p.m.</p>
        <p>Here's one show where onlookers won't get restless, since the audience must move from site to site along with the performers.</p>
        <p>The setting is casual, and children are welcome.  ''Kids come who don't normally attend dance performances,'' Anne Kuite, a spokeswoman, said.  ''They play on the side and sometimes watch and move along with the dancers.''</p>
        <p>This is the 10th season of summer dance at Wave Hill, produced in partnership with Dancing in the Streets. Seating is strictly bring-your-own, and picnicking is not allowed on the lawns. Performances are free, but there is an admission fee of $4, with no extra charge for sunsets. For more information, the number to call is (718) 549-3200.</p>
        <p>Where the New Music Is</p>
        <p>''Fugitive Star'' is coming to a theater near you -- that is if you happen to live near the Spanish Courtyard at Caramoor in Katonah. No, this is not a movie featuring Harrison Ford. The title refers to music commissioned by Caramoor and composed by Augusta Read Thomas. The piece will be performed not once but twice -- before and after intermission -- during a concert on July 28 by the Avalon String Quartet, which is completing a yearlong residency at Caramoor. The concert begins at 6:30 p.m. and includes music by Mozart and Brahms.</p>
        <p>The theory is that new music is often unpalatable because it is unfamiliar and that a second hearing will yield, if not hummable tunes, then at least a modicum of understanding. Using another audience-friendly technique, Caramoor has invited Ms. Thomas, the composer-in-residence at the Chicago Symphony Orchestra, to discuss her work from the stage. After that,  you're on your own, folks.</p>
        <p>A compact disc of ''Fugitive Star'' will be released the night of the premiere for $14.95. The recording was made in Caramoor's Music Room, using new Direct Stream Digital technology, which is said to capture more nuance than conventional compact disks. It will be some time, however, before listeners can experience the enhanced quality. The new format, Super Audio Compact Disc, requires a compatible player not yet available commercially.</p>
        <p>ROBERTA HERSHENSON</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
