<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>AT THE GALLERY WITH/Mark Judelson; From Older Artists, Works That Mirror Lifelong Experiences</title>
    <meta content="16ART.$28" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215254"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Rockland County (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Arts Council of Rockland</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Judelson, Mark</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lombardi, D Dominick</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E3D81F38F935A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="816" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>AT THE GALLERY WITH/Mark Judelson; From Older Artists, Works That Mirror Lifelong Experiences</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By D. DOMINICK LOMBARDI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lombardi, D Dominick</byline>
      <dateline>SPRING VALLEY</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with Mark Judelson, director of Arts Council of Rockland who comments on annual exhibition of work done in variety of media by artists at differing levels of talent who are all older residents of Rockland County, NY; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR 25 years, the Arts Council of Rockland has put together an annual exhibition of work done in a variety of media by artists at differing levels of talent. What ties the show together is that all the artists are older residents of Rockland County.</p>
        <p>Mark Judelson, the director of the Arts Council of Rockland, talked recently about the project.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR 25 years, the Arts Council of Rockland has put together an annual exhibition of work done in a variety of media by artists at differing levels of talent. What ties the show together is that all the artists are older residents of Rockland County.</p>
        <p>Mark Judelson, the director of the Arts Council of Rockland, talked recently about the project.</p>
        <p>Q. Why has your institution dedicated so much time and effort to this one segment of the population?</p>
        <p>A. I see shows like this as a service to the community.</p>
        <p>Group exhibitions which feature the art of senior citizens benefit both the artist and the visitor. Each side learns from the other.</p>
        <p>I've also noticed a physical change in the artists. At the opening, you could see them as they came up the stairs, a bit hunched over and looking a little weary.</p>
        <p>As they approach their work, they straighten up, becoming more attentive and aware of the excitement around them. It's pride that does that -- they are focused on something very positive, having friends and family members enjoying their work, which in turn increases their self-esteem.</p>
        <p>Q. The exhibit and the opening festivities were financed, in part, by Conseco Life Insurance Company of New York. How did that come about?</p>
        <p>A. Conseco is approached on an annual basis.</p>
        <p>They've responded generously, giving us funds that cover things such as administrative costs and expenses like entertainment at opening receptions. They play a very important role in the success of the exhibition.</p>
        <p>Q. Do you see a common thread throughout the works on display here?</p>
        <p>A. Yes, they all see the world through their unique and individual lifelong experiences. These 42 people have all been through a lot, and I think that is what comes out in their work. It's also very interesting that the young children that come through here have this wide-eyed look about them, as if there is more here than first meets the eye. It's as if they're looking for something -- some secret.</p>
        <p>Q. Mary Evelyn O'Connor is the one artist in the show who has taken part in all 25 exhibitions. How did she get started?</p>
        <p>A. She is actually a student, studying under Sister Adele Myers at the Thorpe Village Retirement Community. Four more of Sister Myers's students are in the show, too: Regina Gobbo, George Holmes, Leonilda O. Malmberg and Ms. Chidwick.</p>
        <p>Q. One artist, Olga Porumbaru, is a well-known professional, which further amplifies the diversity of this exhibition. How did she get involved in this show?</p>
        <p>A. She has lived in Rockland since 1996 and feels it important to have local visibility. She recently unveiled her latest mural at the Rockland County Health Department and created a calendar this year for them.</p>
        <p>Q. You mentioned earlier that every year, 6 to 10 senior residents from the Association of Retarded Citizens have their art in the show.</p>
        <p>Their work varies greatly from the Abstract Expressionist style of painting by Francis Martin to what one might call a fantasy painting by Irving Birnbaum. There are a few hand-made paper collages by Joan Harris and a quilt by a trio of artists: Ms. Martin, Angelo Caparco and Beverly Soconis. How do they see this exhibition experience?</p>
        <p>A. Just this past week a group of the ARC artists came here to take a group portrait. The photograph ran in their newsletter. They're very proud of their work. They all pointed out their work to me that day, saying, ''That clown is mine,'' or ''I did that one.''</p>
        <p>Q. Edward J. Brophy is a mountain climber, and the painting he did is of Hook Mountain in Rockland County. What is he like?</p>
        <p>A. He's a lot like his art. You wouldn't know to look at him that he is a senior citizen. He's very much the mountain climber type -- brawny, very healthy and strong -- and his painting is quite powerful.</p>
        <p>Q. Varda A. Corish's painting ''Country Journey'' is very compelling -- her attention to detail is wonderful. She died this past year and her husband submitted ''Country Journey'' for this show. How did that come about?</p>
        <p>A. He called to ask if he could bring a painting in. I felt it was a fitting testimonial to their relationship and to art's ability to transcend time.</p>
        <p>Some of the artists and their works are pictured on Page 13. ''Golden Harvest: Senior Art Celebration'' will be on display at the Arts Council of Rockland through July 25. The number to call for more information is (845) 426-3660.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
