<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dancing the Lily With the 'Capos' in Williamsburg</title>
    <meta content="16LORE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215297"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="CITY LORE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Italian-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parades</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">St Paulinus</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Virgin Mary</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Duffy, Peter</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parades</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02E2DC163BF935A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1536" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dancing the Lily With the 'Capos' in Williamsburg</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER DUFFY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Duffy, Peter</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article describes scene on Giglio Sunday, during Feast of Our Lady of Mount Carmel and St Paulinus, as more than 200 Italian-American men 'dance' 85-foot-tall aluminum-and-papier-mache obelisk and several-ton medieval boat through streets of Williamsburg section of Brooklyn, NYC; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MORE than 100 years ago, in a small pocket of Brooklyn, some immigrants from Nola, Italy, decided they couldn't live without their native city's grandest event.</p>
        <p>So they organized a summer festival that had as its centerpiece a ritual dating back centuries. On allotted days, a few hundred men carried a floridly decorated obelisk and a medieval boat through the streets to commemorate events in the life of St. Paulinus, Nola's patron saint. It wasn't quite like back home, where eight towers and a boat were paraded through Nola, a small city near Naples, but it soon became a cherished part of life in Italian Williamsburg.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MORE than 100 years ago, in a small pocket of Brooklyn, some immigrants from Nola, Italy, decided they couldn't live without their native city's grandest event.</p>
        <p>So they organized a summer festival that had as its centerpiece a ritual dating back centuries. On allotted days, a few hundred men carried a floridly decorated obelisk and a medieval boat through the streets to commemorate events in the life of St. Paulinus, Nola's patron saint. It wasn't quite like back home, where eight towers and a boat were paraded through Nola, a small city near Naples, but it soon became a cherished part of life in Italian Williamsburg.</p>
        <p>Last Sunday, an 85-foot-tall aluminum-and-papier-mache tower, called a giglio, weighing four tons and taking its name from the Italian word for lily, and a several-ton boat were ''danced,'' in church parlance, up and down Havemeyer and North Eighth Streets on Williamsburg's north side by more than 200 men. A cadre of experienced ''capos'' directed the lifts by barking commands in Italian, while brass bands on each structure blasted out rousing marches. The streets and rooftops were jammed with onlookers, stuffing themselves with zeppoles, calzones and sausages.</p>
        <p>''You can tell the people who are seeing it for the first time,'' said Salvatore Primeggia, a lifter who teaches sociology at Adelphi University. ''Their jaws drop. Their eyes get wide.''</p>
        <p>Giglio Sunday, as the first Sunday of the celebration is called, is the highlight of the Feast of Our Lady of Mount Carmel and St. Paulinus, which ends tonight. The 11-day event does not last as long as it did in the past and now the giglio (pronounced JEE-lee-oh) is only danced on two days, the last of which was yesterday, without the boat.</p>
        <p>But that doesn't mean the tradition is fading. Organizers say it is as strong as it was 30 years ago.</p>
        <p>Ask anyone who has grown up around the feast, and it is easy to see why. The experience has an unbreakable grasp on their lives.</p>
        <p>''It's in my veins,'' said Joe Peluso, 51, who has been involved in the event since he was 4. ''It's in my blood. I don't know what I would do without it.''</p>
        <p>People who have left the neighborhood return from as far away as Florida for a date that ranks in importance with Christmas and Easter on the local calendar. Local residents speak of how their heart leaps when they hear the first notes of ''O Giglio e Paradiso'' (''The Giglio of Paradise''), the feast's eminently clappable theme song, after a year away from it. Parties are held in the same homes every year, and old friends greet one another with embraces and kisses.</p>
        <p>Although the composition of the neighborhood has been changing in recent years, it still retains an Italian-American identity, and both young and old are involved. Children from 5 to 12 are initiated by lifting a ''children's giglio'' on two nights during the feast.</p>
        <p>Last year, girls were permitted to participate for the first time, a hotly debated change that had been tabled for four years by the executive board. But the lifting of the main four-ton giglio and two-and-a-half ton boat remains the province of men.</p>
        <p>''I hope so,'' said Gabrielle Marino, 10, when asked, after laboring under the children's giglio last week, if she'd like to help hoist the adult giglio. ''I want to carry on a tradition in my family.''</p>
        <p>More than anything, this event is all about tradition. Celebrated for the 113th year in Brooklyn, the festival acts out a drama that dates back to the year 409, when Paulinus was named the bishop of Nola. After the city was raided by Mediterranean conquerors, Paulinus offered himself to the invaders in exchange for a widow's son they had kidnapped, or so the story goes. The bishop was taken and imprisoned in North Africa. A Turkish sultan who learned of his selfless act bartered for his freedom. When Paulinus returned to Nola on the sultan's boat, the townspeople greeted him carrying lilies.</p>
        <p>Although there is debate about the story's historical accuracy, people from Nola started building large replicas of the lilies and the boat to honor their saint's sacrifice.</p>
        <p>Today eight gigli and a boat are danced on the first Sunday after June 22, St. Paulinus's feast day, in Nola. The towers, built by private individuals, are entered in competitions for best music, best dance and best design. A few Brooklynites with roots in Nola still return to the old country for the raucous occasion.</p>
        <p>Unlike the Italian version, the Williamsburg spectacle is a cooperative undertaking overseen in all aspects by the church. At the top of the hierarchy is Msgr. David Cassato, the charismatic pastor of Our Lady of Mount Carmel Shrine Church. A gifted speaker who  wears a goatee speckled with gray, Monsignor Cassato cut a dashing figure in his fuchsia and red cassock as he walked through the streets early on Giglio Sunday, before the lifts.</p>
        <p>He was part of a procession that was traveling to the homes of important members of the feast's organizational structure. At each home, the group halted and the band played a tune. Then a middle-aged man emerged from behind the front door to the cheers of his friends and family. Monsignor Cassato blessed the assemblage with spirited splashes of holy water and walked with the marchers to the next residence.</p>
        <p>The final stop on the two-mile journey was the home of Anthony Palma, who holds the honored position of No. 1 capo. This person, who serves for two years, is responsible for organizing all aspects of the lifting of the giglio, often called the geel, and the boat. In addition to leading 6 capos, 4 apprentice capos, 8 lieutenants and more than 300 lifters, he also personally commands the first lift of each Giglio Sunday, a significant moment in the life of the feast.</p>
        <p>For Mr. Palma, 47, an operating mechanic for Con Edison, the job is the fulfillment of a lifelong dream.</p>
        <p>''My uncle was No. 1 in 1965-66, and my father was in charge of bazaar,'' he said. ''As a kid you see all this going on around you. I said, 'One day I am going to take that geel off the sidewalk.' ''</p>
        <p>Former No. 1 capos all speak lyrically about their experience. Vincent Patuto, the No. 1 capo for 1997 and 1998, remembers the moment when he thrust his cane into the air for the first time, the signal that directs the lifters to raise the giglio off the ground.</p>
        <p>''You'll never forget it,'' he said. ''Nothing I've ever experienced can compare to it. You are the most authoritative figure on the street and you are attempting to deal with a force field of elements: the music, the weather, the testosterone of the men, the fragrance of the food, the safety factor. You have all of this whirling around like a Tasmanian devil. The excitement of it, it's something, boy.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Peluso, also a former No. 1 capo, said: ''You can't imagine this moment, the feeling you get at that instant. I shake just thinking about it.''</p>
        <p>After Mr. Palma joined the procession, the group headed to a packed church for Mass. After the service and a short lunch, the men gathered for the lifts, which continued for several hours. Although the day was full of fun, it was also serious. Monsignor  Cassato emphasized to his parishioners that the act of lifting is a profound display of faith, powered not by mere muscle but by the Holy Spirit.</p>
        <p>Some men regard their efforts as penance for past sins. Others dedicate their work to the memory of a deceased relative.</p>
        <p>One of the day's most anticipated lifts -- when the giglio and the boat are danced together at the corner of Havemeyer and North Eighth Streets -- was performed in honor of Tee Jay Sampogna, a former No. 1 capo who died shortly after last year's feast.</p>
        <p>Earlier in the day, Mr. Sampogna's 34-year-old son, Frank, wept profusely at a family gathering, stirred by memories of his father. An apprentice capo whose 8-year-old son is already involved in the feast, Frank Sampogna is following in his father's footsteps to the top of the giglio hierarchy.</p>
        <p>''It's kind of a rough go this year,'' he said. ''Every time you see somebody, it's just a different memory. I am dedicating the whole day to him.''</p>
        <p>CITY LORE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
