<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Blues Brothers</title>
    <meta content="16SANTORT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215040"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Santoro, Gene</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cohodas, Nadine</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Spinning Blues Into Gold (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E2DE1F39F935A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1149" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Blues Brothers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Gene Santoro</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Santoro, Gene</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gene Santoro reviews book Spinning Blues Into Gold: The Chess Brothers and the Legendary Chess Records by Nadine Cohodas (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SPINNING BLUES INTO GOLD</p>
        <p>The Chess Brothers and</p>
        <p>the Legendary Chess Records.</p>
        <p>By Nadine Cohodas.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 358 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>St. Martin's Press. $25.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SPINNING BLUES INTO GOLD</p>
        <p>The Chess Brothers and</p>
        <p>the Legendary Chess Records.</p>
        <p>By Nadine Cohodas.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 358 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>St. Martin's Press. $25.95.</p>
        <p>THE history of American vernacular music over the last half-century-plus has often hinged on entrepreneurs who hung out in the shadows between mainstream culture and its marginal cousins. In ways they did not have to intend, these businessmen became mediators, even advocates, for cultural outsiders. Take black musicians. They had limited opportunities at major labels (where they were usually cordoned off into ''race'' record labels), major booking agencies and major performance sites. And so again and again, small labels offering blues or rhythm and blues or gospel popped up across the United States. The label heads, almost all of them white, had individual motives, of course, but most shared a vision of potentially profitable niche markets that were going untapped.</p>
        <p>Such were the Chess brothers, Leonard and Phil, who after World War II started what became Chess Records. Born in Poland, the boys immigrated to America with their family in 1922 and grew up in Chicago. Their businesses -- a junk store, a couple of liquor stores -- moved them steadily into the tangle of racial and ethnic relations that crisscrosses American culture. In 1946, the brothers took over a bar in one of the black Chicago neighborhoods that were filling with Southern migrants. Like other tavern owners, they saw that live bands drew customers, that there was money to be made in black music and its audience -- and that idea shaped the rest of their lives. By the time Leonard died of a heart attack in 1969, at the age of 52, he and Phil owned several record labels, a recording studio, a record distributor, a couple of music publishers, two radio stations and a batch of real estate. More important, they had recorded more than their fair share of the best and most influential sounds of the postwar era.</p>
        <p>As Nadine Cohodas recounts in ''Spinning Blues Into Gold,'' Leonard and Phil Chess formed a bond with their customers and artists that went beyond money. In black neighborhoods in Chicago, then all over the country, they absorbed local culture and sounds, made connections and friends, signed up musicians. They hustled records to D.J.'s, record-store owners and distributors on a road that stretched for years from dusty shacks to cities. By the late 1950's, Chess had grown from an ad hoc two-man operation into a hit-making group of record labels, a kind of miniature major label wrapped in myth. On an early American tour, the Rolling Stones went to Chicago so they could record in the same Chess studios used by their idols in blues and R &amp; B, whose songs the Stones had recorded.</p>
        <p>The births of gritty electric urban blues, rhythm and blues, then rock 'n' roll are among the moments Chess Records helped create and chronicle. The Chess brothers produced records by pivotal innovators like Muddy Waters, Chuck Berry and Etta James; they nearly signed James Brown and Elvis Presley. They not only made money from selling black music to black Americans; like their friend Alan Freed, the legendary disc jockey, they also introduced countless white American youngsters to those sounds.</p>
        <p>Cohodas, the author of ''The Band Played Dixie: Race and Liberal Conscience at Ole Miss'' and ''Strom Thurmond and the Politics of Southern Change,'' connects a lot of dots and corrects earlier versions of Chess history by music writers who relied too heavily on unchecked hand-me-down anecdotes. She has done her homework: interviews with a variety of witnesses enliven her wide-ranging research materials, which include artists' biographies, local newspapers, city directories and trade magazines like Billboard and Cashbox.</p>
        <p>It is almost inevitable that an institutional history like this will at times lapse into somewhat potted thumbnail sketches of individuals, but Cohodas usually keeps these evocative and on point. Her delving into the business ledgers and background, too often glossed over or reduced to easy art-versus-commerce cliches, is particularly strong. However, she does sometimes undercut the depth and strength of her reporting by overinterpreting scenes and characters. She seems defensive, for instance, about calling Leonard and Phil anything tougher than ''frugal,'' though she quotes plenty of witnesses testifying to their notorious unwillingness to part with money. When Dave Usher, the label's production head, asked for a raise after a string of hits in the late 1950's, Leonard's typically tart reply was, ''What do you think, you're one of my family?'' Usher left Chess soon after. His successor, Jack Tracy, negotiated a better deal, including producer royalties. At the end of his first year, the royalties totaled $750, and Leonard barked in his unilateral way: ''We're going to change things. You won't be getting a royalty again.'' Tracy did not even bother to protest.</p>
        <p>Perspective can change a lot, though, and Cohodas rightly, if a bit defensively, tries to put into context the Chesses' financial practices. They bought new Cadillacs and rented apartments and paid lawyers' fees for their artists, but almost never handed out royalty statements. Jerry Wexler, an Atlantic Records executive and a friendly rival of the Chess brothers, saw their approach as updated paternalism. Cohodas points out that many, if not most, labels at the time did similar things and eventually wound up in disputes with their musicians over money, copyrights and the like. She also points out that most of the business was in the brothers' heads, so there is frequently no way to verify Chess Records' numbers and transactions. But once again, she has done her homework: the book's epilogue, ''Lawsuits and Legacies,'' narrates the numerous financial and copyright clashes Chess had with its musicians following Leonard's death.</p>
        <p>Cohodas's dogged reportage powers her book past its relatively minor flaws and serviceable prose. Dotted by irreconcilable memories and unresolvable disputes that she lets stand, it mimics the often ''Rashomon''-like residues of historical memory. One example: When Chuck Berry was arrested, tried and ultimately imprisoned on Mann Act charges in 1959-62, the Chess brothers paid for his lawyers -- according to them. Berry's autobiography, as Cohodas duly notes, denies it. Then again, Berry, who always demanded to be paid in cash for his shows, carting it around in paper bags, was probably the only Chess artist as cheap as the Chess brothers.</p>
        <p>Cohodas has written an in-depth, fact-and-story-rich tour through an important moment in American popular culture. If ultimately it leaves Leonard and Phil Chess themselves as informed sketches rather than fully shaped characters, that is probably how they would have liked it.</p>
        <p>Gene Santoro is the author of a biography of Charles Mingus, ''Myself When I Am Real.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Gene Santoro is the author of a biography of Charles Mingus, ''Myself When I Am Real.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
