<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>INVESTING WITH: Robert L. Friedman; Mutual European Fund</title>
    <meta content="16INVO$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215409"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mutual European Fund</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gould, Carole</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Friedman, Robert L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Investing With</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DEED8173BF935A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="988" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>INVESTING WITH: Robert L. Friedman; Mutual European Fund</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAROLE GOULD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gould, Carole</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Carole Gould Investing with ... column profiles Robert L Friedman, manager of $926.7 million Mutual European Fund, which seeks undervalued European companies; notes fund has returned average 21.6 percent a year for three years through June 30, beating average 14.9 percent for all European stock funds; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AFTER years in the wilderness, value investing is staging a comeback, and Robert L. Friedman, who runs the $926.7 million Mutual European fund, is basking in it.</p>
        <p>''These are good days for value investors,'' Mr. Friedman said from his office in Short Hills, N.J. ''Europeans are running good companies with solid, often global businesses at a time when boards of directors are willing to restructure companies that need it. The confluence makes this better than any other time in European business history.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AFTER years in the wilderness, value investing is staging a comeback, and Robert L. Friedman, who runs the $926.7 million Mutual European fund, is basking in it.</p>
        <p>''These are good days for value investors,'' Mr. Friedman said from his office in Short Hills, N.J. ''Europeans are running good companies with solid, often global businesses at a time when boards of directors are willing to restructure companies that need it. The confluence makes this better than any other time in European business history.''</p>
        <p>His investors are having good days, too. The fund returned 21.6 percent a year, on average, for the three years through June 30, compared with 14.9 percent for all Europe stock funds, according to Morningstar Inc.</p>
        <p>Mr. Friedman, 41, takes a bottom-up approach to picking stocks, seeking good but out-of-favor companies that are selling at cheap prices. Ideally, he wants to buy shares at less than 60 percent of what he thinks they are worth today.</p>
        <p>He looks for evidence of a catalyst that will push up a stock price toward a company's intrinsic worth, like aggressive new management or good prospects for merger, consolidation or a major revamping.</p>
        <p>''Europe is in its infancy in the reorganization of companies,'' Mr. Friedman said. ''Capital markets are opening up, and governments are more willing to let companies restructure. Even Western European countries with strong histories of socialism now recognize the need for corporate access to capital markets and the importance of company shares being properly valued.''</p>
        <p>While the fund has no geographic mandates, most of the companies it holds are in Western Europe. About a quarter of the portfolio is in British stocks, 20 percent in Scandinavia and  15 percent in France; there are smaller concentrations elsewhere. The fund is always at least 80 percent hedged against currency fluctuations, he said.</p>
        <p>By Mr. Friedman's reckoning, large-capitalization stocks are becoming overvalued in Europe, though less so than in the United States. So he is now focusing on companies with market caps of $400 million to $40 billion.</p>
        <p>In evaluating a company's finances, Mr. Friedman is less concerned about revenue growth than  profitability. ''If a company has good margin improvement on stagnant sales growth,'' he said, ''management is doing serious cost-cutting or restructuring.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Friedman brings an American-style activist approach, a hallmark of the Mutual Series funds, to the fund's relationship with companies in the portfolio. ''Shareholder activism will be very important in European markets going forward, because of the growing awareness on the part of institutional investors that management works for shareholders,'' he said, adding that Continental Europe was lagging behind Britain in adapting to the idea.</p>
        <p>He sells stocks when discounts begin to shrink. When shares reach 60 to 90 percent of what he believes they are worth, ''it's time to take money off the table,'' he said. And when they reach their full value, ''we are largely gone.''</p>
        <p>MR. FRIEDMAN sees bargains among European financial and engineering companies.</p>
        <p>One of them, he says, is Irish Life and Permanent, an insurer with a small presence in the United States. ''Ireland has been the tiger economy of Western Europe because of low tax rates, business-friendly government, economic growth in the upper single digits and inflation of less than 3 percent,'' he said, adding that demand for insurance is growing. For this company, he said, the catalyst is a potential rebound of the country's  financial services sector, which was hurt earlier this year by rising interest rates.</p>
        <p>Mr. Friedman bought Irish Life, which trades in London, at prices between $:4.70 and $:5.70 and figures its true worth at about $:10; it closed on Friday at $:5.36.</p>
        <p>Another favorite is Powell Duffryn, a British conglomerate with specialty engineering and port services businesses. Mr. Friedman said it ought to be worth more than $:7 a share; it now trades at $:4.68.</p>
        <p>He took a small initial position at $:6 in early 1999, but rising interest rates depressed port revenue early this year, and the stock price slumped, letting Mr. Friedman scoop up more shares at prices of $:3.50 to $:4. He forecasts earnings growth of 12 to 15 percent a year, he said, because ''management has really restructured the business.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Friedman also likes Internatio-Muller N.V., a Dutch engineering company specializing in plant design and construction that has agreed to merge with a local rival, Stork N.V., and sell off much of its business. Mr. Friedman opposes the timing of the merger; he wants Internatio-Muller to divest its assets first, pay a dividend to shareholders with the proceeds and then complete the merger. Dutch law provides little recourse to block the merger, he said, so he is trying to win over company management to his approach instead.</p>
        <p>Whatever the outcome, he said, the fund will profit. ''There's too much hidden value not to make money here,'' he said, ''but not as much as if they postpone the merger until after the sale.'' He got in at about 20 euros a share in May, and puts the company's intrinsic worth at 18 to 25 euros before the sale and at 30 euros after. It closed on Friday at 18.4 euros.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
