<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>MOVIES: CRITIC'S CHOICE</title>
    <meta content="T14NEW0AA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Television" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215213"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gates, Anita</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E4DB1E38F935A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="592" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>MOVIES: CRITIC'S CHOICE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Anita Gates</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gates, Anita</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Brief reviews of films on television this week; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CAN it possibly have been 22 years since Jill Clayburgh showed usjust how great independence could look and feel in AN UNMARRIED WOMAN (1978)? Ms. Clayburgh is a knockout as an Upper East Side wife, mom and part-time art gallery employee in transition. Michael Murphy plays apologetic selfishness perfectly as the seemingly wonderful New York husband who, out of the blue, announces he's leaving her. (Seems he met a younger woman while buying shirts at Bloomingdale's.) Alan Bates is the gorgeous downtown artist who comes along just as she realies that living through a man can be a very bad idea. Directed by Paul Mazursky, the film is perceptive, intelligent (if a little breathless at times) and very New York, with adolescents making pronouncements about Lina Wertmuller movies - Saturday at 9 p.m. and Saturday/Early Sunday at 2 a.m. and Romance Classics.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CAN it possibly have been 22 years since Jill Clayburgh showed usjust how great independence could look and feel in AN UNMARRIED WOMAN (1978)? Ms. Clayburgh is a knockout as an Upper East Side wife, mom and part-time art gallery employee in transition. Michael Murphy plays apologetic selfishness perfectly as the seemingly wonderful New York husband who, out of the blue, announces he's leaving her. (Seems he met a younger woman while buying shirts at Bloomingdale's.) Alan Bates is the gorgeous downtown artist who comes along just as she realies that living through a man can be a very bad idea. Directed by Paul Mazursky, the film is perceptive, intelligent (if a little breathless at times) and very New York, with adolescents making pronouncements about Lina Wertmuller movies - Saturday at 9 p.m. and Saturday/Early Sunday at 2 a.m. and Romance Classics.</p>
        <p>Yes, children are big fans of Duwayne Dunham's HOMEWARD BOUND: THE INCREDIBLE JOURNEY (1993), but so are a lot of adults. It's an easy film to love, with Caroline Thompson and Linda Woolverton's witty, touching script and Don Ameche, Michael J. Fox and Sally Field supplying the voices of household pets trying to find their way home. Despite procupines, waterfalls and other dangers, the three (a dignified older dog, an impetuous younger one and a sassy cat) battle their way to a happy ending - Sunday at 9 a.m. on Channel 11 and Monday at 8 p.m. on Channel 55.</p>
        <p>Heather, Josh and Mike's bad time in the Maryland woods is back. THE BLAIR WITCH PROJECT (1999), directed and written by Daniel Myrick and Eduardo Sanchez on a less-than-shoestring budget, was last summer's surprise box office hit and a cult favorite before it opened (that darned Web). Heather Donahue, Joshua Leonard and Michael C. Williams star as a filmmaking crew out to document a local legend about a centuries-old witch, said to live deep in the forest, who would kill you as soon as look at you. The film's success gave shaky camera work and up-the-nostrils close-ups a good name, and made twig figures really scary. It's worth a second look, especially for those of us who totally misunderstand the ending - Sunday at 10 p.m. and Friday at 8 p.m. on Showtime.</p>
        <p>Almost every movie fan knows Gene Kelly's title song-and-dance number from SINGIN' IN THE RAIN (1952), but te rest of the movie is pretty great too. After all, Donald O'Connor and Jean Hagen are Kelly's co-stars. Cyd Charisse makes a guest appearance. Kelly and Stanley Donen directed. The script (first-class satire about a silent film star whose voice just isn't going to make the transition to the talkies) is by Betty Comden and Adolph Green. It made the perky 20-year-old Debbie Reynolds a star - Saturday at 3 p.m. on TCM.</p>
        <p>Stephen King's gentle side makes THE SHAWSHANK REDEMPTION (1994), based on his story, a very atypical 1940's prison drama. Tim Robbins stars as an innocent man serving alife sentence for his wife's murder. Morgan Freeman, in an exceptional performance, is Red, the self-described ''only guilty man in Shawshank,'' who becomes his lifelong friend. Mr. Robbins's character, who upgrades the prison library and gives sound financial advice to the staff, ultimately proves himself a man with a purpose. And a gorgeous Rita Hayworth poster. Frank Darabont directed - Sunday at 5 p.m. on TNT.</p>
        <p>Anita Gates</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
