<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nassau Needs Space, but Needs Money First</title>
    <meta content="16SPAC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215197"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Land Use Policies</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conservation of Resources</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Nassau County (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">North Hempstead (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rather, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conservation of Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Land Use Policies</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E7DD1E38F935A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="994" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nassau Needs Space, but Needs Money First</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN RATHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rather, John</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Nassau County, Long Island, amid fiscal crisis, puts forth preliminary plan for preservation and protection of environmentally sensitive lands and scenic open spaces; fiscally robust towns such as North Hempstead are likely to take lead in preserving parcels; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN the worst of financial times for a government struggling to stay afloat on a sea of surrounding wealth, Nassau County is advancing its first comprehensive plan to protect environmentally sensitive lands and scenic open spaces.</p>
        <p>The plan could be a blueprint for the preservation of properties that include Greentree, the 450-acre Whitney family estate in Manhasset, the 81-acre Underhill property in Jericho and parcels as small as two acres in the densely populated Town of Hempstead.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN the worst of financial times for a government struggling to stay afloat on a sea of surrounding wealth, Nassau County is advancing its first comprehensive plan to protect environmentally sensitive lands and scenic open spaces.</p>
        <p>The plan could be a blueprint for the preservation of properties that include Greentree, the 450-acre Whitney family estate in Manhasset, the 81-acre Underhill property in Jericho and parcels as small as two acres in the densely populated Town of Hempstead.</p>
        <p>But with severe budget strictures dimming prospects for county financing of land programs that advanced little even in better days, the fiscally more robust towns in Nassau appear likely to take the lead. North Hempstead is close to formally proposing a $15 million Environmental Legacy Fund and Oyster Bay is discussing a similar program for up to twice that amount.</p>
        <p>County and town officials said the open-space plans, which place high priority on protecting groundwater, were responses to strong public support for preservation. ''This should have been done 20 years ago,'' said May W. Newburger, the North Hempstead supervisor.</p>
        <p>Still to be tested is the public's willingness to pay for such programs. In North Hempstead, the town board is to vote in September on whether to place the $15 million proposal on the ballot in November. The town said the cost would be less than $9 a year for homeowners.</p>
        <p>The officials also see an opportunity to attract funds from the state and federal governments during the current economic expansion. For example, a bill approved in the House and now before the Senate would take some of the $900 million a year paid by companies drilling oil offshore and divide it among the states for preservation.</p>
        <p>In its land preservation efforts, Nassau lags far behind Suffolk, where voter-supported programs began in the 1970's. Suffolk is more than three times the size of Nassau, which covers 183,488 acres. But Suffolk has 37,000 acres of county parks and preserves, more than five times more than in Nassau, with 6,520 acres.</p>
        <p>Six of Suffolk's 10 towns have financed open-space programs, including a $15 million program overwhelmingly approved two years ago by voters in Huntington.</p>
        <p>While North Hempstead and Oyster Bay move to follow the financing examples of the Suffolk towns, Hempstead will rely on available funds for open space and park programs, said Supervisor Richard V. Guardino Jr., who oversees a $50 million budget surplus.</p>
        <p>Mr. Guardino cited one example: a partnership with the state Department of Environmental Conservation under which the department bought more than 70 acres of wetlands in Lido Beach that the town will manage and maintain.</p>
        <p>The newly released Nassau County plan, intended to be the opening phase of a master plan the county adopted in 1998, includes the first inventory of all open spaces. These range from the 3,606 acres of county parks and 2,914 acres of county nature preserves to 6,011 acres of road rights-of-way, 1,050 acres of recharge basins and 714 acres of cemeteries, and include 4,741 acres of estate lands and vacant properties that are available or may become available for development.</p>
        <p>The county plan lays out options for keeping land open: outright purchase, purchase of development rights only, conservation easements and preservation by private groups and businesses.</p>
        <p>Paul F. Ponessa, the director of the Nassau County Planning Commission, said the county would rank properties to place key ones first while assuring protection efforts were extended to all parts of the county. He emphasized that only willing owners would be approached, but neither he nor other officials would discuss specific properties.</p>
        <p>Nor are the owners forthcoming. While the Greentree Foundation, which owns the old Whitney estate, has never publicly expressed interest in selling, the estate -- currently zoned for one house every five acres -- is in a state-designated groundwater protection area that makes its preservation a high priority.</p>
        <p>The Underhill property in Oyster Bay is also in a watershed area. Last week the Appellate Division upheld a ruling that the town had violated state law by relying on a 10-year-old environmental impact statement in approving housing proposed by Tilles Investment, the land's owner.</p>
        <p>Officials and environmental groups supporting the Nassau plan said the county's current financial problems should not detract from preservation plans that are intended to unfold over many years.</p>
        <p>Paul P. Rabinovitch, executive director of the Long Island chapter of the Nature Conservancy, which has played a major role in preservation, said his group had pledged to assist Nassau and saw no reasons to be discouraged by the county's financial situation.</p>
        <p>''Funding is obviously important, but as important is intent,'' he said. ''If the intent is there, preservation will happen, and there are other options for preserving land rather than just to buy it.''</p>
        <p>Joseph H. Lorintz, a lawyer and president of the Society to Preserve Underhill, said the need to protect that property and others was too urgent to be delayed by Nassau's financial malaise. ''Even with the county's miserable financial condition, you can't just ignore the environment,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Others said the county could finance a program by reallocating some or all of the sales tax revenues that the county currently divides among Nassau's three towns and two cities. The revenues, initially provided for landfill closures and solid-waste management, are projected at more than $45 million this year.</p>
        <p>''What you need is a dedicated, earmarked fund, and it should come out of a small portion of the county sales tax,'' said Neal Lewis, executive director of the Long Island Neighborhood Network.</p>
        <p>But town governments would be likely to resist any reduction in their shares. ''Why take money away if we are already doing something?'' Supervisor Newburger asked, a reference to the proposed environmental fund.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
