<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Saving the World, One Sexy Teen at a Time</title>
    <meta content="16MACG$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215145"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION/RADIO"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Macgregor, Jeff</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Povich, Maury</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Maury (Tv Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02EEDA1038F935A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2739" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Saving the World, One Sexy Teen at a Time</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JEFF MACGREGOR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Macgregor, Jeff</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jeff MacGregor article on changes on Maury Povich's daytime talk show, whose ratings have jumped 19 percent since last year after show started featuring burly adults yelling at wayward and delinquent teenage girls; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT seems to me that having created the Internet, the wireless electronic pocket organizer and Oreos that turn your milk bright blue when you dunk 'em, humankind has reached its technological apogee. In so doing, we've solved our most fundamental problems: ''How can I deliver, to someone far away, an annoying online sales pitch for deeply discounted off-season Adirondack time shares?'' and ''I'm a wealthy day trader and an idiot -- what day is it?'' and ''Why is my cookie so tasty yet not at all artistically ambitious or challenging to the eye?''</p>
        <p>This is, of course, the best of all possible times to be alive in this, the best of all possible worlds. Given our many perfections in the physical realm, then, our automotive heated-leather seating surfaces and our battery-operated Furbys and our trip to the moon, shouldn't we turn our collective genius inward, and begin to map the complex strivings of the human spirit? Should we not use our abundant leisure to embark upon great voyages of self-discovery? Should we not, at last, realize the dream of a thousand generations long gone and enter a new golden age of behavioral, sociological and philosophical enlightenment? A renaissance of the heart, a millennium of inner peace?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT seems to me that having created the Internet, the wireless electronic pocket organizer and Oreos that turn your milk bright blue when you dunk 'em, humankind has reached its technological apogee. In so doing, we've solved our most fundamental problems: ''How can I deliver, to someone far away, an annoying online sales pitch for deeply discounted off-season Adirondack time shares?'' and ''I'm a wealthy day trader and an idiot -- what day is it?'' and ''Why is my cookie so tasty yet not at all artistically ambitious or challenging to the eye?''</p>
        <p>This is, of course, the best of all possible times to be alive in this, the best of all possible worlds. Given our many perfections in the physical realm, then, our automotive heated-leather seating surfaces and our battery-operated Furbys and our trip to the moon, shouldn't we turn our collective genius inward, and begin to map the complex strivings of the human spirit? Should we not use our abundant leisure to embark upon great voyages of self-discovery? Should we not, at last, realize the dream of a thousand generations long gone and enter a new golden age of behavioral, sociological and philosophical enlightenment? A renaissance of the heart, a millennium of inner peace?</p>
        <p>Happily for our benighted species, that very process has begun. The ethical, moral and teleological questions that for so long had the likes of Aristotle and St. Anselm and Lord Lloyd-Webber tossing fitfully in their sleep are finally being answered. The dark turnings of human nature are being illuminated. Our primitive quest for the grace that surpasseth understanding is well under way. And thanks to the most useful and compassionate technology of them all, television, we can watch this postmodern reformation of human character played out five days a week. Several times each day, in fact.</p>
        <p>And who, you ask, are we to thank for this inspiring stampede toward a brighter future? Grateful citizens, relieved theologians and giddy philosophers everywhere need really remember only one name: Maury Povich. For it is on his daytime talk show that we as a nation now seek to wrestle with nothing less than original sin itself.</p>
        <p>It turns out that our last 2,000 years of thoughtful argument over mysterious issues of redemption and damnation were nothing but a huge waste of time. We were barking up the wrong tree of knowledge, apparently, because perdition and sin and low self-esteem, Mr. Povich has recently discovered, along with smoking, drinking and breaking curfew, can be averted by one simple thing. By just yelling at our children, or, better still, by hiring burly professionals to yell at our children, we can make the world a sweeter place.</p>
        <p>The ''Maury'' show is, to quote a recent issue of Entertainment Weekly, this season's ''biggest success story'' in syndicated daytime television. The show's ratings are up some 19 percent since last year, and it now occasionally outpoints the popular ''Rosie O'Donnell Show'' in the same time slot here in New York. This ''daytime yakker'' has got the ''big mo,'' they say. How did ''Maury'' do it? How did the show go from eponymous also-ran to daytime juggernaut, more highly rated than even ''The Jerry Springer Show,'' and now running neck and neck with the neckwear savant Regis Philbin and the soon-to-be-marginally-less-ubiquitous Kathie Lee Gifford? What's all the shouting about?</p>
        <p>The shouting is about shouting, actually, because ''Maury'' has bootstrapped itself into the American brainpan by making volume a virtue and battling evil at the top of its lungs. During the May sweeps period, in which ratings are translated into advertising rates and, therefore, profits, wayward teenagers and delinquent children of all stripes were being remade as model citizens on programs subtitled ''My Wild Teen Needs Boot Camp!'' and ''Stop Staring at My Teen Daughter's Body!'' and ''My Teen Needs Sex To Survive!'' Oh, do these kids get yelled at!</p>
        <p>The premise for each episode of these behavioral makeovers, which ran in heavy rotation during sweeps, is easily explained, and their architecture rarely varies. Maury, clad in the stylish vestments of the media priesthood (black V-neck sweater over a white T-shirt), solemnly intones an introduction to the day's battle of Right (Maury) against Wrong (teen girls who dress too provocatively!, teen girls who dress too provocatively and verbally abuse their mothers!, teen girls who dress too provocatively and verbally abuse their mothers while trying to choke them! Teen girls who smoke, drink, do drugs and have sex! Have unprotected sex! Have unprotected sex with multiple partners and dress too provocatively!). A bare handful of shows will include a teenage boy. He will seem lonely and confused.</p>
        <p>What follows is as ritualized as a high Mass. A worried mother is brought onto the set. She is introduced, usually by her first name only and with no further identification. We don't know where she's from or how she came to be here. (Fathers are entirely absent on the vast majority of these programs.) She then describes to Maury, who looks on with an expression of beatific sympathy, her daughter's pattern of delinquency. Most of the girls, it seems, dress far too provocatively for someone their age (which ranges on the shows I've seen from 8 to about 15; apparently all the bad 18-and-ups are over on the Springer show) and are engaged in risky pursuits like smoking and imbibing hard liquor and having -- did we mention this yet? -- sex. The mother's tearful monologue is only occasionally interrupted for a Maurian sidebar like, ''And how many times has she been arrested?'' or ''And then she tried to choke you?'' or ''And how old is the oldest guy you've seen hit on her?'' The mothers are never asked if they're any good at mothering, or work instead at a Hell's Angels meth lab in the desert. It seems, rather, that the troubled adolescent has simply been possessed by an evil spirit.</p>
        <p>By now the studio audience is groaning in disgust and seems very anxious to meet this hell-bound Lolita. Maury obliges and we cut to a jittery, hand-held shot from backstage, where the invariably halter-wearing or tube-topped youngster is either slouching, pacing, standing confrontationally with arms akimbo or gyrating in an overtly, dare we say, provocative manner. Irrespective of body position, each delivers an articulate rebuttal to whatever Mom just said, generally along the lines of ''I'm 14 and I'm a grown-up woman and I can live any way I want to and men buy me things because of my big bosoms and I smoke and I drink and I don't care what that [bleep] says, 'cause she's a [bleep] and don't know nothin' about me.''</p>
        <p>We cut back to Mr. Povich, who clucks his tongue and introduces the debutante in question. She enters the main stage to the derisive catcalls of the audience. Her response? ''You don't know [bleep] about [bleep], so shut up!'' Maury, familiar, no doubt, with Robert's Rules of Order, gavels the crowd into line with the shouted phrase ''Wait a minute! Wait a minute!'' and his prosecution of the case begins. This takes the form of repeating everything the girl just said, while she nods and says ''uh-huh.'' Satisfied that we're all on the same page, sex-and-violence-wise, Maury cuts sharply to the epistemological heart of the matter. ''Why?'' he yodels, his face a medieval woodcut of dour concern, ''Why would you do this?'' Snapping her gum and clearly overmatched, the girl answers for all humanity when she says: ''I don't know. It's fun, I guess.'' O, weakness! O, vanity! Thus is the scene set for the impending exorcism.</p>
        <p>Over the course of the next few segments, paced by the commercial breaks (of which ''Maury'' has many, most having something to do with getting the disability settlement you so richly deserve, or with the show's own solicitations for further troubled, well-built teens), Mr. Povich introduces several more mothers and their fallen angels, each as beguiling and foulmouthed as the first. All the girls seem to break Maury's mighty heart with the news that they want to be exotic dancers when they grow up. The stage is filled with pain, fret and woe; mothers at their wits' end and incorrigible daughters in skimpy outfits, and Maury Povich wrangling it all with only his near-rabbinical persistence and his cue cards to help him.</p>
        <p>There are two main variations of what comes next. In the first, less elaborate version, a couple of streetwise counselors are called on to scare the Satan straight out of these children. On some shows, the first counselor, usually quite a bombshell, seems to be a former sex worker or a disgruntled stripper or a recovering porn star who's there to tell the girls that the glamorous adult entertainment industry isn't the daffy hayride it's made out to be. Again, credentials and bona fides remain murky to viewers. Her fellow counselor is usually a large, loud man with a superfluity of biceps and a larynx the size and density of an anvil. This becomes evident backstage during the ensuing videotape piece in which he roars questions at the hard-bitten little ragamuffins like ''You think you're bad? You think you're BAD?''</p>
        <p>To which the girls can only reply with modest silence. The former burlesque queen, however, is more specific, if less explosive; asking if they all want to die of a drug overdose or get stabbed to death in an alley. Waiting to hear other options, perhaps, no one answers. This means that it's time to put the recalcitrant darlings into the van and drive them to Times Square. Upon arrival, they gather in front of a neon sign advertising one of the few remaining neighborhood sex shows -- to be yelled at some more. ''Don't you want to have your dignity?'' bellows  one counselor. ''Do you want to get AIDS?'' shrieks the other. Next thing you know (''Maury'' editors play fast and loose with chronology in these pieces) everyone is standing in that  alley next to a very sinister dumpster. ''Don't you know that you have to love yourself?'' brays one. ''I love you!'' screams the other. Regret is mumbled. Sniffles snuffled. Tears roll down pubescent cheeks and order is restored to the universe. These girls won't go bad. At least not until someone turns off those camera lights. Fade to black.</p>
        <p>In version two, usually titled ''Teen Boot Camp,'' the scantily clad miscreants are inventoried as before, but are then confronted by men in camouflage fatigues and freshly blocked troopers' hats. Now it's two large men yelling, ''You think you're bad? You think you're BAD?'' (One assumes this to be an effective line of inquiry for many certified psychotherapists.) The kiddies are then hauled off to a boot camp, the location and identification of which are also unclear in some cases; although I caught one show wherein it was actually specified as a facility of the Colorado County Juvenile Boot Camp, located in Texas.</p>
        <p>Upon arrival, the yelling begins in earnest and so do the pushups. With various unidentified drill instructors hollering at them, ''Don't you know you have to love yourself?'' the jumpsuited teens are forced to realize the error of their mulish ways by hauling buckets full of water, eating with utensils and cleaning up after themselves. ''Sir, yes, sir!'' After a few days of basic training (compressed into seconds on tape) sniffles are heard again, tears course down reformed faces and tough love conquers all.</p>
        <p>The bonus round on the boot camp shows, though, is the girls' return from the Inferno. Having been walked through Hell by Master Sgt. Virgil and his shock troops, they are meek as lambs. Hell, apparently, has many toilets that need scrubbing with a toothbrush. The girls reappear, sometimes wearing matching black berets and antisexy khaki coveralls -- paramilitary angels, really -- and are weepily reunited with their moms. Hugs abound and smiles widen and each has a little gift for Uncle Maury, too.</p>
        <p>Maury is happier than anyone at how things turned out, and speaks in a generous and gentle whisper to each of the girls. ''What was it like at night being alone in a cell?'' or ''Were you scared?'' he'll ask, and then extract from each the assurance that they'll never be bad or choke dear mother again. On one such show each was promised a free college education if she could remain revirginized. Souls saved, Maury presents his benediction. Turning to the nearest mother he says, ''As adults we have to assess our behavior, too.'' Chin quivering as if she's hooked to an outlet offstage, Mom agrees. ''Absolutely,'' she chokes out. Roll credits.</p>
        <p>Original sin thwarted and the rites of absolution performed in 44 minutes, plus commercials.</p>
        <p>Maury's not the only one with a new take on ''Crime and Punishment.'' The stalwart Sally Jessy Raphael sends more than her fair share of malevolent teens to boot camp on her syndicated show, too, especially if they trash her green room right on camera; but her version lacks the dire brio Maury brings to the work. Maury has about him the evangelical enthusiasm of a tent-show revivalist. Sally seems to have lost her zest for it, and often as not when reading her cue cards has the appearance of a zoo employee who's inadvertently been darted by her own tranquilizer gun.</p>
        <p>THAT morning television now regularly flirts with this kind of quasi-kiddie pornography and gets away with it should trouble someone, somewhere. But daytime television doesn't seem to merit much serious criticism these days, or cultural oversight; it has become a fact of life that these shows escape examination or community outcry. At least ''The Jerry Springer Show'' only humiliates and abuses consenting adults. Perhaps that's why the ratings are down.</p>
        <p>Even behind the fig leaf of moral reclamation, though, shows of the teen boot camp genre trade on the misdirected and theatrical sexualization of minors. Parents are confused by nothing more than the sexual maturing of their own children, I suppose, so the punitive aspect of these programs, the stamping out of early and inappropriate fires, may explain their popularity among some daytime viewers. What mother, after all, hasn't been appalled or frightened by the behavior of her teenage daughter at one time or another? Comfort lies in seeing that behavior punished and things set right.</p>
        <p>The creepy titillations that also underlie shows of this nature, however, are a different story. Guests on every talk show everywhere are coached by their segment producers to be lively, animated and demonstrative. One can only wonder what these children -- and they are children, no matter how they're built -- are being told to do and say by the producers.</p>
        <p>At a time when one in five wired youngsters say they've been sexually approached on the Internet, when every advertising medium from television to billboards to radio to magazines packages and repackages sex as a marketing tool, when the secret cash cows among the dot-coms are pay pornography sites and an online search for ''schoolgirl sex'' or ''teen sex'' produces hundreds of thousands of hits, can we really be shocked, surprised or self-righteous about the fact that our children spit out lungfuls of the very sexuality we immerse them in? And, having taught them these responses, doesn't it seem unjust to punish them in the village square just to satisfy our own bad appetite for revenge? Are we mad at them or at Britney Spears and Christina Aguilera, the sexually aggressive soft-core prom queens of MTV? Or do we simply punish our children publicly because we resent living in an entertainment nation co-opted by the tastes and buying patterns of teenagers?</p>
        <p>Like Maury says, ''As adults we have to assess our behavior, too.''</p>
        <p>Absolutely.</p>
        <p>TELEVISION/RADIO Jeff MacGregor worked in the television industry for 20 years as writer, producer and network correspondent.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Jeff MacGregor worked in the television industry for 20 years as writer, producer and network correspondent.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
