<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>OUT THERE: St. Petersburg, Russia; In Russia, a Rave Begins With a Mystical Voyage</title>
    <meta content="16PETE$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215378"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Entertainment and Amusements</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">St Petersburg (Russia)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Gulf of Finland</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Varoli, John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barkhin, Mikhail</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia/St. Petersburg</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Finland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Entertainment and Amusements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Military Bases and Installations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E3DA173BF935A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1446" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>OUT THERE: St. Petersburg, Russia; In Russia, a Rave Begins With a Mystical Voyage</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN VAROLI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Varoli, John</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Old Czarist fort in Gulf of Finland, 30 miles off coast of St Petersburg, has become unlikely site of all-night summer raves for Russian youth; photos; dancing, performance art and general merriment was inspiration of Mikhail Barkhin, artist who organized party with several owners of St Petersburg nightclubs (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FROM afar, lasers and strobe lights could be seen bursting mutely from within the island fort, as if it were being consumed by some mysterious battle, transforming it into a radiant beacon amid the 3 a.m. twilight covering the Gulf of Finland.</p>
        <p>But as the ferryboat loaded with young people docked after its three-hour voyage, music pulsating from the turreted fort broke the stillness. On the first weekend of July, as many as 10,000 of Russia's youth laid siege to an abandoned and crumbling Czarist structure some 30 miles off the coast of St. Petersburg for dancing, performance art and general merriment during the season of northern Russia's White Nights, when the sun sets for only three hours.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FROM afar, lasers and strobe lights could be seen bursting mutely from within the island fort, as if it were being consumed by some mysterious battle, transforming it into a radiant beacon amid the 3 a.m. twilight covering the Gulf of Finland.</p>
        <p>But as the ferryboat loaded with young people docked after its three-hour voyage, music pulsating from the turreted fort broke the stillness. On the first weekend of July, as many as 10,000 of Russia's youth laid siege to an abandoned and crumbling Czarist structure some 30 miles off the coast of St. Petersburg for dancing, performance art and general merriment during the season of northern Russia's White Nights, when the sun sets for only three hours.</p>
        <p>''Ever since first visiting the fort three years ago, it has been my obsession to stage a demonstration of modern and electronic culture here,'' said Mikhail Barkhin, an artist who organized the party along with several owners of St. Petersburg clubs, including Decadence, Mama and Griboyedov. ''It's not only a beautiful location, but a dramatic one. The whole event was meant to be an artistic performance, not just a party, and part of the performance was the long voyage to get there, which created the myth, the aura, of voyaging afar to reach some wild destination.''</p>
        <p>Wild it certainly was. The derelict fort, known by its nickname Fort Chumnoi, or Fort Plague, was built 200 years ago to defend St. Petersburg from invasion by sea, but early in the last century it became a medical research center for bubonic plague.</p>
        <p>The 15-hour party featured D.J.'s playing techno music on three of the fort's four floors, as well as outside in the main courtyard. There was also installation art and various performances, including one man who repeatedly shot off a flamethrower from the second floor over the heads of the crowd, which twisted hysterically amid steel and brick debris on the square below. People peered from behind broken walls and windows on each floor surrounding the courtyard, and some danced on the roof as the first glimmers of day appeared around 4 a.m.</p>
        <p>''It's like a Bosch painting come to life,'' said Sergei Bugayev, one of Russia's leading conceptualist artists, who is better known by his nickname, Africa. ''Many of the young people take rave to be something close to religious ecstasy, and the bizarre nature of the event is enhanced with the architectural incongruency of a military site being used to party.''</p>
        <p>Yevgenie Yevdokimov, 27, who grew up in St. Petersburg but has lived in Manhattan since 1996, said, ''I've never seen anything in New York as wild as this.''</p>
        <p>Techno parties are not new in the former Soviet Union. They made their way there about 10 years ago, part of the worldwide dissemination of bass-heavy, thumping dance music. The music played at the fort was in the best traditions of techno from America and Europe. On each floor, various techno subgenres could be heard: drum 'n' bass on one level, hardcore on another, and finally, around 9 a.m. on Sunday morning, a wash of ambient sounds signaling the time to chill out.</p>
        <p>The music might be much the same as elsewhere, but in Russia, techno party locations are becoming ever more exotic. Last summer, dances were held at an uncompleted nuclear power plant in the Crimea, Ukraine, and in May there was one at the testing grounds of the Institute of High Voltage in St. Petersburg.</p>
        <p>Until three years ago, the island fort, under the control of the Russian Ministry of Defense, was a top-secret location forbidden to the public because of the nearby Kronstadt naval base. It took Mr. Barkhin nearly all of the last three years to persuade naval commanders to allow the party.</p>
        <p>Russians sometimes boast that their country is the freest in the world, if not one of the most anarchic, where anything goes. That is sometimes true, in part because of the absence of lawsuits in Russian legal practice, which frees the organizers of events like the island rave from worrying about liability for injuries. But there is also something deeper, more specific to St. Petersburg itself, that explains why thousands would endure a three-hour boat ride to party on a chilly and remote island.</p>
        <p>''Something like this could only happen in St. Petersburg because it is a city with a rich history and many ruins,'' said Yura Nikitin, a Moscovite, as he stood on the roof of the fort and surveyed the crumbling structure. ''People in St. Petersburg are more crazy, gutsy and daring than in Moscow, where people are more pretentious, money-conscious, and if something is just a little bit uncomfortable, they go home.</p>
        <p>''Most stylish things in Russia -- the whole music and dance scene, for instance -- in large part come from St. Petersburg to Moscow, which then develops them commercially and on a bigger scale.''</p>
        <p>Evelyn Domnitch, a Web site designer from Manhattan who grew up in Minsk, Belarus, said: ''It is becoming quite a tradition in Russia to do these extreme parties because the people here are more romantic and free. Westerners are more pragmatic, and worry more about how much something will cost and whether or not there might be a lawsuit.''</p>
        <p>The festivities started under an ominous sign. A last-minute blackout -- the electricity for the party was provided by a nearby naval vessel -- kept revelers waiting on the mainland, and the crowds swelled to dangerous levels, forcing some to return home. Once on the island, people climbed onto dangerous ledges on the fort's roof. Organizers tried, often in vain, to rope off the most threatening areas. Miraculously, there were no apparent injuries.</p>
        <p>''You have to understand that in St. Petersburg we live in darkness for most of the year, and then for a few months in the summer go crazy during White Nights,'' Mr. Bugayev explained.</p>
        <p>Besides music and dancing, the party featured art installations by Ilya Voznesensky, who claims to be a great-grandson of Stalin. His creations were white cloth faces, first designed on a computer, then cut out of cotton and hung inside in front of the fort's open windows. The brisk sea breeze blew the faces into three dimensions, and with the sunrise at around 4 a.m., the light gave the faces a ghostly appearance.</p>
        <p>''I've been to techno parties in France, but this one was unbelievable,'' said Thierry Cabot, a French writer, the day after the party. ''In France we might have such a party at a stadium and get 20,000 people to party all night, but this ran all night and day and was particularly impressive with the White Nights season.''</p>
        <p>But not everyone admired the goings-on in the gulf. ''The fort party was not a good idea because it was dangerous and it encourages the drug culture in Russia, which is already strong and growing,'' said Katya Bokoutchava, 28, a journalist who covers the St. Petersberg club scene and is friendly with the organizers. To express her disapproval, she did not attend the event.</p>
        <p>Mr. Barkhin emphasized that his event was a noncommercial, private affair. It was not advertised, and tickets were free, handed out through a tight-knit group of people within the city's club scene. He called the event a gathering of ''friends and like-minded people who wanted to hang out and experience modern electronic culture,'' meaning techno music and computer-based art.</p>
        <p>By contrast, other techno parties, like this year's version of the Crimean bash, will be commercially exploited, with ticket sales, corporate sponsors and heavy press coverage. Mr. Barkhin said he planned to resist such temptations, even if it meant never staging another event at the fort. ''I don't want my events to go pop, and so this will probably be the last type of event like this,'' he said, staring into the distance over the water. ''But you can be sure we will be back, and with something new.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
