<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cheri Wicks, John Shaw III</title>
    <meta content="16WICK" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Society Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215361"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="WEDDINGS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEDDINGS AND ENGAGEMENTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">WICKS, CHERI ELIZABETH (CHERI ELIZABETH SHAW)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHAW, JOHN HENRY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Weddings and Celebrations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E3DB173BF935A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="562" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cheri Wicks, John Shaw III</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Cheri Elizabeth Wicks, an actress, and John Henry Shaw III, an investment banker, were married yesterday in Lewistown, Mont. The Rev. Carole Sims, an Episcopal priest, officiated at the Symmes/Wicks House, a 1909 Arts and Crafts home that is now a bed-and-breakfast owned by the bride's parents, Carole and Charles Wicks.</p>
        <p>The bride, who works out of New York, has had small parts in Off Off Broadway theater and in television shows including ''Sex and the City'' and ''Law and Order.'' She graduated from the University of Oregon at Eugene. Her father also owns the Lewistown Pharmacy, and her mother is a career counselor for the Human Resource Development Council in Lewistown.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Cheri Elizabeth Wicks, an actress, and John Henry Shaw III, an investment banker, were married yesterday in Lewistown, Mont. The Rev. Carole Sims, an Episcopal priest, officiated at the Symmes/Wicks House, a 1909 Arts and Crafts home that is now a bed-and-breakfast owned by the bride's parents, Carole and Charles Wicks.</p>
        <p>The bride, who works out of New York, has had small parts in Off Off Broadway theater and in television shows including ''Sex and the City'' and ''Law and Order.'' She graduated from the University of Oregon at Eugene. Her father also owns the Lewistown Pharmacy, and her mother is a career counselor for the Human Resource Development Council in Lewistown.</p>
        <p>The bridegroom is a managing director in the New York office of Broadmark Capital, an investment bank. He graduated from Allegheny College. He is the son of Peggy Shaw Rosato of St. Michaels, Md., and the late Mr. Shaw Jr., and the stepson of Dr. Edward J. Rosato. His mother, a psychotherapist, and his stepfather, a psychiatrist, have practices in St. Michaels. His father was a computer systems analyst at the Federal Aviation Administration's technical center in Pomona, N.J.</p>
        <p>The couple were introduced by mutual friends in 1995. He liked her right away, but her first impression of him wasn't a very good one. ''John was a guy in a suit -- no interest,'' remembered Ms. Wicks, who is known for wearing blue jeans, cowboy boots and hats. ''I was really anti-suits at that point. I thought a suit meant you work 9-5, you're rigid, your artistic merits are zero, you're on a treadmill.''</p>
        <p>Then in the summer of 1995, she ran into him at the beach in Point Pleasant, N.J., and had a totally different impression. ''There he was in shorts, hanging out, and he was really funny and smart and athletic,'' she said.</p>
        <p>They soon started dating, and she became known among his friends as the Cowgirl.</p>
        <p>Ms. Wicks does have many of the traits of a cowgirl. She grew up discussing crop prices and weather conditions with ranchers, something she still gets nostalgic about, and she speaks her mind whenever necessary. ''A few weeks after we started dating, we were on the train together,'' Mr. Shaw said. ''It's about 7 a.m. and she says, 'You know, I think I'm falling in love with you.' ''</p>
        <p>He didn't reply immediately. ''I called her when I got to the office,'' he said. ''And I said, 'You know, I think I'm starting to feel the same way.' ''</p>
        <p>He proposed last year, in laconic cowboy style, as she was leaving for her high school reunion in Lewistown. ''You better bring back your grandma's ring,'' he told her. She knew exactly what that meant. She had once told him that if she was ever to marry, she wanted to wear her grandmother's engagement ring.</p>
        <p>The couple wanted to make sure their Montana wedding was especially memorable for their New York City guests, and had a rehearsal dinner, everybody invited, on Friday at Bar 19, a Lewistown cowboy bar with cattle-brand symbols burned into the wooden walls, the bride's favorite decor.</p>
        <p>WEDDINGS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
