<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Nation; Let a Thousand New Voices Bloom</title>
    <meta content="16LEON$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215431"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Communications Commission</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leonhardt. David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radio</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE1D9143BF935A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1118" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Nation; Let a Thousand New Voices Bloom</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID LEONHARDT</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Federal Communications Commission proposes to issue hundreds of free licenses to low-power radio stations for nonprofit groups across the country, finding consolidation in radio industry has left people feeling as though they have no local voice on the airwaves anymore; some members of Congress, mostly Republicans, and large broadcasters oppose move, saying new stations would interfere with signals of existing stations; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AT the beginning of this year, the Federal Communications Commission announced that it was setting up hundreds of free, low-power radio stations for nonprofit groups across the country, in an attempt to increase the diversity of voices on the airwaves. People were invited to submit requests for a license.</p>
        <p>''Radio is our most ubiquitous mass medium,'' said the F.C.C chairman, William E. Kennard, who championed the program. ''People don't feel they have a local voice'' on the airwaves anymore, he added.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AT the beginning of this year, the Federal Communications Commission announced that it was setting up hundreds of free, low-power radio stations for nonprofit groups across the country, in an attempt to increase the diversity of voices on the airwaves. People were invited to submit requests for a license.</p>
        <p>''Radio is our most ubiquitous mass medium,'' said the F.C.C chairman, William E. Kennard, who championed the program. ''People don't feel they have a local voice'' on the airwaves anymore, he added.</p>
        <p>The response exceeded almost everyone's expectations. Thousands of groups wrote to the commission expressing interest, and some 750 applied for the 200 or so licenses in the first 10 eligible states.</p>
        <p>The F.C.C. envisons as many as a thousand micro-stations, each with a broadcast range of seven miles, and with a combined audience of millions for an entirely new group of broadcasters. Analysts called the program  potentially the biggest change in the radio industry since the growth of FM in the 1960's. Perhaps for that very reason, it has touched off a huge battle in Washington.</p>
        <p>Members of Congress, most of them Republican, say that Mr. Kennard is arrogantly trying to create a personal legacy, and they are seeking a way to block the plan. They have been joined by the nation's large broadcasters, including National Public Radio and the  National Religious Broadcasters Association, who claim the new stations would intefere with the signals of exisiting stations. Mr. Kennard has called the opposition's arguments a smoke screen designed to shield the broadcasters from competition.</p>
        <p>At the heart of the fight is the fact that AM and FM radio lack the variety they had two decades ago, in part because stations today are likely to be owned by corporations located far away, and which are relatively indifferent to local issues. To Gary Williams, the director of music and technical services at the Good News Church in Augusta, Ga., which has applied for a license, radio has become nothing but the same ''handful of people who have a great voice all over our country.''</p>
        <p>The applicants for low-power licenses, who want to restore a local and regional element to the airwaves, are a diverse lot. Nearly half are churches, and most of those are the kind of fundamentalist groups often active in conservative politics. Schools make up about 10 percent of the list, according to Media Access Project, a Washington law firm. Other applicants include immigrants' rights groups and a few jazz societies.</p>
        <p>Their collective frustration at not hearing their interests and values on the air is hardly limited to radio; people frequently tell pollsters that they feel prosperous but not particularly connected to their communities.</p>
        <p>''It's a parallel phenomenon to the political one, in which people don't feel the parties represent them,'' said Michael Janeway, a Columbia Journalism School professor and the author of ''Republic of Denial'' (Yale University Press, 1999). ''It may take a populist left turn or a populist right turn, but it's rooted in the vast distancing that people feel from the mainstream institutions that used to represent them.''</p>
        <p>Microradio -- a term popularized by operators of unlicensed, ''pirate'' radio stations and picked up by Mr. Kennard, whose agency had spent years prosecuting them -- offers a chance for people to set up community broadcast institutions, something that has become increasingly hard to come by in recent years.</p>
        <p>Since the Telecommunications Act relaxed ownership rules in 1996, more than half of all radio stations in this country have changed hands, said Reed E. Hundt, the F.C.C.'s former chairman. The number of station owners has declined by about 1,000 over the same period. Last year, the largest owner of stations, Clear Channel Communications, agreed to buy its nearest rival, AMFM Inc., which will create a 800-station giant.</p>
        <p>The companies' new size has given them truly mass audiences for the first time, making them much more attractive to advertisers. Deregulation, in turn, has loosened the rules about advertising, and some stations, having added as 10 extra minutes per hour, now spend almost half of their time broadcasting advertisements.</p>
        <p>As a result, community groups say, they have a much harder time getting on the air. ''There are a lot of needs that fall through the cracks of your commercial radio stations,'' said Reverend James A. Burkett of the ChristLife Community Church, of Athens, Ga., another license applicant.</p>
        <p>Tony Puesan, the founding director of a jazz and blues organization in Washington that is another microradio hopeful, wants to broadcast jazz 24 hours a day and also help aspiring musicians in the city raise money and gain exposure. No commercial radio station in Washington does either now, he said. ''It's important that we as American citizens get a chance to put information out there,'' Mr. Puesan added.</p>
        <p>The debate is particularly important, low-power advocates say, because of radio's historical mission.  When the government first established rules for television and radio broadcasters earlier in the century, it limited the number of national networks in order to set aside a large part of the spectrum for local broadcasters. That decision, said Akhil Reed Amar, a professor at Yale Law School, had its roots in the founders' desire to stitch a number of smaller democracies into a large one.</p>
        <p>Until recently, the F.C.C. even required stations seeking a renewal of their license to explain how they were filling a need in their community, noted Ben H. Bagdikian, a prominent critic of media consolidation.</p>
        <p>OF course, there is a chance that low-power radio will quickly become a moot issue. As more people get access to the Internet and broadband connections allow for rapid transmission of video and speech, people seeking a platform for their views will not need a government license.</p>
        <p>For now, however, posting a message in a chat room remains a poor substitute for broadcasting onto a device that the average American owns five of.</p>
        <p>''There is a radio in every car in the United States,'' said Mr. Hundt, now a consultant at McKinsey &amp; Company. ''There isn't the Internet in every car.''</p>
        <p>That suggests that even if the opponents of low-power radio win the current argument over technical problems, the larger question of who gets to have a voice in a democracy will not go away.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
