<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>One Drugstore Too Many, One Grocery Too Few?</title>
    <meta content="16DRUG" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215405"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: UPPER WEST SIDE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drugstores</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Supermarkets</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cvs Drug Stores</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Rite Aid Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Suba Pharmacy</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Associated Supermarkets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Crow, Kelly</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Supermarkets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugstores</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E5D8173BF935A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="578" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>One Drugstore Too Many, One Grocery Too Few?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KELLY CROW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Crow, Kelly</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on plethora of drugstores but lack of grocery store on Broadway between 102nd and 106th streets; CVS Pharmacy is about to join two Duane Reades, Rite Aid and Suba Pharmacy; Associated Supermarket closed two months ago; photos; chart (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The story of the CVS Pharmacy due to open at Broadway and West 102nd Street is not just about a chain store that squeezes out a Mom and Pop store. This CVS joins a four-block area already crowded by two Duane Reades and a Rite Aid, and replaces a supermarket that residents say they need much more.</p>
        <p>The CVS will also vie with Suba Pharmacy on West 104th Street, which until four years ago was the only drugstore on Broadway from 102nd to 106th Street.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The story of the CVS Pharmacy due to open at Broadway and West 102nd Street is not just about a chain store that squeezes out a Mom and Pop store. This CVS joins a four-block area already crowded by two Duane Reades and a Rite Aid, and replaces a supermarket that residents say they need much more.</p>
        <p>The CVS will also vie with Suba Pharmacy on West 104th Street, which until four years ago was the only drugstore on Broadway from 102nd to 106th Street.</p>
        <p>For neighbors like John Davenport, the closing of an Associated Supermarket two months ago to make way for CVS in October means he must walk four to five extra blocks to one of the area's two remaining supermarkets. And he, like others, is furious.</p>
        <p>''We have been more or less passive,'' Mr. Davenport said. ''But this has enraged us. They've taken away our supermarket and given us another big pharmacy we don't need.''</p>
        <p>A petition to boycott CVS has attracted 3,000 signers, he said, and a meeting is scheduled for 7:30 p.m. on Wednesday at Ansche Chesed Synagogue on West 100th Street.</p>
        <p>CVS is not troubled. ''We're not going to be worried about a few individuals because once the store opens, they'll be very favorable,'' said Mike DeAngelis, a CVS spokesman. ''I can't speak to why the supermarket closed, but we've found that New York City is underserved and needs quality pharmacies. We consider ourselves to be good corporate neighbors.''</p>
        <p>The CVS is one of 200 planned for New York City in the next five years, to compete against Duane Reade and Rite Aid. Rite Aid cut back expansions after profits fell last year.</p>
        <p>The supermarket had at least 10 years on its lease but sold it to CVS for more than $1 million, said Sandy Sirulnick of Seminole Realty, the property owner.</p>
        <p>Teresa Elwert of the West 104th Street Block Association said that business was brisk at Associated Supermarket because two of the nearby pharmacies had also replaced grocery stores.</p>
        <p>''Associated was not my favorite supermarket because its aisles were narrow,'' Ms. Elwert said. ''But we're very sorry we've lost it. It was convenient and the prices were reasonable.''</p>
        <p>She said she feared that supermarkets,  Gristede's on West 100th Street and Sloan's  on West 107th, would capitalize on the departure of Associated by raising prices. Matthew T. Wanning, a spokesman for the Red Apple Group, which owns both, disputed that.</p>
        <p>''Shoppers in this city are not very loyal,'' Mr. Wanning said. ''You raise your prices, and they'll walk another block to the next place.''</p>
        <p>But the next place is not nearby.</p>
        <p>Assemblyman Ed C. Sullivan, who supports the planned boycott, said: ''What's bizarre is that for a long time, we didn't have enough drugstores and we had a lot of supermarkets. Now, we're getting worked over and we don't want it.''</p>
        <p>KELLY CROW</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: UPPER WEST SIDE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
