<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Noir Classic Makes It Back From the Blacklist</title>
    <meta content="16SRAG$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215132"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FILM"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sragow, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dassin, Jules</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Rififi (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E0DC1038F935A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2366" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Noir Classic Makes It Back From the Blacklist</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL SRAGOW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sragow, Michael</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Michael Sragow article on re-release of film noir classic Du Rififi Chez les Hommes, released in US as Rififi, whose writer and director Jules Dassin was blacklisted in 1950's; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN 1954, Francois Truffaut, then a critic, wrote that it was ''the best film 'noir' I have ever seen.'' But in more ways than one, ''Du Rififi Chez les Hommes'' -- released in the United States as ''Rififi'' -- came out of left field. Its writer and director, Jules Dassin, was a blacklisted American expatriate, unemployed since 1950. Furthermore, when he worked in Hollywood, Mr. Dassin had never been the sort of well-adjusted studio hand that Truffaut and his fellow auteur critics typically admired.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dassin had regarded MGM, where he had worked for much of the 40's, as the plushest purgatory. He felt he had begun to grow as a director only when he quit to make socially conscious melodramas for Mark Hellinger (''The Naked City'') and Darryl F. Zanuck (''Thieves Highway'').</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN 1954, Francois Truffaut, then a critic, wrote that it was ''the best film 'noir' I have ever seen.'' But in more ways than one, ''Du Rififi Chez les Hommes'' -- released in the United States as ''Rififi'' -- came out of left field. Its writer and director, Jules Dassin, was a blacklisted American expatriate, unemployed since 1950. Furthermore, when he worked in Hollywood, Mr. Dassin had never been the sort of well-adjusted studio hand that Truffaut and his fellow auteur critics typically admired.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dassin had regarded MGM, where he had worked for much of the 40's, as the plushest purgatory. He felt he had begun to grow as a director only when he quit to make socially conscious melodramas for Mark Hellinger (''The Naked City'') and Darryl F. Zanuck (''Thieves Highway'').</p>
        <p>Still, Truffaut knew masterly moviemaking when he saw it. In the panegryic to ''Rififi'' reprinted in his book ''The Films in My Life,'' he used Mr. Dassin's low-budget caper film to argue that ''a film's success depends more on its director than on massive production resources or the participation of world-renowned actors.'' And when ''Rififi'' opened in New York a year after Mr. Dassin won the best-director prize at the Cannes International Film Festival, Bosley Crowther echoed Truffaut in The New York Times. He followed an initial rave with a Sunday piece positioning ''Rififi'' as the antidote to big-star extravaganzas. The movie ran for 20 weeks in Manhattan at the Fine Arts with subtitles before opening dubbed throughout the metropolitan area.</p>
        <p>Despite the film's success in big cities, Mr. Dassin says, no national distributor would pick it up because of the blacklist unless he took his name off the film or renounced his youthful radicalism. Yet ''Rififi'' became, here and abroad, a benchmark for adventures centering on a group of criminals or agents plotting and executing a big score. Although ''Rififi'' is lowdown and realistic, its influence can be felt both in star-laden escapism from ''Ocean's Eleven'' to ''Mission: Impossible'' (not to mention Mr. Dassin's own 1964 film, ''Topkapi'') and in pungent neo-noir fables like ''The Usual Suspects.''</p>
        <p>For decades, outside of museums or archives, ''Rififi'' has been seen in the United States only in pirated, squint-inducing video editions. That will change on Friday, when Rialto Pictures (the company behind the theatrical rerelease of ''Nights of Cabiria'' and ''Grand Illusion'') brings it back to the Film Forum in Manhattan with a fresh print and newly translated subtitles. The movie has aged superbly. It may not be Mr. Dassin's masterpiece -- that is, I think, the original (1950) ''Night and the City,'' a hard-boiled fable about warped imagination and ambition that he made in London for Zanuck and 20th Century Fox. But on its own terms ''Rififi'' is just about flawless: a genre movie brought off so keenly that it defines that genre's strengths and limits.</p>
        <p>It introduces the characters as quickly as a police lineup. Jean Servais is Tony, an ailing, weathered ex-con who has just finished a five-year term in prison. Carl Mohner is his best friend, Jo, a young married crook Tony refused to give up to the cops. Jo and his pal Mario (Robert Manuel) have hatched a get-rich-quick scheme to knock off a jewelry store on the Rue de Rivoli. Jo and Mario want to break into the shop window in broad daylight and make off with the gems on display. But hard time and bad luck have made Tony tough and maybe desperate. He decides he'll be part of the theft only if his comrades go all the way and crack the jewelry shop's safe. That requires a criminal virtuoso named Cesar: a girl-crazy Italian who speaks little French. He is played by Perlo Vita, a pseudonym for Mr. Dassin.</p>
        <p>As a writer, Mr. Dassin gets his momentum going even before the suspense kicks in, so that you pay attention to the details, not just of fact but of character. Jo's jolly family life with his wife and towheaded son, and the sensual bond Mario shares with his spouse, are as vivid as the way a rival kingpin and nightclub owner controls his kid brother with dope. As a director, Mr. Dassin has perfect pitch. When anything disrupts the film's dry yet convivial tone -- like Tony beating his ex-lover (Marie Sabouret) for taking up with that nightclub owner in his absence -- it registers as a troubling portent, not a dramatic miscue. The movie has been criticized for its astringency: no spontaneous emotion, no tender or playful impulse, goes unpunished. But that's what gives the film its hardscrabble integrity. Mr. Dassin seduces you into thinking that you're joining four underworld musketeers. Then he shows you there's no room in this band for carefree camaraderie.</p>
        <p>THE planning of the grand theft goes on for 10 or 15 minutes; the robbery fills half an hour and unrolls without dialogue. From the gangsters' mapping the neighborhood and casing the joint to their using props as mundane as an ordinary umbrella to keep from setting off a sensitive alarm, this is galvanic cinema. The sequence isn't shot in real time: the robbers do their job from the prime of night straight until morning. But Mr. Dassin calmly details the action so the audience can get into their mind set as Jo and Cesar hammer away at their obstacles and as Tony watches deliverymen, street cleaners and gendarmes make their rounds. The most mundane moment -- like a watchman studying a litterbug's tossed cigarette box -- carries ominous overtones. And the ingenuity of the filmmaking doesn't stop with the robbery: it culminates in the grueling road trip a wounded Tony takes from his enemies' chateau back to Paris, which Mr. Dassin renders with subjective angles and jagged elisions in the editing.</p>
        <p>As the film critic Manny Farber once wrote of John Huston, ''Few directors project so well the special Robinson Crusoe effect of man confronted by a job whose problems must be dealt with, point by point, with the combination of personal ingenuity and scientific know-how characterizing the man of action.'' And few avant-garde films have demonstrated as skillfully as this movie how time and pace affect perception. In ''Rififi,'' static qualities like wariness and patience become almost unbearably dynamic.</p>
        <p>''Rififi'' is often compared to Huston's ''Asphalt Jungle'' (1950), a minor classic in its own right. But the jewel heist in that film goes on for 13 or 14 minutes, tops, and its preamble consists of the mastermind saying he has a plan and then hiring the right men and the wrong fence. Mr. Dassin told me recently on the phone from his home in Athens, ''Please believe me that I saw 'The Asphalt Jungle' after I made 'Rififi,' because a number of people compared these two films.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Dassin, who was born on Dec. 18, 1911, says there was ''no precedent'' for making a caper whose preparation takes up a full third of a film and whose execution is rendered without dialogue or music. But homing in on criminal process was the one way he could think of to handle Auguste le Breton's novel, which he loathed. Truffaut called this source book ''the worst crime novel'' he'd ever read; the only chapter that snagged Mr. Dassin's interest hinged on a minor robbery.</p>
        <p>Once Mr. Dassin decided to focus on the theft, he followed a simple rule of thumb: ''The enemy is noise!'' He continued: ''What I loved and really enjoyed was to see the film in public in Paris. All the nice bourgeois people who go to the movies were rooting for these guys to succeed. I had one of the gang hit a single piano key and the audience jumped. When I was writing it, I knew you had to have that rooting interest; the film would work only if I made people want them to succeed. First I introduced the element of friendship, because if you're going to care for the people who are going to be crooks, you have to have some sympathy for them as people. But part of it is also thinking that these guys are real professionals and work well together. It's like wanting a great star to come up to bat and hit a homer.''</p>
        <p>BY the time Mr. Dassin made ''Rififi,'' he was anything but a star himself. Making ''Brute Force'' (1947), ''The Naked City'' (1948) and ''Thieves' Highway'' (1949), he took enormous leaps as a director, most noticeably in his pioneering use of real locations but also in his skill at shaping real yet heightened performances and at getting audiences to identify with morally mixed characters. But Mr. Dassin had started out as a stage director in the revolutionary New York theaters of the 30's, and had joined the Communist Party after seeing the opening night of ''Waiting for Lefty.'' In 1949 the blacklist put him out of business. Mr. Dassin recalled that the 20th Century Fox chief Darryl F. Zanuck, who hated the blacklist, had urged him to start shooting the London-based ''Night and the City'' with ''the most expensive sequences first -- that way no one would force him to fire me.'' Working with an English crew and an Anglo-American cast, Mr. Dassin made a film unlike any other. He brought London's back alleys and clip joints and arenas alive in an electric, phantasmagoric way, and he coaxed a career-high performance out of Richard Widmark as Harry Fabian, a hustler turned wrestling promoter whom one character describes as ''an artist without an art.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Dassin had his art taken away from him. When he returned to America, the one job he could get was directing Bette Davis in a Broadway revue. ''She was the only one who said, 'They don't tell me what to do.' It was sketches, silly stuff -- and then zero.'' He initially went to Paris to prepare a film with Fernandel. But the producers backed down under the threat of their films' being barred from American release. Mr. Dassin lived through these ''dark days'' with his family in a village outside Paris, forging bonds with fellow blacklisted expatriates like Joseph Losey and John Berry. When the chance to do ''Rififi'' came up, he said, ''it meant a lot to me, because I was unemployable.''</p>
        <p>''I wrote it, directed it and acted in it, and my fee was $8,000,'' he said. ''And I was glad to have it.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Dassin said he landed ''Rififi'' because the producer who had bought the book realized that it had a problem: ''All the bad guys were North Africans.'' With Frenchmen raging over their government's behavior in Algeria, the producer hoped to avoid controversy. ''He told me, 'If we hire you, you can make all the bad guys Americans.' I said, 'Why can't we make them French?' He had never considered it. I was halting in French, but this was written in an argot that many French people didn't know anyway. He gave me the book on a Friday and said I had to tell him on Monday whether I'd do it or not. I asked an agent and friend of mine to come and read the book to me. 'Please don't ask me this,' he said, 'I've been courting this girl for years, and this is the only time she's going to see me.' But he came.</p>
        <p>''The truth is the book shocked me; it was all about Arab bad behavior, including necrophilia. But there was a little chapter in which the men decided to hold something up -- I don't remember if it was a jewelry shop -- in order to do a big job. I made their little job into my big job. On the line to meet a schedule because of bad weather, I wrote the screenplay in 10 days.''</p>
        <p>Truffaut wrote, ''Dassin shot the film on the street during high winds and rain, and he reveals Paris to us Frenchmen as he revealed London to the English ('Night and the City') and New York to the Americans ('The Naked City').'' Indeed, Mr. Dassin remembers traipsing through Paris and dictating much of the script, telling the woman who was taking it down, ''We'll do this scene here and that scene there.'' In general, he said, ''The only way you really prepare locations is to walk.'' Maybe that's why city streets in his films have such bustling vitality.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dassin hired Servais to play the central role of Tony because his bitterness had genuine tang: the actor was then known as a washed-up juvenile. Although the director had planned to use a solid Italian actor to play Cesar, he said, ''The producers were too slow in signing contracts: that's why I had to put on the mustache and play him myself.'' (Abashed at his own acting, he refers to his performing as ''agony, agony.'') For his creative team he signed up Philippe Agostini as his cinematographer (he had shot Marcel Carne's ''Daybreak'') and the legendary Alexandre Trauner and Georges Auric as, respectively, his designer and his composer. ''Auric was a wonderful composer,'' Mr. Dassin recalled, ''and he said, 'I can't wait to do the music for the holdup.' I told him I didn't want any music. He said: 'What do you mean you don't want music? I'll protect you; I'll write the music.' Afterward, I invited him to a screening and said: 'I will show you the scene with the music and without it. You tell me.' He said, 'Take out the music.' ''</p>
        <p>''Rififi Means Trouble,'' said the American ads. But as Mr. Dassin explained: ''The Riff or Riffis were Morocco Berbers, tough fighters. The title of Auguste le Breton's book was 'Du Rififi Chez les Hommes,' translated 'Clashes Between the Men' (in the macho sense). I think that the word Rififi was Breton's invention. The closest translation would be 'pitched battle.' ''</p>
        <p>For lovers of tough-guy moviemaking, ''Rififi'' really means perfection.</p>
        <p>FILM Michael Sragow writes about film for Salon.com and is working on a biography of the director Victor Fleming.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Michael Sragow writes about film for Salon.com and is working on a biography of the director Victor Fleming.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
