<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Friend to Injured Animals Opens a Home</title>
    <meta content="16JOUR$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215223"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="LONG ISLAND JOURNAL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Birds</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Wildlife Rescue Center of the Hamptons</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Frati, Virginia</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fischler, Marcelle S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E6D91E38F935A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1234" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Friend to Injured Animals Opens a Home</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARCELLE S. FISCHLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fischler, Marcelle S</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Long Island Journal column: Virginia Frati, wildlife rehabilitator who has been treating injured and sick wild animals and birds at her home in Noyac since giving up secretarial job three years ago, marks first phase of construction on Wildlife Rescue Center of the Hamptons, state-of-the-art hospital and emergency center in Munn's Pond Park, with ribbon-cutting ceremony; facility described; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FIFTY-ONE wild animals live in Virginia Frati's home in Noyac. Her spare bedroom is a triage center for injured and sick squirrels, rabbits and turtles. Her basement is a wildlife rehab area; the deck a halfway house sheltering orphaned squirrels learning to survive in the woods. And the gazebo on the front lawn doubles as an aviary for recuperating songbirds.</p>
        <p>In a cage in Ms. Frati's office, four baby squirrels, two of whom fell from a nest, scratch on the wire as she approaches, clamoring for attention. Four baby chipmunks, rescued when their nest was bulldozed, scramble about in another cage.  ''They seem friendly, but that's only because I'm still nursing them,'' Ms. Frati said of her bushy-tailed charges, checking on a squirrel whose broken leg she put in a cast, then dispensing advice over the phone to someone who had just found a baby duck stuck in a bulkhead.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FIFTY-ONE wild animals live in Virginia Frati's home in Noyac. Her spare bedroom is a triage center for injured and sick squirrels, rabbits and turtles. Her basement is a wildlife rehab area; the deck a halfway house sheltering orphaned squirrels learning to survive in the woods. And the gazebo on the front lawn doubles as an aviary for recuperating songbirds.</p>
        <p>In a cage in Ms. Frati's office, four baby squirrels, two of whom fell from a nest, scratch on the wire as she approaches, clamoring for attention. Four baby chipmunks, rescued when their nest was bulldozed, scramble about in another cage.  ''They seem friendly, but that's only because I'm still nursing them,'' Ms. Frati said of her bushy-tailed charges, checking on a squirrel whose broken leg she put in a cast, then dispensing advice over the phone to someone who had just found a baby duck stuck in a bulkhead.</p>
        <p>''We try very carefully not to handle them any more than we have to,'' she said. ''We don't want them to get used to us. They could get very tame and that's not good for the animal when he's released in the wild.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Frati, 44, is a wildlife rehabilitator. Three years ago, she gave up her job as a secretary for Suffolk County to become a full-time volunteer, dedicating 15 hours a day, 7 days a week to rescuing animals. And to give the squirrels, ducks, turtles, gulls, geese, pigeons and possums a shelter, she started a not-for-profit outfit, the Wildlife Rescue Center of the Hamptons.</p>
        <p>''I just felt sorry for anything that got injured,'' Ms. Frati said. ''Anything that gets hurt really strikes a chord. When they die I'm upset, and when they fly away I'm terribly happy.'' Ms. Frati is always mindful not to pet, kiss or become too attached to the parade of wildlife she keeps in her home for up to 90 days.</p>
        <p>After a ribbon-cutting ceremony yesterday marking the first phase of construction on a state-of-the-art hospital and emergency center for wildlife in Hampton Bays, Ms. Frati planned to move her menagerie into its Munn's Pond Park headquarters, where several orphaned baby birds have already found a cage to call home. Built by volunteer labor, it will be the first medical facility for wild animals on the East End, complete with a raised bathtub to scrub oil off swans, gulls and loons. Eight other buildings on the site will house songbirds, mammals and waterfowl, said James Hunter, a retired county engineer turned rehabilitator who designed the center. Mr. Hunter used to commute to work with Mrs. Frati. Now he spends his days helping her tend the wildlife.</p>
        <p>A diving-duck facility will have four pools and its own filtering system. The raptor flight-conditioning area will have enough space to allow hawks and owls to fly, swoop down and catch their prey while rehabilitating their wings. Six of the buildings should be completed by September; plans for an educational building, pending approval of the Suffolk County Legislature, are in the works. Total tab: $500,000 in free labor. Fund-raisers will hopefully cover the $250,000 in building materials and $120,000 a year in maintenance costs, Mr. Hunter said.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, in a large box in Ms. Frati's spare bedroom, a pair of wild baby rabbits are recuperating from a trauma. Eight box turtles are dug into the dirt in an eight-foot terrarium next to a Jacuzzi in the sunroom. Some were hit by cars and sport fiberglass patches; others have missing feet or came in with ear and eye infections.</p>
        <p>Two seagulls, unable to fly, share a bowl of bunkerfish in a playpen in her basement. One has a broken wing, the other was shot and is limping due to a problem with his leg. A beat-up crow found in someone's yard is in a box nearby. Ms. Frati flushes its injured left eye daily with a sterile saline solution, administers antibiotics and notes that since she started taking care of it, the bird has begun to stand again.</p>
        <p>''Wild animals don't belong in people's homes,'' said Ms. Frati, showing off the rescued pet iguana who resides in a cage in the living room, alongside a parrot and a cockatiel. Her pet bunnies are in a cage outside. ''This is not the ideal situation to have animals in every room. It affects your home life. It affects the volunteers.''</p>
        <p>The volunteers who help Ms. Frati care for her zoo can frequently be found in her kitchen, whipping up a mix of puppy formula and wildlife supplement for the squirrels or chopping meat and preparing strawberries, melon, mealybugs, dandelions and earthworms for the turtles.</p>
        <p>''They feel like domestic help as opposed to technicians; the center is a place for them to come,'' Ms. Frati said, though she intends to continue providing emergency care at night in her home even after the center opens.</p>
        <p>In the past year, the Wildlife Rescue Center rescued 512 animals and responded to more than 5,000 calls. (The wild animal rescue hot line is 631-728-9453). Most of the animals, Ms. Frati said, were treated and released. With the new facility, Ms. Frati expects to take in 2,000 to 3,000 animals a year.</p>
        <p>More than 50 volunteers rescue and transport the wildlife. And other rehabilitators, like Sigrid Owen, 72, a retired photographer who keeps swans and turtles at her East Hampton home, also provide shelter. Veterinarians donate their expertise.</p>
        <p>''It's an environmental issue, not only a humane issue,'' said Ms. Frati. ''As development increases out here, the encounters with wild animals also increases. They hit windows. They get caught in our fences. They get hit by cars. Our cats kill them. It's almost like a sense of duty. We are doing this to them. We have to help them. Ninety-five percent of everything we get in has been impacted by humans.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Frati, who loves animals but never had many pets, became involved after she saw a woodchuck that had been hit by a car lying on the side of the road. She called the police. They referred her to volunteer wildlife rehabilitators. When she tried calling, she got answering machines.  '' I hung up and left and didn't do anything and it bothered me,'' Ms. Frati recalled. She subsequently studied for her own license and began pursuing wildlife rehabilitation part time. There are about 50 wildlife rehabilitators on the Island.</p>
        <p>''I would get home and there would be hysterical calls on the answering machine,'' she said. ''I felt bad. I was at work. I wasn't here to answer the calls. I tried to limit what I took and only things I could take care of in the morning and at night,'' she said, bothered that no round-the-clock facility existed.</p>
        <p>''I guess it's just the satisfaction of seeing something fly away that you worked so hard to rehabilitate,'' Ms. Frati said.</p>
        <p>LONG ISLAND JOURNAL E-mail address: lijournal@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail address: lijournal@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
