<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Too Many Post-Its</title>
    <meta content="LTR022447" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215449"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MEDICINE AND HEALTH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chesnut, Ann Moritz</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bank, David (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E4D6143BF935A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="354" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Too Many Post-Its</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ann Moritz Chesnut letter on July 2 article views as disturbing thousands of dollars dermatologist Dr David Bank spends each year on publicist6</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Since I am a newsletter editor and communications coordinator for a national voluntary health agency,  ''Doctors Who Love Publicity'' looked like a fascinating piece.</p>
        <p>Then I read the photo caption and my fascination turned to dismay.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Since I am a newsletter editor and communications coordinator for a national voluntary health agency,  ''Doctors Who Love Publicity'' looked like a fascinating piece.</p>
        <p>Then I read the photo caption and my fascination turned to dismay.</p>
        <p>It turned out that the doctor in question, Dr. David Bank, is the head of the dermatology practice that my family and I have patronized regularly for a number of years.</p>
        <p>The partner whom we routinely visit appears to be a thorough and conscientious physician, and we have been very happy with the care provided.</p>
        <p>However, we have noticed lately a proliferation of laminated magazine clippings on display, stacks of high-end women's magazines with Post-it note markers indicating the places where Dr. Bank is quoted, a lot of printed information on chemical peels and liposuction, and an emphasis on cosmetic surgery in general, not to mention an obviously costly renovation and reorganization of the office space.</p>
        <p>The fact that Dr. Bank spends thousands of dollars a year on a publicist is disturbing to me, because it inevitably means that he needs to see more patients and/or charge higher fees in order to meet this added expense.</p>
        <p>It is significant to me that during one visit I remember having with Dr. Bank himself, he encouraged me to consider a costly chemical process that is not covered by health insurance, a process that the partner I routinely see had never felt compelled to mention.</p>
        <p>There is no question in my mind that Dr. Bank and his associates are dedicated and competent doctors, but I am nevertheless concerned to learn that he has set his sights far above the middle-class, run-of-the-mill skin woes that my family bring to Mount Kisco.</p>
        <p>ANN MORITZ CHESNUT  Lake Peekskill, N.Y.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
