<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Jacobs and Favor Hamilton Lead Middle-Distance Resurgence</title>
    <meta content="Y16JAC$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215518"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="OLYMIPICS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Track and Field</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Summer Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sydney (Australia)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Longman, Jere</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Favor Hamilton, Suzy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jacobs, Regina</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004/Track and Field</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia/Sydney</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Track and Field</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E0D7153BF935A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="848" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Jacobs and Favor Hamilton Lead Middle-Distance Resurgence</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JERE LONGMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Longman, Jere</byline>
      <dateline>SACRAMENTO, July 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Regina Jacobs and Suzy Favor Hamilton are medal hopefuls in 1,500 meters at Sydney Olympics (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Although he ran no farther than one lap around the track, Michael Johnson accounted for America's only medal at any distance longer than a full-out sprint at the 1996 Olympics in Atlanta. There is renewed hope for the middle distances at the 2000 Games in Sydney, Australia, where the United States could not only win a medal in the women's 1,500 meters but even win a gold.</p>
        <p>Regina Jacobs, a two-time silver medalist at the world championships, and Suzy Favor Hamilton, only the second American woman to breach four minutes in the 1,500, will face off Sunday at that distance in the United States Olympic track and field trials. While championship races are often tactical and slow, Tom Craig, who is Jacobs's coach and husband, believes Mary Slaney's 17-year-old American record of  3 minutes 57.12 seconds could be in jeopardy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Although he ran no farther than one lap around the track, Michael Johnson accounted for America's only medal at any distance longer than a full-out sprint at the 1996 Olympics in Atlanta. There is renewed hope for the middle distances at the 2000 Games in Sydney, Australia, where the United States could not only win a medal in the women's 1,500 meters but even win a gold.</p>
        <p>Regina Jacobs, a two-time silver medalist at the world championships, and Suzy Favor Hamilton, only the second American woman to breach four minutes in the 1,500, will face off Sunday at that distance in the United States Olympic track and field trials. While championship races are often tactical and slow, Tom Craig, who is Jacobs's coach and husband, believes Mary Slaney's 17-year-old American record of  3 minutes 57.12 seconds could be in jeopardy.</p>
        <p>On June 24 at the Prefontaine Classic in Eugene, Ore., Favor Hamilton ran a searing pace against Gabriela Szabo of Romania, the 1996 Olympic silver medalist, building a 20-meter lead only to be caught at the tape as she stumbled to the track. Szabo's time of 4:00.73 is the fastest time in the world this year, and Favor Hamilton's 4:00.79 is second fastest. Until Friday's victory in the preliminaries in 4:06.16, Jacobs had not run a 1,500 meters outdoors this season. But at the Prefontaine meet she set a personal best of 1:58.08 at 800 meters.</p>
        <p>American women have never won a medal at 1,500 meters since it was added to the Olympic program at the 1972 Games in Munich. The current Olympic champion, Svetlana Masterkova of Russia, however, has undergone a pair of surgeries on her Achilles' tendons and remains an unknown commodity with the Olympics two and a half months away.</p>
        <p>Szabo will run the 5,000 in Sydney and may double in the 1,500. But Jacobs and Favor Hamilton are clearly threats to win the gold medal. Both are at the top of their games after suffering career-altering traumas -- Jacobs overcoming a severe iron deficiency and Favor Hamilton gaining a new resolve after the suicide last year of her brother, who suffered from manic depression.</p>
        <p>Favor Hamilton has made two previous Olympic teams, and only Slaney has surpassed her personal best of 3:58.43 among American women. But Favor Hamilton, who is 31, has also had a reputation as a soft, timid runner who was not fortified athletically or mentally to contend in major races.</p>
        <p>She missed last season after undergoing surgery to repair a torn Achilles' tendon, and on Sept. 9 her brother Dan, who had stopped taking his antidepressant medication, killed himself. His sister has begun using her maiden name again to honor Dan Favor, and she has spoken frequently about her brother's death in hopes of raising awareness about manic depression. She races now to honor her brother, Favor Hamilton said, and she has developed a new urgency and fearlessness in her running.</p>
        <p>''I feel rejuvenated and motivated,'' Favor Hamilton said after winning her preliminary heat in 4:10.29 Friday night. ''I'm a new runner.''</p>
        <p>Jacobs will turn 37 before the Sydney Games begin. She was born in Los Angeles on Aug. 28, 1963, the day that Martin Luther King Jr. gave his ''I have a dream'' speech.</p>
        <p>By age 17, Jacobs was participating in the 1980 Olympic trials as an 800-meter runner. But it was not until the past three years that her career has reached full flower. In 1993, Jacobs was diagnosed with low levels of iron in her body, accounting for her erratic track performances.</p>
        <p>She changed her diet, eating more vegetables and red meat, and began taking iron supplements to boost the deficient levels in her body and to increase her stamina.</p>
        <p>At the 1997 and 1999 world championships, Jacobs lost to Masterkova at 1,500 meters, the second time by less than a second last August in Seville, Spain.</p>
        <p>Jacobs has analyzed Masterkova's running style and has worked hard this season to make her own stride more sound, reaching less with her arms and striking the ground with her feet under her hips for maximum efficiency.</p>
        <p>''Now she's at the point where she's realizing how well she can run,'' Craig said. ''It's confidence, experience. You've been there before. You're more relaxed.''</p>
        <p>Before the Olympics, of course, come the finals of the Olympic trials and a riveting matchup with Favor Hamilton. The top three finishers in the race will qualify for Sydney.</p>
        <p>''After the death of her brother, Suzy is different,'' Craig said. ''She's not afraid of anything. Regina has the same sort of attitude: 'Who cares? Let's go.' It could be tactical or it could be the American record. It's going to be fun. I'd love to see it be the kind of race that can convert 10,000 girls who are playing soccer back to track and field.''</p>
        <p>OLYMIPICS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
