<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Strolling the Aisles on the Web</title>
    <meta content="16SIDE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215193"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Delivery Services</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Boynton, Cynthia Wolfe</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Service Industries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE6DE1E38F935A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="920" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Strolling the Aisles on the Web</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CYNTHIA WOLFE BOYNTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Boynton, Cynthia Wolfe</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Cynthia Wolfe Boynton describes what she likes about shopping online using ShopLink grocery delivery service (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN I asked a friend how she liked using the ShopLink online grocery delivery service, she looked straight at me and said without hesitation: ''Run to the phone and call. You won't regret it for a second.''</p>
        <p>Maybe. I actually like grocery shopping. I like to pick over produce and dig to find the best cuts of meat. But usually I shop with two kids who get restless and a husband who encourages them to ask for every goody, a mix that makes shopping a stressful, not to mention expensive, experience.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN I asked a friend how she liked using the ShopLink online grocery delivery service, she looked straight at me and said without hesitation: ''Run to the phone and call. You won't regret it for a second.''</p>
        <p>Maybe. I actually like grocery shopping. I like to pick over produce and dig to find the best cuts of meat. But usually I shop with two kids who get restless and a husband who encourages them to ask for every goody, a mix that makes shopping a stressful, not to mention expensive, experience.</p>
        <p>ShopLink has at least so far eliminated this stress. No mistakes or mix-ups. And I can't tell you how delightful it is to pull into the driveway from work and see that someone else has done a week's worth of grocery shopping for me. I've had two deliveries to date and was looking for something to criticize. Always the skeptic, I was sure that at least some of my apples would come bruised or my broccoli rabe wilted. Just the opposite was true. My produce has been fresh and all the frozen foods have been rock solid coming out of the refrigerated crates. Even the bananas that I requested to come green, ready to eat in three to four days, were as ordered.</p>
        <p>What I really like about the service is that it has forced me to really put some thought into planning meals and looking at what my family eats, a task every family could probably benefit from. When you have your weekly food items in black and white in front of you, rather than piled into a shopping carriage, it's harder to hide that there are more snack foods than fresh fruits in your diet.</p>
        <p>Here's how ShopLink works: When you sign up for the service online or by phone, an appointment is made for a customer service representative to come to your home. This person walks you through the entire shopping process -- how to navigate the ShopLink Web site, find coupons and sale items, place your order and then check out. This meeting took us about one hour as we decided on the best place for my delivery crates to be left each week, and she explained the additional services ShopLink offers, including film developing, can and bottle redemption, dry cleaning, shoe repair and a full menu of precooked meals that serve up to four people.</p>
        <p>I signed up as a ''Green'' service customer, which allows me to receive four food deliveries a month for $35 a month. (New customers get $25 off their first shopping order, plus the first two months of deliveries free.)</p>
        <p>Wednesday is my delivery day, and I need to get my order in by 2 p.m. Tuesday. Not too difficult a task, considering I can browse and shop anytime I want -- namely, after the kids are in bed and the house is quiet. There's no one to interrupt me as I poke through cabinets and the freezer to see what I have, and what I need.</p>
        <p>The ShopLink Web site has been broken down into categories to help people find things: bakery, produce, meats, canned goods, etc. A search box lets you find specific items fast, or tells you whether a specific brand is carried.</p>
        <p>And the prices? Well, some are higher than what I've seen in my  supermarket, some are lower. I can often buy a pint of fresh blueberries at my supermarket for $2.99 or $3.99. At ShopLink, they cost $4.99. A roll of Mardi Gras paper towels cost 69 cents; a bag of Dole salad cost $3.29; fresh-baked poppy bagels cost 59 cents each. There's no doubt you're paying for convenience. If big savings are what you want, you need to look at the other local Internet grocery giant, Priceline.com., which lets you bid on groceries to try to get the lowest price.</p>
        <p>I used Priceline for about four months, with a $3-a-month service charge, and saved money, especially on diapers and cereal. But it's time-consuming: You pick out items; bid on them; wait to see whether your bid was accepted; print a price confirmation sheet; take that sheet to a participating store, and find your items. It offers savings, but is a lot of work.</p>
        <p>My goal with ShopLink is to factor in the delivery charge and spend no more than I would on a trip to a traditional store. And so far, so good. On my first two orders, I spent about $20 less than I would have at the store; a feat I credit to the thought and planning involved in shopping like this.</p>
        <p>I'm not naive enough, or rich enough, to think that ShopLink will keep me out of grocery stores all together. I'll continue to buy diapers from wherever they're on sale; lunch box and snack foods from the Hostess and Entemann's thrift shops; and health and beauty items places like Kmart. And I'll still have to run out for milk, hamburgers, bread or other things we want or need. But it's wonderful to know that someone else will do the real work for me.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
