<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Canada Sees Violent Turn In the Fight On Abortion</title>
    <meta content="16CANA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000719T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215475"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Threats and Threatening Messages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Assaults</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Canada</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Canada</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brooke, James</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Pharmaceutical, Biotechnology and Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Assaults</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Threats and Threatening Messages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE5DD153BF935A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="694" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Canada Sees Violent Turn In the Fight On Abortion</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BROOKE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brooke, James</byline>
      <dateline>YELLOWKNIFE, Northwest Territories, July 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Canada, traditionally North America's liberal bastion in abortion war, is suddenly gripped by polarizing debate that has gone beyond ideology to an array of violent attacks and threats; in space of one week, right-wing politician with strong anti-abortion views is elected of Canada's main opposition party, Vancouver gynecologist who performs abortions is stabbed in back and death threat is telephoned to leader of national trials of abortion drug (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Canada, traditionally North America's liberal bastion in the abortion war, is suddenly gripped by a polarizing debate that has gone beyond ideology to an array of violent attacks and threats.</p>
        <p>In the space of one week, a right-wing politician with strong anti-abortion views was elected leader of Canada's main opposition party, a Vancouver gynecologist who performs abortions was stabbed in the back and a death threat was telephoned to the leader of national trials of an abortion drug. A man claiming to represent the ''Baby Liberation Army'' called a newspaper to claim  the stabbing and to warn other abortion doctors to ''watch their backs.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Canada, traditionally North America's liberal bastion in the abortion war, is suddenly gripped by a polarizing debate that has gone beyond ideology to an array of violent attacks and threats.</p>
        <p>In the space of one week, a right-wing politician with strong anti-abortion views was elected leader of Canada's main opposition party, a Vancouver gynecologist who performs abortions was stabbed in the back and a death threat was telephoned to the leader of national trials of an abortion drug. A man claiming to represent the ''Baby Liberation Army'' called a newspaper to claim  the stabbing and to warn other abortion doctors to ''watch their backs.''</p>
        <p>Only days earlier, Dr. Ellen Wiebe, the physician who leads the clinical trials of the French morning-after pill RU-486, was seen on national television, discussing tests of the drug that started recently on women in Vancouver and three other cities.</p>
        <p>Today, she has retreated behind a police guard, refusing all interviews. Her earlier television appearances prompted one anti-abortion group to strong verbal criticism of RU-486.</p>
        <p>Police say her public statements may also have spurred an anti-abortion activist to attack Dr. Garson Romalis as he entered his Vancouver clinic. The assailant, described as a clean-shaven white man in his 20's, escaped.</p>
        <p>Dr. Romalis, whose gynecological procedures include late-term abortions for women whose fetuses show signs of severe birth defects, was attacked once before, by a sniper outside his house in 1994. After that shooting, two other Canadian doctors who perform abortions were shot and wounded. The suspect in all three cases, an American anti-abortion activist named James Charles Kopp, is on the F.B.I.'s Ten Most Wanted List for the 1998 killing of a Buffalo, N.Y., doctor, Barnett Slepian.</p>
        <p>Two violent attacks on the same doctor is ''unprecedented,'' said Vicki Sapporta, executive director of the National Abortion Federation, which includes 350 abortion clinics in North America. Dr. Romalis is in stable condition and under police guard in a Vancouver hospital. In ''Nuremburg Files,'' an American anti-abortion Web site that lists North American doctors who perform abortions, the name of Dr. Romalis and several other doctors appear in gray, a code for ''wounded.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Henry Morgentaler, a gynecologist whose insistence on performing abortions led Canada's Supreme Court to legalize abortion fully in 1988, said last week that this violence has had a chilling effect on doctors. In Canada, abortion is not available in Prince Edward Island and access has been reduced in five provinces. Recently, he said, two doctors in Guelph, Ontario, a university city, stopped performing abortions.</p>
        <p>Last year, about 115,000 abortions were performed in Canada. One conservative commentator, Ted Byfield, wrote last month that Canada's Liberal government, instead of promoting the immigration of 200,000 people a year, should rejuvenate Canada's aging population by encouraging women to bring unwanted pregnancies to term and to place the babies up for adoption.</p>
        <p>Last week, anti-abortion forces won a political boost when the Canadian Alliance, the nation's largest opposition party, chose as its leader Stockwell Day, a former evangelical youth pastor. Mr. Day, who most recently was Alberta's provincial treasurer, has played down the abortion issue lately, suggesting it could be decided in an unusual national referendum.</p>
        <p>Some abortion-rights activists charge that Mr. Day's rise has given a green light to the violent fringe of Canada's anti-abortion movement.</p>
        <p>After the stabbing of Dr. Romalis, Mr. Day condemned the use of violence, saying: ''I've been very clear, very clear on this. How would you like me to spell it out? Denounce, condemn, outrageous, untenable.''</p>
        <p>Critics were unmoved.</p>
        <p>''We have Stockwell Day, an evangelical minister, a very religious-right person, signing up members from the anti-choice movement in Canada and spouting anti-choice, anti-abortion rhetoric,'' Marilyn Wilson, president of the Canadian Abortion Rights Action League, said from her office in Ottawa. '' Also, he has to take some responsibility for people taking action who share his beliefs.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Day's campaign manager, Jason Kenney, a member of Parliament for the Alliance, called the accusations ''really outrageous.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  July 19, 2000, Wednesday  Because of an editing error, an article in the Television section on Sunday about the TNT movie ''Nuremberg'' misstated the title held by Robert Jackson before his appointment to prosecute the war crimes trial. He was an associate justice of the Supreme Court, not chief justice.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: July 19, 2000, Wednesday</p>
        <p>Because of an editing error, an article in the Television section on Sunday about the TNT movie ''Nuremberg'' misstated the title held by Robert Jackson before his appointment to prosecute the war crimes trial. He was an associate justice of the Supreme Court, not chief justice.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
