<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Even if the Sermon Isn't Moving, the Church Is</title>
    <meta content="16MAP" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215133"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON THE MAP"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Protestant Churches</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">St Peter's-By-The-Sea Church (Cape May, Nj)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mather, John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Demasters, Karen</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E4DB1038F935A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="718" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Even if the Sermon Isn't Moving, the Church Is</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KAREN DeMASTERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Demasters, Karen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>John Mather, senior warden of St Peter's-by-the-Sea Episcopal church at Cape May Point, NJ, which has been moved four times, answers questions on church's history and its place in the community; photo (On the Map column) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>St. Peter's-by-the-Sea, a small gray church with white trim, sits at the southern tip of New Jersey where the Atlantic meets the Delaware Bay. The church is on a triangle of land just across the street from the beach. But that location is not the only place in Cape May Point where the church has stood. It has been moved four times to get it closer to the ocean and then to move it back from the waves that were threatening to wash it out to sea. John Mather, senior warden of the church, talked recently about the church's history and its place in the community.</p>
        <p>Q. What are the origins of St. Peter's-by-the-Sea?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>St. Peter's-by-the-Sea, a small gray church with white trim, sits at the southern tip of New Jersey where the Atlantic meets the Delaware Bay. The church is on a triangle of land just across the street from the beach. But that location is not the only place in Cape May Point where the church has stood. It has been moved four times to get it closer to the ocean and then to move it back from the waves that were threatening to wash it out to sea. John Mather, senior warden of the church, talked recently about the church's history and its place in the community.</p>
        <p>Q. What are the origins of St. Peter's-by-the-Sea?</p>
        <p>A. The building itself was built as a pavilion for the United States Centennial celebration in Philadelphia in 1876. At that time, the Episcopal Church in what had been known as Sea Grove was holding services in a hotel. The congregation bought what was described as a ''fine yellow pine frame'' building that had been at the centennial and it was moved here and made into a church. We're not quite sure how it was transported and we don't know what pavilion it was at the centennial, although we keep searching records to try to find that out. The parts of the church are bolted together -- sort of like the first prefab building. The exterior is original although the wood on the interior isn't and the steeple was added later. The first service was held July 25, 1880, and there have been services every year since.</p>
        <p>This was always a resort town and still is. But a railroad used to run down here. The church may have been transported in part by rail. A steamship also traveled from Pennsylvania and docked here to let off summer residents. The church may have come down the river and the bay by steamship.</p>
        <p>Q. Why was the church moved?</p>
        <p>A. It started out a few blocks inland, but within a matter of weeks they decided the location was too hot because it was cut off from the sea breezes. The congregation thought it would be cooler near the ocean so that a sea breeze could come through the big windows. It also has large sliding doors, called pocket doors, to allow the breeze in. So in July 1880 it was moved toward the beach. In the fall of 1881 it was moved again to another beach location because of the construction of a large cottage at the other site. But within a few years the ocean was encroaching on the land and threatening the church and other nearby buildings. So in 1903 the church was moved back to near where it started. The beachfront site is now three blocks out in the ocean, and the church is back to being near the beach. You could see the ocean from the pulpit before protective dunes were built.</p>
        <p>Q. What makes the church distinctive now?</p>
        <p>A. St. Peter's has services from May until mid-September. It is one of the few active churches that only has summer services. The church is the only building in Cape May Point that is on both the state and national historic registers. It is a small church that seats about 120. We have two services each Sunday. We get requests all winter long from people who want to have weddings here because of its location and history. We schedule a different priest to conduct the service each Sunday and the first Sunday in August we always have a Bishop from the Episcopal Diocese of New Jersey conduct the service. This is an Episcopal Church and we abide by Episcopal doctrines but we welcome people of all faiths. The first Saturday in August we have a big bazaar and the entire town turns out. Almost everyone in Cape May Point gets involved with the church, no matter what their denomination, and we like it that way.</p>
        <p>KAREN DeMASTERS</p>
        <p>ON THE MAP</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
