<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Crime Takes a Vacation (Yours); Moscow: A violent image is unfounded, but watch the traffic police</title>
    <meta content="MB012537" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215164"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Moscow (Russia)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gordon, Michael R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia/Moscow</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E6D81138F935A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="623" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Crime Takes a Vacation (Yours); Moscow: A violent image is unfounded, but watch the traffic police</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL R. GORDON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gordon, Michael R</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Michael R Gordon travel article holds depiction of Moscow as crime-ridden is unfounded but suggests keeping an eye on traffic police (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Most Americans seem to think that Moscow is the wild, wild East, a land of mafia shootouts, bombings and rampant crime. But while that may be the Moscow depicted in American films, it is not the city that my family and I have lived in for more than four years.</p>
        <p>Moscow is safer than New York and most other American cities. When Russians say they are taking a taxi, they plan to go out to the street, hail a car driven by a stranger and pay him 50 rubles (a little less than $2) for a ride home. Young women do this all the time and there are rarely incidents.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Most Americans seem to think that Moscow is the wild, wild East, a land of mafia shootouts, bombings and rampant crime. But while that may be the Moscow depicted in American films, it is not the city that my family and I have lived in for more than four years.</p>
        <p>Moscow is safer than New York and most other American cities. When Russians say they are taking a taxi, they plan to go out to the street, hail a car driven by a stranger and pay him 50 rubles (a little less than $2) for a ride home. Young women do this all the time and there are rarely incidents.</p>
        <p>The kind of random violence that seems to haunt the United States -- shootings by frustrated investors or alienated children -- is virtually unknown here. There are killings in Moscow, but most of them are very selective. Shootings are Russia's substitute for litigation. And if you do not have a business dispute involving large sums of money, you generally do not have to worry about being a target.</p>
        <p>Still, as in any large city (nearly 11 million people live here), there is crime and it is useful to take a few precautions. For one thing, you should watch out for pickpockets. They are not nearly as bad as in London or Rome, but they can slit open your backpack on the subway and take your purse or wallet before you know it. It is also good to carry some small bills, so that if you decide to give money to a panhandler or make a small purchase you do not have to whip out your entire wad of cash on the street.</p>
        <p>Be careful about the taxi drivers at the airport. Don't pay more than $50 for a ride to the center of town from the Sheremetyevo airport. And it is possible with only a little negotiating to pay considerably less.</p>
        <p>Another prudent measure is to avoid isolated streets or underground passageways late at night. The main thoroughfares in the city center, however, seem to be safe at all hours; Russians are night people, so the streets are populated until the early hours of the morning.</p>
        <p>Moscow is full of nightclubs and casinos. Many of them are not mafia hangouts but they can be on the wild side. So if you meet any of the clientele keep an eye on your drink and on your wallet.</p>
        <p>If you rent a car, you will soon learn that the traffic police are worse than the crooks. In a city where left turns are almost entirely outlawed, yellow caution lights seem to last a millisecond and gridlock is a natural state of affairs, it is easy to commit an unintended infraction.</p>
        <p>And the traffic police often stop drivers for no reason at all, demand to see their documents and manufacture some kind of offense. A small ''fee,'' say 50 or 100 rubles (about $1.80 to $3.60), is usually enough to resolve most situations. But driving while intoxicated is a serious offense and can cost you $100. The best advice is to be careful, stay sober and if stopped insist that you do not understand a word of Russian. Try saying, ''Ya nye ponedelnik.'' That usually frustrates the bribe-takers so much that they give up and let you go.</p>
        <p>MICHAEL R. GORDON is chief of the Moscow bureau of The Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">MICHAEL R. GORDON is chief of the Moscow bureau of The Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
