<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>What They Were Thinking About Race; All-of-a-Kind Family</title>
    <meta content="MB120347" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215101"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Korean-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Simmons, Alisa</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Simmons, Richard (NYC)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Simmons, Jackie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Simmons, Lisa</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine/Columns/What They Were Thinking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E0DF1038F935A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="491" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>What They Were Thinking About Race; All-of-a-Kind Family</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Catherine Saint Louis, Emily Nussbaum, Joshua Green, Reena Jana, Robert Mackey, Andy Young and Chris Mitchell.</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Photo of Alisa, Richard, Jackie and Lisa Simmons, children of black father and Korean mother (What They Were Thinking About Race)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Alisa Simmons, Richard Simmons, Jackie Simmons  and Lisa Simmons, on the New York City subway</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Alisa Simmons, Richard Simmons, Jackie Simmons  and Lisa Simmons, on the New York City subway</p>
        <p>Alisa Simmons (second from left): When people look at me, they tend to fill in the blank with what they're comfortable with and often assume I'm Asian. So I hear things and see things that maybe I wasn't supposed to see or hear. I know what it feels like to be black in America and I know what it feels like to be Asian. Sometimes I'll wear my hair in little knots and put on some ratty jeans. Then, people perceive me as black. I'll walk into a store and I'm followed. But if I walk into the same store with my hair straight, people are more than happy to give me service because they assume I'm Asian.</p>
        <p>Richard Simmons: My father was black to the core, so I consider myself black, too. But my mother's Korean, so people also see something in my face that's Asian. They'll come up to me on the street and ask me straight up if I'm Chinese. I usually just let it pass. It's not that I reject my Korean side, it just isn't a big part of my life. But I've been learning about Korea on my own lately. I know how to say some things. I was in a store this morning. This woman there started speaking a language that sounded to me like Korean. So, in Korean, I said, ''You're speaking Korean,'' and she looked at me like I was totally crazy. She must have been Chinese.</p>
        <p>Jackie Simmons (second from right): We were on our way to the Puerto Rican Day parade, where I ran into one of my students. She told everybody: ''I met Jackie's family and guess what? Her brother's black!'' To me, that epitomizes how we are seen as a family. How people look at you and define your identity for you, subtly, without even knowing it. I felt like it was a great experience, to watch as she realized that people aren't always what you think they are.</p>
        <p>Lisa Simmons (right): My father was stationed in Korea during the Vietnam War. That's where I was born. So I feel as if I have a right to claim both cultures equally. But my father wanted to raise black children. And as much as I wanted to identify with my Korean side, it was cut off to me growing up because my mother wanted to be American. It was easier to be a part of the black community; black people will accept you if you accept their culture. Being Asian is a little bit more amorphous. When you're living in a white-black world, Asian is not always in the mix in people's minds.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
