<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Ethics Policy: Mind-Set Over Matter</title>
    <meta content="16ETHI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215417"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE RIGHT THING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Seglin, Jeffrey L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/The Right Thing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E0D6173BF935A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="775" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Ethics Policy: Mind-Set Over Matter</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JEFFREY L. SEGLIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Seglin, Jeffrey L</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jeffrey L Seglin The Right Thing column reflects on recent survey that seemed to indicate high incidence of illegal or unethical conduct in the workplace, despite presence of ethics programs; notes survey results might be read as indicating greater awareness of ethical standards, thanks to presence of ethics programs; contends good ethics policy is accepted by workers and is enforced; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TO read the news release announcing the results of the first KPMG Organizational Integrity survey, you would think that the American workplace had plunged into a deep ethical malaise.</p>
        <p>''Employees are observing widespread illegal and unethical conduct in the workplace despite the presence of ethics programs,'' the release began. Five out of six respondents said their companies had such programs; three out of four said they had observed unethical or illegal conduct on the job in the past year. The clear implication is that the programs are failing, right?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TO read the news release announcing the results of the first KPMG Organizational Integrity survey, you would think that the American workplace had plunged into a deep ethical malaise.</p>
        <p>''Employees are observing widespread illegal and unethical conduct in the workplace despite the presence of ethics programs,'' the release began. Five out of six respondents said their companies had such programs; three out of four said they had observed unethical or illegal conduct on the job in the past year. The clear implication is that the programs are failing, right?</p>
        <p>Hold on. One could just as easily conclude the opposite -- that all those ethics programs have taught employees to recognize unethical behavior when they see it.</p>
        <p>''I hadn't quite looked at it that way,'' said Richard H. Girgenti, KPMG's national director of investigative and integrity management services. ''But yes, I would say that they may be more apt to know that what they're seeing is unethical as a result.''</p>
        <p>Either inference would be a stretch, really, because no data is offered about the relationship between ethics programs and unethical behavior in the workplace over time.  About all we know for certain from the KPMG survey and one released in June by the Ethics Resource Center, a nonprofit educational and consulting organization in Washington, is that ethics programs, effective or otherwise, are nearly everywhere.</p>
        <p>Nothing so clear can be said about the prevalence of misconduct. In the study by the resource center, only 31 percent of employees said they had observed misconduct over the past year. Whatever the reason for the discrepancy -- varied definitions, survey methods and sample characteristics could all be involved -- the gap is too large for me to take either figure as definitive.</p>
        <p>A cynic would say that such surveys, whatever the results, are just grist for a full-employment call for ethics-program consultants: ''Your ethics policies aren't working? You need us. Working all too well? You need us. Nobody in your industry has a program? You need us. Everyone else has a program? You need us.''</p>
        <p>Perhaps. But with some extrapolating and postulating, it is still possible to glean an insight or two about the relationship between ethics and a company's bottom line.</p>
        <p>In the KPMG survey, for example, 80 percent of employees who felt that management would uphold company ethical standards also believed that current customers would recommend the company to others. The figure falls by half among employees who thought management was not above giving the green light to a bit of impropriety. Watch what happens to recruiting word of mouth: 81 percent of employees who see their management as arrow-straight would recommend their company to potential recruits; only 21 percent with more, er, ethically flexible bosses would do so.</p>
        <p>''Quite frankly, there's a link between how your employees perceive the ethical climate in which they're working and a company's key performance measures for profitability,'' said Laura P. Hartman, an adviser for the resource center survey and a business ethics professor at DePaul University.</p>
        <p>More broadly, both surveys indicate that a written ethics policy, in itself, is not enough to change behavior. Without a commitment from management and a way for people to report ethical lapses without fear of retribution, such policies may do more harm than good.</p>
        <p>''A written policy without anything else is worse than not having a policy,'' Professor Hartman said. ''It really says, 'Here's certain values, but we're going to allow you to break those values or infringe upon those values.'</p>
        <p>''It's like parents who have very strict rules, but they enforce them based on whether they had a good day or not,'' she continued. ''For me, that's horrible. Not only does the kid never know if he's going to be disciplined or not, but he also doesn't learn what the real parameters are. In a company, that's very dangerous.''</p>
        <p>If you really want to know whether company ethics policies are working, survey statistics may be just a distraction. ''Ultimately, a successful program is not identified by whether misconduct is up or down or whatever,'' said Kenneth W. Johnson, a senior consultant at the Ethics Resource Center. ''It's more whether people look at it and say, 'Well, this is just the way we do things around here.' ''</p>
        <p>THE RIGHT THING Jeffrey L. Seglin teaches at Emerson College in Boston and is the author of ''The Good, the Bad, and Your Business'' (John Wiley &amp; Sons). His column on business ethics appears the third Sunday of each month. E-mail: righthng@nytimes.com.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Jeffrey L. Seglin teaches at Emerson College in Boston and is the author of ''The Good, the Bad, and Your Business'' (John Wiley &amp; Sons). His column on business ethics appears the third Sunday of each month. E-mail: righthng@nytimes.com.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
