<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Cell-Phone Company At Old-Economy Prices</title>
    <meta content="16AUDI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000723T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215406"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="INVESTING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cellular Telephones</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Audiovox Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leder, Michelle</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cellular Telephones</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE2D8173BF935A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="708" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Cell-Phone Company At Old-Economy Prices</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHELLE LEDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Leder, Michelle</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Audiovox, mobile phone handset provider, has been reporting stellar sales growth and has surpassed earnings expectations for three quarters, but its stock is down 32 percent for the year, while Standard &amp; Poor's Communications Equipment Index is up 10.7 percent; strong competition, falling profit margins and dependence on one customer for bulk of its sales are among factors holding back stock (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHAT should investors make of Audiovox, the mobile telephone handset provider that has been called the poor man's Qualcomm? Though Audiovox, based in Hauppauge, N.Y., has been reporting stellar sales growth and has surpassed earnings expectations for three quarters, the stock, having soared through March, is now down 32 percent this year, compared with a 10.7 percent climb in the Standard &amp; Poor's Communications Equipment index.</p>
        <p>The reasons include strong competition, falling profit margins and the company's dependence on a single customer for the bulk of its sales.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHAT should investors make of Audiovox, the mobile telephone handset provider that has been called the poor man's Qualcomm? Though Audiovox, based in Hauppauge, N.Y., has been reporting stellar sales growth and has surpassed earnings expectations for three quarters, the stock, having soared through March, is now down 32 percent this year, compared with a 10.7 percent climb in the Standard &amp; Poor's Communications Equipment index.</p>
        <p>The reasons include strong competition, falling profit margins and the company's dependence on a single customer for the bulk of its sales.</p>
        <p>Stacked next to Qualcomm, a much-better-known maker of cellular telephones (as well as chip sets) that became a Wall Street darling, Audiovox remains inexpensive, now trading at $31.375, about 17 times its estimated 2001 earnings of $1.89 a share. Qualcomm, meanwhile, is trading at 46 times 2001 estimates of $1.37 a share, even after falling by about two-thirds this year.</p>
        <p>But the two control similar pieces of the $48.4 billion North American  market for handsets. In 1999, Audiovox had 10 percent, while Qualcomm had 11.2 percent, according to Dataquest, a market tracker.</p>
        <p>As a result, some investors saw Audiovox as a bargain. ''It was a cheap way to play Qualcomm,'' said Jayne Stevlingson, a portfolio manager for the Oppenheimer Discovery fund. But she is now having doubts, and has sold 50,000 of her 300,000 Audiovox shares.</p>
        <p>Alan Alpers, a senior portfolio manager at Navellier Fund Management, has also pulled back, citing the stock's difficulty in breaking past the high $20's. ''Fundamentally, everything looks good, so it's kind of a mystery,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Before last year, Audiovox stock struggled to break $10, as the company was still best known for its decidedly unsexy car audio equipment. Car electronics now makes up only 20 percent of the business, with handsets accounting for the rest. By March 7 of this year, less than a month after it sold 3.1 million shares at $45 each in a secondary offering, the stock had reached a record of $72.50. Then, amid the selloff in technology stocks, Audiovox fell further and faster than most.</p>
        <p>The company's strongest defender is John J. Shalam, 67, the entrepreneur who turned his $15,000 investment 35 years ago into a company that reported $1.16 billion in sales last year, an 89 percent increase over 1998. ''We don't think the ride was justified to $72 because that's not realistic,'' Mr. Shalam, the chief executive, said recently, just after trying to shore up his support at a meeting for analysts and investors in Manhattan. ''But we believe that it deserves to trade at $40 to $50.''</p>
        <p>The five analysts who follow the stock, including four whose firms were involved in the secondary offering, recently raised their earnings expectations for Audiovox. All but one have strong buys on the stock.  ''Compared with its competitors who are trading at 47 times 2001 earnings, this company is clearly undervalued,'' said Michael Sheldon, chief market strategist for Spencer Clarke, an investment boutique in Manhattan that did not help underwrite the stock.</p>
        <p>The analysts' consensus is that Audiovox will earn $1.64 a share for the current fiscal year, which ends on Nov. 30, and $1.89 a share in 2001. But last month, the analysts lowered their 52-week price targets to $40 to $50 a share from as high as $70.</p>
        <p>MR. SHELDON, among others, says he remains concerned about the company's falling  margins. In 1998, Audiovox had gross margins, or profits before interest and taxes, of 14.4 percent. Last year, they fell to 11.6 percent; most analysts expect them to go below 10 percent this year as competitors cut prices.</p>
        <p>Another concern is that up to 80 percent of Audiovox's handset sales  are to one customer, Verizon Communications, the combined Bell Atlantic-GTE cellular service provider.  Mr. Shalam said that having so many orders in hand from Verizon helped the company avoid having  excess inventory. But Ms. Stevlingson worries that ''when you have one customer that controls 80 percent of your revenue, they're basically telling you what to price it at.''</p>
        <p>INVESTING  Correction:  July 23, 2000, Sunday  Because of an editing error, an article last Sunday about investing in Audiovox, the mobile telephone handset provider, misstated its closing stock price and price-to-earnings multiple for Friday, July 14. The stock closed at $20.625, not $31.375, and was trading at 10.9 times estimated 2001 earnings, not 17.</p>
        <p>Also because of an editing error, the article misstated the 2000 performance of the Standard &amp; Poor's Communications Equipment index through July 14. It was down, not up, 10.7 percent.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: July 23, 2000, Sunday</p>
        <p>Because of an editing error, an article last Sunday about investing in Audiovox, the mobile telephone handset provider, misstated its closing stock price and price-to-earnings multiple for Friday, July 14. The stock closed at $20.625, not $31.375, and was trading at 10.9 times estimated 2001 earnings, not 17.</p>
        <p>Also because of an editing error, the article misstated the 2000 performance of the Standard &amp; Poor's Communications Equipment index through July 14. It was down, not up, 10.7 percent.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
