<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Catholics, Festivities and Growing Pains</title>
    <meta content="16CATH" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215220"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Rockville Centre (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Roman Catholic Church</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mchugh, James T (Bishop)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcquiston, John T</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E0DA1E38F935A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1743" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Catholics, Festivities and Growing Pains</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN T. McQUISTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mcquiston, John T</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on challenges facing Catholic Archdiocese of Rockville Centre, Long Island, whose congregants number 1,404,361, a 4.8 percent increase in five years; Bishop James T McHugh, in interview following June 11 rally at Nassau Coliseum, comments on Catholic Church's yearlong Jubilee 2000 celebration and changes in Long Island's Catholic population; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BISHOP JAMES T. McHUGH describes it as a ''year of favor from God,'' and his Rockville Centre Diocese is an enthusiastic participant in Jubilee 2000, the Roman Catholic Church's global, yearlong celebration of the seminal event in Christianity.</p>
        <p>''The celebration reflects the strength of our Catholic identity and has provided us with a sense of who and what we are,'' said Bishop McHugh, who took over leadership of the diocese in January. ''As a result, people are taking a more active role in their parish and the church is growing.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BISHOP JAMES T. McHUGH describes it as a ''year of favor from God,'' and his Rockville Centre Diocese is an enthusiastic participant in Jubilee 2000, the Roman Catholic Church's global, yearlong celebration of the seminal event in Christianity.</p>
        <p>''The celebration reflects the strength of our Catholic identity and has provided us with a sense of who and what we are,'' said Bishop McHugh, who took over leadership of the diocese in January. ''As a result, people are taking a more active role in their parish and the church is growing.''</p>
        <p>According to its own statistics, there were 1,404,361 Catholics in the Rockville Centre Diocese last year, a 4.8 percent increase in five years.</p>
        <p>But the observance also highlights the challenges that the Nassau-Suffolk diocese and its 134 parishes, 428 priests and 1,433 nuns face as they enter a new millennium, including the search for a new generation of priests to serve a congregation that is not only growing but is also getting older and becoming more racially and ethnically diverse.</p>
        <p>As part of the jubilee, more than 10,000 Catholics from across the Island attended a rally on June 11 at the Nassau Coliseum. The event, marking the feast of the Pentecost, emphasized the diversity and richness of the cultures that, Bishop McHugh said, are breathing new life into the church. The Mass was celebrated in English and Spanish; songs were sung in both languages by four choirs, including a 400-member children's choir, a gospel choir and a Spanish choir.</p>
        <p>''This is wonderful and truly as God meant it to be,'' said Angelica Reynolds of Hicksville, a member of the cheering, singing throng. ''There are people of all colors and all nationalities here, singing and praying together.''</p>
        <p>In an interview afterward, Bishop McHugh said: ''The makeup of the population of Long Island and therefore the Catholic church is changing by leaps and bounds. And many of the newcomers, particularly the Hispanics, are fundamentally Catholic. We have to reach out to them and help them along. The Island's African-American community is also growing. We also have new members from Korea, Vietnam, Poland and other countries.''</p>
        <p>Another event at the Coliseum is planned for Oct. 7. ''This ecumenical rally and evening of prayer is an opportunity to say to secular society, which has claimed the millennium as its own, that here is a deeper and richer meaning to the year 2000,'' Bishop McHugh said.</p>
        <p>It has been a year of change for the diocese. Bishop John R. McGann, 75, who led it for more than 23 years, stepped down in January and was succeeded by Bishop McHugh.</p>
        <p>Although Bishop McHugh was told last summer that he has liver and gall-bladder cancer, he said that his cancer was in remission and that he did not expect his illness would limit him in his office. Despite his continuing treatments, he said, his ''energy level has been good and quite up to snuff.''</p>
        <p>Bishop McGann served during a period of unprecedented prosperity on Long Island, where Catholics are by far the largest religious group. His tenure coincided with rising opposition to church positions on such matters as bans on abortion and birth control.</p>
        <p>His projects included a merger of four Catholic hospitals in 1998 to form Catholic Health Services, which is now one of the largest nongovernment employers on Long Island, providing 1,700 hospital beds, nearly a quarter of the total, and jobs for more than 13,000 people.</p>
        <p>In 1999, Long Island's Catholic schools enrolled 3,248 students in kindergartens, 29,129 in primary and elementary schools, 11,216 in junior and senior high schools and 5,358 in colleges and universities.</p>
        <p>The number of people assisted by Catholic hospitals and other charitable and social institutions totaled 1,655,046 last year.</p>
        <p>Bishop McHugh, who was bishop of Camden, N.J., for 10 years before coming to Long Island, served as a staff member of the National Conference of Catholic Bishops in 1965, where he directed offices involved with family life, anti-abortion activities and family planning, and he is expected to remain a forceful advocate of the church's opposition to abortion and birth control.</p>
        <p>Among the many problems Bishop McHugh faces is a shortage of priests. Only one priest was ordained in the diocese last year, so he was more than pleased last month when he ordained two men at a ceremony at St. Agnes Cathedral in Rockville Centre.</p>
        <p>Like many of the clergy who serve in the Brooklyn and Rockville Centre dioceses, the two new priests, Glenn Kennedy and Vincent Schifano, completed their studies at Immaculate Conception Seminary in Huntington.</p>
        <p>For the last 12 years, classes at the seminary have included instruction in Spanish at least three times a week. In addition, students are assigned to the Spanish Institute at the Immaculate Conception Center in Douglaston, Queens. Some students also have the opportunity to travel to Latin America for independent language study.</p>
        <p>''The goal of the diocese is for every priest to be able to hear confession or celebrate Mass in Spanish,'' said Joanne Novarro, a spokeswoman for the diocese.</p>
        <p>Many priests are also conversant in other languages. While priests in 34 parishes hear confessions and celebrate Mass in Spanish, confessions are heard in French at 6 parishes, Italian is used for confession and Mass at 11 parishes and Polish at 7 parishes. Korean is used for Mass at Notre Dame Church in New Hyde Park and Lithuanian for confessions at St. Aloysius Church in Great Neck.</p>
        <p>Father Kennedy, a former real estate agent who once dreamed of becoming a New York City police officer, was born 38 years ago in Rockville Centre. He attended public schools in Deer Park and graduated from the State University of New York at Stony Brook, where he majored in criminal justice.</p>
        <p>''I was thinking about being a police officer,'' he said, ''but because of a sports injury in high school, where I broke an ear drum during playing lacrosse, I flunked the police medical exam. A friend of mine was in the real estate business, so for the next five years I sold real estate.''</p>
        <p>So what made him decide eight years ago to become a priest?</p>
        <p>''That's what everyone asks me,'' he said. ''All I can say is: God does that. He puts the bug in your ear and you either say yes or no.''</p>
        <p>The average age of the nearly 40 men now studying at the seminary is 32, compared to 25 several decades ago, when most priests came up through what was once considered a more traditional path straight from high school and college into the seminary.</p>
        <p>''Society has changed and the church reflects that change,'' Father Kennedy said. ''Many of the men who now enter the priesthood come at an older age after learning that there is more to life than the search for material goods.''</p>
        <p>''Donning the collar is not an easy task,'' he continued. ''When you walk into a crowd, some people smile and nod and say hello. Others turn away and ignore you while others just stare. Some laugh and make fun and say all kinds of things you would not believe.</p>
        <p>''They just don't understand why a person would want to serve the Lord. It's unfortunate, but I'm encouraged by that fact that more and more people are coming back to the church. Those who once as a child or teenager had a taste of the church are now saying to themselves, 'Maybe I should not have left.' ''</p>
        <p>While attending the seminary Father Kennedy spent a pastoral year -- during which seminarians live in a parish and learn firsthand the life of a priest -- at St. Dominic's in Oyster Bay. On June 28 he began his first assignment as a new priest, as assistant pastor at St. Rose of Lima in Massapequa.</p>
        <p>Father Schifano, 40, who was a teacher in Catholic schools for 11 years before deciding to become a priest, was born in Brooklyn. He earned a bachelor's degree in sociology from Queens College and a master's in education from Fordham University.</p>
        <p>''I think I always wanted to be a priest, even as a kid, and when the Pope visited the United States, I finally decided to go for it,'' Father Schifano said.</p>
        <p>Before entering Immaculate Conception Seminary, Father Schifano taught for five years at St. Edmund's School in Brooklyn and for six years at St. Pius X in Rosedale. He spent his pastoral year at St. Sylvester's in Medford.</p>
        <p>For his first assignment, also beginning June 28, he was named assistant pastor at Holy Family in Hicksville.</p>
        <p>But more typical on Long Island are elderly priests who have seen the changes that have swept through the diocese.</p>
        <p>''We do a lot of things now in each parish that we did not even think about 40 years ago,'' said Msgr. George P. Graham, 74, pastor at St. Bernard in Levittown, who entered Immaculate Conception Seminary in the late 1940's, was ordained in 1952 and was serving as a priest in Hewlett when the Rockville Centre Diocese was created by carving it out of the Brooklyn Diocese.</p>
        <p>''Our classes for religious instruction for children, which used to number between 100 and 200, now number 1,500,'' he said. ''And we've got a basketball program with 1,500 boys and girls.''</p>
        <p>With the population of his parish -- and all the Island -- generally getting older, Monsignor Graham said, the church is extending its outreach to the elderly.</p>
        <p>''We have many dedicated people visiting the sick and bringing them Holy Communion to their homes,'' he said. ''We also give them a lift to their doctor's office and help them do some grocery shopping. If there is a need, we are trying to answer the call.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
