<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Steak Pub Missing a Central Ingredient: Steak</title>
    <meta content="16BAR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215355"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: BENDING ELBOWS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bars</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Denny's Steak Pub (Nyc)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leduff, Charlie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bars</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CEFDC173BF935A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="597" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Steak Pub Missing a Central Ingredient: Steak</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLIE LEDUFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Leduff, Charlie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bending Elbows column on Denny's Steak Pub, only bar in Kensington section of Brooklyn, whose kitchen reopened on July 1 and which, despite its name, does not serve steak; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If you are dying for a good steak, and you are thinking about Denny's Steak Pub in Kensington, Brooklyn, you might as well come in a hearse.</p>
        <p>''We got your clams and scampi, scungilli, veal,'' Tom DeRosa says. ''My chili's good, but we don't got no steak.''</p>
        <p>Mr. DeRosa, 55, is the chef de cuisine, whose resume includes Joe's Bar on Avenue U in Gravesend and Vitale's on Avenue P.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If you are dying for a good steak, and you are thinking about Denny's Steak Pub in Kensington, Brooklyn, you might as well come in a hearse.</p>
        <p>''We got your clams and scampi, scungilli, veal,'' Tom DeRosa says. ''My chili's good, but we don't got no steak.''</p>
        <p>Mr. DeRosa, 55, is the chef de cuisine, whose resume includes Joe's Bar on Avenue U in Gravesend and Vitale's on Avenue P.</p>
        <p>''We ought to have steaks, though,  that's a fact,'' says Tommy, mulling it over as he smokes a battered cigar. ''The place is called a steak pub. We ought to have steaks.''</p>
        <p>Denny's, at Church and McDonald Avenues, is the only bar in Kensington. It is a boozy little grotto with soft lighting where a pint goes for two and a quarter. The bartender is quiet because the patrons here are put off by overassiduousness. The air-conditioning is kept low because it makes the old-timers cold.</p>
        <p>They used to serve beef, and the 26-ounce prime rib was known from Coney Island to Bensonhurst. But in 1992 the kitchen was closed.</p>
        <p>''The cook started drinking a lot,'' explains Rich Shoemaker, the barman. ''The food got pretty bad. And then the neighborhood changed.''</p>
        <p>Denny's grand reopening was July 1. On weekends they put cloths on the tables to lend an air of class to the place. But they forgot to put steaks back on the menu.</p>
        <p>Outside the window, 100 Bengali laborers mill about the street, eating seeds and spitting the shells on the sidewalk. All along McDonald Avenue there are Bengali hair salons, Bengali restaurants, Bengali clothing stores and, word has it, a Bengali nightclub open only on weekends.</p>
        <p>''Those people don't eat steak or pasta,'' says John Ryan, 45, a meaty man with ham fists and a long memory. ''They stick to their own and they don't buy anything from anyone but their own kind.''</p>
        <p>This is not a xenophobic rant, John Ryan wants people to know. It is simply the bald, naked truth, and if the truth offends, he says, then so be it, because it's left to people like him to teach the immigrants about being American.</p>
        <p>A mechanic by trade, he is something of an amateur cartographer. He will draw an ethnographic map of the neighborhood as quickly as some can draw directions to their homes.</p>
        <p>The Albanians and Italians on Dahill Road. The Bengalis on McDonald Avenue. The Chinese on East Second Street. The Italians and Irish have East Third Street. Ocean Parkway belongs to the Russian Jews.</p>
        <p>''The neighborhood went down when the kitchen went down, but it's starting to pick back up again,'' Mr. Ryan says.</p>
        <p>''You're getting the new type of immigrant now,'' he says. ''Europeans who want to mix, and the people from Park Slope who can't afford the prices anymore.''</p>
        <p>These people eat pasta, Mr. Ryan says. These people eat steak.</p>
        <p>But if anyone would bother to ask the Bengalis, it would become apparent that many of them like a good steak, too. There's just one problem.</p>
        <p>''Steak?'' A Bengali man on the street said with a laugh. ''They don't have steak in there.''</p>
        <p>CHARLIE LEDUFF</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: BENDING ELBOWS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
