<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Grocery List, Coupons; And, Now, the Internet; As More Markets Go Online, Checkout Begins Behind the Computer</title>
    <meta content="16SHOP$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215245"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coupons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Delivery Services</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Supermarkets</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Boynton, Cynthia Wolfe</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Supermarkets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Service Industries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E3D91F38F935A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1420" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Grocery List, Coupons; And, Now, the Internet; As More Markets Go Online, Checkout Begins Behind the Computer</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CYNTHIA WOLFE BOYNTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Boynton, Cynthia Wolfe</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article describes how grocery shopping in Connecticut has come full circle, thanks to the Internet; online ordering and delivery services have brought return of pre-World War II days, when people commonly telephoned in grocery orders and drivers delivered them; many stores offer online coupons that can be printed out for in-store use; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AS far as Stew Leonard Jr. and other food store owners are concerned, the Internet and its growing number of online home delivery services haven't revolutionized grocery shopping. They've brought it full circle.</p>
        <p>ShopLink.com, Peapod.com and Stop &amp; Shop's new Fairfield County online ordering and delivery service, among others, have brought the return of pre-World War II days, when people commonly telephoned in grocery orders to stores and then drivers delivered them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AS far as Stew Leonard Jr. and other food store owners are concerned, the Internet and its growing number of online home delivery services haven't revolutionized grocery shopping. They've brought it full circle.</p>
        <p>ShopLink.com, Peapod.com and Stop &amp; Shop's new Fairfield County online ordering and delivery service, among others, have brought the return of pre-World War II days, when people commonly telephoned in grocery orders to stores and then drivers delivered them.</p>
        <p>''I grew up riding around on my grandfather's milk trucks,'' said Mr. Leonard, chief executive of the Stew Leonard's stores in Norwalk and Danbury, ''and people loved that personal service.''</p>
        <p>The difference now is that people are using the Internet to buy their groceries.  This use of technology to return to the past is catching on with consumers to such a degree that more and more of the major supermarkets in the state have begun Web sites.</p>
        <p>ShopRite (www.shoprite.com), A.&amp;P. (www.aptea.com), Waldbaum's (www. waldbaums.com) and Stew Leonard's (www.stew-leonards.com) all have Web sites. Stop &amp; Shop launched an online delivery service (www.stopandshop.com) late last month. Many stores offer online coupons that can be printed out for in-store use. And it's not just the big stores that are going online. Independent grocers like Everybody's Food Market (www.foodtips.com/everybodys) in Cheshire and the Porricelli Food Mart stores (www.foodtips.com/porricellis) in Old Greenwich and Cos Cob, for example, have extensive Web sites.</p>
        <p>Then there are the Internet sites that aren't built around stores, like Stamford-based Priceline WebHouse Club (www.priceline.com). Its site allows people to bid on the price they want to pay for groceries, which they then get from existing supermarkets. There are also delivery services like ShopLink.com, Peapod.com and Ben &amp; Izzy's (www.benandizzys.com) of Norwalk, which specializes in organic produce.</p>
        <p>''We want to go retro and bring people back to the time when neighborhoods were visited by fruit and vegetable trucks,'' said Lee Chevron, who started Ben &amp; Izzy's in November 1998 and buys much of his products from Connecticut farms for the 1,000-plus customers he has here. ''We want people to look forward to our visits, and for everyone to have fun with it.''</p>
        <p>Deb Paduda of Madison, who has three children, said she buys most of her groceries from Priceline and saves as much as $15 to $20 each time she shops, which sometimes is as often as four times a week. Priceline customers pay for the items online with a credit card, then go to a participating store with a print-out of their order to pick them up.</p>
        <p>''I go through almost a gallon of milk a day and countless snacks and cereal boxes each week,'' said Ms. Paduda, one of about 50,000 registered users in the state. ''And when I save money on practical things like groceries, I feel better spending on fun things like vacations.''</p>
        <p>The potential for people to ease the stress in their life by buying from an online delivery service, or saving money by buying at a discount, can make online grocery shopping an exciting experience, said Brian Sansoni, a spokesman for the Grocery Manufacturers of America in Washington, D.C.</p>
        <p>But he said it's important for people to remember that the industry is still in experimental stages for both shoppers and sellers. ''Internet grocery shopping is in its infancy, and there are lot of kinks to be worked out, the biggest being which of these business can make a profit and survive,'' Mr. Sansoni said.</p>
        <p>Both online and traditional food stores have razor-thin profit margins and must sell huge volumes to turn profits, he explained. Start-up and delivery costs alone can be astronomical. So far, few online grocers have even come close to breaking even.</p>
        <p>Virginia Harte, associate editor of the Food Institute Report, a national publication that tracks food industry trends for the nonprofit Food Institute in Elmwood Park, N.J., said it's too soon to tell what long-term effects the Internet will have on the way people grocery shop.</p>
        <p>There's also no real accurate way to tell what kind of impact online  delivery and discount services are having on ''brick and mortar'' supermarkets, she said. No one is reporting lost profits or a declined customer base.</p>
        <p>That could be because actual online grocery sales are still small. Nationally, only $200 million was spent at online food markets in 1999, less than 1 percent of the $440 billion in total supermarket sales, according to Jupiter Communications, an Internet research firm in New York. And there's no clear picture of what 2000 will bring.</p>
        <p>According to Greenfield Online, a market research firm in Wilton, a lot of people are also leery about trying it. Of more than 1,708 Internet users the company recently surveyed, 31 percent said they had visited an online grocery site. Of those who had, only 12 percent made a purchase.</p>
        <p>About 62 percent said shipping or delivery charges made them not want to cybershop, while 46 percent said that they didn't like the idea of not being about to touch or see items they might want to purchase.</p>
        <p>Dolores Bova of Milford is also turned off by the fact that most Internet grocers require users to charge items to a credit card. Although she uses the Internet regularly to communicate with friends and family, buy stocks and research medical and travel information, she said online food shopping is out of the question.</p>
        <p>''Let's face it,'' she said. ''Interest charges can add up and at the end of the year wipe out any savings you might have had from bidding on groceries or buying specials,'' said Ms. Bova, 63. ''Besides, there's nothing like picking out your own pear or tomato. How would a company know whether I like my apples hard or over-ripe, my bananas soft or hard?''</p>
        <p>There are also privacy issues. While brick-and-mortar grocery stores have long logged shoppers' habits through the use of discount and loyalty cards, customers can choose whether to use those cards. Online shoppers have no such option. Everything they buy is logged and in most cases the information is easily accessible by manufacturers.</p>
        <p>ShopLink, which regionally delivers from a 83,000-square-foot warehouse in Stratford and has more than 3,100 area families on board, shares customer data with suppliers. But Jayne Fishkind, a psychiatric nurse of Guilford, isn't concerned.</p>
        <p>''Every time I use a credit card or a store card, I'm being tracked,'' said Ms. Fishkind, who said she uses ShopLink to save time. ''At least with ShopLink, I'm being tracked at my convenience.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Paduda's main gripe is with the limited number of brands available from some online sites and the amount of time it takes to search different categories to place an order, not to mention having to deal with slow modems and site glitches from time to time.</p>
        <p>But Joe Porricelli Sr., vice president of the Porricelli food stores, sees the Internet as an unavoidable part of his business. To ''compete with the big guys,'' namely Stop &amp; Shop and ShopLink, he offers Internet-only coupons that can be used in the store. He updates his Web site with weekly specials. He also became part of the Priceline network (the only independent store to date) in March. The stores have also had to learn how to adapt to Priceline. Like at other participating Priceline stores, the staff at Porricelli's has had to learn how to handle prepaid Priceline items. (They're rung up  separately.) Butchers and deli staff have also had to get used to that Priceline customers prepay for specific weights of meat and poultry, so special orders or requests from these customers may be common.</p>
        <p>Mr. Porricelli said that Priceline sales are triple what they were the first week there.</p>
        <p>''Although I have to admit that Internet grocery shopping makes me nervous,'' he added. ''There was a time when you had to worry about a new grocery store opening down the road. Now, you have to worry about the grocery stores that are available in people's homes.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
