<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Summer Storm Disrupts Air Travel and Events</title>
    <meta content="16RAIN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215494"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City Metropolitan Area</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blair, Jayson</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E2D9153BF935A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="560" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Summer Storm Disrupts Air Travel and Events</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAYSON BLAIR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Blair, Jayson</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York region's first major summer storm disrupts air travel, floods roads and some homes and breaks recent string of sunny weekends; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The New York region's first major summer storm churned off the Atlantic yesterday with a deluge that disrupted air travel, flooded roads and broke a recent string of clear and sunny weekend days.</p>
        <p>No serious injuries were reported, but flooding was reported in homes in Springfield Gardens, Queens, where drainage is notoriously bad.  For those who did not have to work or travel, it was a day to stay indoors; many of the day's outdoor events, scheduled for the sunny days of summer, were canceled.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The New York region's first major summer storm churned off the Atlantic yesterday with a deluge that disrupted air travel, flooded roads and broke a recent string of clear and sunny weekend days.</p>
        <p>No serious injuries were reported, but flooding was reported in homes in Springfield Gardens, Queens, where drainage is notoriously bad.  For those who did not have to work or travel, it was a day to stay indoors; many of the day's outdoor events, scheduled for the sunny days of summer, were canceled.</p>
        <p>Among them was the annual parading of the giglio, an 80-foot-tall obelisk-shaped tower that men carry through Williamsburg, Brooklyn, to begin the 12-day southern Italian festival honoring St. Paulinus. Don Mattingly's return to Yankee Stadium for his first Old-Timers' Game was called off, along with a game against the Florida Marlins.</p>
        <p>The rain arrived in thousands of patches the size of a Manhattan block across the region, said Scott Reynolds, a National Weather Service meteorologist in Brookhaven, N.Y.</p>
        <p>''We do need the rain, but we do not need this much,'' Mr. Reynolds said. ''We are not going to have widespread flooding problems; we are going to have local flood problems and underpasses that become flooded.''</p>
        <p>More than two inches of rain fell in Queens, the area hit the hardest, between midnight Friday and noon yesterday, Mr. Reynolds said.</p>
        <p>But the pace of rain slowed later in the day. By 6 p.m., 1.8 inches of rain had been reported in Central Park, with more than two-thirds arriving before noon. The high temperature was 68 degrees. Forecasters predicted patches of fog, but no rain, today and Monday. But they said thundershowers could return Tuesday.</p>
        <p>The weather service monitored several rivers in suburban New Jersey that were flooded last year. On the New Jersey coast, there were reports of minor flooding in Sea Bright.</p>
        <p>''Things seem like they are improving a bit,'' said John Quagliariello, a weather service meteorologist in Mount Holly, N.J. ''We have taken down the flash flood watch that was in effect. The heavier rains were in the north or the east. We are still expecting rain throughout the night, but it does not look like it is going to be enough for flooding.''</p>
        <p>At noon, as the worst patches of rain moved through the area, officials at Kennedy and La Guardia Airports reported delays of up to 45 minutes. Similar delays were reported at Newark International and other airports in the region.</p>
        <p>Not everyone let the rain get in the way. Every Saturday morning, the Hans Christian Andersen Storytelling Society holds readings beside the statue of its patron in Central Park. About a dozen people showed up yesterday to listen to selections from E. B. White's ''Stuart Little. ''The Yankees may cancel their game, the parks department may cancel events, but the Hans Christian Andersen Storytelling Society goes on rain or shine,'' said Diane Wolkstein, a member of the society.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
