<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Hero of the Latino Theater Returns to the Stage</title>
    <meta content="16JONE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215153"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Valdez, Luis</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jones, Chris</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Zoot Suit (Play)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Mummified Deer, The (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E1D81038F935A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2761" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Hero of the Latino Theater Returns to the Stage</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRIS JONES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jones, Chris</byline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Chris Jones profiles and interviews Latino theater playwright Luis Valdez, whose revival of Zoot Suit recently opened at Goodman Theater in Chicago, Ill; he comments on past successes and failures, peculiarities of Latino audiences, his unwillingness to compromise his politics and his first new play in 13 years, The Mummified Deer, which San Diego Repertory Theater will premiere this fall; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ON a winter's day in 1982, Luis Valdez was riding around Chicago in the middle of a blizzard. It was the opening weekend of ''Zoot Suit,'' the movie version of his 1978 musical play about the arrest, imprisonment and subsequent vindication of a group of young Chicanos in World War II Los Angeles: a project with which Mr. Valdez had a great deal of unfinished business.</p>
        <p>Despite a rapturous reception when it opened at the Mark Taper Forum in Los Angeles, ''Zoot Suit'' had gone up in flames on Broadway the following year. Closing after only 58 performances at the Winter Garden Theater, the first Latino play to appear on Broadway racked up losses in excess of $800,000. At the time, it was a substantial amount for the Shubert Organization, which had provided most of the capital.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ON a winter's day in 1982, Luis Valdez was riding around Chicago in the middle of a blizzard. It was the opening weekend of ''Zoot Suit,'' the movie version of his 1978 musical play about the arrest, imprisonment and subsequent vindication of a group of young Chicanos in World War II Los Angeles: a project with which Mr. Valdez had a great deal of unfinished business.</p>
        <p>Despite a rapturous reception when it opened at the Mark Taper Forum in Los Angeles, ''Zoot Suit'' had gone up in flames on Broadway the following year. Closing after only 58 performances at the Winter Garden Theater, the first Latino play to appear on Broadway racked up losses in excess of $800,000. At the time, it was a substantial amount for the Shubert Organization, which had provided most of the capital.</p>
        <p>Worse, the producers had become skittish about the financial viability of a national tour that would, it was thought, only have box-office appeal in the small number of American cities with substantial Latino populations. To the chagrin of an increasingly embittered Mr. Valdez, the tour never materialized.</p>
        <p>A movie version was next on the author's agenda. But studios balked at his insistence that he serve as director, because he had never made a film before. After numerous rejections, the best Mr. Valdez was able to muster from Universal Pictures was a small budget of $1.2 million and a production period of 13 days. To save time and money, he filmed on the stage of the Aquarius Theater on Sunset Boulevard, where the Taper production had enjoyed an extended run. The resulting movie, which included periodic shots of fake audience members in their seats, had a rough-hewn and peculiarly theatrical look.</p>
        <p>In 1982, with negative reviews trickling in from confused film critics, Mr. Valdez knew that the commercial prospects looked iffy. ''The Latino audience does not like to come out while it is still so cold,'' Mr. Valdez recalled last month, arguing that, in the early 1980's at least, Hollywood was woefully ignorant about the tastes of Latino-Americans. ''We were opening a movie in the middle of a blizzard. It was really, really crazy.''</p>
        <p>This time around, the writer and director has returned to Chicago in warmer weather in the hope of resuming a theatrical career that has been lying fallow. On June 26, his 60th birthday, he could be found seated with his family at the Frontera Grill, Chicago's most luxurious Mexican restaurant. The occasion was this summer's major revival of ''Zoot Suit,'' running through July 30 at the Goodman Theater here. The restaurant's chef, Rick Bayless, stopped by to shake Mr. Valdez's hand, while assorted speakers praised his role in the history of the American theater. And despite mixed reviews for ''Zoot Suit,'' Chicago audiences have been appreciative of the chance to see what some would call an American classic.</p>
        <p>The director, Henry Godinez, is a Goodman artistic associate and one of the leaders of Chicago's burgeoning Latino theater community. Mr. Godinez told the assembled guests at the restaurant that he regarded Mr. Valdez as the most significant figure to date in Latino-American theater. ''I stand as evidence that you can live your dreams and work with your heroes,'' the young director said with evident emotion. His eyes dancing with mischief, Mr. Valdez responded with the requisite fatherly grin.</p>
        <p>Actually, the American theater has not heard much from Mr. Valdez in some time. He has not written a new play for more than a decade. Aside from a single small production at the San Diego Repertory Theater two years ago, he had not allowed ''Zoot Suit'' to be produced in more than 20 years before the Goodman's endeavor.</p>
        <p>So what exactly has he been doing all this time?</p>
        <p>''Trying to make movies,'' said the still-handsome writer in a lengthy recent interview at the Goodman. ''Hollywood is a mean seductress, man.''</p>
        <p>The seduction has not led to an especially happy long-term relationship, and it took Mr. Valdez farther from his political and creative roots than he ever intended. In the 1960's and 70's, Mr. Valdez was a prolific writer and much venerated theatrical figure, especially among radical and Latino communities. The son of migrant workers who eventually settled in San Jose, Calif., he earned a degree in English on a scholarship at San Jose State College. In 1965 he joined the San Francisco Mime Troupe, where he was introduced to the political art of agit-prop. That same year, he joined the unionization efforts of Cesar Chavez and founded a touring farm workers' theater company known as El Teatro Campesino to support the strike of Filipino and Chicano migrants against the grape growers in Delano, Calif., the town of Mr. Valdez's birth.</p>
        <p>With both actors and audiences culled from the striking workers, the group specialized in what became known as actos, short dramatic sketches designed to spark political action. El Teatro Campesino, which won an Obie Award in 1968 for its work on tour, often performed on a flatbed truck. Its influences ranged from Bertolt Brecht, via the Living Newspapers of the Federal Theater Project, to popular Mexican comedians of the day.</p>
        <p>In 1970, Mr. Valdez and El Teatro Campesino purchased 40 acres of rural land in San Juan Bautista (now on the fringes of Silicon Valley) and began to work as a collective. Over time, the troupe expanded its political agenda from the farm workers' struggles and, through early works like ''Bernabe'' and ''Soldado Razo'' (''Buck Private''), both in 1970, and ''La Carpa de los Resquachis'' (''The Tent of the Underdogs'') in 1973, Mr. Valdez became the darling of leftist political-theater aficionados.</p>
        <p>By 1978, Gordon Davidson, the artistic director of the Mark Taper Forum, had been up to see Mr. Valdez's work in San Juan Bautista and decided it could have a wider audience. Mr. Valdez, too, had broadened his ambitions beyond community-based theater. This was partly a pragmatic issue. ''I was losing many colleagues because they simply had to go out and make a living,'' he said. But he also wanted to reach a broad popular audience and gain national attention for his art and causes.</p>
        <p>After hearing the broadcast of a radio essay about the Zoot Suit Riots in Los Angeles in 1943, Mr. Davidson asked Mr. Valdez to write a show about the event that sparked the unrest, the killing of a 21-year-old man, Jose Diaz, in what was known as the Sleepy Lagoon murder case. Mr. Valdez responded with a large-scale fictionalized piece, complete with music (by his brother Daniel), dancing and his trademark Brechtian sensibility -- actors directly addressing the audience and suggesting alternate endings for the play.</p>
        <p>The action of ''Zoot Suit'' revolves around the travails of Henry Reyna and other members of the 38th Street Gang of pachucos (a street term for adolescent Mexican-Americans). Following a police raid of a dance, where the rival Downey Gang causes trouble, Reyna and his friends find themselves arrested and charged with murder. Mr. Valdez depicts the sham trial propelled by wartime anti-Chicano fervor that lands the 38th Street boys in San Quentin. Events in the second act focus on the attempts of Anglo political activists to get the convictions overturned on appeal, even as gangs of sailors storm the Los Angeles barrios to strip young Latinos of their beloved zoot suits -- flamboyant outfits characterized by knee-length coats, shoulder pads and baggy trousers drawn in tightly at the ankle.</p>
        <p>''Zoot Suit'' is a distinctive blend of fact and agit-prop fiction. Twenty-four young Chicanos were indeed tried for the murder of Diaz. Twelve were convicted and sent to San Quentin (notwithstanding the absence of any eyewitnesses). A real-life activist named Alice Greenfield worked to overturn the convictions and became the model for the play's character of Alice Bloomfield. (The spunky Ms. Greenfield, now Mrs. McGrath, 83, attended the Goodman opening.) The court scene draws heavily from trial transcripts. But Mr. Valdez also departs from a purely factual approach.</p>
        <p>One of the play's most striking characters is El Pachuco (first portrayed by Edward James Olmos and performed at the Goodman by Marco Rodriguez, who was in the original 1978 ensemble), a zoot-suited narrator who both propels and comments upon the action. Reyna's alter ego and the heart of the play, El Pachuco is the playwright's far-from-subtle attempt to embody the complexities of rebellious teenage Chicano culture in a single semi-mystical individual.</p>
        <p>In 1979, the Taper gave the show a full production. ''It ignited the Latino audience,'' Mr. Davidson said. ''We had to find a way to keep it going.'' The Taper transferred the play to the Aquarius Theater, where it ran for nine months before audiences, Mr. Davidson said, that were predominantly Chicano.</p>
        <p>The subject of Broadway inevitably came up. Though he had been widely quoted in his youth as attacking the commercial theater (he once said that Broadway favored only ''limp, superficial productions''), Mr. Valdez was enthusiastic.</p>
        <p>''Luis wanted to be the first Hispanic playwright on Broadway,'' Mr. Davidson said. ''And he deserved the chance.'' But the transfer was a disaster. There are several theories as to why the success of the play in Los Angeles did not translate to New York. One was that New York's urban Puerto Rican community did not relate to the California Latinos, whose American experience was grounded in agricultural labor. Major newspapers, including The New York Times, did not give the play good reviews. And its agit-prop style befuddled the audience.</p>
        <p>''Broadway musicals didn't have that kind of reality,'' said Kenneth Brecher, executive director of the Sundance Institute, who was then Mr. Davidson's associate artistic director and line producer in New York. ''We had incredible singers, but they weren't Broadway singers.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Davidson said that New Yorkers could not then handle Latino characters behaving with swagger. ''When El Pachuco came out on stage and put his knife through the newspaper,'' Mr. Davidson said, describing the start of the play, ''you could see the audience lean back in their seats, as if he were going to attack them.''</p>
        <p>Two years ago, the seed for the current Chicago revival was planted when Robert Falls, the artistic director of the Goodman, found himself sharing a car to LaGuardia Airport in New York with Mr. Valdez after a meeting in Poughkeepsie, N.Y., of the Theater Communications Group, a service organization for nonprofit theaters. ''I didn't know much about its Broadway history but I was aware of the hand grenade it had launched in Los Angeles,'' Mr. Falls said. ''I told him that if ever there was a time for 'Zoot Suit,' we're living in it now. This is a glorious moment for Latino popular culture. This never felt to me like a play of its time. It feels like a play for now.''</p>
        <p>The temporarily captive Mr. Valdez, who normally likes to direct his own work, found himself listening to a lecture from Mr. Falls on the merits of Mr. Godinez. He was also reminded that a revival of ''Zoot Suit'' would be the first Latino play on the Goodman's mainstage. By the end of the ride, Mr. Valdez had agreed to a full-blown revision of the script that would update the play and incorporate elements of the movie.</p>
        <p>Mr. Valdez has been itching to get back to the theater. During his decade of Hollywood striving, he said, he had come to believe that he would have to compromise his political and aesthetic values if he were to enjoy access to the resources he craved. Although he had considerable popular success with his 1987 film ''La Bamba'' (the musical story of the life and death of the singer Ritchie Valens), it was not his most representative work. '' 'La Bamba,' 'La Bamba,' '' he said. ''Everyone knows me for 'La Bamba.' ''</p>
        <p>But one hit movie was not enough for Hollywood producers to green-light his less mainstream projects. ''It got me a lot of development deals and that was it,'' Mr. Valdez said. ''I've wasted a lot of years playing the casino game in Hollywood. Producers' offices are full of dead scripts with people's names on the side. I've learned my lesson.''</p>
        <p>Octavio Solis, a Latino playwright in residence at the Oregon Shakespeare Festival, believes that Mr. Valdez became frustrated in Hollywood. ''They never trusted his vision enough to let him go his way,'' Mr. Solis said. ''It's a problem familiar to most Latino writers. We often face a certain paternalism -- people telling us that we don't know the business the way they know the business.''</p>
        <p>Some of Mr. Valdez's projects did make it to television. In 1987, his screen adaptation of his stage play ''Corridos: Tales of Passion and Revolution'' was shown on PBS and won a Peabody Award. And in 1991, Cheech Marin and Linda Ronstadt were among the well-known performers working for scale because they believed in Mr. Valdez's PBS production of ''La Pastorela,'' a medieval Spanish miracle play. But the budget of $1.1 million was small and the piece found a bigger audience internationally than in America.</p>
        <p>Here again was the nut of Mr. Valdez's career problem: how to work with political meaning and still snag the money and resources to reach the broad audience for whom his work is designed. ''My problem was always that my projects were too esoteric,'' Mr. Valdez said. ''I was never much interested in writing for sitcoms.''</p>
        <p>His contradictions go deeper than that. He made his mark in worker theater but craves mainstream popularity. He insists on retaining an esoteric didacticism even as he tries to win at the Hollywood slots; the approach may explain why some critics have deemed his film work overly simplistic. Finally, he is too much of a spiritualist to be pigeonholed as a conventional socialist.</p>
        <p>''Luis is an extraordinarily talented writer with an enormous amount to say,'' Mr. Brecher allowed. ''But he always refused to polish. He also has a great grasp of what really matters in life. We always said he spent more time at the altar than at his agent's.''</p>
        <p>And thus, having gone full circle, he has come to worship at the theater. This fall, the San Diego Repertory Theater, where he is an artist in residence, will present the premiere of his first play in 13 years, provisionally titled ''The Mummified Deer.'' ''You might say it's another piece of American border history,'' Mr. Valdez said, waving off further details.</p>
        <p>Despite its revisions, the Chicago critics had faults to find with ''Zoot Suit.'' In The Chicago Tribune, Richard Christiansen described the piece as ''designed to get the juices flowing,'' but he also found ''dead spots'' and compared the work to a ''1930's social melodrama.'' In The Chicago Sun-Times, Hedy Weiss lamented the lack of a live band and complained that ''the characters are cardboard cutouts.'' There is perhaps a paradox in critics deeming Mr. Godinez's revival for the nonprofit Goodman to be overly respectful and too far removed from a musical on Broadway -- where it has already failed. But Mr. Valdez appears to accept the fact that his artistic vision will likely never find commercial favor.</p>
        <p>''Luis Valdez was a trailblazer under unusual conditions,'' said Mr. Solis, whose own play ''Santos &amp; Santos'' opens tomorrow in a production by the Imua Theater in New York. ''His influence is deep, profound and far reaching. His work has been a root source for all of us.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Godinez argues that plays by younger writers like Jose Rivera and Edwin Sanchez have broadened the market for Mr. Valdez's future works. ''The success of what some people like to call magical realism should now make it easier for people to appreciate Luis's kind of stylization,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Valdez is eager to find out the truth of that prediction. ''If you spend all your time chasing the Hollywood dream, you'll never write the plays,'' he said wistfully. ''In theater, I always got my stuff done, even if it meant doing it myself.''</p>
        <p>THEATER Chris Jones writes about touring and Midwestern theater for Variety.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Chris Jones writes about touring and Midwestern theater for Variety.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
