<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Jury's Action Raises Concerns for Tobacco Industry</title>
    <meta content="16TOBA$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215513"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Smoking and Tobacco</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Meier, Barry</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Smoking and Tobacco</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E5D7153BF935A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1180" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Jury's Action Raises Concerns for Tobacco Industry</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARRY MEIER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Meier, Barry</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Failure of tobacco industry's arguments in Miami case could haunt it in future lawsuits or spur it toward overall settlement; but even if cigarette makers succeed in getting award sharply reduced, as many experts expect, or thrown out, staggering size of damage figure stuns some legal experts and sounds alarm bells; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For more than a week, a six-member jury in a Miami courtroom heard the song of the new cigarette industry.</p>
        <p>One by one, the chief executives of Philip Morris, R. J. Reynolds and other major tobacco companies appeared before the jury to tell how they had turned over a new leaf. They had agreed to pay $246 billion to states to fight teenage smoking and help pay for the ills of injured smokers. Some executives told jurors of their efforts to develop less dangerous cigarettes. And, they said, the need to punish their companies with punitive damages was past.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For more than a week, a six-member jury in a Miami courtroom heard the song of the new cigarette industry.</p>
        <p>One by one, the chief executives of Philip Morris, R. J. Reynolds and other major tobacco companies appeared before the jury to tell how they had turned over a new leaf. They had agreed to pay $246 billion to states to fight teenage smoking and help pay for the ills of injured smokers. Some executives told jurors of their efforts to develop less dangerous cigarettes. And, they said, the need to punish their companies with punitive damages was past.</p>
        <p>The Miami jury, when it reached its verdict on Friday, seemed to respond as if it had not heard a word of the executives' testimony or, perhaps worse, as if the industry's arguments had infuriated the jurors more. After five hours of deliberations, they meted out a stunning $144.8 billion punitive award to members of a class-action lawsuit brought on behalf of all Florida residents made sick by smoking.</p>
        <p>The jury foreman confirmed those sentiments on Saturday. ''To minimize the deaths of so many people,'' exclaimed Leighton A. Finegan. ''We have seen the deaths of 400,000 people a year for 50 years. And they stand up in court and say that if we give a huge verdict it's a death warrant for the companies.''</p>
        <p>The failure of the tobacco industry's arguments in the Miami case could haunt it in future lawsuits or spur it toward an overall settlement. But even if cigarette makers succeed in getting the award sharply reduced, as many experts expect, or thrown out, the staggering size of the damage figure stunned some legal experts and sounded alarm bells.</p>
        <p>''I am perfectly willing to believe that the industry has done all the things that the jury believes it has done,'' said Peter Schuck, a Yale Law School professor who has testified as an expert witness for a cigarette maker. ''But as a constitutional matter, this is a terrible way to govern ourselves.''</p>
        <p>But others said the tobacco industry had only itself to blame for the verdict, given its decades-long fight against regulation.</p>
        <p>''This jury's verdict is probably a reflection of frustration at the failure of other branches of government to hold this industry accountable,'' said Matthew Myers, the president of the Campaign for Tobacco-Free Kids in Washington.</p>
        <p>The Miami jury's award is likely to be hotly debated by legal experts and others for months. But in many ways, its size also reflected the unique nature of the Florida case and how it proceeded.</p>
        <p>For one, a class-action case against the cigarette industry had never previously gone to trial. And the jury heard the case in segments. Last year, for example, it found that cigarette producers had conspired to mislead the public about the dangers of smoking. In April, based on that decision, it awarded a record $12.7 million in compensatory damages, or those intended to cover medical costs and pain, to three smokers chosen to represent the class.</p>
        <p>Those findings set the stage for the latest part of the trial in which the jury was asked to decide punitive damages, or those intended to punish a company for its conduct, on behalf of the entire class, a group estimated at 300,000 to 700,000 people.</p>
        <p>The potential for a huge damage award had not been lost on the cigarette makers. In May, they succeeded in getting a bill passed by the Florida Legislature limiting to $100 million the amount of money that a defendant had to post to appeal a verdict in a Florida state case. Previously, defendants had to post the entire amount of an award.</p>
        <p>The companies, along with state officials, had argued that posting a bond to cover huge punitive damages in the case could both bankrupt cigarette makers and jeopardize the $246 billion in payments they are paying states as a result of lawsuit settlements with the industry.</p>
        <p>Even with the potential for immediate financial disaster apparently averted, the stakes were still high as the punitive damages phase of the trial unfolded. And as it did, tobacco producers rolled out an argument against punitive damages that they had been refining over the past year.</p>
        <p>Simply put, it was that the industry had repented. Not only is it paying the states billions, it no longer sends its top executives to Congress to argue that smoking is not addictive and does not cause cancer. It is open. It is honest. It is different. The message did not play with the jurors.</p>
        <p>''I don't know why they ignored,'' the industry's arguments, said Gregory Little, associate general counsel for Philip Morris, ''but I do know they ignored it and I think that it is inappropriate.''</p>
        <p>Clark Freshman, an associate professor at the University of Miami Law School, said he believed that cigarette producers might have undercut themselves when they testified that they could not afford to pay substantial damages.</p>
        <p>''That probably made the jury disregard all their arguments,'' Mr. Freshman said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Finegan, the jury foreman, agreed. ''I felt a great sense of relief that what we did was right and justified, according to the evidence presented,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Robert Rabin, a law professor at Stanford University, also said he believed the jury turned a deaf ear to the industry, a sign that could spell trouble for the industry as it faces punitive damages in other cases.</p>
        <p>''They shifted course and it didn't help them,'' Mr. Rabin said.</p>
        <p>Tobacco industry lawyers like Mr. Little of Philip Morris said they believed the structure of the trial was so unfair and the jury's verdict so absurd that the entire case will be thrown out on appeal.</p>
        <p>And while other class-action lawsuits are looming, Mr. Little said he believed that they would never get to trial because class-action lawsuits are a flawed legal vehicle for resolving smokers' claims.</p>
        <p>For their part, antismoking advocates offered differing views. While some expressed concern that the cigarette industry could use the size of the award to cast itself in the role of legal whipping boy, others, like Dr. David Kessler, the former head of the federal Food and Drug Administration, saw it differently.</p>
        <p>Dr. Kessler, now the dean of Yale Medical School, said that no matter what spin the industry or antismoking advocates put on the award, the message of the jury was clear.</p>
        <p>''The jury award is less important for the money or whether any group of smokers will see any of the damages,'' Dr. Kessler said, ''than it is for the future of the industry.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
