<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Word for Word/ Al Gore's Senior Thesis; Even in College, the Vice President Was No Boob About the Tube</title>
    <meta content="16WORD$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Washington; Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215416"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Harvard University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marks, Peter</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E2D6173BF935A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1314" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Word for Word/ Al Gore's Senior Thesis; Even in College, the Vice President Was No Boob About the Tube</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER MARKS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Marks, Peter</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Word for Word column excerpts Vice Pres Gore's 1969 Harvard senior thesis, The Impact of Televion on the Conduct of the Presidency, 1947-1969; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AH, the lessons learned in youth. About love, faith, family and yes, the power of television to define the modern presidency. This last issue weighed especially heavily on at least one young person, Albert Gore Jr., as revealed in the topic he chose for his senior thesis for the history department at Harvard in 1969. Its title: ''The Impact of Television on the Conduct of the Presidency, 1947-1969.''</p>
        <p>The 84-page paper sheds light on an aspect of political life that would preoccupy Mr. Gore in his career in public office and into the current presidential campaign. Often perceived by voters as stiff and overrehearsed, the vice president has sought advice from image-makers conventional (the media consultant Carter Eskew) and not so (the feminist author Naomi Wolf) for ways to improve his image before the cameras.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AH, the lessons learned in youth. About love, faith, family and yes, the power of television to define the modern presidency. This last issue weighed especially heavily on at least one young person, Albert Gore Jr., as revealed in the topic he chose for his senior thesis for the history department at Harvard in 1969. Its title: ''The Impact of Television on the Conduct of the Presidency, 1947-1969.''</p>
        <p>The 84-page paper sheds light on an aspect of political life that would preoccupy Mr. Gore in his career in public office and into the current presidential campaign. Often perceived by voters as stiff and overrehearsed, the vice president has sought advice from image-makers conventional (the media consultant Carter Eskew) and not so (the feminist author Naomi Wolf) for ways to improve his image before the cameras.</p>
        <p>The fact that he was a senator's son probably didn't hurt the research process: those who granted him interviews included Arthur Schlesinger Jr., who served as special assistant to President John F. Kennedy; Bill Moyers, a former press secretary to President Lyndon B. Johnson and James Reston, a columnist and senior executive at The New York Times.</p>
        <p>PETER MARKS</p>
        <p>Shades of earth-tone suits: every president since Harry Truman, Mr. Gore writes, has had to adjust his image to the demands of the television screen, even those with a special distaste for the process, like Dwight D. Eisenhower:</p>
        <p>He was even persuaded against his will to change to a different style of glasses so that he would come across better, and before long he was using the TelePrompTer to be what he hated most -- artificially sincere.</p>
        <p>For Mr. Gore, John F. Kennedy was the closest thing to a political TV star:</p>
        <p>A large part of the credit for Kennedy's success on television was due to his personality. Not everything can be explained in terms of formats and camera work; there is no objective proof but it is generally agreed that President Kennedy was simply better on television than most. He was equipped with an understanding of the medium and its exigencies, and he knew how to use the visual rhetoric.</p>
        <p>If Kennedy had the small-screen wattage of George Clooney, his successor, Lyndon B. Johnson, was more akin to Drew Carey.</p>
        <p>President Johnson, according to Bill Moyers, often rehearsed TV appearances and watched them on videotape, and after one such tape had run for two minutes, ''the president jumped out of his seat, turned off the monitor and exclaimed, 'God damn, even I can't stand that.' '' He often said, ''I was born with these ears, these eyes, this nose, this drawl; what can I do about it?''</p>
        <p>Even if he couldn't fix the ears, Mr. Gore observes, President Johnson was determined to influence the filming of them.</p>
        <p>Johnson tried to control as many of the mechanics of the broadcasts as he could. He began by advising television cameramen that his best side is his left and he prefers to be photographed on that side at angles of no less than 45 degrees. Stewart Alsop [a journalist] commented that ''anybody but Johnson would have known in advance that the photographers would vie with each other to get pictures on his right side, preferably in the act of stroking his long nose or pulling his ear.</p>
        <p>Mr. Johnson's efforts to bend television news to his will clearly fascinated Mr. Gore. The president's failure to grasp the subtleties of the task is a recurring theme of the paper, as Mr. Gore illustrates in an anecdote about Mr. Johnson's building of a television studio in the basement of the White House.</p>
        <p>Once this studio was set up, it presented irresistible possibilities to Johnson. He began to use it ''at any moment,'' not only for major speeches but for all manner of minor announcements. Many of his appearances didn't even carry a bulletin slug on the wire service reports. This practice had unfortunate consequences: it overexposed the president, it produced friction with the networks and it conflicted with the established expectations of the viewing audience.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore also analyzes the decision by Richard M. Nixon, who had taken office just two months before Mr. Gore submitted his thesis, to forgo giving a State of the Union address just after his inauguration.</p>
        <p>Nixon may be quite correct and quite sophisticated. The State of the Union address is not good television; it draws a large audience because it pre-empts all three networks, but it is a dull show.</p>
        <p>Of the changes wrought by the televised news conference, he writes:</p>
        <p>Before the advent of television, the president was much less guarded in his statements. He had the prerogative of giving background and going off the record completely. If he made a mistake, he could correct it before it got into print; and if a mistake was printed, it was still attributed to a ''White House spokesman,'' or some such euphemism. . . .</p>
        <p>Because there is no longer a margin for error, the president is forced to view the conference much more seriously, and to prepare himself more adequately. Luckily, it is easy to anticipate questions . . . But in order to do so, the president must prepare for 10 times as many questions as are asked.</p>
        <p>Which leads Mr. Gore to this observation:</p>
        <p>The result of this for the president is that he is able to get away with pre-polished answers lacking any depth. It has stripped the press conference of any value it might have once had for putting the president on the spot and probing his thoughts. He now tells the press only what he wants to.</p>
        <p>By 1964, Mr. Gore notes, the televised news conference had become a critical part of the modern presidency (even though some later presidents -- notably Bill Clinton -- would hold them infrequently).</p>
        <p>As a result of Kennedy's proven success, the public and even the press corps had come to expect the television conference. Whether or not Johnson was ''bad'' on television or whether or not he wanted to hold his press conferences was essentially irrelevant. It was, as his predecessor called it, ''one of the tests of the president.'' Many of Johnson's troubles with the press are directly attributable to the fact that he failed this test.</p>
        <p>Mr. Johnson's solution? Intimations of John McCain, and a strategy that Mr. Gore, who actively limits his availability to the media, seems to have taken pains to avoid:</p>
        <p>He threw open his appointment schedule to practically any reporter who wanted to see him and as a result spent many hours each day trying to mollify the increasing criticism.</p>
        <p>In a subsequent chapter, Mr. Gore details his thoughts on why television has become so central to governing:</p>
        <p>Only television effectively stimulates interpersonal contact. Radio came very close; it conveyed an impression of ''personality,'' and increased the importance of the listener's emotional responses, but only one sense was stimulated, and the most important factor in interpersonal contact -- visual recognition -- was still missing.</p>
        <p>And, of course, he warns of the pitfalls of overexposure, a problem he sees through a literary filter:</p>
        <p>In the days when leaders maintained contact with the people through personal contact, it is highly probable that overexposure was a significant factor in effective leadership.</p>
        <p>In Shakespeare's ''Henry IV, Part 1'' Henry speaks of Richard II's leadership: ''Being daily swallowed by men's eyes, they surfeited with honey and began to loathe the taste of sweetness, whereof a little more than a little is by much too much.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
