<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Way We Live Now: 7-16-00: Round Table; Writing About Race (And Trying to Talk About It)</title>
    <meta content="WLN100607" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215093"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Times</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Winerip, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Roberts, Sam</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Boyd, Gerald</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Canedy, Dana</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Behr, Soma Golden</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holmes, Steven A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ojito, Mirta</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Scott, Janny</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Thompson, Ginger</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04EFD61338F935A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="4649" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Way We Live Now: 7-16-00: Round Table; Writing About Race (And Trying to Talk About It)</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Sam Roberts</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Roberts, Sam</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Eight New York Times editors and reporters, black and white, discuss how their own attitudes about race were affected by working on paper's How Race Is Lived in America project; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Times Magazine asked eight New York Times editors and reporters to talk about working on the paper's ''How Race Is Lived in America'' project. Specifically, we wanted to know how their own attitudes about race were affected by the experience. The conversation, held at The Times on June 19, was moderated by Sam Roberts, a Times editor and host of ''New York Close-Up'' on NY 1. The panel consisted of two editors, Gerald Boyd and Soma Golden Behr, and six reporters: Steven Holmes (whose article dealt with race relations in the Army), Dana Canedy (race at a newspaper), Ginger Thompson (a former plantation), Janny Scott (the making of an HBO movie), Mirta Ojito (two Cuban friends now living in Miami) and Michael Winerip (New York City police officers). Holmes, Canedy and Winerip also acted as editors on the project.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Times Magazine asked eight New York Times editors and reporters to talk about working on the paper's ''How Race Is Lived in America'' project. Specifically, we wanted to know how their own attitudes about race were affected by the experience. The conversation, held at The Times on June 19, was moderated by Sam Roberts, a Times editor and host of ''New York Close-Up'' on NY 1. The panel consisted of two editors, Gerald Boyd and Soma Golden Behr, and six reporters: Steven Holmes (whose article dealt with race relations in the Army), Dana Canedy (race at a newspaper), Ginger Thompson (a former plantation), Janny Scott (the making of an HBO movie), Mirta Ojito (two Cuban friends now living in Miami) and Michael Winerip (New York City police officers). Holmes, Canedy and Winerip also acted as editors on the project.</p>
        <p>The following are excerpts from the conversation.</p>
        <p>Roberts: Why is race a more sensitive subject than sex or sexual orientation or ethnicity?</p>
        <p>Holmes: Labels get affixed to people for saying ''the wrong thing.'' It may be unfair but it's true. If a guy says something about women he can jokingly say, ''Well, I'm just a chauvinist, I'm just a chauvinist pig,'' and make a joke out of it. I don't think you run across anybody who would jokingly refer to himself as a racist. It's such a radioactive subject because these labels are so explosive. I mean, you know -- bigot, Uncle Tom, sell out -- you name it.</p>
        <p>Roberts: A number of the people who worked on this series, particularly some of the white reporters and editors, said that they felt a certain inadequacy in dealing with race.</p>
        <p>Boyd: The dirty little secret is that a lot of the black reporters and editors felt inadequate as well.</p>
        <p>Canedy: Plus, ordinarily if you feel inadequate about a story, within two days of reporting you no longer do. It's not the same with race. With race, you can report month after month after month and come to no final conclusion. I can do a business story or a science story or a legal story and figure out right from wrong, up from down. With a race story it's tougher because there are no absolute rights and wrongs.</p>
        <p>Scott: What was different for me was that these stories called for a degree of nakedness that you don't normally experience as a reporter -- it started at the very beginning, when we met all day at Soma's house and we were asked to reveal ourselves in a way that's not normally asked of us. And to reveal ourselves on this incredibly rocky terrain.</p>
        <p>Thompson: Most times when we go into stories, even stories about race, we are able to identify good guy/bad guy, good agency/bad agency. With these stories, there wasn't a conclusion. There wasn't an ''aha moment.''</p>
        <p>Canedy: Or a villain or a hero.</p>
        <p>The Difficulty of Talking About Race</p>
        <p>Ojito: I was having lunch, as I often did, with the black subject in my story, Joel, and I was trying to understand exactly what it was that he felt about white Cuban-Americans. And he said, ''I just wish they were all like you [Ojito is a white Cuban-American], that they could be here having lunch with me normally, like you are.'' That was very nice, but I immediately thought, I'm here having lunch with you because I'm writing about you. The truth is that living in Miami I probably would have never met Joel. But after I met him, I liked him.</p>
        <p>Boyd: But that sounds like what people would say about race 30 years ago. That -</p>
        <p>Roberts: What do you mean?</p>
        <p>Boyd: That whites would say, ''Boy, I don't know any blacks.'' But then if they really met a black for some reason, they would say, ''Hey, that black is pretty nice, you know.'' ''One of my best friends is a black boy.'' ''John Doe is a nice black. He is a good man.'' And ''If only -- I didn't know that because I'd never come in contact with him.''</p>
        <p>Thompson: My landlord said that to me just two weeks ago. So don't think. . . . It's not just 30 years ago.</p>
        <p>Boyd: But the difference today is that any well-meaning white or any well-meaning black who wants to be involved, exposed, who wants to deal with somebody of the other race has opportunities.</p>
        <p>Ojito: But I wasn't really referring to the fact that he was black. It's the fact that his world is so different from mine. It's differences in socioeconomic status more than anything else. I mean we wouldn't have met. I wouldn't go to Liberty City normally. That's not where my friends live in Miami. So our worlds would not have come together.</p>
        <p>Scott: These reporting experiences are not like real life. Because in these situations you have the license -- because of what you're doing -- to go like some superconducting supercollider immediately to the heart of the matter. And all of a sudden you can ask the kinds of questions that you would never normally be able to ask. There's this instant intimacy about it. That to me was the most exhilarating thing. You could ask all these taboo questions.</p>
        <p>Holmes: It was exhilarating to try and get people to talk about it. And it makes you wonder, or yearn -- doesn't it make you wonder why more people don't? It makes me yearn for more people to be able to do this.</p>
        <p>Boyd: I don't know why it takes a yearlong New York Times project on how race is lived in America to get a white reporter or a black reporter to have serious conversations with a person of the other race about race.</p>
        <p>Canedy: Well, one of the things our series showed us is that people still live in very segregated worlds.</p>
        <p>Golden Behr: But why don't we even talk to the people at work? What about just turning to the person near you who's of a different race and saying: ''Why are you reacting that way? Why are you so angry?''</p>
        <p>Holmes: Soma, I think you're being nave. I think most of the time when people allow themselves to do that the person either calls them a racist or something else or withdraws.</p>
        <p>Golden Behr: You have to be willing to slip up every once in a while.</p>
        <p>Boyd: I don't understand why it is such an overpowering, difficult, awkward, impossible situation. That day in and day out whites will go home and talk about situations that they disagree with or don't understand but can't confront blacks about. And blacks will go home and basically have the same conversation with their loved ones. I don't understand what it is about race that makes this so -- I mean, I understand people want to be P.C., I understand people don't want to be misconstrued. I understand all those things. But I don't understand what it is about race that makes people unwilling to try, especially given what has gone on in this country over the last 10 years or 15 years.</p>
        <p>Roberts: Has anyone found the answer in the past year?</p>
        <p>Golden Behr: Well, Steve offered an answer. That you get labeled fast. You've got to be careful or somebody will take it wrong. And you have to know somebody pretty well before you take that risk.</p>
        <p>Whose Issue Is It?</p>
        <p>Holmes: For better or worse, race is seen as a black thing. Mike, did you find that there was a sense among the white cops that you were dealing with a black subject here?</p>
        <p>Winerip: Yeah, I think the cops, the black cops and the dark-skinned cops, the Latino cops were much more comfortable talking about race than the white cops. The white cops kept feeling that they would be misconstrued, taken out of context. That they were going to sound as if they belonged on the Abner Louima case or the Diallo case.</p>
        <p>Boyd: But there's talking and there's talking. I mean, I think if you played back our conversation here today you'd probably find that blacks, myself included, have been doing the most talking. I don't think we've been saying anything, frankly. And I think that's often the case, myself included. I think, Sure, you can get blacks to talk about race because it is certainly our world and we live in it and we see it constantly every day. But to what degree do we really allow blacks to say what is truly on their minds, what race does to them, what race means to them, how race makes it impossible for them or how race drives them crazy one way or another. Blacks don't have that conversation. That's not the conversation.</p>
        <p>Roberts: With whites.</p>
        <p>Boyd: With whites. And many of them don't have it with other blacks.</p>
        <p>Holmes: Oh, I think we do.</p>
        <p>Ojito: Isn't part of the problem that whites don't have many black people to have that conversation with? Soma asked why we don't have this conversation in the newsroom. Turn around and talk to your colleague. Well, I don't have a lot of black people to do that with in the newsroom. I have no idea what it was like 15 years ago.</p>
        <p>Boyd: Well, we've got a few more.</p>
        <p>Ojito: But you know what I'm saying. You have to go out of your way to have that conversation.</p>
        <p>Race or Something Else?</p>
        <p>Roberts: Mike, you've said that you and Gerald disagreed about the hip-hop piece. How much of that was race and how much of it was Gerald's own perspective or lack of interest or sense of humor or whatever?</p>
        <p>Boyd: I'm very interested in hip-hop.</p>
        <p>Winerip: Gerald is very interested in hip-hop. It's just that he didn't know it was funny. That's what we argued about.</p>
        <p>Roberts: O.K., but in arguing about that with a black editor, how did that affect the argument?</p>
        <p>Winerip: Sonny Kleinfield [another reporter on the series] had this white hip-hop character who was essentially, I thought, hilarious. One of the phenomena of hip-hop is that white young people sort of adopt this black urban culture. And this guy was that to the ten-thousandth degree. He was so extreme, he was a cartoon.</p>
        <p>I found it funny but Gerald kept saying, ''I don't get this guy.'' It was one of the few times when we were doing this that I really felt as if race might be in the room. Gerald and I screamed at each other the whole series. But a lot of it was about how you do narrative journalism: Is this story too edgy? Is this story mainstream enough? But this was a moment when I felt, I trust my sense of humor. I think it's funny. He doesn't think it's funny. Is it that he doesn't have a sense of humor? Is it that he's black and I'm white?</p>
        <p>Roberts: Gerald, did you see race in that conversation?</p>
        <p>Boyd: To be honest, no. I thought it was his lack of judgment, faulty judgment. But I think the larger issue, which hip-hop certainly represented, was, to what degree is race funny? You're dealing with an issue that has enormous economic, social and even political costs to younger blacks and middle-aged blacks, as well as younger whites. And you're trying to explain it to an audience that is not so young, to make sense out of it. Is it funny? I don't think it is.</p>
        <p>Holmes: What happens when race is involved is that there's always this thought in the back of your mind, as there was in this case. How much does it have to do with taste? And how much does it have to do with race?</p>
        <p>Scott: We have no facility for addressing the subject. We have the facility to say, ''You're from St. Louis. I know it's why you have this St. Louis bias.'' But we're just not comfortable with saying, ''Along with the fact that you're from St. Louis and you're a girl, you're also black.''</p>
        <p>Holmes: Right. I think comfort is the operative word.</p>
        <p>Scott: Getting back to this question of why it's so hard to actually have these conversations, we're just out of practice. Or we've never been in practice. Everybody backs off. I hope in the future I will be less inclined to back off.</p>
        <p>Roberts: Would the stories themselves have come out different if they were written by a white reporter instead of a black, or a black instead of a white?</p>
        <p>Thompson: I certainly think that there would have been different things considered if Mike had written my story.</p>
        <p>Winerip: But if you had 10 white males all doing Ginger's story at The New York Times, you would have had 10 different stories.</p>
        <p>Canedy: Or if you had 10 black reporters, you know, or if Ginger had done my story or if Mike had done my story, the same dynamics would have played out. I mean it has to do with class issues, socioeconomic backgrounds, all those things.</p>
        <p>Thompson: But that doesn't mean race isn't an issue.</p>
        <p>Roberts: So race is one prism but not the only prism.</p>
        <p>The Questionnaire</p>
        <p>Scott: I saw that questionnaire [a list of race-related questions that some reporters asked their subjects and that some also answered themselves] and I thought, Ugh, how much do I want to reveal? Then we also had to ask the same questions of our subjects, and I called up Charles Dutton [one of the subjects of her article], and I went through the questionnaire with him, and it was fun. When I came to the point, ''Did you have white friends as a child?'' he said: ''No, of course I had no white friends. You know I grew up in a black public housing project. There were a couple of white people there, and I played with them maybe in the daytime. But no white person ever came to my house.'' And he was completely frank about it.</p>
        <p>I hung up the phone and I thought, If he can do it, I ought to, too. I should say, Of course there were no black people in my childhood. And then I thought, You can't, as a white person, do that as easily. Even though as a child it's not your decision that you're living in a totally white suburb and going to a totally white school. But that's where the issue of the moral failing comes in. You feel as if it's a failing.</p>
        <p>Roberts: So what did you say on the questionnaire?</p>
        <p>Scott: Well, I didn't answer that question accurately, actually. The question was: Who was the first person of another race who left a meaningful impression upon you?</p>
        <p>What happened was the honest answer was one thing, which I'll tell you. And I went to my husband and I said, ''Should I give this answer, because I know it's embarrassing.'' And he said: ''It will be used against you. It will be used to judge the quality of your story.'' So I gave an answer that was not untrue, but it happened later on.</p>
        <p>The answer that I didn't give was: I grew up in a totally white suburb; I went to very white schools until I was 14. I lived in a very white world. And the first black person to leave a meaningful impression upon me was a woman who sat on a stool at the entrance to the farmers' market where my mother would shop every Saturday -- with a tambourine in her lap, in a long dress, raising money for her church in a part of the town where I lived that we never saw. And every Saturday when we would go to the farmers' market, we were told to go over and give a quarter to Sister Jackson. Now, that was the first person.</p>
        <p>And that's a terribly painfully revealing fact about my past, and I didn't put it in the questionnaire.</p>
        <p>Holmes: Excuse me. What's so painful?</p>
        <p>Scott: Because it shows how benighted my childhood was. And, obviously, Charles Dutton was perfectly comfortable saying the same thing about his own childhood. But he could be comfortable with it, and you tell me why I'm not.</p>
        <p>Holmes: But it wasn't. . . . As you said before, it wasn't your fault.</p>
        <p>Scott: Mike, you seem to understand what I'm saying even though Steve and Dana profess not to. Do you think that they're being honest in saying that it wouldn't be held against me?</p>
        <p>Winerip: I know what you mean. I mean, it's kind of you're less experienced, you're more protected, you grew up in an ivory tower, those kinds of things. And I think we all like to think of ourselves as worldly and urban and having this variety of experiences.</p>
        <p>Holmes: But if you were to say that you didn't know any plumbers or carpenters, nobody would hold that against you. You wouldn't think that would be held against you. But if you didn't know any black people, that would be -</p>
        <p>Scott: Plumbers are not subject to persistent discrimination.</p>
        <p>You Have to Figure Out</p>
        <p>How Whites Want You to Be</p>
        <p>Boyd: What is major to me, because I've seen it time and time again, is the weight blacks give to race. Blacks give race so much weight that you can't be yourself, you have to try to figure out how whites want you to be. And it doesn't change based on how much success you have. That was one of the things that came through in some of our stories. Race is out there, time and time again. And if you're not careful, it's going to reach out and slap you and knock you down in some way and you'll never be able to get up from it. Now, there's some truth in that. I'm not minimizing that. But to give whites and race so much power is to me incredibly destructive and counterproductive and hurts. And yet it happened and it still happens.</p>
        <p>Golden Behr: In our editing discussions we shocked reporters by what we asked them to reflect on and come back at us with. And sometimes we got some fights with reporters who didn't want to go there. There were tears, there was emotion. But there were breakthroughs afterward.</p>
        <p>Holmes: Yeah, but Soma, I'm curious: Did you feel that the race was the reason, that they were afraid of a particular racial aspect of -</p>
        <p>Golden Behr: I think sometimes it was and sometimes it wasn't. I think sometimes people are being protective of something that they didn't want to really write about.</p>
        <p>Looking at Ourselves</p>
        <p>Roberts: Dana, you looked at another newsroom. You looked at Akron. What did looking at that -- the experience of looking at that newsroom -- teach you about our newsroom?</p>
        <p>Canedy: Well, I think one of the things it taught us is that whether you're talking about The New York Times or a bank or a factory or a retail store, institutions struggle with the same kinds of issues of diversity.</p>
        <p>Roberts: Gerald is looking skeptical.</p>
        <p>Boyd: Oh, no, no, no. I think everybody struggles with diversity. What this taught me about The Times and race are a couple of things: that I think it is out there in the thick of our newsroom; it is all over the place; and that we seldom engage it, for whatever reason.</p>
        <p>Holmes: Another thought, which is less about the institution. Dana, you were dealing with this white columnist, who I considered an absolute jerk. I was curious about how you were able to deal with this guy who reveled in his ability to say things that would put black people on edge.</p>
        <p>Roberts: As a black reporter?</p>
        <p>Holmes: As a black reporter.</p>
        <p>Canedy: I don't think he sees himself that way, No. 1. Also, I think the beauty of having time to do these stories is you see people as full, complex characters and not one-dimensional figures. And so in spending a lot of time with him I got to see him as a father, I got to see him as a journalist, I got to see him as a friend, I got to see him in his role as a husband, as someone involved in that community. So it was easier for me to see him not just as someone who'd written some columns that black people used to label him as racist. I had, I think, as tough a time understanding the black columnist just because he, for example, is very shy and was a very reserved person.</p>
        <p>What We Talk About When We Go Home</p>
        <p>Boyd: When I started out in the early 70's, it was very popular to be black. Every white had to have one. And so you'd go to dinner parties and you'd sit around the table and you could tell lies for days and nobody would challenge you. And the assumption was if you were a black professional you could speak for 12, 14 million black people: all black people think this.</p>
        <p>And then something happened in this country as more and more blacks got into the workplace and became professional; it became clear blacks disagreed and we didn't see things all the time alike. But that was 15, 20 years ago. What has happened since then, I think, can basically be described as racial fatigue. I think whites have, in their view, tried to reach out and accept and understand and they feel, for the most part, that blacks have not been responsive. I think blacks feel they have tried to be heard and understood and that whites haven't heard them, haven't been responsive. And so what you have is just indifference.</p>
        <p>And what I've always wondered is how much whites and blacks actually do talk about race in the privacy of their own bedrooms.</p>
        <p>Golden Behr: Whites don't have to think about race very much. I've just grown convinced that blacks think about race all the time because they're the minority in the room all the time and that that just raises a lot of issues for them. And that whites have the luxury, if that's what it is, of cruising along.</p>
        <p>Boyd: We struggled with race, we struggled with -isms a lot in the late 60's and early 70's, whether it was racism or sexism or -- this was the generation that was going to change the world. We were trying to deal with them as well as we could, day in and day out and week in and week out.</p>
        <p>Golden Behr: So do you have racial fatigue?</p>
        <p>Boyd: Oh, yes. Especially after this project.</p>
        <p>Winerip: Well, as a white person I got racial fatigue from this project. I found myself mad sometimes having to think about all this stuff. I didn't want to. It's like what you say, Gerald, I don't think whites have to think about it as much. And this project made me fatigued. I was angry about how much I had to think about it. And I was tired of thinking about it.</p>
        <p>Holmes: What angered you about it?</p>
        <p>Winerip: Trying to get to the bottom of it. Was this moment racial or wasn't it racial?</p>
        <p>Roberts: Janny, that's something you had with Charles Dutton. Is he just kind of a bombastic, aggressive, larger-than-life character or was he acting this way, on some level, because he's black?</p>
        <p>Scott: This is a person who is intensely conscious of race, says he sees race in absolutely every interaction. Months into the process I emboldened myself to ask the question, ''So if race is a factor in everything, how is it a factor in our conversations?'' And he, with characteristic bluntness, said it's a factor in that I distrust you.</p>
        <p>And he said, ''I'm going to say a lot of things to you that you just won't understand.'' At the time, you know, it was painful to hear. In retrospect, it was absolutely true.</p>
        <p>Roberts: Why did he talk to you?</p>
        <p>Scott: I asked him that question and he said, ''Well, I haven't seen any black reporters around here.''</p>
        <p>Is This Race?</p>
        <p>Thompson: Well, I guess what I was thinking is that blacks all the time are thinking: Is this race? Am I being perceived some way because I'm black? I think that black people are constantly filtering race in the way that we are thinking about how we are being perceived in a conversation.</p>
        <p>Canedy: I wanted to give an example of that. As a black business reporter at The New York Times, I have to interview C.E.O.'s of Fortune 500 companies all the time. Sources I've made over the phone and have talked to for months and have never met, a lot of times they really don't know that I'm black. I can't tell you the number of times I've shown up at companies. I mean, I could be the only one in the lobby, and the executive assistant for the C.E.O. will walk right past me two or three times, just not even seeing me because they weren't expecting a black person. There have been plenty of times when I'm going to an interview with a source who has given me good information but has never met me. And I have to think, Oh, boy, when this person discovers I'm black -- what I call black surprise -- is the dynamic of the relationship going to change?</p>
        <p>The Takeaway</p>
        <p>Roberts: What did you want readers to come away with? What do you want them to walk away with that they didn't have before?</p>
        <p>Canedy: I hope they don't walk away at all. I mean really, I hope that conversations are going on now and that there's a momentum that continues for a while.</p>
        <p>Boyd: I think people assume an awful lot when it comes to race. That if they explored it or put it out there or challenged it or threw it up, it would probably not hold up. Maybe truth is a bit more complicated than they believe.</p>
        <p>Roberts: Has working on this series changed you?</p>
        <p>Golden Behr: It has changed how I think of some of my friends. A couple of them admitted that they didn't see, they didn't understand, the drama of this. Which really shocks me. We showed what's going on in a silent world where people don't go, and I thought that was an enormous contribution. I hope people will understand that there is a lot of unfinished work to do to understand each other. I found it pretty shocking to find people who said, ''Well, isn't that just another story about race?''</p>
        <p>Thompson: It's what race is in America. It's not Diallo. It's working in the same office every day. Someone described it as a low-grade fever. Something you go home with every day and it gnaws at you, it nags at you and you're irritable over it.</p>
        <p>Scott: It just gets down to what we've been talking about, that everything seems to be seen differently by different people. You can never get your hands around what exactly it is that you're talking about. And then to be entrusted with so much of two people's lives and to try to get within that at this elusive thing. . . . I feel humbled by it.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
