<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Family That Clowns Together</title>
    <meta content="16WILD$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000723T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215150"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FILM"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Comedy and Humor</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wayans Family</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wild, David</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Scary Movie (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Comedy and Humor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04EFD91038F935A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2271" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Family That Clowns Together</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID WILD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wild, David</byline>
      <dateline>BEVERLY HILLS, Calif.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>David Wild article on emergence of Wayans family as major American comedy dynasty and whose latest movie, Scary Movie, has just been released; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE Wayans brothers have finally arrived.</p>
        <p>Not just to breakfast -- for which they are varying degrees of fashionably late -- but as a major comedy dynasty. With last weekend's successful opening of ''Scary Movie'' -- the ''Airplane''-like spoof of body-count horror flicks such as ''Scream'' and ''I Know What You Did Last Summer'' -- this family that often plays together has taken a collective giant step forward. Directed by Keenen Ivory Wayans, 42, and showcasing the acting and writing talents of his younger brothers Shawn, 29, and Marlon, 27, ''Scary Movie'' took in an impressive $42 million at the box office in its first weekend and seems likely to make the family hot in Hollywood.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE Wayans brothers have finally arrived.</p>
        <p>Not just to breakfast -- for which they are varying degrees of fashionably late -- but as a major comedy dynasty. With last weekend's successful opening of ''Scary Movie'' -- the ''Airplane''-like spoof of body-count horror flicks such as ''Scream'' and ''I Know What You Did Last Summer'' -- this family that often plays together has taken a collective giant step forward. Directed by Keenen Ivory Wayans, 42, and showcasing the acting and writing talents of his younger brothers Shawn, 29, and Marlon, 27, ''Scary Movie'' took in an impressive $42 million at the box office in its first weekend and seems likely to make the family hot in Hollywood.</p>
        <p>As individuals, members of the Wayans family have long been familiar faces and respected comic figures. They have enjoyed assorted levels of success as stand-up comedians and on television shows like the influential early-90's Fox sketch-comedy show ''In Living Color'' and the more recent UPN sitcom ''The Wayans Brothers.'' On the big screen, meanwhile, family members also have appeared together in various combinations in ''Hollywood Shuffle'' (1987), ''I'm Gonna Get You Sucka'' (1988), '' 'Mo Money'' (1992) and ''Don't Be a Menace to South Central While Drinking Your Juice in the Hood'' (1996).</p>
        <p>Still, the Wayanses are not really a package deal like, say, the Marx Brothers. They are more like a loosely formed but tightly knit mutual admiration society -- and they do much of their best work together.</p>
        <p>Now, with ''Scary Movie'' -- marked by a broad tone and an interracial cast that includes Carmen Electra and Shannon Elizabeth -- they have established themselves as a force with which Hollywood will gladly reckon. ''I think this is what's going to lift the whole dynasty off,'' said Bob Weinstein, co-chairman of Miramax with his brother, Harvey, who released the film through their company's Dimension division. ''They've had a particular audience and this is going to widen their audience even more.''</p>
        <p>Gathering recently at a Beverly Hills breakfast spot to discuss the rise of their family -- and taking every opportunity to plug ''Scary Movie'' -- Keenen, Shawn, Marlon and Damon, 39, were in high spirits.</p>
        <p>''We're the black Beatles,'' said Shawn, with mock bravado.</p>
        <p>''This movie is 'There's Something About Mary' funny, which is funny to everybody,'' offered Damon. ''And I'm not even in it.''</p>
        <p>Along with the jovial back-and-forth comes a sense of how the brothers work together. ''We know each other's sensibility,'' Keenen said. ''If Damon comes and gives me a note, I listen, because he's my third eye. Same with these two guys. We energize each other.''</p>
        <p>Damon pointed out that some of the energy comes from ''a friendly competition'': ''If I'm in a scene with Keenen and I look him in the eye, I know if I don't get the laugh, he's gonna get it. That keeps everybody raising the bar.''</p>
        <p>Watching the Wayans brothers collaborating on ''Scary Movie,'' Mr. Weinstein said, both impressed and amused him: ''I work with my brother, and I see their interaction and it makes me laugh. Marlon and Shawn wrote the script, but being their brother, Keenen didn't have to be nice about telling them, 'Go write it over 20 more times.' ''</p>
        <p>Still, judging from the hugs and kisses at their breakfast get-together, it seems this family remains unusually close. ''But,'' said Marlon, ''it's hard to get everybody. The West Coast family, we get together often -- birthdays, weekends. The East Coast family, we all get together at least three or four times a year.'' He went through the family roster, explaining who lives where.  Concluding a bit breathlessly, he added, ''If I forgot anyone, forgive me.''</p>
        <p>While the setting for this business-related family reunion was pretty elegant, the conversation kept drifting back to a more humble location: the Robert Fulton Houses, a housing project in the Chelsea section of Manhattan. That's where all 10 Wayans children -- from oldest to youngest, Dwayne, Keenen, Deidre, Damon, Kim, Elvira, Nadia, Devon, Shawn and Marlon -- spent at least a portion of their childhood. These four sons of Howell (who, paradoxically, sold condoms for a living) and Elvira Wayans recalled their early days as bittersweet. Often completing one another's sentences and cracking themselves up, they explained how the good, the bad and the ugly of their upbringing helped them make their names in show business.</p>
        <p>Keenen remembers the day his family moved into ''the projects'' as the happiest of his mother's life. They had been living in a Harlem tenement he recalled as ''rat-infested, with lots of junkies.'' He continued: ''Every day my mother was fighting to keep us from getting hurt. I remember her looking out our window when we got to the projects and seeing a garage across the street, and my mother just smiling. But it was one of the first integrated projects in Manhattan, and the racial tension was unbelievable. Grown people were throwing bottles at us. My mother wound up getting into fights -- fistfights -- on a regular basis. A lot of that subsided. By the time Marlon and Shawn came along----''</p>
        <p>''----We were dating white women,'' Marlon interrupted, with a hearty laugh.</p>
        <p>Eventually, Keenen said, the projects became ''a really fun place -- no crime, no racism.'' But the Wayans family hardly enjoyed a worry-free existence. Simply feeding all those mouths was difficult. Breakfast was puffed rice cereal bought in bulk. Lunch was grilled cheese sandwiches with, as Shawn described it, ''government cheese where the cheese don't melt.'' Sometimes, they ate ''peanut butter or jelly,'' Marlon added. ''We never had peanut butter and jelly.''</p>
        <p>There was, they agreed, lots of love and there were lots of shining bright spots. For instance, there was the time Keenen brought Eddie Murphy over to the projects.</p>
        <p>''He made us like the coolest kids on the block,'' Shawn recalled. ''Everybody in the projects emptied out of 10 buildings and just lined up.''</p>
        <p>''Crackheads got off crack just to come upstairs,'' Marlon added.</p>
        <p>''They were bringing back TV's,'' Keenen said with a laugh.</p>
        <p>Keenen said he was the first Wayans to want to be a comedian. ''I had the dream since I was 6, but I didn't want to hear anything negative about it so I never told anyone,'' he said. His sister Kim was more up-front, he recalled with a grin: ''Kim was in any play at any expense, both to her dignity and her pocket book.''</p>
        <p>The comedy god in the Wayans household was Richard Pryor, and even though their mother, who had been a social worker, pushed education, a turning point came when Keenen decided to drop out of Tuskegee Institute in Alabama.</p>
        <p>''I'll never forget the night Keenen sat on the dryer and told my mother he was quitting college after three and a half years of engineering school to go to California and pursue acting and stand-up,'' Marlon said.</p>
        <p>Their mother, Shawn said, lit into Keenen ''very poetically.'' He went on: ''We watched that as kids, and I had to applaud him. That was the biggest impact on my life in terms of mentally going, 'You can do it.' Knowing how against it my parents were, it took such bravery.''</p>
        <p>According to Keenen, the shared pain of their childhood is the best explanation for all the comic talent in a single family. ''Comedy is pain,'' he said. ''You can't be funny if you haven't experienced pain. You can be witty, but the real comic stars -- Richard Pryor, Lenny Bruce, Sam Kinison -- these guys were in deep pain and stand-up was a cathartic experience. Great stand-up comedy comes from the darkest places.''</p>
        <p>Comedy also requires discipline, and there was plenty of that, Damon said: ''We had a father who ran a tight ship. He was a general. You didn't want to experience the wrath of Howell. And my mom was a real lioness when you crossed her kids.''</p>
        <p>All four Wayanses agreed that their mother is probably the funniest member of the family, but only when angered. ''When my mom's mad, she's a genius,'' Damon said. ''When she's not, she's corny. She's clever -- a lot of plays on words. But when she gets mad, that's when you pull up a chair.''</p>
        <p>Though the Wayans men are more famous, Marlon said, ''the women in our family are hilarious.'' So why do the men dominate professionally?</p>
        <p>''I think women have a harder time with rejection,'' Keenen said. ''I always used to say you have to be impervious to the word 'No.'  'No' means, 'Not right now.' It definitely can't mean 'No.' That's why people who have less fare better in show business: because they're not accustomed to getting it the first time around.''</p>
        <p>Kim Wayans wasn't so sure. ''I just don't think any of the other girls were drawn that way,'' she said later, by telephone. ''This is my calling. This is what I'm supposed to be doing.''</p>
        <p>Fans were first exposed to the Wayans family through ''In Living Color,'' for which Keenen was the driving force. The hip-hop-inflected show featured Kim, Damon, Dwayne, Shawn and Marlon, as well as Jim Carrey and Jamie Foxx, then unknown. And by the time ''In Living Color'' became a hit, there was a new attitude in the Wayans home. When Marlon had to decide between furthering his education at Howard University and entering the family business in California, he said, he found his mother ''sitting on a whole new washing machine now with her fur and diamonds, going: 'Baby, don't be a jackass. Do like Keenen, go take yourself out there and become an actor. Because Mama's about to go out there and be a Fly Girl, you hear.' ''</p>
        <p>''Marlon had the opposite tongue-lashing,'' Keenen said. ''It was hilarious.''</p>
        <p>Later, in 1995, Marlon and Shawn teamed up for ''The Wayans Brothers.'' That show was regarded as a hit only with black audiences, though the Wayanses have their doubts about the picture of America portrayed by the Nielsen ratings.</p>
        <p>''I don't know any brothers with Nielsen boxes,'' Marlon said.</p>
        <p>''I know some with pirated bootleg cable boxes that some guy named Nielsen got for them, but no Nielsen boxes,'' Shawn joked. ''I think it's all based on suburban homes.''</p>
        <p>''We were heavy urban,'' Marlon said, ''but we have everyone coming up to us.''</p>
        <p>Eric Gold, who manages Keenen, Damon, Shawn and Marlon and was a producer of ''Scary Movie,'' thinks the family falls into a Keenen branch and a Damon branch. ''They have a little bit of a hierarchy within their group because they were such a large family, and one had to look out for the other,'' he said. But, he added, ''There was no question that Keenen played the part of Papa Bear.''</p>
        <p>As for Keenen, he sees no danger of the kind of feuding that often splits show-business families into opposing camps. ''The rifts that most families have are not the results of show business, they're the result of a shaky foundation,'' he said. ''We have a very strong foundation. Show business is not strong enough to divide us.''</p>
        <p>According to Kim, everyone would give up show business ''in a heartbeat'' if it were to begin eroding the family's ties.</p>
        <p>Damon agrees. ''Individually, we've all achieved a certain amount of success, but I believe that collectively, we're unstoppable,'' he said. ''We squash any feuds because that's unhealthy -- in the end, family's all you got. When I'm on my death bed, I want to look up and see family, not fans.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, the next generation of Wayanses has already begun arriving on the scene -- a prospect the brothers don't find scary. ''We encourage it,'' Damon said. ''That's what we're trying to build -- so that we've got something to leave for them, a playground for them.''</p>
        <p>In the meantime, there's much more to come from this generation. Damon goes into production in October on his midseason sitcom for ABC. He's taking advice from the family on the show. ''I'm the stubborn one -- every time I didn't trust the family, I failed,'' Damon said. ''I did this other show for Carsey-Werner. Keenen said, 'What do you know about being a cop?' I said, 'It's Carsey-Werner,' and it failed.'' Damon's new show concerns what happens when a man cheats on his wife and the balance of power shifts. The show, formerly known as ''Wife and Kids,'' may become ''The Damon Wayans Show.''</p>
        <p>Marlon says that when a Wayans project doesn't pan out, like Keenen's late-90's talk show, ''we make jokes and move on.'' Everyone agreed there's strength in numbers.</p>
        <p>In the end, for Damon, it all comes down to love and respect: ''The reason we're all coming together is that together, we all win. People come up to me and go, 'Man, I love your family.' They sometimes give me individual accolades, but for the most part it's, 'I love what your family does.' That means that my family's success is my success. And my success is . . . my success.''</p>
        <p>With that, the Wayans brothers unite in some serious laughter.</p>
        <p>FILM David Wild is a contributing editor of Rolling Stone and the author of ''The Showrunners'' which will be published in paperback this fall.</p>
        <p>Correction:  July 23, 2000, Sunday  An article on July 16 about the Wayans family misidentified the television network that carried the program ''The Wayans Brothers.'' It was WB, not UPN.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: July 23, 2000, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article on July 16 about the Wayans family misidentified the television network that carried the program ''The Wayans Brothers.'' It was WB, not UPN.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">David Wild is a contributing editor of Rolling Stone and the author of ''The Showrunners'' which will be published in paperback this fall.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
