<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Identity Crisis</title>
    <meta content="16LECLAIT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215035"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leclair, Tom</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chacon, Daniel</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Chicano Chicanery: Short Stories (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E3DE1F39F935A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="677" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Identity Crisis</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Tom LeClair</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Leclair, Tom</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Tom LeClair reviews book Chicano Chicanery: Short Stories by Daniel Chacon (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Chicano Chicanery</p>
        <p>Short Stories.</p>
        <p>By Daniel Chacon.</p>
        <p>152 pp. Houston:</p>
        <p>Arte Publico Press.</p>
        <p>Paper, $11.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Chicano Chicanery</p>
        <p>Short Stories.</p>
        <p>By Daniel Chacon.</p>
        <p>152 pp. Houston:</p>
        <p>Arte Publico Press.</p>
        <p>Paper, $11.95.</p>
        <p>''Silence, exile and cunning,'' Joyce's Stephen Dedalus said before leaving his poor homeland. ''Talk, immigration and chicanery'' might be the slogan of Daniel Chacon's hopeful characters. Although a collection of stories, this book is ''A Portrait of the Chicano Artist as a Young Man,'' with the author becoming more literary as the pieces accumulate. In the final fiction, ''Story #7 in D Minor,'' Chacon appears as the keynote speaker at a celebration his characters put on. Here the author also handily mentions several kinds of fiction in ''Chicano Chicanery'' -- including the ''standard identity story'' and the ''cultural story'' -- but not the postmodern pastiche of ''Story #7.''</p>
        <p>Chacon isn't quite up to imitating Donald Barthelme and David Foster Wallace, but he does mature work in his other categories. His best ''cultural story'' is ''Godoy Lives.'' A young Mexican named Juan decides to sneak into the United States with the identity card of a dead man named Godoy. At the border, Juan just happens to be examined by Godoy's cousin, who hasn't seen Godoy for years and doesn't know he's dead. The cousin takes Juan home with him, and from this coincidence many benefits flow, including a visit from Godoy's well-off mother, who fortunately happens to be senile. Chicanery works for everyone except Juan's abandoned wife and kids. Juan doesn't recognize his exile from himself, but characters in the stories that follow are plagued by split or fake identities.</p>
        <p>In ''The Biggest City in the World,'' Chacon reverses the south-to-north movement of ''Godoy Lives.'' A Chicano graduate student named Harvey Gomez, who is not fluent in Spanish, clings to Professor David P. Rogstart on a trip to Mexico City. But when Gomez loses his wallet, he refuses to seek aid from his mentor, tours the city and, in the words of a soon-to-be-cheated taxi driver, finally becomes ''a Mexican.'' Chacon's ending is as satisfyingly ambiguous as Godoy's meeting his ''mother.''</p>
        <p>The most original of Chacon's ''standard identity stories'' is ''Spring Break,'' in which three young Chicanos, one of them a Harvard student, steal a steer in Fresno. First they can't kill it, then can't butcher it and finally have to bury it in one character's backyard. Chacon subtly contrasts the three youths, loads the piece with wonderful authenticating detail and combines the ''standard'' loss of innocence with a larger loss -- of experience, the knowledge the boys might well have had in Mexico.</p>
        <p>Unfortunately, ''Chicano Chicanery'' has too many ''standard'' identity stories, fictions that reveal little about being Chicano. Many of the collection's 13 stories are told by high school or college students, and they're redolent of workshop fiction. Except for a few Spanish phrases, perfunctory description of gang members' clothes and scattered references to Mexican dishes and American barrios, most of the school stories could be about clique, rather than ethnic or class, conflict. The situations tend to be predictable, and the outcomes -- betrayal and violence -- predetermined.</p>
        <p>The Chicano newscaster in ''Aztln, Oregon'' ends up acting like one of Chacon's boys. Hoping to become a national figure, Ben Chavez does a report on gangs, but it's not as radical as he wanted it to be. Frustrated, he displaces his rage onto his appreciative Anglo boss and beats him up. Chavez wants to ''go deeper and deeper,'' but Chacon doesn't often drill down far enough. Like a journalist, he reports on characters and their doings rather than creating them from precise circumstances and coiled histories. And when Chacon lets his characters tell their own stories, his prose is rarely invigorated by the oral and colloquial.</p>
        <p>The work in ''Chicano Chicanery'' is frequently thin in texture, as if ethnic idiosyncrasies had been subtracted, and thus the stories are like Juan in ''Godoy Lives'' -- without a substantial identity.</p>
        <p>Tom LeClair teaches English at the University of Cincinnati. His second novel, ''Well-Founded Fear,'' is published this month.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Tom LeClair teaches English at the University of Cincinnati. His second novel, ''Well-Founded Fear,'' is published this month.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
