<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Business Comes a-Courtin' to Cold Spring Harbor</title>
    <meta content="16BIZ.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215222"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="L.I.@WORK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biotechnology</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Watson, James D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Strugatch, Warren</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Pharmaceutical, Biotechnology and Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Biotechnology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7D91E38F935A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1214" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Business Comes a-Courtin' to Cold Spring Harbor</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WARREN STRUGATCH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Strugatch, Warren</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on possibility that Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory may seek a more Long Island-based view as it continues to expand; business, government and academic leaders hope to foster biotechnology industry similar to ones that cluster around biotech corridors in Cambridge, Mass, San Francisco, San Diego and Austin, Tex; lab president and Nobel laureate Dr James Watson notes that its fund-raising scope has been national and its teaching and research scope has been international; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ONE night two months ago, James Watson -- Nobel laureate, president of Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory and inspiration to several generations of scientists -- rose from his seat to accept a Lifetime Achievement Award from the Long Island Association, the region's largest business group. Although the scientist lives and works just minutes from the posh country club the group favors for major events, most of the black-tie attendees were meeting Dr. Watson, discoverer of the structure of DNA, for the first time.</p>
        <p>No slight was intended. It's just that the lab's international focus, and the continuous pursuit of financing, keep Dr. Watson, 72, on the road.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ONE night two months ago, James Watson -- Nobel laureate, president of Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory and inspiration to several generations of scientists -- rose from his seat to accept a Lifetime Achievement Award from the Long Island Association, the region's largest business group. Although the scientist lives and works just minutes from the posh country club the group favors for major events, most of the black-tie attendees were meeting Dr. Watson, discoverer of the structure of DNA, for the first time.</p>
        <p>No slight was intended. It's just that the lab's international focus, and the continuous pursuit of financing, keep Dr. Watson, 72, on the road.</p>
        <p>But even when he's home, he moves in different circles. While the lab is host to thousands of visitors a year at its scientific meetings and conferences, guests are more likely to hail from Australia than Amityville. The lab remains enigmatic, if not unknown, to the local business community.</p>
        <p>''We don't usually turn to Long Island to meet our needs,'' Dr. Watson said. ''In terms of fund-raising, in terms of grantsmanship, in terms of research funding, our scope is entirely national. In our role as a teaching place and a research place, we are small and focused, but very international.''</p>
        <p>In recent years, the lab has come under pressure to be a bit more, well, neighborly. Business, government and academic leaders hope to foster a biotechnology industry here, and are pressuring the lab to play a leadership role. They point to burgeoning biotech corridors in Cambridge, Mass., San Francisco, San Diego and Austin, Tex., where prestigious research institutions galvanize intensely cerebral and collaborative communities known as clusters.</p>
        <p>That has not happened here. During the 1990's the lab spun off 14 companies based on its patents, siting all but four elsewhere in the country. According to Bruce Stillman, the lab's director and Dr. Watson's chosen successor, the choices were driven by business realities: each company was sited where it seemed most likely to prosper.</p>
        <p>''It isn't easy for small biotech companies to grow on Long Island,'' Dr. Stillman said. ''Just getting appropriate commercial space can be very, very difficult.''</p>
        <p>The L.I.A. and other business and government leaders acknowledge his point, but rue the exodus of jobs and capital. According to the group's chief economist, Pearl Kamer, the 14 spinoff companies have hired 1,722 people, all but 226 of them employed off Long Island. Only OSI Pharmaceuticals in Uniondale, with nearly 200 employees, raises a blip on the local economic radar. Most of the aggregate financial benefits, including $357 million in annual expenditures, accrue off-Island.</p>
        <p>''I would like for the lab to take a pro-Long Island view in terms of siting spin-off companies here,'' Mr. Crosson said. ''I would like their stance to be: Let's build up a Long Island genetics corridor. It's regrettable and avoidable that those companies were spun off elsewhere.''</p>
        <p>Signs are the lab is prepared to play a more active local role. Construction is nearly complete on the $15 million Biosciences Park, a collaboration between the lab and the State University of New York at Farmingdale. The original plan was to build an incubator. When OSI Pharmaceuticals, which had outgrown its Uniondale building, began looking elsewhere for space, the plan was hurriedly revised. The new plan cedes most of the building to OSI, positioning it as an anchor for the expected cluster.</p>
        <p>When the project is complete, supporters say Long Island will finally have the infrastructure it has been lacking: brainy scientists, trained students looking for part-time work and entry-level positions, incubator space near permanent space for expansion, all of it centralized. Advocates hope the new park stems the biotech exodus.</p>
        <p>It has been tried before. The Island's original high-tech incubator is in Stony Brook, and there are three others: two, in Bethpage and Stony Brook, for computer software; and one, also in Farmingdale, for manufacturing. Another biotech incubator, operated by the North Shore-Long Island Jewish Health System in Manhasset, is nearing completion.</p>
        <p>Does the profusion of incubators undercut their chances of achieving critical mass?</p>
        <p>''Absolutely not,'' said Peter Goldsmith, chairman of Listnet, a Great River software and technology co-op. ''Demand for tech centers is so great on the Island.''</p>
        <p>John Cleary, a Farrell Fritz lawyer who is chairman of the Farmingdale incubator, said the formula has worked elsewhere. ''You want to bring together different companies having the same discipline in a geographically defined area,'' he said. ''As you develop synergistic relationships, the cluster draws other companies.''</p>
        <p>The dynamic of such clusters is more interactive, and social, than is the case in most industries.</p>
        <p>''It isn't just coming to work, going into the office and leaving at 5 o'clock,'' Mr. Cleary said. ''It's a question of interacting with people of like mind dealing with similar issues in a congenial environment.''</p>
        <p>But tradition and the lab's culture are not on their side. According to Dr. Watson, the lab's mission is to focus on pure scientific research, untainted by commercialism.</p>
        <p>''Maybe 2 percent of our revenues come from commercial applications,'' he said. ''Transferring technology to business is nice, especially if it's something our scientists want to do. We like to help make that happen. But it isn't our mission. Our mission is to do pure, bleeding-edge science.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Stillman, who became director in 1994, offered a similar emphasis on separating research from commerce. He agreed, however, that the development of a biotech corridor would allow the lab to transfer technology to local companies more easily.</p>
        <p>''It's rather a Catch-22,'' Dr. Stillman said. ''You can't attract biotech companies until you have established a cluster. But you don't have a cluster until you attract the companies.''</p>
        <p>For biotech executives and investors, a cluster assures enough trained employees to provide adequate staffing. For employees, clusters mean competition, and competition means higher wages and career mobility. That, in turn, attracts better employees, or so goes the theory.</p>
        <p>Mr. Crosson sees the lab's role in developing the Biosciences Park as an indication it expects to play a bigger role in the local economy.</p>
        <p>''Dr. Watson is indeed very familiar with the Long Island economy, despite the fact that he is on the road so much of the time,'' Mr. Crosson said. ''And I think that Dr. Stillman will prove to be even more involved with Long Island.''</p>
        <p>Invited recently to address a luncheon in Hauppauge held by another business group, Dr. Stillman encountered an audience eager to learn more about the lab and the opportunities in genomics and biotechnology.</p>
        <p>''Afterwards, so many people approached asking to come visit the lab that we are organizing a tour specifically for that group,'' he said. ''I was delighted to see so much enthusiasm. However, I was a bit surprised that some of the business people seem never to have heard of us.''</p>
        <p>L.I.@WORK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
