<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>It's More Than Just a Deli, And Soon It Will Be Less</title>
    <meta content="16DELI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215400"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: PARKCHESTER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Delicatessens</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Jack's Deli (Nyc)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Parkchester Preservation Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giancaspro, Jack</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Critchell, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03EFD9173BF935A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="462" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>It's More Than Just a Deli, And Soon It Will Be Less</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID CRITCHELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Critchell, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jack Giancaspro, owner of Jack's Deli in Parkchester housing complex in East Bronx, decides to close after 22 years rather than accept 40 percent rent hike from Parkchester Preservation Co; residents decry decision; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The evening twilight was streaking through the windows of Jack's Deli on Metropolitan Avenue as Jack Giancaspro stood by the locked front door, ready to admit one last customer in need of a pastry, cold cuts or just a cup of coffee.</p>
        <p>In the store, tucked in the mammoth Parkchester housing complex in the East Bronx, the mood was grim. As two employees cleaned up, the talk was dominated by the store's impending closing after 22 years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The evening twilight was streaking through the windows of Jack's Deli on Metropolitan Avenue as Jack Giancaspro stood by the locked front door, ready to admit one last customer in need of a pastry, cold cuts or just a cup of coffee.</p>
        <p>In the store, tucked in the mammoth Parkchester housing complex in the East Bronx, the mood was grim. As two employees cleaned up, the talk was dominated by the store's impending closing after 22 years.</p>
        <p>Mr. Giancaspro had just received a letter terminating his lease from the Parkchester Preservation Company, the nonprofit concern that bought Parkchester last year and is overhauling the crumbling complex.</p>
        <p>''I can't talk about it; I'm going to start crying again,'' said Irma O'Reilly as she scrubbed a counter. ''We know all of the people in the neighborhood, and Jack is the only one left who takes care of people.''</p>
        <p>Known for his smile and friendly banter, Mr. Giancaspro has built a loyal following since moving into this storefront. More than 2,000 people have signed petitions asking the landlord to keep the business open.</p>
        <p>''When the old people get sick, he sends his delivery boys to pick up their medication and deliver it to them,'' said a Parkchester employee. ''Who is going to take care of them if he leaves?''</p>
        <p>The deli's new landlord informed Mr. Giancaspro in January that his lease renewal, due on March 31, would include an increase of nearly 40 percent, to $2,750 a month, from $2,000, Mr. Giancaspro said.</p>
        <p>''I didn't think that a 40 percent hike was fair, so I didn't bite,'' he said, noting that he had offered what he considered to be a fair compromise.</p>
        <p>But no compromise was reached, and the landlord plans to replace Jack's Deli with a self-help community center, said Cheri Fein, a spokeswoman for Rubenstein Associates, which represents Parkchester.</p>
        <p>Ms. Fein said the complex had sought other tenants after getting the impression that Mr. Giancaspro would not renew his lease.</p>
        <p>''He wanted the right to sell his lease and wasn't showing a strong interest in staying in the community,'' Ms. Fein said. ''He finally accepted to renew two days before the lease expired.'' By that time, Ms. Fein said, a new tenant had been found.</p>
        <p>Mr. Giancaspro remains philosophical about the closing; some of his customers are less sanguine.</p>
        <p>''This is not just some bodega with a beat in the background,'' said Adrian Jones, a regular. ''This is a real deli.''</p>
        <p>DAVID CRITCHELL</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: PARKCHESTER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
