<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>White Plains Workers Protest Lack of a Pact</title>
    <meta content="16PACT$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215256"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Government Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fringe Benefits</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">White Plains (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kilgannon, Corey</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Government Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fringe Benefits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E1D81F38F935A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="814" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>White Plains Workers Protest Lack of a Pact</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By COREY KILGANNON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kilgannon, Corey</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Several hundred municipal employees stage demonstration over lack of salary increase since 1997 and city's refusal to continue paying half of dental insurance premiums (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LAST Monday at City Hall, White Plains leaders approved a $175 million mega-movie theater and shopping center project planned for Town Center, lauding it as a sign of economic prosperity washing into the city.</p>
        <p>But outside City Hall, at the bottom of its broad steps, many of the city's rank-and-file workers were crying poverty, complaining that in its best of times the city is paying its workers as if it were the worst.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LAST Monday at City Hall, White Plains leaders approved a $175 million mega-movie theater and shopping center project planned for Town Center, lauding it as a sign of economic prosperity washing into the city.</p>
        <p>But outside City Hall, at the bottom of its broad steps, many of the city's rank-and-file workers were crying poverty, complaining that in its best of times the city is paying its workers as if it were the worst.</p>
        <p>Several hundred municipal employees, from accountants to custodians, carried signs complaining of salaries that have not increased since 1997 and of the city's refusal to pay half the cost of workers' dental insurance, as it used to.</p>
        <p>Contracts for the city's police and fire departments have also expired, and both groups, which are currently entering arbitration to settle their contracts, say they are underpaid.</p>
        <p>The 400 or so municipal workers are beginning their third straight year working under the terms of a contract that expired on July 1, 1998.  Workers say that despite complaints about salaries, they have remained  with the city because of the benefits package, but now that premiums for dental insurance are rising that enticement is fading.</p>
        <p>Clarence Thrower, a 40-year White Plains resident and a laborer in the city's Highway Department, said some of his co-workers, frustrated over lack of a new contract, have quit over the last two years to take jobs with private companies, and he is considering doing the same.</p>
        <p>''White Plains is the most expensive city in the county to live in,'' asserted Mr. Thrower, who is paid $27,000 a year. ''Without help from my wife, I'd sink like a piece of lead.''</p>
        <p>All but one worker at the rally wore red T-shirts bearing the name of their union, the Civil Service Employee Association. The exception was ToniAnn Sanin, a senior account clerk in the Finance Department. As a sarcastic gesture, she wore the blue ''We Are Family'' T-shirt that the city gives its workers to wear at public events when the mayor salutes his ''family'' of city workers, often with with the song ''We Are Family'' blaring over loudspeakers.</p>
        <p>''He calls us his family, but you don't treat your family like this,'' Ms. Sanin said. ''We take care of this city, and it's one of the best maintained in Westchester, but that all may change because no one cares about us and it hurts morale.''</p>
        <p>City officials dismiss what the workers say as melodrama designed to gain power at the negotiating table. Elisabeth Wallace, a personnel officer, said the city was simply following a longstanding policy of pattern bargaining, in which each division is offered a contract equal to what the others are getting. In negotiations, the city has offered raises of roughly 3 percent for 1999 and 2000.</p>
        <p>Under the terms of the 1997 contract, the city paid half of the $1,550 that it cost to provide each worker with dental insurance. But that figure has increased to $2,300, and the city is offering no more than the $766 it paid in 1997. ''They want us to pay 50 per cent of their premiums, and we can't do it,'' said Ms. Wallace. ''It must come out of their salary. If we agreed to it, we'd have to give it to the other units.''</p>
        <p>Union officials, she said, have abruptly canceled many meetings  during negotiations, which began in May 1998, and have rejected the city's offer of a contract equal to those of other city workers, including the police, fire and sanitation departments. The union is essentially delaying proceedings for a year, she added, by filing a complaint over what she described as a relatively minor issue, whether three housing department security guards would be included in the city contract.</p>
        <p>While negotiations with city workers remained stalled, the contract with the White Plains Police Department expired in June 1999. Lower salaries and longer hours than those in other police forces are causing ''badge drain,'' said James Carrier, president of the White Plains Police Benevolent Association. Seven officers have left the force in the past year to join other forces, he said.</p>
        <p>''We're the county seat, and it's a busy job,'' he said, ''but we're consistently ranked among the lowest paid forces in the county.'' A rookie officer in White Plains makes $37,000 a year and after three years can expect a maximum of $55,000, at least $5,000 less than forces in most other cities in the county.</p>
        <p>The P.B.A. and the city are meeting with an arbitrator on Thursday. The P.B.A. is demanding that officers be allowed to work four days a week, a policy adopted by many other police forces. Ms. Wallace said the city would not consider this.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
