<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Nation: The Cold War Lives; In Search of a Missing Link in the Logic of Arms Control</title>
    <meta content="16SCHM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215426"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Missiles and Missile Defense Systems</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schmitt, Eric</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Missiles and Missile Defense Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00EEDB143BF935A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1243" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Nation: The Cold War Lives; In Search of a Missing Link in the Logic of Arms Control</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC SCHMITT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schmitt, Eric</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>US and Russia still maintain thousands of nuclear-tipped missiles at each other, the legacy of a different age; no one has quite figured out how many are still needed, how to think about them and where they should be aimed; these questions are largely overlooked in debate about proposed national missile defense and worry over nuclear-weapons proliferation; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THERE is a dirty little secret in American arms control circles these days: No one really knows where the nation's nuclear doctrine is headed.</p>
        <p>The principal arguments heard here are for or against missile defenses, and about strategies to fight the spread of nuclear weapons. One might think that underlying all of them is a solid understanding of why the United States and Russia have the number and types of nuclear-tipped missiles that they have.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THERE is a dirty little secret in American arms control circles these days: No one really knows where the nation's nuclear doctrine is headed.</p>
        <p>The principal arguments heard here are for or against missile defenses, and about strategies to fight the spread of nuclear weapons. One might think that underlying all of them is a solid understanding of why the United States and Russia have the number and types of nuclear-tipped missiles that they have.</p>
        <p>But that is hardly the case. The United States and Russia are still pointing thousands of missiles at each other (setting examples for imitators from Pakistan to India), even though Moscow and Washington no longer fight for the world's hearts and minds and threaten global extinction in the process.</p>
        <p>These missiles were designed for a different age, and no one has exactly figured out how many are  still needed, how to think about them and where the Pentagon should point them today.</p>
        <p>''We haven't rethought the purposes of nuclear weapons since the end of the cold war,'' said Michael Krepon, president of the Henry L. Stimson Center, a research group.</p>
        <p>That is in the background as President Clinton prepares to decide whether to begin building a $60 billion defensive system to protect the United States against limited missile attacks, and as he weighs last week's failed test of the system.</p>
        <p>If one could design a system from scratch to defend against a resurgent Russia some day, it would presumably look quite different than the one in place now. Mr. Krepon said he would allow for a system of unlimited defenses and tightly constrained offensive weapons. Other experts would recommend a defense that intercepted missiles just after launching, rather than in space. The notion of nuclear deterrence -- and, by implication, massive retaliation -- still enjoys bipartisan support, but some critics say the uncertainty about what might deter a so-called rogue state makes missile defenses necessary. Others say deterrence is immoral.</p>
        <p>Those options illustrate how the question of the Russian-American missile balance affects every aspect of nuclear proliferation and defensive missile strategy. Imagining a different balance among the nuclear superpowers, one can also imagine how differently a potential little nuclear power like North Korea -- or a medium-size one like China -- might see itself fitting in.</p>
        <p>Not that there is any wide agreement on what effect an effort to create a missile defense might have. Many experts say it would just complicate efforts to stop proliferation, by tempting potential enemies into building up their forces to overwhelm the defense.</p>
        <p>Indeed, there has never been anything obvious about the proper nuclear strategy to adopt. Even during the cold war, American strategic doctrine steadily evolved, from one  of large-scale retaliation in the 1950's to a focus on obtaining arms control accords, starting in the 1970's.</p>
        <p>Today, just as NATO's relevance came under scrutiny after the collapse of Communism, so too have traditional theories of arms control.</p>
        <p>In May, Gov. George W. Bush, the presumptive Republican presidential nominee, suggested a break from decades of strategic theology when he said he would consider deep unilateral cuts in American warheads while building robust defenses to be shared with European allies and, perhaps, one day with Russia or China.</p>
        <p>In suggesting that, Mr. Bush repudiated a governing assumption of American arms control that the ability of each side to annihilate each other created a safer world by making the temptation to use nuclear weapons unthinkable.</p>
        <p>''Whether you agree with missile defenses or not, what Bush did was quite important,'' said Robert A. Manning, the director of Asia Studies at the Council on Foreign Relations, who said he has informally advised the Bush campaign. ''He was overturning a paradigm of the cold war, and saying Russia is not a problem, why target them?''</p>
        <p>IN fact, the roughly 2,200 Russian targets in the Pentagon's strategic war plan are based on assumptions about the way policy makers expect Russia to behave. The United States still presumes a series of nuclear exchanges based on exceptionally deep rivalries and differences. That may have been true 20 years ago, but is it still true now?</p>
        <p>The Clinton administration acknowledges the paradox, but says it's still prudent to keep a hedge. In a report last September, the intelligence community concluded: ''The Russian threat, although significantly reduced, will continue to be the most robust and lethal.''</p>
        <p>No wonder the Pentagon brass is wary of cutting America's atomic stockpile below 2,000 to 2,500 warheads, as proposed under the strategic arms agreement known as Start 3. ''These forces represent our nation's ultimate insurance policy,'' Adm. Richard W. Mies, who heads  the military's strategic forces, told senators in June. ''Nuclear weapons help keep the cold war cold.''</p>
        <p>It was a curious phrase. Is there still a cold war? Does the strategy  still work the same way?</p>
        <p>One thing that has certainly changed is the clear American advantage in conventional weaponry over all its potential adversaries, and even over its allies. Some conservatives who are eager to erect an extensive missile defense have begun to argue that deterrence as a  strategy is immoral, and irrelevant.</p>
        <p>''Would we really incinerate every Iraqi because of some action by Saddam Hussein?'' asked Senator Jon Kyl, an Arizona Republican. ''I'm not sure we would, and I'm not sure we should.''</p>
        <p>For many conservatives, missile defense has become a new orthodoxy. But they say Mr. Clinton's proposal to shield the United States from only a handful of missiles -- from countries like North Korea, Iran and Iraq -- is ill-conceived.</p>
        <p>Senator Carl Levin, a Michigan Democrat and a staunch supporter of arms control, counters that so long as an effective missile defense does not create more diplomatic problems than it solves, it could lessen the ability of a small, hostile nuclear power to threaten the West with nuclear blackmail.</p>
        <p>BUT critics argue that any missile defenses will upset deterrence's delicate balance. Moscow fears that even a small system would be a step  toward a larger one that Russia could not afford to match. So it is threatening to freeze arms cuts if Washington bolts the treaty, as Mr. Bush has suggested he might do.</p>
        <p>And China's top arms control negotiator warned last week that Beijing's arms control and nonproliferation agreements with the West could be imperiled. China now has only a handful of long-range missiles; an American missile defense might encourage them to seek parity with the American and Russian arsenals, many experts say, adding that if China ratchets up its nuclear arsenal, it's a safe bet that India and Pakistan will quickly follow. Which leads back to why Russia and America have their arsenals. Without an obvious rationale for that, it is only more difficult to persuade New Delhi or Islamabad to curb their own nuclear appetites.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
