<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Growing Memories of Generous Friends</title>
    <meta content="16WGAR$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215210"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="IN THE GARDEN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GARDENS AND GARDENING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Faust, Joan Lee</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEEDC1E38F935A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="811" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Growing Memories of Generous Friends</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOAN LEE FAUST</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Faust, Joan Lee</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Joan Lee Faust In the Garden column recalls fond memories of friends who have given her plants she that now grow in her garden; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AS I was weeding the little rock garden recently, I was reminded how many friends are represented in the yard. They have given me plants over the years and because the plants have settled in and now belong to the place, they always make me think of the dear people who gave them to me.</p>
        <p>One of these memory plants recalls my friend Esther Legeyt Bailey every time I am near the splendid dwarf boxwood she gave me many years ago. Mrs. Bailey was one of the best plant propagators I have ever known. She could grow anything, from seed, cuttings or small pieces of plants. Her entries at the North American Rock Garden shows always seemed to nab the blue ribbons.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AS I was weeding the little rock garden recently, I was reminded how many friends are represented in the yard. They have given me plants over the years and because the plants have settled in and now belong to the place, they always make me think of the dear people who gave them to me.</p>
        <p>One of these memory plants recalls my friend Esther Legeyt Bailey every time I am near the splendid dwarf boxwood she gave me many years ago. Mrs. Bailey was one of the best plant propagators I have ever known. She could grow anything, from seed, cuttings or small pieces of plants. Her entries at the North American Rock Garden shows always seemed to nab the blue ribbons.</p>
        <p>The dwarf boxwood she gave me was probably a sprout of Buxus microphylla compacta although she told me she was not quite sure what it was. The plant she gave me was tiny, about the size of a Ping-Pong ball. Now it is about the size of a basketball and thriving. She would be proud to see it.</p>
        <p>Harold Espstein, probably the finest plantsman I have ever known,  gave me two fine skimmia plants.  When he gave me the skimmias, he reminded me that they needed to be planted in a place where the soil drained well. I did, and the plants are thriving. They seem to belong where they grow. Since skimmias are like holly in that male and female flowers are on different plants, the two sorts have to be near each other to supply those splendid red berries. Their foliage is evergreen, too, a rather handsome pair to have around. These skimmias are true garden show-offs.</p>
        <p>But I was not as lucky with the Arisaema sikokianum that Mr. Epstein gave me. This is an extremely handsome Japanese jack-in-the-pulpit that most everyone seems to grow well. Mr. Epstein was surprised I did not have one in my garden as he was a great promoter of Japanese plants for American  gardens. He gave me a plant and told me exactly how and where to plant it.</p>
        <p>I thought I followed the directions, carefully, but the plant did not make it. Mr. Epstein , I am sure, must have been very disappointed with me when I told him the dreadful news.  But, in his greenhouses, he had scads of a darling ebony spleenwort, the crested one that is hard to find. This little fern thrived everywhere in the greenhouse, almost like a weed. When the greenhouses was being cleaned out my dear friend Lois Himes, who worked with Mr. Epstein's plants, made sure I got some of those delicate ferns. They are now thriving in a rock wall.</p>
        <p>Then there are the most unusual Fritillarias in my garden. They bloom steadily each spring with their somewhat regal spikes. This magnificent Fritillaria verticillata is a treasure that another dear friend, Sydney Eddison gave me. This unusual plant has quite a history.</p>
        <p>The species was a treasure of Carl Krippendorf, whose garden is now being maintained by the Cincinnati Nature Center.</p>
        <p>Mr. Krippendorf was the grandfather of Mary Ley, a close friend of Sydney Eddison, who also had the fritillaria in her own garden.</p>
        <p>One day, while visiting Sydney Eddison's garden, I admired this unusual fritillaria and was given a sampling. The plant has since found its new home in my garden to its liking and has been divided several times and boasts a few spots in my perennial garden. Mrs. Eddison also gave me an especially attractive Corydalis cheilanthifolia with lovely bright yellow flowers and beautiful fernlike  foliage. It also thrives and in fact has many, many seedlings. Some are left to grow, others are pulled up. This generous friend loves to share. My part is to be careful about admiring plants in her beautiful garden!</p>
        <p>I will always be indebted to Ellie Spingarn, another plant propagator who can grow just about anything from seed. She is a master at judiciously placing campanulas in a wall. Her walls are rich with the lovely blooms of Campanula garganica and I have tried to duplicate, with modest success, some of her abilities.</p>
        <p>These are just but a few of the many plants that thrive and are reminders to scores of friendships. But remember one thing: Although a particular plant is lovely in a friend's garden, it may not be suited to yours.</p>
        <p>Plants have specific needs and unless these needs are satisfied, the results can be disappointing. The same is true for picking plants by pictures from catalogs. Unless the garden has the right conditions that the plant needs, the results may be hopeless.</p>
        <p>IN THE GARDEN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
