<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Red Dot, Meet Green: If It's Tuesday, Network!: Prague; Bells Are Ringing For 'M-Commerce'</title>
    <meta content="MB061603" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215464"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE2D6143BF935A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="623" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Red Dot, Meet Green: If It's Tuesday, Network!: Prague; Bells Are Ringing For 'M-Commerce'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER GREEN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a polo shirt and jeans, Richard Seewald, a lawyer, stands on the terrace of the Fromin discotheque overlooking the church spires of Prague, scouting for places to invest $50 million for his Internet venture capital fund, Redstars.com.</p>
        <p>He sees potential pots of gold here. The Czech economy has begun to stabilize after two years of recession, and prospects look good for Internet business, particularly in ''m-commerce,'' the new tag for buying and selling over the mobile telephones that are ubiquitous in Central Europe.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a polo shirt and jeans, Richard Seewald, a lawyer, stands on the terrace of the Fromin discotheque overlooking the church spires of Prague, scouting for places to invest $50 million for his Internet venture capital fund, Redstars.com.</p>
        <p>He sees potential pots of gold here. The Czech economy has begun to stabilize after two years of recession, and prospects look good for Internet business, particularly in ''m-commerce,'' the new tag for buying and selling over the mobile telephones that are ubiquitous in Central Europe.</p>
        <p>''The Internet here has taken off in the past six to eight months, so there is a need for what we do,'' Mr. Seewald said. ''The buzz up to now has been ex-pat companies; now we are getting more and more local business plans'' -- not just those of Americans with an idea that was too late for Silicon Valley.</p>
        <p>''Wireless is totally the buzz,'' agreed Adam Healey, a 25-year old New Yorker, as the constant ringing of mobile phones filled the room. Mr. Healey's Samba Digital Media, an  Internet services company based in Prague, just pulled in $2.5 million of venture capital. Mr. Healey had just finished briefing 200-odd entrepreneurs who filled the disco. ''Ask yourself which investor you can hang out and have a beer with,'' he said. ''You're going to be spending a lot of time with them, so you'd better like them.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Healey's company produces Web pages and e-commerce solutions for companies around the world. Like many local ventures, he combined the entrepreneurial skills of the young Americans who have flocked to Prague with the technical knowledge of Czech software engineers. Now he is moving a step further -- to m-commerce -- and he has come to First Tuesday to spread the gospel.</p>
        <p>''The Czechs have one of the highest penetrations of mobile phones in the world,'' he said. ''It's a lot easier for someone to buy a mobile than a PC.'' And because of the lack of credit card use and consumer credit, the firms that operate digital mobile phone networks take the credit risk. With only about 6 percent of Czechs having regular Internet access at their homes or offices, m-commerce is likely to outstrip the PC-based internet for most consumer use.</p>
        <p>Jan Krasnan, 21, a student at the prestigious Prague School of Economics, also has big plans. He does not have a business card yet; his nameplate has just an e-mail address. With fellow students, he is perfecting a secret mobile phone application as part of a national student contest to join an Internet incubator.</p>
        <p>''Ideas I have, but I am keeping them for myself,'' Mr. Krasnan said. ''Of course we want to be rich, but we really want to create something that isn't here. We want to change the world.''</p>
        <p>Martin Vedej will settle for changing the way that Czechs think about the Internet. ''Companies here are still investing in traditional marketing tools such as printed stuff,'' complained Mr. Vedej, 25, managing director of Frontline Management, another e-solution provider for the Czech market. ''They don't appreciate the potential of the Internet. They are just waiting.'' The first time Mr. Vedej came to a First Tuesday, earlier this year, he didn't even know what venture capital was. Now he has a business plan and is looking for investors.</p>
        <p>Karel Kosman, another red-dot wearer, fears that Prague's Internet boom may have gathered speed too quickly. ''The situation is a little like the Wild West here. People are snapping up any deals at all. It's not healthy. People are going to lose money.''</p>
        <p>PETER GREEN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
