<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Leaders in Congress Agree to Debt Relief for Poor Nations</title>
    <meta content="18DEBT$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/18/world/18DEBT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239797"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kahn, Joseph</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Callahan, Sonny (Repr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001018T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E1DD143EF93BA25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="991" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Leaders in Congress Agree to Debt Relief for Poor Nations</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSEPH KAHN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kahn, Joseph</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Congressional leaders say they will grant Pres Clinton $435 million he seeks to forgive debts of world's poorest nations this year as part of global debt relief initiative; accord is sign that street protests and parish actvisim about globalization problems have had impact on Congress; Rep Sonny Callahan cites support for debt relief from diverse political, cultural and religious leaders, interview (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Congressional leaders said today that they planned to grant President Clinton all the money he had sought to forgive debts of the world's poorest nations this year, a victory for a coalition of rock stars, religious figures and charity groups that have made debt forgiveness a moral touchstone for wealthy nations.</p>
        <p>The agreement to allot $435 million for the United States' share of a global debt relief initiative this year, though still subject to final approval in both the House and the Senate, is a sign that street protests and parish activism about the problems of globalization have had an impact on Congress, which has been chary about foreign aid for the last decade.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Congressional leaders said today that they planned to grant President Clinton all the money he had sought to forgive debts of the world's poorest nations this year, a victory for a coalition of rock stars, religious figures and charity groups that have made debt forgiveness a moral touchstone for wealthy nations.</p>
        <p>The agreement to allot $435 million for the United States' share of a global debt relief initiative this year, though still subject to final approval in both the House and the Senate, is a sign that street protests and parish activism about the problems of globalization have had an impact on Congress, which has been chary about foreign aid for the last decade.</p>
        <p>Among the diverse political, cultural and religious leaders to throw their weight behind debt relief recently are Pope John Paul II; Pat Robertson, the Republican televangelist; Bono, singer of the Irish pop group U2, and George W. Bush. Their support tipped the balance in the Republican-led Congress, which had not previously offered much support for calls by developing countries for debt relief.</p>
        <p>''The debt relief issue is now a speeding train,'' Representative Sonny Callahan, an Alabama Republican who is the ranking member on the House committee that controls the foreign aid budget, said in an interview. ''We've got the pope and every missionary in the world involved in this thing, and they persuaded just about everyone here that this is the noble thing to do.''</p>
        <p>If, as is now expected, the money is included in final appropriations bills working their way through Congress, the United States would be spared the embarrassment of being the only major industrial nation unwilling to pay its share of a $90 billion global debt relief plan.</p>
        <p>The international movement to reduce the debt burden of 41 poor nations in Africa and Latin America began in Europe several years ago, and European parliaments have made funds available to forgive debts much more readily than Congress.</p>
        <p>Leaders of developing nations have been pressing for donor nations to forgive past debts, arguing that many of the debts were incurred by earlier -- and often corrupt -- governments that misused aid.</p>
        <p>Congressional support for the measure is a victory for the Clinton administration, which has been working to reassure lawmakers that the money made available to poor nations by relieving some debt payment obligations would be used for humanitarian purposes only. President Clinton committed the United States to participate in debt relief at a meeting of world leaders in the summer of 1999, and he has been working to generate bipartisan political support for the measure.</p>
        <p>Late last month, Mr. Clinton invited Congressional leaders to the White House to discuss debt relief with Mr. Robertson, the conservative Christian preacher who has run for president as a Republican, and Bono,  who wore a black leather jacket and one earring to the session. A group of multinational businesses, including Merck, Motorola, Caterpillar and Goldman Sachs, also joined the debt relief push earlier this month.</p>
        <p>''It's not often we have a chance to do something that economists tell us is a financial imperative and religious leaders say is a moral imperative,'' Mr. Clinton said after that meeting.</p>
        <p>Several groups have expressed caution about the debt relief plan. Senator Phil Gramm, a Texas Republican, has said that the money should not be granted until international financial institutions like the World Bank and the International Monetary Fund overhaul the way they do business and improve their effectiveness. Some of the debt relief money would replenish the coffers of the financial institutions, the primary lender to the poorest nations.</p>
        <p>Clinton administration officials say they have won support for a variety of changes at the I.M.F. and the World Bank.</p>
        <p>Other lawmakers said they worried that the plan was ill conceived because it would bail out bankers rather than generating new cash to help poor people. A United Nations report on debt relief also faulted the plan for what it said was an unrealistic view of how it could help poor nations develop faster, predicting that the program would end up relieving only a small portion of the outstanding debt and force poor nations to rely on fresh loans.</p>
        <p>Republicans came under pressure this month from Mr. Bush, who championed debt relief in his second debate with Vice President Al Gore.</p>
        <p>Vice President Gore has been a strong supporter of the administration's debt-relief plan.</p>
        <p>Anti-globalization protesters who took to the streets in Seattle late last year, and in Washington and Prague earlier this year, have made debt forgiveness a priority at both the World Bank and the I.M.F.</p>
        <p>The debt relief effort still faces one significant obstacle. Congress has the power to deny an I.M.F. request to reallocate some of its gold reserves to support the monetary fund's own commitment to debt relief, an accounting change that the fund says would free $570 million to relieve poor nations' debt. The accounting provision does not require any more money from the United States.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gramm, who heads the Senate Banking Committee, which has oversight over the issue, has so far declined to support the accounting change. He presented the Treasury Department with a lengthy list of changes he wants completed at the financial institutions, which he has said tend to support corrupt dictatorships and waste billions in taxpayer money on ill-conceived rescue efforts for failed economies.</p>
        <p>Lawmakers familiar with the negotiations in Congress said they believe that Mr. Gramm had softened his demands in recent days, recognizing that debt relief had become a priority for Republicans as well as Democrats.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
