<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Classic Sauce Takes On A New Partner</title>
    <meta content="18MINI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/18/living/18MINI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239663"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE MINIMALIST"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shrimp</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bittman, Mark</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Columns/The Minimalist</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shrimp</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001018T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04EEDB163EF93BA25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="507" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Classic Sauce Takes On A New Partner</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Mark Bittman</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bittman, Mark</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mark Bittman describes making shrimp, Roman style; recipe (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN and around Rome, a simple but powerful tomato sauce spiked with garlic, chilies and mint is traditional with tripe. But tripe is a hard sell to most Americans, and it has to cook a long time to become tender. Substitute shrimp and the dish is not only irresistible but practically done as soon as you add them to the hot sauce.</p>
        <p>The tomato sauce itself is made in a relatively standard way but with a couple of minor twists. The garlic is used generously and in chunks, and it is browned nearly to the point of bitterness to make it extra strong. The chilies add a noticeable measure of heat. And the mint contributes much more energy than the usual parsley or basil.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN and around Rome, a simple but powerful tomato sauce spiked with garlic, chilies and mint is traditional with tripe. But tripe is a hard sell to most Americans, and it has to cook a long time to become tender. Substitute shrimp and the dish is not only irresistible but practically done as soon as you add them to the hot sauce.</p>
        <p>The tomato sauce itself is made in a relatively standard way but with a couple of minor twists. The garlic is used generously and in chunks, and it is browned nearly to the point of bitterness to make it extra strong. The chilies add a noticeable measure of heat. And the mint contributes much more energy than the usual parsley or basil.</p>
        <p>You can use fresh chilies, like jalapenos or Thai chilies (start with one or two, stemmed and seeded), or dried chilies. Or you can just use cayenne, crushed red pepper flakes or even the Thai or Vietnamese chili pastes sold in jars.</p>
        <p>The sauce is cooked just long enough for the tomatoes to render their juice and begin to fall apart; it should not be allowed to become too dry. The finished dish should be a moist, almost soupy stew, rather than shrimp coated in a thick paste.</p>
        <p>This consistency makes the dish ideal as a topping for pasta. Just cut the amount of shrimp to about a pound; with a pound of pasta as the base, there's no need for more than that. Start the water for the pasta when you start the sauce, and begin cooking the pasta at the same time as the shrimp.</p>
        <p>With pasta or without, it's the mint that is the star component here. It grows wild in the hills around Rome, and is featured in a number of classic dishes. Dried mint will do (add it a couple of minutes before the sauce is done), but fresh mint is readily available and far superior.</p>
        <p>SHRIMP, ROMAN STYLE  Time: 30 minutes</p>
        <p>2 tablespoons extra virgin olive oil  1 tablespoon garlic, peeled and coarsely chopped  6 dried red chilies, or to taste  4 cups chopped fresh tomatoes (or 1 28-ounce can plum tomatoes, chopped, with their juice)  Salt and freshly ground black pepper  1 to 2 pounds shrimp, peeled and, if you like, deveined  1 cup chopped fresh mint, or 1 tablespoon or more dried mint.</p>
        <p>1. Put the olive oil in a large, deep skillet, and turn the heat to medium. Add the garlic and chilies. When the garlic begins to color, cook carefully until it browns just a bit. Turn the heat off for a minute to avoid spattering, then add the tomatoes.</p>
        <p>2. Turn the heat to medium-high and bring to a boil, then reduce the heat to medium, and simmer 10 to 15 minutes, stirring occasionally. Add salt and pepper to taste.</p>
        <p>3. Add the shrimp and cook, stirring occasionally, until they are all pink, 5 to 10 minutes. Taste, and adjust seasoning; the sauce should be quite strong. Stir in the mint, and serve.</p>
        <p>Yield: 4 servings.</p>
        <p>THE MINIMALIST</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
