<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Manila Journal; This Whistle-Blower Could Topple a President</title>
    <meta content="Y18MAN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/18/world/18MANI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239724"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bribery</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Philippines</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Singson, Luis (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Estrada, Joseph (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Aquino, Corazon C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Philippines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Philippines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bribery</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001018T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E7DB173EF93BA25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1120" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Manila Journal; This Whistle-Blower Could Topple a President</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARK LANDLER</byline>
      <dateline>MANILA, Oct. 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gov Luis Singson, who threatens to bring down Philippines government with charge that Pres Joseph Estrada accepted over $8 million in kickbacks from illegal gambling, sounds more like cheerful accomplice than angry avenger, interview; describes Estrada's gambling habits; ex-Pres Corazon C Aquino joins calls for Estrada's resignation; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Luis Singson, the man who may bring down the president of the Philippines, was holding court in a sun-drenched room at the Manila Yacht Club. His black-and-white motor yacht, which he says he bought with winnings from gambling, was tethered to a pier outside.</p>
        <p>''I never thought it would come to this,'' Mr. Singson, 59, said with a shrug, as his diamond-studded Rolex glinted in the light. ''I wish it would all blow over so I could get back to my boat.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Luis Singson, the man who may bring down the president of the Philippines, was holding court in a sun-drenched room at the Manila Yacht Club. His black-and-white motor yacht, which he says he bought with winnings from gambling, was tethered to a pier outside.</p>
        <p>''I never thought it would come to this,'' Mr. Singson, 59, said with a shrug, as his diamond-studded Rolex glinted in the light. ''I wish it would all blow over so I could get back to my boat.''</p>
        <p>By accusing the Philippine president, Joseph Estrada, of accepting more than $8 million in kickbacks from illegal gambling, Mr. Singson, the rough-edged provincial governor of Illocos Sur, has overnight become the most sensational whistle-blower in this country's history.</p>
        <p>Yet with his tales of bribery, kickbacks, late-night gambling sessions  and personal feuds -- all delivered without a hint of regret -- Governor  Singson sounds less like an angry avenger than a cheerful accomplice.</p>
        <p>''If it is now against the law, I am willing to go to jail,'' he said. ''It would be an honor to go to jail with the president.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Estrada has denied accepting any bribes from gambling rackets. His spokesman, Ricardo Puno, said today that the president would respond to the governor's other claims in the courts, not in the news media.</p>
        <p>Few people are talking about jail just yet for either Mr. Estrada or Mr. Singson, who is often called by his middle name, Chavit. But the political firestorm unleashed by the president's former crony has gathered such fury that many people here believe that it will force Mr. Estrada to resign.</p>
        <p>Today, former President Corazon C. Aquino added her voice to those calling on the president to step down. Mrs. Aquino, who still wields enormous influence here as the icon of Philippine democracy, said there were ''moments when love of country calls for supreme self-sacrifice, even if it means resignation.''</p>
        <p>Speaking at the Edsa Shrine, built to commemorate her People Power uprising, which toppled Ferdinand Marcos in 1986, Mrs. Aquino said the president had brought shame on his office ''by the sordid company he keeps.''</p>
        <p>That was a reference to Mr. Singson and several other cronies -- politicians and businessmen -- who shadow Mr. Estrada everywhere, drinking and gambling with him into the small hours of the morning.</p>
        <p>While the hard living of Mr. Estrada, a former actor, has been the subject of much commentary since he was elected in 1998, Mr. Singson's disclosures have added fresh color to the portrait of a president who lives like a rock star.</p>
        <p>In an interview today, Mr. Singson said Mr. Estrada frequently convened late-night rounds of mah-jongg, either at Malacanang, the presidential palace, or on board the presidential yacht. The games, he said, sometimes extended over two days, particularly if the president was losing.</p>
        <p>''Sometimes we'd let him win,'' Mr. Singson said, noting that the stakes could rise to 40 million Philippine pesos, more than $800,000.</p>
        <p>It was in a mah-jongg game with the president, Mr. Singson said, that he won the money to buy his yacht. Mr. Estrada, apparently not miffed at this loss, suggested that the governor name the boat Escalera, a word that signifies the mah-jongg equivalent of a royal flush in cards.</p>
        <p>If Mr. Singson had stuck to gossiping about Mr. Estrada's habits, his comments would have been merely conversation. But he says he struck a Faustian bargain with the president, agreeing to pay him a cut of the proceeds from illegal gambling in his province, in return for state funds for Illocos Sur.</p>
        <p>''I admit, it was for my self-interest,'' Mr. Singson said. ''But I was used. How can you say no to a president?''</p>
        <p>Between 1998 and last August, Mr. Singson says, he delivered more than $8 million in kickbacks to Mr. Estrada. He says he decided to reveal the arrangement out of pique that Mr. Estrada awarded a lucrative gambling license to one of Mr. Singson's political rivals, who happens to be the governor's cousin.</p>
        <p>''It began as a personal dispute,'' he said. ''I told them to stop the game, and I would go home and leave them alone.''</p>
        <p>When the president and his advisers got wind of Mr. Singson's plans, he said they flooded him with phone calls, pleading with him to remain silent. But by then, he said, he felt he owed it to his family, and the country, to reveal the corruption at the core of the political system.</p>
        <p>''I want the whole world to know what kind of a government we have,'' he declared. ''If we cannot get justice through an impeachment, we will go into the streets and force the president to resign.''</p>
        <p>Given his recent disclosures, Mr. Singson is an unlikely candidate to inherit Mrs. Aquino's mantle. He said he did not attend a Mass today where opposition leaders gathered because he did not want to taint them.</p>
        <p>But he said he had put himself at risk in accusing Mr. Estrada. On Oct. 3, just before he was scheduled to publicize his allegations, Mr. Singson said, his car was surrounded by policemen after he left a meeting in a Manila hotel. He said he was ordered to step out of the car.</p>
        <p>He happened to be talking on a cellular phone to the officials with whom he had just been meeting. He asked them to come down to the hotel parking lot, at which point the police officers said they were merely issuing the governor a traffic ticket. Mr. Singson believes he narrowly escaped an ambush. Many political experts here say his story has the ring of truth.</p>
        <p>Credibility, or the lack of it, is at the heart of Mr. Singson's campaign against Mr. Estrada. With his high-roller image and his yacht -- not to mention a submarine that he he says he also owns -- Mr. Singson is an odd whistle-blower. But some analysts say it is precisely his checkered history that makes him credible.</p>
        <p>So what does the governor want?</p>
        <p>''If the president steps down, I will go back to my province and retire,'' he said. ''I want to enjoy my Escalera.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
