<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>If Home's Too Far to Get to, a Place in Harlem Beckons</title>
    <meta content="18UNDE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/18/living/18UNDE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239669"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="$25 AND UNDER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Miss Maude's Spoonbread Too (NYC Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Asimov, Eric</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Columns/$25 and Under</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001018T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807E6D9163EF93BA25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="637" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>If Home's Too Far to Get to, a Place in Harlem Beckons</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Eric Asimov</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Asimov, Eric</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Eric Asimov reviews Miss Maude's Spoonbread Too, on Lenox Avenue near 137th Street in Harlem ($25 and Under column) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN a world that reveres the richest and the greatest, it's reassuring to know that a corner in heaven is reserved for the homiest, too. Miss Maude's Spoonbread Too, a bright new restaurant in Harlem, celebrates the virtues of family meals without the childish nostalgia implicit in expressions like ''comfort food.''</p>
        <p>The generous portions of Southern dishes are not only robust and hearty, but also sometimes subtle, which should be no surprise, since Miss Maude's is owned by Norma Jean Darden, the caterer and cookbook author, who also owns Miss Mamie's Spoonbread Too on 110th Street.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN a world that reveres the richest and the greatest, it's reassuring to know that a corner in heaven is reserved for the homiest, too. Miss Maude's Spoonbread Too, a bright new restaurant in Harlem, celebrates the virtues of family meals without the childish nostalgia implicit in expressions like ''comfort food.''</p>
        <p>The generous portions of Southern dishes are not only robust and hearty, but also sometimes subtle, which should be no surprise, since Miss Maude's is owned by Norma Jean Darden, the caterer and cookbook author, who also owns Miss Mamie's Spoonbread Too on 110th Street.</p>
        <p>Ms. Darden has made a career of exploring the links between family and food, especially as they existed among Southern blacks in the first three-quarters of the 20th century. Her cookbook, ''Spoonbread and Strawberry Wine,'' written with her sister, Carole Darden, and reissued by Doubleday in 1995, tells the story of her own family through recipes. Miss Mamie's is geared more to takeout, while Ms. Darden's catering operation, Spoonbread Inc., offers fancier Southern and Caribbean cuisine.</p>
        <p>But Miss Maude's practically invites you in for a meal. Its walls are adorned with kitchen tools and black-and-white family photos, while each of its shiny red or yellow tables holds a fat, fresh rose.</p>
        <p>Meals begin with a basket of mildly spicy corn bread, grainy and not too sweet, and are served Southern style, with large portions of two sides. My favorite dish was the smothered pork chops ($11.95), thin but flavorful enough to stand up to the peppery brown gravy. Close behind were the excellent fried shrimp ($10.95), with a salt-and-pepper flavor that almost resembled that of Cantonese salt-and-pepper shrimp but had traces of cornmeal in the delectable crust.</p>
        <p>Fried chicken ($9.95) was as it should be, with a crisp, oniony crust that remained united with the meat, which in turn retained its chicken flavor. Short ribs ($12.95) were tender and very meaty, as were pork ribs ($10.95) baked with a barbecue sauce that was sweet and citrusy, but also packed some spicy heat. Though covered in the same sauce, barbecued chicken ($10.95) was too dry, but meatloaf ($9.95) with a brown onion gravy was tangy and moist.</p>
        <p>Side dishes were all excellent: collard greens spiked liberally with smoked turkey; macaroni and cheese, soft and runny but with barely crisp edges; candied yams, bathed in orange and pepper; and eggy, mustardy potato salad.</p>
        <p>At one side of the dining room, a bright display case shows off oversize cakes, pies and cobblers. Except for banana pudding ($3.50), produced in all its soft vanilla-wafer glory, the desserts are a disappointment. Sweet potato pie ($3), apple cobbler ($3.50) and coconut cake ($3.50) all taste as if they've been waiting a tad too long to be served.</p>
        <p>Chances are, though, you will be so well fed you won't have room for dessert. The spirit will be well fed, too, as if you just got a care package from home, no matter where you grew up.</p>
        <p>Miss Maude's Spoonbread Too  547 Lenox Avenue, near 137th Street, Harlem; (212) 690-3100.</p>
        <p>BEST DISHES: Smothered pork chops, fried shrimp, fried chicken, short ribs, pork ribs, meatloaf, collard greens, macaroni and cheese, candied yams, potato salad, banana pudding.  PRICE RANGE: Dinners, $9.95 to $12.95.  CREDIT CARDS: All major cards.  HOURS: Sunday, 11 a.m. to 9:30 p.m.; Monday through Thursday, noon to 9:30 p.m.; Friday and Saturday, noon to 10:30 p.m.  WHEELCHAIR ACCESS: Everything is on one level.</p>
        <p>$25 AND UNDER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
