<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Madison Avenue goes west, and it's chocolate perks, Frankie Avalon redux and casual dress.</title>
    <meta content="Y18ADC$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/18/business/18ADCO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239719"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trade Shows and Fairs</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Association of National Advertisers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Elliott, Stuart</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Advertising (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trade Shows and Fairs</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001018T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E0DC173EF93BA25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1295" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Madison Avenue goes west, and it's chocolate perks, Frankie Avalon redux and casual dress.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Stuart Elliott</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Elliott, Stuart</byline>
      <dateline>DANA POINT, Calif.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Stuart Elliott column on highlights, lowlights and sidelights of 2000 annual conference of Association of National Advertisers in Dana Point, Calif (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HERE are some highlights, lowlights and sidelights of the 2000 annual conference of the Association of National Advertisers, which took place here from Friday through Monday:</p>
        <p>ACTING UP  This was the first meeting of the association, the trade organization for the country's biggest marketers, since two actors' unions, the Screen Actors Guild and the American Federation of Television and Radio Artists, went on strike against advertisers and agencies in May. And since the unions had already demonstrated at the agencies' annual conference, this time it was the advertisers' turn to be targets.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HERE are some highlights, lowlights and sidelights of the 2000 annual conference of the Association of National Advertisers, which took place here from Friday through Monday:</p>
        <p>ACTING UP  This was the first meeting of the association, the trade organization for the country's biggest marketers, since two actors' unions, the Screen Actors Guild and the American Federation of Television and Radio Artists, went on strike against advertisers and agencies in May. And since the unions had already demonstrated at the agencies' annual conference, this time it was the advertisers' turn to be targets.</p>
        <p>Members of the two unions picketed in front of the hotel where the conference was held, the Ritz-Carlton Laguna Niguel. And they hired airplanes to fly over Salt Creek Beach, behind the hotel, towing banners supporting the strike.</p>
        <p>The banners promoted a boycott against three products sold by a large association member, Procter &amp; Gamble. One read ''Boycott Crest Tide &amp; Ivory -- Who's Next?'' Another read ''Turn the Tide Against Corporate Greed.''</p>
        <p>On Sunday, the banners drew amused comments from the announcer for a National Scholastic Surfing Association competition on the beach over a public address system audible to passers-by. As the boycott banner flew overhead, the announcer, Mike Morgan, doubted its effect: ''People are going to buy soap,'' he said. ''We don't live in France; we buy soap here.''</p>
        <p>Negotiations between the unions and representatives of the advertisers and agencies are scheduled to resume in New York on Thursday.</p>
        <p>PUTTING THE BITE ON CONSUMERS --  There was a reminder on the beach, as if one were needed, of the ubiquity of the advertising messages financed by the giant marketers that belong to the association. Trash barrels carried sales pitches for an ''anniversary collector's edition'' of the movie ''Jaws,'' available on videotape and DVD.</p>
        <p>LOCAL HEROES -- Two speakers at the general session on Saturday made geography the subject of jokes.</p>
        <p>''Here we are in sunny, friendly, outgoing California,'' said Philip B. Dusenberry, chairman of the BBDO New York unit of BBDO Worldwide, part of the Omnicom Group. ''We have a different attitude in New York: start every day with a smile -- and get it over with.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Dusenberry was followed by John D. Bowlin, president and chief executive of the Miller Brewing unit of Philip Morris, who is based in Milwaukee. He sang the praises of Wisconsin in October when, as he put it, spouses turn to each other and say, ''Look out the window, honey, and see if the lake is frozen.''</p>
        <p>ON THE DOT -- The moderator for the general session was Lou Dobbs, the former host of the ''Moneyline News Hour'' on CNN who is now chairman and chief executive of Space.com, which operates a Web site. He made his foray in dot-com entrepreneurship the point of several japes.</p>
        <p>For instance, after John J. Sarsen Jr., president and chief executive of the association, gave a speech about how to profit in the ''new e-conomy,'' Mr. Dobbs said: ''That word 'profit.' It seemed a little hostile.''</p>
        <p>P &amp; GEE -- Alan G. Lafley, the new president and chief executive of Procter &amp; Gamble, made his first major public speech at the conference, at the general session on Sunday. He signaled his intent to change P.&amp; G. without saying a word: he came out onto the stage clad not in the corporate uniform of a suit, dress shirt and tie but in a blue sport shirt, open at the collar, and a pair of green casual slacks.</p>
        <p>NESTLE GIVES THE VERY BEST -- One unexpected dividend for those who attended the general session on Sunday was a panoply of treats provided by a speaker, Joe M. Weller, chairman and chief executive of Nestle USA.</p>
        <p>Outside the room were tables covered with ''fresh baked Nestle Toll House cookies,'' as signs promoting the giveaway read.</p>
        <p>Inside, in front of each attendee's seat, was a ''goody bag'' filled with Nestle chocolates; bag of Nestle Pretzel Flipz, pretzels coated with white fudge; and a coupon for a free package of the Stouffer's Oven Sensations line of frozen food.</p>
        <p>As attendees digested his largess, Mr. Weller said, ''I'm one speaker who regards people eating as he talks not as bad manners, but as the epitome of good taste.''</p>
        <p>HOT AND JUICY -- The attendees ate up the self-deprecating remarks of R. David Thomas, founder and senior chairman of Wendy's International, when he received an award from Parade at a dinner on Sunday.</p>
        <p>In discussing the long-running Wendy's campaign featuring him by Bates USA, part of the Bates Worldwide unit of the Cordiant Communications Group, Mr. Thomas said: ''When I started doing the commercials, we didn't know what to do. And I was cheap.''</p>
        <p>''After 11 years and more than 740 commercials, I'm in the Book of Records for 2001,'' he added. ''You know what for? For not getting one right.''</p>
        <p>DANA POINT 92629 -- In a Southern California coincidence, at a reception Sunday night, two attendees were standing next to each other and chatting. One was Dylan J. Doherty, global director for agency management and advertising production at the Seagram Spirits and Wine Group in New York. The other was Brandon B. Bergmark, interactive sales category manager for America Online in San Francisco.</p>
        <p>A passer-by, noticing their name badges, remarked that Dylan and Brandon were the names of two principal characters on ''Beverly Hills 90210,'' the popular television series about Southern California teenagers.</p>
        <p>JARGON 'R' US -- Whenever and wherever marketers gather, buzzwords are sure to be heard. And this conference was no exception.</p>
        <p>At one point in his speech, Mr.  Lafley referred to ''channel-blind marketing plans.'' Translation: using the media appropriate to reach the intended customers for a product, rather than favoring traditional media like broadcast network television.</p>
        <p>Douglas M. Sweeny, vice president for business strategy at I.B.M., said that after significantly changing how they operate, I.B.M. executives had ''five-X'ed'' the company's market value. Translation: The price of I.B.M. stock has increased fivefold.</p>
        <p>AND THE WINNER ISN'T -- Amid the proliferation of awards for advertising, one awards competition is being discontinued. The association and its counterpart, the American Association of Advertising Agencies, have decided to end the Casie Awards for Outstanding Interactive Advertising and Web Sites.</p>
        <p>Casie is derived from the Coalition for Advertiser Supported Information and Entertainment, founded by the two associations, and the awards had been presented at the advertiser association annual conference since 1996. Michael Donahue, executive vice president of the agency association, said that while Casie would definitely continue its work, focusing on issues like guidelines and standards to measure interactive advertising, ''there are a lot of other awards now'' for Internet campaigns.</p>
        <p>BACK TO THE BEACH -- While the conference organizers were praised for its substantive content and how smoothly it was run, they drew the most cheers for a decision to eliminate the black-tie dinner that had ended each meeting for many years. In its place was a casual party on Salt Creek Beach with the singer Frankie Avalon as entertainment.</p>
        <p>Mr. Avalon's nostalgic act was much appreciated by the attendees, most of them in his demographic. He kidded his work in the California surfer musical films of the 60's like ''Beach Blanket Bingo,'' and prefaced his performance of ''Why (Because I Love You)'' by proclaiming, ''I recorded this song in '59 -- 1859.''</p>
        <p>And before a dance contest that paid tribute to ''American Bandstand,'' the daily TV show broadcast from Mr. Avalon's hometown, Philadelphia, he expressed his dismay over the popularity of rap music.</p>
        <p>''It's not that I don't like it,'' he said. ''I can't remember all those words.''</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
