<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Will Senate Race Take Them Out to the Ballgame?</title>
    <meta content="18ROOT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/18/politics/18ROOT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239763"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nagourney, Adam</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lazio, Rick A (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001018T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E6D6173EF93BA25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="630" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Will Senate Race Take Them Out to the Ballgame?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM NAGOURNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nagourney, Adam</byline>
      <dateline>RIVERHEAD, N.Y., Oct. 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Repr Rick Lazio and Hillary Rodham Clinton, candidates for US Senate from New York, discuss upcoming World Series between New York Yankees and New York Mets (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The setting was a cabbage farm here in a remote stretch of Suffolk County, but Representative Rick A. Lazio and his tiny audience of local farmers had strayed beyond the topic of crops to an issue of more immediate concern.</p>
        <p>''Mets in seven -- that's what I'm hoping for,'' Mr. Lazio said, swinging away at the question he had been waiting for. ''A Subway Series.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The setting was a cabbage farm here in a remote stretch of Suffolk County, but Representative Rick A. Lazio and his tiny audience of local farmers had strayed beyond the topic of crops to an issue of more immediate concern.</p>
        <p>''Mets in seven -- that's what I'm hoping for,'' Mr. Lazio said, swinging away at the question he had been waiting for. ''A Subway Series.''</p>
        <p>A few hours later, in Buffalo, Hillary Rodham Clinton, who had spent her day giving a speech on foreign policy, was confronted with a similar question as she rushed past a group of waiting reporters. ''I am looking for a Subway Series,'' she responded.</p>
        <p>Forget the speculation and anxiety surrounding the Yankees and the Mets and their legions of competing fans. The potential of a World Series involving New York's two teams has set off a just-as-fervent -- O.K., almost-as-fervent -- round of maneuvering, tactical planning and speculating among supporters of the candidates in the World Series of Senate campaigns.</p>
        <p>Perils and opportunities lie ahead. It was not simply fan loyalty that led Mr. Lazio to find his way to Shea Stadium on Monday night, as the Mets clinched the National League pennant. ''I happened to be at the game last night -- on the Mets side,'' he recounted here. ''Does that betray where I am?''</p>
        <p>As any politician knows, a visit to any ballpark almost invariably inspires boos. But Mr. Lazio was cheered by fellow Mets fans who happily recognized the challenger to Mrs. Clinton, the recent arrival to New York State whose baseball credentials are, well, open to debate.</p>
        <p>Indeed, baseball has been a difficult subject for Mrs. Clinton since the White House ceremony for the World Series champions last year, when she she plopped a Yankees cap on her head and proclaimed herself a Yankees fan. While Mrs. Clinton and her friends asserted that this was, in fact, historically accurate, that moment quickly became a symbol of Mrs. Clinton as a carpetbagger and, fairly or not, as an untrustworthy politician.</p>
        <p>So if there was exuberance in Mr. Lazio's camp today, the atmosphere at the Clinton headquarters was considerably more cautious. Howard Wolfson, Mrs. Clinton's communications director, would not entertain any questions about the subject this afternoon.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wolfson said his only concern was the well being of his favorite team, the Yankees. ''Talking about it will jinx it,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Other campaign officials said the subject has come up a few times in staff meetings in recent days, as the first lady's aides have considered such thorny questions as whether it made sense for Mrs. Clinton to attend a game.</p>
        <p>On one hand, she would surely be booed should she attend, and it would give local television stations a reason to run the tape of her putting on the Yankees cap again. Mr. Lazio offered a preview of the political ribbing of Mrs. Clinton when asked if he thought she should attend a game or two. ''The Cubs aren't in it, the White Sox aren't in it -- I don't know why she'd go,'' Mr. Lazio said, smiling as he worked in the mention of the city close to where she grew up.</p>
        <p>That said, there is an argument, several Democrats said, that Mrs. Clinton should just go to the games, early and often, to blunt a week of ''Where's Hillary'' stories in the New York City tabloids (not to mention certain New York City broadsheets).</p>
        <p>And, ultimately, none of it might matter in the end. If there's one thing that both campaigns are convinced of, it is that if there is a Subway Series, no one is going to be paying any attention to either Mr. Lazio or Mrs. Clinton.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
