<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After 44 Years, Another Subway Series</title>
    <meta content="18WED3" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/18/opinion/18WED33.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239733"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001018T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E6DA173EF93BA25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="394" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After 44 Years, Another Subway Series</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial on World Series set between New York Mets and Yankees, first Series between NY teams since 1956; sees Mets pitting their exuberance and unpredictability against Yankees' Series experience and seasoning</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>New York City is back at the center of the baseball universe, where most of its citizens undoubtedly believe it should be. By virtue of the Yankees' thrilling, come-from-behind triumph over the Seattle Mariners last night, following by one day the Mets' victory over the St. Louis Cardinals, New Yorkers can begin obsessing about their first subway Series since 1956, when the Yankees beat the Brooklyn Dodgers in a seven-game World Series that included Don Larsen's perfect game.</p>
        <p>This will be the fourth Series for the Mets in 38 years -- they won in 1969 and 1986 against the Baltimore Orioles and the Boston Red Sox, and lost in 1973 to the Oakland Athletics. It will be the Yankees' fourth Series in five years, and their 37th altogether. So if World Series experience and seasoning are your touchstones, bet the Yankees. But if exuberance and unpredictability are what counts, take the Mets. The Mets are playing spirited baseball right now. True, they played a Cardinals team weakened by the absence of the most feared slugger in the game, Mark McGwire. But essentially the same Cardinals team had swept the Atlanta Braves, and the Mets were able to handle them with ease.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>New York City is back at the center of the baseball universe, where most of its citizens undoubtedly believe it should be. By virtue of the Yankees' thrilling, come-from-behind triumph over the Seattle Mariners last night, following by one day the Mets' victory over the St. Louis Cardinals, New Yorkers can begin obsessing about their first subway Series since 1956, when the Yankees beat the Brooklyn Dodgers in a seven-game World Series that included Don Larsen's perfect game.</p>
        <p>This will be the fourth Series for the Mets in 38 years -- they won in 1969 and 1986 against the Baltimore Orioles and the Boston Red Sox, and lost in 1973 to the Oakland Athletics. It will be the Yankees' fourth Series in five years, and their 37th altogether. So if World Series experience and seasoning are your touchstones, bet the Yankees. But if exuberance and unpredictability are what counts, take the Mets. The Mets are playing spirited baseball right now. True, they played a Cardinals team weakened by the absence of the most feared slugger in the game, Mark McGwire. But essentially the same Cardinals team had swept the Atlanta Braves, and the Mets were able to handle them with ease.</p>
        <p>The Mets' most valuable player was clearly Mike Hampton, a left-handed pitcher who defeated the Cards in games 1 and 5 and pitched 16 shutout innings over the course of those two games. But what makes the Mets interesting is that while they can claim several authentic stars, including Hampton and the catcher Mike Piazza, they find inspiration up and down their lineup, and sometimes in surprising places. The unexpected news in this series was the emergence of Timo Perez, a rookie right fielder who not too long ago was toiling in the lower reaches of the minor leagues, yet always seemed to be on base against the Cardinals.</p>
        <p>For their part, the Yankees have more than history on their side. They seem to have put their season-ending swoon behind them, and they regained some of their old swagger last night with the pitching of Orlando Hernandez and Mariano Rivera and the crushing home run of David Justice. But there is nothing inevitable about these Yankees. And they don't have the town to themselves anymore.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
