<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Islanders Upended in a Matter of Seconds</title>
    <meta content="18ISLE$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/18/sports/18ISLE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239817"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Anaheim Mighty Ducks</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Islanders</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kellner, Jenny</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Anaheim Ducks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Islanders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001018T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05EFDC143EF93BA25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="614" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Islanders Upended in a Matter of Seconds</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNY KELLNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kellner, Jenny</byline>
      <dateline>UNIONDALE, N.Y., Oct. 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anaheim Mighty Ducks defeat New York Islanders, 4-3 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With the Anaheim Mighty Ducks deep in the Islanders' territory on a power play, John Vanbiesbrouck allowed himself the luxury of a quick glance at the scoreboard. The clock showed 15 seconds remaining in the second period.</p>
        <p>For the Islanders, that was too much time.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With the Anaheim Mighty Ducks deep in the Islanders' territory on a power play, John Vanbiesbrouck allowed himself the luxury of a quick glance at the scoreboard. The clock showed 15 seconds remaining in the second period.</p>
        <p>For the Islanders, that was too much time.</p>
        <p>For Teemu Selanne, it was just enough.</p>
        <p>After carrying the puck the length of the ice, Selanne used Islanders defenseman Kenny Jonsson as a screen and scored from the left face-off circle with two seconds remaining in the period to give the Ducks a 4-3 victory over the Islanders tonight before 6,336 at the Nassau Coliseum.</p>
        <p>''Even with a man up, it's a little unnerving to let them come in and make a play like that with 15 seconds left,'' said Vanbiesbrouck, who finished with 28 saves, many of them excellent.</p>
        <p>''I saw him wind up,'' Vanbiesbrouck said of Selanne, but did the goaltender added that he did not see him shoot.</p>
        <p>Jonsson, who was hanging back on the play, took some of the blame while giving Selanne credit.</p>
        <p>''I should have come up,'' Jonsson said. ''It was a great shot by him.''</p>
        <p>The Islanders fell to 0-3-1-0 with the loss, their second straight at home. It also marked the first time since the beginning of the 1995-96 season that they have been without a victory in their first four games. That year, the Islanders started 0-4-1 before winning a game.</p>
        <p>''Look at some of the names on this team.'' Mark Parrish, who scored twice, said. ''It's ridiculous we haven't won a game yet.''</p>
        <p>The Islanders started off aggressively enough, but quickly fell behind 2 minutes 4 seconds into the game when Marty McInnis scored on the first of five Anaheim power plays.</p>
        <p>Parrish scored his first goal of the season at 14:06 of the first period to tie the score at 1-1. He picked up a loose puck in the slot as two Ducks defenders collided and poked it past Guy Hebert for the unassisted goal.</p>
        <p>A little over two minutes later, Oleg Kvasha snared the puck from between Vitaly Vishnevski's skates and beat Hebert from the right side to put the give the Islanders a 2-1 lead. Tim Connolly assisted on the goal with a nice pass to Kvasha, who was moved from center to left wing this week.</p>
        <p>The Ducks tied the score in the second period when Mike Leclerc scored on a give-and-go with McInnis that went over Vanbiesbrouck's shoulder at 6:44.</p>
        <p>Anaheim went ahead, 3-2, after Vanbiesbrouck made a great diving save on Leclerc's shot from 15 feet out, only to have Patrick Traverse pick up the rebound and flip it under the crossbar at 11:05.</p>
        <p>Parrish brought the Islanders back again at 16:55, taking a centering pass from Roman Hamrlik, spinning around in the slot and sending it past Ruslan Salei. But Selanne's goal put the Ducks up for good.</p>
        <p>''I knew there wasn't much time, that's why I wanted to shoot,'' Selanne said of his third goal of the season.</p>
        <p>SLAP SHOTS</p>
        <p>BILL MUCKALT left the game in the first period with a dislocated right shoulder he sustained on a hit from ANDREI NAZAROV. A magnetic resonance imaging test is scheduled for Wednesday, with no prognosis on how long he will be out. Muckalt missed the final 40 games of last season after undergoing surgery to repair a dislocated left shoulder.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
