<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fund Manager, 23 Years Old, Is Arrested on Fraud Charges</title>
    <meta content="Y18HEDG" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/18/business/18HEDG.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239752"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mail Frauds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hedge Funds</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ashbury Capital Partners</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Securities and Exchange Commission</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schiesel, Seth</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yagalla, Mark</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Oberly, Charles M 3d</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hedge Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Futures and Options Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001018T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E5D8173EF93BA25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="460" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fund Manager, 23 Years Old, Is Arrested on Fraud Charges</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SETH SCHIESEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schiesel, Seth</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mark Yagalla, hedge fund manager, is arrested and charged with trying to defraud investors in his fund, Ashbury Capital Partners; Securities and Exchange Commission also files civil fraud complaint against Yagalla and wins court order freezing fund's assets; government contends that Yagalla raised at least $8 million from more than 20 investors, but that when Ashbury had losses, he stopped investing money for fund in June; Charles M Oberly 3d, Yagalla's lawyer, says his client has not yet decided how to plead (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A 23-year-old hedge fund manager was arrested yesterday and charged with trying to defraud investors in his fund, Ashbury Capital Partners, officials said yesterday.</p>
        <p>Mark Yagalla was arrested in Delaware and charged with mail fraud by the United States attorney's office in federal court in Manhattan. The Securities and Exchange Commission also filed a civil fraud complaint against Mr. Yagalla and won a court order freezing the fund's assets.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A 23-year-old hedge fund manager was arrested yesterday and charged with trying to defraud investors in his fund, Ashbury Capital Partners, officials said yesterday.</p>
        <p>Mark Yagalla was arrested in Delaware and charged with mail fraud by the United States attorney's office in federal court in Manhattan. The Securities and Exchange Commission also filed a civil fraud complaint against Mr. Yagalla and won a court order freezing the fund's assets.</p>
        <p>The government contends that Mr. Yagalla raised at least $8 million from more than 20 investors, but when Ashbury had losses he stopped investing money for the fund in June. This summer, the fund, with offices in Greenville, Del., and on Park Avenue in Manhattan, began to send false statements to its investors, the government said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Yagalla also used the fund's money for his own purposes, officials said.</p>
        <p>''It appears that the way he went bad was a combination of trading losses combined with just plain stealing a lot of the money,'' said Wayne M. Carlin, the S.E.C.'s regional director in New York. ''One thing we will need to determine in the course of the case is how much of this money is left.</p>
        <p>''He was using it in a variety of ways to support an extremely lavish personal lifestyle,'' Mr. Carlin added.</p>
        <p>According to one of the government's complaints, Mr. Yagalla was in Las Vegas last week, trying to salvage his fund.</p>
        <p>''Yagalla intended to raise funds to pay back hedge fund investors by selling assets including cars, trucks, jewelry, a helicopter, a limousine company, oil wells, nursing homes and an interest in a horse,'' the complaint said.</p>
        <p>Charles M. Oberly III, Mr. Yagalla's lawyer in Delaware, said his client, who posted bond of $250,000 yesterday, had not yet decided how to plead, and he declined to comment on the accusations.</p>
        <p>''We anticipate that we will cooperate and try to get this matter resolved as best we can,'' Mr. Oberly said.</p>
        <p>According to the government's complaints, Mr. Yagalla and Ashbury solicited investors since at least the summer of 1998 and had described the fund as seeking ''to achieve capital appreciation through a portfolio devoted primarily to short-term trading opportunities in domestic equities.''</p>
        <p>In a letter to investors last month, the fund said it ''continued to remain focused on the 'information revolution' and those stocks tied to the growth of this industry,'' according to one complaint.</p>
        <p>In soliciting potential investors, Mr. Yagalla portrayed himself ''as a successful trader and has boasted that, by trading securities over the last nine years, he has achieved an average of 80 percent return on his investments,'' the S.E.C. said in a statement.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
