<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Torch Singer's Estate May Become a Connecticut Park</title>
    <meta content="18GREE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/18/nyregion/18GREE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239758"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Fairfield County (Conn)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Trust for Public Land</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Herszenhorn, David M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holman, Libby</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001018T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E1D7173EF93BA25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="742" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Torch Singer's Estate May Become a Connecticut Park</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID M. HERSZENHORN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Herszenhorn, David M</byline>
      <dateline>STAMFORD, Conn., Oct. 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Trust For Public Land announces that it has agreed to buy 95 wooded acres surrounding estate known as Treetops in Fairfield County, Conn, that was once owned by torch singer and actress Libby Holman; say land will be preserved as open woodlands next to Mianus State Park; photo; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Claiming a victory against suburban sprawl, government officials and the Trust for Public Land announced today that they had agreed to buy 95 wooded acres surrounding the storied estate here called Treetops, once owned by the torch singer and actress Libby Holman. They said it would be preserved as open woodlands next to Mianus State Park.</p>
        <p>The estate, one of the largest undeveloped parcels in Fairfield County, has been coveted by both builders and preservationists. International Paper, the huge forest products company that owns the property, including the 33-room Treetops house that sits in leafy seclusion near the Stamford-Greenwich border, had been ready to sell to a private developer hoping to build luxury houses.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Claiming a victory against suburban sprawl, government officials and the Trust for Public Land announced today that they had agreed to buy 95 wooded acres surrounding the storied estate here called Treetops, once owned by the torch singer and actress Libby Holman. They said it would be preserved as open woodlands next to Mianus State Park.</p>
        <p>The estate, one of the largest undeveloped parcels in Fairfield County, has been coveted by both builders and preservationists. International Paper, the huge forest products company that owns the property, including the 33-room Treetops house that sits in leafy seclusion near the Stamford-Greenwich border, had been ready to sell to a private developer hoping to build luxury houses.</p>
        <p>The developer, Brickman Associates in New York City, had signed a letter of intent to buy the property. The company's president, Bruce Brickman, vowed today to block the new deal. ''We have a binding letter of intent with International Paper and intend to do everything in our power to enforce it,'' he said. ''If it involves going to court, then we will go to court.''</p>
        <p>Jack Cox, a spokesman for International Paper, said that Brickman Associates had not met certain terms of the letter of intent by an Oct. 2 deadline, allowing the company to pursue another deal.</p>
        <p>Under the deal announced today, International Paper will be paid $11.5 million for 95 acres and a conservation easement over 10 additional acres close to the house. The company will keep the house, which it has been using as a conference center, and five acres immediately surrounding it, with no restrictions on future sales other than existing local zoning laws.</p>
        <p>At a news conference this morning at the Treetops house, the chairman and chief executive of International Paper, John T. Dillon, signed a ceremonial ''compact'' with Gov. John G. Rowland and Tim Northrop, the Connecticut director of the Trust for Public Land, which is a national nonprofit organization dedicated to protecting open space.</p>
        <p>But the document is not a contract of sale. For the deal to go through, the Town of Greenwich must approve spending $3.5 million on the deal and the city of Stamford must approve spending $1.5 million. Also, the Trust for Public Land must complete its effort to raise $3 million in private donations for the purchase. Only the state's contribution, $3.5 million, is fully authorized.</p>
        <p>Lolly Prince, the first selectwoman of Greenwich, expressed confidence that the town would support the spending. ''I know that future generations are going to look back at this time and say we did it right,'' she said. ''I think the citizens of Greenwich have shown their tremendous obligation and tremendous dedication to preserving open space.''</p>
        <p>Although he did not attend the news conference, Mayor Dannel P. Malloy of Stamford has expressed support for preserving the site. And Representative Christopher Shays said that he was confident that city officials would approve the plan. ''The honest fact is that we are seeing continual development,'' Mr. Shays said. ''We need to protect all of the open space we can protect.''</p>
        <p>In 1978, Stamford could have had the property free. The estate of Ms. Holman, who died in 1971, offered it to the city for use as a park and cultural center. But Stamford's finance board did not accept it because of its annual maintenance costs of about $58,000.</p>
        <p>The estate has an elegant and gaudy history. During the 1940's and 50's, parties given by Ms. Holman were attended by celebrities like Elizabeth Taylor, Mike Todd, Truman Capote, Tennessee Williams, Roddy McDowall, Imogene Coca and Martha Raye.</p>
        <p>The property is also the site of an annual spring daffodil show. Ms. Holman planted thousands of the flowers and the corporate owners have opened the estate one weekend a year to let the public see the blooms.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
