<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'Blood Is Boiling' in West Bank and Gaza</title>
    <meta content="Y18ISR$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/18/world/18ISRA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239740"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="WHOSE HOLY LAND?: ISRAEL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">West Bank</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Gaza Strip</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Bethlehem (West Bank)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Orme, William A Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greenberg, Joel</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Gaza Strip</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/West Bank</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001018T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7D9173EF93BA25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1036" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'Blood Is Boiling' in West Bank and Gaza</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM A. ORME Jr. and JOEL GREENBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Orme, William A Jr; Greenberg, Joel</byline>
      <dateline>JERUSALEM, Oct. 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Israeli soldiers continue to battle Palestinians throughout West Bank and Gaza Strip; critics on both sides deride provisional truce; at least one Palestinian policeman is killed in cross-fire at crossing to Gaza; dozens are hurt in clash between mourners at funeral for Bethlehem youth shot by Israeli soldiers and soldiers posted outside Jewish holy site; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Israeli soldiers continued to battle Palestinians throughout the West Bank and the Gaza Strip today, and critics on both sides derided a provisional truce.</p>
        <p>There were violent confrontations near the main crossing points from Israel into the West Bank near Bethlehem and into the Gaza Strip.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Israeli soldiers continued to battle Palestinians throughout the West Bank and the Gaza Strip today, and critics on both sides derided a provisional truce.</p>
        <p>There were violent confrontations near the main crossing points from Israel into the West Bank near Bethlehem and into the Gaza Strip.</p>
        <p>At least one Palestinian policeman was killed in cross-fire at the Erez checkpoint, a crossing to Gaza, while mourners at a funeral for a 14-year-old Bethlehem youth clashed afterward with soldiers posted outside Rachel's Tomb, a Jewish holy site, in an exchange that wounded dozens.</p>
        <p>The youth, Muayed Jawareesh, who died this morning, was shot in the head on Monday when Israeli troops fired on rock-throwing rioters near his home in a Bethlehem refugee camp. He is one of at least 20 minors among the more than 100 people killed in the violence, all but 7 of them Arabs.</p>
        <p>''The people are rebelling,'' said Jawdat Odeh, 30, a construction worker who watched the boy's flag-draped body carried through his neighborhood. ''Their blood is boiling. They won't listen to Arafat. What did we get from this summit? Nothing.''</p>
        <p>But Danny Yatom, Prime Minister Ehud Barak's top security adviser, said this afternoon that it was too early to judge whether the tentative truce would take hold.</p>
        <p>''Regaining control over all of the incidents and the acts of violence by the Palestinian Authority is liable to take some time, but we don't have a lot of time,'' he said. ''We are going to have to see results on the ground within a very short period.''</p>
        <p>There were episodes of violence today that both sides saw as potentially explosive. A Palestinian farm worker was shot dead by Jewish settlers near Nablus in the West Bank, an area where militant settlers live close to volatile Palestinian neighborhoods.</p>
        <p>And an Israeli policeman near Gilo, a Jewish neighborhood in Jerusalem, was critically wounded by gunfire from a nearby Palestinian neighborhood. Much of that neighborhood was evacuated tonight as Israeli tank crews responded with machine-gun bursts. ''It's the first test of the agreement, and it failed,'' said Mayor Ehud Olmert of Jerusalem, who rushed to the scene. ''In the first hours after the agreement, we see an escalation in the most sensitive place in Jerusalem.''</p>
        <p>In Nablus, two Jewish settlers suspected of involvement in the killing there were detained for questioning tonight, the Israeli police said.</p>
        <p>Under the terms announced by President Clinton in Egypt today, Mr. Barak and the Palestinian leader, Yasir Arafat, both pledged to call for an end to the violent hostilities. By late evening, neither had made such an unequivocal public appeal.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Barak issued a statement saying he had ordered Israeli security forces ''to do everything required'' to carry out the agreement and to ''take great care to halt the violence and prevent additional loss of life.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Arafat, in brief remarks to Voice of Palestine radio upon his return to Gaza today, said the success of the agreement would depend on Israel's ''accurate and honest implementation'' of the accord.</p>
        <p>Israeli Army spokesmen said that within several hours the army would lift its ban on travel between major Palestinians cities, and by morning would reopen the border between Egypt and the Gaza Strip. Israeli and Palestinian intelligence officers are to meet tonight to renew their security cooperation, the spokesmen said.</p>
        <p>But they said the military would wait 48 hours before withdrawing forces from major flash points and reopening crossings into Israel from the Palestinian territories -- and would open them then only if Mr. Arafat issued and enforced a call to halt rioting and armed attacks against Israelis.</p>
        <p>''The only way to stop this is for Arafat himself to go on TV or the radio and say clearly and loudly that it should stop,'' said Shlomo Dror, a spokesman for Israeli forces in Gaza and the West Bank.</p>
        <p>Few Palestinians expected to hear a direct appeal from Mr. Arafat. ''Arafat won't make a statement himself,'' Khalil Shikaki, a prominent Palestinian political analyst, predicted. ''He will avoid taking direct responsibility.''</p>
        <p>And many said a public call for calm from the Palestinian leader would not have the impact that Israeli and American officials anticipated. Marwan Barghouti, the West Bank leader of the Fatah militia faction, which Israel holds responsible for most of the armed attacks against its soldiers in that area, declared this afternoon that the street protests would continue until there were signs of resolution of the underlying territorial conflict between Israelis and Palestinians.</p>
        <p>''This summit failed in its reading of the real reasons behind the explosion of this intifada,'' he said in a telephone interview, ''which is the disappointment of the Palestinian public in the peace process and the continuation of occupation.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Barghouti, whose organization is planning demonstrations against the agreeement, refused to say how he and his estimated 2,000 armed followers would respond to a direct order from Mr. Arafat, the leader of Al Fatah, to end the protests.</p>
        <p>Other Fatah activists were less circumspect. Mr. Arafat ''cannot stop the Palestinian street,'' said Husam Khader, a Palestinian legislator from Al Fatah. ''Our intention in Fatah is to escalate confrontation. The street is leading the confrontation, and not officials sitting in their ivory chairs.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Barak's opponents on the Israeli right rejected his renewed appeal for the formation of a ''national emergency'' government with the rightist Likud Party. If the truce holds, they said, there will no longer be an emergency, and if it does not, there should be new elections.</p>
        <p>''Prime Minister Barak needs to be replaced and not saved,''said Limor Livnat, a Likud member of Parliament.</p>
        <p>WHOSE HOLY LAND?: ISRAEL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
