<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mets Fans in the Bronx? Not in Yankee Territory</title>
    <meta content="18CURR$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/18/sports/18CURR.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239823"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Curry, Jack</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001018T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902EEDC143EF93BA25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="738" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mets Fans in the Bronx? Not in Yankee Territory</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jack Curry</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Curry, Jack</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>On Baseball column discusses lack of New York Mets fans at Yankee Stadium during New York Yankees game (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There was a misty rain pelting Yankee Stadium as dozens of hopeful fans gathered outside the players entrance yesterday afternoon. The first pitch was still four hours away, but the fans turned giddy when David Justice nodded to them; they were even excited that Luis Polonia walked within 50 feet of them.</p>
        <p>It was early, but everywhere anyone looked there was nothing but Yankees paraphernalia. Caps, jackets, sweatshirts, T-shirts and even socks. It was all Yankees all the time. They shouted on cue to the television cameras, and Armando Algarin held a sign that said, ''Flushing. How appropriate.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There was a misty rain pelting Yankee Stadium as dozens of hopeful fans gathered outside the players entrance yesterday afternoon. The first pitch was still four hours away, but the fans turned giddy when David Justice nodded to them; they were even excited that Luis Polonia walked within 50 feet of them.</p>
        <p>It was early, but everywhere anyone looked there was nothing but Yankees paraphernalia. Caps, jackets, sweatshirts, T-shirts and even socks. It was all Yankees all the time. They shouted on cue to the television cameras, and Armando Algarin held a sign that said, ''Flushing. How appropriate.''</p>
        <p>After about 15 minutes of studying these soggy fans and listening to them berate the Mets more than the Mariners, a curious assignment was proposed: Find a fan bold enough to wear a Mets cap and celebrate his joy by infiltrating enemy territory.</p>
        <p>When a police officer was asked how far a reporter would have to walk to find a Met fan, he said, ''Flushing.''</p>
        <p>Would it really be that difficult? Surely, there would be someone wearing blue and orange. Surely, there are some fans of Mike Piazza who hang out in the Bronx. The quest started, with no plans to journey to Queens. The hope was that one trip around the streets of the Stadium, home plate and back, would yield at least one Met fan.</p>
        <p>The kiosks alongside Yankee Stadium offered no help to a Mets fan trying to show his support. The vendors sold caps, shirts and bobble-head dolls, but did not offer one Mets item. When the Yankees play the Mets in the World Series, the vendors will only stock souvenirs that feature the Mets with the Yankees.</p>
        <p>''It's Yankee Stadium,'' Mark Laboy said. ''We're not selling Mets stuff. I'm a Mets fan. I'd wear a Met hat, but I've got to wear this uniform.''</p>
        <p>Tommy Voudouris, his friend, quickly said, ''You wouldn't wear a Met hat,'' and that eliminated Laboy from consideration as a Mets fan. Laboy might be a Mets fan, but he was a closet Mets fan and that did not suffice.</p>
        <p>The quest continued, past the man in the wool New York Rangers hat, past the man wearing the New Jersey Devils Stanley Cup hat and past the guy with the soiled Vancouver Grizzlies cap. The jaunt was halfway over and the Braves, the Rangers, the Devils and the Grizzlies all had more representation at the Stadium than the Mets. The same cop offered a lifeline.</p>
        <p>''Why don't you put on a Mets hat?'' he said. ''Then do a story on that.''</p>
        <p>Terrific idea. For someone else. At Pro Cap Dugout, where only baseball caps are sold, there were 600 on display. There were Yankees caps in 15 colors and even one style with the Chinese letters for ''NY'' on the front. But there were no Mets caps.</p>
        <p>Next door at Stan's Sports World, you could buy shirts, shorts, underwear, caps, jackets and jerseys with the Yankees logo and you could even buy a Boston Red Sox pennant. But there were only two lonely racks of Mets caps, practically hidden in a corner of the store.</p>
        <p>''I can't sell Ventura and Piazza shirts,'' said Steve Martucci, the owner. ''There would be a riot.''</p>
        <p>Maybe the cop was right. Maybe this reporter should have worn a Mets cap and described the reaction. The $23 investment could go on an expense statement, and the company provides health insurance in case any injuries were sustained.</p>
        <p>Before that became a necessity, a vision appeared. There he was. The first fan wearing a Mets cap and strolling confidently on River Avenue. His name was Jeffrey Mestrandrea and he was joined by his mother, Judith, who wore a Yankees jersey with No. 14 on the back in honor of Lou Piniella.</p>
        <p>Mestrandrea said it would be foolish for any Yankee fans to be offended by his wearing a Mets cap. His mother, who once sneaked down near the dugout to kiss Piniella, blamed Jeffrey's devotion to the Mets on being a middle child and having blue eyes. They are eager for the Subway Series to start here on Saturday night and wondering who will gloat at breakfast the next morning.</p>
        <p>''If the Mets win, I'll get whatever I want,'' Jeffrey Mestrandrea said. ''I'll have a buffet with pancakes and eggs. If the Mets lose, I'll have Grape Nuts and tea. And I really hate Grape Nuts.''</p>
        <p>ON BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
