<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tyson and Golota: Protect Yourself at All Times</title>
    <meta content="18FITE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/18/sports/18FITE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239721"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BOXING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001018T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07EFDC173EF93BA25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="790" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tyson and Golota: Protect Yourself at All Times</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL PENNINGTON</byline>
      <dateline>AUBURN HILLS, Mich., Oct. 17</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Most major heavyweight fights are promoted with a catchy nickname or slogan that is splashed across every billboard for the bout. No one has bothered to do that for Friday's Mike Tyson-Andrew Golota fight.</p>
        <p>What would it say?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Most major heavyweight fights are promoted with a catchy nickname or slogan that is splashed across every billboard for the bout. No one has bothered to do that for Friday's Mike Tyson-Andrew Golota fight.</p>
        <p>What would it say?</p>
        <p>Come see the knockout, or the disqualification -- or maybe both!</p>
        <p>Or one bites ears, the other hits below the belt -- and they get to punch each other, too!</p>
        <p>If there was any doubt about what is the attraction for this fight, it was summed up by Al Certo, the trainer for the 6-foot-5-inch, 250-pound Golota. ''If Tyson does fight dirty,'' Certo said, ''Golota might pick him up and body slam him or throw him out of the ring.''</p>
        <p>It is this potential for something way out of bounds that brings a certain uneasy fascination -- and edginess -- to the fight, which will be staged at the Palace in Auburn Hills, Mich., because the Roman Colosseum stopped accepting such spectacles centuries ago.</p>
        <p>At today's final official news conference for the pay-per-view bout, Tyson was unusually relaxed and lighthearted, though he did snarl at Golota, who was seated at an adjacent table wearing dark sunglasses.</p>
        <p>''He's a little boy to me,'' Tyson said. ''He's scared to death of me.''</p>
        <p>Asked how long he expected the fight to last, Tyson answered, ''However long it takes to kill somebody.''</p>
        <p>Golota, for his part, joked about his reputation for hitting low. He said he couldn't hit below the belt Friday night because the 5-10 Tyson was too short. ''It's physically impossible for me to throw a punch that low,'' Golota said.</p>
        <p>When asked what he would do if Tyson, who twice bit Evander Holyfield, hit another opponent after the bell and decked the referee in his last fight, started employing shady ring tactics, Golota said, ''I will kick the referee.''</p>
        <p>The biggest news today was the admission by Tyson's handlers that their fighter has changed his anti-depressant medication. Tyson had been taking Zoloft, which, in his last public appearance in September, he blamed for some of his recent erratic behavior. Tyson has switched to an unidentified medicine, something that the Michigan state boxing commission has cleared because it has sanctioned the fight.</p>
        <p>Today, Tyson was generally playful and cheery. ''I feel good, it's great to be here in the city where Joe Louis fought,'' Tyson, whose ring record is 48-3 with 42 knockouts, said. ''Some people can make fun of this fight. It's very serious business to me. Decorum, that's the word I'm looking for. It's going to be a great fight.''</p>
        <p>Tyson only snapped once in his interchange with reporters, when a local television reporter, who is white, asked Tyson about his history of fouls and rough tactics in the ring.</p>
        <p>''I've never done anything he's never done in the ring,'' Tyson said. ''Why don't you ask him, white boy? People say I'm a racist. I feel like you're a racist. You're picking on me. Why don't you ask him? I'm serious, you all know I'm insecure about that.''</p>
        <p>And Tyson still laced his comments with the kind of harsh and profane language he customarily uses. ''He's going to pay,'' Tyson said of Golota. ''I plan a lot of hurt for him. I really want to show him that right now, but I have to wait a few days. I fear no one with a knife or a gun or anything.''</p>
        <p>Golota's unpredictable ring history -- he declined to continue fighting Michael Grant in the 10th round of a 1999 bout he was winning -- does not concern Tyson. Asked if he thought Golota, who has a 36-4 record with 29 knockouts, had the heart of champion fighter, Tyson said: ''I don't know; that's his problem. I'm not here for psychology.''</p>
        <p>Golota, meanwhile, continued to play the role of the jester, which fit the setting.</p>
        <p>''Yeah, sure, I'm afraid before every fight,'' he said facetiously. ''There's no doubt some guys have been intimidated by Tyson. They've been intimidated before they ever got in the ring. But not me. As long as Tyson doesn't bring any voodoo into the ring, I will be all right.''</p>
        <p>Golota has needed his sense of humor.</p>
        <p>When he arrived to train in a suburban Detroit gym on Monday, a banner greeted him outside the facility.</p>
        <p>It welcomed Andrew Golata.</p>
        <p>An ''o'' was quickly scribbled over the ''a'' in Golota's name.</p>
        <p>BOXING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
