<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Getting Involved Up to His Neck</title>
    <meta content="MB005135" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239818"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TV NOTES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carter, Bill</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kelley, David E</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Boston Public (TV Program)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Ally Mcbeal (TV Program)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Practice, the (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001018T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906EFDC143EF93BA25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="691" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Getting Involved Up to His Neck</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL CARTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Carter, Bill</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>David E Kelley comments on work he is doing on his three shows this television season, Boston Public, Ally McBeal and The Practice (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Another television season is under way, and David E. Kelley is back at the salt mine, otherwise known as the desk where he writes scripts in longhand for all his television series.</p>
        <p>That means three shows this season, as it did last fall, with one major difference. Mr. Kelley is much more personally invested in his new series, ''Boston Public,'' than he ever was in ''Snoops,'' a detective show that quickly failed last season.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Another television season is under way, and David E. Kelley is back at the salt mine, otherwise known as the desk where he writes scripts in longhand for all his television series.</p>
        <p>That means three shows this season, as it did last fall, with one major difference. Mr. Kelley is much more personally invested in his new series, ''Boston Public,'' than he ever was in ''Snoops,'' a detective show that quickly failed last season.</p>
        <p>''I learned something from 'Snoops,' '' Mr. Kelley said in a telephone interview. ''I have to be more involved with a show before I can put it up for adoption.''</p>
        <p>And so, Mr. Kelley said, he expects to write ''at least the first six or seven episodes'' of ''Boston Public.'' This high school drama will have its premiere on Monday at 8 on Fox.</p>
        <p>Of course, at the same time, Mr. Kelley finds himself needing to inject new life into ''Ally McBeal,'' his Emmy Award-winning comedy hit --  which showed distinct signs of wearing out its quirky appeal last season -- while also keeping up the quality of ''The Practice,'' his Emmy Award-winning drama on ABC.</p>
        <p>''I am split three ways,'' he said, ''though maybe I'm spending a little more time with 'Boston Public' because we're just getting started.''</p>
        <p>It would be difficult to spend more time on a series than he intends to on ''Ally McBeal,'' however. ''Because of the distinct voice that show requires,'' Mr. Kelley said, ''I'll probably write most if not all of them this season.'' So far Mr. Kelley has been the sole writer or the co-writer of every episode in the three seasons of ''Ally McBeal.''</p>
        <p>His plans for ''Ally'' took a sharp turn in mid-August when the actor Robert Downey Jr. was released from prison and then within days it was announced that he would become the new love interest for Calista Flockhart on the series.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kelley credited Pam Wisne, the president of his production company, for pursuing the actor, a pursuit, he said, that actually began before Mr. Downey even went to prison. Mr. Downey was released in August after serving one year of a three-year sentence on drug charges and he was signed to ''Ally'' a week later.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Kelley said he had three scripts completed by the time he knew Mr. Downey would be added to the cast. So he rewrote several scenes in the show's premiere -- next Monday at 9 on Fox -- to introduce Mr. Downey. He will not be prominent in the show until the fourth episode.</p>
        <p>''We knew we needed to see Ally in a relationship,'' Mr. Kelley said. But a long search for an actor who could stand up to Ms. Flockhart had proved fruitless until Mr. Downey was -- literally -- freed up.</p>
        <p>''We had to have someone who could go toe to toe with Calista in scenes, somebody who can do comedy and drama,'' Mr. Kelley said. ''Good luck trying to find an actor like that. They all have film careers.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Downey has exceeded expectations, Mr. Kelley said: ''He can sing; he can dance. He's perfect for our show.''</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Mr. Kelley is devoting another part of his brain to ''Boston Public,'' which he said differs from his others by being ''much less plot driven.'' The high school arena, unlike the courtroom, brings with it no inherent head-to-head conflict situations.</p>
        <p>''Not that the series is really like a novel,'' Mr. Kelley said, ''but the show is more like a novel than anything else I've done. There is less exposition. Much more happens with the characters. So I've had to keep filling them in and giving them histories as I go along.''</p>
        <p>As for the workload, Mr. Kelley, who said he writes the shows on separate days, said, ''I still like going to work.''</p>
        <p>BILL CARTER</p>
        <p>TV NOTES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
