<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>2 Senate Candidates Eagerly Woo Moderates</title>
    <meta content="Y18FLO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/18/politics/18FLOR.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239726"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: A FLORIDA RACE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Florida</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bragg, Rick</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccollum, Bill (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nelson, Bill (Comr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001018T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE3DB173EF93BA25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1138" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>2 Senate Candidates Eagerly Woo Moderates</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICK BRAGG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bragg, Rick</byline>
      <dateline>MIAMI, Oct. 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Republican Rep Bill McCollum and Democrat Bill Nelson woo moderate voters in Florida United States Senate race by trying to push opponent away from ideological center; Nelson, known as moderate, often labels McCollum as extremist, while McCollum, who has won approval mostly from conservatives, paints rival as liberal; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The nominees for United States Senate here in Florida are grappling for votes from the ideological center by trying to shove each other away from it, the Democrat pushing the Republican farther to the right, the Republican nudging the Democrat toward the left.</p>
        <p>It has made for a sometimes nasty contest in one of the year's most closely watched races, where two political veterans seek to fill the vacancy opened by the retirement of a two-term Republican incumbent, Senator Connie Mack.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The nominees for United States Senate here in Florida are grappling for votes from the ideological center by trying to shove each other away from it, the Democrat pushing the Republican farther to the right, the Republican nudging the Democrat toward the left.</p>
        <p>It has made for a sometimes nasty contest in one of the year's most closely watched races, where two political veterans seek to fill the vacancy opened by the retirement of a two-term Republican incumbent, Senator Connie Mack.</p>
        <p>The Democratic nominee, Bill Nelson, former six-term member of the House and now state insurance commissioner, often labels the Republican, Representative Bill McCollum, who has served in the House for 20 years, an extremist who would sacrifice the elderly, the poor and the  working class to coddle the rich.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCollum, in turn, paints Mr. Nelson as a liberal who would ''tax everything that moves, and some things that don't.''</p>
        <p>In this hardly unique strategy of digging for votes in the middle, Mr. Nelson may have the advantage, because, political experts say, he has much less distance to cover along the spectrum.</p>
        <p>As a congressman, ''he was known as a fairly moderate Democrat,'' said Aubrey Jewitt, a professor of political science at the University of Central Florida, ''and right now that's a good ideological place to be.''</p>
        <p>Mr. McCollum, by contrast, has consistently won approval mostly from conservative Republicans, on  issues like abortion and gun control.</p>
        <p>The race here is crucial to national Democrats' hopes of narrowing the margin of the Republican advantage in the Senate, or perhaps even regaining control there. And a recent statewide survey conducted for The St. Petersburg Times by Schroth &amp; Associates, a polling firm based in Washington, found Mr. Nelson ahead of Mr. McCollum, 45 percent to 34 percent.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nelson, of Melbourne, enjoys name recognition around Florida, having run for statewide office four times, unlike Mr. McCollum, of Longwood, near Orlando, who is in his first statewide race.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCollum did gain attention as one of the House impeachment prosecutors who made the case for conviction of President Clinton before the Senate. And at one point he was expected to receive a lift from the presidential campaign of Gov. George W. Bush, brother of Florida's governor, Jeb Bush, and initially considered the solid favorite to lay claim to the state's 25 electoral votes. But  the Bush campaign has had to fight hard to try to hold off a strong Florida effort by Vice President Al Gore.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCollum concedes that he would have been helped had Mr. Bush led strongly throughout the race and then gone on to win here ''by 10 or 12 points.'' But, he adds, he never planned to run on Mr. Bush's momentum.</p>
        <p>''We're running our own race,'' he said. ''We have to educate the voters on who I am,'' and on the difference between himself and Mr. Nelson.</p>
        <p>''I believe in better government, not bigger government,'' Mr. McCollum continued. ''He believes in bigger government, more taxation and control over people's lives.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Nelson readily acknowledges that he has been helped, and his opponent hurt, by Mr. Gore's good fortunes here.</p>
        <p>''This was going to be a walk for Bush,'' Mr. Nelson said, and if that had happened, ''I knew it was going to be difficult. It makes me a little more comfortable knowing Al Gore is doing so well.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Nelson said that his opponent  had no choice but to paint him as  ''liberal, liberal, liberal'' but that ''that's not my record.'' At the same time, Mr. Nelson said, ''he's trying to make himself into a raging moderate.''</p>
        <p>Television advertisements do  show Mr. McCollum appealing to moderates, saying he is much closer than Mr. Nelson to their ideals.</p>
        <p>Those commercials show the candidate tieless. ''He's trying to portray a more casual image,'' Dario Moreno, a professor of political science at Florida International University, said of Mr. McCollum, whom  voters have described as too stiff, too brittle, too judgmental.</p>
        <p>The two combatants represented neighboring districts as young congressmen back in the 1980's, and voted alike more than half the time.</p>
        <p>But by the time Mr. Nelson left the House in 1990 to run for governor, unsuccessfully, Mr. McCollum had long been compiling a solidly conservative record, and not just on social issues. As a member of a committee that investigated the Iran-contra affair, he found nothing wrong in the actions of the Reagan administration. He would go on to harshly criticize the Clinton administration's handling of the attack on the Branch Davidian compound near Waco, Tex., and to vigorously seek the impeachment and removal of Mr. Clinton, an outcome that, polls found, a majority of Florida voters did not want.</p>
        <p>''I played a role I was assigned,'' Mr. McCollum says now of his task as an impeachment prosecutor, ''and I'm proud of the role I was assigned.  Character, integrity and principles do matter.''</p>
        <p>But nether he nor Mr. Nelson has  talked much about impeachment during the campaign; polls have also shown that people are tired of hearing about it.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nelson and Mr. McCollum side with their parties' presidential nominees on most issues: the environment, the economy, education, abortion and more. Mr. McCollum backs  Mr. Bush's plan to apply a big part of the federal budget surplus to a $1.3 trillion tax cut; Mr. Nelson favors a $500 billion cut similar to the one proposed by Mr. Gore.</p>
        <p>Although both men say they like to talk about the issues, they spend a great deal of time talking about each other. Mr. McCollum has accused Mr. Nelson, as insurance commissioner, of allowing premiums in Florida to skyrocket in the aftermath of  Hurricane Andrew, and Mr. Nelson has shot back, noting that an arbitration panel created by the Republican-controlled Legislature has final say on insurance-rate increases.</p>
        <p>''Mr. McCollum's friends insist on an arbitration panel,'' Mr. Nelson said in a debate in Delray Beach, ''and what they're doing is sticking it to the consumers.''</p>
        <p>And although talk of impeachment has been set aside, that is not to say  Mr. Clinton's name never emerges.  In recent e-mail to his supporters, Mr. McCollum wrote that ''with the exception of Hillary's New York race, my defeat is Bill Clinton's highest political priority.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton has in fact raised money for Mr. Nelson, and stumped for him against Mr. McCollum. Campaign experts say it is not personal. Just politics.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: A FLORIDA RACE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
