<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Playful Souvenir on the Petit Four Plate: The Lollipop</title>
    <meta content="18TEMP$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/18/living/18TEMP.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239692"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TIDBIT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Candy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lollipops</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clark, Melissa</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Candy</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001018T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DEED7163EF93BA25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="501" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Playful Souvenir on the Petit Four Plate: The Lollipop</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MELISSA CLARK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Clark, Melissa</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Melissa Clark on lollipops in unexpected flavors available at several New York City shopes; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE petit four plate is a chef's last chance to dazzle, and most take it very seriously, serving the tiniest, most precise tartlets and truffles. But a few chefs, all within a block or two of each other in Midtown, are getting whimsical as well, sending out the most childish of treats just before the very grown-up check.</p>
        <p>The lollipop is the new kid in Midtown. And it's more than just a sweet: it's a memento of a meal.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE petit four plate is a chef's last chance to dazzle, and most take it very seriously, serving the tiniest, most precise tartlets and truffles. But a few chefs, all within a block or two of each other in Midtown, are getting whimsical as well, sending out the most childish of treats just before the very grown-up check.</p>
        <p>The lollipop is the new kid in Midtown. And it's more than just a sweet: it's a memento of a meal.</p>
        <p>Alain Ducasse, at his restaurant on Central Park South, includes leaf-shaped, citrus-flavored lollipops on the candy cart rolled to the table with caramel nut toffees, madeleines, fruit jellies and nougats. Mr. Ducasse said he began serving lollipops in his Paris restaurant about a year and a half ago for nostalgic reasons: he loved them as a child. Like the brioche handed to patrons as they leave, he said, ''the lollipop is a souvenir, prolonging the moment shared with us.''</p>
        <p>Julian Alonzo, the chef at Brasserie 8 1/2 on West 57th Street, began making savory ''lollipops'' out of partly boned chicken wings, as a garnish for potato-garlic soup. Now, he makes more traditional circular candies in flavors like cherry, spearmint and lime.</p>
        <p>Mr. Alonzo said most diners at lunch take the lollipops with them, sometimes asking for extras to share. But at night, he said, it's not unusual to find people sucking lollipops at the bar, like a cigarette substitute.</p>
        <p>Nathan Ellis, a diner at Brasserie 8 1/2, said he liked the lollipops as ''a little contrast.''</p>
        <p>''I'm sitting there in this very designed, modern space,'' he said, ''and I'm sucking on a 5-cent lollipop.''</p>
        <p>At Sono, on East 57th Street, lollipops are made in flavors reflecting the Japanese-fusion menu, like green tea, cinnamon-clove and yuzu. Diners get them free at lunch, but they are also for sale, two for $1.</p>
        <p>All the chefs make lollipops essentially the same way, by boiling down sugar syrup and cooling it in a mold. Christine Chang, the pastry chef at Sono, adds fruit, spice and tea reductions to the syrup. At Ducasse, lemon or orange zest is infused into the syrup. Brasserie 8 1/2 adds natural extracts.</p>
        <p>These suckers at least resemble the children's kind. The lollipops David Burke makes at ONEc.p.s., in the Plaza Hotel, are definitely for adults only. His version, soft mounds on white sticks, is made of smoked salmon. For private parties, he uses goat cheese. Or foie gras.</p>
        <p>TIDBIT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
