<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Accord by Auction Houses Is Still Unsigned</title>
    <meta content="Y18AUCT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/18/business/18AUCT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239734"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sotheby's</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Christie's</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kaplan, Lewis A (Judge)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vogel, Carol</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001018T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E5DA173EF93BA25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="422" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Accord by Auction Houses Is Still Unsigned</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAROL VOGEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Vogel, Carol</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sotheby's and Christie's auction houses, which agreed a month ago to pay $512 million to settle claims that they cheated buyers and sellers by fixing commission fees, are ordered to appear in court to explain why they have not yet signed final settlement papers; there is speculation that difficulties have emerged that have delayed agreement (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Nearly a month after agreeing to pay $512 million to settle claims that they cheated buyers and sellers by fixing commission fees, Sotheby's and Christie's auction houses still have not signed the final settlement papers, and the judge in the case has ordered them to appear in court Monday to explain why.</p>
        <p>Antitrust lawyers say it is rare for this length of time to go by without a signing, raising speculation that difficulties have emerged that have delayed the agreement.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Nearly a month after agreeing to pay $512 million to settle claims that they cheated buyers and sellers by fixing commission fees, Sotheby's and Christie's auction houses still have not signed the final settlement papers, and the judge in the case has ordered them to appear in court Monday to explain why.</p>
        <p>Antitrust lawyers say it is rare for this length of time to go by without a signing, raising speculation that difficulties have emerged that have delayed the agreement.</p>
        <p>Matthew Weigman, a spokesman for Sotheby's, said yesterday, however, that the auction house ''is working diligently towards submitting the required papers and we expect they will be filed by Oct. 23.'' Andree Corroon, a spokeswoman for Christie's, declined to comment. Boies, Schiller &amp; Flexner, the lead law firm for the roughly 120,000 auction house customers in the class-action suit, also declining to comment.</p>
        <p>Several lawyers close to the case said they believed that two class-action suits filed on behalf of foreign buyers and sellers had been holding up a resolution. The suits, which have been challenged by the Boies firm, open the possibility that the settlement will not close the door on further payments from the case.</p>
        <p>The initial agreement was reached on Sept. 21. In an order signed yesterday, Judge Lewis A. Kaplan of the Federal District Court in Manhattan noted that he had been advised that settlement papers would be signed shortly after that. That he has not received them, he wrote, ''suggests that the parties in fact have not reached agreement.''</p>
        <p>In yesterday's order, he said that if the papers were not signed by Monday he would hold a conference and consider resuming discovery proceedings in the case and reinstating a February trial date.</p>
        <p>Both houses have been embroiled in a federal criminal antitrust investigation which heated up earlier this year when Christie's turned over critical documents outlining collusion in the setting of commission fees. After providing the documents, the company received conditional amnesty from prosecution.</p>
        <p>Earlier this month Sotheby's and its former chief executive, Diana D. Brooks, pleaded guilty to conspiring to violate antitrust laws. Sotheby's agreed to pay a $45 million fine in addition to its obligation in the civil suit. Ms. Brooks faces a possible prison sentence and a large fine. She has agreed to cooperate in a continuing investigation of A. Alfred Taubman, Sotheby's largest shareholder and former chairman.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
