<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Transit Strike in Los Angeles Is Resolved With New Contract</title>
    <meta content="Y18TRA$12" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/18/national/18TRAN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239793"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Los Angeles (Calif)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Transportation Union</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Whitaker, Barbara</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jackson, Jesse L (Rev)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/Los Angeles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001018T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E6DD143EF93BA25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="686" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Transit Strike in Los Angeles Is Resolved With New Contract</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA WHITAKER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Whitaker, Barbara</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, Oct. 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>United Transportation Union members ratify three-year pact with Los Angeles transit system, ending monthlong strike; Metropolitan Transit Authority board unanimously approves pact; Rev Jesse Jackson, who fostered intense talks, comments, news conference; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Buses were scheduled to begin running here on Wednesday morning after both sides in a monthlong transit strike approved an agreement that negotiators had reached early today.</p>
        <p>The strike had shut down the nation's second-largest bus system and stranded hundreds of thousands of commuters.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Buses were scheduled to begin running here on Wednesday morning after both sides in a monthlong transit strike approved an agreement that negotiators had reached early today.</p>
        <p>The strike had shut down the nation's second-largest bus system and stranded hundreds of thousands of commuters.</p>
        <p>Members of the United Transportation Union ratified the three-year contract with the Metropolitan Transit Authority in a vote late tonight. The M.T.A. board unanimously approved the agreement this afternoon. Details of the agreement were to be made public later. .</p>
        <p>''Our goal from the outset was to achieve $23 million in cost savings over the next three years through this contract and we have accomplished that,'' Gary Wosk, a spokesman for the M.T.A., said. ''It's a good situation for our bus operators and also for the taxpayers, who can look forward to expanded service.''</p>
        <p>The sides reached agreement after intense negotiations, fostered by the Rev. Jesse Jackson, that stretched from Monday into early today.</p>
        <p>''We were down to overtime,'' Mr. Jackson said at a news conference where the deal was announced. ''We had just about given up after all night long, then we were awakened this morning by some angel that blessed us out of somewhere with a fresh start, a fresh idea and we shared it with M.T.A. leadership.''</p>
        <p>The union, which represents roughly 4,300 bus drivers and rail operators, had been on strike since Sept. 16. In that period an estimated 450,000 daily riders, mostly the poor and elderly, were left to find alternative transportation, frequently costly and inconvenient, to get to work.</p>
        <p>Bus service was expected to be at 85 percent on Wednesday and full service on Thursday. Train service was to begin on Thursday, allowing time to prepare the stations and electrify the tracks, Mr. Wosk said.</p>
        <p>The union and the M.T.A. had been at odds over proposals by the M.T.A. to reduce overtime pay -- which can add $20,000 to $50,000 to a driver's annual income -- and add part-time workers. The M.T.A. suggested the changes to deal with a $438 million operations deficit that is projected over the next 10 years.</p>
        <p>But on Monday, as the strike came under the scrutiny of state legislators from Los Angeles County in a special hearing, it was suggested that the agency had saved $20 million to $25 million in fuel, pay and other expenses as a result of the strike. M.T.A. executives did not dispute that, but countered that loss of fare revenues, added security and special bus lines had cost the agency $10 million to $15 million. At the hearing,  it was also disclosed that the M.T.A. had paid nearly $1 million for a public relations effort during the strike and more than $1 million for labor consultants.</p>
        <p>But all that seemed forgotten today as both sides concentrated on getting the agreement approved.</p>
        <p>Goldy Norton, a spokesman for the union, said he was confident that the drivers would approve the deal, saying, ''Our general committee believes it will provide the protections our members need during the entire term of the contract.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Wosk said M.T.A. officials were ''just glad it's all over,'' adding: ''I'm sure it comes as a great relief to the 450,000 people who depend on our services every day. They've gone through a lot.''</p>
        <p>Maria Lopez, a domestic worker who lives in the San Fernando Valley, agreed.</p>
        <p>''It's been very hard,'' Ms. Lopez said, waiting for a ride in Studio City.</p>
        <p>She said she had spent the month catching rides with friends and relatives, or paying hefty fares to take cabs.</p>
        <p>''I'm glad it's over,'' she said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
