<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rice Finally Decides to Sign</title>
    <meta content="PL025855" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228923"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PLUS: PRO FOOTBALL -- ARIZONA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000908T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E0DA1139F93BA3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="760" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rice Finally Decides to Sign</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Simeon Rice saga ended yesterday when the disgruntled defensive end signed a $4.25 million, one-year tender offer and returned in time to practice with the Arizona Cardinals.</p>
        <p>Rice, whose 44 sacks over four years are more than the combined career total for the present front four of Arizona's defense, should play Sunday night in the Cardinals' home opener against the Dallas Cowboys, but Coach Vince Tobin would not say how much.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Simeon Rice saga ended yesterday when the disgruntled defensive end signed a $4.25 million, one-year tender offer and returned in time to practice with the Arizona Cardinals.</p>
        <p>Rice, whose 44 sacks over four years are more than the combined career total for the present front four of Arizona's defense, should play Sunday night in the Cardinals' home opener against the Dallas Cowboys, but Coach Vince Tobin would not say how much.</p>
        <p>The Cardinals have asked for a two-week roster exemption, which would allow them to carry 54 players until Rice gets into football shape, and Tobin said the league's response would determine how much Rice is used.</p>
        <p>He told me he's been really working out, and I certainly believe him, Tobin said.</p>
        <p>The team was forced to field a patchwork defensive line in the season opener because of Rice's holdout and an injury to defensive end Andre Wadsworth. Arizona did not have a sack in a 21-16 loss to the Giants.</p>
        <p>Rice made no secret last year about his unhappiness as the Cardinals struggled to a 6-10 record, but he set a team record with 16 sacks and was positioned to get a big contract as a free agent. Then the Cardinals named him their franchise player, offering the average of the top five salaries at the position.</p>
        <p>The dialogue turned bitter as Rice and his agent, Roosevelt Barnes, tried to get the front office to budge.</p>
        <p>Rice said he watched the Cardinals fizzle against the Giants and decided to accept the situation.</p>
        <p>You can't kick a brick and expect it not to hurt, Rice said. I mean, the situation is what it is, and there's no getting out of it. I love to do what I do. My heart brought me back -- the passion of playing.</p>
        <p>His return was delayed 24 hours when Rice took exception to a scolding he received from General Manager Bob Ferguson after reporting Wednesday morning. He took his physical, but then left without signing. (AP)</p>
        <p>DAVIS COULD PLAY: Still nursing a sprained left ankle, running back Terrell Davis gave the Denver Broncos reason to be believe he would play Sunday against the Atlanta Falcons. Davis was held out of practice yesterday for the second straight day, but he reported improvement to his ankle and graduated to jogging from walking.</p>
        <p>My gut feeling is he'll be able to play, Denver Coach Mike Shanahan said. (AP)</p>
        <p>BATCH SIGNS AND SAYS HE'LL START: Just 24 hours after signing a four-year contract extension for $31 million, Detroit quarterback Charlie Batch said he would start Sunday against the Washington Redskins.</p>
        <p>I'm not 100 percent, and there are some things in the game plan that I can't do, but I'll be out there, Batch said after practice.</p>
        <p>Batch broke a bone in his knee during off-season workouts and missed all of training camp and the Lions' 14-10 season-opening victory in New Orleans, in which Stoney Case played quarterback.</p>
        <p>His timing has been really sharp, and based on what I've seen over the past two days, he's ready to go, Detroit Coach Bobby Ross said.</p>
        <p>The status of one of Batch's favorite targets is still in doubt. Herman Moore, who was optimistic earlier in the week about returning from a separated shoulder, suffered a neck stinger during practice and is unsure if he will be able to play. (AP)</p>
        <p>CARRIER SUSPENDED: The league suspended Washington Redskins free safety Mark Carrier one game for his helmet-to-helmet hit on Carolina tight end Wesley Walls in the Redskins' season-opening victory. He will miss Sunday's game against his former team, the Detroit Lions.</p>
        <p>During the second quarter of the Redskins' 20-17 victory last Sunday, Carrier knocked a pass away from Walls as he hit him. Walls was on the ground for a moment, then got up and played the rest of the game.</p>
        <p>Carrier, 32, has served one-game suspensions in each of the past two seasons for helmet-to-helmet contact. Including fines and a written warning, the league has cited him seven times in his 11-year career. (Bloomberg News)</p>
        <p>PLUS: PRO FOOTBALL -- ARIZONA</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
