<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Connecticut Sues H.M.O.'s Over Handling Of Patients</title>
    <meta content="08CONN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/08/nyregion/08CONN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228777"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Health Maintenance Organizations and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Oxford Health Plans</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cigna Health Plans</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">CIGNA HealthCare of Connecticut</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Foundation Health Systems Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Physicians Health Services</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Anthem Health Plans</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Anthem Blue Cross &amp; Blue Shield</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zielbauer, Paul</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blumenthal, Richard (Atty Gen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Pharmaceutical, Biotechnology and Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000908T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05EFD71239F93BA3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="746" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Connecticut Sues H.M.O.'s Over Handling Of Patients</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAUL ZIELBAUER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zielbauer, Paul</byline>
      <dateline>HARTFORD, Sept. 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Connecticut Atty Gen Richard Blumenthal files federal lawsuit against four of state's largest HMO's, charging them with improperly denying medical claims, obstructing access to prescription drugs, delaying payments to doctors and misinforming patients about their rights to appeal decisions about their health care; four HMO's are Oxford Health Plans, Cigna Health Plans and its CIGNA HealthCare of Connecticut subsidiary, Foundation Health Systems and its subsidiary, Physicians Health Services of Connecticut, and Anthem Health Plans and its Anthem Blue Cross and Blue Shield of Connecticut; all four HMO's issue statements stressing their commitment to high-quality patient care (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Connecticut's attorney general filed a federal lawsuit today against four of the state's largest H.M.O.'s charging them with improperly denying medical claims, obstructing access to prescription drugs, delaying payments to doctors and misinforming patients about their rights to appeal decisions about their health care.</p>
        <p>The civil lawsuit, filed in United States District Court in Hartford, seeks to represent thousands of clients who, according to Attorney General Richard Blumenthal, have suffered physically and financially from the organizations' practice of putting profits ahead of patient care.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Connecticut's attorney general filed a federal lawsuit today against four of the state's largest H.M.O.'s charging them with improperly denying medical claims, obstructing access to prescription drugs, delaying payments to doctors and misinforming patients about their rights to appeal decisions about their health care.</p>
        <p>The civil lawsuit, filed in United States District Court in Hartford, seeks to represent thousands of clients who, according to Attorney General Richard Blumenthal, have suffered physically and financially from the organizations' practice of putting profits ahead of patient care.</p>
        <p>''They have engaged in a pattern of conduct that has denied essential medical treatment to patients,'' Mr. Blumenthal said at a news conference in his office this morning. ''They have forced people to accept less-effective care simply so the company can increase its profits.''</p>
        <p>All four companies named in the suit issued statements today stressing their commitment to high-quality patient care. Two offered to meet with Mr. Blumenthal to discuss the charges. Oxford Health Plans, based in Norwalk, Conn., went further, contesting many of the lawsuit's allegations and chiding the attorney general for not having met with company officials to discuss the allegations against them.</p>
        <p>The three other H.M.O.'s and their Connecticut subsidiaries named in the suit are Cigna Health Plans, based in Bloomfield, Conn., and its subsidiary, CIGNA HealthCare of Connecticut; Foundation Health Systems of Los Angeles, and its subsidiary, Physicians Health Services of Connecticut; and Anthem Health Plans, in Indianapolis, and its subsidiary, Anthem Blue Cross and Blue Shield of Connecticut.</p>
        <p>Together, the four national H.M.O.'s provide medical services to more than 800,000 Connecticut residents, as well as hundreds of thousands of others in New York and New Jersey.</p>
        <p>A district court judge must determine whether the lawsuit meets the legal requirements for the class-action status Mr. Blumenthal is seeking. If it does, Connecticut would become the first state to file such a suit against H.M.O.'s and the first to do so on behalf of consumers, Mr. Blumenthal said.</p>
        <p>In 1998, Texas filed a suit against Aetna U.S. Healthcare accusing it of  providing improper financial incentives to doctors to limit patient care. The two sides settled the suit earlier this year.</p>
        <p>The lawsuit filed today seeks no money award; instead, Mr. Blumenthal said he intended to provoke the four H.M.O.'s into reconsidering what he called ''misguided management'' that put patients in danger.</p>
        <p>Specifically, the suit contends that the H.M.O.'s illegally deny hospitalization costs beyond a set number of days, regardless of a patient's medical needs. It also charges the companies with so strictly limiting the list of prescription drugs they will subsidize that they effectively deny patients necessary medicines, without denial notices or notifying clients of their rights to appeal. The H.M.O.'s also intentionally ignore inquiries from their clients, the lawsuit claims.</p>
        <p>''We're looking for fundamental, far-reaching changes to the way they do business,'' Mr. Blumenthal said.</p>
        <p>Internal documents outlining the  policies of H.M.O.'s, he added, will provide powerful evidence that they have consistently violated federal guidelines that require them to administer health plans solely in the interest of their patients.</p>
        <p>The suit does not charge Physicians Health Services with denying prescription drugs to clients, a charge Mr. Blumenthal brought against the company in a previous lawsuit. Dismissed by a federal court judge, that suit is now being considered by a federal appeals court.</p>
        <p>In an e-mail message, a spokeswoman for Oxford Health Plans said that today's broad allegations were misguided.</p>
        <p>''Oxford pays clean claims on average within seven days (significantly faster than industry norms), Oxford answers member inquiries in a timely manner, Oxford has all but eliminated retrospective denials through a concurrent review program we introduced over a year ago and Oxford offers drug benefits approved by the Connecticut Department of Insurance which are clearly described to members in their policy certificates,'' said the spokeswoman, Maria Gordon Shydlo.</p>
        <p>David Olson, a spokesman for Foundation Health Systems, called today's suit ''old news'' because it repeated allegations in lawsuits filed by private plaintiffs against his H.M.O. and many others. ''The only thing that's new is that the attorney general has decided to join the fray,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
