<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>While Lieberman Baits Bush on Stump, Gore Rarely Mentions Him</title>
    <meta content="Y08LIE$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/08/politics/08LIEB.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228816"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: REPORTER'S NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lieberman, Joseph I (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perez-Pena, Richard</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/Joseph I Lieberman</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000908T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE6DD1339F93BA3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="982" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>While Lieberman Baits Bush on Stump, Gore Rarely Mentions Him</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD PEREZ-PENA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Perez-Pena, Richard</byline>
      <dateline>SPRINGFIELD, Mo., Sept. 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Reporter's Notebook on presidential race; Al Gore rarely mentions George W Bush on stump, leaving running-mate, Joseph Lieberman, to tear into policies and strategies, though not personalities, of Republican ticket (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On a day the Democrats devoted to trumpeting their economic goals, Vice President Al Gore, speaking in Cleveland, never mentioned the Republicans.</p>
        <p>But in a speech on the same topic today at Southwest Missouri State University here, Mr. Gore's running mate, Senator Joseph I. Lieberman, spoke in dire terms of the economic plans of Gov. George W. Bush of Texas, the Republican presidential nominee. Mr. Bush's proposals would ''send us back down the drain of deficits, rising interest rates and rising unemployment,'' Mr. Lieberman said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On a day the Democrats devoted to trumpeting their economic goals, Vice President Al Gore, speaking in Cleveland, never mentioned the Republicans.</p>
        <p>But in a speech on the same topic today at Southwest Missouri State University here, Mr. Gore's running mate, Senator Joseph I. Lieberman, spoke in dire terms of the economic plans of Gov. George W. Bush of Texas, the Republican presidential nominee. Mr. Bush's proposals would ''send us back down the drain of deficits, rising interest rates and rising unemployment,'' Mr. Lieberman said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lieberman has adopted the traditional role of the ticket's No. 2, taking the lead in attacking the opposition, allowing Mr. Gore to remain, if not above the fray, then less deeply mired in it. At every stop, Mr. Lieberman vows not to make personal attacks on Mr. Bush and his running mate, Dick Cheney, and so far he has not. But he has not hesitated to tear into their policies and strategies.</p>
        <p>''He's running around signing a book of blank checks drawn on an account that his tax cuts have already depleted,'' Mr. Lieberman said today of Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>On Monday, he lit into Mr. Bush much more strongly than Mr. Gore did for refusing to take part in two of the three debates proposed by a bipartisan commission, stopping just short of accusing Mr. Bush of being afraid to debate.</p>
        <p>''I think that Governor Bush is making an end run around the established rules of presidential debates,'' he said. ''It's like one of the teams in the Super Bowl, a few weeks before the Super Bowl, saying, 'I don't want to play in that city, I don't want to play by those rules, and I don't want to play in front of so many people.' ''</p>
        <p>Democratic campaign officials acknowledge the difference between Mr. Lieberman's approach and Mr. Gore's but say it is not a result of any grand strategy. ''It's what they're comfortable with,'' one aide said.</p>
        <p>Campaigning High on a Hog</p>
        <p>For the last two weeks, Medicare has been front and center in the national campaign. There have been days when the Democrats have talked about little else. So it must have been a surprise to Senator Lieberman when he took questions today from workers at a Harley-Davidson motorcycle plant in Kansas City, Mo., and the first query, from a young man, was this: ''I notice none of you guys who are running are talking about Medicare.''</p>
        <p>Instead of becoming agitated, Mr. Lieberman gently corrected the misimpression and reiterated the points he and Vice President Gore had made dozens of times.</p>
        <p>The senator seemed a bit out of place on the factory floor. Harley workers, it turns out, look a lot like the stereotype of Harley riders, with a sizable quotient of black T-shirts over jeans, beards, ponytails, sunglasses worn indoors and people who generally looked as if they might be auditioning for ZZ Top.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lieberman, in jeans and a blue dress shirt, even went for a spin around the parking lot on the back of a hog driven by a company employee -- while wearing a helmet, of course. When it was noted that Michael S. Dukakis's image suffered when he was seen wearing a helmet -- in his case, while driving a tank -- during the 1988 presidential campaign, Mr. Lieberman said, ''It was another act of courage.''</p>
        <p>Learning to Grin and Bear It</p>
        <p>When Mr. Gore picked Mr. Lieberman as his running mate, the focus -- both in the news and in the senator's comments -- was on his being the first Jew nominated by a major party for national office.</p>
        <p>Lately, Mr. Lieberman has shifted somewhat away from the topic, but others raise it so often that he could not drop it if he wanted.</p>
        <p>At the motorcycle plant, a woman asked him how, if he became president, his religion would influence the selection of Supreme Court justices. He said his Judaism ''doesn't specifically relate to these kinds of decisions.''</p>
        <p>This theme has led to some of the campaign's more awkward moments. At a recent rally in Claymont, Del., Senator Joseph R. Biden Jr., Democrat of Delaware, pointed into the audience and said to Mr. Lieberman: ''Joe, you see that woman over there? She's Jewish, you're Jewish, we're Catholic. But I say no purgatory for her. Straight to heaven.''</p>
        <p>The senator's smile never wavered.</p>
        <p>Evoking an Unpopular War</p>
        <p>At every stop, Mr. Lieberman mentions that Mr. Gore ''volunteered for service in Vietnam.'' It seems an odd tribute, given that Mr. Gore and Mr. Lieberman came to oppose United States involvement in the war, as did tens of millions of other Americans.</p>
        <p>But the explanation may lie in the fact that the line always draws hearty applause. And this mostly from crowds of Democrats, people who, presumably, would be less inclined than Republicans to view the war favorably. It is, if nothing else, a sign of America's continued ambivalence about the war.</p>
        <p>Arnold Schmidt, a 49-year-old construction worker who heard Mr. Lieberman speak at a Labor Day festival in Detroit on Monday, said he was opposed to the war when it was under way and had not changed his views. But he cheered loudly at the mention of Mr. Gore's tour in the Army.</p>
        <p>''He served his country, and you've got to respect that,'' said Mr. Schmidt, who escaped the draft by having a high lottery number. ''If he didn't go, someone else would have went, like me.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: REPORTER'S NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
