<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CLASSICAL MUSIC AND DANCE GUIDE</title>
    <meta content="08CLAS$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228734"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000908T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E4DF1239F93BA3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="3192" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CLASSICAL MUSIC AND DANCE GUIDE</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A selective listing by critics of The Times of new or noteworthy opera, classical music and dance events this weekend in the Northeast.</p>
        <p>Classical Music</p>
        <p>BARGEMUSIC. There is no better place in New York City to experience chamber music with the proper intimacy than at the concerts presented by Bargemusic, the rewarding weekly series that takes place on an acoustically ideal and commodious barge in the shadow of the Brooklyn Bridge. The pianist Diane Walsh will begin tonight's program with Bach's Partita in D minor for Piano. Then the violinist Ida Levin joins her for Beethoven's Sonata for Violin and Piano (Op. 96). Finally, the cellist David Soyer joins the group for Dvorak's Piano Trio in F minor. Tomorrow night and Sunday afternoon the program will also begin with a solo piano work, Beethoven's Sonata in F (Op. 54), performed by Cynthia Raim. Haydn's Piano Trio in D minor and Schumann's ebullient Piano Quartet will follow, with Carmit Zori (violin), Robert Rinehart (viola) and Fred Sherry (cello). Enjoy the music while taking in a spectacular view of Lower Manhattan. Bargemusic, Fulton Ferry Landing, Brooklyn. Tonight and tomorrow night at 7:30; Sunday at 4 p.m. Tickets: $27; $25, senior citizens; $15, students. Reservations: (718) 624-4061 or 624-2083 (Anthony Tommasini).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A selective listing by critics of The Times of new or noteworthy opera, classical music and dance events this weekend in the Northeast.</p>
        <p>Classical Music</p>
        <p>BARGEMUSIC. There is no better place in New York City to experience chamber music with the proper intimacy than at the concerts presented by Bargemusic, the rewarding weekly series that takes place on an acoustically ideal and commodious barge in the shadow of the Brooklyn Bridge. The pianist Diane Walsh will begin tonight's program with Bach's Partita in D minor for Piano. Then the violinist Ida Levin joins her for Beethoven's Sonata for Violin and Piano (Op. 96). Finally, the cellist David Soyer joins the group for Dvorak's Piano Trio in F minor. Tomorrow night and Sunday afternoon the program will also begin with a solo piano work, Beethoven's Sonata in F (Op. 54), performed by Cynthia Raim. Haydn's Piano Trio in D minor and Schumann's ebullient Piano Quartet will follow, with Carmit Zori (violin), Robert Rinehart (viola) and Fred Sherry (cello). Enjoy the music while taking in a spectacular view of Lower Manhattan. Bargemusic, Fulton Ferry Landing, Brooklyn. Tonight and tomorrow night at 7:30; Sunday at 4 p.m. Tickets: $27; $25, senior citizens; $15, students. Reservations: (718) 624-4061 or 624-2083 (Anthony Tommasini).</p>
        <p>HUDSON VALLEY CHAMBER MUSIC CIRCLE. This chamber music organization is paying tribute to Margaret Creal Shafer, its artistic director since 1977, and welcoming her successors, the violinist Jaime Laredo and the cellist Sharon Robinson, with a gala concert. Mr. Laredo and Ms. Robinson are among the performers, who also include the pianists Ursula Oppens, Todd Crow, Blanca Uribe and Richard Wilson; the cellist Andre Emilianoff; and the violinist Rolf Schulte. Also participating are the poet John Ashbery, the composer Joan Tower and the conductor Leon Botstein. The program includes works by Ms. Tower, Mozart and Schubert. Tomorrow at 7 p.m., Olin Hall, Bard College, Route 9G, Annandale-on-Hudson, N.Y. (845) 338-1172. Tickets: $30 (Allan Kozinn).</p>
        <p>MUSIC MOUNTAIN. It is hard to see why this attractive chamber music festival, in its 71st year, has not developed a higher profile. On Sunday, to end the season, John Solum, a flutist long connected with the Connecticut Early Music Festival, will appear with the Hanoverian Ensemble and others in a program of Bach. This should represent a considerable change of pace from the program tonight, by the Original Salty Dogs Jazz Band. Tonight at 8 and Sunday at 3 p.m., Music Mountain, Music Mountain Road, Falls Village, Conn., (860) 824-7126. Tickets: $18; $10 for students (James R. Oestreich).</p>
        <p>NATIONAL SYMPHONY ORCHESTRA. Leonard Slatkin and the orchestra get their season off to an adventurous start with a 10-day festival centering on Beethoven as heard through the ears of others, mostly Mahler. Tonight they will present Beethoven's Fifth Symphony, first in Liszt's reduction for solo piano, played by Frederic Chiu, then in Mahler's expanded orchestration. Tomorrow they will perform Mahler's retouching of the ''Eroica'' Symphony and his expansion of Beethoven's Opus 95 String Quartet; as an attractive bonus, orchestra members will play the quartet as Beethoven wrote it, along with works of Haydn and Schubert, in a free program at 6 p.m. on the Millennium Stage. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8:30, Kennedy Center Concert Hall, Washington, (202) 467-4600. Tickets: $19 to $66 (Oestreich).</p>
        <p>NEW YORK VIRTUOSI. This freelance orchestra, conducted by Kenneth Klein, has offered some interesting programs of contemporary American music over the years, but this weekend it is turning its attention to more standard fare. Included on its program is Mozart's Concerto in E flat for Two Pianos (the soloists are Theo Lieven and William Grant Nabore), Vivaldi's Concerto for Four Violins and Orchestra (Op. 3, No. 10) and Beethoven's Seventh Symphony. There is a human interest note here: Mr. Nabore's biography says that he is of ''African, Native American, Scots, Jewish and French ancestry,'' and that Ulysses S. Grant was his great-great-uncle. The musical ramifications of all this are probably nil, but one hopes that the pianist's expansive gene pool has diluted his great-great-uncle's vaunted indifference to music, about which he once said, ''I know two tunes; one is Yankee Doodle, and the other isn't.'' Tonight at 8, Alice Tully Hall, (212) 875-5050, and tomorrow at 2 p.m., New Jersey Performing Arts Center, Newark, (888) 466-5722. Tickets: $15 to $35 (Kozinn).</p>
        <p>SOUTH MOUNTAIN CONCERTS. Is there music in the Berkshire Hills after Tanglewood and other major summer festivals have closed? Yes indeed, in perhaps the oldest festival of them all, now in its 82nd season. Here, the Orion String Quartet will play Mozart's Flute Quartet in C (K. 285b), with Tara Helen O'Connor as flutist; Beethoven's String Quartet in E minor (Op. 59, No. 2); and Wynton Marsalis's Quartet No. 1. Sunday at 3 p.m., South Mountain Concert Hall, Routes 7 and 20, Pittsfield, Mass., (413) 442-2106. Remaining tickets: $24 (Oestreich).</p>
        <p>TRIBUTE TO JENNY LIND. By all accounts, the coloratura soprano Jenny Lind, born in Stockholm in 1820 and dubbed the Swedish Nightingale by her devoted fans around the world, had a remarkably fresh, clear and agile voice. That said, the adoration she received seems to have been out of proportion to her vocal gifts. But she was obviously a captivating artist who conquered America in a grand tour organized by no less than P. T. Barnum. To celebrate the 150th anniversary of her momentous New York debut at Castle Garden on Sept. 11, 1850, the Museum of the City of New York is presenting a ''Tribute to the Swedish Nightingale'' on Sunday afternoon. F. Paul Driscoll, the managing editor of Opera News, will begin the program with a lecture on Lind's career. It will also include readings from period press accounts and from Barnum's colorful memoirs. Charlotte Philley and Deborah Saverance, sopranos from the Metropolitan Opera Chorus, will then sing arias and songs associated with Lind, accompanied by Steven Eldredge, a pianist. Museum of the City of New York, 1220 Fifth Avenue, at 103rd Street; Sunday at 2 p.m. Free with suggested contribution: $7; $4 for students, the elderly and children; $12 for families. Information: (212) 534-1672, extension  206 (Tommasini).</p>
        <p>Dance</p>
        <p>DANCENOW DOWNTOWN FESTIVAL 2000. Five shows over two days will feature work by just about everyone who has put a toe to a downtown stage floor in recent years. Tonight 18 choreographers and companies will show their stuff, among them Karl Anderson, Robin Staff, Jeanette Stoner, Sally Hess and Tami Stronach. Tomorrow 20 choreographers and groups will present work, among them Eric Dunlap, Gabrielle Lansner, Lisa Nicks and Doug Elkins. Today at 7 and 9 p.m. Tomorrow at 1, 3 and 5 p.m. Tickets: $4 with a festival dancecard; $10, single tickets. Joyce SoHo, 155 Mercer Street, (917) 930-4327 (Jennifer Dunning).</p>
        <p>DANCE SPACE CENTER'S SECOND INTERNATIONAL STUDENT SHOWCASE. Choreography by 16 international center students from 10 countries. Tomorrow at 8 p.m.; Sunday at 7 p.m. Also Sept. 16 at 8 p.m. and Sept. 17 at 7 p.m. Tickets: $12. Evolving Arts Theater at Dance Space Center, 451 Broadway, between Grand and Canal Streets, SoHo, (212) 625-8369 (Dunning).</p>
        <p>DANCE THEATER OF HARLEM. Made up of radiant, nuanced classicists, the Dance Theater of Harlem will be seen in a wide-ranging repertory this weekend. Tonight, tomorrow and Sunday, for example, the dancers will shift from George Balanchine's ''Four Temperaments'' to the second act of ''Creole Giselle'' to Robert Garland's ''Return,'' set to Aretha Franklin and James Brown. Tomorrow night the program includes Augustus van Heerden's new ''Memento Mori'' and ''South African Suite,'' three pieces by Arthur Mitchell (the company's director), Mr. van Heerden and Laveen Naidu, set to music by the Soweto String Quartet. Tonight at 8; tomorrow at 2 and 8 p.m.; Sunday at 3 p.m. Tickets: $35 to $55. City Center, 131 West 55th Street, Manhattan, (212) 581-1212 (Dunning).</p>
        <p>FOLK PARKS 2000. Presented by the Center for Traditional Music and Dance, Folk Parks 2000 is a free daylong festival featuring music and dance from around the world by artists in New York City. Tomorrow, noon to 8 p.m. Damrosch Park at Lincoln Center, (212) 571-1555. Rain date: Sunday (Dunning).</p>
        <p>JAMES HANSEN AND RACHEL THORNE GERMOND. Choreographers who think about the nature and the qualities of dance, Mr. Hansen and Ms. Germond will present three dances each to music ranging from Dusty Springfield to Rorem to Bellini to Vivaldi. Tonight and tomorrow night at 9. Tickets: $12; $10 for students. Merce Cunningham Studio, 55 Bethune Street, West Village, (718) 768-5508 (Dunning).</p>
        <p>JETTE PERFORMANCE COMPANY. Jay T. Jenkins, the artistic director and choreographer of the Jette Performance Company, has choreographed Nickelodeon commercials, the film ''House Party'' and music videos and shows for artists including Prince, Salt-n-Pepa and Cindy Lauper. His company will perform dances, including the new ''Newfunkfoya!'' and ''JazzIz.'' Tonight and tomorrow night at 8; Sunday at 3 p.m. Tickets: $25 (tonight, includes post-performance reception); $20, tomorrow and Sunday; $15 for students and the elderly. Dance Theater Workshop, 219 West 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 924-0077 (Dunning).</p>
        <p>JODI LISS: DANCE/IDEAS. Jodi Liss gets this week's award for the most intriguing themes -- or titles -- for her dances: ''Leviathan,'' ''In India,'' ''Old-Fashioned Couple Dances'' and ''Scenes From Sisterhood.'' A fifth piece, ''Baroque,'' is a masked solo. Tomorrow at 8 p.m.; Sunday at 2 p.m. Tickets: $10; $7 for students, artists and the elderly. Bridge for Dance, 2726 Broadway, at 104th Street, (212) 774-6713 (Dunning).</p>
        <p>TRANSMISSION PROJECTS. Anika Tromholt Kristensen, a Danish choreographer, and Cynthia Hopkins, a composer, have created a piece based on ''The Legend of St. Julian Hospitaler,'' a short story by Flaubert. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8. Tickets: $10. Smack Mellon Studios, 56 Water Street, Brooklyn Heights, (212) 982-5299 (Dunning).</p>
        <p>''Y DANCE!'' Silly question. At any rate, dance returns to the 14th Street Y this weekend in an imaginative two-program series of work by veteran and fledgling choreographers, including Beverly Blossom, Susan Marshall, Kraig Patterson, Amos Pinhasi and Ryan Kelly. Sunday's program honors Oceola Bragg, the gentle doyenne of dance at the Y in earlier years. Tomorrow at 8:30 p.m.; Sunday at 2 and 7:30 p.m. Tickets: $15. Sol Goldman YM-YWHA of the Educational Alliance, 344 East 14th Street at First Avenue, East Village, (212) 780-0800, extension 248 (Dunning).</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
