<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; System Fails, But Player Prospers</title>
    <meta content="08FREE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/08/sports/08FREE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228766"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Philadelphia Eagles</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Dallas Cowboys</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Freeman, Mike</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Staley, Duce</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Mike Freeman</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Dallas Cowboys</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Philadelphia Eagles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000908T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E3D91239F93BA3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="855" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; System Fails, But Player Prospers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIKE FREEMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Freeman, Mike</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mike Freeman Sports of The Times column says Duce Staley exemplifies what happens when football scouts completely miss boat on prospect; notes many scouts dismissed Staley as too small and too slow in 1997, and eight running backs were picked ahead of him in draft that year; says Staley, practically invisible to National Football League in 1997, rushed for 201 yards on 26 carries in Phiadelphia Eagles' recent game against Dallas; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FINDING a franchise player in the National Football League draft is one of the great challenges of our time, even more difficult than deciphering the latest rap lyrics or discovering intelligent life on other planets. A scout once compared the excitement of watching a top quarterback prospect to the day that he got married. It is true the scout needs to get a life, but his words explain just how desperate teams are to select that special player.</p>
        <p>Which brings us to the Philadelphia Eagles running back Duce Staley, a franchise player if there ever was one, and someone who exemplifies what happens when professional football's anal, fat-pinching, stopwatch-obsessed system completely misses the boat on a prospect.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FINDING a franchise player in the National Football League draft is one of the great challenges of our time, even more difficult than deciphering the latest rap lyrics or discovering intelligent life on other planets. A scout once compared the excitement of watching a top quarterback prospect to the day that he got married. It is true the scout needs to get a life, but his words explain just how desperate teams are to select that special player.</p>
        <p>Which brings us to the Philadelphia Eagles running back Duce Staley, a franchise player if there ever was one, and someone who exemplifies what happens when professional football's anal, fat-pinching, stopwatch-obsessed system completely misses the boat on a prospect.</p>
        <p>Staley may prove to be one of the great runners of the next five years, but when he was coming out of the University of South Carolina in 1997, scouts called Staley too small and too slow. Eight running backs were picked ahead of him in the draft that year, none of whom have proven to be better than Staley.</p>
        <p>The N.F.L.'s scouts try so hard. Each year they log tens of thousands of miles going to various college campuses, staying in hotels, motels or their brother-in-law's basement, just so they can get up at 5 in the morning to time some college prospect in the 40-yard dash. Then, when the scouting process is done, teams design computer graphs and flow charts that rival NASA's. They know what a player ate last Thursday and if his children's children will prefer boxers or briefs.</p>
        <p>Then someone like Staley sneaks through the cracks and makes the  system look ridiculous. Last week against Dallas it was Staley, practically an invisible man to the N.F.L. as a college prospect, who rushed for 201 yards on 26 carries, the fifth-best opening-game performance since 1933. He became the Eagles' first 200-yard runner since Steve Van Buren in 1949 and gives the team hope of capturing the National Football Conference East.</p>
        <p>Right now, Staley, after rushing for 1,273 yards last season, is probably one of the top five to seven runners in the game, a younger version of the St. Louis superstar, Marshall Faulk. But where did Staley come from? He emerged despite an N.F.L. system that sometimes relies too heavily on numbers and not enough on what happens on the field, which should be the bottom line.</p>
        <p>Staley transferred from Itawamba Community College in Fulton, Miss., to South Carolina, where he stunned coaches with his quickness and toughness. Still, N.F.L. scouts were not impressed. At barely 5 feet 11 inches and just over 200 pounds, Staley simply did not fit the N.F.L. prototype for a featured running back. So he was picked in only the third round of the draft by Philadelphia, not an obscenely low selection, but too low for someone with his apparent talent.</p>
        <p>Warrick Dunn, Antowaine Smith, Tiki Barber, Byron Hanspard, Corey Dillon, Sedrick Shaw, Troy Davis and Jay Graham were all chosen before Staley. Dunn has been mediocre; Smith and Barber are solid but not as durable as Staley; while Hanspard, Shaw, Davis and Graham -- supposedly bigger or faster players who would fit better in the professional ranks than Staley -- were all busts. Dillon has exceptional talent but is a troublemaker off the field.</p>
        <p>Staley is cognizant he was an afterthought in the scouting process, and it remains a source of motivation. ''Sometimes you have to fight through things and be a man who makes it happen yourself,'' Staley said. ''Especially in what I do for a living, no one is going to hand you anything. You have to pick yourself up.''</p>
        <p>Sometimes the N.F.L. does get it right, teams go against the system, and pick that obscure player who fails to fit into the picture-perfect frame. The Giants selected the Lambuth University wide receiver Ron Dixon in the third round despite the fact he was not from a football powerhouse. Dixon might be one of the best picks of the entire 2000 draft.</p>
        <p>But too many teams stick to the numbers. One team's scout, when rating Staley as an N.F.L. prospect in 1997, was disappointed in his speed -- he was timed at 4.65 seconds in the 40-yard sprint, considered slow for a runner. A scout on a different team felt Staley's smallish frame was too slight to accommodate his inside running style in the pros. Yet another team's scout wrote the following in a report: ''A backup at most.''</p>
        <p>The system hiccuped. It goofed, but Staley prospers. Now Staley can only laugh, and his chuckle will grow louder as those supposedly slow legs carry him to the Pro Bowl.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
