<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.N. Speakers Urge Increase In Charity To the Poor</title>
    <meta content="Y08LEA$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/08/world/08LEAD.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228821"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SUMMIT IN NEW YORK: THE ORATORS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wren, Christopher S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mbeki, Thabo (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chretien, Jean (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Amato, Giuliano (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chavez, Hugo (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000908T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E1DD1339F93BA3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="528" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.N. Speakers Urge Increase In Charity To the Poor</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER S. WREN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wren, Christopher S</byline>
      <dateline>UNITED NATIONS, Sept. 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Succession of leaders speaking on second day of UN Millennium Summit call for industrialized world to show more tangible charity toward world's poor, although few speakers offer specific remedies beyond debt forgiveness; South African Thabo Mbeki, Venezuelan Pres Hugo Chavez, Italian Prime Min Giuliano Amato, Canadian Prime Min Jean Chretien and others quoted (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A succession of leaders speaking on the second day of the United Nations' Millennium Summit today demanded, with passion and often eloquence, that the industrialized world show more tangible charity toward the world's poor.</p>
        <p>''Billions among the living struggle to survive in conditions of poverty, deprivation and underdevelopment as offensive to everything humane as anything we decry about the second millennium,'' President Thabo Mbeki of South Africa said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A succession of leaders speaking on the second day of the United Nations' Millennium Summit today demanded, with passion and often eloquence, that the industrialized world show more tangible charity toward the world's poor.</p>
        <p>''Billions among the living struggle to survive in conditions of poverty, deprivation and underdevelopment as offensive to everything humane as anything we decry about the second millennium,'' President Thabo Mbeki of South Africa said.</p>
        <p>''The poor of the world stand at the gates of the comfortable mansions occupied by each and every king and queen, president, prime minister and minister privileged to attend this unique meeting,'' Mr. Mbeki said.</p>
        <p>Still, relatively few speakers of the 70 leaders who were scheduled to speak today offered specific remedies beyond debt forgiveness, leaving it to some Western countries, like Canada and Italy, to endorse additional, if less dramatic, measures.</p>
        <p>A declaration to be signed on Friday when the summit meeting ends has set ambitious benchmarks for resolving the global ills of war, disease, poverty and environmental degradation. One such goal proposes to reduce by half over the next 15 years the number of people earning less than a dollar a day.</p>
        <p>To achieve that, President Hugo Chavez of Venezuela reckoned, ''we should increase that income to levels of fairness and dignity for 140,000 persons each day of each month and of each year from the present until Dec. 31, 2015.''</p>
        <p>The Italian prime minister, Giuliano Amato, agreed that radical efforts were required. ''Debt cancellation is important, indispensable even, but not enough,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He proposed opening markets to developing countries by abolishing quotas and tariffs and allocating fresh resources for education.</p>
        <p>Acknowledging the misgivings expressed about the impact of globalization on poor countries, Prime Minister Jean Chretien of Canada said: ''We must share the benefits of globalization. We must give it a human purpose and a human face. The poorest countries require access for their goods to export markets. Faster, deeper and broader debt relief should be pursued vigorously.'' And Mr. Chretien added, ''We must ensure that the benefits of the information revolution are shared by all.''</p>
        <p>King Harald V of Norway observed that poverty is inextricably linked to problems like environmental deterioration. ''For we shall never be able to cooperate effectively on how to husband the scarce resources of our planet, how to prevent the degradation of the environment, as long as so many are trapped in hopeless poverty,'' he said.</p>
        <p>President J. J. Rawlings of Ghana blamed Western corporations for ''thrusting'' corruption on Africa, which, he contended, ''has drained some of our countries of resources which should have been used to improve the quality of life of the poor and disadvantaged.''</p>
        <p>''There will be less corruption in Africa,'' he said, ''if there is no place to hide the proceeds of corruption or if the proceeds of corruption, once uncovered, are returned to their real owners, the people of Africa,'' he said.</p>
        <p>SUMMIT IN NEW YORK: THE ORATORS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
