<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>N.F.L. MATCHUPS WEEK 2</title>
    <meta content="08MATC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228879"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">George, Thomas</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000908T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E4DB1339F93BA3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="3100" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>N.F.L. MATCHUPS WEEK 2</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS GEORGE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">George, Thomas</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Matchups for Week 2 of National Football League season; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SUNDAY 1 P.M.</p>
        <p>Cleveland (0-1) at Cincinnati (0-0)  Imagine being the Bengals, trudging through the off-season, minicamps, training camp and preseason games and then, on opening weekend, being idle. That is what happened to them last week since the Bengals were the only team to be saddled with an open date on kickoff weekend. Now comes the payoff. A new stadium will be christened, named after the team's founder, Paul Brown. It is a beauty that sparkles in downtown Cincinnati. And the Bengals get to play their longtime rival, the Browns. Watch quarterback Akili Smith to the rookie receiver Peter Warrick. This is the start of something special.  Bengals, 27-17</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SUNDAY 1 P.M.</p>
        <p>Cleveland (0-1) at Cincinnati (0-0)  Imagine being the Bengals, trudging through the off-season, minicamps, training camp and preseason games and then, on opening weekend, being idle. That is what happened to them last week since the Bengals were the only team to be saddled with an open date on kickoff weekend. Now comes the payoff. A new stadium will be christened, named after the team's founder, Paul Brown. It is a beauty that sparkles in downtown Cincinnati. And the Bengals get to play their longtime rival, the Browns. Watch quarterback Akili Smith to the rookie receiver Peter Warrick. This is the start of something special.  Bengals, 27-17</p>
        <p>Jacksonville (1-0) at Baltimore (1-0)  Baltimore has never beaten Jacksonville. It has tried eight times and failed and the last time was in Baltimore last November, when Jacksonville scored 23 fourth-quarter points to win, 30-23. Baltimore, though, is building confidence. Quarterback Tony Banks is 7-4 as the Ravens' starter. They are 7-0 when back Priest Holmes rushes for 100 or more yards. And check out these amazing numbers -- Ravens receiver Qadry Ismail produced one 100-yard receiving game in his first 87 pro games but has 4 in his past 6 games. How does a guy get faster as he gets older? Actually, it's that the Ravens use Ismail and feature him.  Ravens, 26-24</p>
        <p>Kansas City (0-1) at Tennessee (0-1)  Against Buffalo, Tennessee quarterback Steve McNair threw 14 incomplete passes out of 31 attempts. There were no touchdown passes. The Titans are a strong team, but they have a weakness -- not enough big plays downfield. Nearly everything the Titans get on offense comes in a grinding running game and its short passing game. Receiver Carl Pickens is supposed to help free this offense. Playing against Kansas City instead of Buffalo will help. The Chiefs allowed 386 yards of offense in losing to Indianapolis last Sunday. Tennessee might not match that but should come close. And it looks to extend its unbeaten streak in Adelphia Coliseum to nine games.  Titans, 24-10</p>
        <p>Chicago (0-1) at Tampa Bay (1-0)  Cade McNown fell 3 points shy of matching Minnesota and Daunte Culpepper last Sunday. This time he tries against Shaun King, who, like McNown and Culpepper, is one of the Class of '99 quarterbacks. McNown threw for 290 yards and two touchdowns against the Vikings but surprisingly ran 10 times for 87 yards and a touchdown. This is not supposed to be his game -- scrambling and running instead of throwing -- but McNown can do it. For the Bears to win, it will be with McNown's arm instead of his legs. But that does not look very likely. Tampa Bay has won four straight in its division. And Tampa Bay has beaten Chicago in five straight games. Make it six.  Buccaneers, 23-6</p>
        <p>Giants (1-0) at Philadelphia (1-0)  Both the Giants and Eagles are off to fast starts on the ground. The Giants' leader is Tiki Barber, who is averaging 11.1 yards per carry. Philadelphia's leader is Duce Staley, who gained 201 rushing yards vs. Dallas. In beating Dallas, Philadelphia scored 41 points on the road; the Eagles wanted to reverse the Dallas dominance over them and look to do the same against the Giants. If both teams' running attacks are neutralized, the game will come down to quarterbacks Donovan McNabb and Kerry Collins. At this juncture, go with Collins.  Giants, 19-17</p>
        <p>Green Bay (0-1) at Buffalo (1-0)  The Green Bay offense sank against the Jets and now plays the defense that led the league a season ago. That is a bad combination. Packers quarterback Brett Favre says he is ready to throw the ball short and long against Buffalo, that his arm is still sore, but sound. By the time the Buffalo defense is finished chasing and hitting him, Favre will have more pain than simply in his arm. The Bills' defense is much further along than the Packers' offense and it will show in this game. Buffalo has never lost to Green Bay in three previous games in Buffalo, though the last one was in 1994.  Bills, 23-9</p>
        <p>SUNDAY 1 P.M.</p>
        <p>Miami (1-0) at Minnesota (1-0)  The key attraction here is the Miami defense and cornerbacks Patrick Surtain and Sam Madison against Vikings receivers Randy Moss and Cris Carter. But Miami must also focus on offense. Against Seattle, quarterback Jay Fiedler made enough good plays and running back Lamar Smith (27 carries, 145 rushing yards) ran rampant on natural grass. Can both accomplish that against Minnesota on artificial turf inside a dome? Probably not. The Vikings win this game on defense with turnovers.  Vikings, 21-6</p>
        <p>Oakland (1-0) at Indianapolis (1-0)  Since the Raiders have never played in the RCA Dome, they are in for a treat. Well, more like a scare -- because the fans there are loud and wave their white towels in a frenzy and whoop it up, making it nearly impossible for visitors to hear the signal calls. The fans are as scary as the Colts' offense, which is shifty and speedy at receiver (Marvin Harrison), cool and calm at quarterback (Peyton Manning) and bullish yet stylish at tailback (Edgerrin James). If Tim Brown makes two touchdown catches, he will pass Fred Biletnikoff as the Raiders' all-time leader.  Colts, 26-17</p>
        <p>SUNDAY 4:15 P.M.</p>
        <p>St. Louis (1-0) at Seattle (0-1)  The Rams are the champs, the Seahawks are downtrodden. They performed miserably against Miami last week and quarterback Jon Kitna was the focal point, throwing four interceptions and fumbling, too. He was so bad that Mike Holmgren, Seattle's coach, believes Kitna can only improve and will. Seattle's defense possesses the personnel to run with the Rams. And Seattle will be focused, and prepared to answer all the critics after their listless opening game. After all of that drama against Denver on Monday night, and then having to travel out West, the Rams are ripe to be upset.  Seahawks, 30-28</p>
        <p>Washington (1-0) at Detroit (1-0)  Washington won 16 straight in this series before Detroit finally snapped the hex, winning last year at home, 33-17. It was Detroit's first victory over Washington since 1965. Both teams are headed in positive directions. Washington continues to mesh a galaxy of stars; Detroit simply hopes to get its main man back -- quarterback Charlie Batch. He has made a speedy recovery from a knee injury sustained during the preseason and is expected to play on Sunday. But the difference in this game is quarterback Brad Johnson against a suspect secondary.  Redskins, 27-23</p>
        <p>Carolina (0-1) at San Francisco (0-1)  These teams let the ball fly when they meet. Last year, there were 15 touchdowns scored in their two games, and 8 of them were for 20 or more yards. San Francisco has won seven consecutive home openers but figures to struggle with the Panthers. Panthers back Tim Biakabutuka averaged 5.9 yards per carry last week against Washington and can match that against the 49ers' defense, insuring that Carolina wins the possession war.  Panthers, 28-20</p>
        <p>Atlanta (1-0) at Denver (0-1)  Dan Reeves makes his return to Mile High Stadium, and this one will also be his last trip, since the Broncos move into a new stadium next year. Reeves coached the Broncos from 1981 through 1992. Two years ago, he lost to them in Super Bowl XXXIII, 34-19. Good thing he has receiver Shawn Jefferson on his side. Jefferson played most of his career with quarterback Drew Bledsoe in New England, and then in one game in Atlanta -- last Sunday against the 49ers -- gained a career high in receiving yards (148). Jefferson will make a mark in this game, too. But not enough to overcome the Broncos' balanced offense, which excels at home.  Broncos, 30-24</p>
        <p>New Orleans (0-1) at San Diego (0-1)  Both teams fought hard in their losses last week -- the Saints by 4 points to Detroit and the Chargers by 3 points to the Raiders -- but both also showed that they are short in manpower. Both simply need more good players. Neither has enough speed. Neither starting quarterback (Jeff Blake for New Orleans, Ryan Leaf for San Diego) is consistent. Neither defense sacks the quarterback enough. Neither makes enough big plays. But both are close.  Chargers, 16-13</p>
        <p>SUNDAY 8:20 P.M.</p>
        <p>Dallas (0-1) at Arizona (0-1)  Yes, Dallas gained 167 yards and allowed 425 against Philadelphia last week. And quarterback Jake Plummer's passing yardage (318) was nearly twice as much as Dallas's total offense. Troy Aikman sits this one out, recovering from a concussion. There is no way the Cardinals should lose this game. They are at home, have played well against Dallas in recent seasons and don't have to face Aikman or the new receiver Joe Galloway, out for the year with a knee injury.  Cardinals, 27-21</p>
        <p>Game of the Week</p>
        <p>New England 0-1 Jets 1-0  These teams meet for the fourth straight season in a prime-time game, this one on Monday night, when both teams' fans and peers will get a look at the rivalry between the franchises. It runs deep, from management to coaches to players. The Patriots seek to heal their offense. It was squashed last week vs. Tampa Bay, and the offensive line, in particular, was tossed around. In addition, running back Kevin Faulk caught 11 passes, and that indicates simply not enough pass protection from the line nor production from the Patriots receivers. The Jets feel good about winning on the road, at Lambeau Field no less. The matchup of the Patriots' defense against the Jets' offense decides this game. This is where the best talent resides in this game and it will be an intriguing match of brawn and wits. Give the Patriots' defense the edge.  Patriots, 17-16</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
