<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>That Mystery That No One Wants to Think About Is Getting More Complex</title>
    <meta content="08TVWK" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/08/arts/08TVWK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228731"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TV WEEKEND"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Death and Dying</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Public Broadcasting Service</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Moyers, Bill</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Salamon, Julie</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">On Our Own Terms: Moyers on Dying (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Death and Dying</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000908T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE6DF1239F93BA3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1357" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>That Mystery That No One Wants to Think About Is Getting More Complex</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Julie Salamon</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Salamon, Julie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Julie Salamon reviews PBS documentary series, On Our Own Terms: Moyers on Dying; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In America, a nation of strivers, people want to believe that everything is subject to improvement, even dying. But while death remains (presumably) a constant, the act of dying has become more complex. Medical advances have prolonged life, but often in an undesirable form, forcing doctors to reconsider their roles and obligations. Terminally ill patients may think they want to take control of their mortality with physician-assisted suicide, then find they are afraid.</p>
        <p>So dying remains a mystery, subject to legal, medical, theological, emotional and economic considerations. No one wants to think about it, but eventually everyone must. To help, Bill Moyers has provided an extraordinary guide with ''On Our Own Terms,'' his panoramic and often profoundly moving vision of how we die in America today.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In America, a nation of strivers, people want to believe that everything is subject to improvement, even dying. But while death remains (presumably) a constant, the act of dying has become more complex. Medical advances have prolonged life, but often in an undesirable form, forcing doctors to reconsider their roles and obligations. Terminally ill patients may think they want to take control of their mortality with physician-assisted suicide, then find they are afraid.</p>
        <p>So dying remains a mystery, subject to legal, medical, theological, emotional and economic considerations. No one wants to think about it, but eventually everyone must. To help, Bill Moyers has provided an extraordinary guide with ''On Our Own Terms,'' his panoramic and often profoundly moving vision of how we die in America today.</p>
        <p>In this four-part, six-hour PBS series, Mr. Moyers and his crew cover a lot of physical as well as emotional ground, featuring doctors and patients from all over the country in all kinds of financial and family circumstances and uncovering heart-wrenching and sometimes surprising stories of fortitude and fragility, indifference and love.</p>
        <p>While many of the intimate case studies Mr. Moyers presents offer the intense emotion of great drama, he always aims to instruct. So in addition to the six hours presented on television, PBS has produced elaborate amplification at www.pbs.org, making this program a vivid illustration of how television and the Internet are becoming increasingly linked. Throughout the program, references to corresponding links on the PBS Web site appear on-screen. The Web site offers comprehensive information on both practical and intangible matters, including financial planning for terminally ill patients, various treatment alternatives and ''taking a spiritual inventory.''</p>
        <p>Unlike the new genre of hospital documentaries like ABC's excellent series ''Hopkins: 24/7,'' Mr. Moyers and his producers don't try to mimic the fast-paced style of prime-time television dramas -- though these cameras also follow patients into conferences with their doctors and into their homes. Often the cameras stop to show pictures of the patients before, when they were happy and whole, and these ordinary snapshots take on layers of poignancy and meaning. Viewers meet people who face death with humor as well as resoluteness, like the retired math teacher who refers to each weekly gathering with her children and grandchildren as ''the last supper.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Moyers isn't afraid to linger, to acknowledge the knotted layers of his subject. Introducing the third episode, ''A Death of One's Own,'' which deals with assisted suicide, Mr. Moyers notes that the subject is often sensationalized by the media and pointedly observes that in this program ''Dr. Kevorkian is not heard from.''</p>
        <p>Generally, Mr. Moyers is an unobtrusive but steady presence, introducing each episode and then occasionally appearing on camera to ask a gently leading question. (''Is it hard to have to focus on him all the time?'' he asks a dying man's wife.)</p>
        <p>The producers have assembled a remarkable array of subjects, people whose obsession with death -- whether personal or professional -- provokes multifarious thoughts about it. They found Thomas Lynch, the Michigan undertaker who is also an author on the subject, a homespun poet and philosopher, and a smart, sensitive doctor specializing in palliative care at Mount Sinai Hospital in Manhattan. She requires her medical students to read Tolstoy's ''Death of Ivan Ilyich,'' about a man who is dying without anyone's acknowledging that his death is imminent.</p>
        <p>The undertaker from Michigan wonders why so many people ask for funerals without flowers, but when Diana, Princess of Wales, died, strangers offered flowers in abundance. A doctor in Charlottesville, Va., tries to convince a group of medical students that to stop giving a patient food and air through tubes isn't killing him, just letting him die. In New York City, a young man's family, refusing to acknowledge that their son is dying, wants to reduce his pain medication so that he can be alert enough to fight the disease that will kill him anyway.</p>
        <p>The series falters only in the last episode, ''A Time to Change,'' which becomes preachy as it poses important questions about the financial challenges of providing good end-of-life care to everyone. In part because many of the patients featured here are too far gone to make a connection, some of the immediacy of the earlier episodes is diminished.</p>
        <p>The series shines with its individual portraits, some of which have the resonance of good literature. In ''A Death of One's Own,'' Jim Witcher, a veterinarian in Louisiana, and his wife, Susie, are living their lifelong dream of owning a horse farm in retirement -- a dream fulfilled except that he is dying of Lou Gehrig's disease, a creeping paralysis that will steadily destroy every function. He wants to be put to sleep before he dies a miserable death, the way he often relieved the suffering of animals when he was in practice, but assisted suicide is illegal in Louisiana and against his family's religious beliefs.</p>
        <p>His wife sympathizes enormously but can't promise him she'll fulfill his wishes. It's too much for her to be both a grieving wife and an ethicist. So she does what she is able, caring for him at home because, she says, clearly loving, she can't bear the thought of a stranger ''wiping his bottom.'' It is wrenching to watch her struggle to hoist her husband from his wheelchair onto a plastic chair for his shower, then bathe him with the same strong hands she uses to soap and rinse their horses.</p>
        <p>The first episode, ''Living With Dying,'' begins with Bill Bartholome, a pediatrician in Kansas City, an articulate observer of his own dying. It reveals no secrets to say that Dr. Bartholome dies at the end of the program. That's the point of his presence.</p>
        <p>But first, he engages the audience with his matter-of-factness, which transmits deep intelligence and bravery. When he received his diagnosis, it seemed appropriate to him that he should be stricken. ''Why not have it be somebody who can deal with it?'' he says.</p>
        <p>Dr. Bartholome possesses the mixed blessing of being able to diagnose his illness (esophageal cancer) and to monitor its progress. After initially experiencing ''a kind of grief I had never known,'' he says, he determined to live with vibrancy as ''a terminal person.'' He doesn't want to kill himself as he nears death; nor does he want to prolong his life. He just wants to die at home, with his wife present, as comfortably as possible.</p>
        <p>For him, this is a personal decision, though Mr. Moyers demonstrates that Dr. Bartholome is part of a wider movement to humanize the dying process. Hospitals like Mount Sinai have established palliative care units whose focus is not on curing patients but on easing their pain, though patients still may request medical treatment beyond painkillers. Then there are hospices, where the emphasis is strictly on comfort, not cure.</p>
        <p>Mr. Moyers meets with Dr. Bartholome and his wife over a period of months, and the patient is visibly losing ground, dropping 20 pounds in less than a month. By the end this tall man weighs 154 pounds, a shadow of the hearty 216-pound fellow seen in a snapshot happily holding a freshly caught fish.</p>
        <p>He writes a journal about his experience and confesses in one interview that he is in pain, but decided not to take his medication that day so he could think clearly. ''I want to be master of ceremonies at this thing,'' he says of his death. Perhaps we dare not ask for anything more.</p>
        <p>ON OUR OWN TERMS  Moyers on Dying  PBS, Sunday night through Wednesday night at 9  (Channel 13 in New York)</p>
        <p>A four-part series. Bill Moyers and Judith Davidson Moyers, executive editors; Elena Mannes, series producer; Gail Pellett and Ms. Mannes, producers; Alison Amron, Donna Marino, Nobuko Oganesoff and Sharon Sachs, editors; Gail Ablow, William Brangham and Paco de Onis, field producers; Felice Firestone, director of production. Produced by PublicAffairs Television. Deborah Rubinstein, director of special projects. Ms. Moyers and Judy Doctoroff O'Neill, executive producers.</p>
        <p>TV WEEKEND</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
