<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Mother's Selfless Love and Dignity</title>
    <meta content="08SOLA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/08/arts/08SOLA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228727"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zambrano, Benito</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holden, Stephen</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Solas (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews/By Stephen Holden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000908T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07EED61539F93BA3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="855" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Mother's Selfless Love and Dignity</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN HOLDEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Holden, Stephen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Stephen Holden reviews Solas, film by Benito Zambrano; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>One of the good things that can come with age, if we're lucky, is a growing capacity to feel and to give our unconditional love. And Benito Zambrano's quietly moving film ''Solas'' explores this gift with a depth and subtlety that remind you,  indirectly, of why the movies are so infatuated with violence.</p>
        <p>It's so much easier to portray anger on the screen (it's a shortcut to feeling) than to evoke the kind of watchful, selfless devotion that radiates from the film's central character, who is identified only as Mother (Maria Galiana). Because it's the kind of feeling that affects things only gradually, it is almost impossible to portray on the screen without some sentimental amplification.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>One of the good things that can come with age, if we're lucky, is a growing capacity to feel and to give our unconditional love. And Benito Zambrano's quietly moving film ''Solas'' explores this gift with a depth and subtlety that remind you,  indirectly, of why the movies are so infatuated with violence.</p>
        <p>It's so much easier to portray anger on the screen (it's a shortcut to feeling) than to evoke the kind of watchful, selfless devotion that radiates from the film's central character, who is identified only as Mother (Maria Galiana). Because it's the kind of feeling that affects things only gradually, it is almost impossible to portray on the screen without some sentimental amplification.</p>
        <p>But Ms. Galiana's still, intensely concentrated portrait of a woman who changes people's lives through small acts of kindness shows that great screen acting doesn't necessarily rely on psychologically revealing dialogue.</p>
        <p>This sober Spanish film, so pointedly antithetical in spirit to the zany, sexually charged antics of Pedro Almodovar and his imitators, has few frills. No heavenly choirs or misty-eyed close-ups are trotted out to push our emotional buttons. Except for Antonio Meliveo's discreetly melancholy score, the movie is almost as plain as its central character.</p>
        <p>A stout, weather-beaten woman of around 70 who moves slowly and rarely cracks a smile, Ms. Galiana projects the earthy solidity of someone who despite coming from humble circumstances and being illiterate is at home in the world because she doesn't expect much of life. In one of her few remarks about herself, she gravely professes to have a clear conscience. Those words, along with her simple acts of thoughtfulness, suggest that she is devoutly religious, although she keeps most of her feelings to herself.</p>
        <p>She has made a rare journey into the city (the movie was filmed in Seville) to be with her husband (Paco De Osca) while he recovers from surgery. Hour after hour she sits patiently at his bedside lost in her thoughts while crocheting. When he addresses her, he turns out to be a bitter old tyrant who baits his wife by claiming to detect the smell of a man on her. Having endured his cruelty for years, she seems almost impervious. But eventually we learn that he used to be an abusive drunk who gambled, womanized and physically abused his wife and his daughter, Maria (Ana Fernandez), with whom she is staying.</p>
        <p>Wiry, nervous, and consumed with rage, Maria is definitely her father's child, although she hates him for refusing to pay for any higher education.</p>
        <p>Furious that she has to earn a living doing menial labor (she works for a cleaning service), she loathes her bosses, looks down on her co-workers, drinks heavily and fantasizes about winning the lottery. And when a friendly neighborhood bartender who fancies her isn't looking, she blithely steals his liquor.</p>
        <p>Maria's nearly hopeless life reaches a crossroads when she becomes pregnant by her boyfriend,  Juan (Juan Fernandez), a burly truck driver who uses her for sex and refuses to accompany her to an abortion clinic when she pleads with him to go.</p>
        <p>While visiting, her mother takes in the whole sad picture of Maria's life without comment and bit by bit she begins to brighten it up. She shops for food. She cooks, places flowers in Maria's bleak apartment and installs a chair she has found on the street. By chance, she also meets her daughter's downstairs neighbor (Carlos Alvarez-Novoa), a lonely old man whose only friend is his loyal dog, Achilles. The two strike up a courtly friendship, and she gives him simple, healthful meals.</p>
        <p>One day, as she is going home from the hospital, Achilles signals that there is trouble. She enters the apartment to find him stricken with diarrhea, and despite his protestations insists on cleaning him up.</p>
        <p>Their friendship has only lasted a matter of days before it's time for her to leave and take her husband home. But before departing, she introduces Maria to the neighbor. The introduction proves profoundly life-changing for the two neighbors, who had never spoken.</p>
        <p>''Solas,'' which opens today at Lincoln Plaza, eventually makes a bold narrative leap that is not entirely convincing. And its final scenes are a bit too patly sentimental for comfort. But Ms. Galiana's quietly monumental performance is one for the ages.</p>
        <p>She is every mother who ever watched a grown-up child stumble through life, swallowed her sadness and disapproval and did what she could to help.</p>
        <p>SOLAS  Written and directed by Benito Zambrano; in Spanish, with English subtitles; director of photography, Tote Trenas; edited by Fernando Pardo; music by Antonio Meliveo; production designer, Lala Obrero; produced by Antonio P. Perez; released by Samuel Goldwyn Films-Fireworks Pictures. At Lincoln Plaza Cinemas, Broadway at 62nd Street. Running time: 98 minutes. This film is not rated.</p>
        <p>WITH: Maria Galiana (Mother), Ana Fernandez (Maria), Paco De Osca (Father), Carlos Alvarez-Novoa (Neighbor), Juan Fernandez (Juan) and Antonio Dechent (Doctor).</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
