<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TRANSACTIONS</title>
    <meta content="08TRNS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228922"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000908T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E1DA1139F93BA3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1074" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TRANSACTIONS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
        <p>National League  SAN DIEGO PADRES--Recalled INF Gabe Alvarez from Las Vegas of the PCL.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
        <p>National League  SAN DIEGO PADRES--Recalled INF Gabe Alvarez from Las Vegas of the PCL.</p>
        <p>BASKETBALL</p>
        <p>National Basketball Association  CHICAGO BULLS--Signed C Brad Miller to an offer sheet for a three-year contract.</p>
        <p>FOOTBALL</p>
        <p>National Football League  JETS--Signed OT Cornell Green to the practice squad. Terminated the contract of OT Jeff Pilon from the practice squad.  NFL--Fined Minnesota Vikings DE Talance Sawyer $7,500 for an illegal hit on Chicago Bears QB Cade McNown on Sept. 3 and Oakland DE Regan Upshaw $7,500 for a late hit on San Diego QB Ryan Leaf on Sept. 3. Suspended Washington Redskins S Mark Carrier for one game for an illegal hit on Carolina Panthers TE Wesley Walls.  ARIZONA CARDINALS--Signed DE Simeon Rice.  CINCINNATI BENGALS--Signed S-KR Tremain Mack to a one-year contract extension through the 2001 season.  MINNESOTA VIKINGS--Signed OT Reginald Nelson to the practice squad.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
        <p>National Hockey League  ISLANDERS--Signed D Roman Hamrlik to a four-year contract.  RANGERS--Signed F Johan Witehall.  NHL PLAYERS' ASSOCIATION--Announced the retirement of D Dave Ellett.  ATLANTA THRASHERS--Agreed to terms with D Andrei Skopintsev.  BUFFALO SABRES--Signed F Vladimir Tsyplakov to a one-year contract and D Jason Woolley to a multiyear contract extension.  COLORADO AVALANCHE--Signed F Milan Hejduk to a four-year contract.  EDMONTON OILERS--Agreed to terms with C Doug Weight on a one-year contract.  FLORIDA PANTHERS--Signed LW Josh Olson.  MONTREAL CANADIENS--Signed RW Dainius Zubrus to a two-year contract.  NASHVILLE PREDATORS--Signed RW Scott Hartnell to a three-year contract.</p>
        <p>SOCCER</p>
        <p>Major League Soccer  TAMPA BAY MUTINY--Named Bill Dunn vice president-corporate partnerships, Blake Cronin sales manager-soccer community, Valerie Lossa and Kate Kowalczyk account executives and Janet Vasquez sales manager-hispanic markets.</p>
        <p>COLLEGE</p>
        <p>ATLANTIC COAST CONFERENCE--Announced the formation of the ACC/SEC Regional Officiating Program. Named John Guthrie head of the program.  BARUCH--Named Kenyatta Pious men's assistant basketball coach.  CALDWELL--Named Jill Fishchman and John DeSio women's assistant coaches, Robert Kearns assistant baseball coach and Edwin Schieferstein women's assistant soccer coach.  CAL POLY-SLO--Promoted Mike LaPlante to associate athletic director for advancement, Chris Baker to assistant athletic director for marketing-promotions, and Jason Sullivan to assistant athletic director for media relations.  CHATTANOOGA--Named Don Harris women's sports information officer.  CINCINNNATI--Named Keith LeGree men's assistant basketball coach.  DAVIDSON--Named Jim Conlon men's and women's swimming and diving coach.  DREXEL--Named Jay Oxenberg operations coordinator-recreation.  DUQUESNE--Named Jim Curti assistant golf coach.  GUILFORD--Named Adam Taylor assistant baseball coach and Rob Woodall assistant athletic trainer.  HARTFORD--Named Chris Pompey men's assistant basketball coach.  HARTWICK--Named Allison Blixt, women's assistant field hockey coach, Catherine McEnroe, women's assistant soccer coach, and Aileen Gerhardt, women's assistant volleyball coach.  LEMOYNE--Named Anthony Staffiere women's assistant basketball coach.  MANHATTANVILLE--Named Matthew Bucci sports information director.  NEW ENGLAND--Named Leslie Mourmouras men's and women's assistant cross-country coach.  RAMAPO--Named Salma Goldstein men's tennis coach and Kathleen Finnegan women's assistant basketball coach.  RHODE ISLAND--Named Brad Bustin and Marc Pantazis assitant baseball coaches and Hector Cardona women's soccer coach.  ST FRANCIS, PA.--Named Jacob Morton men's assistant basketball coach.  ST. JOSEPH'S, PA.--Named Chris Branscome and Jack Ruggero men's assistant soccer coaches.  SANTA BARBARA--Named Pam Tanase women's water polo coach.  SETON HALL--Named R.J Boergers assistant athletic trainer.  SYRACUSE--Named Todd Wyant associate athletic director for student-athlete support services.  WAKE FOREST--Named Jennifer Hoppe women's assistant cross-country and track &amp; field coach.  WAYNE STATE, MICH.--Named Melvin Foreman men's tennis coach and Mike Horn golf coach.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
