<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>As Camps Open, Simply Be Aware: Devils Are Planning More of the Same</title>
    <meta content="MB022514" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228873"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Free Agents (Sports)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Jersey Devils</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Yankeenets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yannis, Alex</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lamoriello, Lou</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New Jersey Devils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Free Agents (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000908T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E5DB1339F93BA3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="672" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>As Camps Open, Simply Be Aware: Devils Are Planning More of the Same</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEX YANNIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Yannis, Alex</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lou Lamoriello will enter his 15th year dictating fortunes of New Jersey Devils as team opens training camp; says sale of team to YankeeNets will not alter team's philosophy or its approach to restricted free agents; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The more things change around the Devils, the more they remain the same. The sale of the team to YankeeNets will not alter the team's philosophy or its approach to restricted free agents: Lou Lamoriello will not yield.</p>
        <p>Lamoriello, who enters his 15th year dictating the team's fortunes as the Devils open training camp today, will have to deal with the restricted free agents Jason Arnott and Scott Niedermayer. Arnott, a center, scored the overtime goal that clinched the Stanley Cup, and Niedermayer is the team's most skillful defenseman.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The more things change around the Devils, the more they remain the same. The sale of the team to YankeeNets will not alter the team's philosophy or its approach to restricted free agents: Lou Lamoriello will not yield.</p>
        <p>Lamoriello, who enters his 15th year dictating the team's fortunes as the Devils open training camp today, will have to deal with the restricted free agents Jason Arnott and Scott Niedermayer. Arnott, a center, scored the overtime goal that clinched the Stanley Cup, and Niedermayer is the team's most skillful defenseman.</p>
        <p>But Arnott and Niedermayer are certain to miss the first day of camp because they did not report for their physicals yesterday at the training facility in West Orange, N.J. This is nothing new for the Devils, because Lamoriello often finds himself in contract showdowns with his players, showdowns that he always seems to win.</p>
        <p>Niedermayer sat out until November two years ago and Arnott signed qualifying offers the last two seasons.</p>
        <p>It has been a short off-season for the Devils, who won the Stanley Cup only 90 days ago by dethroning the Dallas Stars. It was New Jersey's second Cup victory in the last five years. Now, it is back to work for the players and for Lamoriello, who said the transition in ownership from John McMullen to Puck Holdings has been flawless.</p>
        <p>''Nothing has been interrupted about the way we've been doing things,'' Lamoriello said.</p>
        <p>Just as in his first 14 years with the Devils, Lamoriello is involved in every aspect of the team's business. One of his tasks will be to avoid the fiasco of 1996, when the Devils failed to make the playoffs after their first Stanley Cup triumph in 1995. Interestingly, there is one glaring similarity between then and now: Claude Lemieux will not be a Devil.</p>
        <p>''It's definite that Claude will not be returning,'' said Lamoriello, who first parted ways with Lemieux in 1995 even though Lemieux was the most valuable player in the Stanley Cup playoffs that summer.</p>
        <p>Unlike Arnott and Niedermayer, Lemieux is an unrestricted free agent. He is seeking a four-year deal for about $15 million, figures not part of Lamoriello's vocabulary.</p>
        <p>Lamoriello admitted that ''you never replace a Claude Lemieux,'' but he feels he has the closest thing in Turner Stevenson, a strong wing who Lamoriello has called ''a prototype, Devil-type forward who plays, hits and can fight.''</p>
        <p>The Devils acquired Stevenson from Columbus as the future consideration in the deal that sent Krzysztof Oliwa to the expansion Blue Jackets.</p>
        <p>Lamoriello also hopes that he has a good replacement for Oliwa in Jim McKenzie, who signed as a free agent in July after spending last season with Anaheim and Washington.</p>
        <p>Lamoriello and Coach Larry Robinson must find replacements for defensemen Vladimir Malakhov who signed with with the Rangers, and Brad Bombardir, who was traded to the expansion Minnesota Wild for goaltender Chris Terreri. Subsequently, Terreri was selected by Minnesota in the expansion draft.</p>
        <p>Willie Mitchell and Josef Boumedienne are the leading candidates to replace Malakhov and Bombardir.</p>
        <p>Mitchell would have probably made the team last year but broke his arm in training camp, while Boumedienne is considered a top prospect. Boumidienne, a native of Sweden who has been playing in Europe, was the Devils' seventh choice in the 1996 draft.</p>
        <p>''Any time you come off a championship season you have high expectations,'' Lamoriello said. ''But you also have to be realistic that at the start of the season there will be 10 to 15 teams with a chance. Then, in the middle of the season, there will be 8 to 10 teams to challenge for the title. I hope we will be there at the end.''</p>
        <p>Lamoriello brushed aside any fears of repeating what happened in 1996.</p>
        <p>''That was a new experience for a lot of people,'' he said. ''The people who played 10 minutes in 1995 thought they should be playing 15 in 1996 and didn't deserve to play 5. We have different kind of people now.''</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
