<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Recovery Slow, But Martin Gains Semis</title>
    <meta content="08TENN$10" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/08/sports/08TENN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228855"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="U.S. OPEN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Open (Tennis)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Robbins, Liz</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Martin, Todd</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johansson, Thomas</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Open (Tennis)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000908T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E0DC1339F93BA3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="950" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Recovery Slow, But Martin Gains Semis</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIZ ROBBINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Robbins, Liz</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Todd Martin eliminates Thomas Johansson to advance to semifinals at United States Open; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When he stormed to a two-set lead in last night's quarterfinal match of the United States Open, Todd Martin forgot his legs felt as if they were attached to cinder blocks, his broken-down body hastily repaired by intravenous fluids and massages for the previous 48 hours.</p>
        <p>Martin, 30, at first moved nimbly and seemed like the folk hero inspired by his own resuscitation two nights earlier in his five-set comeback victory over Carlos Moya.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When he stormed to a two-set lead in last night's quarterfinal match of the United States Open, Todd Martin forgot his legs felt as if they were attached to cinder blocks, his broken-down body hastily repaired by intravenous fluids and massages for the previous 48 hours.</p>
        <p>Martin, 30, at first moved nimbly and seemed like the folk hero inspired by his own resuscitation two nights earlier in his five-set comeback victory over Carlos Moya.</p>
        <p>But his limited supply of energy, physical and mental, could not last. Not when his opponent, Thomas Johansson, had obviously cribbed a page from Martin's two-sets-down comeback chapter, and rocked aces that threatened to send the match into the murky five-set territory. Martin's legs crawled from side to side, but trailing by 4-2 in the fourth set, he knew what he had to do.</p>
        <p>''I understood I didn't need to do everything perfectly,'' Martin said. ''I just needed to do something at the right time better than Thomas could.''</p>
        <p>Leading, two sets to one, Martin recovered from that 4-2 deficit in the fourth set and won, 6-4, 6-4, 3-6, 7-5. He earns a return trip to the United States Open semifinals, where he will face 20-year-old Marat Safin tomorrow.</p>
        <p>''Being in the semis of the Open was the greatest thing since sliced bread,'' said Martin, who lost in the final to Andre Agassi last year. ''Cutters are still sharp. This is awesome.''</p>
        <p>Safin, seeded sixth, defeated 14th-seeded Nicolas Kiefer, 7-5, 4-6, 7-6 (5), 6-3. Safin played both brilliant and head-scratching tennis on the Arthur Ashe Stadium Court on Day 11 of the Open to advance to his first semifinals of a Grand Slam event.</p>
        <p>While Safin arrives on the adrenaline of youth, Martin advances one more round with the veteran experience, his legs aching.</p>
        <p>Instead of being the Bunyanesque crowd-pleaser of Tuesday night, Martin was more the gray-haired man from the Midwest last night. He was not flashy, but he was triumphant when it counted, offering a few well-timed fist-pumps reminiscent of his battle cries in the magical morning hours one round before.</p>
        <p>''It's not supposed to happen every day of the year,'' he said of his unusual show of emotion. ''But you do need to draw on energy that is there in the crowd. And then from there, their energy inspires more energy from you.''</p>
        <p>Martin, who is running on adrenaline and infused hydration, was not the only medical miracle on the court last night. Last year, one week before the Open, doctors diagnosed a viral infection around the lining of Johannson's heart. The 25-year-old from Sweden recovered, but had a rocky year, losing in the first round of 10 of 15 tournaments before the Open.</p>
        <p>He looked lost early. A break in the fifth game was all Martin needed to win the first set. In the second set, again in the fifth game, Martin earned the only break he needed. When he ripped a crosscourt winner with an unforgiving angle, Martin clenched his fist.</p>
        <p>In the third set, Johansson got his break in the fourth game and he won the set on his 15th of 23 aces in the match, committing just three unforced errors that whole set. ''He was too good; he really picked his serve up,'' Martin said. ''Walking back and forth to receive his serves really took me out of my rhythm.''</p>
        <p>By then, Martin was showing signs of fatigue, not able to run to every drop shot. Johansson broke him in the first game of the fifth set, when Martin's backhand half-volley landed in the net. Johansson finished a love service game with his 20th ace to take a 4-2 lead. But Martin held on his serve and carried the momentum. He broke Johansson on a forehand that clipped the baseline and sent him clenching his fist and Johansson spiking the ball in anger.</p>
        <p>Martin capitalized on the ugly points, and suddenly they were back on serve, and Johansson was serving to reach a tie breaker. Martin had two match points when he blasted a forehand cross court and Johansson's backhand fell into the net.</p>
        <p>Martin's tempered mood afterward was in contrast to the more playful Safin earlier in the day.</p>
        <p>A booming 6-foot-4-inch Russian baseliner with a bronze tan, Safin boasted about not smashing his racket for five straight matches now, since way back in the first round of the Open.</p>
        <p>If he can figure out who he is -- a 20-year-old with the attention span of a bored A student, or one of the top men's players -- his career could take another turn. Yesterday, his personalities swiveled back and forth again, as did his concentration.</p>
        <p>Consider this swing yesterday: Kiefer held a 5-2 lead and was serving for the set at 5-3. But Safin broke him and won four straight games to take a 1-0 lead in the match. ''I knew I was very close to losing this set, so I was a hundred percent concentrated,'' Safin said.</p>
        <p>The percentage plummeted in the next set, as Safin responded in reverse to momentum. Kiefer took advantage.</p>
        <p>Kiefer saved three match points in the final set, but Safin finished off the match on his serve, blasting a second serve 131 miles an hour for a service winner. Safin had 16 aces, 47 winners and 42 unforced errors.</p>
        <p>U.S. OPEN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
