<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Giants Are Wary Of Eagles' Offense</title>
    <meta content="08GIAN$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/08/sports/08GIAN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228783"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Philadelphia Eagles</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Giants</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hermoso, Rafael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Staley, Duce</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Philadelphia Eagles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000908T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E4D61239F93BA3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="712" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Giants Are Wary Of Eagles' Offense</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RAFAEL HERMOSO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hermoso, Rafael</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., Sept. 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Philadelphia Eagles' primary threat in upcoming game against New York Giants will be Duce Staley (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Eagles began the season with a successful onside kick. Their pass rush tormented Dallas for five sacks, and Troy Aikman was knocked out of the game with the ninth concussion of his career. But nothing scares the Giants more than the Eagles' offense.</p>
        <p>''They're going to run the ball, and they're going to run the ball quite a bit,'' the Giants' defensive coordinator, John Fox, said today.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Eagles began the season with a successful onside kick. Their pass rush tormented Dallas for five sacks, and Troy Aikman was knocked out of the game with the ninth concussion of his career. But nothing scares the Giants more than the Eagles' offense.</p>
        <p>''They're going to run the ball, and they're going to run the ball quite a bit,'' the Giants' defensive coordinator, John Fox, said today.</p>
        <p>The Eagles' primary threat is Duce Staley, who terrorized the Cowboys, rushing for 201 yards on 26 carries to lead a 41-14 romp. Staley averaged 80 yards in the Eagles' two losses last season to the Giants, but Giants Coach Jim Fassel said that Staley is a more physical runner.</p>
        <p>''He gets a lot of violent yards,'' Fox said.</p>
        <p>The Eagles' offense, however, is not one-dimensional. Donovan McNabb is a strong-armed, mobile quarterback who scrambled 5 times for 29 yards against Dallas.</p>
        <p>''You have to decide: can we get to him, can we put pressure on him and do we need to heat him up to make him ineffective,'' Fassel said.</p>
        <p>Linebacker Jessie Armstead said, ''When he gets outside the pocket, he's just like another running back.''</p>
        <p>The Giants sense that their 21-16 victory over an injury-ravaged Arizona team was not a true indication of where they stand. The defense held Arizona to 3 points for 58 minutes Sunday before nearly wasting all of a 21-3 lead in the closing minutes, and the defensive line did not register a sack.</p>
        <p>Fassel has been careful not to criticize his defensive line, but he has also made it clear he would like to see some sacks, or least some pressure on the quarterback.</p>
        <p>Defensive end Michael Strahan had just 5.5 sacks last season after a combined total of 29 in 1997 and 1998. Sunday, after the Cardinals lost right tackle L. J. Shelton to a knee injury on the first play from scrimmage, Strahan played some series on the right side against the second-team tackle Ethan Brooks and still could not record a sack.</p>
        <p>Strahan, who returned an interception of Eagles quarterback Doug Pederson for a touchdown in overtime last season, has kept a low profile this week. Fox stood up for him today.</p>
        <p>''I think what's frustrating is a lot of emphasis is put on sacks, and obviously we'd all like to see them,'' Fox said. ''There's more to playing defensive end in this league than just sacks.''</p>
        <p>Just getting beyond the line of scrimmage will be a tough task. Right tackle Jon Runyon and left tackle Tra Thomas weigh a combined 679 pounds.</p>
        <p>Fox refrained from calling too many blitzes against the Cardinals, instead looking for pressure on Jake Plummer from his four linemen. They did not get it. The Giants' only sack came from middle linebacker Mike Barrow with 47 seconds left.</p>
        <p>Barrow, a speedy free-agent acquisition, should help the Giants' run defense, which has slipped since Fassel's first year in 1997. It allowed only 90.7 yards per game that season, third best in the National Football League. That dropped to 23rd (125.3 yards) in 1998, but rebounded to 13th (97.5 yards) last season.</p>
        <p>The Giants would suffer if strong safety Sam Garnes is unavailable after sustaining a concussion Sunday. He would play a big role in the run defense and his replacement is Lyle West, a second-year player whose experience before this season was limited to six games on special teams last season.</p>
        <p>EXTRA POINTS</p>
        <p>Quarterback KERRY COLLINS sympathized with TROY AIKMAN after the Cowboys passer sustained his ninth concussion, against the Eagles Sunday. ''You're talking about your mental health, not just your physical health, but your mental health as well for the rest of your life,'' Collins said. He had a mild concussion three years ago and felt fortunate that he has remained relatively healthy, but was resigned to the possibility it could happen again. ''It's part of your job,'' Collins said. ''You play the game and if you get hit, you get hit.''  . . . Coach JIM FASSEL said safety SAM GARNES (concussion) and tight end PETE MITCHELL (knee) have a 50-50 chance of playing Sunday.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
