<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>It's a Handshake and Small Talk for Clinton and Castro</title>
    <meta content="Y08CAS$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/08/world/08CAST.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228819"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SUMMIT IN NEW YORK: A CUBAN MOMENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Cuba</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Castro, Fidel (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Albright, Madeleine K (Sec)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sanger, David E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Cuba</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Cuba</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000908T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E2DD1339F93BA3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="647" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>It's a Handshake and Small Talk for Clinton and Castro</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID E. SANGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sanger, David E</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>White House acknowledges that Pres Clinton actually shook hands with Fidel Castro when two encountered each other at UN luncheon, and apparently spoke to each other for first time; Sec Madeline Albright quickly cautions that there 'was no substance' in conversation, although, with US-Cuban relations, even empty talk is brimming with symbolism (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The last time President Clinton and Fidel Castro were in the same room, in October 1995 at a United Nations reception in New York, the Secret Service deftly kept the two men apart. Not a word or a handshake was exchanged.</p>
        <p>So anyone tracing the glacial progress in Cuban-American relations -- always a sensitive political issue, especially in New Jersey,  New York and Florida, three key states in the coming presidential election -- should note that the White House this week quietly reversed its Cuban handshake policy. After changing its story several times, the White House press office said yesterday that Mr. Clinton and Mr. Castro actually shook hands on Wednesday, on the edges of a luncheon for the meeting of world leaders at the United Nations. It was apparently the first time Mr. Castro, 74, had ever shaken hands with a sitting American president.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The last time President Clinton and Fidel Castro were in the same room, in October 1995 at a United Nations reception in New York, the Secret Service deftly kept the two men apart. Not a word or a handshake was exchanged.</p>
        <p>So anyone tracing the glacial progress in Cuban-American relations -- always a sensitive political issue, especially in New Jersey,  New York and Florida, three key states in the coming presidential election -- should note that the White House this week quietly reversed its Cuban handshake policy. After changing its story several times, the White House press office said yesterday that Mr. Clinton and Mr. Castro actually shook hands on Wednesday, on the edges of a luncheon for the meeting of world leaders at the United Nations. It was apparently the first time Mr. Castro, 74, had ever shaken hands with a sitting American president.</p>
        <p>Moreover, the president of the United States and the leader who has bedeviled every occupant of the White House since the Eisenhower administration apparently spoke to each other for the first time. But this afternoon, Secretary of State Madeleine K. Albright, who usually describes all conversations between her boss and other national leaders as deep and important, was quick to caution that ''there was no substance'' to the conversation.</p>
        <p>But in relations with Cuba, even empty talk is brimming with symbolism.</p>
        <p>The last time Vice President Al Gore talked Cuba policy -- about the fate of Elian Gonzalez, the young boy who was ultimately returned to Cuba over the objections of his Miami relatives -- it dominated campaign news for days. And so even the thought of Mr. Clinton and Mr. Castro making polite conversation is bound to be viewed with suspicion by Cuban-Americans already smarting from the Elian incident. Perhaps that explains why the White House spokesman, Joe Lockhart, when first asked about the encounter, said reports of a handshake were ''not true.'' Later, other officials said Mr. Lockhart had been insufficiently briefed. ''On background,'' one official said, ''I can confirm there was a handshake.''</p>
        <p>With all this diplomatic sensitivity on display, Dr. Albright and the White House went to some lengths yesterday to make the point that Mr. Clinton did not seek out one of the world's last true Communist leaders. ''As I understand it,'' Dr. Albright said, ''it was a chance encounter that Mr. Castro initiated, and they talked for a couple of minutes, and there was no substance.'' Administration officials were under strict orders not to detail the small talk.</p>
        <p>This was not the first time Mr. Castro has had an encounter with top American leaders.</p>
        <p>Soon after coming to power in 1959 after the Cuban revolution, Mr. Castro flew to Washington and met the sitting vice president, Richard M. Nixon. President Eisenhower had decided that it was not appropriate for him to see Mr. Castro because of the unsettled situation in Cuba. So Mr. Eisenhower's secretary of state, Christian Herter, asked Mr. Nixon to meet the Cuban leader and give the president his assessment of him.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, when the White House spokesman finally confirmed that President Clinton and Mr. Castro had indeed shaken hands, he pointed out that President Bush had also come close to Mr. Castro several times, including at a conference in Rio de Janeiro in June 1992. But the two apparently never spoke, and certainly never shook hands, according to reports at the time, although Mr. Bush applauded several times during a speech by Mr. Castro.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Clinton is not about to repeat the experience. Almost all the world leaders attending the summit meeting here were invited to a reception yesterday at the Metropolitan Museum of Art. But the White House made a point of keeping Mr. Castro's name off the list.</p>
        <p>SUMMIT IN NEW YORK: A CUBAN MOMENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
