<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>So Who Is She? His Lover, His Muse or His Nightmare?</title>
    <meta content="08POLA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/08/arts/08POLA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228725"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">New York Film Festival</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holden, Stephen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carax, Leos</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Pola X (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New York Film Festival</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New York Film Festival</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000908T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE4D61539F93BA3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="802" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>So Who Is She? His Lover, His Muse or His Nightmare?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Excerpts from Stephen Holden's October 5 review of Pola X, film by Leos Carax that was shown at 1999 New York Film Festival; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''Pola X'' was shown as part of last year's New York Film Festival. Following are excerpts from Stephen Holden's review, which appeared in The New York Times on Oct. 5. The film, in French with English subtitles, opens today at the Angelika Film Center, Mercer and Houston Streets, Greenwich Village.</p>
        <p>With ''Pola X,'' a noisy epic swirl of breast-beating, hair-tearing angst and portentous symbolism, the 39-year-old director Leos Carax captures the dubious title of French cinema's reigning mad romantic. This sometimes intoxicating, often infuriating film about the frenzied downward spiral of a naive young writer in search of ultimate truth was adapted from Melville's 1852 novel,</p>
        <p>''Pierre, or the Ambiguities.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''Pola X'' was shown as part of last year's New York Film Festival. Following are excerpts from Stephen Holden's review, which appeared in The New York Times on Oct. 5. The film, in French with English subtitles, opens today at the Angelika Film Center, Mercer and Houston Streets, Greenwich Village.</p>
        <p>With ''Pola X,'' a noisy epic swirl of breast-beating, hair-tearing angst and portentous symbolism, the 39-year-old director Leos Carax captures the dubious title of French cinema's reigning mad romantic. This sometimes intoxicating, often infuriating film about the frenzied downward spiral of a naive young writer in search of ultimate truth was adapted from Melville's 1852 novel,</p>
        <p>''Pierre, or the Ambiguities.''</p>
        <p>Although much of the film is set in and around contemporary Paris, its portrait of Pierre (Guillaume Depardieu, the very blond son of Gerard) -- who furiously rejects his upper-class background and embraces ''la vie de boheme'' -- is turgid 19th-century hokum brought to life with a wild, flailing passion.</p>
        <p>The agent of Pierre's downfall is a witchy phantom, Isabella (Katerina Golubeva), who claims to be his half-sister and who first appears to him in  dreams, then later stalks him in the flesh. Enthralled by this grim, vampirish creature of darkness who dresses like a peasant and wears no makeup, Pierre adopts her as his muse, lover and destroyer.</p>
        <p>When we first meet Pierre, he is the pampered, golden young author of a best-selling cult novel written under the pseudonym Aladin. The movie's ravishing early sequences drool over Pierre's privileged existence on a picture-perfect Normandy estate where he lives with his adoring (and controlling) widowed mother, Marie (Catherine Deneuve).</p>
        <p>Pierre is engaged to Lucie (Delphine Chuillot), an ingenuous blond aristocrat whom he regards as a beautiful, unformed child. But their storybook romance is shadowed by Pierre's troubled dreams, Isabella's lurking presence and the barely concealed resentment of Pierre's cousin, Thibault (Laurent Lucas), who is also in love with Lucie.</p>
        <p>When the young writer finally confronts the woman who has been haunting him, she pours out her personal history in a long, dreadfully written speech consisting of broken sentences that sketch a fearful personal history scarred by poverty and war. Guilt-ridden and convinced that Isabella holds the key to his destiny, Pierre impulsively flees his privileged life and takes her to Paris, where they set up housekeeping in a giant surreal warehouse on the outskirts of the city. Here Pierre abandons his computer to write his manuscripts by hand and gets involved with an unidentified terrorist group.</p>
        <p>Like the replica of the Pont Neuf that dominated Mr. Carax's last film, the notoriously expensive and hyper-romantic ''Lovers on the Bridge,'' the warehouse is this movie's coup de cinema. With its yard guarded by howling black dogs straining at their leashes, the place suggests a giant, festering Pandora's box that harbors all the emotional, spiritual and political ills of the world. In the heart of this structure, connected to the outside world by a narrow metal bridge, a gaunt, wild-eyed conductor leads an orchestra in an ear-splitting symphony of industrial rock.</p>
        <p>''Pola X'' is best appreciated as a raw, undigested allegory that  changes in meaning as the film goes along. (The title is an acronym for the French ''Pierre, ou les Ambiguites,'' with an X for draft 10 of the script.)</p>
        <p>At first Isabella appears to be a symbol of the third world hammering insistently at the door of affluent Western Europe. But she turns out to be much more. An omniverous and irresistible erotic force, a walking nightmare, she is the personification of a chaotic darkness that Pierre (and perhaps Mr. Carax himself)  perceives as the unbearable truth that must be pursued, even if it proves to be beyond the grasp of art.</p>
        <p>The movie itself is chaotic. Some characters aren't identified, and others abruptly disappear and then unexpectedly return. The acting, although intense, only fitfully rises to the mythic level the director is aiming for. Mr. Carax is much better at creating pungent atmospheres than at structuring scenes. But ''Pola X'' still has its share of dazzling and  disturbing images: in addition to the  industrial landscape, a bride on a pedestal being fitted for a gown, lovers grappling in an ominous semi-darkness and a woman streaking through the night on a motorcycle that suddenly crashes.</p>
        <p>For all its mess and romantic excess, ''Pola X'' has enough fireworks to keep you in your seat. When it's over, you'll know you've had an experience.</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
