<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Safety Can Cost Too Much</title>
    <meta content="08LEVY$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/08/opinion/08LEVY.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000909T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228774"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tires</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Defective Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recalls and Bans of Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bridgestone Tire &amp; Rubber Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ford Motor Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Levy, Robert A</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Defective Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recalls and Bans of Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tires</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000908T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E2D71239F93BA3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="677" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Safety Can Cost Too Much</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Robert A. Levy</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Levy, Robert A</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Op-Ed article by Robert A Levy of Cato Institute warns that current public upset over defective tires should not forestall more dispassionate look at pluses and minuses of granting federal government yet more regulatory authority (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After 88 deaths and who knows how many serious injuries, the temptation is almost irresistible to bring the boot of government down more heavily on the neck of Firestone and, by extension, other tire makers and auto-related industries. But the current environment -- perhaps best characterized as near-hysteria -- is precisely the wrong one in which to be formulating new regulations. We need to step back and take a dispassionate look at both the pluses and minuses of granting the federal government yet more authority in this area.</p>
        <p>That's not to say that Firestone and Ford should escape punishment if the evidence supports civil liability or even criminal sanctions. The government regulations that are in place must be enforced, along with common law and statutory remedies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After 88 deaths and who knows how many serious injuries, the temptation is almost irresistible to bring the boot of government down more heavily on the neck of Firestone and, by extension, other tire makers and auto-related industries. But the current environment -- perhaps best characterized as near-hysteria -- is precisely the wrong one in which to be formulating new regulations. We need to step back and take a dispassionate look at both the pluses and minuses of granting the federal government yet more authority in this area.</p>
        <p>That's not to say that Firestone and Ford should escape punishment if the evidence supports civil liability or even criminal sanctions. The government regulations that are in place must be enforced, along with common law and statutory remedies.</p>
        <p>The broader question, however, is what sort of regime should be put in place for the next safety-related problem.</p>
        <p>Every year 40,000 Americans die in auto-related accidents. We could eliminate that horrific cost overnight by banning automobiles, or requiring every car to have the safety features of a tank, or mandating that cars be designed to travel no faster than five miles an hour. Of course, those remedies all sound silly. We have decided that the benefits of driving today's cars at today's speeds outweigh the costs -- enormous though they are -- of 40,000 annual deaths.</p>
        <p>That utilitarian calculus is applied every day in various contexts. Sometimes we analyze the cost-benefit tradeoffs explicitly; other times, as in the example of auto deaths, only implicitly. Either way, there's nothing misguided or immoral about it.</p>
        <p>In the Firestone case, there are two important guideposts.</p>
        <p>First, will any particular proposed new rule lead to unintended, adverse consequences? Government regulation frequently imposes hidden and substantial costs on industry and, indirectly, on consumers. In part, that's because bureaucrats operate with perverse incentives. If a product is not recalled and injuries occur, government will inevitably be blamed. If there is a recall when there was really little threat to safety, however, the regulators are not likely to be criticized. The likely result is more recalls and regulations than are justified by the facts -- and greater costs in both higher prices and lost opportunities as good products are kept off the market.</p>
        <p>Second, are there more cost-effective, less intrusive means of attaining the desired objectives? Government regulation is not the only safeguard for consumers against corporate negligence or corruption. The market itself provides a protection: who will now buy Firestone products, unless they can be proved safe? The courts provide another. Not only Firestone, but its parent company and Ford as well, can be sued for compensatory and maybe punitive damages. Then there are private certifying organizations, like Consumers Union and Underwriters Laboratory, which would undoubtedly take on a greater role if government were not involved.</p>
        <p>In any situation where government is tempted to step in, there is also the deeper question of whether federal intrusion is even authorized by the Constitution. In the Firestone case, the answer is clearly yes. Since tires are integrally related to maintaining the free flow of commerce among the states, Congress can pass appropriate legislation under the Commerce Clause -- though arguably rules emanating from an administrative agency like the National Highway Transportation Safety Administration are a usurpation of Congress's legislative powers. Safety regulations applied to many other products, however, like guns and drugs, are justified only by a tortured reading of the Commerce Clause.</p>
        <p>In the Firestone case, as in every other, the reflexive lurch toward more government as the solution might satisfy our desire to do something, but we must also consider whether the action we contemplate will be fair and will advance our larger goals.</p>
        <p>Robert A. Levy is senior fellow in constitutional studies at the Cato Institute.</p>
        <p>Correction:  September 9, 2000, Saturday  An article in Business Day on Aug. 31 about a regulatory agency investigation of defective Firestone tires misstated the name of the agency. The error also occurred in an editorial on Thursday and an Op-Ed article yesterday. The agency is the National Highway Traffic Safety Administration, not the National Highway Transportation Safety Administration.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: September 9, 2000, Saturday</p>
        <p>An article in Business Day on Aug. 31 about a regulatory agency investigation of defective Firestone tires misstated the name of the agency. The error also occurred in an editorial on Thursday and an Op-Ed article yesterday. The agency is the National Highway Traffic Safety Administration, not the National Highway Transportation Safety Administration.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Robert A. Levy is senior fellow in constitutional studies at the Cato Institute.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
