<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Clinton Won't Meet His Goal Of Mideast Peace, Aides Fear</title>
    <meta content="08MIDE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/08/world/08MIDE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228809"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SUMMIT IN NEW YORK: CAMP DAVID AFTERMATH"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Temple Mount (Jerusalem)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Middle East</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Jerusalem</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barak, Ehud (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arafat, Yasir</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perlez, Jane</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel/Jerusalem</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000908T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E1DE1339F93BA3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1258" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Clinton Won't Meet His Goal Of Mideast Peace, Aides Fear</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE PERLEZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Perlez, Jane</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>White House, having made sustained effort to seal Middle East peace accord, has begun to sense that solution is slipping away, and will not come during Pres Clinton's term; Clinton has met with Prime Min Ehud Barak and Yasir Arafat during UN summit, but Arafat reportedly failed to give assurances that he will agree to solution on Jerusalem; private assessments are gloomy, although neither Barak nor Arafat have threatened to walk away; US official notes that Arafat denies basic respect to negotiating partner when he refuses even to recognize existence of Temple Mount that is most sacred of all places to Jews; Barak reiterates that Jerusalem and Temple Mount are cornerstone of Jewish identity; photo; reminds Arafat that when Jesus walked in Jerusalem he saw not churches or mosques but the Jewish Temple (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After a sustained effort to seal a Middle East peace accord, the White House has begun to sense that a solution is slipping away, and senior administration officials say they are preparing themselves for the likelihood that a deal will not come during President Clinton's time in office.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton is not about to give up abruptly what has been one of his most cherished and hard-fought foreign policy goals, but senior administration officials said the momentum generated at the Camp David summit meeting in July had been lost.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After a sustained effort to seal a Middle East peace accord, the White House has begun to sense that a solution is slipping away, and senior administration officials say they are preparing themselves for the likelihood that a deal will not come during President Clinton's time in office.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton is not about to give up abruptly what has been one of his most cherished and hard-fought foreign policy goals, but senior administration officials said the momentum generated at the Camp David summit meeting in July had been lost.</p>
        <p>President Clinton has met this week with Prime Minister Ehud Barak of Israel and Yasir Arafat, the Palestinian leader, while the men are in New York for the United Nations talks.</p>
        <p>But senior administration officials said Mr. Arafat had failed to give sufficient assurances that he would agree to a solution on Jerusalem and, in particular, on sovereignty over the sites there that are sacred to Muslims, Jews and Christians.</p>
        <p>In public yesterday, President Clinton and Secretary of State Madeleine K. Albright kept open the possibility of future meetings. But even Mr. Clinton suggested that he would not meet again with Mr. Arafat or Mr. Barak this week.</p>
        <p>And in private, assessments were even gloomier.</p>
        <p>Neither Mr. Barak nor Mr. Arafat have threatened to walk away. They have both pledged to keep going, administration officials said.</p>
        <p>But the administration is not prepared to keep talks going for the sake of talking, a senior official said.</p>
        <p>''It's not our job to give it life support if it's not breathing,'' the official said. ''On the one hand, we heard some movement but not sufficient, and not with the kind of precision that we need to hear, that looks anything like a process that goes to closure.''</p>
        <p>During the eight years of his presidency, Mr. Clinton has spent more time than any other president talking and negotiating with Israelis and Palestinians in search of a final peace agreement. He oversaw the momentous signing ceremony for the Oslo peace accords in 1993 at the White House, where he extended his arms to ensure a handshake between Mr. Arafat and Prime Minister Yitzhak Rabin. And the president also helped broker the accords reached after great pain at Wye Plantation in 1998. But yesterday, Mr. Clinton sounded uncertain about future steps.</p>
        <p>''I don't know if there will be any more meetings while we are here,'' Mr. Clinton said before meeting this morning with the President Kim Dae Jung of South Korea. ''We'll see where we are and whether anything else can be done while we're here.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Albright said at a news conference, ''The truth is, just look at the calendar, and there is not a lot of time.''</p>
        <p>For the first time, Mr. Clinton's senior advisers are beginning to talk about their achievements at Camp David as possibly being material for another administration to build on.</p>
        <p>''Before Camp David, there was a huge iceberg,'' said President Clinton's national security adviser, Samuel R. Berger. ''We sent an icebreaker through it, and we cracked it open 100 different ways -- refugees, Jerusalem, security, borders.</p>
        <p>''The good news is that this is no longer just an iceberg, it's 100 pieces of ice. Can this be reassembled into something like a bridge? I don't know.''</p>
        <p>The emphasis on the shortage of time by Dr. Albright was prompted by several factors. First, there is the belief within the administration that the longer the two sides remain apart, the harder it becomes to put the pieces back together.</p>
        <p>One administration official said confidence was being lost, not unlike the drift that occurred after talks between Israel and Syria ended in Shepherdstown, W.Va., this year and were never reconvened.</p>
        <p>Just as important, Prime Minister Barak must start to try to repair his weak political situation at home by the beginning of next month. Parliament returns to session at the end of October, and if a peace agreement looks impossible, Mr. Barak wants to spend most of October reconfiguring his government by joining with the rightist Likud Party and others.</p>
        <p>Thus, even though Mr. Clinton made conceptual breakthroughs at Camp David, there was not enough time left to delve into the finer details of the weighty issues of religion and national identity.</p>
        <p>''In the final analysis, this issue may have too far to go -- from 2000 years of history and 52 years of not really coming to grips with shared aspirations,'' one senior official said.</p>
        <p>The main sticking point remained the Temple Mount, known to Arabs as Haram al-Sharif.</p>
        <p>Mr. Arafat has been saying since the Camp David talks, when the question of sovereignty over the site was raised, that the Temple does not exist, a senior administration official said. By insisting that what the Jews consider to be the most sacred of their holy sites was not even a Jewish place, Mr. Arafat was denying a basic respect to his main negotiating partner, the official said.</p>
        <p>''This can't be solved by denying the beliefs of one of the great religions,'' the official said.</p>
        <p>For Jews, the Temple Mount is the most sacred of all places, the site of the First and Second Temples destroyed by the Babylonians and the Romans. Among the Muslims, the site and its two Muslim shrines, the Dome of the Rock and Al Aksa Mosque, are among the holiest of all sites.</p>
        <p>At Camp David, Mr. Barak tentatively agreed to the notion that the Palestinians could be granted religious sovereignty over the Mount, with the Israelis retaining political sovereignty. But after leaving Camp David, Mr. Barak made clear that nothing was agreed to until every aspect of the deal was agree to.</p>
        <p>At a news conference at the United Nations yesterday, Mr. Barak, who has come under fire at home for conceding too much at Camp David, reiterated that Jerusalem and the Temple Mount ''are the cornerstone of Jewish identity.''</p>
        <p>''No Israeli prime minister will ever be able to sign a document that gives up sovereignty to the Temple Mount to the Palestinians,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Barak then went on to chide Mr. Arafat for his attitude to the Temple Mount, and for his attitude to the peace talks.</p>
        <p>This was not the time, the prime minister said, for Mr. Arafat ''to rewrite the history of the three monotheistic religions.''</p>
        <p>''The very word of Temple Mount tells the real story of Temple Mount,'' Mr. Barak said. When Jesus walked in Jerusalem, Mr. Barak said, he did not see Christian churches or Muslim mosques. ''What he could see is the Jewish Temple.''</p>
        <p>The fairly harsh words about Mr. Arafat appeared to reflect the Israeli leader's increasing frustration with what he considers the Palestinian's refusal to seriously negotiate. In private meetings with American Jews since he has been here, Mr. Barak has said that he cannot give more in negotiations. He has also described the chances of a peace deal as well under 50 percent.</p>
        <p>SUMMIT IN NEW YORK: CAMP DAVID AFTERMATH</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
