<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Chief Justices to Meet on Abuses in Judicial Races</title>
    <meta content="Y08JUD$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/08/national/08JUDG.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228788"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Judges</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Glaberson, William</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Judges</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000908T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E0D61239F93BA3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="789" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Chief Justices to Meet on Abuses in Judicial Races</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM GLABERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Glaberson, William</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Chief justices of 15 states will hold unusual meeting to try to curb abuses in bitter judicial election contests; several cite million-dollar war chests, attack ads and distortion of records (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The chief justices of 15 states are planning an unusual ''summit meeting'' to try to limit what some of them describe as increasing abuses in bitter election contests for judgeships.</p>
        <p>Several of the chief justices call  the conference a response to growing concerns about the million-dollar war chests, attack advertising and even outright distortion of an opponent's record that seem to have become more widespread in judicial races this year and threaten public confidence in the courts.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The chief justices of 15 states are planning an unusual ''summit meeting'' to try to limit what some of them describe as increasing abuses in bitter election contests for judgeships.</p>
        <p>Several of the chief justices call  the conference a response to growing concerns about the million-dollar war chests, attack advertising and even outright distortion of an opponent's record that seem to have become more widespread in judicial races this year and threaten public confidence in the courts.</p>
        <p>''Within the last few years, this has become a national problem and one that has to be looked at nationally, not just in whatever state is having an election at the moment,'' said the chief justice of Texas, Thomas R. Phillips, an organizer of the meeting.</p>
        <p>The conference is to be held in Chicago this December, attended by the chief justices of the 15 most populous states where at least some judges are elected.</p>
        <p>Chief Justice Phillips, himself an elected official, and others said that  rather than proposing wholesale changes in judicial selection systems that vary widely by state, the participants would look for limited reforms that can be more easily achieved.</p>
        <p>For example, the chief justices, who will be accompanied by legislative leaders and court-reform advocates, are likely to evaluate official voter information projects that already exist in several states, with an eye to extending them elsewhere,  said Roger K. Warren, president of the National Center for State Courts in Williamsburg, Va., which is coordinating the conference. These voter information projects try to present neutral information on judges' records so that voters do not have to rely on campaign allegations.</p>
        <p>Other possible proposals, Mr. Warren said, include trying to remove judicial elections from the broader political fray by scheduling them  when there are no other elections,  and increasing the length of judges'  terms so that they need not face election so frequently.</p>
        <p>Randall T. Shepard, the chief justice of the Indiana Supreme Court, said several chief justices discussed the idea of a summit meeting when they gathered at a judicial conference in Rapid City, S.D., last month.</p>
        <p>''There was general agreement,'' he said of the increasingly rough-and-tumble nature of some judicial campaigns, ''that this trend is not good for the country.''</p>
        <p>Forty-two states elect judges at some level, according to the American Bar Association. Until recent years, races for judgeships in many of those states were polite affairs.</p>
        <p>But aggressive campaigning has now grown sharply. Some candidates make false charges against their opponents. Others, despite rules intended to forbid the practice, indicate how they would decide on issues like  the death penalty or abortion.</p>
        <p>By wide agreement among experts on judicial politics, the campaigns this year are among the most aggressive ever. Several candidates in primaries in Illinois each spent $1 million in races for the Supreme Court, and Idaho, Michigan, Ohio, Alabama and other states have seen particularly bruising campaigns.</p>
        <p>Some of the chief justices said they had grown alarmed at the changing climate even if they had not yet noticed it in their own states.</p>
        <p>New York's chief judge, Judith S. Kaye, said she was not aware of campaign problems there. But, Judge Kaye said, ''we have a very cynical public generally, and this just feeds the cynicism of the public to have people raising these huge sums for judicial campaigns and running campaign ads that are false.'' (Since 1977, judges on New York's top court, the Court of Appeals, have been appointed by the governor after screening by a commission. But many other judges in New York are elected.)</p>
        <p>Some critics of the current state of affairs say incumbent judges are unlikely to come up with meaningful reform of a system from which they have benefited. Tom Smith, the director of Public Citizen's Texas office, said his group was supportive of the summit idea, but skeptical.</p>
        <p>''It is our fear,'' Mr. Smith said, ''that what will result is a strategy for defense of the system rather than an effort to find solutions.''</p>
        <p>According to the organizers, top judges from the following states are expected to attend the conference: California, Florida, Georgia, Illinois, Indiana, Michigan, Missouri, New York, North Carolina, Ohio, Pennsylvania, Tennessee, Texas, Washington and Wisconsin.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
