<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Giuliani Asks U.S. to Assume Security Costs</title>
    <meta content="08RUDY$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/08/nyregion/08RUDY.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228810"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lueck, Thomas J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000908T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E1DE1339F93BA3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="340" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Giuliani Asks U.S. to Assume Security Costs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS J. LUECK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lueck, Thomas J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mayor Rudolph W Guiliani writes to Pres Clinton asking for $25 million in federal reimbursement for 'extraordinary security measures' being provided by New York City during United Nations Millennium Summit; says State Dept has traditionally shortchanged city in UN security; Giuliani also reiterates his frequent demand that UN diplomats pay their parking tickets (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Citing what he called the ''extraordinary security measures'' that are being provided by New York City during the United Nations Millennium Summit, Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani yesterday wrote to President Clinton asking for $25 million in federal reimbursement. He said the State Department had traditionally shortchanged the city in United Nations security.</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani also reinterated what has become a traditional demand -- that United Nations diplomats pay their parking tickets. They have long cited diplomatic immunity in violating the city's parking rules.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Citing what he called the ''extraordinary security measures'' that are being provided by New York City during the United Nations Millennium Summit, Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani yesterday wrote to President Clinton asking for $25 million in federal reimbursement. He said the State Department had traditionally shortchanged the city in United Nations security.</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani also reinterated what has become a traditional demand -- that United Nations diplomats pay their parking tickets. They have long cited diplomatic immunity in violating the city's parking rules.</p>
        <p>''We are talking about major amounts of money,'' the mayor said, adding that ''maybe it wouldn't be a bad idea if somebody stood up, the president, the secretary of state'' to insist on restitution to the city. He said the worst United Nations scofflaw, Russia, had accumulated $7.2 million in unpaid parking tickets and penalties since 1995.</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani's complaints elicited little response from the White House or the State Department yesterday.  Stephen Boyd, a spokesman for the president, declined comment. Philip T. Reeker, a spokesman for the Madeleine K. Albright, the secretary of state, said, ''We have not seen the specific request and it is premature to comment.''</p>
        <p>In his letter to the president, the mayor said this week's huge United Nations event -- with 149 world leaders and their staffs, the largest assembly of foreign dignitaries in its history -- had placed a huge burden on the Department of Transportation, the Office of Emergency Management, and other city agencies responsible for public safety.</p>
        <p>The biggest single expense, he said, has been incurred by the Police Department, which has diverted 6,000 uniformed officers and 750 detectives each day during the summit for United Nations security.</p>
        <p>Although the State Department has agreed to reimburse the city for some expenses, including the $8 million anticipated in police overtime, the mayor said it had refused to pay for officers reassigned to the United Nations during their regular hours and several security measures the city has taken.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
