<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gore Gets Powerful Help From Cabinet</title>
    <meta content="Y08GOR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/08/politics/08GORE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228799"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE VICE PRESIDENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rubin, Robert E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Seelye, Katharine Q</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bowles, Erskine B</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tyson, Laura D'Andrea</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Summers, Lawrence H (Sec)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sperling, Gene (Chmn)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000908T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06EFDF1339F93BA3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1317" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gore Gets Powerful Help From Cabinet</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHARINE Q. SEELYE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Seelye, Katharine Q</byline>
      <dateline>CARBONDALE, Pa., Sept. 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vice Pres Al Gore is relying on expertise, advice and support of Clinton cabinet members like Robert E Rubin, former treasury secretary who appears with Gore to endorse his economic plan; others helping campaign include Lawrence Summers, Erskine Bowles, Laura D'Andrea Tyson and Gene Sperling; photo of Gore at stop in Scranton (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Vice President Al Gore may be trying to rid himself of President Clinton, but he is making no attempt to escape from the Clinton cabinet.</p>
        <p>In fact, the vice president is relying more and more these days on the expertise, advice and support of a gallery of members and former members of the cabinet.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Vice President Al Gore may be trying to rid himself of President Clinton, but he is making no attempt to escape from the Clinton cabinet.</p>
        <p>In fact, the vice president is relying more and more these days on the expertise, advice and support of a gallery of members and former members of the cabinet.</p>
        <p>Nowhere was this more evident than in Cleveland on Wednesday, when Mr. Gore delivered a major speech laying out his vision of the economy for the next decade. At his side was Robert E. Rubin, who, as Mr. Clinton's former treasury secretary and one of the most respected figures who have played a role in the current prosperity, is regarded as the administration's economic superstar.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rubin provided not only his presence and reputation to vouch for Mr. Gore's ability to keep the economy sound. He helped put in place the fundamental principles -- chiefly, paying down the debt and heeding the bond market -- that underpin Mr. Gore's own economic plan.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rubin was not the only Clinton appointee helping Mr. Gore on his economic blueprint. The list of brainstormers reads like a who's who of the Clinton administration's economic elite -- Lawrence H. Summers, the current treasury secretary; Erskine B. Bowles, Mr. Clinton's former chief of staff; Laura D'Andrea Tyson, former chairwoman of Mr. Clinton's Council of Economic Advisers; and Gene Sperling, the president's top in-house economic adviser.</p>
        <p>The degree to which Clinton appointees are campaigning on behalf of the vice president is rare in modern political history and reflects the confluence of several factors: Mr. Clinton's serious investment in getting Mr. Gore elected; Mr. Gore's need to have people with policy expertise and marquee names vouching for his participation in important decisions within the Clinton administration; the desire by the cabinet members themselves to use to the fullest their waning months in the limelight and, perhaps for some, a desire to improve their chances of appointment to a Gore administration.</p>
        <p>There is nothing illegal about cabinet secretaries' electioneering. The Hatch Act prevents government employees from spending official time on political work, but presidential appointees are exempt from that restriction.</p>
        <p>Having cabinet-level experts at his disposal is an enormous advantage of incumbency, and Mr. Gore has not been shy about using it.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Gore is deeply familiar with policy details, his ability to call forth the armies of the administration to speak on his behalf have bolstered one of the central tenets of his candidacy -- that he is, as Bill Clinton has often argued, the most qualified person in history to run for the presidency.</p>
        <p>Greg Simon, a senior Gore adviser, said the campaign was thrilled to be able to showcase the cabinet. ''We've had the most stable cabinet of any recent administration, so these are people who have become authorities,'' he said. ''There's no substitute for having Bob Rubin talk about economic prosperity or Donna Shalala talk about health or Andrew Cuomo talk about inner cities. Each of these people is a shining star.''</p>
        <p>He also said that the cabinet's campaigning for Mr. Gore was a benefit of his having been so involved in the administration. ''This isn't a situation where you have a vice president and cabinet warring among itself, the way Johnson and Kennedy did, or an office kept in the dark, the way Quayle was,'' he said. ''You have a vice presidential staff that was fully integrated into all the cabinet agencies.'' Marshall Wittmann, a conservative policy analyst at the Hudson Institute, said that the extent to which current and former members of the administration were working for Mr. Gore appeared ''unprecedented.''</p>
        <p>''I don't know of a single former official who has come back and worked so prominently for a vice president,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He suggested that such action showed both an extraordinary degree of loyalty within the administration as well as the degree of determination in helping Mr. Clinton establish a political legacy.</p>
        <p>Moreover, he said, Mr. Gore's election would provide some ''vindication'' of Mr. Clinton's mixed tenure.</p>
        <p>This is a tricky area for Mr. Gore to navigate. On the one hand, he says he is not running for a third Clinton term, and he has sought to close the Clinton chapter of his career.</p>
        <p>He often says, as he did here today at a high-tech company, that he is not running on the ''past performance'' of the economy but on his own plan for a stronger economy in the future.</p>
        <p>For months, Mr. Gore has routinely relied on Mr. Clinton's political appointees to advance his cause. Mr. Rubin even stumped with him in New Hampshire last winter. Many have been with the Clinton administration for years and are seen not so much as auditioning for a Gore administration but as making themselves more marketable for the private sector as the end of the Clinton era nears.</p>
        <p>Virtually the entire cabinet has participated in one form or another in the Gore campaign. Most commonly, they are hosts for conference calls with reporters. Frequent conference-callers are Dr. Shalala, the secretary of health and human services, who conducted one on Tuesday to critique Gov. George W. Bush's plan for prescription drug coverage.</p>
        <p>A few days before, Dr. David A. Kessler, former head of the Food and Drug Administration and now dean of the Yale School of Medicine, took part in a conference call to preview a week of Gore speeches on health-care issues. A few days later, Ms. Tyson, who had served on the 1999 Medicare Commission, conducted a conference call to discuss Mr. Gore's plan to save Medicare.</p>
        <p>Alexis M. Herman, Mr. Clinton's secretary of labor, has been one of the most visibly involved in Mr. Gore's campaign, particularly in his efforts to reach out to black voters. She and Rodney Slater, the transportation secretary, who is also black, were on hand to brief reporters when Mr. Gore addressed the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People last month in Baltimore. Ms. Herman also played an advisory role as part of Mr. Gore's  vice-presidential screening committee and is part of the team working out the debate schedule.</p>
        <p>One of the most striking examples of Mr. Gore's reliance on the Clinton cabinet was his selection earlier this summer of William M. Daley, Mr. Clinton's commerce secretary, as his campaign chairman to replace the ailing Tony Coelho.</p>
        <p>Dr. Shalala, the health secretary, is one of the cabinet members most actively campaigning for Mr. Gore. She says she is doing so because she believes in Mr. Gore's proposals and admires his wife. ''It's both a personal commitment to them and a real commitment on my part to the programs,'' she said in an interview.</p>
        <p>She said she had made it clear that she was not interested in a job in a Gore administration. Moreover, she said, she just flat-out loves politics.</p>
        <p>''I love the rough and tumble,'' she said.</p>
        <p>She also said she closely follows the rules about having the campaign, not the taxpayers, pay for her political trips. But she also noted that cabinet secretaries are on duty 24 hours a day and get no vacation, and that part of their jobs are political.</p>
        <p>One of those who seemed to be trying openly to parlay his position into a Gore administration was Bill Richardson, Mr. Clinton's energy secretary.</p>
        <p>He was widely considered a possible vice-presidential running mate for Mr. Gore until problems within his department's purview derailed him.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE VICE PRESIDENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
