<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rickety Japanese Banks; As Borrowers Collapse, Is New Bailout Needed?</title>
    <meta content="Y08BAN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/08/business/08BANK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228771"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Japan</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Fuji Bank Ltd</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Industrial Bank of Japan Ltd</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nippon Credit Bank Ltd</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Shinsei Bank</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Strom, Stephanie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shiozaki, Yasuhisa</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000908T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E0D81239F93BA3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1963" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rickety Japanese Banks; As Borrowers Collapse, Is New Bailout Needed?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHANIE STROM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Strom, Stephanie</byline>
      <dateline>TOKYO</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Collapse of several corporate borrowers raises prospect that Japanese financial system might fail unless it receives a government bailout; government has so far spent $238 billion on overhaul of financial system, out of $666 billion allocated for purpose in 1998, when financial system nearly collapsed; even more has been spent to prop up banks and other financial institutions indirectly, through credit-guarantee programs and the like; growing number of politicians, economists and government officials believe Japan never entirely repaired its banking system after money banks stumbled into crisis in autumn 1997; Yasuhisa Shiozaki, legislator from governing Liberal Party and lonely advocate of financial restructuring, doubts government has will for second round of refinancing; financial scene at some of Japan's large banks, including Fuji Bank, Industrial Bank of Japan, Nippon Credit Bank and Shinsei Bank (formerly Long-Term Credit Bank) discussed; graphs; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>First, there was the failure of the Sogo Company, a lumbering department store chain that was crushed earlier in the summer by its $17 billion in debt.</p>
        <p>Then, a construction contractor, Inoue Kogyo, was rescued from a similar fate when its banks forgave $136 million in debt; Hazama, another construction company, may receive similar treatment for about $1 billion worth.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>First, there was the failure of the Sogo Company, a lumbering department store chain that was crushed earlier in the summer by its $17 billion in debt.</p>
        <p>Then, a construction contractor, Inoue Kogyo, was rescued from a similar fate when its banks forgave $136 million in debt; Hazama, another construction company, may receive similar treatment for about $1 billion worth.</p>
        <p>Most recently, the central bank moved to raise interest rates, if only fractionally.</p>
        <p>Any one of those events increased the strain on Japan's rickety banking system. The question now is whether their combined effect will be toxic, forcing the government to intervene as it did two years ago when the financial system came close to collapsing.</p>
        <p>So far, 25 trillion yen in tax money has been spent, or $238 billion at current exchange rates, on a government overhaul of the financial system, out of $666 billion allocated for that purpose in 1998. Even more has been spent to prop up banks and other financial institutions indirectly, through credit-guarantee programs and the like.</p>
        <p>''We are standing at the same divide where we were standing two years ago, when we recapitalized the banks,'' said Yasuhisa Shiozaki, a youngish legislator from the governing Liberal Democratic Party, who has been a rather lonely advocate of painful financial restructuring. ''We can either recapitalize the banks again, or we can just let them go bust.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Shiozaki is perhaps the boldest of a growing group of politicians, economists and government officials who think that Japan never entirely repaired its banking system after many banks stumbled into crisis in autumn 1997, falling victim to profligate lending policies and social pressure to maintain relationships, whatever the cost.</p>
        <p>Senior officials at the watchdog Financial Supervisory Agency have  been telling reporters and analysts that three or four more big banks should have been nationalized in 1998, along with the ones that were -- the Long-Term Credit Bank and the Nippon Credit Bank. But politicians, they say, would not sanction such radical surgery.</p>
        <p>Mr. Shiozaki doubts that the government has the will for a second round of refinancing in the wake of Sogo's collapse, when a plan to spend close to $1 billion to waive debt and keep the company afloat was swamped in an outcry of public disapproval.</p>
        <p>Ruling-party politicians quickly scrapped the plan, and Sogo failed, blowing away the fig leaf that covered Japan's supposedly resolved bad-debt problems. ''What we found out with Sogo and afterward is that the essential and fundamental problems of the Japanese economy were still there or perhaps even worse,'' Mr. Shiozaki said.</p>
        <p>Although a second injection of public money into the banking system may be unlikely, the government has proved itself adroit at devising bank rescue programs in disguise.</p>
        <p>A decision to postpone a deposit-insurance program that would limit government protection to about $95,000 a depositor, rather than the unlimited protection in place since 1996, was aimed at protecting the regional banks and local lenders that might easily see their customers flee for bigger, sounder institutions if the plan were to start in March 2001 as originally intended.</p>
        <p>And the government's $285 billion credit-guarantee program for small and midsize enterprises is as much about supporting banks as about helping struggling mom-and-pop businesses.</p>
        <p>Takatomo Nakagawa, a researcher at Teikoku Data Bank, remarked: ''The companies using this program were, in many cases, using the money especially to pay back existing bank loans, not only for the operations of the company. The money was used for the banks.''</p>
        <p>As of March, the major banks had more than $40 billion reserved against bad debts, but James P. Fiorillo, senior banking analyst at ING Barings in Tokyo, estimates that those reserves would cover only about 2.5 percent of their potential problem loans. He says he doubts that all bad debt has been properly classified and that real estate collateral has been properly valued.</p>
        <p>Officials are more optimistic. Statistics show that the big banks have enough reserves to cover 25 percent of the roughly $188 billion in bad debts held at the end of March.</p>
        <p>In the fall of 1998, the government enacted sweeping financial overhaul legislation aimed at setting the banking system -- which had nearly collapsed within the preceding year -- back on its feet.</p>
        <p>In exchange for an infusion of public money totaling eight trillion yen, or $76 billion, the banks were forced into a wholesale re-evaluation of their loan portfolios, urged to consolidate and exhorted to focus on profitability rather than the relationships that determined past business decisions.</p>
        <p>The government spent an additional 6.8 trillion yen, or $64.7 billion, rehabilitating the nationalized Nippon Credit Bank and Long-Term Credit Bank. ''I think people forget how much has been accomplished in less than two years,'' said Yoshimasa Hayashi, a young member of the upper house of Parliament. ''The commitment to financial reform continues to be strong.''</p>
        <p>While an impressive wave of consolidation in the last two years has reduced the number of Japan's biggest banks by half, to 10 from 20 two years ago, it has yet to produce obvious efficiencies. Nor has consolidation noticeably changed the type of business that banks in this country do or the way they do it.</p>
        <p>The banks have yet to incur the costs of bringing their technology up to date; in the meantime, nimbler new financial institutions that have linked their fortunes to the Internet are plowing new ground.</p>
        <p>To make matters worse, the banks' basic lending business remains in a prolonged slump. Borrowers are either desperately trying to reduce their debts or increasingly relying on the capital markets for their borrowing needs.</p>
        <p>And the banks are struggling with negative forces over which they, and the government, have little or no control. Credit-rating agencies warn that bankruptcies, ratcheting up every month, are likely to reach a high this year as bigger and bigger debtors collapse. Bankruptcies rose 21 percent in July compared with July 1999, according to Teikoku Databank, and the total debt owed by companies that collapsed tripled, to $2.4 billion.</p>
        <p>''If we see an avalanche of new bad debts into the system,'' Mr. Fiorillo said, ''the banks do not appear to have enough resources to cope comfortably with the problem.''</p>
        <p>The wave of bankruptcies is forcing banks to sell shares they hold, seeking to raise money to cover losses. That, along with sales by foreigners, has contributed to a drop in stock prices -- further eroding the value of investment portfolios.</p>
        <p>ING Barings estimates that the more than seven trillion yen in profit that Japanese banks boasted last year, when the stock market had a miniature recovery, had as of July turned into roughly 500 billion yen in losses with the market's fall.</p>
        <p>In addition, the agency charged with overhauling the financial system, the Financial Reconstruction Commission, has been buffeted by a series of scandals that created a revolving door in its leadership and undermined its power and credibility. In the last 10 months, the commission has had four chiefs, two of whom were forced to resign.</p>
        <p>''The head of the organization has been changed too frequently, and that is not good,'' said Hakuo Yanagisawa, the member of Parliament who served for a year as the commission's first chief before he was replaced in a routine cabinet shuffle.</p>
        <p>To critics, all this suggests that the government must find some way of overcoming popular resistance to injecting more money into the banking system. ''Public funds are going to be used,'' Mr. Shiozaki said, ''either through the Deposit Insurance Corporation or by letting banks go bust, or injecting more capital into them.''</p>
        <p>[Friday morning, Moody's Investors Service cut Japan's domestic-currency credit rating one notch, to Aa2, saying the government was running up too much debt in its efforts to ignite economic growth.]</p>
        <p>But others think that Mr. Shiozaki and his like are alarmists. ''The problems emerging now are more or less within the scope of what we anticipated,'' Mr. Yanagisawa said.</p>
        <p>Still accorded a great deal of respect, he is credited with forcing the consolidation that has reconfigured the landscape of Japanese banking. Bankers feared him and reformers praised him.</p>
        <p>It was during his tenure that Long-Term Credit, once the flagship of the Japanese banking system, was sold to a group of foreigners led by Ripplewood Holdings L.L.C., a private equity firm based in New York. That move has had significant repercussions. Long-Term Credit, now known as the Shinsei Bank, refused to participate in the debt restructuring plan for Sogo.</p>
        <p>Ripplewood seemed aware when it bought the Long-Term Credit Bank that many of its loans were effectively unrecoverable. It demanded that the government promise to fully compensate the bank on any loans that fell in value by 20 percent or more for three years after the sale -- even though Tokyo had supposedly transferred all bad loans from the bank to the Deposit Insurance Corporation long before.</p>
        <p>Many politicians now argue that the government agreed to that provision because it also knew that a good portion of Long-Term Credit's loan portfolio was suspect, but could not win political sanction to pull the plug on well-connected companies like Sogo, Daiei, Kumagai Gumi and the Saison group -- which have strong ties to leaders of the ruling party.</p>
        <p>Yoshimi Watanabe, a Liberal Democrat in the lower house of Parliament, says that this failure to weed out bad debts thoroughly and consign them to the Deposit Insurance Corporation was a basic flaw in the whole bank rescue program.</p>
        <p>''The original evaluation of those loans was totally wrong,'' he said. ''The banking bureau at the Ministry of Finance was claiming these loans were 'gray' loans, not bad loans, but in fact these loans were to companies that had a high probability of going bankrupt or were effectively bankrupt already.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Yanagisawa acknowledged that some assumptions made when the Financial Reconstruction Commission was established have proved faulty. ''We had hoped that those companies would have made strenuous efforts to restructure themselves in the period before their loans were transferred to Shinsei,'' he said. He also said government economic forecasts had been too rosy, skewing projections about corporate recovery.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Yanagisawa insists that today's problems are largely ones of perception, not asset quality.</p>
        <p>''There is no one who can explain to the Japanese public that these problems are within the bounds of what we had anticipated,'' he said. ''Government authorities had envisaged this scenario.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
