<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Opera Gets a Razzing With Word and Melody</title>
    <meta content="08WHAL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/08/arts/08WHAL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228709"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Foundry Theater</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bruckner, D J R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eckert, Rinde</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">God Created Great Whales Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000908T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E3D81539F93BA3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="542" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Opera Gets a Razzing With Word and Melody</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Excerpts from D J R Bruckner's June 17 review of The Foundry Theater production of Rinde Eckert's And God Created Great Whales, at Bessie Schonberg Theater (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Foundry Theater production of ''And God Created Great Whales,'' written and composed by Rinde Eckert, which ran for two weeks in June at the Bessie Schonberg Theater in Chelsea, has begun a run through Oct. 31 at the 45 Bleecker Theater in Greenwich Village. Here is an excerpt from a review by D. J. R. Bruckner that appeared on June 17.</p>
        <p>Total magic is what Rinde Eckert delivers. He has the gift of writing both words and music very well, and from one moment to the next for 75 intense minutes he delightfully subverts every expectation he arouses.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Foundry Theater production of ''And God Created Great Whales,'' written and composed by Rinde Eckert, which ran for two weeks in June at the Bessie Schonberg Theater in Chelsea, has begun a run through Oct. 31 at the 45 Bleecker Theater in Greenwich Village. Here is an excerpt from a review by D. J. R. Bruckner that appeared on June 17.</p>
        <p>Total magic is what Rinde Eckert delivers. He has the gift of writing both words and music very well, and from one moment to the next for 75 intense minutes he delightfully subverts every expectation he arouses.</p>
        <p>Consider the story: an indifferent composer is losing his mind. He has taped instructions to himself to guide him through every step of the great work of his life before darkness falls. Trapped in his studio, the only person he can talk to is a woman, a figment of his imagination. And the composition he struggles to complete? An opera of ''Moby-Dick.'' So this musical play seems to be about the mad summoning up the mad. But that's not it.</p>
        <p>As Nathan, the composer, Mr. Eckert has a command of gesture that lets him fly from fear to fury and from dancing to dying in an instant. To watch Nathan degenerate from a nimble prankster to a blank lump is scarcely bearable. And Mr. Eckert's singing, whether in falsetto or baritone, can be thrilling. Vocally and dramatically he is wonderfully matched by the Broadway star Nora Cole. There are depths in her voice in dark moments that haunt the ear for hours.</p>
        <p>But it is not the dark moments in this play that reveal how serious Mr. Eckert is. He is a wary explorer of mindlessness in theater and a fiendish detective of moribund trends in opera. After you have heard Mr. Eckert describe in a few notes on the piano each of a dozen Melville characters Ms. Cole names, you will find it very hard to sit through almost any opera I can think of without laughing once in a while. And as Nathan approaches some of the grander scenes in his version of ''Moby-Dick,'' the barely suppressed parody of modern productions of grand opera is simply exquisite.</p>
        <p>I think there is not a musical joke here that will elude even people who can't read a note.</p>
        <p>David Schweizer, the director, creates a rhythm that is palpably musical. There is a sense of continual opening up -- intellectually, emotionally and visually. The stage, festooned with dangling recorders and other technoprops of modern sound, appears held in an undulating net of bare colored bulbs that telegraph a code as sun rises, storm falls or hell breaks loose. At the end they are employed like paintbrushes when Ahab's storm crashes to an end. Nathan's tape tells him, ''If you are still listening it is too late,'' and Nathan, still as a stone, sits in a white glow as though watching, alone and uncomprehending on shore, while we out in the dark float away.</p>
        <p>The emotion that washes over the audience is astonished satisfaction, as though we had done it all ourselves.</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
