<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cheering Hip, Hip, Hooray For the Good Ol' Ethical Way</title>
    <meta content="08TAKI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/08/arts/08TAKI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228698"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TAKING THE CHILDREN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nichols, Peter M</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Bring It on (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Space Cowboys (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Art of War, the (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Columns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Columns/Taking the Children</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Columns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Columns/Taking the Children</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000908T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE3D91739F93BA3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1111" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cheering Hip, Hip, Hooray For the Good Ol' Ethical Way</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Peter M. Nichols</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nichols, Peter M</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Peter M Nichols reviews Bring It On, The Art of War and Space Cowboys, movies appropriate for young children and teenagers (Taking the Children column); photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bring It On  Kirsten Dunst, Eliza Dushku, Jesse Bradford, Gabrielle Union, Clare Kramer  Directed by Peyton Reed  PG-13 110 minutes</p>
        <p>''We're sexy and cute and smart to boot,'' chants the Rancho Grande High School cheerleading team, the Torros, five-time national cheering champions. They are also cheats, or so it is charged by the East Compton Clovers, a largely black rival squad.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Bring It On  Kirsten Dunst, Eliza Dushku, Jesse Bradford, Gabrielle Union, Clare Kramer  Directed by Peyton Reed  PG-13 110 minutes</p>
        <p>''We're sexy and cute and smart to boot,'' chants the Rancho Grande High School cheerleading team, the Torros, five-time national cheering champions. They are also cheats, or so it is charged by the East Compton Clovers, a largely black rival squad.</p>
        <p>It seems that the Torros planted a spy with a video camera and stole the Clovers' routines. Shocked to the quick, the Torros' new captain, Torrance (Ms. Dunst), proposes devising new steps, leaps and tosses. Her teammates tell her to forget it. Who cares if the routine was stolen? Besides, there isn't time to hone a new one before they're out there on ESPN defending their title.</p>
        <p>The persistent Torrance brings in a choreographer named Sparky, who installs a new act he has also sold to a half-dozen other cheerleading teams up and down the Southern California coast. That doesn't help clear the cheating cloud when the Torros are the second team to perform the same routine at the regionals. Even more determined to achieve originality, Torrance devises gyrations incorporating jazz, martial arts and mime. Bring on those Clovers.</p>
        <p>VIOLENCE -- None.  SEX -- Torrance and her teammates live in scanty cheering outfits, bikinis and nighties. But while there are plenty of sexual asides and assessments of body parts, the film stays clean and sportif.  PROFANITY -- A little, but not overdone.  FOOTNOTE -- Without making an issue of it, the movie has a sharp ear for the put-downs, rejection and personal viciousness that high school students reserve for one another. The male Torros rouse general homophobia.</p>
        <p>For Which Children?  AGES 3-9 -- Older viewers in this group will be caught up, but considering the slightly risque nature of the proceedings, perhaps not.  AGES 10 AND UP -- Parents' choice, but the film is loud fun, and in its brushes with ethics and tolerance even relatively substantive, given its subject.</p>
        <p>The Art of War  Wesley Snipes, Anne Archer, Marie Matiko, Maury Chaykin, Cary-Hiroyuki Tagawa, Michael Biehn, Donald Sutherland  Directed by Christian Duguay  R 105 minutes</p>
        <p>At millennium time in Hong Kong, the banalities are in full swing when a dervish in a tuxedo leaps onto a Las Vegas-style runway and drop-kicks his way through a squad of goons sent to collar him. But this is no musical. Shaw (Mr. Snipes) works for a covert action unit belonging to (ready?) the United Nations. And now that dirty little band, headed by the world body's director of security (Ms. Archer), no less, faces its largest assignment: strike back at those trying to sabotage an impending trade agreement with China.</p>
        <p>The globe itself hangs in the balance, at least to hear the secretary general (Mr. Sutherland) tell it. ''There's no free lunch; you have to pay the piper,'' he says, quitting just short of ''the buck stops here.'' But it's Shaw who is bounced around by sadists who also make an awful mess out of attractive young interpreters and electronic eavesdropping specialists.</p>
        <p>Who is behind all this? Looks like ''the triad,'' one of those inscrutable Asian conspiracies tied to sleazy-looking types who seem to have escaped from a Jackie Chan movie without their sense of humor. Then the Chinese ambassador, named Woo, is shot in midspeech, allowing the movie to take note of ''a war on Woo.''</p>
        <p>Pounding around New York one step behind or ahead of evil forces, Shaw befriends Julia (Ms. Matiko), a young woman whose connection with this mess isn't entirely clear but who at one point is made to strip and throw all her clothes out the window of a speeding car because she is unwittingly wearing a planted microphone. Back at the United Nations, the secretary general considers bringing in the president of the United States.</p>
        <p>VIOLENCE -- Numerous killings are gratuitously, leeringly brutal. One woman's head is repeatedly smashed through a heavy mirror.  SEX -- No one seems much in the mood, although prostitutes are fleetingly shown at work with a North Korean general and Julia ends up demurely in the buff.  PROFANITY -- A full complement.</p>
        <p>For Which Children?  AGES 14 AND UP -- They wouldn't keep making junk like this if it didn't sell to teenagers. With that in mind, the film is typical of its kind.</p>
        <p>Space Cowboys  Clint Eastwood, Tommy Lee Jones, Donald Sutherland, James Garner, Marcia Gay Harden, William Devane, Loren Dean, Courtney B. Vance, James Cromwell  Directed by Clint Eastwood  PG-13 105 minutes</p>
        <p>As a test pilot who took experimental aircraft to the edge of the stratosphere in the 1950's, Frank Corvin (Mr. Eastwood) naturally assumed that he would be among the first sent into space. In fact, Frank only got to shake hands with the first, a chimpanzee named Mary Ann. So it was, too, with his pilot friends, Hawk (Mr. Jones), Jerry (Mr. Sutherland) and Tank (Mr. Garner), all of whom were passed over when the space program moved from the military to the civilian-led National Aeronautics and Space Administration.</p>
        <p>Frank owed his dumping to Bob Gerson (Mr. Cromwell), a spotlight-hogging space administrator. But the worm turns in the year 2000 when a Russian satellite, aloft for 30 years, loses control and threatens to crash back to earth. Frank inadvertently designed the guidance system on that old bird back in 1969 (the Soviets stole his specifications), and he's the only one who can keep the thing flying now.</p>
        <p>After refusing on principle, Frank signs on -- with stipulations. He'll fix the craft, but only if NASA sends him and his cronies up in a space shuttle. Gerson is apoplectic. Frank and the others are well into senior citizenhood. To prepare, they run geezerly laps, sweat streaming down sagging flesh. Still, old Hawk and Jerry manage some womanizing, and the four of them pull it together long enough to qualify physically while, this being the movies, mastering the intricacies of shuttle operation.</p>
        <p>Aloft, though, Houston and the old guys definitely have a problem. For one thing, the Russian ship is not exactly the wayward clunker everybody assumed it was. Then Hawk decides to fly himself to the moon, while his pals prefer flying by the seat of their pants.</p>
        <p>VIOLENCE -- Frank and Hawk trade punches outside a bar.  SEX -- Occasional winks and references.  PROFANITY -- The talk gets salty.</p>
        <p>For Which Children?  AGES 3-8 -- Too static and windy for the very young.  AGES 9-11 -- They may be antiques, but the four pilots and their adventure make a nice family film, with a lot of humor, warmth and just enough excitement.  AGES 12 AND UP -- Possibly, but in the main teenagers aren't drawn by the geriatric set, even in space.</p>
        <p>TAKING THE CHILDREN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
