<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Leaders of Aryan Nations Found Negligent in Attack</title>
    <meta content="Y08ARY$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/08/national/08ARYA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228828"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fringe Groups and Movements</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Assaults</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Idaho</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Aryan Nations</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Southern Poverty Law Center</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Keenan, Victoria</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Keenan, Jason</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dees, Morris</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Teague, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Butler, Richard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Verhovek, Sam Howe</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Idaho</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Northwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Idaho</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Assaults</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fringe Groups and Movements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000908T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E7DC1339F93BA3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="999" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Leaders of Aryan Nations Found Negligent in Attack</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAM HOWE VERHOVEK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Verhovek, Sam Howe</byline>
      <dateline>COEUR d'ALENE, Idaho, Sept. 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Idaho jury orders leaders of Aryan Nations to pay $6.3 million to victims of attack two years ago by men serving as security guards at Coeur d'Alene compound; civil rights groups hope to bankrupt hate group with verdict, obtained by Southern Poverty Law Center and Morris S Dees Jr; group's leader, Richard Butler, and deputy, Michael Teague, are ordered to pay most of money to Victoria Keenan and her son Jason, now 21, who were attacked when they stopped car on road to look for lost wallet (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Issuing a verdict that civil rights organizations hope will bankrupt one of the nation's largest white-supremacist groups and limit its ability to preach hate, a state jury in northern Idaho today ordered leaders of the Aryan Nations to pay more than $6 million to the victims of an attack two years ago by men who were serving as security guards at the group's compound near here.</p>
        <p>Richard Girnt Butler, the 82-year-old self-described pastor of the Aryan Nations, and his deputy, Michael Teague, were ordered by the nine-woman, three-man jury to pay most of the $6.3 million in damages.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Issuing a verdict that civil rights organizations hope will bankrupt one of the nation's largest white-supremacist groups and limit its ability to preach hate, a state jury in northern Idaho today ordered leaders of the Aryan Nations to pay more than $6 million to the victims of an attack two years ago by men who were serving as security guards at the group's compound near here.</p>
        <p>Richard Girnt Butler, the 82-year-old self-described pastor of the Aryan Nations, and his deputy, Michael Teague, were ordered by the nine-woman, three-man jury to pay most of the $6.3 million in damages.</p>
        <p>The findings were delivered late this afternoon in the Kootenai County Courthouse, which was under heavy police security throughout the six-day trial. The verdict prompted tearful hugs among the plaintiffs, a mother and son who were beaten and shot at in the attack, and their lawyers.</p>
        <p>The defendants responded defiantly outside the courthouse, even as protesters shouted at them to stop their ''message of hate'' and urged them to get out of Idaho.</p>
        <p>The verdict was obtained by the Southern Poverty Law Center, a nonprofit organization based in Alabama that has successfully sued the Ku Klux Klan and other racist organizations on behalf of other victims of hate-motivated crimes.</p>
        <p>Morris S. Dees Jr., a founder of the center, hailed the jury's findings as a powerful message against ''violent racists,'' one that could force the group out of its 19-acre property, about 20 miles north of here.</p>
        <p>''We intend to take every single asset from the Aryan Nations now and forever,'' Mr. Dees said at a news conference after the verdict was announced. ''We intend to even take the name Aryan Nations and hopefully, through the judicial process, close a sad chapter in this nation's history.''</p>
        <p>The jury found that Mr. Butler and the Aryan Nations were liable for $4.8 million and Mr. Teague was liable for $600,000. The guards were liable for most of the remaining amount.</p>
        <p>The multimillion-dollar award also represented the kind of message that many community leaders here had sought, hoping that it might help the area shed what they called North Idaho's distorted image as a haven for people with racist views.</p>
        <p>Mr. Butler scoffed at the verdict, variously comparing himself to the Apostle Paul and to signers of the Declaration of Independence who were harassed for their views.</p>
        <p>''This is nothing,'' he said, after the verdict. ''We have planted seeds.''</p>
        <p>A lawyer for the group said an appeal was planned.</p>
        <p>The extent of group's assets remained unclear, raising questions about whether Mr. Butler and his followers, whose numbers have been described by the local authorities as dwindling, would pay anything close to the full amount if the award is upheld. Nonetheless, Mr. Dees vowed that it was the beginning of the end for the group and that the verdict was a rebuke of the Aryan Nations leaders, who were technically found to be negligent in the training and supervision of the security guards who carried out the attack.</p>
        <p>The plaintiffs, Victoria Keenan, now 44, and her son, Jason, now 21,  were beaten and shot at by three  security guards in July 1998. They had asked the jury for nearly $12 million in compensatory and punitive damages.</p>
        <p>Mr. Butler's lawyer, Edgar J. Steele, argued throughout the trial  that however offensive jurors might find the views of Mr. Butler, he should not be held responsible for the actions of a group of drunken men.</p>
        <p>Mr. Steele said the Aryan Nations property was not the incubator of violence that Mr. Dees had portrayed it to be.</p>
        <p>Ms. Keenan and her son were attacked after stopping their car near the entrance to the Aryan Nations property near Hayden Lake on their way home from a wedding. They were looking for a wallet that Mr. Keenan had accidentally dropped from their 1977 Datsun. He had been in the Job Corps and had thrown his Job Corps card out the window on a whim and, inadvertently, his wallet along with it. He quickly retrieved the wallet, but when the car started, it backfired, Ms. Keenan told the police after the incident.</p>
        <p>At the compound, three guards, one of whom later told the police that he had thought the place was about to be attacked by militant Jews, picked up their guns, jumped in a pickup truck and chased the car. They shot at the car, flattening a rear tire and forcing the car into a ditch.</p>
        <p>In tearful testimony, Ms. Keenan said one guard, Jesse Warfield, 45,  struck her with the butt of a rifle, grabbed her by the hair and screamed at her.</p>
        <p>Ms. Keenan said that she begged the men not to kill her son and that one of the guards then asked her if she was Indian. She testified that while she is part Cherokee, she told the men, ''No, I'm a poor white farm girl.'' A guard then said that because they were white, the men would let them go.</p>
        <p>At the trial, another security guard, John Yeager, 21, testified that he was too drunk that night to remember whether he or the other men had fired at the Keenans.</p>
        <p>Mr. Yeager and Mr. Warfield have pleaded guilty to criminal assault and are in prison, while the third guard, Shane Wright, 23, remained a fugitive.</p>
        <p>The two imprisoned men were brought here for the trial and testified that they had been responsible for their actions, a point repeated by Mr. Steele.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
