<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Giants Engage in Battle for Billings as DaimlerChrysler Conducts Assignment Review</title>
    <meta content="Y08ADC$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/08/business/08ADCO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228761"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Daimlerchrysler Ag</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Omnicom Group</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">True North Communications</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bbdo Worldwide</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Fcb Worldwide</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Elliott, Stuart</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Advertising (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000908T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E2DA1239F93BA3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1110" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Giants Engage in Battle for Billings as DaimlerChrysler Conducts Assignment Review</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STUART ELLIOTT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Elliott, Stuart</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Omnicom Group and True North Communications are squaring off in huge advertising review called by DaimlerChrysler Group unit of DamilerChrysler AG; assignments, with spending estimated at $1.3 billion, are now divided between Southfield, Mich, offices of BBDO Worldwide, part of Omnicom, and FCB Worldwide, part of True North (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The battle lines are already being drawn in one of the biggest confrontations in Madison Avenue history.</p>
        <p>Two giant agency companies -- the Omnicom Group and True North Communications -- are squaring off in a huge review unexpectedly called by a major client they share, the DaimlerChrysler Group unit of DaimlerChrysler A. G. The company is undertaking a review for assignments with spending estimated at $1.3 billion, out of a total spent last year of $1.5 billion. The work is now divided between the Southfield, Mich., offices of BBDO Worldwide, part of Omnicom, and FCB Worldwide, part of True North.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The battle lines are already being drawn in one of the biggest confrontations in Madison Avenue history.</p>
        <p>Two giant agency companies -- the Omnicom Group and True North Communications -- are squaring off in a huge review unexpectedly called by a major client they share, the DaimlerChrysler Group unit of DaimlerChrysler A. G. The company is undertaking a review for assignments with spending estimated at $1.3 billion, out of a total spent last year of $1.5 billion. The work is now divided between the Southfield, Mich., offices of BBDO Worldwide, part of Omnicom, and FCB Worldwide, part of True North.</p>
        <p>Top executives representing both sides of what is already being called the shootout in Southfield have taken the unusual step of issuing statements that aggressively welcomed the review; each confidently predicted his side would prevail.</p>
        <p>''One of us will be right,'' said Allen Rosenshine, chairman and chief executive at BBDO Worldwide in New York. Asked in what his optimism about BBDO's chances was rooted, he replied, ''In reality.''</p>
        <p>His competitor, David Bell, chairman and chief executive at True North in Chicago, said: ''This is an opportunity for us to take them out, and that's exactly how we're approaching it. What we will be doing is what it takes to win.''</p>
        <p>The review, which is likely to end with the DaimlerChrysler Group assignments for creative and media duties consolidated at a single shop, is indicative of the ferment roiling agencies as restless clients seek more efficient and effective campaigns. Indeed, Omnicom and True North figured in other big decisions yesterday involving another blue-chip advertiser, the Kraft Foods unit of the Philip Morris companies.</p>
        <p>''When a merger of the magnitude of the one that created DaimlerChrysler takes place,'' Mr. Rosenshine said, referring to the acquisition by Daimler-Benz of the Chrysler Corporation, which now operates under the DaimlerChrysler Group name, ''it is not a shock to us'' that the merged company would intensify efforts ''to provide cost savings.''</p>
        <p>The remarks by Mr. Rosenshine and Mr. Bell did not prevent a decline in the prices of shares of Omnicom and True North traded yesterday on the New York Stock Exchange. True North's tumble was steeper, down 14.8 percent, or $6.50, to $37.50 versus 2.1 percent, or $1.75, to $80, for Omnicom. Analysts who follow agency industry stocks attributed that disparate performance to the fact that almost all the True North DaimlerChrysler accounts are part of the review, compared with fewer of Omnicom's.</p>
        <p>Some analysts lowered their ratings of True North stock as a result of the review. They said a larger percentage of total True North revenue compared with Omnicom comes from the assignments in review, about 9 percent versus 1 percent.</p>
        <p>If True North lost the $140 million in annual revenue from the automaker, it ''could wipe out most of the company's organic growth for one year,'' said Michael J. Russell Jr., an analyst at Morgan Stanley Dean Witter in New York who reduced his rating of True North to neutral from strong buy. (He maintained a strong buy on Omnicom.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Rosenshine said ''it's fair to say'' on a total percentage basis that ''True North has 'more to lose.' ''</p>
        <p>''I would classify the stock market reaction as unusually rational,'' he added, chuckling. ''Not exuberant, but rational.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bell, for his part, said: ''We are very confident. We think we bring an enormous amount of weight to tilt the scale in our favor before the shootout.'' A decision is expected in the fourth quarter.</p>
        <p>The battle began late Wednesday afternoon when the DaimlerChrysler Group announced the review, which involves the assignments to create national and regional-dealer general market campaigns for the cars, trucks, minivans and sport utility vehicles sold under the Chrysler, Dodge and Jeep brand names as well as the DaimlerChrysler Group corporate image account.</p>
        <p>The BBDO Southfield office handles the Dodge work, with spending last year of $651.9 million, according to Competitive Media Reporting in New York, a unit of Taylor Nelson Sofres. The FCB Southfield office handles the rest of the assignments, which include Chrysler, $251.9 million; Jeep, $277.2 million; and corporate, $67.3 million.</p>
        <p>Also included in the review are the media planning and buying duties now consolidated at a BBDO sibling, PentaCom in Troy, Mich. If FCB was to best BBDO, those duties would presumably be shifted to an FCB operation now dedicated to international media buying for DaimlerChrysler, called the DaimlerChrysler Media Alliance.</p>
        <p>Or the Media Alliance could take over PentaCom, just as in 1993 a FCB predecessor, Bozell Worldwide, took over the Jeep creative assignment from the Southfield office of Campbell Mithun.</p>
        <p>Excluded from the review are assignments handled by Omnicom agencies like the creative duties for Mercedes-Benz, at Merkley Newman Harty in New York, with spending estimated at $115.1 million, and so-called customer relationship management programs, at InterOne Marketing in Troy.</p>
        <p>Lifting spirits at True North as the shootout began was word that Kraft had shifted the creative duties for Jell-O gelatin, pudding and snacks to the New York office of FCB from the New York office of Young &amp; Rubicam Advertising. Spending last year was estimated at $42 million.</p>
        <p>FCB adds Jell-O to Kraft creative assignments that include Cool Whip, DiGiorno Pizza and Kraft macaroni and cheese dinners. Y.&amp; R. Advertising, which keeps Kraft creative tasks for brands like Crystal Light soft drink mix and Toblerone chocolate, had created Jell-O campaigns since 1926. The agency developed Jell-O's sponsorships of radio and television series like ''The Jack Benny Program'' and ''The Aldrich Family,'' hired endorsers like Bill Cosby and created the familiar ''J-E-L-L-O'' jingle and slogans like ''There's always room for Jell-O.''</p>
        <p>But there's no more room for Jell-O at Y.&amp; R Advertising.</p>
        <p>Also yesterday, Kraft confirmed reports in Advertising Age and Adweek that it would review its media planning and buying assignments in the United States and Canada, to consolidate those tasks for brands with spending estimated at $800 million. Those assignments are now divided among the media agencies allied with the Kraft creative agencies.</p>
        <p>Kathy Knuth, a Kraft spokeswoman in Northfield, Ill., identified the participants as: MindShare, part of the WPP Group; Optimum Media Direction, part of Omnicom; the Starcom MediaVest Group, part of the B Com3  Group; and TN Media, part of True North.</p>
        <p>To achieve its goals of ''operational efficiencies'' and ''a quicker, more nimble response to marketplace opportunities,'' she said, Kraft may consolidate the duties at one shop.</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
