<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="08DIGE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228780"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000908T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E6D61239F93BA3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1073" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Veto by Clinton Is Upheld On Repeal of Estate Tax  Supporters of a bill to repeal the federal tax on large estates failed in an attempt to overturn President Clinton's veto of the measure, killing the issue for the year in legislative terms but leaving it very much alive politically.</p>
        <p>Republicans said they were eager to take the debate to the campaign trail, where they said it would attract support from small business owners, farmers and entrepreneurs. Democrats said they would continue to make their case that while the tax should be reduced for family-owned farms and businesses, the measure that was rejected would eat up too much of the budget surplus. [Page A22.]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Veto by Clinton Is Upheld On Repeal of Estate Tax  Supporters of a bill to repeal the federal tax on large estates failed in an attempt to overturn President Clinton's veto of the measure, killing the issue for the year in legislative terms but leaving it very much alive politically.</p>
        <p>Republicans said they were eager to take the debate to the campaign trail, where they said it would attract support from small business owners, farmers and entrepreneurs. Democrats said they would continue to make their case that while the tax should be reduced for family-owned farms and businesses, the measure that was rejected would eat up too much of the budget surplus. [Page A22.]</p>
        <p>DuPont Warns of Profit Shortfall  DuPont, the nation's biggest chemical company, warned that soaring costs for fuel and raw materials, the declining value of the euro and potentially lower sales would push earnings for the rest of the year 2 percent to 5 percent below Wall Street expectations. Shares of DuPont fell $4.88, to $42.13, and other chemical stocks declined, but many analysts said investors overreacted. [C2.]</p>
        <p>Qwest to Eliminate 13,000 Jobs  Qwest Communications said that it would lay off nearly 13,000 employees, including 1,800 contract workers, and increase capital spending in an effort to bolster efficiency after its $44 billion acquisition of U S West. [C6.]</p>
        <p>Dutch Internet Company Is Sold  In a race to become the America Online of Europe, Italy's second-largest Internet service provider, Tiscali, agreed to buy the Dutch company World Online for $5.1 billion. [C6.]</p>
        <p>Nasdaq Rebounds After 2-Day Slide  Technology stocks rebounded after a two-day downturn while blue-chip shares fell on earnings warnings. The Nasdaq composite index rose 85.01 points, or 2.1 percent, to 4,098.35. The Dow Jones industrial average was down 50.77 points, or 0.5 percent, to 11,259.87, and the Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index gained 10.26 points, or 0.7 percent, to 1,502.51. [C8.]</p>
        <p>Koppel Signs 5-Year ABC Contract  Ted Koppel, the anchor of the ABC News ''Nightline'' program since it made its debut in 1980, has agreed to stay with the program for the next five years, though he will appear as the anchor less frequently. Under a five-year contract, Mr. Koppel will be the anchor three nights a week, starting in January. He has also agreed to be the host of six special weeklong ''Nightline'' series a year. [C8.]</p>
        <p>Daimler Touches Off Agency Battle  Two giant agency companies -- the Omnicom Group and True North Communications -- are squaring off in a huge review called by a major client they share, the DaimlerChrysler Group. Shares of Omnicom and True North fell, with True North dropping $6.50, or 14.8 percent, to $37.50, and Omnicom sliding $1.75, or 2.1 percent, to $80. Stuart Elliot: Advertising. [C8.]</p>
        <p>Post Office and FedEx Discuss Deal  The United States Postal Service and FedEx are discussing a partnership that would help the post office increase revenue while giving FedEx a low-cost way to reach millions of residential customers. [C2.]</p>
        <p>President of Mitsubishi to Resign  Katsuhiko Kawasoe, the president of Mitsubishi Motors, said he was resigning because of a cover-up of customer complaints. [C5.]</p>
        <p>VoiceStream Deal Clears a Hurdle  Deutsche Telekom's proposed acquisition of VoiceStream Wireless cleared its first regulatory hurdle, but lawmakers urged the White House to do more to force the privatization of foreign phone companies before they are allowed to buy American companies. [C21.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
