<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cone Is Healing Quickly, While Mendoza's Hopes Fade</title>
    <meta content="08PINS$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/08/sports/08PINS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228827"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olney, Buster</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cone, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mendoza, Ramiro</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000908T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEEDD1339F93BA3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="897" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cone Is Healing Quickly, While Mendoza's Hopes Fade</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olney, Buster</byline>
      <dateline>KANSAS CITY, Mo., Sept. 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Yankees pitcher David Cone is encouraged about his chances of quickly coming back from separated left shoulder; Ramiro Mendoza is not expected to play again this season (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>David Cone can't catch but he can throw, and Ramiro Mendoza can catch but he can't throw. When the two right-handers teamed up to toss the ball with the pitching coach, Mel Stottlemyre, in the outfield here this evening, Cone grinned broadly, encouraged about his chances of quickly coming back from a separated left shoulder. Mendoza, on the other hand, was dour, knowing his season was probably finished.</p>
        <p>Mendoza threw batting practice Monday and his shoulder hurts again, a major setback for the Yankees, who had hoped to have him back in the bullpen before the playoffs. Manager Joe Torre would not say that Mendoza will definitely not pitch again this season, but he gave every indication that this was so.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>David Cone can't catch but he can throw, and Ramiro Mendoza can catch but he can't throw. When the two right-handers teamed up to toss the ball with the pitching coach, Mel Stottlemyre, in the outfield here this evening, Cone grinned broadly, encouraged about his chances of quickly coming back from a separated left shoulder. Mendoza, on the other hand, was dour, knowing his season was probably finished.</p>
        <p>Mendoza threw batting practice Monday and his shoulder hurts again, a major setback for the Yankees, who had hoped to have him back in the bullpen before the playoffs. Manager Joe Torre would not say that Mendoza will definitely not pitch again this season, but he gave every indication that this was so.</p>
        <p>''He can't pick up a ball,'' Torre said. ''Here we are, it's the seventh of September. It certainly is a step backwards. He's shut down until I don't know when.'' Mendoza said after the game that he can't throw for four weeks. A Yankees spokesman who talked to the team trainers said Mendoza won't pitch for 10-14 days.</p>
        <p>The Yankees kept Mendoza out of numerous trade proposals in the last two years, including a possible deal for center fielder Jim Edmonds this spring, after the versatile reliever pitched effectively in several different roles into the postseason. His performance against Boston in last year's American League Championship was pivotal.</p>
        <p>But Mendoza was erratic before going on the disabled list with shoulder trouble in June. He pitched once in July before returning to the disabled list, and now he is probably out for the year. The Yankees originally thought that Mendoza's trouble was merely weakness in the back of his shoulder, but the problem could be more serious than that, Torre said.</p>
        <p>Torre eagerly anticipated Mendoza's return after seeing him throw in batting practice Monday, but now he will proceed under the assumption that Mendoza will not be able to help his muddled middle relief. The left-hander Mike Stanton has allowed 16 hits, 12 runs and 4 homers in his last four and one-third innings, blowing a 2-1 ninth-inning lead in Wednesday's 3-2 loss to the Royals.</p>
        <p>The right-hander Jeff Nelson has thrown better in his last few outings, but Torre still seems reluctant to completely trust him after Nelson's month-long control problems. Jason Grimsley, an important part of the bullpen in the first three months, has been used one time in the last 10 days. His earned run average has climbed from 2.23 on June 14 to 4.50. Mariano Rivera, the closer, has been good but vulnerable.</p>
        <p>Torre is going to have to rely on somebody, and it figures that Dwight Gooden, who has been steady in his relief work and has shown he can warm up relatively quickly, will assume more responsibility. Torre could also audition the rookie Craig Dingman in the last days of the regular season.</p>
        <p>Cone, who was pessimistic about his chances of returning this season after he was hurt Tuesday, surprised the Yankees by the range of motion he showed with his left arm today.</p>
        <p>Initially, Cone had been told he would need a week off from even throwing a ball. But he threw in the outfield today, with Mendoza as his caddy, and Torre embraced the idea that Cone could pitch again Sept. 15, missing only one start, the game in Boston on Sunday.</p>
        <p>''It looks like he's going to be back a lot sooner than we anticipated,'' Torre said.</p>
        <p>If Cone does come back, he could contend for a spot in long relief, though the Yankees might go with Randy Choate, a left-handed specialist, instead.</p>
        <p>Randy Keisler, called up from Class AAA a couple of days ago, will start in Cone's place against the Red Sox. The 24-year-old left-hander from Texas pitches with a style similar to Denny Neagle.</p>
        <p>He has an average fastball, 87 to 89 miles an hour, that he uses to set up a devastating changeup and a decent curve. Some of Keisler's former managers like his demeanor on the mound and the confidence he projects. Some of the Yankee coaches summoned Andy Pettitte to the bullpen to watch Keisler Wednesday, then told the rookie to stand on the mound and act as if he was going to throw a pitch. Pettitte cracked up laughing, recognizing that Keisler's mannerisms resembled his own.</p>
        <p>Keisler, who would have been part of the trade for Detroit's Juan Gonzalez if that deal had not fallen apart, said he would have been extremely disappointed if the trade had gone through. ''Now I'm one of 30 guys playing on the best sports franchise,'' he said. ''I wouldn't trade that for anything.''</p>
        <p>Keisler has never been in Fenway Park. In fact, he has never been in Boston. ''I just hope we get through the first,'' he said, acknowledging the jitters he will feel. ''Then I'll be all right.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
