<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>How Does This Manhattan Love Story End? Flip a Coin.</title>
    <meta content="08WHER" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/08/arts/08WHER.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228717"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Spoonamore, Stephen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Van Gelder, Lawrence</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Where Everything Is Everything (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000908T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E4D71539F93BA3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="481" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>How Does This Manhattan Love Story End? Flip a Coin.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAWRENCE VAN GELDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Van Gelder, Lawrence</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lawrence Van Gelder reviews Where Everything is Everything, play written and directed by Stephen Spoonamore; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Stephen Spoonamore, the playwright responsible for last year's torturous ''Noah's Archive,'' has done it again. That is to say, he has written another tedious play.</p>
        <p>This one is titled ''Where Everything Is Everything.'' And not content with having written it, Mr. Spoonamore, who is also the producer, has directed it with a hand that appears to know no restraint.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Stephen Spoonamore, the playwright responsible for last year's torturous ''Noah's Archive,'' has done it again. That is to say, he has written another tedious play.</p>
        <p>This one is titled ''Where Everything Is Everything.'' And not content with having written it, Mr. Spoonamore, who is also the producer, has directed it with a hand that appears to know no restraint.</p>
        <p>To compound the miseries of this self-indulgent exercise at the Ryan Theater at New York Performance Works on Chambers Street, ''Where Everything Is Everything'' is a play with a gimmick. At the end of Act I, a coin toss supposedly decides whether Mr. Spoonamore's account of young love in Manhattan will conclude as a comedy or a tragedy. This gamble means that anyone sufficiently masochistic to return for a another look at this play stands a 50-50 chance of being bored in the same way yet again.</p>
        <p>Stripped to its essentials, ''Where Everything Is Everything'' tells of the romance of Dan Kurlingham and Tracy Cochran. At 32, he is a foul-mouthed, arrogant lord of financial services. At 25, she is an insecure graphic designer who makes inroads on Dan's purported heart when she has the temerity to almost tell him that he is an ass.</p>
        <p>To their credit, as they play all six roles in this play, Paul Sparks, a survivor of ''Noah's Archives,'' and Daisy Eagan, who won a 1991 Tony Award in ''The Secret Garden,'' bring professionalism to material that is by turns purposelessly wordy, uninteresting, unfunny and embarrassing.</p>
        <p>Not content with tracking Dan and Tracy through meeting and dating, the playwright provides interludes in which his stars, garishly costumed, impersonate guides to the manners and mores of Manhattan, where, he says, everything is everything.</p>
        <p>These attempts at humor and knowingness vacillate between the futile and the tasteless. At one point on a recent evening, when poor Ms. Eagan was called upon to don a sequined red costume in midspeech, it failed to assume the proper shape, requiring her to explain that it was intended to be the Big Apple (rather than the squashed plum tomato it resembled).</p>
        <p>When it comes to worthwhile theater, not much of anything is to be found at ''Where Everything Is Everything.''</p>
        <p>WHERE EVERYTHING IS EVERYTHING</p>
        <p>Written and directed by Stephen Spoonamore; lighting by Robert Williams; sets by Sean Patrick Anderson; costumes by Charlene Alexis Gross; sound by Michael Wrobleyski; stage manager, Rebecca Wilson. Presented by CBT Productions, in association with Greg Trautman and Cold Productions. At New York Performance Works, Ryan Theater, 128 Chambers Street, at West Broadway, TriBeCa.</p>
        <p>WITH: Paul Sparks (Main Man Dan, Dan Kurlingham and Renee) and Daisy Eagen (Traveler Tracy, Tracy Cochran and Carla).</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
