<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TV's Bad Boy, Underground and Underfoot</title>
    <meta content="08PROF" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/08/nyregion/08PROF.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228763"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PUBLIC LIVES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Popular Entertainers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Subways</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Tad Low</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dewan, Shaila K</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Low, Tad</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Subway Q &amp; A (TV Program)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Pop-Up Video (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Public Lives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Subways</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000908T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEEDA1239F93BA3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="998" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TV's Bad Boy, Underground and Underfoot</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SHAILA K. DEWAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dewan, Shaila K</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of Tad Low, prankster whose latest television program is Subway Q &amp; A, in which he appears in subway car, camera crew in tow, to interview riders; Low's aim is to elevate real people to celebrity, and to destroy machine of celebrity culture; his program, Pop-Up Video, has included string of stunts that make television executives understandably wary; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR those of you reading this on the subway, a warning: don't look up. In a few moments, the doors will open, and it very well might be Tad Low getting on, trailed by a camera crew. Draw your newspaper up a little higher. Because if Mr. Low sees you, he will talk to you.</p>
        <p>To him, a subway car is nothing more than a cocktail party, and he the appointed ice-breaker. He will try anything, even thrust his head in your lap, to divert you from the carefully laid path of your day, to cajole you into, say, going to feed the sea lions in the Central Park Zoo. Or to maneuver himself to your apartment, looking for sandwich fillings for the Wonder bread he's carrying. Or (women only, please) to persuade you to dine with him on the train, on a portable table with a rose and, in your face, a microphone.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR those of you reading this on the subway, a warning: don't look up. In a few moments, the doors will open, and it very well might be Tad Low getting on, trailed by a camera crew. Draw your newspaper up a little higher. Because if Mr. Low sees you, he will talk to you.</p>
        <p>To him, a subway car is nothing more than a cocktail party, and he the appointed ice-breaker. He will try anything, even thrust his head in your lap, to divert you from the carefully laid path of your day, to cajole you into, say, going to feed the sea lions in the Central Park Zoo. Or to maneuver himself to your apartment, looking for sandwich fillings for the Wonder bread he's carrying. Or (women only, please) to persuade you to dine with him on the train, on a portable table with a rose and, in your face, a microphone.</p>
        <p>Come to think of it, a newspaper shield won't stop Mr. Low, any more than being called ''the biggest idiot on television'' by Entertainment Weekly in 1994 stopped him from creating ''Pop-Up Video,'' which in 1996 saved VH1 from obscurity and unleashed a hyena pack of imitators. The only way to protect yourself: don't sign the form permitting him to use you on ''Subway Q &amp; A.'' That's Mr. Low's new show on the Metro Channel, New York's latest reason to give in and get cable.</p>
        <p>''Subway Q &amp; A'' showcases the charming side of Mr. Low, 33, a reality prospector who might fairly be called an MTV-style Studs Terkel. But it is only one prong of his two-pronged manifesto: to elevate real people to celebrity, and to destroy the machine of celebrity culture.</p>
        <p>The urge to destroy the celebrity culture has been channeled most productively in ''Pop-Up Video.'' In it, blurbs superimposed on music videos inform viewers that, for example, in a Paula Abdul video meant to inspire environmentalism, the grass was painted green. But Mr. Low's guerrilla tactics have led to a string of stunts that make television executives understandably wary.</p>
        <p>In March, he stormed the stage at the TV Guide awards show when Carson Daly's ''Total Request Live'' on MTV beat out ''Pop-Up.'' ''This is robbery!'' he shouted, rather ungraciously, before being escorted off stage. But Mr. Low insists that it wasn't a matter of sour grapes. ''I was trying to expose the fallacy behind award shows,'' he says.</p>
        <p>In June, Mr. Low was forced off the staff of ''Pop-Up'' and split with his partner, Woody Thompson. The partnership first soured in 1998, when Mr. Low and Mr. Thompson appeared on Oprah Winfrey's show.</p>
        <p>To the staff's horror, Mr. Low took a camera backstage and refused to give it up, stuffing the tape down his pants. The VH1 publicist fled in tears, and the executive producer threatened to cancel that segment of ''Oprah'' until, minutes before air time, Mr. Low relinquished the tape. ''I wanted to really show what the experience was like,'' he says.</p>
        <p>BUT Mr. Low, who grew up in luxury in Greenwich, Conn., the son of an investment banker, sometimes chooses more trivial targets. In April, his membership in the Yale Club was suspended after he pelted the Whiffenpoofs, a singing group, with crudites and cheese cubes. He was protesting the club's policy that guests' drinks must be charged to a member's tab.</p>
        <p>Now, Mr. Low. Must you be so . . .?</p>
        <p>But how to finish that question without feeling rather like a humorless assistant principal?</p>
        <p>Mr. Low is sitting in the Holland Bar on Ninth Avenue, drinking beer on ice (an anti-dehydration measure,  he says) while a man in a baseball cap pantomimes along to ''Hello Dolly,'' Mr. Low's jukebox selection.</p>
        <p>A man who has been fired from many jobs, from MTV cultural correspondent to co-host of Brandon Tartikoff's ''Last Call,'' Mr. Low is explaining his latest troubles. After shooting a ''Subway Q &amp; A'' segment in which he, determined to seal New York's status as urban amusement park, dressed up as a giant teddy bear, he entered the Metro Channel offices and grabbed a woman's derriere. Tomorrow, he must answer to the human resources director. ''It was obviously a joke,'' he said. ''I'm not Bob Packwood. I'm a bear.''</p>
        <p>''This is what happens inside of corporate America,'' he fumes. ''You try to do something slightly innovative, slightly energetic, slightly celebratory of alive spirit, and instantly you're being talked to.''</p>
        <p>Never apologetic, Mr. Low takes his failures as proof of his genius. He co-produced an alternative to the Olympics in which people competed to unwrap CD's and parallel park. It was the lowest-rated TV special ever.</p>
        <p>''I know that if you're that wrong, you're very, very right,'' Mr. Low says. ''To come up with the lowest-rated show in the history of television, that is more meaningful to me than seven Emmys.''</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Low still shops ideas to networks (Nickelodeon is on the verge of taking ''Phly,'' in which taped conversations are played over a montage of images in a kind of video rebus game), his big-picture plan is one that has given him what he craves: total creative control. It's Spin the Bottle Dot Com, an Internet ''network'' that features three-minute shows.</p>
        <p>On it, Mr. Low seems to be emphasizing real people over media-bashing. His current favorite idea is ''Good People,'' a talk show in which a waitress, say, could be asked what it's like to watch caffeine junkies get their fix. ''Come on, I would much rather hear about that than Brad Pitt's latest project,'' he says. ''But will America want to see it?''</p>
        <p>PUBLIC LIVES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
