<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Schools Try To Smooth The Bumps On Day 1</title>
    <meta content="08SCHO$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/08/nyregion/08SCHO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000911T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228868"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Board of Education (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hartocollis, Anemona</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Levy, Harold O (Chancellor)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000908T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E7DB1339F93BA3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1157" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Schools Try To Smooth The Bumps On Day 1</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANEMONA HARTOCOLLIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hartocollis, Anemona</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York City's 1.1 million public school children begin classes, from prekindergarten to high school; Mayor Rudolph W Giuliani and Chancellor Harold O Levy hail opening as smooth and untroubled in Queens school they visit; elsewhere across city, principals, parents and teachers cope with kinds of opening-day disruptions and disappointments that have become almost institutionalized in many public schools; Levy says he is ending hiring freeze that has prevented more successful schools from hiring certified teachers they want; says Board of Education has complied with court order requiring it to hire certified teachers for vacancies in worst elementary schools; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As Harold O. Levy, the freshman chancellor, arrived at Central Park East, a public elementary school in East Harlem, on the first leg of a back-to-school tour, he was startled yesterday morning to find the school's administrator mopping up spilled coffee in a cafeteria swirling with excited children and their anxious parents.</p>
        <p>''The first thing I thought was, this is a custodian I could love,'' Mr. Levy said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As Harold O. Levy, the freshman chancellor, arrived at Central Park East, a public elementary school in East Harlem, on the first leg of a back-to-school tour, he was startled yesterday morning to find the school's administrator mopping up spilled coffee in a cafeteria swirling with excited children and their anxious parents.</p>
        <p>''The first thing I thought was, this is a custodian I could love,'' Mr. Levy said.</p>
        <p>The administrator, Bruce R. Kanze, shrugged off the mistaken identity. ''If there's a spill in the cafeteria, I'm going to mop it up,'' he said later. ''It's just a reflex.''</p>
        <p>Yesterday was a day for mopping up spills large and small, as 1.1 million New York City schoolchildren began classes, from prekindergarten to high school, after the summer.</p>
        <p>Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani and Mr. Levy, in a ceremonial joint visit to a school in Queens, hailed the opening as smooth and untroubled. And it was true: the day seemed unmarred by the kind of crises -- from asbestos contamination to overcrowding -- that have become as much a back-to-school ritual as new book bags and the right hairstyle.</p>
        <p>But across the city, principals, parents and teachers coped with the kinds of opening-day disruptions and disappointments -- classes in trailers, inexperienced teachers, a false bomb scare in a Bronx school -- that have become almost institutionalized in many public schools.</p>
        <p>At Central Park East, Adrienne Mason, the mother of a second grader, was alarmed to see the chancellor, thinking that it was better for the school she loved to be left alone by the central bureaucracy.</p>
        <p>''The Board of Education has a policy,'' Ms. Mason, a health care marketer, candidly told the chancellor, buttonholing him in the hallway. It destroys anything that works, she said.</p>
        <p>One shadow was lifted yesterday when Mr. Levy said he was ending a hiring freeze that prevented the more successful schools from hiring the certified teachers they wanted. Mr. Levy said that the board had complied with a court order requiring it to hire certified teachers for vacancies in the worst elementary schools. Some vacancies, he said, may remain in middle and high schools.</p>
        <p>The need for qualified teachers is particularly acute this year because children face new Regents mathematics examinations this year, in addition to the one-year-old English examinations, as a requirement for graduating from high school. The system must also show that it can help more than 20,000 students who were held back at the end of this summer, under a tough new policy to end social promotion.</p>
        <p>''This year's asbestos crisis is personnel,'' said Noreen Connell, executive director of the Educational Priorities Panel, a nonprofit group that monitors city schools. ''There is a shortage of good teachers, and this is a good economy. Many of them can walk with their feet, going to easier, higher-paying jobs in the suburbs.''</p>
        <p>Among districts with opening day problems was Washington Heights in Manhattan, where Dominican immigration has swelled enrollment. At P.S. 192, elementary school classes were going smoothly, but more than 300 middle-school students waited nearly two hours in a cramped auditorium for buses to take them across town because their local schools could not accommodate them.</p>
        <p>As distraught and angry mothers waited outside, some ducking into nearby bodegas to buy orange juice for their captive children, district officials said the charter company that ran the buses was late, but they could not explain why.</p>
        <p>At P.S. 25 in Bedford-Stuyvesant, Brooklyn, one of the city's lowest-performing schools, a small group of parents complained that the new principal, Leroy Johnson, had previously presided over a school that had been forced to close because of poor performance, Intermediate School 74 in the Bronx.</p>
        <p>Irwin Kurz, instructional superintendent for the Chancellor's District for troubled schools, said Mr. Johnson had a history as a trouble-shooter and had been hired to turn P.S. 25 around with the help of 13 teaching fellows -- teachers recruited from other professions this year through a program established by Mr. Levy.</p>
        <p>In Queens, 80 children who had failed eighth grade, under the new policy on social promotion, were quarantined in trailers behind an elementary school, P.S. 100 in Ozone Park. There they became instant pariahs -- resented by parents at the elementary school, surrounded by security guards and forbidden to enter the main school building, even to eat lunch.</p>
        <p>Matthew Bromme, the district superintendent, said that the 80 students were part of the Eight-Plus program established by the board as a transition between middle school and high school, and that they would move on by February.</p>
        <p>In Manhattan, middle-class parents at successful yet fragile schools, like Middle School 54 and P.S. 163, both on the Upper West Side, worried that their best teachers were being reshuffled to failing schools in the Bronx and Brooklyn, robbing Peter to pay Paul, under the court order agreed to by the state, the city and the teachers' union.</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Levy, now entering contract negotiations with teachers, has made hiring and keeping qualified teachers a theme of his new administration, the city has not been able to meet its goal of hiring only certified teachers throughout the system. The teachers' union reported yesterday that of the teachers hired this fall, 4,100 were certified, and 2,500 were uncertified. That is in a system where about 15 percent of all teachers are uncertified, and more in the most troubled schools.</p>
        <p>Randi Weingarten, president of the union, the United Federation of Teachers, said that she had met with 800 teacher leaders yesterday and heard many accounts of budget reductions that had forced high schools to cut back on teaching positions.</p>
        <p>Board officials said they could not confirm the union's figures on uncertified teachers. They added that additional money had been allocated to high schools over the last two weeks.</p>
        <p>Several principals said that the school system was being overly dogmatic in its push to hire certified teachers, a position that Mr. Levy has hinted he agrees with.</p>
        <p>At Central Park East, Mr. Levy waxed a bit rhapsodic, but steered clear of any grand claims for the day, perhaps realizing that they might come back to haunt him. ''What I'm satisfied with is that there are 78,000 teachers doing God's work,'' he said before moving on to three other schools in three other boroughs. ''We should celebrate the fact that schools are opening. School opening is a new beginning.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  September 11, 2000, Monday  A picture caption on Friday about the opening of public schools in New York City misstated the location of Public School 212 in Queens. It is in Jackson Heights, not Forest Hills.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: September 11, 2000, Monday</p>
        <p>A picture caption on Friday about the opening of public schools in New York City misstated the location of Public School 212 in Queens. It is in Jackson Heights, not Forest Hills.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
