<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Postal Service and FedEx Discuss Partnership</title>
    <meta content="Y08FEDE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/08/business/08FEDE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228743"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Delivery Services</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Postal Service</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Express Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Parcel Service</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zuckerman, Laurence</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Service Industries</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000908T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E7DC1239F93BA3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="538" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Postal Service and FedEx Discuss Partnership</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAURENCE ZUCKERMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zuckerman, Laurence</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>US Postal Service and FedEx Corp are discussing partnership that would help service increase revenue while giving FedEx low-cost way to reach millions of residential customers; partnership could be blow to industry leader, United Parcel Service, which delivers 12 million packages a day; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The United States Postal Service and the FedEx Corporation are discussing a partnership that would help the service increase revenue while giving FedEx a low-cost way to reach millions of residential customers.</p>
        <p>William J. Henderson, the postmaster general, said yesterday that executives from both organizations had been meeting in Washington and Memphis, where FedEx is based, and that the outline of a deal could be ready to be presented to the Postal Service's 11-member board as early as next month.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The United States Postal Service and the FedEx Corporation are discussing a partnership that would help the service increase revenue while giving FedEx a low-cost way to reach millions of residential customers.</p>
        <p>William J. Henderson, the postmaster general, said yesterday that executives from both organizations had been meeting in Washington and Memphis, where FedEx is based, and that the outline of a deal could be ready to be presented to the Postal Service's 11-member board as early as next month.</p>
        <p>''We are optimistic that we can reach some agreement,'' he said. ''We think there are big opportunities for the Postal Service and FedEx.''</p>
        <p>FedEx also confirmed that the two sides were talking, but a spokesman declined to provide any details.</p>
        <p>Mr. Henderson said the alliance could enable the post office to take advantage of FedEx's extensive air network while letting FedEx piggyback on the service's network of mail carriers. For example, mail carriers could pick up returns for FedEx's catalog clients on their regular rounds, saving FedEx the expense of having to visit thousands of homes.</p>
        <p>A partnership between the post office and FedEx could be a blow to United Parcel Service, which is the industry leader, delivering 12 million packages a day. FedEx delivers 3.3 million shipments a day. It dominates the overnight segment of the market and has been trying to expand its less speedy ground-delivery service.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Henderson said that the post office would not make an exclusive agreement with FedEx on any service except a contract to provide air transportation. ''In terms of access or use of the Postal Service or leveraging our assets, we are open to negotiating with anybody,'' he said.</p>
        <p>That may blunt some of the opposition to a deal but also make it less attractive for FedEx. ''If they are saying, 'We would like to strike a deal with FedEx, U.P.S., DHL and anybody else who is interested,' said Norman Black, a U.P.S. spokesman, ''yes, we would seriously look at what they are proposing.''</p>
        <p>But he said that it did not appear that that was what the service was doing based on reports of the talks, which appeared yesterday in The Washington Post and The Wall Street Journal. ''You are left with the impression that they would use taxpayer-paid employees to favor one competitor over another,'' he said. ''And we don't believe that Congress and the United States Postal Rate Commission would find that proper.''</p>
        <p>Because of an $800 million shortfall in revenue, the post office is expected to lose $300 million in the fiscal year ending this month, its first loss since 1994. During the heavy mailing seasons each fall and winter, the service makes substantial profits that are whittled away when mail volume drops in the spring and summer. Mr. Henderson said he was looking for ways to increase revenue and offset the fixed costs of the Postal Service's vast delivery network by, in effect, renting it out to companies like FedEx.</p>
        <p>Shares of FedEx fell 45 cents yesterday, to $39.82, on the New York Stock Exchange.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
