<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>7 Guitarists Take On the Brooklyn Bridge</title>
    <meta content="24BRAN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217340"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Combustion Chamber (Music Group)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ratliff, Ben</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Branca, Glenn</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gosfield, Annie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kline, Phil</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000724T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906EFDE123AF937A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="646" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>7 Guitarists Take On the Brooklyn Bridge</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN RATLIFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ratliff, Ben</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ben Ratliff reviews performance of Glenn Branca symphony, conducted by composer, by Annie Gosfield's trio, Combustion Chamber, and by Phil Kline as part of Creative Time's Music series at Brooklyn Bridge Anchorage (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Glenn Branca's symphonies go backward and forward. Their grand, stormy electric-guitar sound became an aural icon of American underground music in the 1980's, and it is a sound that is still demanded of him by commissions. On the other hand it's clear that where he wants to go -- as shown by several recorded pieces over the last five years -- is writing for a large acoustic orchestra and attaining a greater range of expression and nuance, rather than dealing in sheer power.</p>
        <p>But that amplified power can't be denied, a fact proven on Thursday night at the Brooklyn Bridge Anchorage, when Mr. Branca played his Symphony No. 12 (subtitled ''Tonal Sexus'') with instrumentation similar to what he used at the beginning of his symphonic career, a group of seven guitarists (separated into soprano, tenor and alto), bass and drums. In terms of harmonic movement the piece is miles ahead of where Mr. Branca began; there was a time when he often stayed with one chord while doggedly exploring the higher-frequency overtones of single notes. But on the outer levels, No. 12 holds fast to the idea of the constant crescendo, which was there in his work from the start. Virgil Moorefield's drumming maintained the unpretentious, 4/4 drum rhythms from rock that Mr. Branca so loves.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Glenn Branca's symphonies go backward and forward. Their grand, stormy electric-guitar sound became an aural icon of American underground music in the 1980's, and it is a sound that is still demanded of him by commissions. On the other hand it's clear that where he wants to go -- as shown by several recorded pieces over the last five years -- is writing for a large acoustic orchestra and attaining a greater range of expression and nuance, rather than dealing in sheer power.</p>
        <p>But that amplified power can't be denied, a fact proven on Thursday night at the Brooklyn Bridge Anchorage, when Mr. Branca played his Symphony No. 12 (subtitled ''Tonal Sexus'') with instrumentation similar to what he used at the beginning of his symphonic career, a group of seven guitarists (separated into soprano, tenor and alto), bass and drums. In terms of harmonic movement the piece is miles ahead of where Mr. Branca began; there was a time when he often stayed with one chord while doggedly exploring the higher-frequency overtones of single notes. But on the outer levels, No. 12 holds fast to the idea of the constant crescendo, which was there in his work from the start. Virgil Moorefield's drumming maintained the unpretentious, 4/4 drum rhythms from rock that Mr. Branca so loves.</p>
        <p>It was concise: a 40-minute, one-movement, 920-measure piece. (The stone archways near the stage allowed one to see what the guitarists were reading from, and some of them had refashioned Mr. Branca's score so that it simply had large measure numbers, a chord symbol and an indication of dynamics.) Every stretch of the music was full of commotion; the higher-pitched instruments would land on a note and make a massed unison of it, while the rest of the ensemble churned away in contrary harmonic motion.</p>
        <p>Though it never lost its basic loudness, the music breathed; at irregular intervals blocks of guitarists increased or decreased the attack on their chords. Mr. Branca hasn't lost his curiosity about overtones, and the massed sounds rang terrifically in the vast, high-ceilinged space. And at certain points strong major-key plateaus emerged from these shifting harmonic sands.</p>
        <p>Mr. Branca, as always, threw himself into the music; it's clear that he writes these pieces for the thrill of his own emotional demolition, and he's a pleasure to watch as he releases himself. He conducted without using a score; one of his guitarists, Carolyn Master, signaled the band at certain important moments. In an unbuttoned overshirt with cuffs flapping, torn jeans and high-top sneakers, Mr. Branca became a barometer of the music's intensity, gyrating at the knees, hips and wrists, screaming (though inaudible over the din) some sort of chant mimicking some phrases in the music, looking like a cartoon of Jekyll becoming Hyde.</p>
        <p>The multichambered space enabled each act on the bill -- part of Creative Time's Music in the Anchorage series -- to play in a different physical area, and the audience walked from one performance to another. Most of the evening, as it turned out, dealt with overtones.</p>
        <p>Annie Gosfield's trio, Combustion Chamber, had it in her dense, rising and falling synthesizer and slide-guitar chords. And Phil Kline presented an audience-performed piece, in which he distributed a few dozen boom boxes to audience members and asked them to roam around the space. Here the seesawing chords twinkled, and the slightly out-of-sync effect -- the audience members didn't press the play-buttons at exactly the same moment -- gave it an everywhere-and-nowhere feeling. Toward the end the tones suddenly started rising sharply. The audience members, in on the music, looked at one another and smiled in a sweet, look-what-we-did way.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
