<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Johnson and Greene Painfully End Duel</title>
    <meta content="24OLYM$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217449"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="OLYMPICS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Track and Field</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Longman, Jere</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Capel, John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnson, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greene, Maurice</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004/Track and Field</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Track and Field</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000724T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00EFDF133AF937A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1256" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Johnson and Greene Painfully End Duel</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JERE LONGMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Longman, Jere</byline>
      <dateline>SACRAMENTO, July 23</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Maurice Greene and Michael Johnson are injured during 200 meters run at US Olympic track and field trials, which is won by John Capel; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was the nervous hope of Maurice Greene's coach that Greene and Michael Johnson would not try to run each other into the ground and get injured at the Olympic trials, saving their legs and their egos for September at the 2000 Summer Games in Sydney, Australia.</p>
        <p>''You've got to know when to pick your fights,'' John Smith said. ''The race to lay it all out is the Olympic Games.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was the nervous hope of Maurice Greene's coach that Greene and Michael Johnson would not try to run each other into the ground and get injured at the Olympic trials, saving their legs and their egos for September at the 2000 Summer Games in Sydney, Australia.</p>
        <p>''You've got to know when to pick your fights,'' John Smith said. ''The race to lay it all out is the Olympic Games.''</p>
        <p>Smith's fear, expressed last month, was eerily prescient, foreshadowing today's unimaginable occurrence in the most anticipated sprint matchup in more than a decade.</p>
        <p>After cramping in his hips at the start of the 200 meters, Johnson, the world record-holder at 200 and 400 meters, pulled up in the middle of the curve, stumbled, grabbed his seizing left hamstring and fell to the track, grimacing. He was carried off on a stretcher. Coming out of the curve in sixth place, Greene, who holds the world record at 100 meters, also began limping, ran gingerly as he decelerated, then also stopped before the finish line. Later, on this disappointing 26th birthday, he had ice applied to his strained left hamstring.</p>
        <p>John Capel, a former wide receiver and the 1999 collegiate champion at 200 meters at the University of Florida, took first place in 19.85 seconds, a personal best, as 34-year-old Floyd Heard took second in 19.88 and Coby Miller finished third in 19.96.</p>
        <p>But these achievements will quickly fade into trivia questions. What will be remembered are the stunning injuries and the fact that the United States faces the first Olympic 200 of the millennium without Johnson, the defending Olympic champion and world record-holder at 19.32 seconds, and Greene, the defending world champion with a personal best of 19.86.</p>
        <p>''Shakespearean,'' said Craig Masback, the head of USA Track and Field, the sport's national governing body. ''The two leading protagonists injure themselves and a young kid who no one thought could win runs one of the best times ever. An incredible drama that no one expected.''</p>
        <p>It remains to be seen whether lingering effects from the cramp will hinder Johnson's preparation to defend his Olympic title at 400 meters and to win a gold in the 1,600-meter relay. And whether Greene can recover to win gold medals at 100 meters and in the 400-meter relay. Johnson's injury, which he did not believe was a strain or a tear, conjured images of his withdrawal from a 1997 match race over 150 meters against Donovan Bailey of Canada, the 1996 Olympic champion at 100 meters. Despite Johnson's unsurpassed speed and endurance in the long sprints, today's events will certainly lead to questions -- however undeserved -- about his brittleness during times of extreme speed.</p>
        <p>''I couldn't stop; you guys would have killed me,'' Johnson told reporters, explaining why he did not withdraw before the final, showing his sensitivity to such questions. ''The position I'm in. Who I am, the times that I've run. I accepted the position I'm in and I did as well as I could.''</p>
        <p>Greene said: ''I felt a strain in my hamstring. I stopped before I tore something. I don't think it had anything to do with the heat or the rivalry. I was just trying to do something my body wasn't ready to do.''</p>
        <p>At the least, Johnson and Greene should receive points for giving the 200 final a try. In Saturday's preliminaries, Johnson felt a cramp in his right thigh. This morning, he had swelling in the thigh and his coach, Clyde Hart, said Johnson's chances of running the semifinals did not look good.</p>
        <p>But Johnson went to the practice track, and for two hours he warmed up and got massages from his physical therapist. After Johnson put on spikes and sprinted from a set of blocks, it became clear that the early pessimism had abated with the tightness in his thigh muscle.</p>
        <p>For the semifinal, Greene drew Lane 4, with Johnson in Lane 5. Johnson false-started once, and in the restart, Greene made up the stagger early, gaining a slight lead coming out of the curve. Johnson, however, blew past him on the homestretch, shut down with 15 meters remaining and conceded the heat to Capel.</p>
        <p>The final was run less than two hours later in heat that reached 118 degrees on the track, which could have led to dehydration and cramping. Johnson said he thought he had consumed sufficient amounts of water, but added, ''Maybe I didn't get enough.'' He drew Lane 4 for the final and fell into trouble immediately, failing to make up the stagger on Capel in Lane 5 before his leg began cramping.</p>
        <p>''It didn't hurt in the semis,'' Johnson said of his right thigh. ''What happened in the final was somewhat of a surprise.''</p>
        <p>The Olympic trials require that track and field athletes finish among the top three to qualify for the Summer Games. There are no wild-card entries. Johnson said he thought the system should be changed to allow wild cards, but not until after he retired, so that it would not appear that he was being granted any special favors.</p>
        <p>''It would cause too much craziness,'' Johnson said.</p>
        <p>As Johnson warmed up for the semifinal, his agent, Brad Hunt, said that the sprinter's main concern was not his leg but how he would be portrayed by the media. He has been touchy about remarks from other sprinters and track insiders, who have questioned his appetite for important matchups since he dropped out of the match race against Bailey with a strained thigh muscle.</p>
        <p>After Johnson withdrew from the 200 meters at the 1999 national championships, citing a thigh injury, Greene accused Johnson of ducking him.</p>
        <p>While a withdrawal in today's final may prevent further risk to a cramping hamstring, it may not prevent an injury to Johnson's reputation among track insiders, said Ato Boldon of Trinidad, who finished third to Johnson in the 200 at the Atlanta Olympics and trains daily with Greene in Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>''The general public will think: 'This guy's run 19.32, he's the world record-holder. He pulled up, so what, it's not a big deal,' '' Boldon said. ''People in track and field know Maurice has accused Michael of ducking him. They don't care if Michael's legitimately hurt.''</p>
        <p>Hunt bristled at Boldon's remarks, while Johnson finished his warm-ups before today's semifinal.</p>
        <p>''I just hope for the sake of Ato Boldon and Maurice Greene that they have the opportunity for the track community to give a damn about what they're doing at age 33,'' he said.</p>
        <p>In the weeks leading up to the race, Johnson and Greene became embroiled in exchanges of trash-talking. Today, Greene said that he met Johnson after the race as the two athletes were being drug-tested and told him, ''Get well,'' but that Johnson did not respond.</p>
        <p>''It's disappointing,'' Johnson said of not being able to defend his Olympic title at 200 meters. In Atlanta he became the first man to win the 200 and 400 meters at the same Olympics. He had also been seeking a double victory in Sydney. ''You can't have everything. I still have a chance to represent my country in the 400. I can't be too disappointed. I'll move on.''</p>
        <p>OLYMPICS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
