<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Neagle, Left-Handed Prankster, Fits In With Yanks</title>
    <meta content="24YANK$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217425"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Tampa Bay Devil Rays</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Curry, Jack</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Tampa Bay Devil Rays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Tampa Bay Rays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000724T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00EED6123AF937A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="962" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Neagle, Left-Handed Prankster, Fits In With Yanks</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Curry, Jack</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Yankees defeat Tampa Bay Devil Rays, 5-1; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Denny Neagle was quietly pulling on his uniform yesterday when a piece of fruit glanced off him. The new Yankee and eternal prankster turned and only saw reporters, so he resumed getting dressed. But Neagle was plunked by another slab of fruit a few seconds later and it baffled him. Who was toying with him on the only day when he is serious?</p>
        <p>It was 90 minutes before Neagle tossed his first pitch in a scintillating 5-1 victory over the Tampa Bay Devil Rays, but he was suddenly interested in flying fruit. Finally, someone informed Neagle that Mariano Rivera had whipped a couple of fruit fastballs at him.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Denny Neagle was quietly pulling on his uniform yesterday when a piece of fruit glanced off him. The new Yankee and eternal prankster turned and only saw reporters, so he resumed getting dressed. But Neagle was plunked by another slab of fruit a few seconds later and it baffled him. Who was toying with him on the only day when he is serious?</p>
        <p>It was 90 minutes before Neagle tossed his first pitch in a scintillating 5-1 victory over the Tampa Bay Devil Rays, but he was suddenly interested in flying fruit. Finally, someone informed Neagle that Mariano Rivera had whipped a couple of fruit fastballs at him.</p>
        <p>''Very nice,'' said Neagle, a smile creasing his thick face. ''Very nice.''</p>
        <p>From a pregame target to a game-time dominator to a postgame enthusiast, it has quickly become obvious that Neagle is comfortable with the Yankees and that the Yankees are comfortable with him. Neagle acted as if Yankee Stadium was his own playground by pitching a four-hitter to win his second start as a Yankee and also win his 100th career game.</p>
        <p>With his father, his wife and his 6-month-old son among the 45,528 fans, Neagle pleased the Yankees and frustrated the Devil Rays by mixing in fastballs, sliders and changeups. Neagle asked David Cone to remind him to save yesterday's game ball, but, after catcher Jorge Posada squeezed Jose Canseco's pop-up to end the game, Neagle pumped his fist and remembered to tuck the ball in his glove.</p>
        <p>''It's nice to get your 100th win no matter where you get it, but this is going to make it a little more special,'' said Neagle, whose career record is 100-62. ''To be able to look back and say that my 100th win was a complete game in front of a packed house at Yankee Stadium is special.''</p>
        <p>Neagle is an intriguing character. He loves to do imitations, play jokes and pitch. He has also exhibited excellent control and poise since the Yankees obtained him from the Reds 12 days ago. With an earned run average of 1.06 since then, Neagle might be the Yankees' best starter.</p>
        <p>''He's doing exactly what we hoped he would do,'' General Manager Brian Cashman said. ''Our scouts saw him as a tremendous pitcher. Everything they said was right.''</p>
        <p>As Cashman spoke with reporters about imminent negotiations with the left-handed Neagle for a multiyear deal, which would probably be in the four-year, $36 million range, Neagle shouted, ''Brian, you want to bang it out right now?''</p>
        <p>Cashman quickly said, ''Let's do it.''</p>
        <p>Neither one of them was joking that much. Manager Joe Torre and the Yankees have raved about playing behind Neagle, who rests his left foot on the extreme right side of the rubber and barely moves. He works quickly and effectively; he even waved to the fans in the right-field bleachers when they chanted his name in the first inning. Cone and the former Yankee David Wells are the only other starters who have ever acknowledged the bleacher creatures.</p>
        <p>''I was talking to Clay Bellinger, and he said they've probably read about how goofy I am,'' Neagle said. ''So I figured I should do it.''</p>
        <p>Bryan Rekar throttled Chuck Knoblauch (0 for 12) and Derek Jeter (0 for 11) before yesterday, but they started the Yankees' first rally in the fourth inning. Knoblauch singled to left and Jeter smashed a run-scoring double to left-center. One out later, Bernie Williams ripped another run-scoring double to make the score 2-0. The Yankees added three more runs in the fifth when they were helped by Rekar's throwing error.</p>
        <p>With a 5-0 lead, Neagle cruised. Tampa Bay's Greg Vaughn doubled to open the seventh, but Fred McGriff's double merely sent him to third. It was the best chance the Devils Rays had, but Neagle kept the damage to one run by notching two grounders and striking out Mike DiFelice. Neagle struck out eight, walked one and retired the side in order six times.</p>
        <p>''He seems like he gets ahead of everybody,'' Posada said. ''With any pitch and in any situation.''</p>
        <p>By the time Neagle showered, he was back to being a prankster. He was amused that Rivera felt comfortable enough to toss fruit at him, but Neagle was plotting revenge.</p>
        <p>''These guys are getting to know me,'' Neagle said. ''I don't like to even be touched before I pitch. But the good thing is he doesn't know that I know he did it. Maybe I'll leave him one of those 6 a.m. room service breakfast orders.''</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>Some members of the Yankees' hierarchy are still pushing for the team to acquire RONDELL WHITE from Montreal because they do not believe that DAVID JUSTICE and GLENALLEN HILL are adequate in left field. . . . DENNY NEAGLE questioned why BARRY LARKIN, his former teammate, rejected the chance to play for the Mets. ''You do have to wonder why he wouldn't want to at least take the opportunity to go to a team like the Mets, who have a chance to go to the postseason,'' Neagle said.</p>
        <p>DEREK JETER saw his close friend GERALD WILLIAMS leap over the center-field fence to rob him of a two-run homer and said, ''He shouldn't even call me anymore after that. That's ridiculous.'' . . . RAMIRO MENDOZA (right shoulder) will make a 50-pitch minor league rehabilitation start today and should join the Yankees this week in Minnesota.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
