<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Corporate Equity Offerings Planned for the Week</title>
    <meta content="24EQUI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217344"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000724T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E7DD123AF937A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1211" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Corporate Equity Offerings Planned for the Week</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The following equity and convertible debt offerings are expected this week:</p>
        <p>Account4.com Inc., Newton, Mass., an initial public offering of 4 million shares. Robinson-Humphrey Co.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The following equity and convertible debt offerings are expected this week:</p>
        <p>Account4.com Inc., Newton, Mass., an initial public offering of 4 million shares. Robinson-Humphrey Co.</p>
        <p>Applied Molecular Evolution Inc., San Diego, an initial public offering of 3.8 million shares. CIBC Wood Gundy.</p>
        <p>Arena Pharmaceuticals Inc., San Diego, an initial public offering of 5 million shares. ING Barings.</p>
        <p>Avici Systems Inc., North Billerca, Mass., an initial public offering of 6 million shares. Morgan Stanley Dean Witter.</p>
        <p>Blue Martini Software Inc., San Mateo, Calif., an initial public offering of 7.5 million shares. Goldman, Sachs &amp; Co.</p>
        <p>Camtek Ltd., Israel, an initial public offering of 5.6 million ordinary shares. CIBC Wood Gundy.</p>
        <p>Chiles Offshore L.L.C., Houston, an initial public offering of 8 million shares. CS First Boston.</p>
        <p>ClearWave N.V., Amsterdam, the Netherlands, an initial public offering of 10.6 million shares. Bear, Stearns &amp; Co. and Salomon Smith Barney.</p>
        <p>Coherent Inc., Santa Clara, Calif., 3 million shares. UBS Warburg.</p>
        <p>Convergent Group Corp., Englewood, Colo., an initial public offering of 6 million shares. Robertson Stephens.</p>
        <p>Corvis Corp., Columbia, Md., an initial public offering of 27.5 million shares. CS First Boston.</p>
        <p>Crown Castle International Corp., Houston, 11 million shares of the shelf. Goldman, Sachs &amp; Co. and CS First Boston.</p>
        <p>Digital United Holdings Ltd., Taiwan, an initial public offering of 10 million shares. Donaldson, Lufkin &amp; Jenrette.</p>
        <p>Discovery Partners International Inc., San Diego, an initial public offering of 5 million shares. Chase H&amp;Q.</p>
        <p>Evoke Communications Inc., Louisville, Colo., an initial public offering of 7 million shares. Salomon Smith Barney.</p>
        <p>Gemini Genomics P.L.C., Cambridge, England, an initial public offering of 6 million American depository shares; each A.D.S. represents two ordinary shares. SG Cowen.</p>
        <p>Genencor International Inc., Palo Alto, Calif., an initial public offering of 7 million shares. Merrill Lynch &amp; Co.</p>
        <p>GlobeSpan Inc., Red Bank, N.J., 8 million shares. Robertson Stephens and Morgan Stanley Dean Witter.</p>
        <p>Illumina Inc., San Diego, Calif., an initial public offering of 5 million shares. Goldman, Sachs &amp; Co.</p>
        <p>Interland Inc., Atlanta, an initial public offering of 5 million shares. Bear, Stearns &amp; Co.</p>
        <p>inTEST Corp., Cherry Hill, N.J., 2 million shares. Needham &amp; Co.</p>
        <p>IntraLinks Inc., New York, an initial public offering of 4.6 million shares. J.P. Morgan Securities.</p>
        <p>Keryx Biopharmaceuticals Inc., Jerusalem, an initial public offering of 4.6 million shares. Roth Capital Partners.</p>
        <p>Lattice Semiconductor Corp., Hillsboro, Ore., 4 million shares. Goldman, Sachs &amp; Co. and Morgan Stanley Dean Witter.</p>
        <p>Lexent Inc., New York, an initial public offering of 5.8 million shares. CS First Boston.</p>
        <p>Mainspring Communications Inc., Cambridge, Mass., an initial public offering of 3.5 million shares. Morgan Stanley Dean Witter.</p>
        <p>Nassau Broadcasting Corp., Princeton, N.J., an initial public offering of 12.4 million class A shares, 9.9 million in the United States and Canada. Merrill Lynch &amp; Co.</p>
        <p>Polycom Inc., Milpitas, Calif., 2.6 million shares. Morgan Stanley Dean Witter.</p>
        <p>RITA Medical Systems Inc., Mountain View, Calif., an initial public offering of 3.4 million shares. Salomon Smith Barney.</p>
        <p>Semitool Inc., Kalispell, Mont., 4.1 million shares. Bear, Stearns &amp; Co.</p>
        <p>Serono S.A., Geneva, an initial public offering of 77.9 million American depository shares; each A.D.S. represents one-fortieth of a bearer share. Merrill Lynch &amp; Co.</p>
        <p>SpectraSite Holdings Inc., Cary, N.C., 14.5 million shares. Morgan Stanley Dean Witter.</p>
        <p>Tripath Technology Inc., Santa Clara, Calif., an initial public offering of 7.5 million shares. Salomon Smith Barney.</p>
        <p>Tumbleweed Communications Corp., Redwood City, Calif., 3 million shares. CS First Boston.</p>
        <p>TyCom Ltd., Pembroke, Bermuda, an initial public offering of 43.5 million shares. Goldman, Sachs &amp; Co. and Salomon Smith Barney.</p>
        <p>ValiCert Inc., Mountain View, Calif., an initial public offering of 4 million shares. Deutsche Bank Alex. Brown and Merrill Lynch &amp; Co.</p>
        <p>WebEx Inc., San Jose, Calif., an initial public offering of 3.5 million shares. Goldman, Sachs &amp; Co.</p>
        <p>(Source: MCM EquityWatch.)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
