<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Caramoor's Annual Show Of Respect For Bel Canto</title>
    <meta content="24CARA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217364"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="OPERA REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Caramoor International Music Festival</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Orchestra of St Luke's/st Luke's Chamber Ensemble</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tommasini, Anthony</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bellini, Vincenzo (1801-35)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Crutchfield, Will</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Pirata, Il (Opera)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000724T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E5DC123AF937A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="760" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Caramoor's Annual Show Of Respect For Bel Canto</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY TOMMASINI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tommasini, Anthony</byline>
      <dateline>KATONAH, N.Y., July 22</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anthony Tommasini reviews performance of Bellini's Il Pirata, with Will Crutchfield conducting Orchestra of St Luke's at Caramoor International Music Festival, Katonah, NY; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Will Crutchfield may still be best known from his tenure as a music critic for The New York Times, from 1983 to 1989. He left daily journalism to become a vocal coach and conductor. But in taking up conducting, he was resuming an earlier career in music, which began when he was a rehearsal pianist and accompanist with the Virginia Opera Association.</p>
        <p>Don't expect to see him tackling the touchstone symphonic works of Mahler and Stravinsky. His more modest ambition was to champion operas from the Baroque era and especially the still-misunderstood early 19th-century period of Italian bel canto. Mr. Crutchfield brings vast knowledge and palpable involvement to this repertory, which is why ''Bel Canto at Caramoor,'' his annual concert performances of a bel canto opera at the Caramoor International Music Festival here, have become a summertime draw for opera lovers in the region.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Will Crutchfield may still be best known from his tenure as a music critic for The New York Times, from 1983 to 1989. He left daily journalism to become a vocal coach and conductor. But in taking up conducting, he was resuming an earlier career in music, which began when he was a rehearsal pianist and accompanist with the Virginia Opera Association.</p>
        <p>Don't expect to see him tackling the touchstone symphonic works of Mahler and Stravinsky. His more modest ambition was to champion operas from the Baroque era and especially the still-misunderstood early 19th-century period of Italian bel canto. Mr. Crutchfield brings vast knowledge and palpable involvement to this repertory, which is why ''Bel Canto at Caramoor,'' his annual concert performances of a bel canto opera at the Caramoor International Music Festival here, have become a summertime draw for opera lovers in the region.</p>
        <p>On Saturday night, with the Orchestra of St. Luke's and a cast headed by the promising young soprano Indra Thomas, Mr. Crutchfield presented Bellini's seldom-heard ''Il Pirata'' (''The Pirate''), and as usual it was a rewarding event. Bellini was a few days shy of 27 when ''Il Pirata'' received it premiere at La Scala in Milan in 1827.</p>
        <p>This is the third of the composer's 10 operas, but his first great one. It would be easy to dismiss its story of two warring royal houses in 13th-century Sicily as the stuff of typical Italian melodrama. Having driven his enemy Gualtiero away, Ernesto, the Duke of Caldora, forces the woman Gualtiero loves, Imogene, into marriage. Years later Gualtiero, now the head of a band of pirates, returns to Caldora to find Imogene the mournful mother of his rival's son. When he kills Ernesto in a duel, Imogene is driven to distraction, and in what would become a bel canto trademark the opera ends with a mad scene for the soprano.</p>
        <p>Still, this was Bellini's first work with the librettist who would become his dream collaborator, Felice Romani. Together they found in this material an affecting tale of resignation and pointless tragedy.</p>
        <p>Mr. Crutchfield is not the most nimble technician, although he is getting stronger in this regard, and the orchestra played with suppleness and clarity. Conductors who do not trust Bellini try to pump up the works with energy and drama. Mr. Crutchfield, wisely, let this refined score speak for itself, shaping the arching melodic lines with subtlety and unhurried elegance.</p>
        <p>For example there was great dignity in the scene in which Gualtiero, upon first seeing Imogene with her young son, hugs the boy, singing poignantly, ''I clasp him to my breast and yield him back to your sorrow.'' Lesser dramatists than Bellini and Romani would have had them hurling insults at each other.</p>
        <p>Ms. Thomas, who will sing the role of Liu in Puccini's ''Turandot'' at the Metropolitan Opera this fall, did not start off well. She essentially has a lustrous and rich voice, but she seems to need more technique to back it up. Sometimes her pitch wavered and her sound turned edgy. But as the performance went on, she gained in confidence and presence. And the mad scene was a triumph, especially its reflective first half, ''Col sorriso d'innocenza,'' in which Ms. Thomas's affinity for long-spun, slow melodic phrases was impressive. The audience awarded her a tremendous ovation.</p>
        <p>As Gualtiero, Francisco Almanza, a young tenor, was a late substitute for Bruce Fowler, who was indisposed. Though Mr. Almanza has the makings of a good tenor, he was clearly taxed by the role on this night. Still, he did able work in difficult circumstances. The baritone Daniel Mobbs was a sturdy-voiced Ernesto. Laura Danehower Whyte brought a lovely soprano sound to the smaller role of Adele, Imogene's companion. The chorus, which has a lot to do in this work, sang with robust tone and energy.</p>
        <p>Though ''Il Pirata'' was famously revived at La Scala in 1958 with Maria Callas and Franco Corelli in the leads, it is not often produced these days. Mr. Crutchfield was able to make a strong case for the work, which is exactly why he left criticism.</p>
        <p>OPERA REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
