<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>People</title>
    <meta content="MB235301" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217444"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING -- ADDENDA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Brann Worldwide</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Starlink (Co)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Fcb Worldwide</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hms Partners</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">sfm/media planning</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lauro, Patricia Winters</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eastham, Dennis</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gater, Chris</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">zasky, ken</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">weichselbaum, hart</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">anderson, dana</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schwalbe, Marty</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">dundas, ray</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Solomon, Jerry</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Advertising (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Addenda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000724T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E0DF133AF937A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="846" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>People</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Patricia Winters Lauro</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lauro, Patricia Winters</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Roundup of advertising industry executive changes: president and chief operating officer Dennis Eastham is named to added post of chief executive of Brann Worldwide, succeeding Chris Gater, who continues as chairman; Starlink names Ken Zasky chief operating officer, new post; FCB Worldwide's Chicago office names Hart Weichselbaum executive vice president and account planning director; he succeeds Dana Anderson, named managing director at office; HMS Partners names Marty Schwalbe to new post of executive vice president and director for brand strategy; SFM/Media Planning names Ray Dundas executive vice president and director for national broadcast; he succeeds Jerry Solomon, who left (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>* Dennis Eastham, president and chief operating officer at Brann Worldwide, Deerfield, Ill., part of Snyder Communications, was named chief executive, succeeding Chris Gater, who continues as chairman.  * Ken Zasky, vice president and business director at StarLink, Chicago, was named to the new post of chief operating officer. StarLink is part of the Starcom MediaVest Group, owned by the B Com3  Group.  * Hart Weichselbaum was named executive vice president and director for account planning at the Chicago office of FCB Worldwide, part of True North Communications. He succeeds Dana Anderson, who was promoted to managing director at the office. Mr. Weichselbaum had been planning director at the Richards Group, Dallas.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>* Dennis Eastham, president and chief operating officer at Brann Worldwide, Deerfield, Ill., part of Snyder Communications, was named chief executive, succeeding Chris Gater, who continues as chairman.  * Ken Zasky, vice president and business director at StarLink, Chicago, was named to the new post of chief operating officer. StarLink is part of the Starcom MediaVest Group, owned by the B Com3  Group.  * Hart Weichselbaum was named executive vice president and director for account planning at the Chicago office of FCB Worldwide, part of True North Communications. He succeeds Dana Anderson, who was promoted to managing director at the office. Mr. Weichselbaum had been planning director at the Richards Group, Dallas.</p>
        <p>* Marty Schwalbe was named to the new position of executive vice president and director for brand strategy at HMS Partners, Columbus, Ohio. He had been executive vice president and corporate director for strategy and convergence at Fahlgren, Dublin, Ohio.  * David Marans was named to the new post of media research director at Mindshare, New York, the media services joint venture of two WPP Group units, Ogilvy &amp; Mather and J. Walter Thompson. He had been head of the Thompson media research group.  * Kristine Barakat was named to the new post of director for new business development at Razorfish, New York. She had most recently been director for international marketing at Frank N. Magid Associates, London.  * Christopher Ross, international account director at DDB Worldwide, New York, part of the Omnicom Group, was named to the new post of general manager at the New York office of DDB Digital Worldwide.  * Ray Dundas, executive vice president for network negotiations at SFM/Media Planning, New York, part of the Media Planning Group division of Havas Advertising, was named executive vice president and director for national broadcast. He succeeds Jerry Solomon, who left. SFM/Media Planning is the new name for what had been SFM Media.  * David Rockland was named senior vice president and global director at the Ketchum Reputation Laboratory, New York, a new unit of the Ketchum division of the Omnicom Group, focusing on the connection between corporate reputation and business performance. Mr. Rockland had been senior vice president and managing director at Roper Starch Worldwide, Washington.  * Allan Infeld, vice president for advertising sales at the MTVi Group, New York, part of the MTV Networks unit of Viacom Inc., was named senior vice president for advertising sales. He succeeds Peggy Mansfield, who left to become general manager at TeenPeople.com, New York, part of the People Group at Time Inc., a unit of Time Warner.</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING -- ADDENDA</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
