<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TECHNOLOGY: The Real Foundation Of the Software World; Behind-the-Scenes Programmers Are Bricklayers of Internet Economy</title>
    <meta content="24DEVE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217352"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shortages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lohr, Steve</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/World Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shortages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000724T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E3DD123AF937A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1888" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TECHNOLOGY: The Real Foundation Of the Software World; Behind-the-Scenes Programmers Are Bricklayers of Internet Economy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVE LOHR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lohr, Steve</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Big computer software companies seek to woo outside programmers to use their software tools and technology as software industry again has up-for-grabs feel of early days of personal computer industry; want to supply 'platforms' on which large numbers of programmers for old-line companies will develop software applications for Internet; graph of shortage of qualified applicants for technology jobs; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gazing out at the nearly 7,000 software developers assembled in Orlando two weeks ago, William H. Gates recalled how much things had changed since his company, Microsoft, was founded in 1975. Back then, he said, there were fewer people in the software industry than had gathered that morning in the cavernous convention center. ''It was a tiny, tiny business,'' recalled Mr. Gates, Microsoft's chairman.</p>
        <p>Software, to be sure, is a big business today. But in many ways, it once again has the up-for-grabs feel of the early days of the personal computer industry, before Microsoft became the dominant force. And that is why big companies like Microsoft, I.B.M., Oracle and Sun Microsystems are spending so much time, energy and money these days trying to woo outside programmers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gazing out at the nearly 7,000 software developers assembled in Orlando two weeks ago, William H. Gates recalled how much things had changed since his company, Microsoft, was founded in 1975. Back then, he said, there were fewer people in the software industry than had gathered that morning in the cavernous convention center. ''It was a tiny, tiny business,'' recalled Mr. Gates, Microsoft's chairman.</p>
        <p>Software, to be sure, is a big business today. But in many ways, it once again has the up-for-grabs feel of the early days of the personal computer industry, before Microsoft became the dominant force. And that is why big companies like Microsoft, I.B.M., Oracle and Sun Microsystems are spending so much time, energy and money these days trying to woo outside programmers.</p>
        <p>''It's nice to be in demand, and in a satisfying profession that has turned out to be fairly lucrative,'' observed Basim Kadhim, a 29-year-old programmer who telecommutes from Bend, Ore., to Silicon Valley.</p>
        <p>The corporate campaigns are a sign that the industry is entering ''a disruptive new era of opportunity in software,'' according to Richard Doherty, president of Envisioneering, a technology research firm.</p>
        <p>The opportunity lies in building all the software needed to make the promise of Internet commerce a reality. So far, e-commerce is in its infancy, rarely going beyond browsing the Web and executing some rudimentary transaction, like buying books online or ordering office supplies on an in-house corporate Web site. And the information is still typed by hand on a computer keyboard.</p>
        <p>But for software developers like Mr. Kadhim, the goal is to help build a far smarter Internet, where most exchanges of information would be automated. Before long, for example, information from the purchasing department of a carmaker might be shuttled automatically to and from the accounting department of a parts supplier. Most steps in a transaction would be computer-to-computer communication, eliminating mounds of paperwork and hours of human toil.</p>
        <p>Or a person's cell phone or Palm-like device might be able to automatically match his calendar with the doctor's schedule, suggesting times for a check-up. Thousands of similar labor-saving uses will add up to the next generation of e-commerce, representing the real payoff from the Internet -- both in terms of personal convenience and economic productivity.</p>
        <p>Software will make it happen. And most of the work will be done not by engineers at the big software houses like Microsoft, I.B.M. and Oracle, but by the 80 percent of programmers who labor, often in relative obscurity, at old-line companies, Web site contractors, computer consultants and elsewhere.</p>
        <p>Such programmers are in demand because they are the ones who write all the handcrafted software programs that keep the nation's computer-dependent economy running. And many thousands of them now face the task of bringing brick-and-mortar businesses into the future. They are the bricklayers of the Internet economy.</p>
        <p>This army of behind-the-scenes programmers will largely determine who the big software winners will be in this, the Internet era of computing.</p>
        <p>Today, companies that include Microsoft, I.B.M., Sun, Oracle, BEA, Hewlett-Packard and others are scrambling to establish their software tools and technology as ''platforms,'' or environments, in which large numbers of programmers will want to develop software applications for the Web. The stakes are high. The market for such e-commerce platform software, according to some analysts' projections, could grow to as much as $100 billion over the next decade.</p>
        <p>No one expects any single supplier to become as powerful as Microsoft has been in personal computing, because Internet computing is such a diverse milieu, with many of the key technology standards in the public domain. But the PC era proved the importance of attracting developers. Today, many technologists still believe Apple's Macintosh and I.B.M.'s OS/2 were better operating systems than Microsoft's Windows. But Microsoft lured far more developers to write applications for Windows.</p>
        <p>''A platform is an ecosystem,'' noted Charles Fitzgerald, director of business development in the developer division at Microsoft. ''And there are a few thousand people at Microsoft whose job it is to help developers.''</p>
        <p>Microsoft plans to spend $2 billion over the next three years on the tools and training to help software developers build Web applications using Microsoft technology. I.B.M. also puts a $2 billion price tag on its three-year Internet software initiative intended to lure developers to its camp. Other companies are also spending heavily to win over developers.</p>
        <p>''Software developers are a hot commodity today, and they increasingly drive platform decisions within companies,'' explained Valerie Olague, who is leading the I.B.M. program. ''We can only be successful if we attract developers.''</p>
        <p>As a group, the developers seem beyond the reach of conventional salesmanship. They are the kind of people who cultivate deep intellectual interests in particular fields like Japanese animation and science fiction, according to research done for I.B.M. by Renegade, a marketing firm. They share the mindset that drives a person to stay up all night to solve the puzzle of a few buggy lines of programming code.</p>
        <p>Certainly, at industry events, developers want to do more than drink and dance. So I.B.M. is sponsoring gatherings in cities including New York, Seattle and San Francisco, which feature talks by renowned Internet programmers and team coding contests with hand-held computers as prizes.</p>
        <p>There is no hard sell. The goal is primarily to prompt the developers to go to I.B.M.'s Web site, because increasingly, company Web sites and specialist sites like Slashdot (''News for Nerds'') are where developers  hang out, exchange tips and download software to try out.</p>
        <p>Developers seem most impressed by the simple beauty of code that works. At the Microsoft Developers Conference in Orlando recently, the crowd yawned when Microsoft executives talked of the company's Internet vision. They clapped politely for the slick videos and chuckled at the early morning warm-up routine of the comedian Richard Jeni, who began, ''I couldn't be more excited to be here if I knew what you guys did for a living.''</p>
        <p>But the rousing applause came for a string of programming code, written partly in the hot new Internet standard, XML -- for Extensible Markup Language -- that was projected onto giant blue screens and performed precisely as it was supposed to.</p>
        <p>Software programming is problem solving, and developers tend to gravitate to the technology that is the most useful for the task at hand. The young developer from Oregon, Mr. Kadhim, speaks of the appeal of software as a kind of infinitely malleable medium for technical artistry. ''You get a rush when you build something and make it work,'' he said. ''It's like cracking a puzzle.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kadhim has a Ph.D. in computer science, and he is fluent in programming languages including Basic, Cobol, C, C++, Java and Linux. He calls himself a ''Linux lover,'' referring to a version of the Unix operating system that is distributed free over the Internet and is regarded as a threat to Microsoft's Windows.</p>
        <p>Yet in January, Mr. Kadhim joined Fujitsu Software, which makes specialized software tools for Cobol programmers. And he was in Orlando at the Microsoft conference, demonstrating how some of Microsoft's new technology can bring applications written in Cobol, a 40-year-old programming language still widely used in business, onto the Web.</p>
        <p>''I'm doing this because it's a challenging software engineering problem -- how do you bring so much of the old world into the future?'' he said. ''So far, most of the Web development amounts to toy applications, interesting but not yet hooked to the core of our economy. And Cobol, whether you like it or not, is at the heart of our economy.''</p>
        <p>In New York, Elaine Power manages a group of two dozen programmers at Organic, a Web site builder and consultant. Ms. Power, 36, got a taste for computers as a teenager in Britain when she wrote a program in BASIC, a simple programming language, that sent a digital ball bouncing around the screen of her brother's personal computer. The fascination was enough to prompt her to major in computer science in college and eventually learn computer languages ranging from Fortran to Java.</p>
        <p>Most of the young engineers she works with today program in Java, an Internet programming language developed by Sun Microsystems. They see it as the programming language of the moment, and a skill of the future. ''Programmers can be very religious about their platform and their tools,'' Ms. Power said.</p>
        <p>But experienced programmers tend to value flexibility rather than religion because the field moves so quickly. In the 1960's, after all, Cobol was the hot programming language, the skill of the future.</p>
        <p>''Being a good programmer is a lot like being a good carpenter,'' said Tim Howes, chief technology officer of Loudcloud, a start-up founded by Mr. Howes and three other former executives of Netscape, the Internet pioneer. ''You should have a breadth of knowledge and know when to use the appropriate tool -- when to use your hammer, your saw and your screw driver.''</p>
        <p>Today, many companies are using a variety of tools when building Web applications rather than becoming overly dependent on any single technology supplier.</p>
        <p>Last year, a group of longtime Silicon Valley software developers founded Liquidprice, a reverse-auction Web service, which allows electronics retailers and auto dealers to bid for the business of individual consumers on the basis of where they live and what products they want. To run the service, Liquidprice, based in Cupertino, Calif., deploys a smorgasbord of software -- Oracle for the database, Microsoft for its Web servers, Java as its main programming language, and I.B.M.'s Websphere as the development environment for its specialized Web applications.</p>
        <p>At each tier, says Piyush Gupta, the president and co-founder, the company has insured that it can quickly switch to other suppliers. The trickiest one to abandon would presumably be its Web development software, Websphere. Still, it is a tentative win indeed for I.B.M. in the emerging market for Web development software. Liquidprice engineers have written a thin layer of code intended to isolate the company's in-house applications from the I.B.M. software.</p>
        <p>''The day Websphere doesn't satisfy me, we'll switch,'' Mr. Gupta said. ''For the smart developers, the world of being locked in to any one software vendor is over.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
