<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Campaign at Midsummer</title>
    <meta content="24MON1$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217399"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000724T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEFD9123AF937A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="674" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Campaign at Midsummer</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial says that presidential campaign seems destined to be remembered as contest between student-body president and an amiable slacker and that contrasting images suggest nation is in for an even harsher campaign than anyone expected; says race is much more competitive than it appeared only weeks ago (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Already it has become the campaign that people like to complain about. Why isn't Vice President Al Gore less leaden and more popular within his own party? What does Gov. George W. Bush really mean by compassionate conservatism, and does he know enough to be president? Whoever wins, about half of the American people will blame the news media either for giving Mr. Gore a free ride on his campaign fund-raising past or for not quizzing Mr. Bush hard enough about foreign policy.</p>
        <p>Part of the whinging about the available choices is a habit that became deeply embedded in late-20th-century politics. Candidates were either too much a part of the Washington crowd (Richard Nixon, Walter Mondale) or too provincial and untested (Jimmy Carter, Ronald Reagan, Bill Clinton). And part of this year's complaining has to do with the dynastic resumes of the two candidates and the striking, almost archetypal contrast between their personalities. This election is destined to be remembered as a contest between an aspiring student-body president and an amiable slacker, to paraphrase an incisive description by The Times's Maureen Dowd.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Already it has become the campaign that people like to complain about. Why isn't Vice President Al Gore less leaden and more popular within his own party? What does Gov. George W. Bush really mean by compassionate conservatism, and does he know enough to be president? Whoever wins, about half of the American people will blame the news media either for giving Mr. Gore a free ride on his campaign fund-raising past or for not quizzing Mr. Bush hard enough about foreign policy.</p>
        <p>Part of the whinging about the available choices is a habit that became deeply embedded in late-20th-century politics. Candidates were either too much a part of the Washington crowd (Richard Nixon, Walter Mondale) or too provincial and untested (Jimmy Carter, Ronald Reagan, Bill Clinton). And part of this year's complaining has to do with the dynastic resumes of the two candidates and the striking, almost archetypal contrast between their personalities. This election is destined to be remembered as a contest between an aspiring student-body president and an amiable slacker, to paraphrase an incisive description by The Times's Maureen Dowd.</p>
        <p>These contrasting images are firmly fixed in the public perception, and they point us toward some reasons that with the convening of the Republican convention on July 31, we are going to see an even harsher campaign than anyone expected. The crowning reason for this is that the race is much more competitive than it appeared a few weeks ago. Even though Mr. Gore has been struggling, the national polls last week closed to within a couple of points. And as Richard Berke and Adam Clymer showed in an electoral-vote analysis in The Times on Friday, the contest looks even closer when viewed as a showdown for a handful of swing states including Michigan, Missouri, Florida, Illinois, Ohio, New Jersey and Pennsylvania. Slim margins in a few crucial states produce mean campaigns.</p>
        <p>But that is only part of the story. The personalities of the candidates and their strategic imperatives also play a role. The Bush campaign has to sell a candidate whom people like but view as untested and too much a product of easy street. The Gore campaign has to promote a candidate with plenty of baggage and a considerable ability to irritate people, even within his party's core constituencies. If likability and baggage are allowed to remain key issues, Mr. Gore suffers. If experience and policy expertise come to the fore, Mr. Bush gets in trouble, a key reason for Mr. Gore's renewed assault on the governor's record in Texas.</p>
        <p>If a contest becomes focused on pocketbook concerns, social issues and ideology, voters tend to scurry back to their home parties. Suburban Republicans really do like tax cuts. Pro-choice women really do have to worry about what a Bush victory would do to the Supreme Court. Mr. Gore needs a big Democratic homecoming, since vice presidents running to keep their parties in power have a hard time attracting crossover voters. In practical terms, that means Mr. Gore needs to have his current poll number, around 41 percent, up to 47 to 49 percent by Election Day. Political professionals will be watching Mr. Bush's post-convention polls to assess the bounce he gets from his television time and his carefully orchestrated vice-presidential search. In the run-up to the election, the most striking point of agreement between strategists in both parties is that the winner will have a very narrow margin. The outcome may depend on whether the fervent Mr. Gore or the more laid-back Mr. Bush is better at making voters comfortable with personal images that are firmly and probably unalterably fixed in the public consciousness.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
