<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Possible Terrorist Links Sting Quiet Neighborhood</title>
    <meta content="Y24RAI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217396"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Lebanon</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hezbollah</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Firestone, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hammoud, Mohammed Youssef</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Lebanon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Lebanon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000724T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E3D9123AF937A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1051" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Possible Terrorist Links Sting Quiet Neighborhood</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID FIRESTONE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Firestone, David</byline>
      <dateline>CHARLOTTE, N.C., July 23</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Arrest of Mohammed Youssef Hammoud and 17 other people charged with conspiracy to smuggle cigarettes and send profits to support Hezbollah, radical Islamic group, unsettles people in Charlotte, NC, where Hammoud lived; government charges Hammoud was leader of support group, whose members met regularly in his home and elsewhere to denounce US and collect money that was sent to organization in Lebanon (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The meetings would always start after dark. Three nights a week, as the stream of cars turned onto the residential street and parked, the neighbors would start wondering all over again: what was going on inside that house?</p>
        <p>It had a basketball goal and a barbecue grill, and appeared to be an unremarkable two-story emblem of suburban conformity except for those strange gatherings that lasted past the normal bedtime of Donnefield Drive. By breakfast, all the cars were gone.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The meetings would always start after dark. Three nights a week, as the stream of cars turned onto the residential street and parked, the neighbors would start wondering all over again: what was going on inside that house?</p>
        <p>It had a basketball goal and a barbecue grill, and appeared to be an unremarkable two-story emblem of suburban conformity except for those strange gatherings that lasted past the normal bedtime of Donnefield Drive. By breakfast, all the cars were gone.</p>
        <p>''We all had theories,'' said Scott Furr, who lives across the street. ''My girlfriend thought they were religious meetings, because she thought she heard some singing. Some people thought it was drugs. But I just thought it was a party house, where they got together and had a good time. Boy, were we wrong.''</p>
        <p>The mystery was solved on Friday, when the owner of the house was arrested, with 17 other people, and charged with being part of a conspiracy to smuggle cigarettes and send the profits to Hezbollah, the radical Islamic group based in Lebanon. The federal government said the homeowner, Mohammed Youssef Hammoud, was the leader of a Hezbollah support group that met regularly in his home and elsewhere to denounce the United States and collect money that was sent to the organization in Lebanon.</p>
        <p>Because the State Department lists Hezbollah as a terrorist group, Mr. Hammoud and several of those arrested were charged with, among other things, providing aid to a foreign terrorist organization. It is one of the first major arrests under the antiterrorism law passed in 1996 in the wake of the 1995 bombing in Oklahoma City.</p>
        <p>None of those arrested were charged with planning violent acts, but the possible presence of a Hezbollah group on a quiet street in Charlotte -- a financial capital that lacks even the slightest trace of intrigue or subversion -- was oddly unsettling to residents here.</p>
        <p>''It doesn't make any sense to me,'' said Dwayne Eldridge, another neighbor of Mr. Hammoud. ''I mean, we thought they were strange because they didn't wave back or talk to anybody on the block. But that doesn't mean we thought they were helping terrorists or anything. I guess you never really know your neighbors.''</p>
        <p>One possible explanation for the group's presence here may lie in the nature of the charges against its members.</p>
        <p>According to an affidavit filed by United States Attorney Mark T. Calloway in Federal District Court here on Friday, the group raised money by buying large quantities of cigarettes in North Carolina, where the tax is only five cents a pack, and smuggling them to Michigan, where the price of cigarettes is much higher because of the 75-cent state tax. The 70-cent profit on each pack produced hundreds of thousands of dollars that, the government charged, was helping to finance Hezbollah activities.</p>
        <p>''With one load of illegal cigarettes in a panel van, you can make a profit of $8,000 to $10,000,'' said Earl Woodham, a spokesman for the Charlotte office of the federal Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco and Firearms.</p>
        <p>Those arrested will be able to enter formal pleas to the charges at hearings beginning on Wednesday. At least six of the 18 were released on  bond over the weekend.</p>
        <p>In Beirut on Saturday, Hezbollah issued a statement denying that it had any ties to those who were arrested or to any other ''organizational structures'' in the United States. Several Muslims who showed up this weekend at the Cedars Lebanese Restaurant and grocery store in Charlotte -- only to find it had been shut down by the government as a money-laundering front for the group -- insisted that those arrested had nothing to do with Hezbollah.</p>
        <p>A man who identified himself only as Ahmed said he was a friend of some of the suspects. Brandishing the business cards of two Federal Bureau of Investigation agents as proof, he said his home had been searched by agents on Friday before he was allowed to go. He said the only money sent to Lebanon by those arrested went to relatives or to legitimate charities.</p>
        <p>''They are only doing this because we are Arabs and this is not an Arab place,'' he said. ''I know the people in this store. They are regular businessmen who would never smuggle cigarettes or get involved with terrorism. The F.B.I. took the Koran from my home. It just shows the real reason they are doing this.'' In the store window, tongs were dripping with crumbs next to a pan of baklava.</p>
        <p>Around the corner, at the only other store here that sells halal meat, approved for use by orthodox Muslims, patrons said several thousand Muslims lived in the area, only a small portion of whom were Lebanese. No one in the store said they believed the charges were true, and several said the civil liberties of the suspects had been violated.</p>
        <p>When the antiterrorism law was passed, civil libertarians said they were concerned that the law infringed on free speech and free association. Damon Camp, an associate professor of criminal justice at Georgia State University in Atlanta who specializes in domestic terrorism, said that prosecutions under the law have been rare, and this could provide an interesting test case if the defendants challenge that charge.</p>
        <p>He noted, however, that the suspects were also charged with cigarette smuggling, a more routine crime that does not raise the same civil liberties issues.</p>
        <p>An interesting twist in this case is the group's extensive use of computers, several of which were seized as evidence. Mr. Eldridge, the neighbor of Mr. Hammoud, said he saw five desktop computers removed from the house, and an empty Dell computer carton was in the garbage can outside the house. The affidavit, citing confidential sources, said that Mr. Hammoud downloaded speeches and songs from Hezbollah sites on the Internet to use at the meetings.</p>
        <p>Another man charged on Friday, Said Mohammed Harb, was accused of running a fraudulent Web site design business that had done so well he recently bought a $36,000 BMW and a Lincoln Navigator.</p>
        <p>A source ''believes this business is fraudulent, and involves the theft of credit card numbers, but Harb is being extremely secretive about it,'' the affidavit said. ''The business is called Digital Karma.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
