<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Tale So Tall That It Might Even Be True (Or Nearly)</title>
    <meta content="24CARD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217343"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BRIDGE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bridge (Card Game)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Truscott, Alan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Crossword and Games/Bridge</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bridge (Card Game)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000724T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E7DD123AF937A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="587" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Tale So Tall That It Might Even Be True (Or Nearly)</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Alan Truscott</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Truscott, Alan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alan Truscott bridge column on perhaps mythical tale of hand once played at Manhattan bridge club; diagram (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When the Cavendish Club was on East 74th Street in Manhattan and near the end of its existence, one of the regulars was Baron Munchausen, a distant relative of the legendary Teutonic teller of tall tales. He claims to have held the South hand in a money game and heard his right-hand opponent open seven spades.</p>
        <p>This was a situation, as close to unique as one could be, in which a player could pinpoint an opposing hand exactly after hearing one bid. East was a sound bidder, so the only hand he could have, given South's holding, was a singleton club ace and 12 solid spades.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When the Cavendish Club was on East 74th Street in Manhattan and near the end of its existence, one of the regulars was Baron Munchausen, a distant relative of the legendary Teutonic teller of tall tales. He claims to have held the South hand in a money game and heard his right-hand opponent open seven spades.</p>
        <p>This was a situation, as close to unique as one could be, in which a player could pinpoint an opposing hand exactly after hearing one bid. East was a sound bidder, so the only hand he could have, given South's holding, was a singleton club ace and 12 solid spades.</p>
        <p>That meant that West was void in spades and would not know what to lead against seven no-trump. Full of his customary bravado, Munchausen made that bid and was doubled on his right.</p>
        <p>The spotlight was now on West, who was somewhat dazed by an auction that he, like the rest of the world, had never heard before. The Lightner double, asking for an unusual lead, did not seem to offer any guidance in this situation.</p>
        <p>Leading one's long suit against no-trump is standard, and it was right here for a reason that was far from obvious. East would not have doubled holding 13 spades, so he had to have an ace. If it was a red ace, the contract was almost sure to be defeated with any lead. The chance that the declarer would take 13 tricks in clubs and one of the red suits was negligible.</p>
        <p>So West should have led a club, which would have given the defense 13 tricks and a penalty of 3,500. Instead he did not reason correctly and led the diamond jack. Munchausen, finding exactly the dummy he needed, quickly gathered in six diamond tricks and seven heart tricks, scoring 1,790.</p>
        <p>''That is new to me,'' declared Munchausen thoughtfully. ''A grand slam for either side that depends on the opening lead.''</p>
        <p>The Baron asserts that the player in the East seat was Jack Dreyfus, who is as well known in the private world of rubber bridge as he is in the public world of finance. He now had to suffer some weird advice from Munchausen.</p>
        <p>''You should have made a lead-directing opening bid of one club,'' he suggested, ''and then bid seven spades. That would have guarded against the actual situation and prevented me from brilliantly bidding seven no-trump.''</p>
        <p>Dreyfus might have replied that one club could end the bidding, an event that was very slightly more likely than the deal itself. But his reply is not on record, nor do we know what he had to say about his partner's opening lead. There is, indeed, no certainty that he was in the club at all that day.</p>
        <p>A friendly merger is about to reduce the number of clubs in the New York metropolitan area by one. Beginning on Wednesday, the Bridge Haven Club in Queens will be absorbed by the FrankLin Club in Franklin Square on Long Island, with a full program of duplicate games, rubber bridge, instruction and backgammon. The managers will be Frank Allison, Lin Fisher, Keith Garber and Michael Benjamin. Information: (516) 483-5918.</p>
        <p>BRIDGE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
