<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; Wanted: Better Luck, And Better Players</title>
    <meta content="Y24ARAT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217381"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Davis Cup</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Spain</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Araton, Harvey</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcenroe, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Spain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Harvey Araton</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Spain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Davis Cup</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000724T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E2DB123AF937A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="855" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; Wanted: Better Luck, And Better Players</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HARVEY ARATON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Araton, Harvey</byline>
      <dateline>SANTANDER, Spain</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Harvey Araton Sports of The Times column on Spain's victory over US in Davis Cup competition; US team captain John McEnroe comments (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>JOHN McENROE believed that he had inherited a sure thing, ''two of the best players that ever lived,'' for his first go-round as the United States Davis Cup captain. He finished the year here yesterday with, for all intents and purposes, an expansion team.</p>
        <p>He can't open his wallet, like George Steinbrenner, and buy himself a champion. There is no salary cap to finagle. Being the big-market team, or the global superpower, doesn't help when your most potent weapons disarm themselves. If Pete Sampras and Andre Agassi couldn't be counted on for McEnroe's debut season, there is no reason to expect them to join him under stressful scheduling conditions next time around.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>JOHN McENROE believed that he had inherited a sure thing, ''two of the best players that ever lived,'' for his first go-round as the United States Davis Cup captain. He finished the year here yesterday with, for all intents and purposes, an expansion team.</p>
        <p>He can't open his wallet, like George Steinbrenner, and buy himself a champion. There is no salary cap to finagle. Being the big-market team, or the global superpower, doesn't help when your most potent weapons disarm themselves. If Pete Sampras and Andre Agassi couldn't be counted on for McEnroe's debut season, there is no reason to expect them to join him under stressful scheduling conditions next time around.</p>
        <p>Next year, eight of the potential World Group opponents would have home-soil advantage against the United States, and two others are yet to be determined by coin flip. Good luck getting Sampras to Moscow, Agassi to Prague.</p>
        <p>In other words, what we saw here this weekend, a 5-0 semifinal Spanish breeze for a date in December's final against Australia, is what we've got.</p>
        <p>''What can I tell you?'' McEnroe said, after Spain swept the meaningless reverse singles, with Juan Balcells rallying to defeat Jan-Michael Gambill, 1-6, 7-6 (2), 6-4, after Juan Carlos Ferrero outlasted Vince Spadea, 4-6, 6-1, 6-4. ''That's Davis Cup right now. Andre wasn't here. Pete's not here. Chang doesn't want to play. Courier retired. I'm totally spent. I'm not sure if it's emotional or not, but I'm about to heave.''</p>
        <p>Like most tennis rides McEnroe has taken, Davis Cup 2000 was a roller coaster, until it derailed and crashed in this coastal resort city. He came into the job with a well-deserved reputation for volatility, so, of course, his every word and move were scrutinized, sometimes to absurdity. Newspapers here belabored his accidentally knocking a camera from a child's hand.</p>
        <p>Well behaved is not generally a description that fits McEnroe, but he did avoid international incident, created no scenes here with linesmen or umpires and made a point of congratulating the Spanish players after every depressing match. Yet McEnroe, who has seldom raised an issue and then conceded it had two sides, also came to grips with an important lesson these past six months that coaches and captains must inevitably learn.</p>
        <p>It's not about him.</p>
        <p>''Obviously one of the reasons I was hired was so I would make a difference in getting players to play,'' he said earlier in the week. ''I clearly haven't succeeded.''</p>
        <p>In the final analysis, at least for this year, McEnroe was no more empowered, or effective, than were his predecessors. He was certainly edgier and more interesting than Tom Gullikson. His celebrity and personality raised the team's visibility. But even his knack for the well-timed sound bite may work against him.</p>
        <p>He straddles a dangerous line, balancing roles as a well-received commentator and Davis Cup captain. On television, among other places, McEnroe feels compelled to speak his mind. If Todd Martin chokes at Wimbledon, it's McEnroe's job to say it. If there are questions about the extent of Sampras's injury, it's his job to ask them.</p>
        <p>Subtlety, unfortunately, has never been his style.</p>
        <p>''When Sampras loses, he's hurt. When he wins, you stink,'' McEnroe wrote in his London newspaper column earlier this month. At the same time, he was still campaigning, hoping, for Sampras to join him here.</p>
        <p>Sampras, not surprisingly, won Wimbledon and went home. Agassi, not wanting to risk his United States Open chances, phoned in the report of a fender bender from Las Vegas. McEnroe brought the junior varsity and the United States was swept.</p>
        <p>''We'll have to wait and see next year,'' said McEnroe, who has an out on his three-year contract but is insisting he will not overreact. ''I'd like to think it's bad luck.''</p>
        <p>The luck of the draw is one thing, the arbitrary nature of Davis Cup. McEnroe's real problem is bad timing. He has become captain when there are no rising American stars, no highly ranked players in their early 20's, before they become too big, too independent to blow him off.</p>
        <p>Chris Woodruff, who won the fifth match that saved McEnroe from a first-round embarrassment in Harare, Zimbabwe, in February, is 27. Spadea, another journeyman, is 26. The 23-year-old Gambill, the Wimbledon quarterfinalist, is being touted as the future. He coughed up the fifth match, to Balcells, the match ending in a swirling rain, and under a rumbling sky.</p>
        <p>McEnroe could always be counted on to bring thunder to tennis, but his team succumbed meekly and he left quietly, skipping a news conference (a fine is possible) and telephoning news of his bout with nausea on the ride to the airport in Bilbao.</p>
        <p>Other than Chicago for another seniors event, it's difficult to know where Captain McEnroe goes from here.</p>
        <p>''It's been disappointing, no question,'' he said earlier. ''But you let it sink in, dwell on the positive, the wins instead of the losses.''</p>
        <p>Bottom-line translation: he'll always have Harare.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
