<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>DEUTSCHE TELEKOM TO PAY $50 BILLION FOR U.S. COMPANY</title>
    <meta content="24PHON" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Front Page; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217419"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cellular Telephones</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Foreign Investments</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Germany</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Deutsche Telekom</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Voicestream Wireless Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sorkin, Andrew Ross</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Romero, Simon</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cellular Telephones</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Investments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000724T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E4D6123AF937A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1451" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>DEUTSCHE TELEKOM TO PAY $50 BILLION FOR U.S. COMPANY</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW ROSS SORKIN and SIMON ROMERO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sorkin, Andrew Ross; Romero, Simon</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Deutsche Telekom agrees to acquire VoiceStream Wireless Corp, upstart American cellular communications company, for $50,7 billion, despite political opposition in Washington; will reportedly pay equivalent of $195 per share, more than double company's stock price only two months ago; deal, if completed would be first acquisition of American telecommunications company by corporation in which foreign government holds controlling stake; VoiceStream, year-old company with 2.3 million subscribers, is still not profitable, but its rapid growth and scope of its network, with potential to reach 70 percent of US population, makes it attractive to Deutsche Telekom, which has long sought foothold in US telecommunications; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Despite political opposition in Washington, Germany's largest telephone company, Deutsche Telekom, agreed last night to acquire an upstart American cellular communications company, the VoiceStream Wireless Corporation, for $50.7 billion.</p>
        <p>The deal, if completed, would be the first acquisition of a telecommunications company in the United States by a corporation in which a  foreign government holds a controlling stake.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Despite political opposition in Washington, Germany's largest telephone company, Deutsche Telekom, agreed last night to acquire an upstart American cellular communications company, the VoiceStream Wireless Corporation, for $50.7 billion.</p>
        <p>The deal, if completed, would be the first acquisition of a telecommunications company in the United States by a corporation in which a  foreign government holds a controlling stake.</p>
        <p>Only a year old and still not profitable, VoiceStream, with more than 2.3 million subscribers, is the nation's eighth-largest wireless company -- far smaller than the leader, Verizon Wireless, which has 25.9 million subscribers.</p>
        <p>But VoiceStream's rapid growth and the geographic scope of its network, with the potential to reach 70 percent of the United States population, make it attractive to Deutsche Telekom, whose chairman, Ron Sommer, has long sought a foothold in  United States telecommunications.</p>
        <p>Executives for both companies were still meeting with their bankers and lawyers last night and were not available for comment.</p>
        <p>But people involved in the deal said Deutsche Telekom had agreed to pay the equivalent of $195 a share -- more than double the stock's price only two months ago. The shares, whose price has risen in recent weeks on speculation of a takeover, closed Friday at $149.75.</p>
        <p>Even if the deal is blocked by political opposition or falls apart for other reasons, Deutsche Telekom  has separately promised to make a $5 billion cash investment in Voice Stream. That investment is meant to enable VoiceStream to bid aggressively in the auctions the Federal Communications Commission plans to hold in September for licenses for a new generation of mobile telephones.</p>
        <p>If the merger does not go through, the $5 billion investment would still give Deutsche Telekom a 10 percent stake in VoiceStream, which is based in Bellevue, Wash., and was founded by a longtime cellular industry executive, John W. Stanton, who is the company's chief executive.</p>
        <p>But the merger is far from a certainty. In recent weeks lawmakers in both the Senate and House, anticipating a move by Deutsche Telekom, introduced legislation with the intent of preventing the German company from acquiring an American telephone company. And last week the chairman of the Federal Communications Commission, citing those concerns, said any telecommunications deal involving a foreign government-owned company would face heavy scrutiny.</p>
        <p>The Deutsche Telekom-Voice Stream deal would bring the German government's stake to less than a majority share -- to 45 percent, compared with the current 58 percent.</p>
        <p>But the Congressional opponents, who include the Senate majority leader, Trent Lott, Republican of Mississippi, and his Democratic counterpart, Senator Tom Daschle of South Dakota, seek to bar any transfer of wireless licenses to any company in which a foreign government owns more than 25 percent.</p>
        <p>''There are certainly members who will want to look at this issue,'' a member of Mr. Daschle's staff, Ranit Schmelzer, said last night.</p>
        <p>Reed E. Hundt, a former F.C.C. chairman who is now a consultant in Washington with McKinsey &amp; Company, predicted the deal would eventually be completed -- but not unless the German government reduced its stake in Deutsche Telekom to 25 percent or less.</p>
        <p>''Congress and the F.C.C. have always thought that 20 to 25 percent was the maximum ownership,'' Mr. Hundt said. ''Beyond that level, it didn't constitute control. But it did constitute a risk of undue influence. No one's going to change that attitude about the percentage.''</p>
        <p>If the deal is approved by regulators, a process that could take more  than a year even without Congressional opposition, Deutsche Telekom would finally realize its ambition to own a telephone network in the United States, the world's largest telecommunications market.</p>
        <p>The price would also be the richest ever for a wireless telephone company, calculated on a per-subscriber basis of about $20,000. The previous most expensive wireless deal by that measure was the $8,000 per customer that France Telecom recently agreed to in a deal to buy Orange P.L.C., Britain's third-largest wireless operator, for $37.5 billion. Deutsche Telekom argues that the price is not exorbitant given the potential of the market.</p>
        <p>''The price they're paying is expensive but it's hard to put a price on the national exposure they get with the company,'' said Eric Melloul, a telecommunications analyst at Argus Research.</p>
        <p>Deutsche Telekom has agreed to pay VoiceStream 3.2 of its own shares and $30 in cash for every VoiceStream share. As a result of the deal, VoiceStream would control about 22 percent of Deutsche Telekom. Deutsche Telekom would also assume about $5 billion in debt from VoiceStream. VoiceStream's management team would stay on and Mr. Stanton would assume a seat on Deutsche Telekom's management board. VoiceStream would eventually be rolled into T-Mobile, Deutsche Telekom's wireless unit.</p>
        <p>If VoiceStream decides at any point to walk away from the deal, it will have to pay Deutsche Telekom about a $1 billion break-up fee.</p>
        <p>Just how did a company not many people have heard of become a prize worth more than $50 billion to the world's second-largest telephone company?</p>
        <p>Much of the reason has to do with VoiceStream's potential, analysts said. Not only has it assembled a nearly nationwide network, but it is one of the few American wireless companies not already part of a larger corporation.</p>
        <p>VoiceStream's relatively short history began in 1995. It was then that Mr. Stanton, a former executive at McCaw Cellular, began acquiring digital wireless licenses for his company, Western Wireless, which he created after Craig McCaw sold McCaw Cellular to AT&amp;T. In May of 1999 Mr. Stanton formed Voice Stream as a spin-off from Western Wireless, focusing on digital wireless communications.</p>
        <p>VoiceStream then grew through acquisitions, buying the OmniPoint Corporation of Bethesda, Md., for $2 billion, and Aerial Communications of Chicago for $3 billion. Hutchison Whampoa Ltd. of Hong Kong and Finland's Sonera quickly took notice, acquiring minority stakes in Voice Stream.</p>
        <p>For Deutsche Telekom, the deal with VoiceStream comes after several botched attempts to expand beyond its borders. Most recently, talks collapsed between Deutsche Telekom and Qwest Communications International, the Denver-based telephone company. Deutsche Telekom also failed to acquire Telecom Italia in a very public and protracted bidding war with Olivetti last year.</p>
        <p>And last fall the German company was outbid by WorldCom in an attempt to acquire the American long-distance and wireless company Sprint. The Worldcom-Sprint merger was called off in the face of antitrust opposition in Europe and the United States.</p>
        <p>VoiceStream was particularly attractive to Deutsche Telekom because it was one of the few American wireless companies that transmits using a format known as GSM -- short for global system for mobile communications.</p>
        <p>GSM is a more common standard in Europe and Asia, meaning overseas customers who traveled in the United States would have an easier time communicating with a GSM phone than with phones using standards like CDMA, for code division multiple access, or TDMA, for time division multiple access, which are more common in the United States.</p>
        <p>But differences in all the various standards are expected to become less significant, as future generations of wireless networks around the world are based on more compatible technologies.</p>
        <p>For Deutsche Telekom and Voice Stream, the bigger obstacle could be political. But the companies can expect support for their deal from the European Union. The union has countered the Congressional opposition to Deutsche Telekom, arguing that the United States government would be in violation of its World Trade Organization commitment to open markets to competition if it decided to block the deal.</p>
        <p>But the Congressional opponents draw a distinction between foreign companies and companies in which foreign governments hold a large stake.</p>
        <p>Last Friday, Senator Conrad Burns, the Montana Republican who is the chairman of the communication subcommittee of the Senate Commerce Committee, and Senator Ernest F. Hollings, the ranking Democratic member, who is the chief sponsor of the legislation to block Deutsche Telekom, sent a ''Dear Colleague'' letter to their fellow senators.</p>
        <p>''We want to state clearly that we are not opposed to private foreign investment in the United States telecommunications industry,'' said the letter, which did not mention Voice Stream by name, but did mention Deutsche Telekom. ''Clearly, we did not deregulate U.S. telecommunications to permit the regulated foreign government-owned telecommunications companies to take over the U.S. market.''</p>
        <p>Such investments can reduce free competition, the letter said, because government-owned companies ''can raise staggering amounts of capital and the financial markets assume that their governments will not allow them to fail.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
