<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Deutsche Telekom Deal: Did Barriers Fall in Europe, Just to Rise in the U.S.?</title>
    <meta content="Y24REGU" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217386"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Protectionism (Trade)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Foreign Investments</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Germany</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">World Trade Organization</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Voicestream Wireless Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Deutsche Telekom</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">European Union</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Andrews, Edmund L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Protectionism (Trade)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Investments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000724T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E5DA123AF937A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1140" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Deutsche Telekom Deal: Did Barriers Fall in Europe, Just to Rise in the U.S.?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDMUND L. ANDREWS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Andrews, Edmund L</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Congressional moves to block acquisition of VoiceStream Wireless Corp by Deutsche Telekom, which is owned by German government, could invite retaliation against American communications companies active in Grmany and elsewhere in Europe, and might also run afoul of US commitments to World Trade Organization (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Through much of the 1990's, the United States led the world in opening the telecommunications industry to competition.</p>
        <p>But as Deutsche Telekom attempts to buy a fast-growing American company, the VoiceStream Wireless Corporation, Congressional leaders sound as if they have not been paying much attention to Europe for the last five years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Through much of the 1990's, the United States led the world in opening the telecommunications industry to competition.</p>
        <p>But as Deutsche Telekom attempts to buy a fast-growing American company, the VoiceStream Wireless Corporation, Congressional leaders sound as if they have not been paying much attention to Europe for the last five years.</p>
        <p>Spurred by Ernest F. Hollings, the South Carolina Democrat, the Senate is now weighing legislation that would block the German company from buying VoiceStream or almost any other American telecommunications company, because Deutsche Telekom's majority owner is the German government.</p>
        <p>And last week, responding to a letter from Senator Hollings and 29 other lawmakers, the Federal Communications Commission chairman, William E. Kennard, said an acquisition of an American telephone company by Deutsche Telekom would face heavy regulatory scrutiny.</p>
        <p>But blocking a Deutsche Telekom deal could invite retaliation against American communications companies active in Germany and elsewhere in Europe, and might also run afoul of United States commitments to the World Trade Organization.</p>
        <p>Under current American policy, foreign companies are allowed to acquire American communications companies if the buyer is based in a country that is a member of the W.T.O. -- as are Germany and all other members of the European Union. Mr. Hollings's proposal would block the F.C.C. from transferring, for at least a year, a radio license to a company in which a government owns a significant stake, even if it is less than 50 percent. Separate legislation supported by Senator Trent Lott, the majority leader, would effectively block acquisitions by such companies on a permanent basis.</p>
        <p>At first blush, the reasoning of the Hollings camp seems straightforward: the German government still owns about 57 percent of Deutsche Telekom, and Senator Hollings argues that the government could subsidize unfair competition or use its regulatory power to favor Deutsche Telekom in Germany over foreign rivals.</p>
        <p>The fears are not entirely misplaced. Germany, along with most other European countries, has a history of impeding competition. As recently as three years ago, Deutsche Telekom was an arrogant, bloated and overpriced company that depended on regulatory protection.</p>
        <p>But those days are over. In the last four years, the German government has been selling off shares in Telekom about as fast as the market could absorb them. In three separate offerings, the government has sold nearly $30 billion worth of shares,  and officials have said repeatedly that they intend to continue that process until the government's stake is at or near zero.</p>
        <p>More important, the German government has drastically deregulated the country's communications market, savaging Deutsche Telekom's core telephone business.</p>
        <p>Since 1998, when the European Union ordered all member countries to open the telephone markets to competition, the German company has lost about 30 percent of its long distance market to domestic and foreign carriers and has been forced to slash some of its rates as much as 70 percent to keep from losing even more.</p>
        <p>The process has hardly been perfect. Deutsche Telekom has tried to block rivals by charging them high fees to connect to its network and charging customers huge fees for changing telephone companies. But German regulators have slapped down most of those efforts, with the result that rivals have made big inroads into its revenues and profits.</p>
        <p>Last year, Deutsche Telekom's revenues for wired telephone service declined as a result of price cuts and customers who changed carriers, although the company largely compensated for the shortfall through booming growth in its mobile telephone business. But in wireless, too, the company faces an extraordinary array of foreign and domestic rivals.</p>
        <p>Earlier this year, for example, Vodafone AirTouch of Britain acquired the German company Mannesmann, which is equal to Deutsche Telekom in the wireless business and is a strong second-place competitor in wired telephone service.</p>
        <p>France Telecom recently acquired MobilCom, a growing German provider of local, long distance and wireless services. France Telecom is also part of a group that will bid in auctions for new German licenses to offer advanced, or so-called third-generation, wireless services.</p>
        <p>The American communications company BellSouth and the Dutch carrier Royal KPN jointly acquired a wireless network, E-Plus, in Germany recently. And British Telecommunications, Britain's dominant telephone company, owns part of a fourth wireless network in Germany.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, American companies like WorldCom are building fiber optic networks across Germany and the rest of Europe. Scores of new companies, many backed by American investors, are building their own fiber optic networks in Europe to offer high-speed Internet services.</p>
        <p>Far from being a heavy-handed ally of Deutsche Telekom, German regulators have more often than not  supported its rivals, like Mannesmann, on crucial pricing issues.</p>
        <p>In Brussels, the antitrust regulators for the European Union's European Commission have added to the pressure. Trying to force more competition in local telephone service, they demanded that Deutsche Telekom sell off its nationwide cable television network.</p>
        <p>To be sure, Deutsche Telekom has tried to retain as many of its old privileges as possible. In selling off the cable network, it insisted on breaking up the nationwide system into nine regions, with the clear intention of preventing rivals from creating a nationwide competitor.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, the German company is not only selling majority stakes in the cable systems but selling them to American companies. Callahan Associates International, a Denver-based company founded by a former executive of the regional Bell company U S West, Richard Callahan, is buying two of Deutsche Telekom's biggest cable systems for more than $5 billion.</p>
        <p>Mr. Callahan's plan is to upgrade the cable systems to also offer telephone and high-speed Internet service. Certainly he has experience: While at U S West, he helped start the British cable company Telewest, one of the first cable systems in the world to offer both telephone service and cable television over the same network.</p>
        <p>Given the raucous competition in German telecommunications, the talk of a Congressional blockade of Deutsche Telekom in the United States has already set off an alarm at the European Union.</p>
        <p>The issue of the German government's majority ownership of Deutsche Telekom could turn out to be moot. In its bid to acquire Voice Stream for $50.7 billion in stock and cash, the company's executives say the government's stake would be diluted from 58 percent to 45 percent as a result of issuing new shares to pay for the purchase.</p>
        <p>Wilfried Schneider, a spokesman for the European Union in Washington, said that a Congressional effort to block the Deutsche TelekomVoiceStream deal would violate the 1997 World Trade Organization agreement to open telecommunications markets to private and publicly owned companies.</p>
        <p>''We think Congress should prevent this proposal from becoming a law,'' Mr. Schneider said. ''It sets a bad example because it looks like some kind of protectionist move.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
