<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gore's Post-Primary Pace Worries Some Democrats</title>
    <meta content="Y25VEE$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202244"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE VICE PRESIDENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">House of Representatives (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Seelye, Katharine Q</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rangel, Charles B (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Torricelli, Robert G (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000525T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02EEDC153DF936A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1178" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gore's Post-Primary Pace Worries Some Democrats</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHARINE Q. SEELYE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Seelye, Katharine Q</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 24</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Rep Charles B Rangel, who has been campaigning across nation for fellow House Democrats, says local officials are concerned that Vice Pres Al Gore's campaign is adrift and could weaken Democratic drive to recapture House, interview; Sen Robert G Torricelli, who heads Senate Democrats' re-election committee, agrees; he and Rangel hold Gov George W Bush has made better use than Gore of post-primary season (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two important Democrats on Capitol Hill say that Vice President Al Gore's presidential campaign is adrift and can weaken the Democratic drive to recapture the House unless corrected.</p>
        <p>Representative Charles B. Rangel, the Manhattan Democrat who has been campaigning across the country for fellow House members, said local officials had expressed concern that the Gore campaign had not inspired confidence.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Two important Democrats on Capitol Hill say that Vice President Al Gore's presidential campaign is adrift and can weaken the Democratic drive to recapture the House unless corrected.</p>
        <p>Representative Charles B. Rangel, the Manhattan Democrat who has been campaigning across the country for fellow House members, said local officials had expressed concern that the Gore campaign had not inspired confidence.</p>
        <p>''People are starting to ask, 'When does he get started? When does he get focused? How did Bush catch up? When does the show hit the road?' '' Mr. Rangel said in an interview on Tuesday. ''They're saying, 'If this is a policy to lay back and wait for the debates, then share it with somebody!' There's no fiery speeches being given; we don't have the surrogates out there.''</p>
        <p>Senator Robert G. Torricelli, the New Jersey Democrat who is chairman of the Senate Democrats' re-election committee, conceded today that ''there is a problem.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Torricelli described the problem: ''Until Al Gore actually goes to Los Angeles and receives his party's nomination and campaigns in his own right, he will still be identified by most Americans as Bill Clinton's vice president. There is still not a separate identity, and only the dramatic departure from Los Angeles is going to create this new identity.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Rangel and Mr. Torricelli, and others in their party, said they were concerned that Gov. George W. Bush of Texas, Mr. Gore's Republican rival, had made better use of the post-primary season than Mr. Gore had. They also worried that the Gore campaign did not seem to be responding to recent polls that have shown him trailing Mr. Bush and losing support among broad segments of the public, including suburban women, white men and every age group except the elderly.</p>
        <p>In a radio interview this morning, Mr. Gore brushed aside questions about being stalled in the polls, insisting that such surveys this far in advance of Election Day -- Nov. 7 -- are ''notoriously wrong.''</p>
        <p>''I'm not trying to have an impact on the polls,'' Mr. Gore said on the ''Diane Rehm Show'' on public radio station WAMU in Washington. ''I'm trying to deliver a message to the people of this country.''</p>
        <p>''But it's not getting across, perhaps,'' Ms. Rehm interjected.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore responded, ''The process of communication that takes place in a campaign is not best analyzed on a daily or hourly basis.''</p>
        <p>He suggested that his strategy against Governor Bush -- which his advisers said was rooted in the compare-and-contrast method he used against former Senator Bill Bradley of New Jersey in the primaries -- would need time to yield results.</p>
        <p>''I think that the dialogue on complex issues often takes time,'' Mr. Gore said. ''It takes time for facts to emerge, for judgments to sink in, for people to really come to a conclusion about how they feel about the candidates, about the positions on the issues and about where we're going in the future.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Rangel and Mr. Torricelli said there was plenty of time for Mr. Gore to recover. Mr. Rangel described the atmosphere among his fellow Democrats as one of concern, not alarm. ''This is May,'' he said. ''When the question is raised'' with campaign officials, he said, ''they say no one gets serious until Labor Day.''</p>
        <p>Of course, elected officials like Mr. Rangel have a huge stake in the party's success in November. If Democrats win back the House, Mr. Rangel is in line to become chairman of the powerful Ways and Means Committee, and broadcasting concern about the presidential campaign this early is one way of nudging Mr. Gore into trying to fix things before they become worse.</p>
        <p>Senator Torricelli said of the Gore campaign's problem: ''It is both manageable and, I suspect, temporary.''</p>
        <p>For weeks now Mr. Bush has managed to dominate the race with a policy proposals intended to paint him as a more moderate candidate.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore's supporters worry that during that same period, the vice president has appeared more reactive than proactive.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore's last major address that drew front-page coverage was on April 30, when he spoke in Boston on foreign policy and raised questions about Mr. Bush's ''cold war'' mindset. Since then, Governor Bush has largely dictated the issues.</p>
        <p>Eleanor Holmes Norton, a Democrat who is the District of Columbia delegate, said Mr. Gore had ceded the spotlight to Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>''His poll numbers flow directly from his disappearance from the radar screen for a number of weeks while Bush pressed the 'on' button and kept himself on the screen,'' she said. Representative Eliot L. Engel, a Bronx Democrat, said that Mr. Gore had not capitalized on his victory in the primaries. ''We thought at the end of the primaries that Bush was all the way to the right and Gore was well-positioned and I had hoped we would see a change in the polls, but we're seeing slippage and that's disappointing,'' Mr. Engel said.</p>
        <p>''With Bill Clinton, he gets up every morning and wants to meet voters. Al Gore, he does what he has to do, but I don't think he relishes that, and I think people pick up on that. He needs to talk very positively for what he stands for rather than being negative about Bush.''</p>
        <p>Gore advisers keep saying that the vice president is ''right on the issues'' and that his positions, from tolerance on social matters like abortion to paying down the national debt, are more in tune with those of a majority of Americans. Nonetheless, political analysts say Mr. Gore seems to have trouble articulating that message.</p>
        <p>Prof. James A. Thurber, director of the Center for Congressional and Presidential Studies at American University and a member of the audience this morning while Mr. Gore was interviewed at the radio station, said that even after almost a quarter century in politics, Mr. Gore still did not grasp some of the fundamentals of political communication.</p>
        <p>''I thought his answers on Social Security were good for my class in public policy,'' Professor Thurber said, ''but not great in terms of things to take away to a wider audience that does not know all the details of what's wrong with Social Security and whether it's working or not.''</p>
        <p>The Democratic National Committee, which raised $26.5 million tonight, is gearing up to spend millions of dollars for commercials promoting Mr. Gore's biography -- to convey the human side of a candidate whom voters perceive as someone born in a blue suit behind a podium.</p>
        <p>Steve Grossman, a former national chairman of the Democratic Party, said, ''He obviously has to do an even more effective job at articulating his values and his priorities and connecting passionately to voters.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE VICE PRESIDENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
