<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>PUBLIC LIVES</title>
    <meta content="25PUBL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202169"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Lifetime Television</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cosby, Ennis William, Foundation</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barron, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Williams, Lena</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chase, Chevy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wasserstein, Wendy</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">American Daughter, an (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Public Lives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000525T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E0DA143DF936A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="708" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>PUBLIC LIVES</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BARRON with Lena Williams</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Williams, Lena; Barron, James</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Public Lives column; comedian Chevy Chase discusses his relationship with President Clinton; Wendy Wasserstein discusses casting of her new play An American Daughter by Lifetime cable network; scene at benefit for Ennis William Cosby Foundation described (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Political Advice From a Comedian</p>
        <p>CHEVY CHASE, who became a star on ''Saturday Night Live'' when he lampooned the 38th president (Gerald R. Ford), was reminiscing about the advice he gave the candidate who was elected the 42nd president in 1992 (Bill Clinton). And yes, Mr. Chase refers to the president by his first name.</p>
        <p>''To me, the whole issue is going to be, as it was with Bill when he first ran, how to be on TV,'' Mr. Chase said the other night at the Chelsea Piers, where he was honored at a gala for the Rainforest Alliance, which works to conserve the world's endangered tropical forests.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Political Advice From a Comedian</p>
        <p>CHEVY CHASE, who became a star on ''Saturday Night Live'' when he lampooned the 38th president (Gerald R. Ford), was reminiscing about the advice he gave the candidate who was elected the 42nd president in 1992 (Bill Clinton). And yes, Mr. Chase refers to the president by his first name.</p>
        <p>''To me, the whole issue is going to be, as it was with Bill when he first ran, how to be on TV,'' Mr. Chase said the other night at the Chelsea Piers, where he was honored at a gala for the Rainforest Alliance, which works to conserve the world's endangered tropical forests.</p>
        <p>Referring to Mr. Clinton, Mr. Chase said: ''I used to talk to him all the time when he was on his bus tour. TV is the issue. I told Bill when he started to campaign: 'You're answering questions too fast. You sound like a kid. George Bush is the president. He looks like it and he acts like it. Take more time, take a minute -- or what you think is a minute -- to answer a question. Look presidential.' He would call me and ask 'How'm I doing?' ''</p>
        <p>So what about this year's campaign?</p>
        <p>''Right now, Bush comes off as the more competent fellow -- and he certainly has all the money to be on TV anytime he wants -- and Gore comes off a little stiff,'' he continued. ''But when it comes to substantive issues and the two of them debate, I think -- and hope -- that the country will see that Gore is way ahead of Bush.''</p>
        <p>Playwright Busy; Outcome Pleasing</p>
        <p>The producers of the Lifetime cable network's version of WENDY WASSERSTEIN's play ''An American Daughter'' telephoned to arrange a conference call last September, when she was preoccupied with her new daughter.</p>
        <p>''I was in the hospital, had just had a baby, and they said, 'What number are we reaching you at?' '' she recalled on Tuesday. ''I said, 'I've taken an office.' I thought, I'm not going to confuse them and tell them I'm at Mount Sinai and had a baby three months early. They said, 'Will you be available in an hour for a casting conference?' I thought, I don't know, they might be teaching me how to pump the milk, so I said, 'I don't know about that, I might be busy then.' I think that was the day they took me upstairs to see my daughter, so I missed the casting call.''</p>
        <p>But Ms. Wasserstein was pleased with the choices. CHRISTINE LAHTI, TOM SKERRITT and LYNNE THIGPEN got major parts in the film, which was shown at Lincoln Center on Tuesday. Ms. Thigpen had been in the 1997 Broadway production.</p>
        <p>Cosby Foundation Holds Fund-Raiser</p>
        <p>The comedian BILL COSBY could not sit still during a benefit for the Ennis William Cosby Foundation on Tuesday. Mr. Cosby seemed determined to shake every hand and kiss every cheek -- and there were more than 600 guests.</p>
        <p>So Mr. Cosby and his wife, CAMILLE COSBY, worked their way through a crowd that included SARAH FERGUSON, the Duchess of York; DAVID N. DINKINS, the former mayor; JOHN F. STREET, the mayor of Philadelphia; AHMAD RASHAD, an NBC sportscaster; the songwriters and singers NICK ASHFORD and VALERIE SIMPSON; ED BRADLEY, a correspondent for the CBS News magazine ''60 Minutes''; and JEANNE MOUTOUSSAMY-ASHE, the widow of Arthur Ashe.</p>
        <p>The foundation was established in 1997 after Mr. Cosby's son, Ennis, was shot to death while changing a tire in Los Angeles. The benefit, which was held at Cipriani on East 42nd Street on Tuesday, was the foundation's first fund-raiser.</p>
        <p>STEVIE WONDER donated a song written in memory of Ennis Cosby, and the priciest item at an auction conducted by WILLIAM W. STAHL JR., a vice president of Sotheby's, was a party for 10 with dinner prepared by the Cosbys' chef, JOHN-CONRAD STE. MARTHE.</p>
        <p>The winning bidder was the lawyer JOHNNIE L. COCHRAN JR., who got it for $15,000.</p>
        <p>JAMES BARRON with Lena Williams</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
