<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: CAMPAIGN BRIEFING</title>
    <meta content="Y25CAM$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202209"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000525T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E6DF153DF936A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="589" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: CAMPAIGN BRIEFING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by B. Drummond Ayres Jr.</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE DEMOCRATS</p>
        <p>BARRY LOOMS AGAIN -- Marion S. Barry Jr., once the very popular, very visible and very controversial mayor of Washington, is telling friends he may run again, this time for a seat on the City Council. Though out of office for 14 months, Mr. Barry still has a large political following in the city. But should he run, he faces a couple of major obstacles: the person who holds the council seat Mr. Barry is eyeing has no intention of going quietly, and the present mayor, Anthony A. Williams, says he will support Mr. Barry in just about anything except a return to office. Mr. Barry served on the City Council before being elected mayor, an incumbency notable, among other things, for his imprisonment on a drug conviction. On his release, he was elected once more to the City Council and capped his comeback by being elected mayor again. Mr. Williams, who was elected mayor by campaigning largely against mismanagement and overspending in the Barry era, said recently that he would support Mr. Barry ''in whatever capacity other than serving on the City Council.'' Harold Brazil, the council incumbent Mr. Barry may challenge, announced last week that he was running for re-election so that he could help the city continue its recovery.</p>
        <p>Irvin Molotsky (NYT)</p>
        <p>THE REPUBLICANS</p>
        <p>BUSH ON CHARACTER -- Taking his campaign to a major swing state, Gov. George W. Bush of Texas declared yesterday in Detroit that education was ''the new civil right.'' With Michigan's popular Republican governor, John Engler, at his side, Mr. Bush spent more than an hour discussing the importance of equal access to education with students, teachers, parents and volunteers at the Cornerstone Schools, a private religion-oriented group of middle and elementary schools. ''We can't have any gaps of hope in the country,'' Mr. Bush said. ''The American dream is available for everyone, which means every child must be educated.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE DEMOCRATS</p>
        <p>BARRY LOOMS AGAIN -- Marion S. Barry Jr., once the very popular, very visible and very controversial mayor of Washington, is telling friends he may run again, this time for a seat on the City Council. Though out of office for 14 months, Mr. Barry still has a large political following in the city. But should he run, he faces a couple of major obstacles: the person who holds the council seat Mr. Barry is eyeing has no intention of going quietly, and the present mayor, Anthony A. Williams, says he will support Mr. Barry in just about anything except a return to office. Mr. Barry served on the City Council before being elected mayor, an incumbency notable, among other things, for his imprisonment on a drug conviction. On his release, he was elected once more to the City Council and capped his comeback by being elected mayor again. Mr. Williams, who was elected mayor by campaigning largely against mismanagement and overspending in the Barry era, said recently that he would support Mr. Barry ''in whatever capacity other than serving on the City Council.'' Harold Brazil, the council incumbent Mr. Barry may challenge, announced last week that he was running for re-election so that he could help the city continue its recovery.</p>
        <p>Irvin Molotsky (NYT)</p>
        <p>THE REPUBLICANS</p>
        <p>BUSH ON CHARACTER -- Taking his campaign to a major swing state, Gov. George W. Bush of Texas declared yesterday in Detroit that education was ''the new civil right.'' With Michigan's popular Republican governor, John Engler, at his side, Mr. Bush spent more than an hour discussing the importance of equal access to education with students, teachers, parents and volunteers at the Cornerstone Schools, a private religion-oriented group of middle and elementary schools. ''We can't have any gaps of hope in the country,'' Mr. Bush said. ''The American dream is available for everyone, which means every child must be educated.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush said he also believed character education courses should be available in every school. ''Public schools should not mix religion in the classroom.'' he said. ''But we should not fear teaching values that are embraced by all religions.''</p>
        <p>Nichole M. Christian (NYT)</p>
        <p>THE ISSUES</p>
        <p>HESTON AND GORE, ARMED -- Charlton Heston's vow as president of the National Rifle Association to defend to the death the right to bear arms drew a chuckle yesterday from Vice President Al Gore, the association's top political target. Mr. Gore said Mr. Heston and other association officials were dead wrong when they said last week at the association's annual convention in Charlotte, N.C., that he wanted to disarm America. Alluding to the moment at the convention when the Mr. Heston raised a flintlock musket over his head and pledged to die defending his constitutional right to have it, Mr. Gore said in an interview with National Public Radio: ''I have no intentions of proposing or supporting policies or allowing policies that would disarm America. What I have proposed that has upset him so much is a set of common-sense restrictions on the availability of handguns.'' Referring to defending his right to bear arms to the death, Mr. Heston said, ''So as we set out this year to defeat the divisive forces that would take freedom away, I want to say those fighting words, for everyone within the sound of my voice to hear and to heed, and especially you, Mr. Gore.'' When Mr. Heston's comment with musket raised was read to Mr. Gore yesterday, he chuckled.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
