<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>GARDEN Q.&amp; A.</title>
    <meta content="25QNA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202127"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Galitzki, Dora</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000525T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03EFD7173DF936A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="761" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>GARDEN Q.&amp; A.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Dora Galitzki</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Galitzki, Dora</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Answers to readers' questions on plants that are slow to get established and on the hazards of overmulching; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Grumpy When Moved</p>
        <p>Q. I have a garden in eastern Long Island. It gets sun three-fourths of the day, and the soil, which has been improved over the years, drains well. I have an Oriental poppy, which has not bloomed since I planted it two years ago, and a Baptisia australis, which did not bloom last year. The baptisia was divided the year previous. Can you tell me what the problem is, and what can be done to make them bloom?</p>
        <p>A. Descriptions of Baptisia australis may vary in how they rave over the indigo-blue flowers or pea-like, blue-green leaves, but the one phrase you'll always find is ''slow to get established.'' That's horticulture-speak for grumpy, stubborn or resentful plants, those that don't appreciate being transplanted, divided or having their roots disturbed and show their resentment by refusing to bloom for a year or two. Or three.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Grumpy When Moved</p>
        <p>Q. I have a garden in eastern Long Island. It gets sun three-fourths of the day, and the soil, which has been improved over the years, drains well. I have an Oriental poppy, which has not bloomed since I planted it two years ago, and a Baptisia australis, which did not bloom last year. The baptisia was divided the year previous. Can you tell me what the problem is, and what can be done to make them bloom?</p>
        <p>A. Descriptions of Baptisia australis may vary in how they rave over the indigo-blue flowers or pea-like, blue-green leaves, but the one phrase you'll always find is ''slow to get established.'' That's horticulture-speak for grumpy, stubborn or resentful plants, those that don't appreciate being transplanted, divided or having their roots disturbed and show their resentment by refusing to bloom for a year or two. Or three.</p>
        <p>Impatient gardeners wish everything worked on the same timetable as annuals. While an annual is always in a hurry, perennials take their time settling in and getting to know the neighborhood before they commit to something as energy-sapping as a flower. Assuming your baptisia and Oriental poppy have decided that this is home, you should see flowers this summer or next.</p>
        <p>Any time you divide, plant or transplant something whose descriptions include phrases like ''a challenge to transplant'' or ''slow to take hold,'' always do a little research so you can move it at the proper time. Take a big ball of soil with it, to disturb the roots as little as possible, and prepare to wait it out.</p>
        <p>Among the challenges are platycodon (balloon flower), helleborus (hellebore), dictamnus (gas plant), aconitum (monkshood) and asclepias (butterfly weed).</p>
        <p>When Mulch Is Too Deep</p>
        <p>Q. My community hires a landscaping company to take care of gardening for all residents. There are many trees 8 to 10 years old, and they pile dirt about 10 inches high around the trunks. My question is, is that a good idea?  A. No. Covering a tree trunk with soil, or even a too-thick layer of mulch, frequently leads to problems. Both soil and mulch will retain moisture, and if the trunk is constantly damp the bark will eventually weaken and rot. When the moist bark freezes and thaws in winter, it expands, contracts, and eventually splits. Both the rotting and the splitting let insects and diseases invade the tree. And the pile protects those insects from their predators.</p>
        <p>With mulch, the answer is easy --  just pull it back to leave a space between it and the trunk. But piling soil on can lead to another problem. Roots, which we think of in their role of absorbing water and nutrients or as an anchor so the tree doesn't fall over when you lean against it, also absorb oxygen that filters down through the soil from the air. Every tree has an optimum depth for its roots -- deep enough to protect the roots and let them anchor the tree, shallow enough to get both the air and the water it needs.</p>
        <p>By the time a tree is as old as yours are, it has established itself and gotten comfortable. Pile extra soil on, especially over the area where the roots meet the trunk, and it no longer can get all the oxygen it needs. You won't hear gasping or choking sounds, but gradually its health and vigor decline, reducing its ability to fend off diseases and increasing its susceptibility to insect attack. It may die, or it may just suffer in silence, depending on how sensitive the species is. Maple, beech, oak and willow are especially resentful of being smothered.</p>
        <p>The same advice applies to mulch. Three or four inches is fine, because mulch isn't as dense as soil, but more than that can lead to problems in the long run. And the long run is what trees are all about.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
