<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.N. Allows Cambodians to Take Part in Trial of Khmer Rouge</title>
    <meta content="25CAMB" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202200"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">War Crimes and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cambodia-International Relations-US</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Cambodia</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Khmer Rouge (Cambodia)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Crossette, Barbara</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Cambodia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Cambodia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War Crimes, Genocide and Crimes Against Humanity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000525T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE2D6143DF936A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="552" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.N. Allows Cambodians to Take Part in Trial of Khmer Rouge</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA CROSSETTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Crossette, Barbara</byline>
      <dateline>UNITED NATIONS, May 24</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>United Nations concedes to Cambodia right to appoint one of two prosecutors in war crimes trials for Khmer Rouge; compromise seems to have surmounted major hurdle in eventually bringing former Khmer Rouge leaders to trial; human rights groups score deal, which also calls for three of five judges to be Cambodians; Clinton administration reportedly strongly backed deal (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After months of often rancorous exchanges over who should ultimately control war crimes trials for the Khmer Rouge, the United Nations has conceded to Cambodia the right to appoint one of two prosecutors. The compromise appears to have surmounted a major hurdle in eventually bringing former leaders of the Khmer Rouge to trial.</p>
        <p>Human rights groups immediately criticized the deal under which either the Cambodian prosecutor or a co-prosecutor appointed by the United Nations could proceed with a case if a five-judge panel does not block it. The groups said the United Nations had compromised its requirement that the trials be conducted by allowing the prosecutors total independence.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After months of often rancorous exchanges over who should ultimately control war crimes trials for the Khmer Rouge, the United Nations has conceded to Cambodia the right to appoint one of two prosecutors. The compromise appears to have surmounted a major hurdle in eventually bringing former leaders of the Khmer Rouge to trial.</p>
        <p>Human rights groups immediately criticized the deal under which either the Cambodian prosecutor or a co-prosecutor appointed by the United Nations could proceed with a case if a five-judge panel does not block it. The groups said the United Nations had compromised its requirement that the trials be conducted by allowing the prosecutors total independence.</p>
        <p>In addition to allowing co-prosecutors, the deal also provides that the panel of judges will include three members from Cambodia and two nominated by the United Nations. Initially, the United Nations would have preferred to model this panel on the war crimes tribunals used in the Balkans and Rwanda, which are outside the control of national governments.</p>
        <p>The agreement was arrived at in part last month through the intercession of Senator John F. Kerry, Democrat of Massachusetts, who discussed the urgency of establishing a tribunal with Cambodian leaders, and through a long series of negotiations between a United Nations team and Cambodia's prime minister, Hun Sen.</p>
        <p>The deal must be approved by the Cambodian legislature before the tribunal can begin prosecuting cases against former members of the Khmer Rouge, an extreme leftist movement that decimated Cambodian society in the 1970's. More than a million people were executed or died from hard labor, dislocation, starvation and disease.</p>
        <p>Officials said the deal signaled that Mr. Hun Sen, himself a former lower-ranking Khmer Rouge official, had given up having total control over the tribunal.</p>
        <p>''The secretary general considers the prime minister's response a positive development,'' said Fred Eckhard, the spokesman for United Nations Secretary General Kofi Annan. But the United Nations is refusing to discuss the agreement, and plans to send its legal counsel, Hans Corell, back to Cambodia to discuss details. In the past, Mr. Hun Sen has changed his position and undercut agreements.</p>
        <p>Officials here and in Cambodia said that the Clinton administration, with few foreign policy breakthroughs to its credit as it enters its final months, strongly backed the deal, apparently finalized in an exchange of letters between Mr. Hun Sen and Mr. Annan this week.</p>
        <p>At the Lawyers Committee for Human Rights, Bruce Broomhall, the international justice coordinator, said that this provision is a welcome development, but overall he remains skeptical of the agreement.</p>
        <p>''This rewards political intransigence by compromising on the integrity of the tribunal,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Kenneth Roth, executive director of Human Rights Watch, said in an interview that he sees many pitfalls in the deal.</p>
        <p>''We're afraid that this is a precedent that will come back to haunt the U.N. elsewhere,'' Mr. Roth said. ''The U.N. has been a very firm custodian of fair trial standards, and prosecutions have been conducted with scrupulous regard for due process.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
