<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Investigators Identify Security Breaches at Several U.S. Agencies</title>
    <meta content="25SECU$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202193"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Buildings</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Impersonations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forgery</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Identification Devices</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">General Accounting Office</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Central Intelligence Agency</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Bureau of Investigation</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Justice Department</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Labaton, Stephen</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Entertainment and Amusements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Identification Devices</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Buildings (Structures)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000525T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E0D7143DF936A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="523" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Investigators Identify Security Breaches at Several U.S. Agencies</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN LABATON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Labaton, Stephen</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 24</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>General Accounting Office undercover investigators probing security at government agencies were able to effortlessly enter 19 sensitive federal builds, including Central Intelligence Agency, Federal Bureau of Investigation, Pentagon and Justice Department by flashing fake police badges; say they made counterfeit identification cards using software available on Internet (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Flashing fake police badges that were movie props and other bogus law enforcement identifications, undercover investigators effortlessly entered 19 sensitive federal buildings including the Central Intelligence Agency, the Federal Bureau of Investigation, the Pentagon and the Justice Department where the investigators sauntered into the attorney general's fifth-floor suite of offices.</p>
        <p>The examination of security, performed by the General Accounting Office at the request of Republican lawmakers from the House of Representatives, was described on Tuesday in private briefings to the agencies and will be the subject of a Congressional hearing on Thursday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Flashing fake police badges that were movie props and other bogus law enforcement identifications, undercover investigators effortlessly entered 19 sensitive federal buildings including the Central Intelligence Agency, the Federal Bureau of Investigation, the Pentagon and the Justice Department where the investigators sauntered into the attorney general's fifth-floor suite of offices.</p>
        <p>The examination of security, performed by the General Accounting Office at the request of Republican lawmakers from the House of Representatives, was described on Tuesday in private briefings to the agencies and will be the subject of a Congressional hearing on Thursday.</p>
        <p>In written testimony prepared for the hearing, the G.A.O. investigators said they made the counterfeit identification cards from software that is easily obtainable from the Internet. They said they also claimed to be armed and carried satchels into the buildings that were never searched or passed through metal detectors and were large enough to carry explosives, chemical or biological weapons or listening devices.</p>
        <p>The investigators said they were able to roam unescorted through most of the buildings, including at the State and Justice Departments. In all, the investigators were able to penetrate 19 buildings and two airports using the phony badges and identifications, though at three of the buildings, they had to try twice before getting in.</p>
        <p>They also managed to park a van in the courtyard of the Justice Department without having its contents examined.</p>
        <p>Republican lawmakers who disclosed the results of the inquiry today said that it highlighted significant and systemic security problems that continued to plague the Clinton administration.</p>
        <p>In recent months, the State Department has been reeling from a series of security lapses, including the disappearance of a lap-top computer that contained highly sensitive files concerning intelligence sources and weapons proliferation.</p>
        <p>Before that incident, officials discovered an eavesdropping device in a State Department conference room and expelled a Russian diplomat from the country. And in 1998, a man in a tweed sport coat strolled into the executive secretary's office, six doors down from the secretary of state's office, and left with sheaves of classified documents while two secretaries worked nearby.</p>
        <p>''This is a shocking report revealing a dangerous vulnerability plaguing thousands of people who work in our public buildings,'' said Representative Henry J. Hyde, the Illinois Republican who heads the House Judiciary Committee. ''Complacency in matters of security is a serious threat to the orderly functioning of our government.''</p>
        <p>Representative Bill McCollum, the Florida Republican who asked the accounting office to perform the review, said the inquiry had demonstrated ''that far too many of our security facilities where top secret and sensitive information is kept have an open door policy.''</p>
        <p>Administration officials said they were troubled by the findings and had already undertaken to correct the security lapses.</p>
        <p>''Obviously, the attempts to come into the department have caused concern,'' said Gretchen Michael, a spokeswoman for the Justice Department.</p>
        <p>Ms. Michael said the department had adjusted its security procedures as a result of the inquiry, which she said could not be disclosed for security reasons.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
