<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Jury Sees Taped Statement About Shelter Island Killing</title>
    <meta content="25SHEL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202205"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Shelter Island (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcquiston, John T</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Payne, Kenneth</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cook, Curtis</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island/Shelter Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000525T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE0D6143DF936A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="778" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Jury Sees Taped Statement About Shelter Island Killing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN T. McQUISTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mcquiston, John T</byline>
      <dateline>RIVERHEAD, N.Y., May 24</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Murder trial of Kenneth H Payne continues, Riverhead, NY; videotaped confession of defendant calmly and politely telling investigators how he shot and killed his neighbor Curtis Cook on remote Shelter Island two years ago is played to jury (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The videotaped confession of a defendant calmly and politely telling investigators how he shot and killed his neighbor on remote Shelter Island two years ago, was played to a wide-eyed jury today in a darkened courtroom.</p>
        <p>Appearing on a large screen in Suffolk County Criminal Court here, the defendant, Kenneth H. Payne, said in the confession that he shot his neighbor and friend of 20 years, Curtis Cook, not because he was angry with him, but because Mr. Cook had bragged about how he planned to beat charges that he molested an 8-year-old Shelter Island girl.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The videotaped confession of a defendant calmly and politely telling investigators how he shot and killed his neighbor on remote Shelter Island two years ago, was played to a wide-eyed jury today in a darkened courtroom.</p>
        <p>Appearing on a large screen in Suffolk County Criminal Court here, the defendant, Kenneth H. Payne, said in the confession that he shot his neighbor and friend of 20 years, Curtis Cook, not because he was angry with him, but because Mr. Cook had bragged about how he planned to beat charges that he molested an 8-year-old Shelter Island girl.</p>
        <p>The taped confession was described by the defense in opening arguments on Monday as the key piece of evidence that would prove that Mr. Payne, 44, a carpenter, had acted in self-defense, to protect himself, his family and his girlfriend.  The recording was made by Suffolk County homicide detectives at the Shelter Island police station less than five hours after the shooting on April 27, 1998.</p>
        <p>The defense insists, however, that the confession supports its argument that Mr. Payne, 44, intentionally killed Mr. Cook, 42, in a sudden rage.  On the tape, Mr. Payne told how he picked up a 12-gauge shotgun he used for hunting deer, loaded it with two shells, walked next door to Mr. Cook's house, knocked on the door and then shot him at point-blank range when he opened the door.</p>
        <p>''Were you going to kill him at the time you pulled back the safety on your gun?'' the investigator asked Mr. Payne on the video.</p>
        <p>''That's a tough one,'' Mr. Payne responded.</p>
        <p>''Did you know what you were doing at the time?'' he was asked.</p>
        <p>''I'm not sure I can remember what I was thinking,'' Mr. Payne said. ''All I can remember is that he opened the door. I looked him straight in the eye. He said, 'Oh my God,' and I shot him. I can't give you an explanation of my emotions at that very moment.''</p>
        <p>The killing was the first homicide recorded in the 300-year history of the island, which lies between the North and South Forks of eastern Long Island.</p>
        <p>Today, the jury sat transfixed, with all eyes on the large screen that displayed the larger-than-life image of Mr. Payne and the investigator who questioned him, Janet Albertson, an assistant Suffolk County District Attorney.</p>
        <p>Mr. Payne told Ms. Albertson that after he shot Mr. Cook, he returned to his trailer, leaned the shotgun against a barbecue grill and called his estranged wife and friends to tell them that he had just shot Mr. Cook and that Mr. Cook ''would not hurt anybody else's kids.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Payne said that he had two children, who visited him every other  weekend and that his wife, from whom he had separated six years ago, was concerned that Mr. Cook was living next door to him and might molest the children.</p>
        <p>When asked at the end of the confession if he wished he had done anything differently the night of the shooting, Mr. Payne said: ''If I could do that night all over again, I would have stayed home and watched TV.  But I can't change what happened.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Payne's lawyer, Stephen J. Wilutis, said during the break in the proceedings that his client had shown little emotion during the 40-minute taped confession because ''he was in a state of shock.'' Mr. Wilutis said he planned to call Mr. Payne to testify in his own defense sometime next week.</p>
        <p>The prosecutor, Christopher Clayton, an assistant Suffolk County District Attorney, noted outside court that Mr. Payne did not say in his taped and written confessions that  Mr. Cook had, as he now claims, threatened to kill him or that Mr. Cook had threatened to sexually abuse Mr. Payne's wife, their 11-year-old daughter and his girlfriend, Charlotte Cunha.</p>
        <p>The prosecution contends that the defense's contention that Mr. Payne acted in self-defense and out of concern for his family's safety was a convenient afterthought.</p>
        <p>The playing of the video followed by one day the damaging testimony of Mr. Payne's former girlfriend, Ms. Cunha, who was the last person to see him before the shooting.</p>
        <p>Under questioning by the prosecution, she told the jury she was unaware of any threat that Mr. Cook might have made against her. She said that she had given Mr. Payne a ride home from a bar shortly before the shooting, and that Mr. Payne was drunk and ''very agitated.'' Mr. Payne insisted in his confessions that he had had only one beer that night.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
