<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Court Rejects Appeal by Brooklyn Garment Workers</title>
    <meta content="Y25KNIT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202181"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Arbitration, Conciliation and Mediation</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Claiborne, Liz, Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mademoiselle Knitwear Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Henriques, Diana B</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Arbitration, Conciliation and Mediation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000525T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E6D8143DF936A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="680" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Court Rejects Appeal by Brooklyn Garment Workers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DIANA B. HENRIQUES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Henriques, Diana B</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Federal appeals court in Manhattan refuses to reinstate class-lawsuit filed in 1997 against Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees by union members who contended that they were not fairly represented in complex arbitration case against clothing manufacturer Liz Claiborne; workers, who had been employed at Mademoiselle Knitware, sweater factory in Brooklyn that is now defunct, had filed lawsuit against union and two of its locals; court affirms trial judge's decision last summer that neither parent union nor two locals owed workers any 'duty of fair representation' under federal labor laws (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A federal appeals court in Manhattan has refused to reinstate a class-action lawsuit filed in 1997 against a leading garment industry union by union members who contended that they were not fairly represented in a complex arbitration case against the clothing manufacturer Liz Claiborne.</p>
        <p>The workers, who had been employed at Mademoiselle Knitware, a sweater factory in Brooklyn that is now defunct, had filed the lawsuit against the Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees, known as Unite, and two of its locals.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A federal appeals court in Manhattan has refused to reinstate a class-action lawsuit filed in 1997 against a leading garment industry union by union members who contended that they were not fairly represented in a complex arbitration case against the clothing manufacturer Liz Claiborne.</p>
        <p>The workers, who had been employed at Mademoiselle Knitware, a sweater factory in Brooklyn that is now defunct, had filed the lawsuit against the Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees, known as Unite, and two of its locals.</p>
        <p>The unusual dispute, pitting union members against their own leaders at what had once been a showcase factory in the garment industry, boiled down to the issue of who actually had the legal duty to protect the interests of the Brooklyn workers.</p>
        <p>In a ruling released Tuesday, the United States Court of Appeal for the Second Circuit affirmed a trial judge's decision last summer that neither the parent union nor the two locals owed the Brooklyn workers any ''duty of fair representation'' under federal labor laws.</p>
        <p>The dispute involved the parent union, Unite; Local 23-25, which represented Claiborne workers; and Local 155, which represented workers at Mademoiselle.</p>
        <p>In 1992, Claiborne had promised a Unite official, who was also manager of Local 23-25, that it would order a specific volume of sweaters from Mademoiselle. When Claiborne reneged, Local 23-25 filed an arbitration case against Claiborne on behalf of the Mademoiselle workers, who were represented by Local 155.</p>
        <p>The union won that arbitration case and, when Claiborne still did not supply the promised orders, it filed a second case in 1996 to enforce the earlier ruling.</p>
        <p>But in May 1997, during collective bargaining talks with Claiborne, Unite and Local 23-25 agreed to nullify the first arbitration award, drop the second arbitration case and free Claiborne from its commitment to order sweaters from Mademoiselle. In turn, Claiborne agreed to pay $750,000 into a fund to be distributed to the Local 155 workers but to be administered by Local 23-25.</p>
        <p>A group of workers at Mademoiselle later accused Unite and Local 23-25 of selling them out in exchange for a separate pact, concluded around the same time, which obligated Claiborne to pay $13 million in damages to the parent union and the Claiborne local. They further accused their own local of failing to protect them in the dispute.</p>
        <p>But under federal labor law, the trial court found, the only union legally obligated to protect the Mademoiselle workers was their own collective bargaining unit, Local 155.</p>
        <p>That local could not be held liable in the class-action case, however, because it had no role in the disputed settlement, the trial court concluded. And Unite and Local 23-25, which had negotiated the settlement, could not be held liable because neither was the designated collective bargaining unit for the Mademoiselle workers.  Thus, neither had a legally enforceable duty to act in the best interests of Local 155's members.</p>
        <p>The appellate court affirmed that interpretation. ''Generally, the duty of fair representation arises only with respect to a union entity that is certified as the exclusive bargaining representative of a group of employees,'' the appeals court found.</p>
        <p>Jo-Ann Mort, a spokeswoman for Unite, said the union was ''delighted'' by the appeals court's refusal to reinstate the Mademoiselle case, which Unite had long argued was without merit.</p>
        <p>''We hope that this concludes this unfortunate chapter and allows us to get back to doing what we have done all along, namely, providing our members with the best representation possible,'' Ms. Mort said.</p>
        <p>Howard Rhine, a lawyer representing the Mademoiselle workers, said he was considering petitioning the United States Supreme Court to take up the issue. ''There has to be a remedy if there is a wrong,'' he said. ''But what this court is saying is that no one is responsible.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
