<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Blood, Sweat and Never a Tear for Lemieux</title>
    <meta content="25PUCK$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202262"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Philadelphia Flyers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Jersey Devils</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lapointe, Joe</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New Jersey Devils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Philadelphia Flyers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000525T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E1DA153DF936A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="860" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Blood, Sweat and Never a Tear for Lemieux</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Joe Lapointe</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lapointe, Joe</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>On Hockey column discusses New Jersey Devils victory over Philadelphia Flyers in sixth game of NHL playoff series; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When he arrived at the postgame news conference last night, Coach Larry Robinson of the Devils sat in a chair and then quickly jumped up. ''Ugh!'' he said with a look of bemused disgust. ''All wet!''</p>
        <p>It was soaked because Claude Lemieux had just got up, leaving behind a few ounces of perspiration. Robinson will be willing to pay the dry-cleaning bill if he gets one more sweaty effort like the one Lemieux offered last night. Lemieux scored the go-ahead goal and helped inspire the winning one in a 2-1 victory over the Philadelphia Flyers in Continental Arena that evened the Eastern Conference finals at three victories apiece.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When he arrived at the postgame news conference last night, Coach Larry Robinson of the Devils sat in a chair and then quickly jumped up. ''Ugh!'' he said with a look of bemused disgust. ''All wet!''</p>
        <p>It was soaked because Claude Lemieux had just got up, leaving behind a few ounces of perspiration. Robinson will be willing to pay the dry-cleaning bill if he gets one more sweaty effort like the one Lemieux offered last night. Lemieux scored the go-ahead goal and helped inspire the winning one in a 2-1 victory over the Philadelphia Flyers in Continental Arena that evened the Eastern Conference finals at three victories apiece.</p>
        <p>This was a bravura performance by Lemieux, the kind for which he has been known in 15 seasons of Stanley Cup playoff combat. It was the kind of showing that has earned him three Stanley Cup rings with three teams and a Conn Smythe trophy as most valuable player in the tournament in 1995, when the Devils won the championship. His goal, on a rebound, came at 11 minutes 26 seconds of the third period, breaking a scoreless tie and the sweet tension of a remarkable game. It was the sort of contest that demanded someone take command. So Lemieux did.</p>
        <p>''I just love the moment,'' Lemieux said, smiling through his craggy, scarred facial features. ''I'm certainly not going to wait for another guy. I want to take charge.'' Referring to this round over all, Lemieux said: ''We've made this a very exciting series.''</p>
        <p>With its rugged play and high stakes, it has become a Lemieux sort of series, especially with the Devils on the brink of elimination for the last two games. This goal was his third of this round and his fourth over all in the tournament. It is for games such as these that Lemieux was reacquired by the Devils during the season in a trade with Colorado. Although he had some good games in the first two rounds, he had only one goal and said he was slumping.</p>
        <p>''Slow start for me,'' he said. ''I started second-guessing my ability. People were asking for goals.''</p>
        <p>Perhaps it took a tough team like the Flyers to bring out the best in him. In Game 3, Lemieux was knocked dizzy for a few minutes by a flying elbow from John LeClair. But his play kept improving. He got involved in the pushing, shoving, slashing and trash-talking that always increases when close rivals play close games.</p>
        <p>After Game 2, Rick Tocchet of the Flyers revealed that Lemieux had looked at the captain's ''C'' on the jersey of Eric Desjardins and asked the Philadelphia defenseman if the letter stood for ''selfish.''</p>
        <p>He spoke other words to other people. One was Alexander Mogilny, like Lemieux a trade acquisition this season. Mogilny has been pressing, not scoring as many goals as others had hoped he would. ''He and I had a little talk today,'' Lemieux said. ''I know how badly he's wanted to score in these playoffs, how bad he wants to make this opportunity count for himself. I said 'One big one will make up for 10 others.' ''</p>
        <p>Mogilny had a great chance earlier, but missed the net. But at 16:33, he flipped a puck past Brian Boucher to give the Devils a 2-0 lead. It proved important because Eric Lindros got one back for the Flyers in the final minute. When asked about Lemieux afterward, Mogilny said: ''He's been a big inspiration to me and to everyone in the room.''</p>
        <p>Most inspirational, according to Lemieux, has been Robinson, who screamed at the team in a postgame tirade after they fell behind by three games to one last Saturday night. At that point, they could have quit on themselves and the coach could have let them. But Robinson refused and demanded more. ''He believes in us,'' Lemieux said. ''If he believes in us this much, we've got to believe in ourselves.''</p>
        <p>Since then, they have won two games and have a chance to finish their comeback in Game 7 in Philadelphia tomorrow night. To advance to the finals against Dallas or Colorado, they will again have to get the best of Boucher, a rookie who is establishing impressive credentials, but they may be wearing him down. Early last night, his mask took a slap shot from Scott Gomez that knocked his screws loose. He stopped Bobby Holik on a breakaway. His goal posts beat Patrik Elias and Petr Sykora. ''We kept getting opportunities,'' Lemieux said. ''Something had to happen at one point or another.''</p>
        <p>And something must happen tomorrow. What was a good series early has become a great one late. A special finish could make it memorable.</p>
        <p>''You can get that in the playoffs,'' Lemieux said, referring to momentum. ''It seems to snowball. You can't be stopped. We've played with everything and nothing to lose. We're feeling really good about ourselves.''</p>
        <p>ON HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
