<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Judge Suggests U.S. Remedy For Microsoft Is Inadequate</title>
    <meta content="25SOFT$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Front Page; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202234"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Justice Department</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Microsoft Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jackson, Thomas Penfield (Judge)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brinkley, Joel</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000525T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE5DC153DF936A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1279" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Judge Suggests U.S. Remedy For Microsoft Is Inadequate</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOEL BRINKLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brinkley, Joel</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 24</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Judge Thomas Penfield Jackson raises serious questions about Justice Department's bid to break Microsoft into 2 parts, seeming to suggest plan does not go far enough; lauds brief from group of computer industry executives suggesting breaking company into three parts; asks government to quickly revise antitrust remedy proposal; rejects Microsoft's bid for months of added hearings, surprising and upsetting company; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The federal judge trying the Microsoft antitrust case raised serious questions today about the government's plan to break up the company, seeming to suggest that he did not think the plan went far enough.</p>
        <p>The judge, Thomas Penfield Jackson, praised a brief submitted by a group of computer industry executives -- including many of Microsoft's rivals -- that called for breaking the company into three parts instead of two, as the government has proposed. He called it ''an excellent brief, excellent brief.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The federal judge trying the Microsoft antitrust case raised serious questions today about the government's plan to break up the company, seeming to suggest that he did not think the plan went far enough.</p>
        <p>The judge, Thomas Penfield Jackson, praised a brief submitted by a group of computer industry executives -- including many of Microsoft's rivals -- that called for breaking the company into three parts instead of two, as the government has proposed. He called it ''an excellent brief, excellent brief.''</p>
        <p>With an uncharacteristically determined manner, the judge also bluntly rejected Microsoft's request for months of additional hearings on the remedy for its antitrust violations, telling stunned Microsoft lawyers near the end of the day, ''I am not contemplating any further process.''</p>
        <p>Judge Jackson asked the government to submit a revised version of its remedy proposal by Friday, modified in small ways to reflect answers to questions he asked in court today. And he gave Microsoft 48 hours after that to comment on the form, not the substance, of the revised proposal.</p>
        <p>Then, two years and six days after the landmark antitrust suit was filed, Judge Jackson formally closed the proceedings, saying: ''The matter is submitted. Thank you, counsel.'' His ruling on a remedy could come as soon as next week.</p>
        <p>On April 3, Judge Jackson found Microsoft in wide violation of federal and state antitrust laws. The next day, he told lawyers for both sides that he wanted to conclude the proceedings quickly. After the government put forward its breakup plan on April 28, Microsoft responded with a request for six months of preparation followed by a new trial.</p>
        <p>Microsoft officials were surprised and upset by the decision to close the record today. A few minutes after the hearing adjourned, William H. Neukom, Microsoft's chief counsel, said: ''We had sought to have our day in court on remedies, but the judge has decided not to do that. So this case will now be decided at the court of appeals, and we will be raising issues of procedure in our appeal, as well as issues of fact and law.''</p>
        <p>The Justice Department had no comment.</p>
        <p>Almost as soon as the remedy hearing opened this morning, the judge asked questions suggesting his state of mind, though he never explicitly said his ruling would call for a breakup of the company or anything else.</p>
        <p>The government's proposal would create one company for Microsoft's operating systems and another company that would hold everything else, including applications software, like the word processor Word and the spreadsheet program Excel, and Microsoft's Internet properties.</p>
        <p>Soon after Kevin O'Conner, an assistant attorney general from Wisconsin who represents the 19 states that are partners in the government's suit, began describing merits of the plan, the judge interrupted, saying, ''The effect of a bisection will in effect be to create two separate monopolies, with no incentive to interfere with each other's profitability.''</p>
        <p>He noted that one outsider's brief he received in recent weeks had made that point. He was apparently referring to a plan proposed recently by several prominent academic economists to split Microsoft into five companies, including three competing operating-system companies.</p>
        <p>Later, the judge asked David Boies, the Justice Department's lead trial lawyer, about another supporting brief, submitted by the Computer and Communications Industry Association and the Software and Information Industry Association. It proposed dividing Microsoft into three companies, including one that would sell only Internet Explorer, the company's Web browser.</p>
        <p>''Rather than reorganizing Microsoft into only a Windows company and a single applications company,'' the brief said, ''the court should supplement plaintiffs' proposed final judgment by separating the Internet Explorer product and personnel into a third, independent company.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Boies did not criticize the idea in court and said it might hold merit, but added that the government was trying to reduce the complexity of its proposal.</p>
        <p>Judge Jackson said: ''You talk of the simplicity of implementation of your proposals, but they are anything but simple. I don't think'' Microsoft ''will be willing to cooperate.'' He then wondered aloud why the government plan gave Microsoft the responsibility to determine how the company should be divided.</p>
        <p>Mr. Boies responded, ''We give them the opportunity to do it first, but if they come back with something that simply doesn't meet our requirements, the government will have to do it.'' The judge nodded.</p>
        <p>When Microsoft's turn came to promote its own proposed remedy, the judge asked no questions. And to Microsoft's request for a delay, the judge told a company lawyer: ''I find it somewhat ironic that your client believes its travails will end at the court of appeals, and yet wants to spend more time in this court.''</p>
        <p>John Warden, a Microsoft lawyer, insisted that he found the idea ''that we would have some final resolution today really incredible.'' When another company lawyer made the same point, the judge snapped, ''This case has been pending for two years.'' Later Mr. Warden complained that the government's remedy proposal had been pending for less than a month.</p>
        <p>Officials familiar with the government position say Microsoft has known since abortive settlement talks in March 1999 that the government might seek to break up the company. A specific breakup proposal was put on the table during court-sponsored mediation talks early this year. Microsoft refused to discuss the idea at either juncture.</p>
        <p>Along with the breakup plan it submitted to the judge, the government proposal includes several temporary rules to alter Microsoft's conduct while the breakup would be carried out. Mr. Warden complained that one of them, requiring Microsoft to divulge technical information on Windows to other software companies, was ''confiscatory.'' It would require Microsoft to turn trade secret over to ''all of our fiercest competitors'' as well as ''pirates and counterfeiters,'' he added.</p>
        <p>A short time later, responding to Microsoft's complaints, the judge remarked: ''I ask you if forfeiture is not a traditional, equitable remedy.''</p>
        <p>As their day in court seemed to be slipping away this afternoon, Microsoft's lawyers hurriedly entered into the record an ''offer of proof,'' which included summaries of testimony that the company would have hoped to offer in further hearings on a remedy.</p>
        <p>Among the 16 academic experts, Microsoft executives and others cited in the 35-page brief were William H. Gates, the company's chairman, and Steven A. Ballmer, the president and chief executive. Microsoft said both would have come to testify. In Mr. Gates's printed declaration, he said the company was working on ''a new vision of the future,'' specifically ''making the Internet more useful by creating the first Internet-based platform for software developers.'' But Mr. Gates added that the ''project will be doomed to failure at the outset if Microsoft is split along the arbitrary lines proposed by the government.''</p>
        <p>Microsoft said the declarations were not ready when it filed its response to the government plan this month. It said it wanted to enter them into the record now so the court of appeals would see them.</p>
        <p>Whatever Judge Jackson's comments and actions today might bode, investors did not seem disheartened. Microsoft's stock closed up $2.375, at $65.5625.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
