<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Democrats Raise Record $26.5 Million at Gala</title>
    <meta content="Y25GOR$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202258"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: FUND-RAISING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Seelye, Katharine Q</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Tipper</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000525T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E2DA153DF936A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="985" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Democrats Raise Record $26.5 Million at Gala</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHARINE Q. SEELYE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Seelye, Katharine Q</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 24</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Biggest political fund-raiser ever raises $26.5 million in three hours for Democratic National Committee; Democrats bill event as tribute to Pres Clinton, who attends with his wife, Hillary; Vice Pres Gore, designated beneficiary of party's treasure chest, attends with his wife, Tipper; event underscores sad reality for Gore: in joint appearances of Clintons and Gores, Pres Clinton steals the show; crowd greets him with rock-concert-like shrieks; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Most people shelled out just 50 bucks, but some could not help giving or gathering $500,000. So there were different ''tiers'' of donors in kind of a class system sprayed throughout the giant MCI Sports Center tonight, but all of them were part of a history-making event: the biggest political fund-raiser ever, raising $26.5 million in three hours for the Democratic National Committee.</p>
        <p>The Democrats billed the event as a tribute to President Clinton, and the donors, from those in black tie to those in blue jeans, were beckoned by the Midas of fund-raisers, Terry McAuliffe, who, in the end, squeezed 13,625 people into a space designed for 12,000.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Most people shelled out just 50 bucks, but some could not help giving or gathering $500,000. So there were different ''tiers'' of donors in kind of a class system sprayed throughout the giant MCI Sports Center tonight, but all of them were part of a history-making event: the biggest political fund-raiser ever, raising $26.5 million in three hours for the Democratic National Committee.</p>
        <p>The Democrats billed the event as a tribute to President Clinton, and the donors, from those in black tie to those in blue jeans, were beckoned by the Midas of fund-raisers, Terry McAuliffe, who, in the end, squeezed 13,625 people into a space designed for 12,000.</p>
        <p>Vice President Al Gore, the designated beneficiary of the party's treasure chest, hailed Mr. McAuliffe as ''the greatest fund-raiser in the history of the universe.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore, dressed in a sage polo shirt with his Palm Pilot clipped to his blue jeans, also declared that he would make reform of the campaign finance system a top priority if elected president.</p>
        <p>Some of those who had come up with half a million dollars for the party included representatives of organized labor, fresh from their defeat on Capitol Hill at the hands of the Clinton administration on the China trade bill.</p>
        <p>But that battle seemed distant as many in the arena emitted rock-concert-like shrieks when Mr. Clinton was introduced and Tina Turner's pulsating hit, ''You're Simply the Best,'' blared through the loudspeakers.</p>
        <p>Unfortunately for Mr. Gore, this is the tune that his campaign has been road-testing as his campaign theme song.</p>
        <p>And it underscored a sad reality for Mr. Gore: As at some of the other joint appearances of the Clintons and Gores in the past, while Mr. Gore is meant to be the star, Mr. Clinton steals the show. ''Four more years!'' was shouted from the crowd as he spoke.</p>
        <p>Al DiRienzo, 68, a bricklayer from Maryland, reflected the sentiment. He said that he was supporting Mr. Gore but that his affection was for Mr. Clinton.</p>
        <p>''This is the greatest president we've ever had,'' Mr. DiRienzo said, ''and it's a shame we can't vote for him again.''</p>
        <p>After Tipper Gore and Hillary Rodham Clinton spoke, the arena fell dark for a video tribute to Mr. Clinton and his administration. It was a paean to overcoming adversity and was awash in sentimentality.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Clinton took the stage, he opened with a fierce defense of the fund-raising event itself,</p>
        <p>which was challenged by demonstrators in the arena who, referring to money in politics, yelled, ''Stop the corruption!''</p>
        <p>''I don't believe that it's corruption to take money to pass the Brady bill instead of beat it,'' Mr. Clinton responded. He went on to say that it was not corrupt to work for passage of other measures like the Family and Medical Leave Act and the patients' bill of rights that have been opposed by special interests who gave money to the Republicans.</p>
        <p>''I think that's good for America,'' the president declared. ''That's why we are here. That's why you are here. We made a difference, and I'm glad you are here to help us win the next election.''</p>
        <p>And he offered more intimate musings, including a sidelong glance at his advancing age.</p>
        <p>Referring to the video that had just unfolded, Mr. Clinton told the audience: ''I had sort of mixed feelings looking at that film, actually. I watched myself get grayer and grayer and grayer, and I thought to myself, before I got into my second term here, I was always the youngest person who did everything. Now I'm up here in my old boots and my old jeans, and I'm just kind of an old, gray-haired redneck trying to put in some good months here.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore also confronted the notion that the event might be inappropriate, but with a suggestion that it would not be repeated.</p>
        <p>''If you entrust me with the presidency, the good news is that we can all come back here in four years and it won't cost much at all'' because, he said, he is committed to bringing ''meaningful'' change to the campaign finance system.</p>
        <p>And he did succeed in bringing the crowd to its feet with a rousing campaign appeal that grew in intensity. ''You stick with me, I'll keep this prosperity going,'' he asserted. ''We'll give the medical decisions back to the doctors and the nurses and take them away from the accountants! From the H.M.O.'s and the insurance companies! We'll raise the minimum wage a dollar an hour!''</p>
        <p>By now he was yelling: ''We'll make sure everybody participates! We'll bring our people together!''</p>
        <p>Tables for dignitaries were spread across the floor of the sports arena, where guests were served barbecue from restaurants in Arkansas and Tennessee, home states of the president and vice president, along with bottles of merlot and chardonnay. Up in the bleachers, guests had to buy their food at the regular arena prices. A medium-sized soft drink cost $3.75.</p>
        <p>John Bunting, 56, who works in social services in Baltimore, was one of those in the cheap seats, paying $50 to attend tonight's party. Surveying the arena, he said most people probably came to pay tribute to Mr. Clinton.</p>
        <p>''It's not that Vice President Gore falls short,'' he said, ''it's that we're talking about the king.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: FUND-RAISING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
