<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Wary India Prepares to Step Back Into Sri Lanka's War</title>
    <meta content="Y25LANK" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202165"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">India-International Relations-Sri Lanka</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tamils (Ethnic Group)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sri Lanka</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">India</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Jaffna (Sri Lanka)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dugger, Celia W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Sri Lanka</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Sri Lanka</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000525T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E5DA143DF936A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1243" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Wary India Prepares to Step Back Into Sri Lanka's War</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CELIA W. DUGGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dugger, Celia W</byline>
      <dateline>NEW DELHI, May 24</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>India, gingerly stepping back into Sri Lanka's long battle against separatist ethnic Tamil rebels, indicates its Navy is prepared to evacuate 30,000 Sri Lankan troops if asked by Sri Lankan government; says it has two ships standing by to evacuate troops and civilians from Jaffna peninsula, near India's southern coast, if cease-fire is declared; Sri Lanka is not now ready to withdraw and turn city of Jaffna over to rebels as fighting continues; rebels, while greatly outnumbered by demoralized Sri Lankan troops, are expertly led, ruthlessly focused and financed by Tamils abroad; map; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>India, chastened by its disastrous intervention more than a decade ago in the brutish war that has long plagued Sri Lanka, its island neighbor to the south, is nonetheless gingerly stepping back into a conflict that has once again reached a crisis stage.</p>
        <p>Officials here continue to say India will not send in its own troops or supply arms to Sri Lanka, which is battling separatist ethnic Tamil rebels. But the defense minister and the national security adviser have suggested in recent days that the Indian Navy is prepared to evacuate 30,000 Sri Lankan troops at the request of the Sri Lankan government under certain conditions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>India, chastened by its disastrous intervention more than a decade ago in the brutish war that has long plagued Sri Lanka, its island neighbor to the south, is nonetheless gingerly stepping back into a conflict that has once again reached a crisis stage.</p>
        <p>Officials here continue to say India will not send in its own troops or supply arms to Sri Lanka, which is battling separatist ethnic Tamil rebels. But the defense minister and the national security adviser have suggested in recent days that the Indian Navy is prepared to evacuate 30,000 Sri Lankan troops at the request of the Sri Lankan government under certain conditions.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for India's Ministry of Defense, Pramod Bhatnagar, said in an interview Tuesday that the navy had two large ships standing by to evacuate troops and civilians from the Jaffna peninsula, a small finger of land just miles from India's southern coast, though only if a cease-fire is declared between the government and the rebels.</p>
        <p>''The moment we receive an order, we will go into action,'' he said. ''It will be essentially a peace mission.''</p>
        <p>At this point, the Sri Lankan government is not ready to withdraw and turn over the city of Jaffna in the Tamil-dominated north of this majority Sinhalese nation to the rebels.  But the boastful declarations of military and political leaders that the country would fight to the last man to defend Jaffna are sounding more tentative as the fighting continues to rage.</p>
        <p>The Sri Lankan president, Chandrika Kumaratunga, said in an interview published today in The Hindu, a national Indian newspaper, that the military still holds two-thirds of the Jaffna peninsula but added that the rebels are putting up ''a very determined fight.'' Withdrawal, she said, ''does not seem a possibility at this moment.''</p>
        <p>Military analysts and Western diplomats say they doubt that the government can hold on indefinitely even though its troops outnumber the rebels by 6 to 1. The Sri Lankan military has been weakened by a highly politicized command structure, a demoralized rank and file and planes that don't fly, they say. Mrs. Kumaratunga herself acknowledged shortcomings in the military strategy.</p>
        <p>In contrast, the rebels, who call themselves the Liberation Tigers of Tamil Eelam, have proved to be a motivated, expertly led force that is ruthlessly focused on winning a homeland for the country's Tamil minority and is financially supported by a large Tamil diaspora.</p>
        <p>India, which has it own chronic secessionist problem in Kashmir, has a tortured history in the Sri Lankan conflict.</p>
        <p>In the 1980's, under Prime Minister Indira Gandhi, India -- which has a huge Tamil population in its south -- covertly armed and trained separatist Tamil militants from Sri Lanka and allowed them to set up bases in the southern Indian state of Tamil Nadu.</p>
        <p>Sri Lankan historians see Mrs. Gandhi's meddling in the affairs of Sri Lanka as a cynical effort to court political support among Tamils in southern India and to assert India's dominance over its smaller neighbor.</p>
        <p>But India succeeded only in helping to unleash a war that has taken more than 60,000 lives and has entangled India itself.</p>
        <p>Rajiv Gandhi, who succeeded his assassinated mother as prime minister, sent in Indian troops in 1987 with the aim of quickly imposing a settlement of the ethnic conflict. At its peak, more than 75,000 Indian troops were on Sri Lankan soil. Almost three years later, India pulled out with none of its aims achieved and more than 1,000 of its men killed.</p>
        <p>In 1991, Mr. Gandhi, who was then out of office and campaigning to regain his post, was assassinated by a suicide bomber from the Tigers, one of the guerrilla groups India had trained. The conspirators in his murder have been sentenced to death and the Tigers banned in India.</p>
        <p>Sri Lanka itself said good riddance when India departed in 1990. But 10 years later, facing a renewed onslaught from the Tigers, it has turned to India for military assistance.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Kumaratunga alluded to India's moral responsibility in her interview with The Hindu, noting that it was India that ''supported the terrorists on their soil, gave them not just refuge, but arms and training so that they could come back and start the war.''</p>
        <p>She said India should now be using its influence to bring the Tigers to the negotiating table. Sri Lankan officials have been meeting with a delegation from Norway over the past three days that is trying to ''facilitate'' peace talks between the government and the rebels that broke off five years ago.</p>
        <p>India, as well as the United States and other western nations, have taken the position that the conflict can only be resolved through negotiation, and that the solution should preserve the territorial integrity of Sri Lanka, while granting greater autonomy to the Tamils.</p>
        <p>India, which is deeply embroiled in a conflict with anti-India guerrillas to its north in the state of Kashmir, cannot afford to encourage Tamil nationalists in south India by countenancing the creation of a separate Tamil nation in Sri Lanka.</p>
        <p>For now, though, the immediate crisis is a military one in the Jaffna peninsula. The Tigers controlled the city of Jaffna from 1990 to 1995, lost it to the government for the past five years and claim they are moving closer to recapturing it.</p>
        <p>There are fears that the Tigers, who are infamous for assassinating their Tamil rivals and other political leaders, will kill many civilians whom they consider government collaborators. The American State Department has categorized the Tigers as a terrorist organization.</p>
        <p>Fighting has been raging in the north in recent days, but it is difficult to know what is happening on the ground. The government has banned reporters from the battle zone and imposed severe censorship on the press.</p>
        <p>In the past week, it has closed two newspapers for defying the censor: the Sunday Leader, a weekly newspaper based in Colombo, and Udayan, Jaffna's Tamil newspaper. The coverage of the crisis has been largely reduced to regurgitating press releases issued by the government.</p>
        <p>If the time comes when the government has to withdraw from Jaffna, Sri Lankans may well be unprepared for the defeat. That would prove politically costly for President Kumaratunga's party, which faces parliamentary elections by October.</p>
        <p>No one knows how long the government can hang on in Jaffna. It has been buying arms and aircraft from abroad to resupply the men fighting there. Kingsley de Silva, a historian who is executive director of the International Center for Ethnic Studies in Kandy, Sri Lanka, said he believes Mrs. Kumaratunga will try to hold on militarily in Jaffna until after the elections if at all possible. ''I do not think the government can survive if there is a massive evacuation,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
