<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ruling on Immunity Puts Chile Closer to Trial of Pinochet</title>
    <meta content="25CHIL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202232"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immunity From Prosecution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Chile</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Krauss, Clifford</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pinochet Ugarte, Augusto (Gen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lagos, Ricardo (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Chile</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Chile</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immunity From Prosecution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000525T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E7DC153DF936A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="823" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ruling on Immunity Puts Chile Closer to Trial of Pinochet</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFFORD KRAUSS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Krauss, Clifford</byline>
      <dateline>LIMA, Peru, May 24</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Chilean appeals court strips Gen Augusto Pinochet of immunity, removing key obstacle to his possible trial for abuses during his 17 years as dictator; it could take years of legal wrangling before trial of ailing 84-year-old can begin; ruling shows courts will take independent stands after decades of subservience to military and Pres Ricardo Lagos will let mechanisms of justice go forward despite friction with military and threats by congressional conservatives to bottle up much of his program if Pinochet prosecution continues; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Chilean appeals court has stripped the immunity of Gen. Augusto Pinochet, removing an important obstacle in the way of his possible trial. He faces charges that he was involved in the kidnapping, murder and torture of thousands during his 17 years as Chile's dictator.</p>
        <p>The decision of the Court of Appeals is subject to a possible reversal by the Supreme Court, and even lawyers working to prosecute General Pinochet say it could take years of legal wrangling before a trial could begin, and that is assuming that the general, now 84, lives that long. He has circulatory problems and has a history of strokes and diabetes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A Chilean appeals court has stripped the immunity of Gen. Augusto Pinochet, removing an important obstacle in the way of his possible trial. He faces charges that he was involved in the kidnapping, murder and torture of thousands during his 17 years as Chile's dictator.</p>
        <p>The decision of the Court of Appeals is subject to a possible reversal by the Supreme Court, and even lawyers working to prosecute General Pinochet say it could take years of legal wrangling before a trial could begin, and that is assuming that the general, now 84, lives that long. He has circulatory problems and has a history of strokes and diabetes.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, the 13-9 decision by the appellate judges, voted in private on Tuesday but leaked to local reporters, demonstrates that Chile's courts are willing to take independent stands after decades of subservience to the armed forces.</p>
        <p>It also demonstrates the commitment of President Ricardo Lagos, the recently inaugurated Socialist, to let the mechanisms of justice go forward despite friction with military commanders and threats by congressional conservatives to bottle up much of his program if the prosecution of General Pinochet continues.</p>
        <p>Carlos Salinas, acting legislative director of Amnesty International USA, said: ''Throughout Pinochet's captivity in Great Britain, the Chilean government repeatedly insisted that he be returned for prosecution in Chile. This appears to be the first step toward the Chilean government making good on its promise.''</p>
        <p>General Pinochet's legal troubles began in earnest in late 1998 when he was arrested in London on a Spanish warrant charging him with human rights violations. The general, who is a senator for life under a constitution written while he ruled, and thus has immunity, was released by British authorities in February after doctors said he was not physically and mentally fit to stand trial.</p>
        <p>While legislators have a cloak of immunity, judges may strip it away if they have evidence that a crime may have been committed. General Pinochet has the right to challenge the court's ruling on immunity.</p>
        <p>Once the matter is settled, there are several legal issues that must be ruled on, including whether General Pinochet is mentally fit to stand trial and whether he would be tried by a civilian or military court.</p>
        <p>General Pinochet now faces 108 criminal complaints, mostly filed by family members of about 3,000 people who disappeared after his violent 1973 coup against President Salvador Allende Gossens.</p>
        <p>Through a spokesman, General Pinochet recently said, ''I never ordered anybody to be killed or tortured.''</p>
        <p>Judge Juan Guzman, who is prosecuting Mr. Pinochet, has anchored his case on 19 people who have been missing since they were dragged out of prisons by soldiers led by some of General Pinochet's top aides in the weeks after the coup.</p>
        <p>The 19 people -- who were among 75 prisoners believed to have been summarily executed -- have never been found, but the Supreme Court has accepted Judge Guzman's interpretation that they should be considered kidnap victims, rather than dead. If the bodies were found, the slayings could possibly be covered by a general amnesty involving most rights violations committed during the early years of the dictatorship, though there is a court challenge arguing that mass murder and torture are crimes against humanity superseding any amnesty. But considering the prisoners to be kidnapped, and possibly still held, offers a loophole for the prosecution.</p>
        <p>Congressman Pablo Longueira of the Independent Democratic Union, who is opposed to the general's prosecution, recently called the legal interpretation behind Judge Guzman's prosecution ''a ridiculous joke.'' He added, ''We all know those people are dead.''</p>
        <p>The Independent Democratic Union and another conservative party had been in negotiations with President Lagos to rewrite sections of the Constitution that limit the president's appointment powers over military commanders and that give the military powers to appoint senators. But the talks have bogged down as Mr. Lagos has refused to interfere in the judicial proceedings and as government attorneys have joined in the prosecution.</p>
        <p>President Lagos has been equally forceful in displaying his resolve as top military commanders have showed displeasure with the prosecution of their former commander in chief. After a high-level lunch of top military and police commanders on May 15 was interpreted as a show of defiance, President Lagos publicly scolded them in a diplomatic but pointed statement.</p>
        <p>Since his return from Britain, Mr. Pinochet has been keeping as low a profile as possible. He has not been attending Senate sessions, even for important votes, and he has not spoken out on the issues of the day.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
