<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Commencement; Tomorrow's Engineers Leave the Nest</title>
    <meta content="25COMM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202190"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cooper Union</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wyatt, Edward</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gould, Stephen Jay</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000525T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE3D7143DF936A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="634" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Commencement; Tomorrow's Engineers Leave the Nest</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWARD WYATT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wyatt, Edward</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Commencement exercise held for Cooper Union for the Advancement of Science and Art; Steven Jay Gould, paleontologist and evolutionary theorist, speaks (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Students at the Cooper Union for the Advancement of Science and Art in the East Village are known to spend several days before the opening of school each fall camping out under the street lights in Cooper Square to secure a prime space in the school's famously cramped studios for architecture, art and engineering.</p>
        <p>So it should not be surprising that Joshua A. Kritzer, a candidate for a bachelor's degree in engineering at Cooper Union's 141st commencement, made sure that his wife, Amy Kritzer, showed up nearly three hours before yesterday's ceremony to be first in a long line for a seat in the school's Great Hall.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Students at the Cooper Union for the Advancement of Science and Art in the East Village are known to spend several days before the opening of school each fall camping out under the street lights in Cooper Square to secure a prime space in the school's famously cramped studios for architecture, art and engineering.</p>
        <p>So it should not be surprising that Joshua A. Kritzer, a candidate for a bachelor's degree in engineering at Cooper Union's 141st commencement, made sure that his wife, Amy Kritzer, showed up nearly three hours before yesterday's ceremony to be first in a long line for a seat in the school's Great Hall.</p>
        <p>Many of the other spouses and family members who crowded the Great Hall to see Cooper Union confer 175 bachelor's degrees and 12 master's degrees in architecture, art, engineering and science had to settle for at least their second choice for a seat in an auditorium with one of the most renowned histories and worst sightlines of any in the city.</p>
        <p>With nearly every seat behind a support pole, ''it does remind me of Yankee Stadium before they renovated it,'' said Stephen Jay Gould, the paleontologist and evolutionary theorist, who addressed the graduates and received an honorary Doctor of Humane Letters degree.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, Mr. Gould said, he accepted the invitation to speak in the Great Hall because of its distinguished history, which includes the 1860 speech by Abraham Lincoln that cleared the way for his nomination for president; because his professional hero, Charles Darwin, published his seminal work in 1859, the same year that Peter Cooper endowed the school that now bears his name; and because Professor Gould thought he could say something new in a graduation speech.</p>
        <p>In the end, Mr. Gould acknowledged, he said nothing truly new. ''They taught you good things here,'' he said. ''You can make a difference. Go out and do it.''</p>
        <p>Every one of Cooper Union's nearly 1,000 students receives free tuition, paid for by income from the university's substantial real estate assets, including the land under the Chrysler Building, as well as the usual array of endowments and annual gifts.</p>
        <p>The competition for admission to those precious spots is so fierce that an observer might mistakenly think the years that follow could only be anticlimactic -- particularly at a school that, from its location on the edge of the East Village, has plenty of offerings for excitable souls just outside its doors.</p>
        <p>But Cooper Union graduates form a sort of ''trauma bond'' with the institution, said Malini Ramanarayanan, a candidate for a chemical engineering degree who gave the student address at the ceremony.</p>
        <p>Working night after night and into sunrise after sunrise at their drafting tables and art studios produces in Cooper Union students an intensity about their work, an intimacy with their peers and a solidarity with the institution that is unparalleled, Ms. Ramanarayanan said.</p>
        <p>Cooper Union apparently feels the same bond. In addition to degrees, the school bestowed no fewer than 65 academic prizes on its 187 newly minted alumni. Matthew Stephen Foster, a graduate of the electrical engineering program, received three, in addition to a National Science Foundation fellowship for graduate study in physics at the University of California at Santa Barbara.</p>
        <p>Echoing the students' sentiments regarding their bond with Cooper Union was John Jay Iselin, who is stepping down in June after 12 years as president of Cooper Union and thus was presiding at his final school commencement. Under Dr. Iselin, the school received its first seven endowed professorships, opened a small, specialized high school and helped to establish a business improvement district to improve its often scruffy neighborhood.</p>
        <p>Upon being appointed president emeritus yesterday, Dr. Iselin said he would, like Cooper Union's graduates, ''be able to claim forever a connection to this great institution.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
