<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Knicks' Opponents Playing Mind Games</title>
    <meta content="25WISE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202247"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Indiana Pacers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wise, Mike</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New York Knicks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Indiana Pacers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000525T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E3DB153DF936A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="887" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Knicks' Opponents Playing Mind Games</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Mike Wise</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wise, Mike</byline>
      <dateline>INDIANAPOLIS</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>On Baseketball column on Indiana Pacers preparing for second game of playoff series against New York Knickerbockers (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>One moment the Knicks were locked in mortal combat with Miami, often pulled out of bounds by their shorts. The next, they were dazed by Indiana's bombs, retreating for cover against another fierce playoff rival.</p>
        <p>Marcus Camby and his teammates tried yesterday to clear the cobwebs. Seventy-two dizzying hours will make you do that.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>One moment the Knicks were locked in mortal combat with Miami, often pulled out of bounds by their shorts. The next, they were dazed by Indiana's bombs, retreating for cover against another fierce playoff rival.</p>
        <p>Marcus Camby and his teammates tried yesterday to clear the cobwebs. Seventy-two dizzying hours will make you do that.</p>
        <p>''It's almost like you have to shift gears,'' Camby said. ''You go from a banging, physical series for seven games to a team with new plays, new personnel, a team that can shoot the ball from the 3-point line much better than Miami. The lithe forward scratched his head as he sat on a wooden bleacher at Conseco Fieldhouse. Tonight the Knicks will try to tie the four-of-seven-game Eastern Conference finals against the Pacers at one victory apiece.</p>
        <p>''You just have to re-work your mind,'' Camby said.</p>
        <p>It is premature to take apart the Knicks for their wire-to-wire 102-88 loss in Game 1. Fatigue, travel and little time to prepare for the Pacers give them legitimate excuses. Yet, as Game 2 approaches, the larger issue is whether they understand who they are playing.</p>
        <p>For all the physical pain players like Alonzo Mourning, Dan Majerle and P. J. Brown administered, the respect between the Knicks and the Heat deepened with each game of their riveting semifinal series. Maybe not to a point in which you would refer to it as a gentlemen's competition, but at least they appreciated the effort put forth by the other side. Knicks Coach Jeff Van Gundy said: ''You can't help but have empathy for who lost that series. It was that close.''</p>
        <p>The Pacers' Reggie Miller has not been to the N.B.A. finals. He could care less how the Knicks felt about anything, much less losing the series to his team.</p>
        <p>''Indiana, the pain of losing to us last year, fueled a great determined effort on their part,'' Van Gundy said. ''Even though we talked about it many times, our players underestimated what it was going to take to compete with this team. This team, I hate this cliche -- mission -- but they have an unbelievable passion to get there.'' The Knicks and Heat banged bodies and made it impossible for either side to crack 90 points. But the rules of their duel were also understood: You walked 10 paces before you turned and fired. In this series, you are lucky if you get nine steps before Miller has already taken a shot.</p>
        <p>''Player-wise, it's more personal,'' Camby said. ''Last series was more about Riley, he used to coach the Knicks and all the hoopla. But now it's about Reggie, his comments he made before Game 1, saying we're arrogant, we don't respect them and stuff like that. It's a mental adjustment, no doubt.''</p>
        <p>It is easy to overanalyze a 14-point loss, and wonder if you are not reaching for something that is not as relevant to a contentious playoff series as you originally thought. But even if you discount how the Knicks need to mentally approach the Pacers, you can't discount what they did to New York on the court Tuesday night.</p>
        <p>The Pacers make a higher percentage of free throws and 3-pointers than anyone in the league. They are the fourth-best scoring team. They can run or slow it down, go inside with Rik Smits or outside with Miller. They beat teams with their passing much easier than with their one-on-one isolations.</p>
        <p>Jalen Rose may be one of only a few Pacers who can create his own shot. But the sum of their parts -- Miller, Mark Jackson, Smits, Dale Davis and a deep bench -- makes them the most genuine team still left in the playoffs.</p>
        <p>''They are a unique team,'' Van Gundy said. ''Most teams in this league are probably more athletic than they are but there are no more skilled teams than Indiana. This is a great offensive team. They pass well, they shoot well, they know how to move the ball. They can shoot at any range.''</p>
        <p>Said Patrick Ewing: ''This team definitely has more firepower than Miami. Miami is a better defensive team than they are.''</p>
        <p>During the preseason, the Knicks met San Antonio in one of those National Basketball Association money-making excursions in which you find out more about your team before the season begins. Yet with the memory of their finals loss fresh, the Knicks came out and treated the game as if it meant something.</p>
        <p>''We treated it like a seventh game all because of the pain of losing in the finals,'' Van Gundy said. ''And they were, like, chilling out, because it was an exhibition game.''</p>
        <p>He shook his head. ''Our guys just don't understand it. I think it's not as much as adjusting to a new offense as it is a mental adjustment.''</p>
        <p>Like Camby said, re-work the mind. Before Reggie turns and fires.</p>
        <p>ON PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
