<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TRANSACTIONS</title>
    <meta content="25TRAN$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202358"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000525T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E5D9133DF936A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1525" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TRANSACTIONS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AUTO RACING</p>
        <p>NASCAR--Fined Winston Cup series driver Joe Nemechek $15,0000 and penalized him for rough driving during The Winston at Lowe's Motor Speedway.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AUTO RACING</p>
        <p>NASCAR--Fined Winston Cup series driver Joe Nemechek $15,0000 and penalized him for rough driving during The Winston at Lowe's Motor Speedway.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL  Major League Baseball</p>
        <p>MLB--Suspended Los Angeles Dodgers C Chad Kreuter, coach Rick Dempsey, coach John Shelby and coach Glenn Hoffman for eight games; LHP Carlos Perez, OF F.P. Santangelo and OF Gary Sheffield for five games; P Mike Fetters for four games; and RHP Terry Adams, RHP Darren Dreifort, RHP Eric Gagne, LHP Onan Masaoka, RHP Alan Mills, RHP Antonio Osuna, RHP Chan Ho Park, C Todd Hundley, 1B Eric Karros, OF Geronimo Berroa and OF Shawn Green for three games each for going into the stands during a fight with fans at Wrigley Field on May 16.</p>
        <p>American League</p>
        <p>CLEVELAND INDIANS--Placed RHP Paul Shuey on the 15-day disabled list, retroactive to May 21. Purchased the contract of RHP Tim Drew from Akron of the Eastern League.  KANSAS CITY ROYALS--Signed Tony Muser, manager, to a two-year contract extension.  MINNESOTA TWINS--Named Jerry Bell chief operating officer in addition to his duties as club president, and Chris Clouser chief executive officer.  OAKLAND ATHLETICS--Recalled INF Frank Menechino from Sacramento of the Pacific Coast League. Sent INF Jorge Velandia outright to Sacramento.</p>
        <p>National League</p>
        <p>ATLANTA BRAVES--Placed RHP Kevin McGlinchy on the 15-day disabled list. Recalled RHP Kerry Ligtenberg from Richmond of the International League.  NEW YORK METS--Signed INF Jed Hansen to a minor league contract.  PHILADELPHIA PHILLIES--Agreed to terms with OF Lawrence Alexander.  SAN FRANCISCO GIANTS--Activated OF Ellis Burks from the 15-day disabled list. Optioned RHP Ben Weber to Fresno of the Pacific Coast League.</p>
        <p>California League</p>
        <p>SAN JOSE GIANTS--Placed C Sammy Serrano on the disabled list, retroactive to May 23. Received C Bob Niemet from extended spring training.  SALEM AVALANCHE--Acquired RHP Steve Matcuk from Carolina of the Southern League. Sent RHP Rob Burger to Asheville of the South Atlantic League.</p>
        <p>Frontier League</p>
        <p>COOK COUNTY CHEETAHS--Signed RHP Gerald Yuscavage, LHP Nick Morris and RHP Raul Rivera.  DUBOIS COUNTY DRAGONS--Signed OF Ben Danosky. Released OF Tom Kuempel and RHP Todd Anderson.  JOHNSTOWN JOHNNIES--Released OF Daryl Rutherfod, LHP Rick Swanger, OF-1B Dawan Elliott, OF Mike Dieke and C Eric Mathews.  RIVER CITY RASCALS--Signed RHP Shawn Hoggs and OF Travis Dawson. Announced the retirement of RHP Josh Levey.  SPRINGFIELD CAPITALS--Signed LHP Jeremy Cox and RHP Chris Havens.</p>
        <p>BASKETBALL  National Basketball Association</p>
        <p>NBA--Fined Miami Heat owner Micky Arison $25,000, G Tim Hardaway $20,000, and F Jamal Mashburn $10,000 for criticizing officials following Game 7 of the Eastern Conference semifinals.</p>
        <p>Women's National Basketball Association</p>
        <p>MIAMI SOL--Signed F-C Karina Rodriguez.</p>
        <p>Continental Basketball Association</p>
        <p>CBA--Promoted Matt Correa from basketball operations coordinator to director of basketball operations.</p>
        <p>United States Basketball League</p>
        <p>ATLANTIC CITY SEAGULLS--Released C Alvin Robinson, F Eric Coates and G Donnie Seales.  FLORIDA SEA DRAGONS--Signed C Earl Ike. Activated G Keweemada King from the inactive list. Placed G Franklin Paul, G Brandon Wharton and F Ajani Williams on the inactive list.  OKLAHOMA STORM--Placed C Brett Robisch on the inactive list. Signed F Brian Montonati.</p>
        <p>FOOTBALL  National Football League</p>
        <p>ARIZONA CARDINALS--Signed OT Jerry Drake to a one-year contract.  ATLANTA FALCONS--Waived TE Brian Saxton.  CHICAGO BEARS--Named Scott Campbell director of pro personnel.  CINCINNATI BENGALS--Signed OT Willie Anderson to a six-year contract extension.  HOUSTON--Promoted Mike Maccagnan from pro scout to coordinator of college scouting.  JACKSONVILLE JAGUARS--Signed OL Mark Baniewicz.  NEW YORK JETS--Re-signed NT Jason Ferguson. Signed WR Windrell Hayes.</p>
        <p>Canadian Football League</p>
        <p>BRITISH COLUMBIA LIONS--Signed QB Donnie Davis.  CALGARY STAMPEDERS--Signed LB Kent Ring and QB Troy Kopp.  SASKATCHEWAN ROUGHRIDERS--Signed QB Keith Smith. Announced the retirement of QB Steve Sarkisian.</p>
        <p>Arena Football League</p>
        <p>LOS ANGELES AVENGERS--Signed DS Kevin Cobb. Activated FB-LB Brian Easter from the refused to report list. Activated FB-LB Terrance Petty from the injured reserve list and placed him on waivers. Placed OL-DL Bruce Walker on waivers. Placed DS Ken Haslip on the injured reserve list.  OKLAHOMA WRANGLERS--Signed QB Justin Fuente.</p>
        <p>SOCCER  Major League Soccer</p>
        <p>COLUMBUS CREW--Named Dave Stephany assistant director of public relations, Ryan Smith event manager and Kristine Hoolwerf marketing coordinator.</p>
        <p>VOLLEBALL  American Volleyball Coaches Association</p>
        <p>AVCA--Announced the resignation of Sandra L. Vivas, executive director, effective July 31.</p>
        <p>COLLEGE</p>
        <p>ATLANTIC 10--Announced Richmond will join the conference in all sports, effective July 1, 2001.  ARMSTRONG ATLANTIC--Named Michael Butler men's golf coach.  FLORIDA INTERNATIONAL--Named Joe Barantovich, Hurlie Brown, James Colzie, Carmen Grosso, Bruce Hardy and Curt Wiles assistant football coaches.  FRANKLIN--Named Lori Wilkerson assistant director of athletics and volleyball coach.  GREENSBORO--Announced the resignation of Bill Chambers, men's basketball and cross country coach.  HOUSTON--Announced the resignation of Chris Huston, women's soccer coach.  LEHMAN--Named Steven Schulman men's basketball coach.  MONTANA STATE--Announced the resignations of Heidi Tate, tennis director and women's tennis coach, and Dean Owen, men's tennis coach.  OREGON--Signed Bill Moos, athletic director, to a four-year contract extension.  PRESBYTERIAN--Named Paul Maxwell men's tennis coach.  SAN DIEGO ST.--Promoted Rick Bay from athletic director to executive director of athletics and special assistant to the president, and signed him to a five-year extension.  TIFFIN--Named Jeremy Croy track and field coach and women's cross-country coach.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
