<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With Smiles and Cell Phones, a Last-Minute Assault on the Undecided</title>
    <meta content="Y25SCE$09" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202196"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE CHINA TRADE VOTE: THE LOBBYISTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">China-International Relations-US</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">World Trade Organization</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rosenbaum, David E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000525T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE4D6143DF936A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="946" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With Smiles and Cell Phones, a Last-Minute Assault on the Undecided</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID E. ROSENBAUM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rosenbaum, David E</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 24</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Some 50 business lobbyists worked to nail down votes of undecided lawmakers before House passage of China trade bill; opponents of measure were also out in force, despite vote count that showed them losing; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>By this morning it was quite clear that the China trade bill would pass, but no one on either side was taking chances.</p>
        <p>From a stuffy conference room in the basement of the Capitol, about 50 business lobbyists were dispatched, cell phones in hand, in a final effort to nail down the votes of the dozen or so lawmakers who were still thought to be undecided.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>By this morning it was quite clear that the China trade bill would pass, but no one on either side was taking chances.</p>
        <p>From a stuffy conference room in the basement of the Capitol, about 50 business lobbyists were dispatched, cell phones in hand, in a final effort to nail down the votes of the dozen or so lawmakers who were still thought to be undecided.</p>
        <p>A lobbyist for Procter &amp; Gamble, for instance, was sent to see Representative Ernie Fletcher, a Republican from Kentucky. The company makes Jif peanut butter in Mr. Fletcher's district and employs 239 workers.</p>
        <p>An official from United Parcel Service went to see Representative Robert C. Scott, Democrat of Virginia. U.P.S. has a hub in Newport News in Mr. Scott's district.</p>
        <p>Representative Van Hilleary, Republican of Tennessee, had his arm twisted by a lobbyist from TRW, which has about 500 workers at an automotive plant in Morristown in Mr. Hilleary's district.</p>
        <p>''We can't afford to get overconfident,'' said Johanna Schneider of the Business Roundtable, an organization of giant corporations, who was working from the room in the basement, Room HC-8.</p>
        <p>And despite vote counts that showed them losing, the opponents of the measure were also out in force today. Scores of union members from back home were on the phone, and at least a dozen labor officials from across the country were on Capitol Hill.</p>
        <p>Art Pulaski, president of the California A.F.L.-C.I.O., paid a final call on Representative Henry A. Waxman, a Democrat from Los Angeles, who had not tipped his hand on how he would vote.</p>
        <p>In the end, Mr. Fletcher, Mr. Hilleary and Mr. Waxman voted for the bill. Mr. Scott voted against it.</p>
        <p>They, and the handful of other lawmakers who were truly undecided as the vote approached, were besieged in the last few days, and the pressure peaked this morning.</p>
        <p>''It's like a big wave hitting the shore,'' said Representative Vito J. Fossella, a Republican from Staten Island, who did not let on until just before the vote that he planned to support the legislation.</p>
        <p>He said he took a call this morning from a driver for U.P.S. whom he had met at a Boy Scout function on Staten Island last weekend. He was also called by members of the food workers union. The driver favored the trade bill; the food workers were against it.</p>
        <p>For the first time since he entered Congress three years ago, he said, he was lobbied by rank-and-file workers in financial services companies -- at the banks and brokerage houses and insurance companies -- who live on Staten Island, or in the slice of his district that is in southwestern Brooklyn, and work in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>''I finally decided, I don't see how voting no is in America's interest,'' Mr. Fossella said.</p>
        <p>For him and the others who were undecided -- most genuinely trying to weigh the national security and economic implications of the legislation as well as the direct interests of their constituents -- all the attention was exhausting.</p>
        <p>''I finally let people know today I needed some space to breathe,'' said Representative John E. Sweeney, a freshman Republican from upstate New York.</p>
        <p>He more or less decided overnight to vote for the measure, Mr. Sweeney said, but at 3 this afternoon he still had qualms and was following the debate on television in his office, ''just to make absolutely sure I'm making the right decision.''</p>
        <p>As a matter of policy, Mr. Sweeney said, he concluded that ''we lose a little more than we gain if the status quo remains.''</p>
        <p>''But in the end,'' he said, ''you always vote your district.''</p>
        <p>And his district, which includes Saratoga Springs and Glens Falls along the upper Hudson River, was divided.</p>
        <p>He heard, he said, from the dairy farmers and the apple and pear growers and small-business owners who favored the concept of expanded trade with China. And he heard from the paper workers and other union members who feared losing their jobs.</p>
        <p>Former President George Bush called recently. So did Defense Secretary William S. Cohen. The congressman was given a special briefing by the Central Intelligence Agency. Dennis Hughes, president of the A.F.L.-C.I.O. in New York, visited him on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>''I've talked to absolutely everybody,'' Mr. Sweeney said. ''It was a very hard call.'' He finally voted yes.</p>
        <p>Representative Peter Deutsch, a Democrat from southern Florida, dropped out of sight today while he pondered his decision. He took no calls and held no meetings.</p>
        <p>''I've made myself available to everybody for weeks,'' Mr. Deutsch said. ''Today I needed to think on my own.''</p>
        <p>He especially thought, he said, about the huge Motorola plant in his district with its 2,000 workers and its hopes of selling two-way radios in China.</p>
        <p>''There are very few values I would put above them,'' he said. ''But national security is one of them.''</p>
        <p>Just after lunch, about three hours before the vote, Mr. Deutsch decided to vote against the bill.</p>
        <p>THE CHINA TRADE VOTE: THE LOBBYISTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
