<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Internet Star Is Born</title>
    <meta content="12FILM$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206837"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MEDIA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E4DE173EF931A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1071" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Internet Star Is Born</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICK LYMAN</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, June 11</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>All Joe Nussbaum wanted was to have his foot in the door.</p>
        <p>''Basically, we made this short film last year, me and some old college friends, trying to get noticed by development executives and studio executives,'' said Mr. Nussbaum, a 27-year-old director. ''We made it as a calling-card film, which hopefully would open the door for major projects for us. Which it did. Which is great.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>All Joe Nussbaum wanted was to have his foot in the door.</p>
        <p>''Basically, we made this short film last year, me and some old college friends, trying to get noticed by development executives and studio executives,'' said Mr. Nussbaum, a 27-year-old director. ''We made it as a calling-card film, which hopefully would open the door for major projects for us. Which it did. Which is great.''</p>
        <p>The nine-minute film that Mr. Nussbaum directed is ''George Lucas in Love.'' It is a parody of the Oscar-winning ''Shakespeare in Love,'' except that instead of Shakespeare working through his writer's block to create ''Romeo and Juliet,'' it features a young actor playing the lovesick, college-age George Lucas surrounded by people recognizable as prototypes for the characters in Mr. Lucas's Star Wars series. Mr. Lucas attended the University of Southern California's film program, as did Mr. Nussbaum and his co-writer on the film, Daniel Shere.</p>
        <p>The film rapidly became an underground hit last summer in Hollywood, where private videotapes of it were eagerly passed around, resulting in a burst of national publicity and the beginnings of a directing career for Mr. Nussbaum. But it did not end there. In October, the movie became the debut attraction on a streaming-video Web site called Mediatrip.com. In April, it was released as a video, which is being sold exclusively through Amazon.com.</p>
        <p>On April 21, the film's first day of release, it immediately shot to No. 1 on the Amazon sales charts and has been in the top 10 almost every day since. On many of those days, it has even outsold the heavily promoted video release of Mr. Lucas's own ''Star Wars: Episode 1 -- The Phantom Menace.'' Even as recently as late last week, ''George Lucas in Love'' ($7.99) was No. 3 on the Amazon sales chart, and ''Episode 1'' ($16.95) was a distant No. 15.</p>
        <p>''That's strange, huh?'' said Austin Harrison, chief executive of Mediatrip. ''It's No. 3. That just cracks me up.''</p>
        <p>There has been much speculation in Hollywood about how the Internet might prove to be a solid showcase and lucrative marketing tool for films, like shorts, that never get  real theatrical runs. But ''George Lucas in Love'' is one of the first films actually to open on the Internet and then have success as a video release.</p>
        <p>Joseph Levy, the producer and another of Mr. Nussbaum's college friends, said the $25,000 it cost to make the film came out of the pockets of the director, the producer, the composer, the writers and others involved in the project. All the money they made selling the Internet rights to Mediatrip -- about $1,500 -- was plowed back into the film, Mr. Levy said, producing film prints that could be shown at film festivals. Only now, with the video sales, do the filmmakers stand to make some money.</p>
        <p>Inadvertently, Mr. Levy said, the filmmakers seem to have tapped into an audience of the Star Wars films and science-fiction fans, exactly the sort of people who are most likely to watch short films on the Internet.</p>
        <p>''Our only intention back when we made it last year was to do something that would get agents and producers to put the tape into their VCR's instead of throwing it away,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Although the video is now available only through Amazon, Mr. Harrison said plans are being made to expand sales to video stores and other outlets. International rights and sales to airlines and others are also being discussed. And by the end of the year, there will be a ''George Lucas in Love'' videodisc that will include the nine-minute short, profiles of the filmmakers and some extra features that Mr. Harrison was reluctant to discuss.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lucas has been a good sport about it all, praising the film and even requesting a copy of the poster promoting the movie, which was promptly sent to him.</p>
        <p>Initially, Mr. Nussbaum said, no thought was given to posting the film on the Internet. But then, several of the new, entertainment-oriented dot-coms began calling and making offers.</p>
        <p>''It was like, wow, we certainly didn't make this for the Internet, but we'd be fools not to put it on the Internet,'' Mr. Nussbaum said. ''What is it they say? If three people tell you you're drunk, you'd better sit down? Well, if four Internet sites tell you they want your movie, you'd better put it on the Internet.''</p>
        <p>When the numbers of people watching the movie on Mediatrip grew into the hundreds of thousands, with active chat rooms about the film and more than 600 posted reviews, it seemed only natural to try to release it on videotape, Mr. Harrison said. ''People would literally post on the bulletin board, 'When is the video coming out?' '' he said.</p>
        <p>Soon after the film had its first burst of publicity last summer, Mr. Nussbaum signed a couple of development deals for films that were never made.</p>
        <p>''They ended up going the way of many Hollywood movies,'' he said. ''They dissolved.''</p>
        <p>He is not complaining, though. He has been working regularly, making television commercials and is in the final stages of negotiating another studio deal for his feature-film debut. Since the movie came out, meanwhile, Mr. Levy has taken a job creating digital entertainment for the Internet.</p>
        <p>''We would always say to each other, 'How long is our window?' '' Mr. Nussbaum said. '' 'How long can you be the buzz? How long can you be the hot thing?' We figured it would be quite short. Of any industry in the world, Hollywood has been built on flashes in the pan. We fully expected that if we did well, it would have to be quick, we'd have to jump on it. But here it is, what, a year later? And it's still going.''</p>
        <p>MEDIA</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
