<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Stewart Takes a Lead Role As the U.S. Captures Its Cup</title>
    <meta content="12SOCC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206877"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SOCCER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E4D9173EF931A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="850" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Stewart Takes a Lead Role As the U.S. Captures Its Cup</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JERE LONGMAN</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., June 11</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A few days earlier, Earnie Stewart's face had swelled like a balloon, his diet had been reduced to bananas and his noted fear of flying had been matched by the universal nightmare of repeat visits to the dentist.</p>
        <p>''We almost sent him home,'' said Bruce Arena, coach of the United States men's soccer team.</p>
        <p>Stewart, the fleet wing who had a solid season in the Netherlands this year, had taken an elbow to the face on June 3 against South Africa in the first game of the U.S. Cup. Nerve damage to a tooth required three visits to the dentist for a root canal, a new filling and drainage of fluid that had left the right side of his face as puffy as pastry.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A few days earlier, Earnie Stewart's face had swelled like a balloon, his diet had been reduced to bananas and his noted fear of flying had been matched by the universal nightmare of repeat visits to the dentist.</p>
        <p>''We almost sent him home,'' said Bruce Arena, coach of the United States men's soccer team.</p>
        <p>Stewart, the fleet wing who had a solid season in the Netherlands this year, had taken an elbow to the face on June 3 against South Africa in the first game of the U.S. Cup. Nerve damage to a tooth required three visits to the dentist for a root canal, a new filling and drainage of fluid that had left the right side of his face as puffy as pastry.</p>
        <p>''I was in a lot of pain,'' Stewart said.</p>
        <p>The pain and swelling subsided, which was good news for the Americans, who defeated a severely weakened Mexico team, 3-0, today to win the U.S. Cup. Stewart showed cool professionalism in the wilting heat in front of 45,008 at Giants Stadium, setting up the first goal for Brian McBride, nearly scoring twice himself and demonstrating the possibility of creative, intricate combinations with the blistering Cobi Jones as the United States begins qualifying next month for the 2002 World Cup that will be held in Japan and South Korea.</p>
        <p>The Americans expect to open the semifinal round of qualifying in the North American, Central American and Caribbean region on July 16 at Guatemala or Antigua. For the Americans, erasure of the debacle that was the 1998 World Cup in France cannot begin quickly enough.</p>
        <p>The United States finished 32nd out of 32 teams, collapsing from deficient play on the field, indecisive coaching by Steve Sampson and internal finger-pointing by the players. There is a new coach and a seemingly new attitude among the Americans, who appear joined by a common purpose instead of being divided by malignant cliques.</p>
        <p>''I won't say much about it, but it's a lot better now,'' Stewart said.</p>
        <p>There are many questions still to be answered during World Cup qualifying. Four players missing today because of injuries -- forward Joe-Max Moore, midfielder Eddie Lewis and defenders Robin Fraser and Eddie Pope -- could make the starting lineup. And Tony Sanneh still has to learn that he is now playing right back, not cornerback, on defense.</p>
        <p>But Arena has repaired the tattered communication lines between coaches and players, who appear to have a clear sense of what is expected of them, when they must conform, when they have freedom.</p>
        <p>In the past, Stewart appeared to waste much of his time on the wing with aimless running. But there is a new purpose to his game, which could be troublesome to opponents as he continues his interchangeable shifting with Jones from midfield to forward and back again.</p>
        <p>''We don't have any problem substituting back and forth,'' Jones said. ''He can go up front a while, and I'll go wide, then he can go wide and I'll go up front. We've played together through two or three coaches, we're roommates on the road, pretty good friends. There's a natural knowledge of each other.''</p>
        <p>In the 33rd minute today, a magnificent three-pass combination put the Americans up, 1-0. Stewart played a ball from 30 yards out toward Jones in the middle of the field. Jones tapped it back to Stewart, who charged the penalty area, dribbled to the end line and crossed to McBride for a wide-open shot from 6 yards.</p>
        <p>''Bruce has given them to freedom to roam the field,'' the playmaker Claudio Reyna said of Stewart and Jones. ''When you have players who are allowed to roam with that kind of speed, it makes it difficult for defenders. Bruce gives them the chance to do what they do best. He doesn't stick them in one position. That creates a lot of danger.''</p>
        <p>Today's opponent was essentially the Mexican club team Pumas, not the Mexican national team. From the beginning, the Mexicans were overmatched. In the 70th minute, defender Christian Ramirez received his second yellow card for dragging Jones down on a breakaway and was ejected. Playing a man up for the final 20 minutes, the Americans scored twice more as Frankie Hejduk tipped in a Jones shot that deflected off the post and Ante Razov stole a sloppy back pass and slipped a left-footed shot into the net.</p>
        <p>A tired Stewart was replaced by Hejduk in the 76th minute, but he had played impressively with his quiet leadership and clamorous speed.</p>
        <p>''If you always stay in the same position, it's a lot easier for defenses to zone,'' Stewart said. ''If you're switching, it confuses defenses and you get guys open.''</p>
        <p>Ireland, which played to a 1-1 tie with the United States last week, earned second place in the tournament after defeating South Africa, 2-1, in today's second game at the Meadowlands.</p>
        <p>SOCCER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
