<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>METRO BRIEFING</title>
    <meta content="12MBRF$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206914"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E1D6173EF931A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1560" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>METRO BRIEFING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by Anthony Ramirez</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NEW YORK</p>
        <p>GUNS TRACED  Four Southern states with weak gun sale laws were the source of nearly a fourth of the guns used last year in crimes outside the state where they were purchased, according to a report released yesterday in Washington by Senator Charles E. Schumer. ''A vast network of gun runners uses our highways like firearms freeways to traffic illegal guns to criminals,'' said Mr. Schumer, a Democrat from New York. Using data obtained from the federal Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco and Firearms, a study by the senator shows that thousands of guns were channeled to buyers in the Northeast and Midwest, where state gun sale laws are stricter. Out of 30,453 guns used in crimes outside the state where they were first purchased, 7,494 were bought in Florida, Georgia, Mississippi or Texas, the senator's report said. New York, one of the states with strong gun sale regulations, suffers heavily from the inequality in gun sale laws, Mr. Schumer's report said. For instance, 1,685 guns used in  crimes in New York State last year were first sold in Florida, Georgia, the Carolinas or Virginia, while only 61 guns used there were first sold in New York.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NEW YORK</p>
        <p>GUNS TRACED  Four Southern states with weak gun sale laws were the source of nearly a fourth of the guns used last year in crimes outside the state where they were purchased, according to a report released yesterday in Washington by Senator Charles E. Schumer. ''A vast network of gun runners uses our highways like firearms freeways to traffic illegal guns to criminals,'' said Mr. Schumer, a Democrat from New York. Using data obtained from the federal Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco and Firearms, a study by the senator shows that thousands of guns were channeled to buyers in the Northeast and Midwest, where state gun sale laws are stricter. Out of 30,453 guns used in crimes outside the state where they were first purchased, 7,494 were bought in Florida, Georgia, Mississippi or Texas, the senator's report said. New York, one of the states with strong gun sale regulations, suffers heavily from the inequality in gun sale laws, Mr. Schumer's report said. For instance, 1,685 guns used in  crimes in New York State last year were first sold in Florida, Georgia, the Carolinas or Virginia, while only 61 guns used there were first sold in New York.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: UNION CANDIDATE  The New Directions Caucus, a faction of the Transport Workers Union, has chosen Roger Toussaint as its candidate in December's presidential election at Local 100, which represents 33,000 transit workers. Mr. Toussaint, who urged workers to reject last December's contract as not generous enough, said he had a good chance of winning because in 1997 the New Directions presidential candidate, Tim Schermerhorn, lost by just 600 votes. Last week the parent union appointed a monitor to oversee Local 100 finances, and Mr. Toussaint said he feared that the parent union would cancel the election and appoint a trustee to run the financially troubled local.</p>
        <p>Steven Greenhouse (NYT)</p>
        <p>BROOKLYN: FATAL CRASH  A 23-year-old Brooklyn man was killed and three people were injured early yesterday when a car crashed and rolled over on the Belt Parkway, the police said. The authorities said Igor Shafran, 26, of 2155 82nd Street was driving fast when he lost control about 4:50 a.m. The car struck a guardrail and flipped over, and Steven Duvidson, of 310 Brightwater Court, Brooklyn, died after being thrown from the rear seat, the police said. Two other passengers suffered minor injuries. Mr. Shafran, who was also ejected, was taken to Lutheran Medical Center, where he was listed in serious condition. He was charged with driving while intoxicated, the police said.</p>
        <p>C. J. Chivers (NYT)</p>
        <p>WHITE PLAINS: GUN BILL  The Westchester County Legislature has passed a scaled-down gun safety bill that requires owners to keep a locking device on their guns or to keep their guns in a locked container. In addition, devices like trigger locks must be included with all guns sold in the county. The bill originally required both locked containers and trigger locks, but it was revised after gun owners said the bill would be too restrictive and would make it hard to use weapons in self-defense.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>CONNECTICUT</p>
        <p>WINDSOR LOCKS: AIRPORT FEE  Passengers flying out of Bradley International Airport will find ticket prices going up. The airport plans to increase the fee it adds to each ticket, known as a facility charge, to $4.50, up from $3. The change would increase revenue from a source that has brought the state $38.3 million toward airport improvements since 1993, said Robert Juliano, head of the aviation and ports bureau of the State Transportation Department. In March, Congress approved an aviation bill that allowed airports to raise the charge, which typically is $3, to as much as $4.50.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>CALENDAR  Today</p>
        <p>TAX MEETING  The State Taxation and Finance Department holds an open meeting at 11 a.m. in Building 9, W. A. Harriman State Office Campus, Western Avenue, Albany. For more information: (518) 457-2244.</p>
        <p>Tomorrow</p>
        <p>POWER PLANT HEARING  State officials hold a public hearing to consider an application by Pacific Gas &amp; Electric for a certificate of environmental compatibility to build the nation's largest power plant in Athens, Greene County. Community and environmental groups say the plant would mar the landscape and disrupt a spawning ground for fish. The hearing is scheduled for 10 a.m. in Room A, Swan Street Building, Empire State Plaza, Albany. For more information: (518) 474-2500.</p>
        <p>ENVIRONMENTAL FUND</p>
        <p>A public hearing on North Hempstead's proposed Environmental Legacy Fund, at 7 p.m. at Marcus Avenue and New Hyde Park Road, Clinton G. Martin Park Auditorium, New Hyde Park. The $15 million fund would buy land and restore environmentally important areas and waterways. For more information: (516) 869-7710.</p>
        <p>MOSQUITO CONTROL  Public forum on mosquito-control efforts in Long Beach at 7 p.m. in Long Beach City Hall, 1 West Chester Street. For more information: (516) 571-6204.</p>
        <p>Thursday</p>
        <p>RENT PROPOSAL  Public hearings are scheduled on the New York City Rent Guidelines Board's proposal for the largest rent increases since 1996. The hearings are to be held at Cooper Union, at Seventh Street and Third Avenue, Manhattan. Testimony on residential hotels will be from 10 a.m. until noon, and testimony on apartments and lofts will be from 1 to 5:30 p.m. and 8 to 9:30 p.m. The deadline for speakers to register is 1 p.m. Wednesday. For more information: (212) 385-2934.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
