<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Home Prices Out of Reach For Many, Survey Finds</title>
    <meta content="12CITI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206886"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E0D8173EF931A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="736" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Home Prices Out of Reach For Many, Survey Finds</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL JANOFSKY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The nation's expanding economy has produced an unintended downside, rapidly increasing housing costs that are denying many working-class wage earners an affordable place to live, especially in urban areas.</p>
        <p>The growing gap is a major finding of the Clinton administration's fourth annual State of the Cities report, an assessment of the nation's economic health that otherwise reflects favorably on cities and suburbs that are enjoying overall low unemployment and high rates of home ownership.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The nation's expanding economy has produced an unintended downside, rapidly increasing housing costs that are denying many working-class wage earners an affordable place to live, especially in urban areas.</p>
        <p>The growing gap is a major finding of the Clinton administration's fourth annual State of the Cities report, an assessment of the nation's economic health that otherwise reflects favorably on cities and suburbs that are enjoying overall low unemployment and high rates of home ownership.</p>
        <p>But the economic growth that administration officials say has led to 22 million new jobs in the last seven years has helped push housing costs beyond the reach of many workers. The report found that the shortage of affordable houses and rental units is particularly acute in cities like Denver and San Francisco, where high-tech companies have led the boom.</p>
        <p>''We have become a victim of our own success,'' Housing Secretary Andrew M. Cuomo said in an interview. ''We have a great economy, and I hope it keeps going. But we also have to manage the downside of good economic times.'' Mr. Cuomo is scheduled to present the report today in Seattle at a meeting of the National Conference of Mayors.</p>
        <p>The report suggests that the federal government can help close the housing gap by providing more financial assistance in the form of vouchers that could be applied toward rental costs and, for the first time, mortgage costs.</p>
        <p>In that sense, the report does more than point out a problem: It also supports the administration's housing budget request for the 2001 fiscal year, a $32.1 billion proposal that represents a 23 percent increase over last year and would be the largest housing budget in two decades. Last week, the House Appropriations Committee approved all but $2.5 billion of the administration's request.</p>
        <p>The report concludes that the economic health of cities, in general, has continued to improve in recent years, spurred by job creation in high-tech industries that is three times the growth rate for jobs in other industries. The combination has resulted in a 4.7 percent population increase in the nation's 331 largest metropolitan areas between 1990 and 1998, compared with an overall decline of 3.1 percent from 1970 to 1980.</p>
        <p>While that swing has infused cities with a new vitality through ethnic and racial diversity, as the report says, it has helped drive up housing costs at a rate far beyond inflation. In cities like New York, Denver and San Francisco, competition for even small apartments has led to monthly rents of $2,000 and more.</p>
        <p>In addition, job growth in cities and a growing disdain for long commutes from the suburbs have led many people to seek housing closer to their city jobs, only to find that  prices in many neighborhoods are increasing at annual rates of 20 percent and more.</p>
        <p>The result, the report says, is a record number of ''worst case needs,'' which represents families who pay more than half of their income for housing or families in  inadequate housing. In 1997, the last year for which statistics are available, the number of these families reached 5.4 million, a 12 percent increase over the same group in 1991.</p>
        <p>''To make matters worse,'' the report said, ''the number of affordable housing units is shrinking just when it needs to expand.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Cuomo said the challenge for the Clinton administration in its final months would be to help moderate wage earners gain access to better housing while doing nothing that interrupts overall economic growth.</p>
        <p>What could make the efforts easier, he said, was what he perceived as a new willingness by Republicans to seek answers to the same problems. He recalled that four years ago Senator Bob Dole, the Republican challenger to President Clinton, favored eliminating the Housing Department.</p>
        <p>But after Mr. Cuomo's address today to the mayors, a majority of whom are Democrats, Gov. George W. Bush of Texas planned to lay out his plans for housing and economic development in a speech to the same group by satellite.</p>
        <p>''We've come a long way in four years,'' Mr. Cuomo said. ''Four years after Republicans wanted to get rid of us, Governor Bush has a competing plan. I'd say that was progress.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
