<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Foreign Affairs; Unfinished Business In Syria</title>
    <meta content="12FRIE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206913"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/Thomas L Friedman</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E4D6173EF931A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="840" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Foreign Affairs; Unfinished Business In Syria</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS L. FRIEDMAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>What is Hafez al-Assad's legacy? How should his epitaph read? That's an easy one. His gravestone should read: ''Hafez Assad, feared and ferocious president of Syria: He stayed too long and he died too soon.''</p>
        <p>That's Hafez Assad -- for years the Middle East leader most incapable of change, and then, finally, when he realized that change was mandatory if he wanted to turn over a stable Syria to his son, Bashar -- he bowed out before getting the really hard stuff done.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>What is Hafez al-Assad's legacy? How should his epitaph read? That's an easy one. His gravestone should read: ''Hafez Assad, feared and ferocious president of Syria: He stayed too long and he died too soon.''</p>
        <p>That's Hafez Assad -- for years the Middle East leader most incapable of change, and then, finally, when he realized that change was mandatory if he wanted to turn over a stable Syria to his son, Bashar -- he bowed out before getting the really hard stuff done.</p>
        <p>Let's look closely at Mr. Assad's ambiguous reign. What do we mean he stayed too long? Well, in the fall of 1977, just before going to Jerusalem, President Anwar Sadat of Egypt went to Damascus to meet with Mr. Assad and encourage him to follow Egypt's lead with Israel. Mr. Assad refused, and he spent the next 23 years resisting the Egyptian approach, and then trying to prove that he could get more from Israel and give less.</p>
        <p>And what does Mr. Assad have to show for those 23 years? Not much. At best he will remembered for what he didn't do, not for any positive accomplishments: He did not, in his eyes, ''sell out'' to Israel. He did not meet the embarrassing end of other Soviet-era dictators who were toppled by popular movements. With his brutal fist, he did not let ethnically divided Syria fall into civil war like Lebanon. He did not, like Saddam Hussein, allow himself to be sucked into a devastating war with the world's only superpower. He did not lose Syria's grip over Lebanon.</p>
        <p>So many ''He did nots.'' But not a lot of ''He dids.'' By any normal criteria, Mr. Assad would have to be judged one of the most overrated leaders ever. Economically, Syria today is a backwater -- the last country in the Middle East to introduce fax machines and the Internet, a country with a crumbling industrial base, a corrupt, 19th-century banking system, an utterly backward educational system and not a single world-class export of any product or service. If Syria were in Asia, it would be called North Korea.</p>
        <p>In recent years, though, Mr. Assad finally got the message -- that he had to modernize and open the country. And one of the people whispering that most often to him was his son and designated heir, Bashar. So Mr. Assad started bulldozing the road, but he left three huge boulders -- boulders that would have been difficult for even him to move, but will be even harder for his son, an eye doctor, who starts with much less legitimacy and none of his father's godfather-like skills at destroying enemies without mercy.</p>
        <p>The first and biggest boulder left for Bashar is modernizing Syria and shifting the base of Syrian unity from the war with Israel to building a 21st-century state. President Assad had begun that task last year with a series of internal purges, but it was slow going. Mr. Assad was ambivalent about opening Syria's windows, and he had created so many competing power centers, spying agencies and military units -- all of which reported to him and all of which he played against one another -- that when he initially tried to turn things over to his son, some of those power centers resisted. So father and son started purging: Former Prime Minister Mahmoud Zubi killed himself last month after being sent for trial on corruption charges. Former army chief Hikmat Shehabi also was targeted on corruption charges. But this is an unfinished war, and Bashar will not consolidate his rule, or be able to push his reform agenda, without winning some cock fights with other Syrian roosters.</p>
        <p>The second bit of unfinished business is the peace with Israel. Mr. Assad refused any compromise with Israel on the Golan, even when only 200 yards were left in dispute. He also refused to show any warmth to the Israeli people. Will Bashar be able to summon the strength and legitimacy to offer compromises his father would not, but which are essential for any deal with Israel?</p>
        <p>The last bit of unfinished business was Lebanon. Israel's unilateral pullout from south Lebanon has naturally triggered questions in Lebanon: If the Israelis are gone, why is the Syrian army still here? Bashar will eventually have to work out a new basis for Syria's continued presence in Lebanon. Not easy.</p>
        <p>It is rather fitting that Hafez Assad died in mid-conversation on the phone with the president of Lebanon. Because in many ways he was also in mid-conversation with the people of Syria and Israel as well. These were conversations too late in coming. Bashar will now have to finish the calls. I wonder what he'll say.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
