<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Pursuit of Microsoft: Rare Synergy With Company's Rivals</title>
    <meta content="12SOFT$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206848"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E4DD173EF931A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2140" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Pursuit of Microsoft: Rare Synergy With Company's Rivals</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVE LOHR</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>William H. Gates, the chairman of Microsoft, has no doubts about who is responsible for his company's antitrust woes. During a news conference last Wednesday, hours after a federal judge ordered that Microsoft be split in two, Mr. Gates spoke pointedly of the ''competitors that have been behind this lawsuit.''</p>
        <p>What part did Microsoft's rivals play? The competitors, to be sure, played a crucial role throughout the investigation, litigation and sanctions phase of the suit by the Justice Department and 19 states. It was, in fact, a 222-page white paper written in the summer of 1996 by lawyers for Netscape Communications, Microsoft's main rival in the market for Internet browsing software, that caught the attention of Joel I. Klein, head of the Justice Department's antitrust division, and prompted him to order an investigation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>William H. Gates, the chairman of Microsoft, has no doubts about who is responsible for his company's antitrust woes. During a news conference last Wednesday, hours after a federal judge ordered that Microsoft be split in two, Mr. Gates spoke pointedly of the ''competitors that have been behind this lawsuit.''</p>
        <p>What part did Microsoft's rivals play? The competitors, to be sure, played a crucial role throughout the investigation, litigation and sanctions phase of the suit by the Justice Department and 19 states. It was, in fact, a 222-page white paper written in the summer of 1996 by lawyers for Netscape Communications, Microsoft's main rival in the market for Internet browsing software, that caught the attention of Joel I. Klein, head of the Justice Department's antitrust division, and prompted him to order an investigation.</p>
        <p>At the trial, a procession of competitors -- representing Netscape, Sun Microsystems, America Online and others -- testified against Microsoft. And in the months and weeks before the government presented its proposal in April to break up Microsoft, industry executives -- some rivals of Microsoft and some not -- were shown or read individual sentences and paragraphs in drafts of the remedies plan by government lawyers, who then asked if the provisions seemed sensible.</p>
        <p>The scale of the antitrust case, including the extent of consultation with industry rivals, was extraordinary, government officials acknowledge. But the methods employed were not: Despite all the information and interpretation given to the government from other companies, industry executives and government lawyers say the Justice Department kept its own counsel as it sifted evidence and built its case.</p>
        <p>The government charged, and the court found, that Microsoft is a monopoly that has thwarted competition and innovation. Some of the evidence came from competitors, but much of it came from Microsoft's e-mail and internal documents.</p>
        <p>''The industry's role in a case like this is as a resource -- a source of ideas, comments, facts and analysis,'' said David Boies, the Justice Department's chief trial lawyer. ''But the government brought the Microsoft case because the evidence was there. And the most powerful documents were ones created by Microsoft itself.''</p>
        <p>Yet, to bring and win the Microsoft suit, the government had to build a relationship of cooperation and trust with the industry. When the investigation started in 1996, there was skepticism in Silicon Valley -- home to many of Microsoft's rivals -- about the wisdom of working with the government.</p>
        <p>A consent decree with Microsoft that the Justice Department signed in 1994, and that a court approved a year later, had mainly focused on a modest change in Microsoft's licensing practices. In Silicon Valley, the consent decree was regarded as a slap on the wrists that did nothing to loosen Microsoft's control of computing. So, many companies were reluctant to cooperate with the government and risk angering Microsoft.</p>
        <p>To meet with the Justice Department, some industry executives insisted on strict conditions to ensure anonymity. Late in 1997, the chief executive of a Silicon Valley company agreed to meet only at a hotel suite in Washington -- not at the Justice Department's offices -- and only with a promise that any notes of the meeting could not mention him or his company, recalled Daniel Rubinfeld, former chief economist in the department's antitrust division.</p>
        <p>The chief executive did eventually agree to send a senior member of his management team to testify in the Microsoft trial, which began in October 1998.</p>
        <p>Indeed, that kind of visible industry support -- sending witnesses to testify in a high-profile, high-pressure trial -- was needed to present a convincing case in court. And Justice Department officials stressed that point in meetings with industry executives. ''They did say repeatedly that if you don't stand up and take this on, neither will we,'' recalled William J. Raduchel, a former senior executive at Sun Microsystems who is now chief technology officer of America Online.</p>
        <p>Yet throughout the case, the government and Microsoft's competitors had a delicate, often wary relationship, according to both prosecutors and industry executives.</p>
        <p>And no wonder. The Justice Department's antitrust division receives a steady stream of complaints from companies about their rivals. Much of this proves untrue or exaggerated upon investigation, prosecutors note. And the government's policy is not to inform anyone in advance about whether it will take action.</p>
        <p>Several industry executives who cooperated in the prosecution described dealing with the Justice Department as ''speaking through a one-way mirror.'' The government officials asked questions, and they answered. That approach, apparently, remained consistent -- from the initial investigation, right through to consulting on the proposed remedies.</p>
        <p>One executive recalled being asked to comment on the government's sanctions plan. ''It was, 'Does this sentence make sense to you,' or 'If the following rule were in place, do you think PC makers would choose operating systems other than Microsoft's Windows,' '' the executive said. ''But you never quite know what they're up to. I had no idea they were going to propose breaking Microsoft in two.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Raduchel, who spoke with Justice Department officials several times in the last few years, remarked: ''I really believe that you can't lobby them. But what you can do is educate them. They gradually came to realize that seemingly arcane details of software really do matter.''</p>
        <p>The education process did take time. It took the government investigators a while to appreciate the legal significance of a meeting in June 1995 between Microsoft and Netscape executives, for example, even though the Justice Department received a detailed account of the meeting two days after it occurred.</p>
        <p>The account came in a letter to the department from Gary L. Reback, a lawyer representing Netscape, who described how Microsoft had used access to its industry-standard Windows operating-system technology to threaten Netscape. He also attached notes of the meeting taken by Marc Andreessen, co-founder of Netscape, which strongly suggested that Microsoft had made an offer to Netscape to divide the market for Internet browsing software -- an offer that, if proved, was a violation of antitrust law.</p>
        <p>That June 1995 episode eventually became an accusation in the government's suit against Microsoft, one that Judge Thomas Penfield Jackson accepted as a fact and ruled to be illegal. Yet at the time, word of the meeting did not set off alarm bells in Washington.</p>
        <p>''You have to understand that back then, the Internet was just starting to take off,'' said Roberta Katz, the former general counsel of Netscape, ''and people other than techies did not understand the Internet or software. The troops at Justice, understandably, had a lot of learning to do.''</p>
        <p>And Netscape certainly helped. ''My whole approach,'' Ms. Katz said, ''was to get to the point where they really understood what was going on. After that, if the government did anything or not was obviously up to them. And they totally held their cards closely. There was never a time when the Justice Department let us know what they were going to do.''</p>
        <p>The Netscape white paper in August 1996 helped get things started. Despite its dull title, ''White Paper Regarding the Recent Anticompetitive Conduct of the Microsoft Corporation,'' the paper often reads more like a book than a legal document. Indeed, its 222 pages are formatted and laid out like a book, with attractive typefaces and chapter headlines like ''A Fork in the Road'' and ''Microsoft's Fear: The Threat to Its Desktop Monopoly.''</p>
        <p>The Netscape white paper was never made public, but it was passed to some industry executives and state attorneys general, in addition to the Justice Department. An industry executive allowed a reporter for The New York Times to read parts of the document. It was written mainly by Mr. Reback and Susan Creighton, then both lawyers at Wilson Sonsini Goodrich &amp; Rosati in Palo Alto, Calif., with contributions from Garth Saloner, an economist at the Stanford University business school.</p>
        <p>The Netscape document includes a litany of accusations against Microsoft. These were backed up with e-mail messages that Netscape had received, from personal computer makers and others, about Microsoft's actions.</p>
        <p>But the one assertion that really interested Mr. Klein, the Justice Department's antitrust chief, was that in June 1996 Microsoft had threatened to cancel Compaq Computer's license to use Windows unless Compaq stopped featuring Netscape's browser over Microsoft's. To Mr. Klein, this seemed to be evidence of Microsoft's selling its Windows operating system to PC makers on the condition that the manufacturers also take the Microsoft browser. To him, the threat violated the 1994 consent decree and raised broader antitrust issues about the company's behavior.</p>
        <p>Microsoft has argued that its browsing software should be considered part of Windows -- one product, not two, and thus not an antitrust violation. In June 1998, a federal appeals court agreed with Microsoft in a related case. But after reviewing the evidence, Judge Jackson ruled that Microsoft had illegally tied two products.</p>
        <p>The government pursued some accusations in the Netscape white paper and set others aside. Over all, though, the legal and economic theory in the Netscape document is remarkably similar to the themes laid out in the government's suit two years later. The core of the case the Justice Department lawyers presented at trial was that Microsoft had illegally maintained its monopoly by engaging in a broad pattern of practices intended to stifle the competition posed by Internet software.</p>
        <p>''This is, at bottom, a very simple case,'' the Netscape white paper stated. ''It is about a monopolist (Microsoft) that has maintained its monopoly for more than 10 years. That monopoly is threatened by the introduction of a new technology (Web software) that is a partial substitute -- and, in time -- could become a complete substitute for the monopoly product.''</p>
        <p>The Netscape white paper also pointed toward a broader public-policy issue surrounding Microsoft. Personal computers were the way people get onto the Internet and thus, the paper asserted, Microsoft's industry-dominant Windows operating system could give the company a gatekeeper's control of the flow of information and electronic commerce in the future.</p>
        <p>''There is no reason to believe,'' the Netscape document warned, ''that Microsoft's monopoly power will be confined to a single industry.''</p>
        <p>That broader message resonated beyond the software industry, and eventually led executives in other industries to raise concerns about Microsoft with the government. Andrew Steinberg, who was then general counsel of Sabre, the computerized airline reservations system, recalled traveling through Silicon Valley early in 1997. Sabre had recently begun a travel Web site, Travelocity, and Microsoft had a competing site, Expedia. Mr. Steinberg was told of the Netscape white paper, and he obtained a copy from Netscape.</p>
        <p>Reading the document had a ''profound effect'' on him, recalled Mr. Steinberg, who is now an executive vice president of Travelocity. ''It struck me that this was a serious threat to competition over the Internet and the future prospects of our company.''</p>
        <p>Other industry executives had similar worries about Microsoft's power and its potential use of that power. Executives from many companies expressed such concerns in meetings with the Justice Department -- including those from Time Warner, Disney, Sabre, General Motors and Palm, according to people who attended or knew of those meetings.</p>
        <p>Further white papers were produced. Netscape updated its original document, and then provided still another with a more detailed focus on e-commerce and media over the Internet, ''Access Denied: Microsoft's Strategy for Overriding Consumer Choice.'' The other companies that sent white papers to the government included Apple Computer, Sabre and the makers of speech-recognition software, according to people familiar with those documents.</p>
        <p>The suit the government brought against Microsoft was based on accusations about what Microsoft had done, rather than what it might do. But the government has said it took action partly to protect innovation in the future and to keep the Internet open to competition.</p>
        <p>''The role of the browser as the gateway to the Internet was significant to bringing this case,'' said Mr. Boies, who presented the case against Microsoft in court for the Justice Department. ''It's what made this case important.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
