<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Paulson Ends Long Wait With Victory in the Buick</title>
    <meta content="12GOLF" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206905"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02EED7173EF931A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="981" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Paulson Ends Long Wait With Victory in the Buick</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFTON BROWN</byline>
      <dateline>HARRISON, N.Y., June 11</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After four holes of a sudden-death playoff, a 47-minute weather delay and 102 starts on the PGA Tour without a victory, Dennis Paulson finally tasted triumph today.</p>
        <p>Making a superb up-and-down on the final hole, Paulson won the Buick Classic on the fourth playoff hole, sinking a 4-foot putt to win after David Duval missed a 5-footer. Paulson's first career victory came the hard way, against a star-studded leader board on a demanding Westchester Country Club course that served as a prelude to this week's United States Open.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After four holes of a sudden-death playoff, a 47-minute weather delay and 102 starts on the PGA Tour without a victory, Dennis Paulson finally tasted triumph today.</p>
        <p>Making a superb up-and-down on the final hole, Paulson won the Buick Classic on the fourth playoff hole, sinking a 4-foot putt to win after David Duval missed a 5-footer. Paulson's first career victory came the hard way, against a star-studded leader board on a demanding Westchester Country Club course that served as a prelude to this week's United States Open.</p>
        <p>It ended on the par-4, 374-yard 17th hole, when Paulson turned the tables on Duval. Duval reached the front of the green in two shots, while Paulson's second shot went long, into the deep rough behind the green. But after Duval lagged his first putt within 5 feet of the hole, Paulson hit a magnificent chip to 4 feet, and Duval then missed his putt. That opened the door for Paulson, who made his par put to win the first-place check worth $540,000.</p>
        <p>Paulson (65-68-75-68), who started the day two strokes off the lead, and Duval (70-67-70-69) were eight under par for the tournament (276), one stroke ahead of Sergio Garcia of Spain, who finished third after losing a three-shot lead on the back nine. Greg Norman was fourth at six under, his best finish since last year's British Open.</p>
        <p>But for Paulson, who lost last year's Buick Classic in a playoff with Duffy Waldorf, the feeling of victory was almost indescribable.</p>
        <p>''It still hasn't hit me yet,'' said Paulson, a 37-year-old Californian who spent years playing on the Asian and Nike tours. ''It's going to be fun going to Pebble Beach and to be a bigger part of the story, instead of just another guy teeing up.''</p>
        <p>It was a difficult loss for Duval, the world's No. 2-ranked player, who has not won since April 1999. He said he was not sure what happened on his final putt, the missed 5-footer. ''I don't know if I pulled it, or just hit a bad putt, or if it just broke more than I thought,'' he said. ''I just missed.''</p>
        <p>On the third playoff hole, Duval made a terrific putt, a 40-footer uphill for birdie on the par-5, 526-yard No. 18 that nearly won the tournament. But Paulson answered with a pressure putt of his own, a 6-footer for birdie that forced the playoff.</p>
        <p>Paulson's putter was good to him all day. He earned his way into the playoff by making a sensational 35-foot putt for birdie during regulation at No. 18, which put him in the clubhouse at eight under par before the 47-minute delay. Duval was two groups behind Paulson, still on the course at eight under. But he missed birdie opportunities on the final two holes of regulation.</p>
        <p>Duval missed a 10-foot putt for birdie at No. 17. Then, after his tee shot at No. 18 landed in the fairway, the horn blew to suspend play because of lightning. After resuming play, Duval hit his second shot at No. 18, a 3-iron that hit the rock-hard green and bounced into the deep rough. Duval failed to get up-and-down from there, settled for par and headed into the playoff.</p>
        <p>The day started with Waldorf leading at seven under par, a stroke ahead of seven players. But most of those contenders faltered on the back nine.</p>
        <p>Earlier, Garcia was in excellent position, storming to a three-stroke lead after 10 holes by making five birdies. He drove the green on two par-4 holes -- the 326-yard No. 7 and the 314-yard No. 10. Both of those prodigious drives led to two-putt birdies, and Garcia left the 10th green three strokes ahead of Duval, Chris Perry and Joey Sindelar.</p>
        <p>But at No. 10, momentum began to swing from Garcia and toward Paulson and Duval. Garcia had a 12-foot putt for eagle at No. 10 but was distracted by a photographer's camera just as he was about to strike the ball. He backed away and glared at the cameraman, then missed the putt and settled for a birdie.</p>
        <p>Things soon got worse for the 20-year-old Garcia. He pulled his tee shot well left at No. 11, into the rough and under a tree. Instead of playing a safer shot and chipping back into the fairway, Garcia tried to hit a low 5-iron under the trees toward the hole. His club clipped a branch on his backswing, and he advanced the ball only about 40 yards, still in the deep rough. His next shot landed just short of the green, and after chipping 8 feet right of the hole, Garcia missed the putt and double-bogeyed.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Paulson made a 22-footer for birdie at No. 11, pulling him into a tie for the lead with Garcia. Garcia made a costly bogey at No. 17 to fall to six under, and even a birdie at No. 18 kept him one stroke out of the playoff.</p>
        <p>Still, Garcia, who shot a 65 Saturday and a 68 today after barely making the cut, was pleased with his best finish of the year. ''It shows I'm still the same guy as last year,'' said Garcia, the runner-up at last year's P.G.A. Championship.</p>
        <p>But for the first time in his career, Paulson won an event on the tour. Asked what it meant, he had a ready answer.</p>
        <p>''I know,'' he said, ''that I'm going to be able to move into my new house now, no problem.''</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
