<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="12DIGE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206846"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E5DD173EF931A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1034" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>U.S. Focus Groups Gauge Attitudes About Internet  In what may be the first comprehensive look at public attitudes about the Internet, results from focus groups held around the country by the nonprofit Markle Foundation showed that participants seemed to trust business over government to regulate the Internet, echoed the call of buyer beware when it came to privacy and fraud but also seemed to expect some type of rules or protections.</p>
        <p>The sessions were perhaps most significant in underscoring the complex and tough task facing policy makers around the world as they seek to govern the Internet. [C4.]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>U.S. Focus Groups Gauge Attitudes About Internet  In what may be the first comprehensive look at public attitudes about the Internet, results from focus groups held around the country by the nonprofit Markle Foundation showed that participants seemed to trust business over government to regulate the Internet, echoed the call of buyer beware when it came to privacy and fraud but also seemed to expect some type of rules or protections.</p>
        <p>The sessions were perhaps most significant in underscoring the complex and tough task facing policy makers around the world as they seek to govern the Internet. [C4.]</p>
        <p>Congress is expected to pass legislation this week that would make electronic signatures and records as legally binding as pen-and-paper versions. [C4.]</p>
        <p>Internet Cooldown Hasn't Hit Jobs  Despite the recent sell-off in technology stocks and an increasing number of failing dot-coms, the search for the best high-technology employees continues. True high-technology jobs remain an employee's market, with far more jobs than job candidates. But what has changed recently is what it takes to lure away a new senior-level employee: cash. Stock options, particularly in companies not yet public, have considerably less allure than they did just a few months ago. Now companies are finding they must pay more in salary and options as well as a bonus and other perks. New Economy. [C4.]</p>
        <p>Pledges Renewed to Ease Shopping  A report in 1998 showed that two-thirds of Web shoppers abandoned their ''shopping carts'' before buying something, and e-commerce companies pledged to improve the shopping experience. But because investors showed little inclination to penalize e-tailers for failing to close the sale, these resolutions were neglected, and consumers continued to abandon their carts. Now Web merchants are under pressure to make money, and they are suddenly getting serious in their efforts to squeeze whatever cash they can from site visitors. Bob Tedeschi: E-Commerce Report. [C14.]</p>
        <p>Diamond Stock Listing in Question  Oryx Diamonds, a company with close ties to the governments of Congo and Zimbabwe, may be thwarted in an effort to trade on the London Stock Exchange, executives close to the company said. [C16.]</p>
        <p>The All-in-One Telephone Number  A telecommunications engineer has patented a system that would allow people to have just one phone number for all their telecommunications devices, reducing the need for longer telephone numbers and more area codes. Sabra Chartrand: Patents. [C6.]</p>
        <p>A 'George Lucas' Sleeper Hit  ''George Lucas in Love,'' a nine-minute parody of ''Shakespeare in Love'' in which the lovesick, college-age George Lucas is surrounded by people recognizable as prototypes for the characters in his Star Wars series, rapidly became an underground hit last summer in Hollywood. But it did not end there. In October, the movie became the debut attraction on Mediatrip.com, a streaming-video Web site. And in April, it was released on videotape, sold exclusively through Amazon.com. On April 21, the film's first day of release, it immediately shot to No. 1 on the site's sales charts. [C15.]</p>
        <p>Summer TV Becomes Less Stagnant  Summer, which for most of television history has been a desert of reruns and rejects, has suddenly become perhaps the best place to roll out a new show, especially if it takes some risks and breaks new ground. [C15.]</p>
        <p>Machine Tool Orders Decline 22%  Orders for machine tools decreased an estimated 22 percent in April, to $450 million from a revised $577 million in March. [C16.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
