<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>As the Coliseum Comes Down, a Long-Missing City Vista Starts to Open Up</title>
    <meta content="12MATT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206897"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="METRO MATTERS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Metro Matters</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E2D7173EF931A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="795" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>As the Coliseum Comes Down, a Long-Missing City Vista Starts to Open Up</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOYCE PURNICK</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DON'T look now, but 59th Street is back.</p>
        <p>Actually, do look now at what used to be New York City's intolerable hulk, the Coliseum on Columbus Circle. It could be a few months from disappearing forever, and despite the unsightliness of the demolition job on Broadway between 58th and 60th Streets, this happens to be one breathtaking scene.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DON'T look now, but 59th Street is back.</p>
        <p>Actually, do look now at what used to be New York City's intolerable hulk, the Coliseum on Columbus Circle. It could be a few months from disappearing forever, and despite the unsightliness of the demolition job on Broadway between 58th and 60th Streets, this happens to be one breathtaking scene.</p>
        <p>Come to Columbus Circle and see sun, light and air, of which New York has much too little. There's so much sun and sky, you could be in Phoenix. Despite the rubble, the hanging black drapes of safety netting, the dangling concrete slabs, the site is all opened up.</p>
        <p>It won't be for long, but the coming replacement for the Coliseum and its companion 26-story office building at 10 Columbus Circle doesn't look as though it will make the same mistakes.</p>
        <p>What was always wrong about the Coliseum was its original conception. It was, as an exhibition hall, broad and impenetrable, a wall of blond brick. There it sat at the gateway to Central Park -- an unblinking barrier.</p>
        <p>It was windowless, squat, and erased 59th Street between Broadway and Columbus Avenue. Obliterated it. There was nothing particularly great about that stretch of 59th Street, but it was part of the city's fine east-west grid, which creates the perception of light and space. The grid allows glimpses of sky, of the Hudson and East Rivers. Of New Jersey.</p>
        <p>''The Coliseum closed off 59th Street,'' said Kent Barwick, president of the Municipal Art Society. ''For a long time, we were urging the city to do a better job, so when you went down Central Park South you could see that there was sky there. That's the great feature of Manhattan. Even though we have skyscrapers, we see light at the end of the tunnel.''</p>
        <p>Twelve years ago, Metro Matters argued (not quite seriously) that 59th Street between Broadway and Columbus Avenue should make a comeback and predicted (quite seriously) that it never would. Well, M.M. was technically right, but figuratively wrong. Apologies. The razing of the Coliseum has returned 59th Street to us in spirit.</p>
        <p>Of course, that won't last; a location that rivals the Arc de Triomphe's for drama is not about to stay vacant. Soon, maybe by the fall, construction will begin for Columbus Centre, two 750-foot towers on a large base, to be built by Related Companies. The project emerged from more than 15 years of false starts, litigation and an economic crash that killed an earlier proposal. It will include the headquarters of Time Warner, studios for its Cable News Network and New York 1 television news operations, restaurants, stores, a hotel, condominium apartments, a 12-screen movie theater, up to 600 parking spaces -- and the first permanent home for Jazz at Lincoln Center.</p>
        <p>It is hardly low-rise or scaled modestly in any way. But thanks to city planners, community critics, its own architects and Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani, who intervened and thwarted another design, Columbus Centre shows no signs of becoming a walled-in colossus. The city and the Metropolitan Transportation Authority, owner of the property, imposed design guidelines that, among other things, were aimed at opening up the 2.5 million-square-foot project. Its main feature is dividing the site with a ''view corridor'' -- space -- about where 59th Street would be.</p>
        <p>THE final design is to be announced June 28. City officials say that the two towers will be separated by 85 feet, 25 feet more than the width of the typical city street. The project's 150-foot-high base, 50 feet higher than the Coliseum, is hardly small. But it is to have a glass ''curtain,'' a spectacular Central Park view from the jazz center, and views from the outside  into the center.</p>
        <p>If the advance billing is accurate, the design doesn't sound like another blank wall.</p>
        <p>So New York isn't really getting back a piece of 59th Street, but the next best thing -- the sense that it is there. Plus, the city rebuilt the park opposite the Coliseum site, simplified the spaghetti of streets and messy parking areas around the statue of Columbus, and created a real traffic circle.</p>
        <p>Given the history of this bedeviled corner of Manhattan, maybe more trouble lurks. Maybe Columbus Centre won't be as advertised. Or maybe New York City will have finally given itself a world-class treat.</p>
        <p>Amazing what rediscovering a bit of 59th Street can do.</p>
        <p>METRO MATTERS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
