<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Addis Ababa Journal; Where Stuffed Hyena Dwells With Emperor's Bed</title>
    <meta content="Y12ETHI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206863"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E5DB173EF931A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1221" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Addis Ababa Journal; Where Stuffed Hyena Dwells With Emperor's Bed</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By IAN FISHER</byline>
      <dateline>ADDIS ABABA, Ethiopia</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sometime when Sebatu Gebre Yesus was  young  he cannot remember when -- he began collecting things. This is unusual for at least two reasons. Not many Ethiopians are collectors. At 79, far along a life of quiet closeness to power and heartbreak because of it, he claims to be the only one.</p>
        <p>Second, he is a collector who makes no distinction between the priceless and the junky. A pair of Baccarat chandeliers from the palace of Emperor Haile Selassie sit not far from a souvenir thermometer larded with a fat Napoleon. Bronzes from Benin, worth a small fortune, are just down the way from a bongo with a split drumhead. He owns a Monet, along with bizarre portraits of unknown children. He will take orphaned runt or pedigree, and love it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sometime when Sebatu Gebre Yesus was  young  he cannot remember when -- he began collecting things. This is unusual for at least two reasons. Not many Ethiopians are collectors. At 79, far along a life of quiet closeness to power and heartbreak because of it, he claims to be the only one.</p>
        <p>Second, he is a collector who makes no distinction between the priceless and the junky. A pair of Baccarat chandeliers from the palace of Emperor Haile Selassie sit not far from a souvenir thermometer larded with a fat Napoleon. Bronzes from Benin, worth a small fortune, are just down the way from a bongo with a split drumhead. He owns a Monet, along with bizarre portraits of unknown children. He will take orphaned runt or pedigree, and love it.</p>
        <p>''Favorites?'' asks Mr. Gebre Yesus, a trim man with a white goatee and a neat gray suit with three buttons. ''No difference to me. I respect them all as good friends. But no preferences, like with my children.''</p>
        <p>This makes a tour though Mr. Gebre Yesus's new museum here -- opened to the public in May after a lifetime in the making -- an eclectic experience. It is apparently the only private collection in Ethiopia open to the public, and if it were only a collection of Mr. Gebre Yesus's fancies it would still be an interesting, certainly idiosyncratic, addition to Ethiopia's heritage. (The steps leading up the museum, for instance, are decorated with six bombs from the struggle with the Italians, dressed up as planters.)</p>
        <p>But the place has an emotional center: Mr. Gebre Yesus's troubled relationship with the emperor himself, deposed in 1974, feeble and, some say senile, but considered a deity in parts of the Caribbean. Mr. Gebre Yesus got a hold of the emperor's bed, made of iron and gilt and maybe nine feet tall, before he took the crown in 1930. He has his lawn furniture, his bamboo rocking chair, the heraldry worn by his horse.</p>
        <p>And in the first room of the museum is a painting, which Mr. Gebre Yesus recently commissioned, of himself standing in a courtroom before the emperor. The room also has a series of works on Ethiopia's beating the Italian Army on the battlefield in 1896, but this painting is definitely not about victory.</p>
        <p>''Never on my side -- never,'' Mr. Gebre Yesus said, standing in front of the painting. ''But still he used my services all the time. It was a terrible time for me. Financially I was crushed. He did it deliberately.''</p>
        <p>He had known the emperor since boyhood, because his sister was married to the emperor's chauffeur. So the emperor made sure all the children were educated, and Mr. Gebre Yesus as a boy had what he calls an ''active mind.'' He loved languages, and learned English, French and Italian. He said the emperor begged him to join the government but he refused. Still, he translated several books -- one on English common law -- for the emperor.</p>
        <p>What he loved most was plants, and he became a landscaper (his work is on display at the new and truly sumptuous Sheraton here in Addis Ababa). He had a garden, where he bred the best quality plants and where the emperor went to rest, fully documented in Mr. Gebre Yesus's collection of photographs.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gebre Yesus, with eight children to feed, also dabbled in property -- and here was the problem with the emperor. The people around the emperor wanted Mr. Gebre Yesus's land and slowly, though the machinery of Haile Selassie's autocratic and centralized state, he lost his holdings. The painting documents one of the legal disputes, presided over by the emperor. Mr. Gebre Yesus lost.</p>
        <p>''He gave me education, of course, and we had good family relations,'' he said. ''But at the later stage he was a danger for me. He was very unfair.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Gebre Yesus lived much longer, bought some of the emperor's things -- including his baroque living room furniture -- and now is charging a token price of admission for people to see it. Most of the emperor's belongings, bought at auction here, are in the Ethiopian heritage section -- one of 10 different parts of the museum. The others include porcelain, household ornaments, paintings, African art and Western art.</p>
        <p>Nearly every section is a tribute to the high and the low. There are four dozen or so clocks, some ornately carved antiques, some bland plastic. There are Ethiopian manuscripts and fine paintings by modern Ethiopian artists, as well as a shelf filled with two stuffed crocodiles, a lizard and a dusty, ratty hyena. He likes hats, coins, miniatures, silverware, musical instruments, old Ethiopian crosses, busts, books, maps, photographs.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gebre Yesus has an aversion to debt, so the museum itself was built slowly over the last four and a half years. The house itself, built the same slow way, is distinct: a fortress with passageways, a replica of an Ethiopian obelisk and a sculpture of Mr. Gebre Yesus himself perched on a second story.</p>
        <p>''When you do it yourself, you can play,'' he said.</p>
        <p>His collection came together over decades, and followed no particular course. He bought whatever fancied him, from the Ethiopian countryside, from merchants, from markets in England or France or West Africa.</p>
        <p>''I was always very much interested in anything that attracted my mind,'' he said. ''I never cared if it was precious or not as long as I liked it.''</p>
        <p>He is baffled that he has never met another Ethiopian with his passion for collecting things. Around Africa, where most people are poor, collecting is a rare thing to find.</p>
        <p>''I always wondered why other people didn't follow me in this matter,'' he said. ''Not even my friends, my closest friends. They don't care how much pleasure I feel in this. It is really unbelievable, but they don't understand it.''</p>
        <p>''It is a habit,'' he said on a tour of  the museum. ''I can't stop.''</p>
        <p>He can pause, however, and did so at an old phonograph with a wooden crank.</p>
        <p>''Let me show you,'' he said. He wound the crank. He had to replace the needle, and his hands had trouble putting it into the arm. After some work, the turntable began to move, the new needle dropped down and the voice of Nat King Cole, singing ''Too Young,'' spun out of the phonograph horn at 78 revolutions per minute.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gebre Yesus smiled. The music was old and crackly but lovely.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
