<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Devils Put the Cup to Bed With a Good-Night Kiss</title>
    <meta content="12HOCK" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206908"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New Jersey Devils</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E5D6173EF931A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="963" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Devils Put the Cup to Bed With a Good-Night Kiss</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Joe Lapointe</byline>
      <dateline>DALLAS</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Along with enthusiasm for their Stars and friendly manners toward visitors, the hockey fans of Texas show a sophistication about the sport that belies their recent arrival in the National Hockey League.</p>
        <p>So when the Devils won the Stanley Cup late Saturday night with a 2-1 victory in the second overtime, a group of men and women in Stars jerseys gathered near the glass as the Devils players posed for pictures with the trophy for about half an hour.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Along with enthusiasm for their Stars and friendly manners toward visitors, the hockey fans of Texas show a sophistication about the sport that belies their recent arrival in the National Hockey League.</p>
        <p>So when the Devils won the Stanley Cup late Saturday night with a 2-1 victory in the second overtime, a group of men and women in Stars jerseys gathered near the glass as the Devils players posed for pictures with the trophy for about half an hour.</p>
        <p>''Skate the cup!'' they chanted, some of them with cameras in their hands. ''Skate the cup!'' It is a modern tradition for teams to take the silver prize in a long, slow procession, holding it high, passing it from hands to hands.</p>
        <p>The Devils, clinching on the road before subdued applause, had simply forgotten. Finally, with about 2,000 people left in Reunion Arena, somebody remembered to start the parade and the Devils went one, tired lap to the respectful applause of their gracious hosts.</p>
        <p>You could excuse their temporary amnesia regarding protocol. Jason Arnott's goal, at 8 minutes 20 seconds of the second extra session, had ended a grueling six-game series that seemed longer. Game 5, a 1-0 Dallas victory, had ended in the third overtime on Friday morning. So the two teams had played more than nine full periods in a span of about 52 hours.</p>
        <p>Arnott, who beat Ed Belfour from close range after a setup from Patrik Elias on Saturday night, had left Game 4 after being hit by the stick-clenching gloves of Dallas defenseman Derian Hatcher. ''I had headaches,'' Arnott said. ''I was a little hazy, but there wasn't anything that was going to stop me. I was going to go through a brick wall if I had to play. Nothing was going to keep me out.''</p>
        <p>Arnott and Elias had extra motivation Saturday because their linemate, Petr Sykora, finished the game in a local hospital bed. He had left the ice on a stretcher in the first period after Hatcher flattened him with a hard check to the head.</p>
        <p>''Our hearts went out to him,'' Arnott said of Sykora. ''To see him get carried off like that was tough. Especially for Patty. They are so close. Patty and I looked at each other and said 'We've got to do this for our boy.' That goal was for him.''</p>
        <p>It also helped people forget about Arnott's cross-checking penalty, late in the first overtime, that gave Dallas a power play that extended into the second overtime. ''I didn't want my teammates to jump on me,'' Arnott said. ''I kind of said it was a bad penalty and kill it off for me, boys, and we'll see what happens.''</p>
        <p>What happened was the second tournament championship for the franchise in six seasons and the end of an era. The Dallas fans, who had celebrated the championship last season, stood near the glass and watched the sincere and sentimental celebration of the Devils players. Claude Lemieux, the veteran, had tears in his eyes as he hugged Scott Gomez, the rookie. Elias lay on the ice, near the spot of Sykora's injury, with Sykora's jersey draped over his chest, as he talked on a cell phone.</p>
        <p>The four Russian players -- Vladimir Malakhov, Sergei Nemchinov, Alexander Mogilny and Sergei Brylin -- gathered around the cup and posed for a photographer. Scott Stevens, the captain, had two trophies to hoist and trouble doing it. He also won the Conn Smythe trophy as most valuable player in the playoffs.</p>
        <p>''It's heavy,'' he said of the cup, ''and I've got a bad shoulder. So it was tough to lift it up.''</p>
        <p>Ken Daneyko, the other veteran defenseman, stood in the corridor outside the locker room for more than an hour, wearing his full uniform. He is 36 and the senior Devil, having joined the team in 1983.</p>
        <p>Daneyko wants to play next season but, with an expansion draft later this month and inevitable churn of a roster, there is no guarantee he will ever again wear the Devils uniform. He used words like ''cherish'' and ''grateful'' and ''heart'' when telling of what this meant to him.</p>
        <p>Along with players, much else might change for the Devils. John McMullen, the owner, is selling the team to the YankeeNets combine. Although General Manager Lou Lamoriello and Coach Larry Robinson will be asked to return, it is not a sure thing that they will be back. As hockey people often do in times like these, Robinson spoke of family, especially of his first grandson, born during the playoffs. Now, he finally gets a chance to see the baby.</p>
        <p>Turning to other subjects, he spoke of the incredible tension of the final two games. ''I think hockey can be really, really proud of the last two games,'' Robinson said. ''I don't think you are ever going to see two buildings that are more tense, with people sitting on the edge of their seats.''</p>
        <p>Robinson reflected on his coaching career, which saw him leave Los Angeles last summer after four undistinguished seasons as a head coach. He returned to New Jersey as an assistant to Robbie Ftorek and replaced the fired Ftorek with eight games left in the regular season.</p>
        <p>A year ago, could Robinson have imagined this scene?</p>
        <p>''Dream on,'' he said.</p>
        <p>ON HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
