<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>3 More Killed as Surge in Crime Continues Throughout Weekend</title>
    <meta content="12CRIM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206889"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01EFD8173EF931A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1184" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>3 More Killed as Surge in Crime Continues Throughout Weekend</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By C. J. CHIVERS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>An outbreak of violence that began Friday night continued unabated yesterday as three people were killed and 28 others were stabbed or shot in attacks throughout the city, the police said.</p>
        <p>The latest crimes included violence in the hours after the Puerto Rican Day Parade -- in which three people were stabbed within 20 minutes; drive-by shootings; robberies gone awry; old disputes that simmered anew and an attack on a group of Hasidic Jews on the Boardwalk in Coney Island that the police described as a bias attack.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>An outbreak of violence that began Friday night continued unabated yesterday as three people were killed and 28 others were stabbed or shot in attacks throughout the city, the police said.</p>
        <p>The latest crimes included violence in the hours after the Puerto Rican Day Parade -- in which three people were stabbed within 20 minutes; drive-by shootings; robberies gone awry; old disputes that simmered anew and an attack on a group of Hasidic Jews on the Boardwalk in Coney Island that the police described as a bias attack.</p>
        <p>Those crimes and others pushed the weekend's toll of violence to unusually high levels. In all, from Friday night through yesterday, the police recorded 40 attacks in which 59 people were shot or stabbed. Six of the victims died.</p>
        <p>''It was a very busy weekend,'' said Marilyn Mode, the Police Department's senior spokeswoman. But she noted that there had nevertheless been less crime than on a typical weekend a decade ago. Murders in the city peaked at 2,245 in 1990, an average of six a day.</p>
        <p>Most of the cases were unsolved yesterday and the authorities said the reasons behind many of the crimes were not clear. Rank and file officers said the surge in violence was partly a result of a brief but oppressive heat wave that made some people irritable, pushed them out of their homes, and increased the number of violent encounters on the street. ''Warm weather, more activity,'' an officer said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Mode rejected that idea. She said no clear pattern could be deduced from the reported attacks. ''I wouldn't make a correlation with the weather,'' she said. ''All of these incidents appear unrelated, and for the most part they appear to be between people who knew each other.''</p>
        <p>''We see ups and we see downs,'' Ms. Mode said.</p>
        <p>The violence after the parade cast a shadow over what had been a festive celebration.</p>
        <p>At 5:05 p.m, a man was stabbed in the face at 87th Street and Madison Avenue, the police said. About 15 minutes later, a 21-year-old man was stabbed in the neck in front of a garage at 115 East 84th Street. Then at 5:25 p.m., the police said, a 30-year-old man was stabbed at 78th Street and Madison Avenue.</p>
        <p>All three victims were in stable condition at various hospitals, the authorities said. None of their names was released, and the police have no suspects and recovered no weapons.</p>
        <p>Not far away, at 86th Street and Lexington Avenue, a person lay bleeding in the gutter, struck in the head by an object that the police believed had been thrown from the roof of an apartment building.</p>
        <p>Yesterday's violence began just after midnight on West 125th Street in Harlem. The police said two groups of young men met on the street between Seventh and Eighth Avenues and tried to settle a long-standing dispute.</p>
        <p>In the ensuing fight, the police said, one of the men, Jose Jones, 20, drew a knife and was then shot repeatedly in the torso. Mr. Jones was pronounced dead at Harlem Hospital minutes after the fight ended. One other young man was shot in the buttocks and four were stabbed. The police said all the men were being questioned and charges were expected to be filed.</p>
        <p>The day's second homicide occurred hours later in Coney Island. The police said that Rudolph Thomas, 23, was found dead at 3:40 a.m. at the intersection of West 24th Street and Mermaid Avenue, the victim of several gunshot wounds. There were few leads and no arrests in the case, the police said.</p>
        <p>Late yesterday, officers in the 72nd Precinct discovered the body of a third homicide victim on the roof of 535 56th Street in Sunset Park, Brooklyn. The man had been stabbed several times, the authorities said. His name was withheld pending the notification of his family.</p>
        <p>In addition to the homicides, detectives were also investigating an attack on eight young Hasidic men as they walked along the Coney Island Boardwalk at 4:20 a.m. The authorities said the men were approached by a group of Hispanic men who yelled anti-Semitic remarks and then assaulted the Hasidim with fists and knives. Four of the young men were stabbed, the police said.</p>
        <p>One of the victims, Matis Gluck, 19, was in critical but stable condition at Coney Island Hospital. The others -- Levi Bensh, 20, Nastali Stauer, 19, and Alexander Follman, 19 -- were treated at the same hospital and  were in stable condition.</p>
        <p>The victims' friends and families gathered at the hospital yesterday, expressing sadness and anger over what they described as a ruthless attack.</p>
        <p>They said the victims were members of the Bobov sect from the Flatbush and Borough Park neighborhoods, and had been attacked and overpowered by as many as 15 men as they walked along the moonlit beach.</p>
        <p>''They were probably out getting something to drink and eat,'' said Mark Bassie, a friend of the stabbed youths. ''They wanted to relax in the city. You tell me the last time Jews were out looking for trouble.''</p>
        <p>Another friend, who declined to give his name, said Mr. Bensh was near death when he arrived at the hospital but his condition had stabilized and he was showing signs of improvement by late in the day.</p>
        <p>Sgt. Gerry Falcon, a police spokeswoman, said the attack on the Hasidic men was being investigated by the department's Hate Crimes Task Force. All the assailants fled after the attack, and there were no arrests as of last night.</p>
        <p>The police said another unprovoked crime occurred around 3 a.m. in East New York, Brooklyn, when two armed men opened fire at a group of people sitting on a stoop at 611 Blake Street. Four people sitting on the steps were struck by bullets and taken to Brookdale Hospital.</p>
        <p>None of the injuries was life-threatening, the police said. The police said the crime had no apparent motive. There were no arrests in the case.</p>
        <p>Detectives were also investigating a double shooting in a Harlem courtyard, at 301 West 130th Street. The police said an argument between two men at 1:30 a.m. escalated when one of the men pulled a pistol and opened fire.</p>
        <p>The man missed his intended victim, but struck Timothy Watson, 21, in the leg and arm, and Mr. Watson's mother, Betty Parker, 50, in the buttocks, and fled. Mr. Watson and Ms. Parker were in stable condition at St. Luke's-Roosevelt Hospital Center. The gunman was not found.</p>
        <p>Two early morning drive-by shootings, one on Atlantic Avenue in East New York and the other in the Fordham section of the Bronx, were also unsolved yesterday. In both cases, the victims were struck by a single bullet each and were in stable condition.</p>
        <p>Ms. Mode said the weekend's tally of crimes was not cause for concern because police statistics indicate that crime rates are still lower than they have been in decades. ''We're still at a level of activity not seen since the '60's,'' she said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
