<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lukas Shows Prowess As Savvy Handicapper</title>
    <meta content="12BELM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206868"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HORSE RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00EFDB173EF931A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1022" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lukas Shows Prowess As Savvy Handicapper</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE DRAPE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Last week D. Wayne Lukas sat down with a legal pad, made columns for his competition in the Belmont Stakes and listed the pros and cons of each horse's chances of winning the third leg of the Triple Crown. The upside of the long shot Hugh Hefner, for example, was that the colt was the lone speed in the race. The downside: he could not carry it one and a half miles.</p>
        <p>The favorite, Aptitude? He would be too far back and have too much to do. When the columns were examined, Lukas believed his colt Commendable had a shot at winning for a single reason. ''He could run his natural race with his tactical speed and have a say in the outcome,'' Lukas said yesterday. ''Everyone else had to change their running styles.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Last week D. Wayne Lukas sat down with a legal pad, made columns for his competition in the Belmont Stakes and listed the pros and cons of each horse's chances of winning the third leg of the Triple Crown. The upside of the long shot Hugh Hefner, for example, was that the colt was the lone speed in the race. The downside: he could not carry it one and a half miles.</p>
        <p>The favorite, Aptitude? He would be too far back and have too much to do. When the columns were examined, Lukas believed his colt Commendable had a shot at winning for a single reason. ''He could run his natural race with his tactical speed and have a say in the outcome,'' Lukas said yesterday. ''Everyone else had to change their running styles.''</p>
        <p>Both scouting reports turned out to be true Saturday. Commendable tracked the front-running Hugh Hefner to the mile mark and scooted past him on the final turn. Aptitude, meanwhile, was in 10th place and indeed too far back to run down Pat Day and Commendable in the stretch.</p>
        <p>Now that the Triple Crown is completed with three horses owning a piece of it, Lukas, as well as horse racing enthusiasts, might as well get out that legal pad again. About the only thing the spring classics proved this time around was that the 3-year-old champion would not be decided until late summer or next season.</p>
        <p>As spectacular as Fusaichi Pegasus looked in the Kentucky Derby, he looked just as ordinary in losing to Red Bullet in the Preakness. As professional as Red Bullet looked in the Preakness, he looked merely competent in finishing second to Fusaichi Pegasus in the Wood. Only because both horses were withheld from the Derby was Commendable -- a horse that had sandwiched a fifth place, four fourth places and a 17th place between his maiden victory and the Belmont score -- can have a claim (at least on paper) to being the best in his generation.</p>
        <p>Now what? The trainer of Red Bullet, Joe Orseno, tossed off a challenge to his competitors yesterday. He said his colt, a victor in four of five starts, was headed to the Grade II Dwyer at Belmont on July 9, the Grade I Haskell for $1 million at Monmouth on Aug. 6, and on to the summer showcase for 3-year-olds, the Grade I Travers, also for $1 million, on Aug. 26 at Saratoga.</p>
        <p>''That's where we're going to be if they want to come,'' Orseno said.</p>
        <p>One horse that Orseno and Red Bullet will hook amid that campaign is More Than Ready -- the Blue Grass runner-up whose fourth-place Kentucky Derby finish was remarkable in light of the blistering pace he helped press. The trainer Todd Pletcher says he will use the mile-and-a-sixteenth Dwyer as a prep for the mile-and-an-eighth Haskell.</p>
        <p>''I think his speed is suited to that distance,'' said Pletcher, who will wait and see how More Than Ready performs before deciding on the mile-and-a-quarter Travers.</p>
        <p>Lukas says Commendable is also a likely starter in the Haskell. Somewhere in that trio of races Red Bullet could also see Postponed, the Peter Pan winner, and Unshaded, the Belmont's third-place finisher. Unshaded's trainer, Carl Nafzger, believes his late-blooming gelding is suited for the Travers and will decide between the Haskell and the Jim Dandy, which is run on the same weekend at Saratoga. His owner, James Tafel, anted up a $100,000 supplemental fee to get in the Belmont only to watch Unshaded's big move in the final turn be sapped by mild heat exhaustion. The gelding wobbled past the finish line and was immediately treated with water and ice. He was fine yesterday, and had earned back the $100,000.</p>
        <p>''The Travers is the race I've wanted since before the Kentucky Derby,'' Nafzger said.</p>
        <p>The situation is just as muddled out West, where Fusaichi Pegasus; The Deputy, the Santa Anita Derby winner; and High Yield, Lukas's top horse and the Blue Grass winner, are based.</p>
        <p>Lukas says High Yield will probably start in the Swaps on July 23 at Hollywood Park. The Deputy and War Chant -- trained by Neil Drysdale -- are also probable starters in the Swaps. The trainer Bobby Frankel says Aptitude, runner-up in the Derby and the Belmont, will stay in New York until he decides where to run him.</p>
        <p>Most important, Drysdale has not decided where his big horse, Fusaichi Pegasus, will run next. Pegasus was scratched from the Belmont last week after cutting his hoof in his stall. Drysdale and the colt's owner, Fusao Sekiguchi, will meet this week in Los Angeles and map out a campaign aimed at winning the $4 million Breeders' Cup Classic on Nov. 4 at Churchill Downs.</p>
        <p>Drysdale will not say for certain, but he may wait until the fall to prep against older horses -- perhaps in the Woodward, a $500,000 race on Sept. 16, and the $1 million Jockey Club Gold Cup on Oct. 14. Both are Grade I races at Belmont.</p>
        <p>''It's premature, but if Mr. Sekiguchi is thinking about the Dubai World Cup next spring,'' Drysdale said by telephone from California, referring to the $5 million race, ''we'll probably not race in the summer. It would be too much on the horse.''</p>
        <p>Last year at this time, the Lukas-trained Charismatic had captured the Derby and the Preakness, and had finished third at the Belmont despite injuring a foreleg in the far turn. The colt had surgery, was retired and was eventually named 3-year-old champion. The Hall of Fame trainer, whose third-string colt gave him his 13th Triple Crown victory, says that this year's spring classics are a wash.</p>
        <p>''Nothing is decided,'' Lukas said. ''In the second season or summer season, we're all going to have to face each other and sort it out.''</p>
        <p>HORSE RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
