<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Media Talk; No More Dog Days of Summer in TV Land</title>
    <meta content="12TUBE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206829"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E7DE173EF931A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="531" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Media Talk; No More Dog Days of Summer in TV Land</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL CARTER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The main thing that the latest television phenomenon, CBS's ''Survivor,'' has in common with the previous television phenomenon, ABC's ''Who Wants to Be a Millionaire'' is not the $1 million ultimate prize.</p>
        <p>The main thing is that both started out as answers to the question: What did you do on your summer vacation?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The main thing that the latest television phenomenon, CBS's ''Survivor,'' has in common with the previous television phenomenon, ABC's ''Who Wants to Be a Millionaire'' is not the $1 million ultimate prize.</p>
        <p>The main thing is that both started out as answers to the question: What did you do on your summer vacation?</p>
        <p>Summer, which for most of the history of television has been a desert of reruns and reject programs, has suddenly become maybe the best place to roll out a new show, especially if it is one that takes some risks and breaks new ground.</p>
        <p>One reason, as numerous television executives have begun to realize, is that in the summer, competition is all but nonexistent. But more important, a show with a fresh approach can fill a crying -- and growing -- need in the rest of the media for something -- anything -- to talk about.</p>
        <p>As Stu Bloomberg, the co-chairman of ABC Entertainment put it, ''In summer, if you have a hit, you have all the attention to yourself.''</p>
        <p>All the attention means dozens upon dozens of interview shows on cable channels and radio stations, joke after joke from David Letterman and Jay Leno and Conan O'Brien, reams of newspaper copy and endless chat on Web sites. The media have become a ravenous beast, with a massive maw, that demands to be constantly fed.</p>
        <p>''If a show can get all that media to itself, it's much much easier to become a hit,'' said Steve Sternberg, a senior vice president with TN Media, a firm that buys television commercial time for advertisers. ''Just like with 'Millionaire,' the media was all over 'Survivor.' It instantly became a water-cooler show. The idea that people won't watch anything in the summer is nonsense. Not everyone is on vacation.''</p>
        <p>The media wave that has emerged from ''Survivor'' has caught the attention of one network that had not committed many resources to summer programming, NBC. Garth Ancier, the president of NBC Entertainment, acknowledged, ''With 'Survivor' grabbing all that attention, we have to have a different strategy for summer.'' Mr. Ancier said NBC has already committed a new budget for programming next summer.</p>
        <p>''I think you'll see every network gearing up for next summer,'' Mr. Sternberg said, ''especially this kind of escapist programming. The key to launching new shows may become finding the place where everybody else is doing repeats.''</p>
        <p>CBS already has much of the rest of this summer locked up with the next iteration of the genre, a broader experiment in televoyeurism called ''Big Brother,'' set to occupy 90 nights beginning on July 6.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sternberg said that one interesting angle to the networks' sudden interest in summer may be how the surge in viewing affects cable channels, which have always taken advantage of the networks' ''gone fishing'' attitude toward the summer months.</p>
        <p>''There definitely may be people who watch less cable this summer because of all this,'' he said.</p>
        <p>BILL CARTER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
