<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bench Finds It Hard To Replace Bryant</title>
    <meta content="12INDY$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206933"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="N.B.A. FINALS: LAKERS VS. PACERS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Indiana Pacers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Los Angeles Lakers</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E3DF143EF931A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="878" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bench Finds It Hard To Replace Bryant</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRIS BROUSSARD</byline>
      <dateline>INDIANAPOLIS, June 11</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With the Los Angeles Lakers' second option on offense, Kobe Bryant, sidelined by a sprained left ankle tonight, forward Glen Rice was expected to go back in time and sink 3-pointers as if it were 1997, the year he was named the most valuable player of the All-Star Game. Relegated to the status of role player this season, Rice was supposed to relish the opportunity to be center Shaquille O'Neal's sidekick.</p>
        <p>But rather than replace Bryant's 20-something points a game, Rice fizzled beneath the intensity of the raucous Conseco Fieldhouse crowd and the pressure of a suddenly tenacious Indiana Pacers defense. Managing only 7 points on 3-of-9 shooting, Rice, the former long-range shooting king, was helpless in stopping the Pacers' charge toward a 100-91 victory in Game 3 of the National Basketball Association finals. Rice's impact was so small that Coach Phil Jackson sat him for all but two minutes of the fourth quarter.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With the Los Angeles Lakers' second option on offense, Kobe Bryant, sidelined by a sprained left ankle tonight, forward Glen Rice was expected to go back in time and sink 3-pointers as if it were 1997, the year he was named the most valuable player of the All-Star Game. Relegated to the status of role player this season, Rice was supposed to relish the opportunity to be center Shaquille O'Neal's sidekick.</p>
        <p>But rather than replace Bryant's 20-something points a game, Rice fizzled beneath the intensity of the raucous Conseco Fieldhouse crowd and the pressure of a suddenly tenacious Indiana Pacers defense. Managing only 7 points on 3-of-9 shooting, Rice, the former long-range shooting king, was helpless in stopping the Pacers' charge toward a 100-91 victory in Game 3 of the National Basketball Association finals. Rice's impact was so small that Coach Phil Jackson sat him for all but two minutes of the fourth quarter.</p>
        <p>''I thought they bodied Glen well off of any screens we tried to provide for him,'' Jackson said. ''He caught the ball, he was crowded and pushed into driving. He got a couple of his baskets off the drive and lost the ball a couple of times off the drive. They identified Glen very well, and I thought they prevented him from getting good looks.''</p>
        <p>Rice's inability to create scoring opportunities off the drive combined with his poor defense on Jalen Rose (21 points) and Austin Croshere (12 points) led Jackson to play him only 27 minutes. After a quiet first quarter in which he scored 2 points, Rice sat for the first eight minutes of the second. Upon re-entering the game, he quickly scored 5 points, including a 3-pointer with seven-tenths of a second left in the half. But the shot was no omen.</p>
        <p>Rice, who made 5 of 6 3-pointers in scoring 21 points in Game 2 on Friday night, after scoring 3 points in Game 1 on Wednesday, went scoreless the rest of the way tonight.</p>
        <p>''I definitely think their defense was a little more aggressive,'' Rice said. ''I just don't think it was a great effort in getting myself involved more. And I spent a little too much time on the bench. I don't know why I was on the bench so long, but we've got Game 4 coming up and we just have to get back to doing the things we did in the first two games.''</p>
        <p>The Lakers, who throughout these playoffs have shown a disturbing propensity to rest on their laurels, felt comfortable before the game after winning Games 1 and 2 of the four-of-seven-game series in Los Angeles. That comfort may have kept them from using Bryant, who walked into Jackson's office 35 minutes before the game and said: ''I can go. I can try it.''</p>
        <p>But Bryant said he felt pain after some lateral slides, and the coach kept him out.</p>
        <p>''He said, 'It hurts,' '' Jackson said. ''I said, 'Well then, let's save it.' We can save this one. And it was a tough decision, but I think it's better for us actually in the long run.''</p>
        <p>Forward Rick Fox said: ''He could've played tonight. It wasn't a do-or-die situation.''</p>
        <p>Most of the Laker players said they expected Bryant to play Game 4 on Wednesday. But Gary Vitti, the Lakers' athletic trainer, refused to speculate. ''This is an inexact science,'' Vitti said. ''He's made very good progress from the time of the injury to right now. I'm very pleased with how it looks. Whether he will continue to progress at this rate, I don't know.''</p>
        <p>The Lakers got 33 points from O'Neal and 14 points from 36-year-old Ron Harper, but no more than 10 from anyone else. They missed Bryant, a first-team all-N.B.A. defender, as much on defense as on offense.  With Bryant in the locker room heating and icing his ankle, the Pacers' perimeter scorers had a ball. Reggie Miller broke out of his two-game slump by scoring 33 points, 5 more than he had in the first two games combined.</p>
        <p>With or without Bryant, the Lakers know they are in for a competitive series. Fox said the Pacers were bolder, brasher and much more aggressive than in the first two games. He said they also attempted to get in the Lakers' heads.</p>
        <p>''They tried to protect the home floor in more ways than one -- verbally, physically, almost psychologically,'' Fox said. ''But you have to understand we come from a psychological background now. That's maybe something we may not have been known for before. We deal with our coaching staff constantly testing us physically, mentally and even sometimes spiritually. This is nothing new.''</p>
        <p>Fox, who had a brief exchange with Rose in the second quarter, seems to be trying to establish a role as an enforcer for the Lakers. When asked what he and Rose were talking about, Fox, who is married to Vanessa Williams, the singer and actress, joked, ''I think Jalen's a fan of my wife's.''</p>
        <p>He then turned serious and said things were getting heated between the clubs.</p>
        <p>''I don't like anybody who stands in the way of a championship,'' Fox said. ''It's battle. It's war.''</p>
        <p>N.B.A. FINALS: LAKERS VS. PACERS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
