<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Let Artistic Gray Areas Be, as Long as Truth Is Out</title>
    <meta content="12REVI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206826"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="REVISIONS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804EFDF173EF931A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1306" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Let Artistic Gray Areas Be, as Long as Truth Is Out</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Margo Jefferson</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Given how many things -- politics, economics, cultural moods and movements -- we preface with amorphous terms like ''post,'' ''trans,'' ''global'' and ''multi,'' we're clearly in a state of high anxiety about how to define them. Definitions mean boundaries, and all of these terms make clear that the boundaries we once knew are disappearing. At most we have borders now, meant to be crossed, redrawn or erased.</p>
        <p>Look at the furor over the Tony-winning show ''Contact.'' It was nominated as a musical. It is all dance and music built around three revuelike sketches, one in pantomime. But the American Federation of Musicians protested the use of tape instead of live music. So did others, Tony voters among them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Given how many things -- politics, economics, cultural moods and movements -- we preface with amorphous terms like ''post,'' ''trans,'' ''global'' and ''multi,'' we're clearly in a state of high anxiety about how to define them. Definitions mean boundaries, and all of these terms make clear that the boundaries we once knew are disappearing. At most we have borders now, meant to be crossed, redrawn or erased.</p>
        <p>Look at the furor over the Tony-winning show ''Contact.'' It was nominated as a musical. It is all dance and music built around three revuelike sketches, one in pantomime. But the American Federation of Musicians protested the use of tape instead of live music. So did others, Tony voters among them.</p>
        <p>A musical must have an original score, people I spoke to said. (The dances in ''Contact'' use an antic mix of music: classical, jazz and rock; Tchaikovsky, Bizet, Stephane Grapelli, Benny Goodman, ''Do You Wanna Dance?,'' ''Runaround Sue'' and more.) What kind of encouragement does this give to lazy, cynical producers who don't want to risk money on more expensive productions with new music that the public must learn to love?</p>
        <p>It's true that the musical can't thrive without new composers. But consider the cultural crimes that have been committed in their name? No sooner did Andrew Lloyd Webber loosen his hold on Broadway than Frank Wildhorn and Elton John arrived.</p>
        <p>The best new composers and lyricists are getting their start in small houses off Broadway's beaten, musically abused track. ''Contact'' imitators aren't likely to be anywhere near as smart or talented as its choreographer and director, Susan Stroman, or its book writer, John Weidman. But that's always the case with imitators, whatever they're copying.</p>
        <p>The musical has been in such bad shape for so long that I'm game for all experiments. Call ''Contact'' a dance play or a musical performance piece; invent a new category for shows that put music, movement and language together in unpredictable ways.</p>
        <p>However it's done, let a show like ''Contact'' stir people to keep inventing musicals instead of copying them. Its form was unusual, but its impulse was primal. It showed us that musicals don't exist except to convince us that the people onstage always feel a song coming on, and therefore, in the succinct words of Gene Kelly, ''Gotta dance, gotta dance, gotta dance.''</p>
        <p>Literature, too, is in something of a tizzy over definitions, appropriations, genres and such. Fiction and nonfiction use each other's techniques. History and fantasy combine forces; memory is both lying and truth telling. And nowhere is all of this clearer than in the historical novel. Look at the furor that broke out a few weeks ago over Susan Sontag's historical novel ''In America'' (Farrar Straus Giroux). It was based on the life of the great Polish actress Helena Modjeska, who emigrated to the United States in 1876 and lived a glamorous and dazzling life. Ms. Sontag has been accused of taking passages from the works of historians, journalists and Modjeska herself that are virtually unchanged and unacknowledged beyond a briefly expressed debt to ''material and anecdotes used and altered.''</p>
        <p>And naturally other writers of historical fiction, as well as historians, began debating the conjunction between what you invent and what you borrow, and what you need to tell the reader about this process. Some go no further than acknowledging the libraries where they did their research. Others supply short bibliographies. I suspect it's often a struggle: what novelist doesn't want to get as much credit as possible for creativity and inventiveness?</p>
        <p>Ms. Sontag's solution, as reported in The New York Times on May 27, was to dismiss the historians and journalists in question, along with Modjeska, as being merely information sources, not writers. She said that while they supplied the raw matter, she produced a work of art. But what interested me most in the end was the question of how history -- fact if you will -- shapes characterization.</p>
        <p>Expressing her surprise that Modjeska scholars were not thrilled, Ms. Sontag concluded: ''She was a great figure. I made her into a marvelous person. The real Modjeska was a horrible racist.''</p>
        <p>Well, I thought, the race card does pop up in unexpected places. Ms. Sontag certainly tries to make her heroine marvelous by propping her up with period dialogue, letters, journals and aphoristic musings. But I would much rather read about a woman of great talent and charisma -- a marvelous creature indeed -- who was also a woman with monstrous beliefs. I want to feel and understand all of this. I don't want things to be prettified and simplified in the name of literary uplift.</p>
        <p>While I was thinking about all this, a 12-year-old friend with excellent taste recommended a historical novel that she loved, Ann Rinaldi's ''Hang a Thousand Trees With Ribbons''(Gulliver Books/Harcourt Brace). It was about yet another immigrant artist (an immigrant by force, not choice), the 18th-century slave and poet Phillis Wheatley. And it presented a good test; I am not alone in having always found poor Phillis an aesthetic trial and psychological embarrassment, despite her interest historically.</p>
        <p>She was taught to read and write by her relatively enlightened Boston owners, petted and coddled as she began to write poems, then examined on her Greek, Latin and verse by a group of Massachusetts men who included the governor and John Hancock. It was then certified that she had indeed written the poems in question.</p>
        <p>One heard from childhood about her precociousness, her piety and her well-behaved poems. What could one feel besides pity or contempt for lines like these, in ''On being brought from AFRICA to AMERICA''?</p>
        <p>Twas mercy brought me from my Pagan land,</p>
        <p>Taught my benighted soul to understand</p>
        <p>That there's a God, that there's a Saviour too;</p>
        <p>Once I redemption neither sought nor knew.</p>
        <p>Ms. Rinaldi doesn't quote these lines in her novel. She quotes very few of Wheatley's proper, Alexander Pope-inspired, acutely melancholy poems. She gives us the Phillis Wheatley who had to learn how to be pious and conventional -- the price of a young slave girl's education -- and who sometimes fought, sometimes embraced her role as the symbol of how a debased race might prove itself worthy of civilization. She shows us how the writing, which always had to meet the approval of her owners and their friends and doubting publishers, was as much genteel bondage as intellectual or spiritual freedom.</p>
        <p>She gives us a spunky, high-strung Phillis Wheatley, but also a Phillis who is crushingly dependent on the kindness of strangers who become first her owners, then her family. She needs to believe in some form of salvation, and she needs to display spiritual obedience. Thanks to Ms. Rinaldi, I now understand what it took for her to write the next lines of that poem, the only racial defense that Puritan Boston and Christian Britain would understand.</p>
        <p>Some view our sable race with scornful eye,</p>
        <p>''Their colour is a diabolic die.''</p>
        <p>Remember, Christians, Negros black as Cain,</p>
        <p>May be refin'd, and join th' angelic train.</p>
        <p>Do I like these lines any better than I did before? No. But now I understand the circumstances and the needs that make her admirable, infuriating and, almost unbearably, sad.</p>
        <p>Give us the infuriating, the shameful and the horrible. The purely noble and marvelous are much too simple.</p>
        <p>REVISIONS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
