<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hard to Ban, Soft Money Is Even Difficult to Define</title>
    <meta content="15SENA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/15/politics/15SENA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230671"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE SENATE CAMPAIGN: THE CHALLENGE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lazio, Rick A (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Levy, Clifford J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000915T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E4D61338F936A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="993" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hard to Ban, Soft Money Is Even Difficult to Define</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFFORD J. LEVY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Levy, Clifford J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>So-called soft money is a more complicated campaign finance issue than it might seem from the thrusting and parrying over it in the Sept 13 debate between Rep Rick A Lazio and Hillary Rodham Clinton; Clinton has raised several million dollars in soft money, and Lazio none, but he has benefited from spending by Republican committees and outside groups independent of the political parties, which is technically not soft money but is effectively the same (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''Let's just get this deal done right now,'' Representative Rick A. Lazio told Hillary Rodham Clinton at their debate on Wednesday night, trying unsuccessfully to persuade her to sign a pledge barring the use of so-called soft money in their Senate race. With a stroke of the pen, Mr. Lazio declared, the two could alter the landscape of modern-day politicking.</p>
        <p>But as with other issues debated, like health care, the thrusting and parrying over soft money obscured a more complicated reality. To begin with, while Mrs. Clinton and Mr. Lazio insist that they favor a ban on soft money in their contest and have issued proposals to to adopt one, they cannot even agree on what soft money is.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''Let's just get this deal done right now,'' Representative Rick A. Lazio told Hillary Rodham Clinton at their debate on Wednesday night, trying unsuccessfully to persuade her to sign a pledge barring the use of so-called soft money in their Senate race. With a stroke of the pen, Mr. Lazio declared, the two could alter the landscape of modern-day politicking.</p>
        <p>But as with other issues debated, like health care, the thrusting and parrying over soft money obscured a more complicated reality. To begin with, while Mrs. Clinton and Mr. Lazio insist that they favor a ban on soft money in their contest and have issued proposals to to adopt one, they cannot even agree on what soft money is.</p>
        <p>Both sides presumably realize that an informal ban with no legal force, drawn up by the very political consultants who have mastered the art of injecting soft money into elections, would be difficult to police.</p>
        <p>It would not be enough for the two candidates to forswear raising soft money in the New York race: they would have to persuade dozens of other politicians to do so as well, from state party leaders to senators in Washington. Not to mention other political groups, some of which are secretive about their activities.</p>
        <p>So the calls for a ban are seen by some experts as a tactic meant to paint the opposition as corrupt. ''I've seen a lot of these pledges, and they are about political advantage, not about results,'' said Fred Wertheimer, president of Democracy 21, an advocacy group that lobbies for tighter campaign finance restrictions.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wertheimer said the only way to rid the campaign finance system of soft money would be to approve legislation pending in Washington, which both candidates favor.</p>
        <p>The two campaigns continued their maneuvering yesterday, with officials holding news conferences and issuing statements to declare that their standard-bearer was the real reformer. But there seemed no movement toward a deal.</p>
        <p>To many advocacy groups unhappy with the campaign finance system, soft money is a major culprit because it essentially allows politicians to circumvent the donation limits for federal races: $1,000 for a primary and $1,000 for a general election.</p>
        <p>Political parties can raise soft money in unlimited amounts from anyone, including unions and corporations. The parties can legally spend it only on so-called party-building activities, like voter drives, not on items that help candidates' campaigns. But the parties have sidestepped the restriction by using soft money to buy commercials that promote or criticize candidates without directly mentioning the elections.</p>
        <p>In alliance with Democratic leaders, Mrs. Clinton has raised several million dollars in soft money -- it is hard to pin down amounts because the donations are channeled through different committees -- in addition to the nearly $22 million in so-called hard dollars she has collected for her official campaign committee.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio has taken in $19.2 million for his campaign committee, and has so far not collected soft money, but he has benefited from spending by Republican committees and outside groups independent of the political parties, like the Republican Leadership Council, which backs moderate Republicans. Technically, this outside spending is not soft money because it is not done by parties, but it is effectively the same.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio has repeatedly called on Mrs. Clinton to forgo the use of soft money. She has responded that she would if Mr. Lazio could persuade the outside groups to stay out of the race. The Clinton campaign says it considers outside spending in its definition of soft money. The Lazio campaign has usually referred to soft money as that spent only by parties.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, Mr. Lazio's campaign manager, Bill Dal Col, wrote to his counterpart on the Clinton campaign, Bill de Blasio, that if Mrs. Clinton agreed to a ban, Mr. Lazio would send letters to these outside groups asking that they ''immediately cease and desist from any political activities designed in any way to influence the outcome of this election.''</p>
        <p>It is unclear how many of these groups would oblige.</p>
        <p>Mr. de Blasio responded with a letter in which he called on the Lazio campaign first to obtain signed pledges from 14 groups that the Clinton campaign believes are trying to defeat Mrs. Clinton, including the American Conservative Union and the Conservative Leadership Political Action Committee.</p>
        <p>During the debate, the candidates also tangled repeatedly over health care, often relying on the same technique they employ in their commercials: taking the other side's votes or positions and casting them in the worst possible light.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio charged that Mrs. Clinton had done nothing to stop her husband from vetoing money for New York's hospitals, and Mrs. Clinton said that Mr. Lazio had backed Newt Gingrich's plan to cut $270 billion from Medicare, the health program for the elderly.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio was referring to billions of dollars in financing for Medicaid, the health program for the poor, which the President removed from the federal budget in 1997 using his line-item veto power. Mr. Lazio did not mention that the Clinton administration later tried to return most of the money, and that all the money was restored after the Supreme Court overturned the president's line-item veto power.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton, in describing the Medicare proposal, repeated a frequent Democratic contention: that the Republicans wanted to sharply reduce financing. In fact, the Republican plan would have reduced the projected rate of growth of Medicare by $270 billion, not cut existing allocations.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton also suggested that Mr. Lazio has opposed efforts in Congress to approve a patients' bill of rights that would give people more authority to sue their health maintenance organizations. She did not note that Mr. Lazio favored an H.M.O. bill presented by the Republican leadership.</p>
        <p>THE SENATE CAMPAIGN: THE CHALLENGE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
