<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pitch to Ventura or Piazza? Expos Make Wrong Choice</title>
    <meta content="15METS$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/15/sports/15METS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230749"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Montreal Expos</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kepner, Tyler</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000915T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E6DB1038F936A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="983" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pitch to Ventura or Piazza? Expos Make Wrong Choice</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kepner, Tyler</byline>
      <dateline>MONTREAL, Sept. 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Mets defeat Montreal Expos, 10-4; photo (M)0</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When his season was at its worst, Robin Ventura would play mind games at the plate. If he told himself to be aggressive, he would swing at a ball in the dirt. If he tried to be patient, he would let a strike go by. His mind was cluttered, and his mechanics were messed up, too.</p>
        <p>Now, Ventura and the Mets are talking about his struggles in the past tense. It may be early for that, but Ventura has become an offensive force when the Mets need him most. The third baseman had three hits tonight, including a three-run homer that sent the Mets to a 10-4 victory over the Montreal Expos.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When his season was at its worst, Robin Ventura would play mind games at the plate. If he told himself to be aggressive, he would swing at a ball in the dirt. If he tried to be patient, he would let a strike go by. His mind was cluttered, and his mechanics were messed up, too.</p>
        <p>Now, Ventura and the Mets are talking about his struggles in the past tense. It may be early for that, but Ventura has become an offensive force when the Mets need him most. The third baseman had three hits tonight, including a three-run homer that sent the Mets to a 10-4 victory over the Montreal Expos.</p>
        <p>The Mets increased their lead in the National League wild-card race to five games over idle Arizona, and remained two games behind Atlanta in the East division after the Braves beat Florida.</p>
        <p>Ventura, who already had singled twice, came up in the seventh inning after an intentional walk to Mike Piazza. He got a first-pitch fastball from the rookie left-hander Sean Spencer and rifled it over the fence in right-center, putting the Mets ahead, 8-3, and giving starter Glendon Rusch some rare run support. Rusch lasted into the eighth inning and improved to 10-10.</p>
        <p>Ventura has been realistic about his responsibilities. No matter how Piazza is hitting -- and right now, he is not hitting at all -- Ventura knows he must drive in runs because he bats behind the Mets' cleanup hitter. Teams would rather make Ventura beat them than let Piazza do it.</p>
        <p>''You bat behind Mike, you have to do a little better than that,'' Ventura said of his season-long slump. ''I didn't get to the point where I was doubting my ability, but I wasn't helping.''</p>
        <p>Manager Bobby Valentine gave Ventura two days off in a row, on Sunday and Monday, and Ventura did not really want them. But he concentrated on correcting his balance at the plate, keeping his head on the ball and standing more upright.</p>
        <p>The adjustments have worked. Ventura tied Wednesday's game with a double and had just his third three-hit game of the season tonight. For the last two days, he has been comfortable every at-bat, and he said he has not had such a stretch this season.</p>
        <p>Piazza's struggles have been harder to analyze. He went 0 for 3 tonight and is batting .135 for September. The lowest he has hit in any month in his career is .232, as a September call-up for the Dodgers in 1992.</p>
        <p>On the flight to Montreal, Mets coaches studied video and noticed no difference in Piazza's mechanics from when he strikes out to when he homers. But Piazza thinks he knows what is wrong: he is not seeing the ball well, pulling off it with his head, and his pitch selection is poor.</p>
        <p>''That's the first rule of hitting, you start swinging at bad pitches, why should they throw you a strike if you're chasing?'' said Piazza, the Mets' catcher. ''When I'm calling a game against a hitter, if I can expand the strike zone, why not do it?''</p>
        <p>There is one physical explanation for Piazza's recent slump: on Wednesday, he said, he felt a spasm in his back, and after he left tonight's game in the eighth inning, he got treatment for it. But it is nothing serious, he said.</p>
        <p>Piazza helped manufacture a run in the third, when he was hit by a pitch, advanced to second on an error, then stole third on a straight steal. He came home on a sacrifice fly, beating a throw from the powerful arm of the Expos' right fielder, Vladimir Guerrero. The way things are going, Piazza was proud of that contribution.</p>
        <p>''I'm a perfectionist and I'm far from perfect lately, but I've got to keep believing and keep battling,'' he said.</p>
        <p>For the first time in a while, the team helped Rusch, who had received a major league-low 3.47 runs per start entering tonight's game. A control specialist, he did not have his best command, walking the leadoff hitter in three innings. But Ventura's homer and a two-run shot by Jay Payton helped Rusch relax and pitch well for the fifth start in a row.</p>
        <p>In his last five starts, Rusch has worked at least six innings every time and has a 2.70 earned run average. Valentine said it is too early to think of how Rusch slots in for a playoff series, but the way he is pitching, he might be earning a chance to start.</p>
        <p>''I've thought about it, and I think I'll be a bullpen guy,'' Rusch said. ''I think I'll be a long man in the pen. If we get to a seven-game series, like in the league championship series, maybe I'll get a chance to start a game in there.''</p>
        <p>The Mets can speak confidently of a postseason trip again. They lost eight of their first 10 games this month, and they admitted they were pressing at times. But the Mets have won four of their last five, and even with their best hitter struggling, the mood is back to normal.</p>
        <p>''I don't do the comparison thing,'' Valentine said. ''We're just playing the way we played all year and coming out on top.''</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>GLENDON RUSCH, who was batting .042 for his career (2 for 48), bounced a single up the middle in the second inning for his first career run batted in.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
