<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>EATING OUT</title>
    <meta content="15EATI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="38" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230581"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000915T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E6DB1538F936A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1626" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>EATING OUT</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Eating Out reviews of Manhattan restaurants that have opened this year; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>New This Year</p>
        <p>A new crop of restaurants will open this fall, but don't overlook some of those that have already arrived in 2000. (These summaries are taken from dining reviews, columns and articles in The Times by William Grimes, Eric Asimov and others.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>New This Year</p>
        <p>A new crop of restaurants will open this fall, but don't overlook some of those that have already arrived in 2000. (These summaries are taken from dining reviews, columns and articles in The Times by William Grimes, Eric Asimov and others.)</p>
        <p>1. Annisa</p>
        <p>** [Rating: 2 stars]</p>
        <p>(212) 741-6699</p>
        <p>13 Barrow Street</p>
        <p>West Village</p>
        <p>$$$ All major cards</p>
        <p>Annisa, whose name means women in Arabic, is a two-woman show. Anita Lo, who worked at Mirezi before it closed, turns out the food; her partner, Jennifer Scism, runs the front of the house. Both seem clear-eyed about the kind of restaurant they want: a place with clean lines, a welcoming, inclusive atmosphere and a quietly persuasive menu full of arresting combinations of ingredients and flavors. Recommended dishes are miso-marinated sable, zucchini blossoms stuffed with falafel, seared foie gras with soup dumplings, apple tart with caramel sauce and carrot-macadamia nut cake.</p>
        <p>2. AZ</p>
        <p>*** [Rating: 3 stars]</p>
        <p>(212) 691-8888</p>
        <p>21 West 17th Street</p>
        <p>Flatiron district</p>
        <p>$$$$ All major cards</p>
        <p>There is a lot of Asie in AZ, but A to Z more accurately reflects the range of influences that Patricia Yeo, a Bobby Flay protegee, brings to her highly inventive, extroverted and wildly successful brand of fusion cooking, with dishes like duck schnitzel, and chicken smoked in Lapsang souchong tea leaves. AZ is gorgeous, an improbable but enchanting blend of strict Asian geometry, Western Art Nouveau and turn-of-the-century Viennese craft influences. The sultry bar and lounge on the ground floor attract the young and the beautiful. In the third-floor dining room, tilted glass panels open up to the sky in clear weather, and a thin sheet of water flows down a stone slab near the entrance. It's a room to dream in, and a threat to steal the show. When the food arrives, however, the stargazing stops. After that, Ms. Yeo holds center stage.</p>
        <p>3. Bandol</p>
        <p>+</p>
        <p>(212) 744-1800</p>
        <p>181 East 78th Street</p>
        <p>Manhattan</p>
        <p>$ All major cards</p>
        <p>Named for a fine Provencal wine, Bandol offers dreamy Mediterranean flavors in a wine bar setting where wine is, thankfully, not overly exalted or romanticized. The chef, James Baron, who is French and was the chef at the Water Club, seems comfortable in this smaller setting. He doesn't settle for a list of menu cliches; even the overly familiar dishes like lamb shank, salmon and scallops have clear, direct flavors that convey their appeal rather than their popularity. The food is very good, and the restaurant's atmosphere is warm and neighborly.</p>
        <p>4. Bayou</p>
        <p>+</p>
        <p>(212) 426-3800</p>
        <p>308 Lenox Avenue, near 125th Street</p>
        <p>Harlem</p>
        <p>$ All major cards</p>
        <p>This handsome Creole restaurant in Harlem would satisfy any New Orleans native's palate. Its chef, Steve Manning, cooked for 10 years at Clancy's, an exceptional insider's spot in New Orleans. He brings the easy confidence of a man who knows Creole cooking inside and out, not straying far from classics yet never descending into cliches. Standouts include rich turtle soup; fried oysters and spinach topped with melted Brie; and crayfish etouffee. Bayou also has an inexpensive but high-quality wine list.</p>
        <p>5. Blue Hill</p>
        <p>** [Rating: 2 stars]</p>
        <p>(212) 539-1776</p>
        <p>75 Washington Place, near Avenue of the Americas</p>
        <p>Greenwich Village</p>
        <p>$$ All major cards</p>
        <p>It takes nerve to place one's faith in the food and nothing but the food. That's exactly what Alex Urena and Dan Barber, the chefs and owners of Blue Hill, have done. Blue Hill, named for a farm in the Berkshires that belongs to Mr. Barber's grandmother, could hardly be more unassuming. The decor barely exists, just enough to give a vaguely pleasant impression. The menu is small, with tiny print. Prices are astoundingly low. By and large the food is refined without being fussy, harmoniously structured and deftly handled. Recommended dishes are poached duck with ragout of corn, pearl onions, crosnes (Chinese artichokes) and baby potatoes; braised cod with mushroom tart; and hanger steak with spinach spatzle and turnips.</p>
        <p>6. Blue Velvet 1929</p>
        <p>+</p>
        <p>(212) 260-9808</p>
        <p>227 First Avenue, near 14th Street</p>
        <p>East Village</p>
        <p>$ All major cards</p>
        <p>With the kitchen headed by Hao Chen, formerly of Indochine, Blue Velvet excels at delicate and fresh Vietnamese appetizers. Spring rolls, which are so often heavy with grease, are instead crisp and narrow. Summer rolls are just as good, and banh cuon (steamed crepes with chicken, shrimp, bean sprouts and shallots) are even better. Compared with the appetizers, main courses are a mixed bag. Try the sliced chicken breast, beautifully flavored with aniselike Thai basil, lemon grass and ginger, or the exceptionally tender and flavorful baby back ribs.</p>
        <p>7. Chicama</p>
        <p>** [Rating: 2 stars]</p>
        <p>(212) 505-2233</p>
        <p>35 East 18th Street, at Broadway</p>
        <p>Flatiron district</p>
        <p>$$$ All major cards</p>
        <p>This restaurant, which takes its name from a Peruvian coastal town, serves a splashy pan-Latin food that matches a raucous party mood. Starters include oven-baked empanada filled with spinach and smoked corn, with wild mushroom ceviche; grilled octopus with black olive sauce and quinoa with bacon; and Peruvian duck ceviche marinated in orange and lime, with spicy duck liver spread and walnut-raisin crisp. Dinner entrees include roast suckling pig with sour orange-garlic mojo, white rice, black beans and sweet plantains; and adobo-rubbed Argentine rib-eye steak with corn pudding, sliced tomatoes and oregano vinaigrette, sprinkled with cabrales cheese.</p>
        <p>8. Guastavino's</p>
        <p>** [Rating: 2 stars]</p>
        <p>(212) 980-2455</p>
        <p>409 East 59th Street</p>
        <p>Manhattan</p>
        <p>$$$ All major cards</p>
        <p>Midtown Manhattan, laid out on the grid plan, does not abound in secret tucked-away corners, but Sir Terence Conran, the English designer, has managed to find one for his new restaurant, Guastavino's. It's hidden in plain sight, in tiled vaults designed by Rafael Guastavino under the Queensboro Bridge. Daniel Orr, formerly the executive chef at La Grenouille, has created an eclectic, almost audaciously democratic menu that puts matzo ball soup next to galantine of foie gras with fig jam. Splurgers can live it up on oysters and caviar. Those with simpler tastes can seek out Waldorf salad, stuffed cabbage with pancetta and tomato, or a country terrine with cranberry chutney.</p>
        <p>9. Meigas</p>
        <p>** [Rating: 2 stars]</p>
        <p>(212) 627-5800</p>
        <p>350 Hudson Street, at King Street</p>
        <p>South Village</p>
        <p>$$$ All major cards</p>
        <p>Meigas, a Spanish restaurant in a former industrial building, is very large with high ceilings and a light, beachy color scheme dominated by sand and aqua that give it the feel of a giant bathhouse. The flavors sing clearly. Ingredients taste exactly like what they are, and in combination they interact without getting lost. This sense of clarity and definition helps elevate rustic dishes like rabbit loin wrapped in bacon and surrounded by sauteed scallops, pearl onions, scallions and garlic confit; and the juicy rib-eye steak, served with potatoes and piquillo peppers.</p>
        <p>10. Sushi Yasuda</p>
        <p>*** [Rating: 3 stars]</p>
        <p>(212) 972-1001</p>
        <p>204 East 43rd Street</p>
        <p>Manhattan</p>
        <p>$$$ All major cards</p>
        <p>Sushi Yasuda is a showcase for Maomichi Yasuda, formerly the star sushi chef at Hatsuhana, one of Manhattan's deluxe sushi shrines, and before that a sushi chef in Japan. Now Mr. Yasuda has opened a place with Hatsuhana's former manager, Shige Akimoto, and Scott Rosenberg, an amateur sushi fanatic. Sushi Yasuda makes a point of carrying fish that most sushi restaurants either can't get their hands on or don't want to bother with. But sushi is only half the story. The daily menu includes a small, transparent sheet of special appetizers worth jumping for, like steamed monkfish liver in a tart ponzu sauce; and deep-fried eel backbones, as salty and crunchy as crisp bacon. For dessert, try the mochi rice ice cream balls.</p>
        <p>11. Tocqueville</p>
        <p>** [Rating: 2 stars]</p>
        <p>(212) 647-1515</p>
        <p>15 East 15th Street, at Union Square West</p>
        <p>$$$ All major cards</p>
        <p>In a small, trapezoidal room off Union Square, this French restaurant is a quiet haven of good taste, food and service. Appetizers include shucked Kumamoto oysters mignonette, and white and green asparagus salad with truffle vinaigrette. Entrees include fillet of wild steelhead salmon with a wasabi crust; pan-roasted country chicken served with whipped potatoes, porcini mushrooms and vegetables; and roast rack of lamb.</p>
        <p>12. Wallse</p>
        <p>** [Rating: 2 stars]</p>
        <p>(212) 352-2300</p>
        <p>344 West 11th Street</p>
        <p>West Village</p>
        <p>$$$ All major cards</p>
        <p>Kurt Gutenbrunner's very appealing little Austrian restaurant has a relaxed neighborhood feeling and a menu devoted for the most part to comfortable favorites like rostbraten (steak in red wine with fried onions), Wiener schnitzel, veal goulash and tafelspitz (boiled beef), as well as slightly more fancified dishes like asparagus with chanterelles in riesling sauce. Appetizers include sauteed rabbit with herb spatzle and sweet peas, and a salad of smoked trout and eel piled high with wild cress. The dessert list includes two strudels, a Viennese coffee sabayon, chocolate-hazelnut cake, and strawberries served with a floral, quintessentially Austrian elderberry sorbet.</p>
        <p>Summaries taken from reviews use the star ratings. Others are taken from the $25 and Under column (+) and articles (++), and capsule revies from New York Today: www.nytoday.com (+++).</p>
        <p>What the Stars Mean</p>
        <p>**** -- Extraordinary  *** -- Excellent  ** -- Very Good  * -- Good  None Poor to Satisfactory</p>
        <p>Price Range  Based on the cost of a three-course dinner, per person, tax, tip and drinks not included.</p>
        <p>$ -- $25 and under  $$ -- $25 to $40  $$$ -- $40 to $55  $$$$ -- $55 and over</p>
        <p>Past Reviews -- Good Eating columns back to June 1998, along with reviews from The Times and capsule reviews by Times critics of additional restaurants not reviewed in the newspaper, are available on New York Today.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
