<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Oracle's Results for Quarter Beat Wall St. Estimates</title>
    <meta content="Y15ORAC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/15/technology/15ORAC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230653"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TECHNOLOGY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Oracle Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fisher, Lawrence M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000915T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E3D81338F936A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="580" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Oracle's Results for Quarter Beat Wall St. Estimates</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAWRENCE M. FISHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fisher, Lawrence M</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO, Sept. 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Oracle Corp posts fiscal first-quarter results that surpass Wall Street estimates; also announces 2-for-1 stock split, 10th since Oracle's initial public offering in March 1986; for quarter ended Aug 31, Oracle reports earnings of $501 million, more than double $237 million posted a year earlier; revenue grew 14 percent, to $2.26 billion; sales of applications software increased 42 percent, to $156 million, while database software sales grew 32 percent, to $585 million (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Oracle Corporation posted fiscal first-quarter results today that handily surpassed Wall Street estimates. The company also announced a 2-for-1 stock split, the 10th since Oracle's initial public offering in March 1986.</p>
        <p>For the quarter ended Aug. 31, Oracle reported earnings of $501 million, or 17 cents a share, more than double the $237 million, or 8 cents a share, it posted in the period a year earlier. Revenue grew 14 percent, to $2.26 billion. Sales of database software beat projections, while those for applications software grew less than expected.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Oracle Corporation posted fiscal first-quarter results today that handily surpassed Wall Street estimates. The company also announced a 2-for-1 stock split, the 10th since Oracle's initial public offering in March 1986.</p>
        <p>For the quarter ended Aug. 31, Oracle reported earnings of $501 million, or 17 cents a share, more than double the $237 million, or 8 cents a share, it posted in the period a year earlier. Revenue grew 14 percent, to $2.26 billion. Sales of database software beat projections, while those for applications software grew less than expected.</p>
        <p>Analysts had expected Oracle to earn 13 cents a share, according to First Call/Thomson Financial.</p>
        <p>Before Oracle announced its results, its shares closed at $84.94, up $3.13. In after-hours trading, shares slipped as low as $82.75.</p>
        <p>''It was a very strong quarter, spectacular in margins, very strong in database and a little lighter than hoped in applications,'' said Robert Austrian, an analyst with Banc of America Securities. He said the best of the fiscal year was ahead and that ''investors will be pretty pleased.'' He added that ''investors with just a little bit of memory will recall'' that last year's first quarter ''was pretty tough.''</p>
        <p>The first quarter has historically been weak for Oracle, based in Redwood City, Calif., and the company fell short of estimates last year. Facing numerous hostile questions from securities analysts, Larry Ellison, Oracle's chairman and chief executive, said at the time: ''One quarter does not make a trend. Place your bets gentlemen.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Ellison sounded a different note today after a year in which the growth of the Internet bolstered sales of both the company's core database products and its suite of business applications. Oracle has also used Internet applications internally to trim $1 billion from expenses. First-quarter operating profit margin increased 11.7 percentage points -- to 29.1 percent from 17.4 percent a year earlier.</p>
        <p>''We are off to our fastest start in six years,'' Mr. Ellison said. ''The spectacular growth in our database business demonstrates that we are continuing to take market share from I.B.M. and Microsoft. We're not losing any deals to Microsoft at all, and very few to I.B.M.''</p>
        <p>Oracle said sales of its applications software increased 42 percent, to $156 million, while database software sales grew 32 percent, to $585 million. Oracle no longer breaks out application sales by category because it is trying to sell most customers the complete suite, although customers pay only for the portions they use. Total software license revenue was up 28 percent, to $807 million, while total service revenue increased 8 percent, to $1.5 billion.</p>
        <p>Responding to questions about the slower-than-expected growth in applications, Mr. Ellison said the sales cycle of the applications suite was longer than for the database software and required approval from a higher level of management.</p>
        <p>''We did not close as much of it as we thought'' in the first quarter, ''but we have tremendous momentum'' going into second quarter, he said, adding that the second quarter would be ''spectacular.''</p>
        <p>TECHNOLOGY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
