<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From the First, a Feud Between Justice Dept. and the F.B.I.</title>
    <meta content="Y15DEC$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/15/national/15DECI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230687"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Plea Bargaining</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Espionage</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Bureau of Investigation</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Justice Department</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Los Alamos National Laboratory</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnston, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reno, Janet (Atty Gen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Freeh, Louis J (Dir)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lee, Wen Ho (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Plea Bargaining</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Espionage</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000915T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE5DE1038F936A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="705" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From the First, a Feud Between Justice Dept. and the F.B.I.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID JOHNSTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Johnston, David</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Sept. 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Atty Gen Janet Reno and FBI director, Louis J Freeh, are under hot glare of criticism for their handling of nuclear secrets case of Dr Wen Ho Lee; law enforcement officials say neither Reno nor Feeeh was directly involved in decisive early phase of investigation, absence some officials say contributed to problems that led to collapse of case against Lee (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Assailed by President Clinton and the federal judge who presided over the nuclear secrets case of Wen Ho Lee, Attorney General Janet Reno and the F.B.I. director, Louis J. Freeh, are once again under the hot glare of criticism for their handling of an important criminal case.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton, in his remarks today, and Judge James A. Parker, in his comments on Wednesday, focused their complaints on the government's demands that kept Mr. Lee in pretrial detention for nine months.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Assailed by President Clinton and the federal judge who presided over the nuclear secrets case of Wen Ho Lee, Attorney General Janet Reno and the F.B.I. director, Louis J. Freeh, are once again under the hot glare of criticism for their handling of an important criminal case.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton, in his remarks today, and Judge James A. Parker, in his comments on Wednesday, focused their complaints on the government's demands that kept Mr. Lee in pretrial detention for nine months.</p>
        <p>The criticism of federal authorities comes after years of conflict and tension between the Justice Department and the Federal Bureau of Investigation about how to obtain evidence in a case that began as an investigation into suspicions that China had obtained atomic secrets through espionage.</p>
        <p>Law enforcement officials said neither Ms. Reno nor Mr. Freeh was directly involved in the decisive early phase of the investigation, an absence that some officials said had contributed to the problems that led to the collapse of the case against Mr. Lee.</p>
        <p>The complaints also come at a time when battles over other issues, like campaign finance, have driven a wedge between Ms. Reno and Mr. Freeh, who deeply embarrassed the attorney general by urging the appointment of an independent counsel to investigate possible violations of political fund-raising laws.</p>
        <p>Today, Mr. Clinton said he was ''quite troubled'' by Mr. Lee's detention in light of the government's willingness to accept a guilty plea to a single count of mishandling classified material.</p>
        <p>Judge Parker said the government's actions were a national embarrassment. ''I feel I was led astray'' by federal prosecutors and the F.B.I., he said at the hearing on Wednesday, when Mr. Lee was freed.</p>
        <p>Judge Parker said they had portrayed Mr. Lee as ''a danger to the safety of this nation'' who should not be released.</p>
        <p>The F.B.I. and the Justice Department had feuded over the Lee case for years, but it was the bureau's suspicion that Mr. Lee was a spy for Beijing that drove the inquiry forward as an espionage case. The bureau's hand was strengthened by Energy Department officials eager to counteract the impression that the agency had failed to impose strict security procedures.</p>
        <p>Agents focused on Mr. Lee in May 1996 after an internal review at the Energy Department determined that he was a chief suspect among a dozen people who might be responsible for China's presumed theft of a design for the highly advanced W-88 thermonuclear warhead.</p>
        <p>But in 1997, Justice Department officials refused to authorize an application for a warrant to monitor Mr. Lee electronically under the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act. The department refused to seek a wiretap on grounds that F.B.I. agents had produced only sketchy information that the scientist had engaged in spying.</p>
        <p>Officials at the F.B.I. and the Justice Department said the dispute over the wiretap was a crucial disagreement, but one in which neither Ms. Reno nor Mr. Freeh became involved, even though serious espionage cases involving American citizens are almost always brought to the attention of the attorney general and the F.B.I. director.</p>
        <p>Later, after some law enforcement officials said that the warrant would have enabled them to prove or disprove the allegations against Mr. Lee, Ms. Reno complained that she was not advised of the dispute over the wiretap and said that Mr. Freeh should have discussed the matter with her. But F.B.I. officials said Mr. Freeh was not aware of it either.</p>
        <p>Unable to tap Mr. Lee's phones, the bureau  resorted to other tactics. An agent posing as a  Chinese intelligence officer approached Mr. Lee, but the scientist rebuffed the overture to spy for Beijing. Suspicions lingered, however.</p>
        <p>In 1999, F.B.I. agents searched Mr. Lee's office computer, finding that he had downloaded from a classified to a unclassified computer system thousands of lines of secret computer codes -- the information that he was finally charged with mishandling.</p>
        <p>The decision to charge Mr. Lee with multiple felonies in what became a 59-count indictment was agreed upon by officials at the Justice Department in Washington, prosecutors in New Mexico and the F.B.I. Mr. Freeh supported the indictment, which was ultimately approved by Ms. Reno.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
