<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Residential Real Estate; Multiple Listings Sought For Homes in Brooklyn</title>
    <meta content="15REAL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/15/nyregion/15REAL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230676"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Brokers and Brokerage Firms</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cooperatives</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Corcoran Group</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">May, William B, Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hevesi, Dennis</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Brokers and Brokerage Firms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooperatives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooperatives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000915T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E5DF1038F936A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="897" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Residential Real Estate; Multiple Listings Sought For Homes in Brooklyn</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DENNIS HEVESI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hevesi, Dennis</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Three multiple listing services that now loosely divide residential real estate market in Brooklyn plan to merge by end of the year; move partly reflects rising prices in communities surrounding historic brownstone Brooklyn; resistance may come from William B May Co and Corcoran Group, two Manhattan-based brokerage houses that dominate higher-end section of Brooklyn; graph shows rise in co-op prices in borough (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Much like Manhattan, Brooklyn has never had a boroughwide multiple listing of homes for sale. Now, reflecting a lack of inventory at a time when prices -- especially in Brooklyn's historic brownstone districts -- have been rising, the three multiple listing services that loosely divide the borough plan to merge by the end of the year.</p>
        <p>''The idea is to create a unified Brooklyn M.L.S.,'' said Gerard Longo, chairman of the South Shore Multiple Listing Service, one of the three services in merger negotiations. ''If we do, we would have probably 450 brokers and 5,000 licensed sales agents as members.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Much like Manhattan, Brooklyn has never had a boroughwide multiple listing of homes for sale. Now, reflecting a lack of inventory at a time when prices -- especially in Brooklyn's historic brownstone districts -- have been rising, the three multiple listing services that loosely divide the borough plan to merge by the end of the year.</p>
        <p>''The idea is to create a unified Brooklyn M.L.S.,'' said Gerard Longo, chairman of the South Shore Multiple Listing Service, one of the three services in merger negotiations. ''If we do, we would have probably 450 brokers and 5,000 licensed sales agents as members.''</p>
        <p>While a handful of major brokerage houses dominate the market in Manhattan, home buyers and sellers throughout most of Brooklyn usually deal with an array of neighborhood-based brokers who may not have access to listings very far from their own communities. Currently, neighborhood brokers in Brooklyn can join one of the three services -- South Shore, Mid-County and Bay Ridge-Bensonhurst -- to share listings and, when a deal is struck, split commissions.</p>
        <p>If the unified service is created, they and their customers would have access to listings throughout most of the borough. (The South Shore service essentially covers the area south of Flatbush to the shore; Mid-County covers Flatbush, Bushwick, Bedford-Stuyvesant and East New York, and Bay Ridge-Bensonhurst covers those communities.)</p>
        <p>''I think it's a good idea,'' Louise Riso, president of the Bay Ridge-Bensonhurst service, said of a merger. She pointed out that while the other boards had approved it, her board would not vote on the plan until Sept. 28. Asked whether there was opposition among her board members, Ms. Riso said that they needed more information before deciding.</p>
        <p>The move toward a merger, said Jacob Shayovitz, a past president of the Brooklyn Board of Realtors, ''is spurred by a falloff in inventory -- it's harder to stay in business -- and also, the technology coming into place.''</p>
        <p>''We are trying to stave off competition from the Internet, big companies that were never in the real estate business before,'' Mr. Shayovitz said, citing Microsoft's Home Advisor. ''Since we are more local, we can better serve the people.''</p>
        <p>Further impetus for the merger is coming from rising prices in communities surrounding historic brownstone Brooklyn. Yet, at the same time, resistance may come from the two major Manhattan-based brokerage houses that dominate that higher-end section of Brooklyn: the William B. May Company and the Corcoran Group.</p>
        <p>''I'm talking personally now,'' said Christopher Thomas, William B. May's vice president for Brooklyn. ''Typically, in multiple-listing situations you have a central authority that imposes its regulations on all the signatories, almost a cartel. And since a multiple listing involves two brokers, each of whom has to be compensated, the seller has less flexibility in negotiating a lower commission. I think a market that offers greater heterogeneity of service is a healthier market.''</p>
        <p>Melinda Magnett, president of the Corcoran Group Brooklyn, said: ''The major reason why it hasn't been necessary to join any of the three listing services, or advantageous to our sellers even, is because the communities they currently serve are not typically areas of choice for our clientele. Not to say that that won't someday happen.</p>
        <p>''Would I join? I'd have to know a lot more. The Brooklyn Board of Realtors doesn't even publish a report.''</p>
        <p>In fact, the only available report on Brooklyn home prices is published by the Corcoran Group, and that is limited to the increasingly expensive brownstone area -- the boundaries of which seem to have stretched in recent years.</p>
        <p>''Bedford-Stuyvesant has not been on our report, to date,'' Ms. Magnett said. ''But we plan to include it in the next go-round because it also has been experiencing price increases.'' A two-family town house on Jefferson Avenue in Bedford-Stuyvesant, originally listed for $350,000, recently sold for $395,000, she pointed out.</p>
        <p>''Brooklyn Heights prices are filtering to surrounding neighborhoods,'' Ms. Magnett said.</p>
        <p>The Corcoran Group's most recent survey on brownstone Brooklyn -- covering Brooklyn Heights, Carroll Gardens, Cobble Hill, Boerum Hill, Park Slope, Clinton Hill and Fort Greene -- reported that the average price of a co-op in the area increased to $231,661 at midyear 2000, from $226,780 at midyear 1999, a seemingly modest 2 percent increase. However, said Steven Knobel, executive vice president of Mitchell, Maxwell &amp; Jackson, the appraisal company that prepares the Corcoran Report, ''When you sell more smaller apartments, the average price per unit comes down.''</p>
        <p>More precisely, Mr. Knobel said, the average price per room in the area rose 12 percent, to $58,968 from $52,880, while the average price per square foot jumped 17 percent, to $260 from $223. More striking is that the price of two-bedroom apartments in the entire area rose 26 percent, to $309,603 from $245,910, and three-bedrooms jumped 34 percent, to $633,815 from $474,375.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
