<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="15DIGE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230677"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000915T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE4DF1038F936A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="972" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Profit Doubles at Oracle And Exceeds Projections  Oracle said its first-quarter earnings more than doubled, beating Wall Street forecasts, driven by better-than-expected sales of its database-management programs.</p>
        <p>Oracle reported earnings of $501 million, or 17 cents a share, compared with $237 million, or 8 cents a share, in the period a year earlier. Analysts had estimated earnings of 13 cents a share. Revenue grew 14 percent, to $2.26 billion from $1.98 billion. [Page C2.]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Profit Doubles at Oracle And Exceeds Projections  Oracle said its first-quarter earnings more than doubled, beating Wall Street forecasts, driven by better-than-expected sales of its database-management programs.</p>
        <p>Oracle reported earnings of $501 million, or 17 cents a share, compared with $237 million, or 8 cents a share, in the period a year earlier. Analysts had estimated earnings of 13 cents a share. Revenue grew 14 percent, to $2.26 billion from $1.98 billion. [Page C2.]</p>
        <p>Colgate Hurt by Analysts' Doubts  Shares of Colgate-Palmolive tumbled 15 percent after analysts expressed doubts that the company will meet sales targets, citing the yearlong plunge in the euro. Stubbornly high petroleum prices, meanwhile, are expected to limit Colgate's ability to cut costs. Shares of Colgate dropped $8.81, to $47.38, and other consumer products stocks fell as well. [C4.]</p>
        <p>Gas Reserves Found in Middle East  Drilling deep below the seas off Israel and the Gaza Strip, foreign energy companies are discovering gas reserves that could lift the Palestinian economy and give Israel its first taste of energy independence. [A1.]</p>
        <p>Blue Chips Fall, but Nasdaq Rallies  Blue chips fell on profit taking and concerns about the drop in the euro, but technology stocks moved higher on upbeat speculation about earnings. The Dow Jones industrial average declined 94.71 points, or 0.9 percent, to 11,087.47. The Nasdaq composite index rose 19.97 points, or half a percent, to 3,913.86, but the Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index fell 4.04 points, or 0.3 percent, to 1,480.87. [C6.]</p>
        <p>Bear Stearns Earnings Fall 5.7%  Bear Stearns said that its third-quarter net income fell 5.7 percent on a decline in investment banking that was partly offset by gains in its trading business. [C2.]</p>
        <p>Disney Redesigns Go.com Portal  Go.com, which was Walt Disney's attempt to build an Internet portal to compete with Yahoo, will test a new design today. [C2.]</p>
        <p>Markets Slump in the Philippines  Concerns about rising unemployment, inflation and lawlessness in the southern islands of the Philippines badly hurt the nation's financial markets. The benchmark stock index fell to a five-week low, and the Philippine peso dropped at one point to its weakest level against the dollar in 32 months. Investors seem to be losing their remaining faith in the ability of President Joseph Estrada's administration to ensure economic security. [C3.]</p>
        <p>No Inflation Seen in Latest Reports  Producer prices fell unexpectedly in August, by 0.2 percent, and retail sales cooled, rising only 0.2 percent, the government reported, indicating that the economy is growing at a pace that is unlikely to ignite inflation. [C4.]</p>
        <p>U.S. Offers Help in Russia Tax Cases  After about two years of investigating the movement of billions of dollars through the Bank of New York, the federal authorities now say that much of the money involved tax evasion by Russian businesses, and the investigators are prepared to assist Moscow if the Russians wish to pursue its own cases. [A16.]</p>
        <p>Auto Relationship Grows Closer  General Motors' increased stake in Suzuki expands a close relationship between the companies that goes back almost 20 years, when Suzuki began supplying small cars to G.M. [C5.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
