<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dropping All of His Objections, Bush Agrees to Panel's Debates</title>
    <meta content="15DEBA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/15/politics/15DEBA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230728"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE DEBATES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vice Presidents and Vice Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Boston (Mass)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Winston-Salem (Nc)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">St Louis (Mo)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Danville (Ky)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Commission on Presidential Debates</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marks, Peter</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Missouri</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/North Carolina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Kentucky</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Kentucky</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Missouri</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/North Carolina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts/Boston</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Kentucky</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/North Carolina/Winston-Salem</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/North Carolina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Missouri/St. Louis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Missouri</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vice Presidents and Vice Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000915T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E3DC1038F936A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1294" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dropping All of His Objections, Bush Agrees to Panel's Debates</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER MARKS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Marks, Peter</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gov George W Bush withdraws all his objections to bipartisan commission's debate schedule and agrees to three 90-minute prime-time encounters with Vice Pres Al Gore next month on college campuses in Boston, Winston-Salem, NC, and St Louis; Bush and Gore will debate under original conditions laid out months ago by Commission on Presidential Debates; decision amounts to retreat by Bush campaign from its efforts over last two weeks to move some of debates to television studios, shorten them and designate who moderators should be; aides to Bush dropped their efforts to orchestrate events in face of mounting criticism from fellow Republicans and growing sense that issue has become distraction; dates for debates are Oct 3, Oct 11 and Oct 17; vice-presidential debate will be held Oct 5 in Danville, Ky; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. George W. Bush withdrew all his objections to a bipartisan commission's debate schedule yesterday, agreeing to three 90-minute prime-time encounters with Vice President Al Gore next month on college campuses in Boston, Winston-Salem, N.C., and St. Louis.</p>
        <p>The agreement, announced after a four-hour meeting in Washington of top officials of the Bush and Gore campaigns and representatives of the Commission on Presidential Debates, means that Mr. Bush and Mr. Gore will debate under all the original conditions laid out months ago by the panel, which has organized the nationally televised forums in every presidential election since 1988.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gov. George W. Bush withdrew all his objections to a bipartisan commission's debate schedule yesterday, agreeing to three 90-minute prime-time encounters with Vice President Al Gore next month on college campuses in Boston, Winston-Salem, N.C., and St. Louis.</p>
        <p>The agreement, announced after a four-hour meeting in Washington of top officials of the Bush and Gore campaigns and representatives of the Commission on Presidential Debates, means that Mr. Bush and Mr. Gore will debate under all the original conditions laid out months ago by the panel, which has organized the nationally televised forums in every presidential election since 1988.</p>
        <p>The decision amounted to a wholesale retreat by the Bush campaign from its efforts over the last two weeks to impose its own schedule, moving some of the debates from campuses to television studios, shortening some of them from 90 minutes to 60 minutes and designating moderators like Larry King and Tim Russert.</p>
        <p>Last Friday, in the face of mounting criticism from fellow Republicans and a growing sense that the issue was becoming a distraction, aides to Mr. Bush announced they were dropping the plans to seek an alternative series of debates. But they continued to insist they were opposed to aspects of the commission plan, like staging the first debate in Boston, near the John F. Kennedy Library, because it commemorated a Democrat.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, the Bush campaign conceded even those points. Under the agreement, the candidates are to meet at the University of Massachusetts in Boston on Oct. 3; Wake Forest University in Winston-Salem on Oct. 11 and Washington University in St. Louis on Oct. 17. The vice-presidential contenders are to debate for 90 minutes at Centre College in Danville, Ky., on Oct. 5.</p>
        <p>The terms, precisely those the commission spelled out when it unveiled the debate locations in January, were accepted months ago by the Gore campaign.</p>
        <p>''The major thing is that the debate debate is over,'' said Paul G. Kirk Jr., the former head of the Democratic Party who is co-chairman of the debate commission. Mr. Kirk told reporters after the meeting, which was held in the offices of the panel's legal counsel, that the session had been without rancor. But he added that ''some things we were not flexible on,'' like the notion of moving any of the sites of the debates.</p>
        <p>''It's four and a half hours in a long campaign,'' Mr. Kirk said, referring to the total length of the three presidential debates. ''And we didn't think it was asking too much, particularly at a time when the electorate is paying more attention than they have been in the past.''</p>
        <p>Both sides professed to be pleased with the outcome.</p>
        <p>During a fund-raiser last night in San Diego, Calif., Mr. Bush said: ''By the way, we agreed on three debates tonight. And I can't wait.</p>
        <p>''I know the man is a great debater, a great debater,'' Mr. Bush said, referring to Mr. Gore. ''But what America wants is a leader.''</p>
        <p>Earlier, Donald L. Evans, Mr. Bush's campaign chairman, said the governor was ''looking forward to a free-flowing, substantive, real and genuine discussion of all the issues.''</p>
        <p>William M. Daley, the chairman of Mr. Gore's campaign, concurred.</p>
        <p>''This is good because the American people want to hear from these people in formal settings that give them the opportunity to express what they will do as the next president of the United States,'' Mr. Daley said.</p>
        <p>Other Bush officials sought to portray the outcome as less than a setback, saying they were pleased that,  as the details are being worked out, the commission is still considering the kind of informal formats Mr. Bush had sought.</p>
        <p>Karen P. Hughes, Mr. Bush's communications director, said the governor had always thought the public would be better served by more casual discussions than by ''the canned and stilted formats that have been the case in past presidential debates.''</p>
        <p>Still, some political professionals wondered whether the Bush campaign had badly miscalculated by offering a counterproposal and trying to make it appear that Mr. Gore was the reluctant debater when he refused to agree to Mr. Bush's terms. The Bush campaign even ran a television commercial taunting the vice president on the issue after Mr. Bush unveiled his debate plan on Sept. 3. In addition to 60-minute debates of CNN's ''Larry King Live'' and ''Meet the Press'' on NBC, the Bush plan called for participation in one commission forum, in St. Louis.</p>
        <p>Some of those who attended the meeting said it was not contentious at all. In fact, they said, the two sides had quickly agreed on most of the disputed items on the agenda, like the locations and lengths of the debates.</p>
        <p>What consumed most of the session, they said, was working out the details; for instance, the question of how members of the audience might be chosen if a town-meeting arrangement were used for one of the debates.</p>
        <p>The formats and moderators for the debates are still up in the air, though it was agreed that there would be one moderator for each  forum, participants said. Mr. Kirk said he believed that many of the remaining issues could be resolved over the next day or two.</p>
        <p>The resolution came as a relief not only to the commission but also to the hosts of the debates. One of the panel's central missions is to involve young people in the process, and that is why the debates have come to be held on college campuses. This year's sites were chosen from dozens of colleges and universities that had submitted proposals.</p>
        <p>''We're ecstatic that we'll be the first presidential debate for 2000,'' said Annemarie Lewis-Kerwin, a spokeswoman for the University of Massachusetts in Boston, the site to which the Bush campaign raised its most serious objections.</p>
        <p>The university has had to raise about $2 million from corporate sponsors and the state Legislature to stage the event, Ms. Lewis-Kerwin said, and it had already spent about $300,000 when Mr. Bush's proposed a plan that threatened to scuttle the Boston debate.</p>
        <p>''There were moments that it was a challenge to keep the morale up, '' she said.</p>
        <p>Under the commission's guidelines, formal invitations are to be sent to the candidates several days before each debate. To qualify, a candidate must have on the date of invitation the support of an average of at least 15 percent of those polled in five national surveys.</p>
        <p>This standard has been criticized by Ralph Nader and Patrick J. Buchanan, third-party candidates who say the threshold is impossible for them to meet. Many political observers say that third-party candidates could hope to register that level in the polls only after an appearance on a nationally televised debate.</p>
        <p>Jamin B. Raskin, a professor of constitutional law at American University who represented Ross Perot in 1996 in an unsuccessful effort to be included in the presidential debates, said a less arbitrary standard would be 5 percent, the threshold required by federal law for a candidate to qualify for public funds.</p>
        <p>''The co-chairmen of the Commission on Presidential Debates go around saying they are not in the business of propping up third-party candidates,'' Mr. Raskin said. ''They're in the business of killing third-party candidates.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE DEBATES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
