<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Columbia May Expand Onto Trump Riverfront Site</title>
    <meta content="15COLU$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/15/nyregion/15COLU.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230743"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Relocation of Business</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Columbia University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Trump, Donald J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Relocation of Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000915T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05EEDC1038F936A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1161" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Columbia May Expand Onto Trump Riverfront Site</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLES V. BAGLI</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Columbia University is talking with Donald J Trump about creating a satellite campus near Trump Place project on the Hudson River; is considering moving its Graduate School of Business and School of the Arts there from Morningside Heights; zoning would also allow university to build two residential towers for faculty members and graduate students; construction projects under way in neighborhood have already prompted complaints from residents; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Columbia University is talking with Donald J. Trump about creating a satellite campus near Lincoln Center at the developer's vast Trump Place project on the Hudson River.</p>
        <p>The main Columbia campus at 114th Street and Broadway in Morningside Heights is starved for land, with 20,000 students crammed onto 36 acres. So the university, according to three people involved in the discussions, is considering moving its Graduate School of Business and the School of the Arts more than 50 blocks south to a 7.5-acre riverfront parcel on West End Avenue between 59th and 62nd Streets.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Columbia University is talking with Donald J. Trump about creating a satellite campus near Lincoln Center at the developer's vast Trump Place project on the Hudson River.</p>
        <p>The main Columbia campus at 114th Street and Broadway in Morningside Heights is starved for land, with 20,000 students crammed onto 36 acres. So the university, according to three people involved in the discussions, is considering moving its Graduate School of Business and the School of the Arts more than 50 blocks south to a 7.5-acre riverfront parcel on West End Avenue between 59th and 62nd Streets.</p>
        <p>The zoning would also allow the university to build two residential towers for faculty members and graduate students on the parcel, which is within two blocks of the Broadway subway line, allowing easy access to the main campus uptown.</p>
        <p>But while Columbia sees the neighborhood as a good place to expand, the West Side is already awash in projects that have prompted residents to complain about overcrowding, traffic congestion and pollution. Nearby, John Jay College and Fordham University are expanding; Steve Ross of the Related Companies is building the 2.7 million square foot Columbus Center complex, and Douglas Durst, the developer, has proposed a large office-and-studio complex.</p>
        <p>A deal would depend not only on winning over the community but also on the price, which could be more than $200 million. The parcel sits at the south end of Trump Place, a 77-acre former railyard from 59th to 72nd Streets, where Mr. Trump and a group of Hong Kong investors are building 16 apartment houses and more than 20 acres of landscaped public parkland.</p>
        <p>Emily Lloyd, executive vice president for administration at Columbia, was noncommittal about the site. ''Whenever there is a property available that looks like it might fit our needs, we try to look at it and assess the feasibility,'' she said. ''We don't comment on particular pieces of land, unless and until we acquire something.''</p>
        <p>But according to people involved in the talks and in Columbia's expansion plans, John Zuccotti, a university trustee who heads the buildings and grounds committee, talked with Mr. Trump about the parcel in August and scheduled a meeting for next week. Mr. Zuccotti, who is chairman of Brookfield Financial Properties, a major New York developer, was out of the country and could not be reached for comment.</p>
        <p>''There's no better site in New York City than this,'' Mr. Trump said yesterday. ''Beyond that I have no comment.''</p>
        <p>Meyer Felderberg, dean of Columbia's business school, said he was aware that the site had ''been under discussion.'' Bruce W. Ferguson, dean of the arts school, said he was unaware of the talks, but not surprised. ''They're always on the lookout for real estate,'' he said. ''It is, after all, the New York discourse.''</p>
        <p>Aside from 65 buildings on the main campus, Columbia owns the 50-story G. E. Building, at Lexington Avenue and 51st Street, and Arden House, an estate in Harriman, N.Y. It sold the land beneath Rockefeller Center in 1985 for $400 million.</p>
        <p>Over the years, the university has bought tenements in Morningside Heights for housing, though its efforts have often run into community opposition. For the most part, it has made do: it built a rare book center atop Butler Library and a computer center under another building. More recently, it shoehorned the Morris A. Schapiro Center for Engineering and Physical Research into a space behind the business school. It also announced plans for a 12-story building at 110th Street and Broadway for faculty housing and a school for faculty and neighborhood children.</p>
        <p>Mr. Felderberg said that space was tight at the business school, where the number of students has risen 15 percent in the last decade to 1,800 students as he added centers for international business, real estate finance and global brand management. ''We are now at the point at which our expansion in terms of size and quality is constrained by space,'' he said. ''But we would be unhappy and uncomfortable about leaving the campus.'' He said he would favor moving nonessential offices off campus, as well as housing. Faculty housing is necessary, he said, to attract top professors.</p>
        <p>The arts school, whose classrooms, offices and studios are now spread among nine campus buildings, is about to study the feasibility of consolidating into two: Dodge Hall, on campus, and Prentice Hall, a Columbia-owned building on 125th Street. The school has about 700 graduate students and offers classes to thousands of undergraduates.</p>
        <p>Two years ago, Columbia also expressed interest in building dormitories, classrooms and studios on Governors Island. The project would have included a conference center for the business school's executive education program, a money-maker for the university.</p>
        <p>But one person involved in the university's expansion plans said that Columbia could no longer afford to address its space problems piecemeal. ''They've got to find some big strategy,'' the executive said. ''Incremental expansion won't do it.''</p>
        <p>The option of buying the Trump parcel emerged only recently. So far, the developer has put up two buildings at Trump Place: a 40-story building with 516 rental apartments and a 46-story tower with 377 condominiums. A third building is nearing completion, and a fourth, a luxury condominium between 70th and 71st Streets, is expected to get under way this fall.</p>
        <p>But for some time, Mr. Trump and his Hong Kong partners have shown a willingness to sell part of the vast tract. In 1998, the Hong Kong group hired Salomon Smith Barney to sell two residential sites, much to Mr. Trump's chagrin. A deal ultimately foundered.</p>
        <p>More recently, Mr. Trump and his partners have sought to sell the south end, a commercial parcel known as the studio site. The developer talked to CBS about building a digital-television studio on the land, but nothing came of it. Two weeks ago, Mr. Trump suggested he might build a casino at Trump Place.</p>
        <p>A deal with Columbia could include two residential sites. At different times, Mr. Trump has said he would sell the sites for anywhere from $90 million to $400 million.</p>
        <p>Columbia University's academic and financial fortunes have been on the rise. Its endowment has swelled to $4.25 billion, from about $1.7 billion in the early 1990's. It has consistently ranked among the top 10 educational institutions in fund-raising, taking in $292 million last year.</p>
        <p>But any proposal for the site would have to go through the city's lengthy land review process. ''One week it's a casino, the next week it's a university campus,'' Assemblyman Scott M. Stringer said. ''Columbia should be prepared for a serious community review process. In light of what we're facing in this neighborhood any new large-scale development has to be examined for traffic and congestion. They're going to have to convince this community that it's environmentally sound.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
