<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Foreign Affairs; Give a Little, Get a Little</title>
    <meta content="15FRIE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="35" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/15/opinion/15FRIE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230632"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Jerusalem</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">West Bank</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Friedman, Thomas L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/Thomas L Friedman</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel/Jerusalem</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/West Bank</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000915T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E6DA1338F936A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="768" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Foreign Affairs; Give a Little, Get a Little</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS L. FRIEDMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Friedman, Thomas L</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Thomas L Friedman Op-Ed column says Palestinian-Israel peace process is at tough juncture, but it is not insurmountable; says most sensitive issues are being dealt with: who should control spiritual heart of Jerusalem, and what will happen to Palestinian refugees outside of Israel and West Bank (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When I was a reporter covering Lebanon's civil war there were mornings when the fighting was so bad I just wanted to write a one-line story: ''Lebanon ended today -- period, paragraph, goodbye.'' But the Lebanese people's indefatigable quest for a normal life always proved me wrong. I've been reminded of that reading all the recent doom-and-gloom stories about how the Palestinian-Israeli peace process is over -- period, paragraph, goodbye. How many times do we have to bury this thing for people to realize that if you think it's over -- you don't understand it?</p>
        <p>Yes, this is a very tough juncture, but it is not insurmountable. We are dealing now with the most sensitive issues: who should control the spiritual heart of Jerusalem -- what Jews call the Temple Mount, where the ancient Jewish Temple once stood, and what Arabs call the Haram as-Sharif, where two of Islam's holiest mosques now stand -- and what will happen to the Palestinian refugees outside of Israel and the West Bank.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When I was a reporter covering Lebanon's civil war there were mornings when the fighting was so bad I just wanted to write a one-line story: ''Lebanon ended today -- period, paragraph, goodbye.'' But the Lebanese people's indefatigable quest for a normal life always proved me wrong. I've been reminded of that reading all the recent doom-and-gloom stories about how the Palestinian-Israeli peace process is over -- period, paragraph, goodbye. How many times do we have to bury this thing for people to realize that if you think it's over -- you don't understand it?</p>
        <p>Yes, this is a very tough juncture, but it is not insurmountable. We are dealing now with the most sensitive issues: who should control the spiritual heart of Jerusalem -- what Jews call the Temple Mount, where the ancient Jewish Temple once stood, and what Arabs call the Haram as-Sharif, where two of Islam's holiest mosques now stand -- and what will happen to the Palestinian refugees outside of Israel and the West Bank.</p>
        <p>Since 1967 Israel has occupied and claimed sovereignty over the Temple Mount. But out of respect for Muslim sensibilities -- and because most rabbis ban Jewish prayer on the Temple Mount for fear that Jews might be treading on the ancient Temple below -- Israel has voluntarily granted Palestinians administrative control there. But the Palestinians are now demanding full sovereignty for any final peace.</p>
        <p>Quite shockingly, though, both Palestinian and Arab leaders have been scoffing at Jewish claims that the ruins of the ancient Jewish Temple are under the Temple Mount. Yasir  Arafat and several other Arab leaders have told U.S. officials that this was a story the Jews just recently invented to justify their hold on Jerusalem. (If Israelis heard the insultingly ignorant things Mr. Arafat has said in private about Jewish claims to Jerusalem, the peace process would really be over.) This is no way to go.</p>
        <p>''The most effective way for the Arabs to limit Israeli claims to the Temple Mount is not by denying them, but by acknowledging them and assuring Israelis that they will be respected, so Israelis would feel comfortable enough to limit themselves,'' argued Stephen P. Cohen, a Middle East expert at the Israel Policy Forum. ''But this sort of recognition of the Israeli narrative by Arab leaders would be a huge step. It would mean acknowledging that Israelis are in Jerusalem, and in the Holy Land, not just because the Arabs could not defeat them, not just because they were driven there by the Holocaust, but because the Jewish people have a deep historical connection to this place.''</p>
        <p>But the same is true for Israel regarding Palestinian refugees. Israel refuses to acknowledge any role in the creation of the refugee problem. Yet Israel wants Palestinian refugees to limit their demands for any right of return to Israel. That is going to be a very hard sell for Mr. Arafat.</p>
        <p>Israel doesn't have to assume explicit responsibility, but it should be generous in saying to Palestinians that they have suffered a historical injustice and have a moral right to return to their original homes -- but that as a practical matter Israel cannot allow more than a symbolic number to return to Israel proper, and the others will either have to reside in the West Bank or accept generous compensation. For Palestinians to limit themselves they need to feel that their narrative as a dispossessed people struggling to recover their homeland is also affirmed.</p>
        <p>But while there is a certain symmetry in these two issues of Jerusalem and refugees, there is no symmetry now between Mr. Arafat and Ehud Barak, Israel's prime minister. Mr. Barak may have bungled his relationship with Mr. Arafat, but within his own political context Mr. Barak has shown a willingness to offer unprecedented compromises, re-educate his own people and stake his whole political career on peace.</p>
        <p>Mr. Arafat has not gone that far -- yet. Some worry that the Palestinian leader, now that he is shedding his revolutionary cloak, is turning out to be an unreconstructed, provincial tribal chief who may not be up to a grand compromise or running a modern state.</p>
        <p>Oh, this struggle will end. Too many people now want it over. But whether it is Mr. Arafat who seals the deal is still an open question.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
