<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Around a Pampered Queen, a Busy Buzz</title>
    <meta content="15PROF" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/15/nyregion/15PROF.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230631"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PUBLIC LIVES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Voter Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Dana E. Owens</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Lane Bryant Stores</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Queen Latifah (Dana E Owens)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Finn, Robin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Public Lives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000915T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E1DB1338F936A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="988" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Around a Pampered Queen, a Busy Buzz</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBIN FINN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Finn, Robin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with Dana E Owens (Queen Latifah), who is in New York to tape second seasons of her talk show, contribute to Rock the Vote campaign, promote her fifth album and be model at the Lane Bryant fashion show; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE zaftig woman in the waffle-weave bathrobe, gray sweat pants and bowling shoes is being attended to by more handlers than this Midtown hotel suite can handle: there are three -- make that four -- publicists, a hairdresser, a makeup artist and a wardrobe coordinator, all hovering around Queen Latifah, a k a Dana E. Owens from Newark, like a herd of worker bees.</p>
        <p>Everyone's edgy because this queen, back in town to tape the second season of her talk show, add her personal politics to the Rock the Vote campaign (please substitute rap for rock), talk up the release of her fifth album, scheduled for November, and hit the fashion show circuit, is a trifle under the weather.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE zaftig woman in the waffle-weave bathrobe, gray sweat pants and bowling shoes is being attended to by more handlers than this Midtown hotel suite can handle: there are three -- make that four -- publicists, a hairdresser, a makeup artist and a wardrobe coordinator, all hovering around Queen Latifah, a k a Dana E. Owens from Newark, like a herd of worker bees.</p>
        <p>Everyone's edgy because this queen, back in town to tape the second season of her talk show, add her personal politics to the Rock the Vote campaign (please substitute rap for rock), talk up the release of her fifth album, scheduled for November, and hit the fashion show circuit, is a trifle under the weather.</p>
        <p>''Aaach-chooo,'' bellows Ms. Owens, balancing a dangerously full coffee cup (coffee and gum have replaced her cigarette habit) and a fistful of home magazines (like crabby Lucy from the ''Peanuts'' strip, she has had real estate envy since childhood, but Ms. Owens finally has the cash to indulge it) before letting loose with a diva-decibel sneeze.</p>
        <p>The minions scatter, then regroup. They have work to do if Ms. Owens, 30, is going to be transformed from frumpy to fabulous on schedule. Happens every day except her days off, and those have been rare since she recorded her first single at 17, sold 400,000 copies of her first album, ''All Hail The Queen,'' in 1989, legitimized female rap by winning a Grammy in 1994 with ''U.N.I.T.Y,'' her just-say-no-to-misogynists manifesto, spent five years on the sitcom ''Living Single'' and made eight films.</p>
        <p>''My mother always said, 'Dana, don't put all your eggs in one basket,' '' says Ms. Owens, who definitely didn't. She also owns Flavor Unit Entertainment, a record label, management firm, and television and film production company. ''I figured if I couldn't be the best rapper on the planet, I'd better have something to fall back on behind the desk.''</p>
        <p>By the way, after 12 years of entrepreneurism, not counting part-time gigs at Burger King and the Wiz during high school, Ms. Owens is tired enough of the grind to fantasize about motherhood. She irreverently calls it ''impregnation,'' and admits she's waiting for a man with a well-stocked wallet, confiding that she has never had a boyfriend with money.</p>
        <p>She has found a nest in suburban New Jersey, not far from her mother in Wayne. If Puffy can infiltrate East Hampton, she figures there's room for Queen Latifah in Upper Saddle River. It's a house on two acres with, most intriguing, 4,500 square feet of unfinished basement. (She has a thing for basements, having begun her rapping career in one.) She envisions maybe a mini-basketball court. Maybe a recording studio. Probably not a gym unless her trainer insists.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, she's got that public face to put on. ''You never really get used to it; you just do it,'' she says.</p>
        <p>SOMEHOW, the suitcase full of makeup has to end up on her skin, and that pile of snap-on hair extensions (you bet they snap) have to embellish what's left of the natural stuff. Ms. Owens used to be a tomboy who had to be reminded, even threatened, by her mother to comb her hair. Not anymore. She's got other people to do it, admits she'd ''have a breakdown'' if she had to go it alone. See, she's a ''spoiled'' star who takes pride in her reputation for being unspoiled. It's her gift for empathy, she says, that makes her unique to the talk show glut: Oprah, watch your back, you've got an ambitious -- hipper -- understudy.</p>
        <p>Ms. Owens is still surrounded by alumni from her basement days. Her security director -- the post became pivotal after she was the victim of an armed carjacking in 1995 and was arrested for packing an unregistered pistol for protection in 1996 -- is her father, a retired Newark police officer. He has reappeared in her life after moving out when she was 10. The ensuing divorce sent her into the projects with her brother and mother, a teacher.</p>
        <p>''Everything now with the family, with life, is good; where I am spiritually, I'm connected to it all,'' she says. ''It's like a plug that fell out of the wall and somebody found it and plugged it back in.''</p>
        <p>Right now Ms. Owens seems more worried about catching a cold than catching hell if she's late to her dress rehearsal for the Lane Bryant fashion show, where she's making her catwalk debut in a thigh-high suede skirt. ''And getting paid for it,'' she whoops, thrilled to shill for a company that ''represents big, beautiful women like me.''</p>
        <p>Her first role model was Jacques Cousteau: such a performer. Even under water. Then came the music: that the industry discriminated against women was a wrong she wanted to set right. And Hollywood? She had to prove that Queen Latifah was an actress, not a novelty act, and as a lesbian bank robber in ''Set It Off'' (1996), she did.</p>
        <p>''When I lost my brother, all my feelings just went numb, I shut down,'' she says, referring to his 1993 motorcycle accident. ''But when I took that part, I really had to deal with my own demons, had to laugh, cry, struggle, falter, even die in the end. It was the first challenge I set for myself after he died. And I came through it.''</p>
        <p>Next challenge: persuading her fans to vote. She gets an expletive out of her system -- blame it on the Republicans -- then wraps up her case in rap: ''If people are going to be apathetic, that's pathetic.'' She even envisions her talk show job, paycheck aside, as a public service: ''Dear Abby for the hip-hop generation, that's me.''</p>
        <p>PUBLIC LIVES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
