<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Youthful Wolfe Filled With Outrage</title>
    <meta content="15WELC$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/15/arts/15WELC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230609"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mint Theater Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wolfe, Thomas Clayton (1900-38)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weber, Bruce</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Welcome to Our City (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000915T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE5DE1338F936A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="954" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Youthful Wolfe Filled With Outrage</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRUCE WEBER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Weber, Bruce</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bruce Weber reviews Mint Theater Company's production of Welcome to Our City by Thomas Wolfe; photo; play was performed twice by Wolfe's fellow Harvard students in 1923 and only once after that, in Zurich in 1962; work is resurrected to mark centennial of Wolfe's birth October 3 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Thomas Wolfe was a long-winded playwright before he took to writing long-winded novels, which he did at least in part because he couldn't get anyone to produce his work for the stage. ''Welcome to Our City,'' a play he wrote while in graduate school at Harvard, was performed twice by his fellow students in 1923 and only once after that, in Zurich in 1962, translated into German. This, in any case, is the claim of the Mint Theater Company, which has resurrected the work in honor of the centennial of Wolfe's birth on Oct. 3.</p>
        <p>There are two possible interpretations for such a sparse production history, the more reverential one being the Mint's: that this is a worthy work lying undiscovered and waiting for rescue from oblivion. It is also the wrong one, for ''Welcome to Our City,'' an outraged treatise on race, class and the evils of American capitalism, is written with all the vociferous self-righteousness of the smartest kid in the class; unhappily, it's also presented that way.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Thomas Wolfe was a long-winded playwright before he took to writing long-winded novels, which he did at least in part because he couldn't get anyone to produce his work for the stage. ''Welcome to Our City,'' a play he wrote while in graduate school at Harvard, was performed twice by his fellow students in 1923 and only once after that, in Zurich in 1962, translated into German. This, in any case, is the claim of the Mint Theater Company, which has resurrected the work in honor of the centennial of Wolfe's birth on Oct. 3.</p>
        <p>There are two possible interpretations for such a sparse production history, the more reverential one being the Mint's: that this is a worthy work lying undiscovered and waiting for rescue from oblivion. It is also the wrong one, for ''Welcome to Our City,'' an outraged treatise on race, class and the evils of American capitalism, is written with all the vociferous self-righteousness of the smartest kid in the class; unhappily, it's also presented that way.</p>
        <p>Set in Altamont, the fictionalized town that Wolfe based on his home, Asheville, N.C., and where he would set much of his later work, the play depicts a place in the middle of a real estate boom, where flush times have encouraged a narrowing of the minds. Jews are disparaged, the local university professor who teaches evolution has been dismissed and the governor is willfully superficial.</p>
        <p>''Gentlemen, in my opinion, God and good weather are the two greatest campaign issues the Democratic Party has ever had,'' he tells a country club dining room full of toadying supporters. ''As you know, in my campaign I came out in favor of both.'' Such is the subtlety of the play's satire.</p>
        <p>The plot is driven by the desire of the city's autocrats to relocate the enclave of black citizens away from the center of town by buying up the homes they live in and evicting them. The plan is thwarted by the refusal of one man to sell; he's a black doctor who owns his own home. He's reviled, of course, by whites for presuming to live above his station, and he also happens to have a daughter who happens to be carrying on with the son of the man who is trying to force him to sell. Friction ensues, then conflagration. At one point, the wife of the leading white character asks her husband, referring to the city's blacks: ''What are we going to do with those people, Will?''</p>
        <p>His reply: ''It begins to look, honey, as if we're going to have to understand them.''</p>
        <p>Get it?</p>
        <p>Eighty years ago, there was, no doubt, a measure of bravery in the play's critique of middle-class white American values and even some prescience in its prediction of race warfare. Certainly Wolfe himself thought so. ''If my play goes on,'' he wrote to his mother, ''I want you to be prepared for execrations upon my head.''</p>
        <p>But righteousness and foresight aren't terribly powerful or interesting when they're dramatized so clunkily, when the dialogue is almost exclusively written in expositional paragraphs, when not a single character has an idiosyncrasy to distinguish him from his stereotype. It's difficult to overstate the tedium of the text, which is the main execration that Wolfe should ever have had hurled at him.</p>
        <p>It would be one thing if the play were presented as an artifact, with an arched eyebrow. But Jonathan Bank, the Mint's artistic director and also the director of this production, is evidently a true believer in the play's substance. His staging is so reverent as to seem fearful of humor or retrospective commentary. Scene after scene consists of people making declamation after declamation, and Mr. Bank lets them speechify without much locomotion. When passions are aroused, the action is stilted; the physical encounters among the characters are simulated with embarrassing awkwardness.</p>
        <p>Indeed, perhaps the most remarkable thing about this production is the curtain call. The play has 23 different roles, and amazingly the Mint -- an eight-year-old company that has salvaged worthier forgotten plays with well-received productions -- has employed 20 actors to fill them. They are variously skilled, from passable to amateurish, but just one performance, that of Colleen Smith Wallnau, is distinctive; her embrace of her dopey, casually racist stereotype is fearless, and her accent is true.</p>
        <p>The big question is how an Off Off Broadway company can afford them all. And you have to wonder why it would spend its resources on a work whose primary value is as a literary curiosity.</p>
        <p>WELCOME TO OUR CITY  By Thomas Wolfe; directed by Jonathan Bank; sets by Vicki R. Davis; costumes by Elly Van Horne; lighting by Randy Glickman; music and sound by Ellen Mandel; fight choreographer, Michael Chin; properties master, Janine Pangburn; production stage manager, Francis Eric E. Montesa. Presented by the Mint Theater, Mr. Bank, artistic director. At 311 West 43rd Street, Clinton.</p>
        <p>WITH: Haakon Jepsen (Henry Sorrell), Patrick Riviere (Joseph Bailey), Frank Swingler (Uncle Amos), Lee Moore (Mr. Rutledge), Michael Moore (Lee Rutledge), Colleen Smith Wallnau (Mrs. Rutledge), Eric R. Moreland (Dr. Johnson), Sylver Gregory (Annie Johnson) and Don Clark Williams (Sam Tipton).</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
