<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Colgate Shares Drop 16% After Reports by Analysts</title>
    <meta content="Y15COL$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/15/business/15COLG.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230657"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Colgate-Palmolive Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Winter, Greg</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000915T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE1D81338F936A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="622" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Colgate Shares Drop 16% After Reports by Analysts</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GREG WINTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Winter, Greg</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Shares of Colgate-Palmolive drop nearly 16 percent after analysts express doubts that company will meet sales targets, citing yearlong plunge in the euro; high petroleum prices are expected to limit Colgate's ability to cut costs; shares drop $8.81, to $47.38 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Shares of Colgate-Palmolive tumbled nearly 16 percent yesterday after analysts expressed doubts that the company would meet sales targets, citing the yearlong plunge in the euro.</p>
        <p>Stubbornly high petroleum prices, meanwhile, are expected to limit Colgate's ability to cut costs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Shares of Colgate-Palmolive tumbled nearly 16 percent yesterday after analysts expressed doubts that the company would meet sales targets, citing the yearlong plunge in the euro.</p>
        <p>Stubbornly high petroleum prices, meanwhile, are expected to limit Colgate's ability to cut costs.</p>
        <p>In recent quarters, Colgate, the maker of America's best-selling toothpaste and dishwashing liquid, has been a bastion of strength in the consumer products industry, consistently meeting and exceeding analysts' forecasts at a time when some of its principal competitors -- including Procter &amp; Gamble, Clorox, and Dial -- have repeatedly warned of lethargic sales. As a result, investor enthusiasm for Colgate has surged, propelling its stock price to 35 times  earnings as of Wednesday, up to 60 percent higher than others in the  category, analysts said.</p>
        <p>But after Colgate executives discussed operations with several analysts on Wednesday, they began predicting that sales would fall short.</p>
        <p>Andrew Shore, an influential analyst with Deutsche Banc Alex. Brown, said that the company's third-quarter results ''will signal a  reversal of fortune.'' Mr. Shore downgraded the company's stock from ''buy'' to ''market perform,'' unleashing a sell-off that clipped nearly $5 billion from Colgate's market value before lunch. Shares of Colgate dropped $8.81 to $47.38, and other consumer products stocks fell, as well, on word of the downgrade.</p>
        <p>Reuben Mark, Colgate's chairman and chief executive, issued a midday statement saying the company expected to meet analysts' earnings expectations, but that did little to reverse the stock's slide. Though Colgate may report high earnings this quarter, analysts fear that the company will have to tap into its reserves and cut back on expenses like advertising to do so, moves that would hurt its future prospects.</p>
        <p>Some analysts speculated that, even if temporary, the company's dip in stock price could make it an acquisition target for overseas companies looking to break into the American market. Both Henkel, the giant German consumer products giant, and Kao, Asia's powerhouse in the industry, are seeking a foothold in the United States. Marketing their own products here would be futile, analysts say, because Americans are fiercely loyal to the brands they recognize, so a takeover of a momentarily rattled company might be appealing.</p>
        <p>Even after yesterday's decline, Colgate's stock price is high enough to dissuade a potential acquirer, some analysts said. Yet the challenges facing Colgate appear to be long term, so Colgate's stock could remain under pressure.</p>
        <p>Like its rivals, Colgate is hurt by high fuel prices, which increase shipping costs. Colgate also uses oil-based resins in packaging for its products. But the company has a difficult time passing rising expenses on to consumers, because increasingly powerful retailers like Wal-Mart and Costco tend to compete on price. Moreover, the big retail chains are bringing out more products of their own, presenting yet  another set of competitors.</p>
        <p>Until now, Colgate has managed to use aggressive marketing to withstand industry pressures, and even gain on its rivals. Colgate toothpaste now outsells Crest, and Palmolive  dishwashing soap beats Dawn in sales, analysts said.</p>
        <p>Colgate-Palmolive has also been buffered by the dominant market position of its Hill Science Diet pet food, a high-end product found in specialty retail stores like Petco and Petsmart. But analysts fear Hill Science's sales growth will reach a plateau now that Procter &amp; Gamble has started selling its premium Iams pet food in supermarkets.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
