<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; Needing New Blood To Survive</title>
    <meta content="15VECS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/15/olympics/15VECSEY.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230639"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">International Olympic Committee</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vecsey, George</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/George Vecsey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000915T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806EEDA1338F936A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="800" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; Needing New Blood To Survive</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGE VECSEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Vecsey, George</byline>
      <dateline>SYDNEY, Australia</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>George Vecsey Sports of The Times column on need for change at International Olympic Committee in light of current and past blunders; calls for chief executive that knows how to handle money, law, public and press; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE sun is setting on fading empires. Gerontocracies are going out of style. The Olympic movement is starting to resemble the Soviet Union in its final days, just before people attacked the Berlin Wall with sledgehammers. In this case, the cracks are appearing from within.</p>
        <p>The newest set of Summer Games is beginning this weekend, following an opening ceremony that should be both touching and spectacular. But there are a lot of extravaganzas in the world, a lot of sporting jamborees, and there is no guarantee that people are going to buy this retro act much longer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE sun is setting on fading empires. Gerontocracies are going out of style. The Olympic movement is starting to resemble the Soviet Union in its final days, just before people attacked the Berlin Wall with sledgehammers. In this case, the cracks are appearing from within.</p>
        <p>The newest set of Summer Games is beginning this weekend, following an opening ceremony that should be both touching and spectacular. But there are a lot of extravaganzas in the world, a lot of sporting jamborees, and there is no guarantee that people are going to buy this retro act much longer.</p>
        <p>The world is getting smaller. The Sydney Morning Herald ran photographs of Darryl Strawberry and Monday night football yesterday. To love the Olympics for the next two weeks, you have to go along with the program -- gold medals, old-fashioned amateur sport, sound mind and sound body, fair play. The old ideals don't work with the world snickering in the background.</p>
        <p>It is the sadness of Juan Antonio Samaranch that he stayed on too long. He knows it. The look of weariness is on his face. He no longer makes any pretense at having fun with this business. It's over. The real question is where the International Olympic Committee goes from here. Can it hold Summer Games in Athens in 2004 and in some undesignated city in 2008 with the guaranteed full obeisance of the host city? Those days may be over. Before the first shuttlecock is fired in anger here, the powers that be have already spent a week that would have embarrassed the average elected public official.</p>
        <p>Samaranch and his Politburo were seen agitating over missing brethren, a boxing fixer from Uzbekistan and a basketball officer from Hong Kong who were denied entry by the Australian government on the grounds of questionable activities. The I.O.C. also seemed highly perturbed about the legal troubles of an Indonesian colleague known for razing the rain forest and supporting an old dictatorship back home. With friends like these . . ., as the saying goes.</p>
        <p>It was extremely bad timing for the Olympic movement to have the next two sets of Games already assigned to cheeky former colonies. People in Australia generally like to hoot at pomposity, and they have surely enjoyed watching the I.O.C. fumble around this week.</p>
        <p>Then there is the ongoing spectacle from Salt Lake City, where two former big shots are set up to take the hit for the rich burghers they served. The I.O.C. heavies are furious that documents from Salt Lake City organizers would be accessible in potential trials.</p>
        <p>''Why didn't you just burn everything like our esteemed colleagues in Nagano did?'' the I.O.C. honchos seemed to be shrieking, while a few Yanks tried to explain that the laws of the land allow distribution of evidence. Peculiar place, this America.</p>
        <p>It's all going bad. Yesterday, Samaranch held his quadrennial news conference before the opening of the Games. As if the mood around the I.O.C. were not operatic enough, somebody piped in the sounds of Pavarotti singing ''Nessun dorma'' from ''Turandot.'' He spoke of the ''enhanced role of women on our executive board,'' noted the inclusion of contemporary athletes, praised alleged advances in testing for drugs, alluded to healing gestures between the two Koreas, between Bosnia and Herzegovina, and the inclusion of athletes from East Timor. He made it all seem so banal.</p>
        <p>Somebody asked if Samaranch planned to go to Salt Lake City in 2002, and he answered: ''If I am invited. I am awaiting an invitation.'' Lawyers will be on call. The future of the Olympic movement is in the hands of the United States Justice Department. If the Games survive, the United States won't be the host for a century.</p>
        <p>While Samaranch presided over this exercise in ostensible democracy, he was flanked by younger I.O.C. officials of some talent and charm and integrity, undoubtedly still hoping for their turn. Have they been tainted by the blatant associations with hustlers from outposts like Uzbekistan and Salt Lake City? Quite possibly.</p>
        <p>What the I.O.C. may need is to go out and hire a chief executive officer who knows how to handle money, handle the law, handle the public, handle the press. It needs a David Stern of the National Basketball Association, a Dick Ebersol of the National Broadcasting Company, a David D'Alessandro of the John Hancock Company, just to mention three skilled Yanks who just might be able to save the I.O.C.</p>
        <p>There are cracks in the Lausanne Wall. A few more snickers from the colonies, and the walls come tumbling down.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
