<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>SPARE TIMES</title>
    <meta content="15SPAR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="37" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230601"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000915T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E2DF1338F936A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="5306" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>SPARE TIMES</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ATTRACTIONS</p>
        <p>Museums and Sites</p>
        <p>AMERICAN MUSEUM OF NATURAL HISTORY, Central Park West and 79th Street. ''Fighting Dinosaurs: New Discoveries From Mongolia,'' featuring one of the most famous fossil finds in the world; through Oct. 29. ''Mongolia Observed: Photographs Present and Past,'' featuring 40 color images by Robert Peck and black-and-white photographs by the explorer Ray Chapman Andrews from the 1920's and 30's. Imax films are ''To Be an Astronaut'' and ''Dolphins.'' In the Imax Theater tonight and tomorrow night at 9, ''Laser Aerosmith in 3-D''; at 10, ''Laser Led Zeppelin.'' Laser show tickets: $12. Museum hours: Sundays through Thursdays, 10 a.m. to 5:45 p.m.; Fridays and Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 8:45 p.m. Admission (suggested donation): $10 for adults; $7.50 for students and the elderly; $6 for children. Combination tickets are available. Information: (212) 769-5100; advance tickets: (212) 769-5200.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ATTRACTIONS</p>
        <p>Museums and Sites</p>
        <p>AMERICAN MUSEUM OF NATURAL HISTORY, Central Park West and 79th Street. ''Fighting Dinosaurs: New Discoveries From Mongolia,'' featuring one of the most famous fossil finds in the world; through Oct. 29. ''Mongolia Observed: Photographs Present and Past,'' featuring 40 color images by Robert Peck and black-and-white photographs by the explorer Ray Chapman Andrews from the 1920's and 30's. Imax films are ''To Be an Astronaut'' and ''Dolphins.'' In the Imax Theater tonight and tomorrow night at 9, ''Laser Aerosmith in 3-D''; at 10, ''Laser Led Zeppelin.'' Laser show tickets: $12. Museum hours: Sundays through Thursdays, 10 a.m. to 5:45 p.m.; Fridays and Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 8:45 p.m. Admission (suggested donation): $10 for adults; $7.50 for students and the elderly; $6 for children. Combination tickets are available. Information: (212) 769-5100; advance tickets: (212) 769-5200.</p>
        <p>AMERICAN MUSEUM OF NATURAL HISTORY'S ROSE CENTER FOR EARTH AND SPACE, Central Park West at 81st Street. This 333,500-square-foot, seven-floor, 120-foot-high exhibition and research center includes the new Hayden Planetarium, the Cullman Hall of the Universe and the Gottesman Hall of Planet Earth. The Hayden Planetarium contains the Space Theater, presenting ''Passport to the Universe,'' and the Big Bang Theater, featuring narrated visual and audio effects simulating the beginning of the universe. ''Starry Nights: Fridays Under the Sphere,'' music tonight from 5:45 and 7:15, with the Mark Whitfield Quartet. Free with admission; food and cash bar. Hours: Sundays through Thursdays, 10 a.m. to 5:45 p.m.; Fridays and Saturdays to 8:45 p.m. Space shows run throughout the day. Admission (suggested donation) to the American Museum of Natural History, which includes the Rose Center: $10; for students and the elderly, $7.50; children 12 and under, $6; under 2, free. Admission to the museum, the Rose Center and the Hayden Planetarium space show: $19; students and the elderly, $14; children 12 and under, $11.50; under 2, free. Information: (212) 769-5100. Reservations: (212) 769-5200.</p>
        <p>MOUNT VERNON HOTEL MUSEUM, formerly the Abigail Adams Smith Museum, 421 East 61st Street, Manhattan. The structure, built in 1799 as the carriage house for Abigail Adams and Col. William Smith, was the Mount Vernon Hotel in the 1830's. Sunday at 2 p.m., ''Lydia Maria Child: A Woman of Her Time,'' a lecture about Ms. Child's writing. Admission: $8; museum members $6. Hours: guided tours every half-hour beginning at 11 a.m.; last tour is at 3:30 p.m. Tuesdays through Sundays, 11 a.m. to 4 p.m.; closed Mondays. Admission: $4; students and the elderly, $3; 12 and under, free. Information: (212) 838-6878.</p>
        <p>MUSEUM OF THE CITY OF NEW YORK, Fifth Avenue at 103rd Street. The museum collects, preserves and presents material related to the city's history. For ''New York Now 2000: Contemporary Work in Photography,'' Sunday at 2 p.m., the photographers Vincent Cianni, Andrew Moore and Susan Wides lecture about their work on exhibition, through Oct. 15. Hours: Tuesdays, 10 a.m. to 2 p.m., for registered groups only; Wednesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Suggested admission: $7; the elderly, students and children, $4; families, $12. Information: (212) 534-1672.</p>
        <p>MUSEUM OF JEWISH HERITAGE: A LIVING MEMORIAL TO THE HOLOCAUST, 18 First Place, at West Street and Battery Place, Battery Park City, Lower Manhattan. Artifacts, documents, photographs, videos and film clips are included in exhibitions on the Holocaust and on Jewish life before and after World War II. ''Children of a Vanished World: Photographs by Roman Vishniac,'' through Oct. 20. Sunday at 2 p.m., panel discussion about Dr. Walter Jonas Judah, the first American-born Jewish student to pursue a medical career in New York; free, with museum admission. Hours: Sundays through Wednesdays, 9 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Thursdays until 8 p.m.; Fridays and the eves of Jewish holidays, 9 a.m. to 3 p.m.; closed Saturdays. Admission: $7; students and the elderly, $5; children 5 and under, free. Tickets can be bought in advance through Ticketmaster, (212) 307-4007, or by calling the museum on the day of the visit, (212) 945-0039. Information: (212) 509-6130.</p>
        <p>STATEN ISLAND INSTITUTE OF ARTS AND SCIENCES, 75 Stuyvesant Place, St. George. Staten Island Ferry tours with a lecture by museum staff members about landmarks including Ellis Island, the Museum of Jewish Heritage, the Statue of Liberty, the World Trade Center, Pouch Terminal and the Brooklyn Bridge. Tours meet at the Council on the Arts and Humanities for Staten Island Visit Center in Whitehall Terminal in Manhattan, Fridays through Oct. 27, at 1:30 p.m. Admission: $5. Reservations for ferry: (718) 727-1135, extension 29. Museum hours: Mondays through Saturdays, 9 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Suggested admission: $2.50; students, children and the elderly, $1.50; free for members. Information: (718) 727-1135.</p>
        <p>WORLD FINANCIAL CENTER, World Financial Center Courtyard Gallery, 200 Liberty Street, between West Street and Vesey Street, Lower Manhattan. ''Carnegie Hall Neighborhood Concert Series,'' with performances by the American Brass Orchestra, Mike Errico, Eliot Fisk, the Flying Neutrinos, Bob Green and Co., Leonore String Quartet, Talujon Percussion Quartet, Chris Washburne and the Syotos Band. On the World Financial Center Plaza, outside the Winter Garden. Tomorrow from 2 to 6 p.m. Free. Information: (212) 945-0505.</p>
        <p>Gardens</p>
        <p>STATEN ISLAND BOTANICAL GARDEN, 1000 Richmond Terrace, Livingston. Tonight, ''Opera in the Garden,'' with the Regina Opera Company performing scenes from ''Madama Butterfly'' and the YehYu Chinese Opera Association performing scenes from ''Farewell My Concubine''; 8 p.m. Admission: $5; $4 for the elderly and students and children under 12. Reservations: (718) 273-8200 extension 1020. ''China: Ancient Art and Sciences,'' featuring 13 artisans from China demonstrating their craft and 300 works of art; through Oct. 1. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Admission to the Chinese Scholars' Garden: $7.50; $5 for the elderly and students and children under 12; under 1, free. Information: (718) 273-8200.</p>
        <p>WAVE HILL, West 249th Street and Independence Avenue, Riverdale, the Bronx. Gardens, greenhouses and woodlands are part of the 28-acre garden and cultural institution. ''Beneath the Bark, Under Leaf and Log,'' an outdoor installation by Sylvia Benitez; through Oct. 30. Tai chi programs, Saturdays at 10 a.m., beginners; 11 a.m., intermediates; $7. Saturdays from 1 to 4 p.m. through Oct. 28, visitors can work along foresters to prune, plant and clear excess vegetation. Tuesdays through Sundays, 9 a.m. to 5:30 p.m. Admission: $4; students and the elderly, $2; Saturdays, free until noon. Information: (718) 549-3200; reservations: extension 213.</p>
        <p>Zoos</p>
        <p>BRONX ZOO, Bronx River Parkway and Fordham Road, Fordham. Some 265 wooded acres are devoted to naturalistic habitats, including Jungle World, African Plains, the Baboon Reserve, the World of Birds, the Aitken Sea Bird Colony (with penguin feedings daily at 3:30 p.m.), Big Birds and the Congo Gorilla Forest (admission: $3 when the gorillas are outside, depending on the weather). The Butterfly Zone is open through Oct. 1, with thousands of butterflies and moths and an area where visitors can see the metamorphosis of chrysalides, or cocoons, into butterflies or moths (Admission: $2). Through Sept. 30, daily tours; reservations necessary: (718) 220-5141. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 10 a.m. to 5:30 p.m. General admission, $9; $5 for children 2 to 12 and the elderly; free general admission for everyone on Wednesdays. Parking: $6. Information: (718) 367-1010.</p>
        <p>Cruises</p>
        <p>CIRCLE LINE CRUISES, leaving from Pier 83, 42nd Street at the Hudson River, Clinton. A two-hour, 24-mile cruise around southern Manhattan passing landmarks like Ellis Island and the United Nations, daily at 11 a.m., 2 p.m. and 4:30 p.m. Tickets: $20; children 12 and under, $10; the elderly, $16. A three-hour, 35-mile cruise around all of Manhattan, daily at 9:30, 10:15 and 11:45 a.m., 12:30, 1:15, 2:45 and 3:30 p.m. Tickets: $24; children 12 and under, $12; the elderly, $19. ''Harbor Lights,'' daily at 7 p.m. Tickets: $20; children 12 and under, $10; the elderly, $16. ''The Beast,'' 30-minute speedboat ride in the harbor, daily, every hour on the hour, 11 a.m. to dusk, except Wednesdays, when it is 2 p.m. to dusk. Tickets: $15; children 5 to 12, $10. Information: (212) 563-3200.</p>
        <p>WORLD YACHT, leaving from Pier 81, 41st Street at the Hudson River, Clinton. Daily dinner cruises along the West Side of Manhattan and around New York Harbor, from 7 to 10 p.m., boarding at 6 p.m. Prices: Fridays, $79.13; Saturdays, $83.46; Sundays, $70.46 (does not include beverages, taxes or gratuities). Brunch cruises sail on Sundays from 12:30 to 2:30 p.m., with boarding at 11:30 a.m. Price: $43.71; children 12 and under, $23.43. Information: (212) 630-8100.</p>
        <p>RECREATION</p>
        <p>''RACE FOR THE CURE,'' Central Park. A five-kilometer walk or run sponsored by the Susan G. Komen Breast Cancer Foundation. Sunday at 9 a.m. Registration fee, $20 in advance, $25 on Sunday. Information: (212) 293-2873.</p>
        <p>''MEMORY WALK 2000,'' Lower Manhattan. A two-mile walk, beginning at Pier 16 and the South Street Seaport. Sunday at 10 a.m.; registration begins at 8 a.m. Registration fee, $17.50. Sponsored by the Alzheimer's Association, New York Chapter. Information: (212) 983-0700, extension 231, or (212) 983-6906, extension 231.</p>
        <p>EVENTS</p>
        <p>''A CLOSE LOOK AT CHINA,'' Jacob K. Javits Convention Center, West 34th Street, at 11th Avenue, Manhattan. A display of art and fashion. Today, noon to 8 p.m. Free. Information: (877) 772-5673.</p>
        <p>OKTOBERFEST, South Street Seaport, Water and Fulton Streets, Lower Manhattan. Today, noon to 9 p.m. Free.</p>
        <p>NEW YORK ARMORY ANTIQUES SHOW, Seventh Regiment Armory, Park Avenue at 67th Street, Manhattan. Today and tomorrow, noon to 9 p.m.; Sunday, noon to 6 p.m. Admission, $10. Information: (212) 472-1180.</p>
        <p>''MEMORIES AND LITERATURE,'' Eldridge Street Project, 12 Eldridge Street, Lower East Side. The transformation of family memories into literature will be discussed by four writers: Andre Aciman, Douglas Century, Johanna Kaplan and Jonathan Rosen. Sunday at 3 p.m. Admission, $6; $4 for students and the elderly. Information: (212) 978-8800.</p>
        <p>15TH AUTUMN CRAFTS FESTIVAL, Lincoln Center. Featuring crafts by about 400 artisans. Tomorrow and Sunday, 11 a.m. to 7 p.m. Free admission.</p>
        <p>BIRD WATCHING IN BATTERY PARK CITY, Lower Manhattan. The first in a series of free bird-watching workshops. Meets tomorrow at 10:30 a.m. in Robert F. Wagner Jr. Park, at West Side Highway and Battery Place. Sponsored by the Battery Park City Parks Conservancy. Information: (212) 267-9700.</p>
        <p>33RD ANNUAL MAYOR'S CUP RACE, Lower Manhattan to Staten Island. More than 30 vessels will take part in a 12-mile race that begins tomorrow at noon at the South Street Seaport and continues to the Verrazano-Narrows Bridge, where participants turn around and head back to the Seaport. Best viewing on land is from Battery Park to North Cove Marina; spectators should take binoculars. There will also be a boat from which to view the race; fee, $25. Information: (212) 748-8738 or (212) 748-8786.</p>
        <p>EVENING BOAT TRIP, Jamaica Bay. Combines a pleasure trip with an exploration of the water and bird life. Tomorrow, 5 to 8 p.m. Sponsored by the Alley Pond Environmental Center, 228-06 Northern Boulevard, Queens. Tickets, $25; $20 for Center members. Information: (718) 229-4000.</p>
        <p>VOLUNTEER DAY AT THE CATHEDRAL OF ST. JOHN THE DIVINE, Cathedral House, Amsterdam Avenue and 111th Street, Morningside Heights. Participants can learn about activities at the cathedral. Tomorrow, 10 a.m. to noon. Information: (212) 932-7347.</p>
        <p>''ARTISTS' STUDIOS IN HARLEM.'' A tour of homes and studios. Sunday at 1 p.m. Fee, $25. Sponsored by the 92nd Street Y. Information: (212) 996-1100.</p>
        <p>''FAMILY SPORTS DAY 2000,'' Chelsea Piers, Field House, Hudson River and West 23rd Street. Featuring soccer, gymnastics, basketball, crafts and entertainment to benefit the city's children in foster care. Sunday, 4 to 7 P.M. Sponsored by New Yorkers for Children. Tickets, $125; $50 for children. Information: (212) 921-9070.</p>
        <p>''JOHN PHILIP SOUSA SPECTACULAR,'' World Trade Center, Tobin Plaza, Church Street between Vesey and Liberty Streets, Lower Manhattan. A free musical salute to the composer featuring the Ridgewood Concert Band and soloists. Sunday at 1 p.m. Sponsored by the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey. Information: (212) 435-4170.</p>
        <p>PROSPECT HEIGHTS HOUSE TOUR, Brooklyn. Visits Victorian and pre-Victorian houses, as well as cultural institutions. Meets Sunday at 1 at the Public School 9 annex, Sterling Place and Vanderbilt Avenue. Tickets, $10 in advance; $15 on Sunday. Information: (718) 707-1277.</p>
        <p>ON THE STREET</p>
        <p>''SALUTE TO WALL STREET FESTIVAL,'' Beaver Street, from Whitehall to William Streets, Lower Manhattan. Today, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. Sponsored by the John Huess House.</p>
        <p>74TH FEAST OF SAN GENNARO, Mulberry Street, between Canal and Houston Streets; and Hester and Grand Streets, between Baxter and Mott Streets, Little Italy. Through Sept. 24. Weekdays, 11:30 a.m. to 11:30 p.m.; weekends, 11:30 a.m. to midnight.</p>
        <p>FLEA MARKET, Southbridge Towers, courtyard, Beekman Street, off Fulton and Pearl Streets. Today and tomorrow, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m.</p>
        <p>GERMAN-AMERICAN STEUBEN DAY PARADE, Fifth Avenue from 63rd to 86th Streets, Manhattan. Tomorrow at noon.</p>
        <p>UNIVERSITY PLACE CORE FESTIVAL, University Place, from Eighth to 14th Street, Greenwich Village. Tomorrow, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. Sponsored by the Congress of Racial Equality.</p>
        <p>CITY ISLAND FAIR AND CLAM CHOWDER CONTEST, Hawkins Street Park, City Island Avenue, the Bronx. Tomorrow, 11 a.m. to 8 p.m. Sponsored by the City Island Chamber of Commerce.</p>
        <p>COLUMBUS AVENUE STREET FAIR, from 66th to 86th Streets, Manhattan. Sunday, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m.</p>
        <p>32ND AFRICAN-AMERICAN DAY PARADE, Harlem. Sunday at 2 p.m., beginning at Adam Clayton Powell Boulevard and 111th Street and heading north to 142nd Street.</p>
        <p>FIFTH AVENUE SUNSET PARK FESTIVAL AND PARADE, Fifth Avenue, from 44th to 59th Streets, Brooklyn. Sunday, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Sponsored by the Sunset Park Community Association Sunset.</p>
        <p>WALKING TOURS</p>
        <p>''JAZZ NIGHTS IN HARLEM.'' With stops at the Apollo Theater and Theresa Hotel, followed by dinner and a stop at a jazz club. Meets tonight and tomorrow night at 7:30 on the northeast corner of Lenox Avenue and 125th Street. Fee: $55. Sponsored by Harlem Heritage Tours. Reservations: (212) 280-7888.</p>
        <p>CARROLL GARDENS AND GOWANUS, Brooklyn. Includes stops at specialty food stores and a discussion of the revitalized Gowanus Canal. Meets tomorrow at 1 p.m. in Carroll Park, at the corner of Smith and Carroll Streets. Fee, $10; $8 for students and the elderly. Sponsored by Historic New York Tours. Information: (718) 729-4055.</p>
        <p>''REVOLUTIONARY MANHATTAN: THE SURRENDER OF FORT WASHINGTON'' takes walkers to the site of the ''Alamo'' of the Revolution. Meets tomorrow at 11 a.m. at the southern entrance to Fort Tryon Park, Margaret Corbin Plaza, near the 190th Street entrance to the A train. Fee, $15. Sponsored by Century Walking Tours. Information: (201) 433-0946.</p>
        <p>''CHILD-FRIENDLY RAMBLE: CHINATOWN FOR CHILDREN.'' Stops on this tour include a Buddhist temple and a Chinese grocery store. Meets Sunday at noon on the northwest corner of the Bowery and Canal Street at the Petrella newsstand. Fee: $6. Sponsored by Dr. Phil's New York Talks and Walks. Information: (888) 377-4455.</p>
        <p>''ASIA FANTASIA IN QUEENS.'' With stops at restaurants, music shops and clothing stores. Sunday at 11 a.m. Fee, $25 (includes lunch). Sponsored by the 92nd Street Y. Information: (212) 996-1100.</p>
        <p>GREEN-WOOD CEMETERY, Brooklyn. Covering the history and architecture of the ''City of the Dead,'' as well as the noted people buried there, including Louis C. Tiffany. Meets tomorrow at 1 p.m. at the entrance at Fifth Avenue and 25th Street, Sunset Park. Sponsored by Big Onion Walking Tours. Fee, $12; $10 for students and the elderly. Information: (212) 439-1090.</p>
        <p>''LOWER EAST SIDE, AND IRISH AND ITALIAN IMMIGRANT HIGHLIGHTS,'' Lower Manhattan. The first tour passes historic and notorious locations from Chatham Square to Seward Park; the second focuses on the churches and other sites of importance to  Irish and Italian communities. The Lower East Side tour runs tomorrow and Sunday at 11:45 a.m.; the Irish-Italian walk follows tomorrow and Sunday at 2:15 p.m. Fee, $11 for one tour, $5 for additional tour. Sponsored by Gotham Walk. Information: (212) 629-1886.</p>
        <p>''ON BROADWAY: HERALD SQUARE AND TIMES SQUARE IN TRANSITION'' proceeds north along Broadway, from 34th to 42nd Streets. Meets Sunday at 1 p.m. on the northeast corner of Fifth Avenue and 34th Street. Sponsored by the Municipal Art Society. Fee, $15; $12 for Society members. Information: (212) 935-3930.</p>
        <p>''ACROSS BROOKLYN BRIDGE: VISTAS, VIEWS AND HISTORY'' combines a stroll with a discussion of the span's history. Meets Sunday at 2 p.m. in front of the fountain in City Hall Park. Fee, $10. Sponsored by Bernie's New York. Information: (718) 655-1883.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
