<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pace Artist Is Designing New Gallery</title>
    <meta content="15INSI$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/15/arts/15INSI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230611"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="INSIDE ART"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Chelsea (NYC)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Kimbell Art Museum (Fort Worth, Tex)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">PaceWildenstein</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Michelozzo di Bartolommeo (15th Century)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Irwin, Robert</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Columns/Inside Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000915T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E4DE1338F936A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1015" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pace Artist Is Designing New Gallery</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Carol Vogel</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Inside Art column; California artist Robert Irwin is designing new Chelsea gallery for PaceWildenstein; other dealers also opening in Chelsea noted; Kimbell Art Museum buys gilt bronze statue of St John the Baptist, recently identified as long-lost masterpiece by 15th-century Florentine sculptor Michelozzo di Bartolommeo; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On Jan. 10, PaceWildenstein plans to close its 10-year-old gallery at 142 Greene Street in SoHo and migrate to Chelsea, opening in mid-March at 534 West 25th Street. While Pace will keep its sleek 57th Street space, its new location will be something of an artwork. Arne Glimcher, chairman of PaceWildenstein, has commissioned the California artist Robert Irwin to design the space.</p>
        <p>Mr. Irwin, whom Pace has represented since 1966, is the design consultant to the Dia Center for the Arts's new branch in Beacon, N.Y. ''We've been watching Bob's drawings of Beacon, and thought he'd be perfect to design our new gallery,'' Mr. Glimcher said. ''Nobody understands light the way Irwin does.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On Jan. 10, PaceWildenstein plans to close its 10-year-old gallery at 142 Greene Street in SoHo and migrate to Chelsea, opening in mid-March at 534 West 25th Street. While Pace will keep its sleek 57th Street space, its new location will be something of an artwork. Arne Glimcher, chairman of PaceWildenstein, has commissioned the California artist Robert Irwin to design the space.</p>
        <p>Mr. Irwin, whom Pace has represented since 1966, is the design consultant to the Dia Center for the Arts's new branch in Beacon, N.Y. ''We've been watching Bob's drawings of Beacon, and thought he'd be perfect to design our new gallery,'' Mr. Glimcher said. ''Nobody understands light the way Irwin does.''</p>
        <p>Though he stresses that he is first and foremost an artist, Mr. Irwin has put on a design hat before, helping with the design of places like the Museum of Contemporary Art in San Diego. ''I looked at other galleries in Chelsea, those swept-out spaces each with elaborate architectural statements,'' he said. ''I'm a fan of modernism, but here it seemed out of character.'' He plans to conceive a design that he feels is more appropriate to Chelsea, with its warehouse buildings and garages dating from the early 20th century.</p>
        <p>''I'm leaving some vestiges of the old building -- a pair of garages -- like the wood beam ceiling,'' he said. He also plans to put in vertical windows with brick columns between them. ''At first it will look symmetrical,'' Mr. Irwin said, ''But they're actually asymmetrical.''</p>
        <p>Around the Corner</p>
        <p>PaceWildenstein is just one of a number of dealers moving to Chelsea. Some have just opened; others, like Pace, are in the throes of renovations.</p>
        <p>Like PaceWildenstein, Mary Boone is keeping her uptown gallery but plans to open in Chelsea on Nov. 4. Her new gallery, at 541 West 24th Street, is in a space that virtually backs up to PaceWildenstein. Charles Cowles, a SoHo dealer who has temporarily taken space at 74 Grand Street after moving out of 420 West Broadway, will be her neighbor. His new gallery, at 537 West 24th Street, is expected to open the first week in January.</p>
        <p>Another hot spot is 535 West 22nd Street, where seven dealers -- six of them from SoHo -- have leased space from Dia.</p>
        <p>Michael Govan, Dia's director, said it had bought the 1917 building, originally a warehouse, in 1992 to exhibit its permanent collection. ''But once our new museum in Beacon got under way we decided to rent it,'' he said. Part of the center's goal is to set an example to try to ensure that the neighborhood will not be taken over by trendy shops: the leases for the building stipulate that all tenants must be art galleries.</p>
        <p>The six SoHo dealers that will be occupying the building are Friedrich Petzel, which opened last week on the ground floor; Marianne Boesky, which opened last week on the second floor; Yancey Richardson, which plans to open on Nov. 11 on the third floor; CRG Gallery, also scheduled to open on Nov. 11 on the third floor; Frederieke Taylor/TZ'Art Gallery, opening on Oct. 21 on the sixth floor; and Julie Saul, also planning to open on Oct. 21 on the sixth floor. Leslie Tonkonow Artworks Projects, which was at 601 West 26th Street, hopes to open on the sixth floor in mid-October.</p>
        <p>After 17 years in the Fuller Building on 57th Street, ACA expects to open in mid-October on the fifth floor of 529 West 20th Street. It will be joined by Paul Rodgers/9W, opening next Friday on the ninth floor. Howard Scott opened last week on the seventh floor.</p>
        <p>Three old-time artist cooperatives -- Bowery Gallery, Prince Street and Blue Mountain -- will be leaving their SoHo space on Dec. 1, after 10 years, and moving to 530 West 25th Street. They hope to reopen in March.</p>
        <p>Kimbell Buys Rarity</p>
        <p>The Kimbell Art Museum in Fort Worth has announced its latest purchase: a gilt bronze statue of St. John the Baptist, recently identified as a lost masterpiece by the Florentine sculptor and architect Michelozzo di Bartolommeo.</p>
        <p>The sculpture, 22 5/8 inches high, was commissioned by Piero de' Medici around 1450 for the church  known as the Santissima Annunziata in Florence.</p>
        <p>The only known works by Michelozzo outside Italy are two fragmentary marble angels in the Victoria and Albert Museum in London. ''There has not been a more important Renaissance discovery than this in a generation,'' said Timothy Potts, director of the Kimbell. ''It's one of the first free-standing sculptures in the Renaissance.''</p>
        <p>The Kimbell bought the sculpture, which depicts St. John the Baptist in his camel-pelt undergarment, a year ago but delayed the announcement while the work was being cleaned by a conservator at the Metropolitan Museum of Art, Jack Soultanian.</p>
        <p>Mr. Soultanian, the conservator responsible for European sculpture at the Met, calls the work ''a masterpiece.''</p>
        <p>''It's heavily cast, and the detailing of the surface is beautifully finished,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Officials at the Kimbell declined to say what the museum paid for the sculpture, but art experts put the price at just under $4 million.</p>
        <p>The sculpture was originally above a baptismal font in the entrance to the church in Florence and is thought to have been removed during renovations in the 18th century. It was later sold, then disappeared. The work surfaced, unidentified, in the collection of Jean-Georges Rueff, a French dealer and decorator, who  owned it for decades before selling it in 1995 to an unidentified Swiss collector through a dealer living in England. At that point an Italian scholar, Giancarlo Gentilini, identified it as a Michelozzo. The same dealer sold it to the Kimbell.</p>
        <p>''I was contacted by a dealer living in London who knew we were looking for great things,'' Mr. Potts said. But he declined to give the dealer's name. Experts would say only that the dealer was Russian-born and lived in Venice before moving to England.</p>
        <p>INSIDE ART</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
