<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CLASSICAL MUSIC AND DANCE GUIDE</title>
    <meta content="15CLAS$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000921T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230595"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000915T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE1D61238F936A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="4440" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CLASSICAL MUSIC AND DANCE GUIDE</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A selective listing by critics of The Times of new or noteworthy opera, classical music and dance events this weekend in the Northeast.</p>
        <p>Opera</p>
        <p>''LUCIA DI LAMMERMOOR.'' Amato Opera's new season begins tomorrow night and, sadly, for the first time in nearly 50 years, the fans of this family-run opera company will not be greeted in the theater lobby by the co-founder, Sally Amato, who died last month at 82. But the company, still run by her husband, Anthony, will open on schedule with a revival of its production of Donizetti's ''Lucia di Lammermoor.'' The soprano Alicia Alexander sings the title role, with Vincent Titone, a tenor, as Edgardo and Justin Ryan, a baritone, as Enrico. Mr. Amato conducts. Amato Opera Theater, 319 Bowery; tomorrow at 7:30 p.m. and Sunday at 2:30 p.m. Tickets are $25 ($20 for seniors and children under 12); information and reservations: (212) 228-8200 (Anthony Tommasini).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A selective listing by critics of The Times of new or noteworthy opera, classical music and dance events this weekend in the Northeast.</p>
        <p>Opera</p>
        <p>''LUCIA DI LAMMERMOOR.'' Amato Opera's new season begins tomorrow night and, sadly, for the first time in nearly 50 years, the fans of this family-run opera company will not be greeted in the theater lobby by the co-founder, Sally Amato, who died last month at 82. But the company, still run by her husband, Anthony, will open on schedule with a revival of its production of Donizetti's ''Lucia di Lammermoor.'' The soprano Alicia Alexander sings the title role, with Vincent Titone, a tenor, as Edgardo and Justin Ryan, a baritone, as Enrico. Mr. Amato conducts. Amato Opera Theater, 319 Bowery; tomorrow at 7:30 p.m. and Sunday at 2:30 p.m. Tickets are $25 ($20 for seniors and children under 12); information and reservations: (212) 228-8200 (Anthony Tommasini).</p>
        <p>''MADAMA BUTTERFLY.'' Puccini's beloved and beautiful potboiler is usually well treated at the New York City Opera. Youth often serves the piece best, and young singers are a specialty at this house. Susan Bullock takes the title role. Andrew Richards is Pinkerton. Jake Gardner sings Sharpless. Jorge Mester conducts Mark Lamos's production.  Tonight at 8. New York State Theater, Lincoln Center, (212) 870-5570. Tickets: $25 to $98 (Bernard Holland).</p>
        <p>''LE NOZZE DI FIGARO.'' This John Copley production has been in the New York City Opera's repertory for about a quarter-century, but it is attractive and compact, and does what a ''Figaro'' production should, which is foster the sense of ensemble and precision comic timing upon which the work depends. The first performance of the season has a cast that, based on past seasons' performances, promises to be fresh and nicely balanced. Sari Gruber is Susanna, Dean Ely is Figaro, Paula Rasmussen is Cherubino, Pamela Armstrong is the Countess and John Hancock is the Count. Steuart Bedford conducts. Tomorrow evening at 8, the New York State Theater, (212) 870-5570. Tickets: $25 to $98 (Allan Kozinn).</p>
        <p>''ROBERTO DEVEREUX.'' Donizetti's rip roarer through English history is a vehicle for its Queen Elizabeth. Lauren Flanigan works assiduously to wrap her considerable talents around the part and with mixed success. The cast is otherwise competent, though not always wisely matched to the roles. But ''Roberto Devereux'' is not that often put on. Mark Lamos's production is worth a listen and a look for bel canto fans. New York City Opera. Tomorrow at 1:30 p.m. New York State Theater, Lincoln Center, (212) 870-5570. Tickets: $25 to $98 (Holland).</p>
        <p>Classical Music</p>
        <p>BARGEMUSIC. There is no better place in New York City to experience chamber music with the proper intimacy than at the concerts presented by Bargemusic, the rewarding weekly series that takes place on an acoustically ideal and commodious barge in the shadow of the Brooklyn Bridge. The program presented tonight and Sunday afternoon offers Stravinsky's ''Soldier's Tale,'' with a fine ensemble of instrumentalists and Toby Appel as narrator. The concert begins with a rhapsodic septet by Andre Jolivet. Tomorrow night three distinguished musicians -- the pianist Gilbert Kalish, the violinist Carmit Zori and the cellist Ronald Thomas -- will play works by Beethoven, Mozart and Mendelssohn. Enjoy the music while taking in a spectacular view of lower Manhattan. Bargemusic, Fulton Ferry Landing, Brooklyn. Stravinsky's ''Soldier's Tale,'' tonight at 7:30 p.m. and Sunday at 4 p.m.; the trio concert, tomorrow at 7:30 p.m. Tickets: $27 regular admission; $25 senior citizens; $15 students. Reservations: (718) 624-4061 or 624-2083 (Tommasini).</p>
        <p>ENGINE 27/ELECTRONIC MUSIC FOUNDATION. As technological innovations increasingly affect the way sound is produced, it is only logical that innovations should affect the places where sound is experienced. Tonight will be the grand opening of Engine 27, a performance space with variable acoustics on Franklin Street in TriBeCa that can be adapted to the needs of the music being performed through the use of surround-sound technology. The mission of the space is to transform the way people experience sound. For the opening, in conjunction with the Electronic Music Foundation, Engine 27 is presenting John Cage's ''Bird Cage,'' a sound installation that uses the aerial acrobatics of bird songs and the loopy recorded voice of Cage himself. This presentation is described as a ''spatialized, new realization'' of the work for a digital age. After tonight's inauguration, the gallery will typically be open from Tuesday through Friday, noon to 5 p.m. Engine 27/Electronic Music Foundation; 173 Franklin Street; an installation of John Cage's ''Bird Cage;'' tonight at 8; admission: $10 (suggested); information: (212) 431-7466 (Tommasini).</p>
        <p>EROICA TRIO. This group of attractive young women -- Adela Pena, violinist; Erika Nickrenz, violist; and Sara Sant'Ambrogio, cellist -- has quickly established itself in the musical scene with a combination of cheesecake publicity and, by all accounts, excellent performances. Both programs here are built around a novelty: Brahms's Opus 18 String Sextet in an arrangement by Theodor Kirchner. Tomorrow, the trio adds works by Lotti and Beethoven; on Sunday, works by Bach, Villa-Lobos and Piazzolla. Tomorrow at 8 p.m., Purchase College Performing Arts Center, 735 Anderson Hill Road, Purchase, N.Y., (914) 251-6200; Sunday at 3 p.m., Bay Street Theater, Sag Harbor, N.Y. (631) 725-9500. Tickets: tomorrow, $31; Sunday, $32 (James R. Oestreich).</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN CHAMBER SINFONIA. Before the big guys of the New York Philharmonic and the visiting Cleveland Orchestra get the new season started in the major halls, here is a chance to catch bright students from the Manhattan School of Music displaying their talents. In fact, one of the works here, Mendelssohn's ''Scottish'' Symphony, affords a lead-in to the Mendelssohn festival Kurt Masur and the Philharmonic are to present in the first three weeks of their season. Appropriately conducted by a Scot, Stewart Robinson, the program also includes ''The Confession of Isobel Gowdie'' by James MacMillan, another Scot, and trumpet concertos by Oscar Bohme and Torelli, with Robert Sullivan as soloist. Tonight at 8, Manhattan School of Music, Broadway at 122nd Street, (212) 749-2802 (ext. 428). Admission: free (Oestreich).</p>
        <p>NATIONAL SYMPHONY ORCHESTRA. Leonard Slatkin and the orchestra get their season off to an adventurous start with a 10-day festival, centering on Beethoven as heard through the ears of others, mostly Mahler. For the second weekend, the program consists simply of Beethoven's Ninth Symphony in one of two Mahler retouchings (from Hamburg, if it matters), with the Cathedral Choral Society. Lest listeners of a Mahlerian cast find the evening too short, preconcert lectures abound: David Pickett, the festival adviser, addresses separate Mahler topics tonight at 7 and tomorrow at 6, and Edward R. Reilly, another authority on the composer, discusses his work as conductor, tomorrow at 5. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8:30, Kennedy Center Concert Hall, Washington, (202) 467-4600. Tickets: $19 to $66 (Oestreich).</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY SYMPHONY ORCHESTRA. Zdenek Macal and the orchestra open their subscription season with a program moving in stages from the urban to the idyllic and from the contemporary to the classic: from Richard Danielpour's ''Toward the Splendid City'' of 1996, which, the composer says, is ''driven by my love-hate relationship with New York City,'' through Respighi's ''Pines of Rome'' to Beethoven's ''Pastoral'' Symphony. Tonight at 8, New Jersey Performing Arts Center, 1 Center Street, Newark; tomorrow night at 8, War Memorial, West Lafayette and Barrack Streets, Trenton, (800) 255-3476. Tickets: $13 to $54; $5 for students; discounts for the elderly (Oestreich).</p>
        <p>SOUTH MOUNTAIN CONCERTS. Is there music in the Berkshire Hills after Tanglewood and other major summer festivals have closed? Yes indeed, in perhaps the oldest festival of them all, now in its 82nd season. Here, the Emerson String Quartet, a group going from strength to strength these days, plays quartets by Haydn (Op. 77, No. 1), Bartok (No. 4) and Beethoven (Op. 59, No. 3). Sunday at 3 p.m., South Mountain Concert Hall, Routes 7 and 20, Pittsfield, Mass., (413) 442-2106. Tickets: $24; sold out, but returns may be available (Oestreich).</p>
        <p>WILD GINGER CHAMBER PLAYERS. This group of musicians from the youthful, energetic and amusingly named Wild Ginger Philharmonic offers two treasures of the chamber repertory: Mendelssohn's Octet and Mozart's Serenade for Winds. Tonight at 8, Christ and St. Stephen's Church, 122 West 69th Street, and tomorrow at 8, Good Shepherd Church, 152 West 66th Street, Manhattan, (888) 444-0353. Tickets are $20, $10 for students and the elderly (Kozinn).</p>
        <p>VECTOR FIVE. This new music program, played by the Fear No Music Ensemble and guests, covers a great deal of stylistic ground, from the rigors of Milton Babbitt to the inventiveness of Kenji Bunch and the conservativism of Stefania de Kenessey. Included are Mr. Babbitt's Composition for Viola, Mr. Bunch's ''Roadtrip'' and Ms. de Kenessey's ''Beating Down,'' as well a ''Trio for Now and Then'' by Yuri Bortz and ''Ballade, Pastorale and Dance'' by Eric Ewazen, who will also perform as a pianist with the ensemble. Tomorrow at 8 p.m., Merkin Concert Hall, 129 West 67th Street, Manhattan, (212) 501-3330. Tickets: $20 (Kozinn).</p>
        <p>Dance</p>
        <p>THE BESSIES. Dance and performance art celebrate themselves, with David Dorfman and Dan Froot, hosts, keeping things hopping as only the lads know how. Tonight at 7. Tickets: $5 (reservations necessary). Joyce Theater, 175 Eighth Avenue, at 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 691-6500, Extension 205 (Jennifer Dunning).</p>
        <p>DANCE SPACE CENTER'S SECOND INTERNATIONAL STUDENT SHOWCASE. Choreography by 16 international center students from 10 countries. Tomorrow at 8 p.m.; Sunday at 7 p.m. Tickets: $12. Evolving Arts Theater at Dance Space Center, 451 Broadway, SoHo, (212) 625-8369 (Dunning).</p>
        <p>DANCE THEATER OF HARLEM. Radiant, nuanced classicists, the Dance Theater of Harlem will be seen in a wide-ranging repertory this weekend. Tonight, tomorrow afternoon and Sunday, for example, the dancers will shift from George Balanchine's ''Four Temperaments'' to the second act of ''Creole Giselle'' to Robert Garland's ''Return,'' set to Aretha Franklin and James Brown. Tomorrow night the program includes Augustus van Heerden's new ''Memento Mori'' and ''South African Suite,'' along with three pieces jointly choreographed by the company director, Arthur Mitchell, Mr. van Heerden and Laveen Naidu, set to music by the Soweto String Quartet. Tonight at 8; tomorrow at 2 and 8 p.m.; Sunday at 3 p.m. Tickets: $35 to $55. City Center, 131 West 55th Street, Manhattan, (212) 581-1212 (Dunning).</p>
        <p>DOWNTOWN ARTS FESTIVAL. The Downtown Arts Festival's Contemporary French Art and Performing Series presents two programs this weekend at the Kitchen. A sample program of Les Spectacles Vivants, put together by Serge Laurent, leading curator and director of live arts at the Pompidou Center, will offer a taste of cutting-edge performance from the center, including dance by Xavier Le Roy and Claudia Triozzi. Tonight and tomorrow at 7:30 p.m. Tickets: $15. Also at the Kitchen are performances by the Compagnie Faim de Siecle. This multi-everything troupe, based in New York and Paris, will present ''Shattered Boxes,'' adapted from Heiner Muller's ''Medeamateria'' trilogy, directed by Ibrahim Quraishi and choreographed by Arthur Aviles. The video component includes an effect that makes audiences seem to disappear, presumably after buying their tickets. Tonight and tomorrow (and Sept. 20 to 23) at 10 p.m. Tickets: $20. The Kitchen, 512 West 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 255-5793 (Dunning).</p>
        <p>FALL PASSAGES 2000. A stellar lineup of choreographers will participate in this benefit for the H.I.V. Arts Network, which provides support to those with AIDS in the performing and fine arts. Among the choreographers and performers are Molissa Fenley, Buglisi/Foreman Dance, Jeffrey Bauer, Arthur Aviles, Keeley Garfield, Richard Daniels and Nicholas Leichter. Tonight at 9; tomorrow and Sunday at 8 p.m. Tickets: $30; $50 includes postperformance reception; $10 for students. Merce Cunningham Studio, 55 Bethune Street, West Village, (212) 385-4945 (Dunning).</p>
        <p>NEW YORK BAROQUE DANCE COMPANY. Rameau's ''Pygmalion,'' conceived as an ''acte de ballet,'' will be performed by the New York Baroque Dance Company with the company director, Catherine Turocy, as the statue whom love makes human. Tomorrow at 2 and 8 p.m.; Sunday at 2 p.m. Tickets: $20 and $30. Florence Gould Hall, 55 East 59th Street, Manhattan, (212) 355-6160 (Dunning).</p>
        <p>JODI OBERFELDER. Six dancers perform heroic feats in acrobatic physical exchanges in ''Slay the Dragon,'' a full-evening piece, set to music by John Zorn, that addresses triumphing against adversity. Tonight (and Thursdays through Saturdays through Oct. 7) at 8 p.m. Tickets: $15 to $20. Flea Theater, 41 White Street, TriBeCa, (212) 226-2407 (Dunning).</p>
        <p>MURRAY SPALDING MOVEMENT ARTS, Unsurprisingly enough, Murray Spalding's ''Mandalas in Movement'' explores geometric patterns through dancers' footwork and positioning in space. The performers have trained in tai chi and hatha yoga as well as traditional dance techniques. Tonight and tomorrow at 8 p.m.; Sunday at 6 p.m. Tickets: $15. University Settlement, 141 Rivington Street, at Eldridge Street, Lower East Side, (212) 501-4751 (Dunning).</p>
        <p>TURANO/FORD DANCE. Nancy Turano, formerly with Ballet Hispanico, is a dancer and choreographer of cool fire. Her full-evening ''Carmen,'' set to music by Bizet and Roland Marconi with costumes by Doris Reyes, promises to be the same. Tonight and tomorrow at 8 p.m. Tickets: $15 to $18. Dicapo Opera Theater, 76th Street and Lexington Avenue, (212) 539-3822 (Dunning).</p>
        <p>REGGIE WILSON'S FIST AND HEEL PERFORMANCE GROUP. Reggie Wilson, a choreographer who marches to his own distinctive though quiet drumbeat, celebrates the new millennium and his own 33rd birthday with ''Wangena -- The birthday concerts.'' Mr. Wilson blends an un-self-conscious postmodernist cool with a lovingly perceptive appropriation of folk materials. His movement vocabulary is varied yet interestingly dry-spirited. Tomorrow (and Sept. 20 to 23 and 27 to 30) at 8 p.m. Tickets: $15 tonight; $20 after tonight. Dance Theater Workshop, 219 West 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 924-0077 (Dunning).</p>
        <p>Correction:  September 21, 2000, Thursday  A picture in Weekend on Friday with the Classical Music and Dance Guide was published in error. It showed Michaela Gurevich in a 1996 production of ''Le Nozze di Figaro,'' not Sari Gruber, who sings Susanna in the New York City Opera's current production.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: September 21, 2000, Thursday</p>
        <p>A picture in Weekend on Friday with the Classical Music and Dance Guide was published in error. It showed Michaela Gurevich in a 1996 production of ''Le Nozze di Figaro,'' not Sari Gruber, who sings Susanna in the New York City Opera's current production.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
