<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Anyone Not a Doctor In the House?</title>
    <meta content="05DOC.$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Health; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/05/living/05DOC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236139"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="AT HOME WITH/THE FISHER FAMILY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fisher Family (Physicians)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Witchel, Alex</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001005T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E7D91E3DF936A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="2199" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Anyone Not a Doctor In the House?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEX WITCHEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Witchel, Alex</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alex Witchel's At Home With column on Fisher family of Manhattan, in which both parents and seven siblings are doctors; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HERE'S a New York story:</p>
        <p>In 1987 I went on a blind date with a budding cardiologist named Eddie Fisher. We had a few beers, some dinner and no chemistry. (He was distinctly unamused when I asked if he could sing.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HERE'S a New York story:</p>
        <p>In 1987 I went on a blind date with a budding cardiologist named Eddie Fisher. We had a few beers, some dinner and no chemistry. (He was distinctly unamused when I asked if he could sing.)</p>
        <p>In February of this year, my husband had what seemed like a scratch on his arm; three days later he was in bed with a raging fever. It took two days for our doctor to call back, staying on the line long enough to suggest a topical cream. By the third day, in a state of hysteria, I called a well-connected friend and asked for help. He called a close friend, a doctor, who referred us to his sister, a specialist in infectious diseases, who saw my husband immediately.</p>
        <p>The close friend was Eddie Fisher.</p>
        <p>A happy ending was had by all: rounds of antibiotics later, my husband was cured, we had a new doctor, and our friend got a kick out of the back story. But when I spoke to Eddie to thank him, and mentioned how interesting it was that both he and his sister had become doctors, he reminded me that he was the eldest of seven children and, in a detail that hadn't existed 13 years ago, said that all seven had become doctors.</p>
        <p>Seven doctors in one family? Well, nine, actually. His father is a doctor, and his mother has a Ph.D. in biophysics (she wanted to be a medical doctor, too, but because she was a girl, her parents said no).</p>
        <p>I found this a fascinating turn of events; most families can't claim two people who can agree what to put on a pizza. So this time, instead of just Eddie, I had a blind date with his whole family: his parents, Hyman and Rosalie; his sisters, Laura, Naomi and Andrea; and his brothers, David, Daniel and Jonathan.</p>
        <p>We met at Eddie's Manhattan apartment on a Sunday evening for a buffet from the Second Avenue Deli, presided over by his wife, Vivian. They have three children, the youngest of whom is 11 months, and Vivian is the kind of girl who runs around in black leggings and actually looks glamorous. Rather than get totally depressed, I focused on my date, which included separate conversations with all nine Dr. Fishers, followed by a group chat.</p>
        <p>The Fisher children range in age from 28 to 42. Though their medical specialties are different, they all either teach or write, as well as practice, and none are surgeons. In these ways they emulate their father, Hyman, 74 and now retired, though still on the faculty of the Mount Sinai School of Medicine. (Each of the children refers to him as a role model.) The Fishers grew up in Livingston, N.J., where their father was the epitome of the small-town doctor who practiced in an office at home and made house calls. Their mother, Rosalie, now 72, decided to have children rather than pursue a medical career after she was married and out of her parents' house. She also taught physics at Brooklyn College, among other places.</p>
        <p>''I was aware of the sexism in my own family, and I was determined not to do the same,'' she said. ''I told my daughters, 'Anything your brothers can do, you can do, too.' It's what I worked hardest at, showing the same attention to the girls' careers and ambitions as I did to the boys'.''</p>
        <p>Neither she nor her husband ever pressured any of the children to become doctors, she said, though attending graduate school, no matter the field, was expected. She worked at keeping the family close-knit; each Fisher seemed more eloquent on the subject of a brother or sister, a son or a daughter, than of him or herself. As Rosalie said: ''Don't let Eddie miss telling you about being an Eagle Scout. It's a highlight.''</p>
        <p>Well, Eddie was just full of secrets, wasn't he? It turns out he made Eagle Scout at 12, while lesser mortals don't until they're 15 or 16. Then again, he is a classic first-born overachiever. Now 42, Edward Fisher is a cardiologist in private practice and teaches at the Mount Sinai School of Medicine. His resume contains five pages of book chapters, reports and other articles he has written alone or with others. But he's (surprise, surprise) modest about it all. ''I was the first, though definitely not the brightest,'' he said. ''Laura was No. 1 in her class of 700 and so was Naomi. To follow them would have really been difficult.''</p>
        <p>Having already met Laura, 41, I knew he did not exaggerate. Beside her own practice in internal medicine, she is an attending physician in infectious diseases and internal medicine at New York Hospital (she is also an expert in Lyme disease) and an assistant professor of clinical medicine at Cornell Medical College.</p>
        <p>Married to Adi Raviv, an Internet entrepreneur, she is the mother of two daughters under 2; her third child is due in December. A woman of great energy, she takes only four weeks of maternity leave, and when she's gone, Eddie covers for her. The two times I saw her in her office she treated her patients with an awesome combination of speed and warmth, all the while completely unaware that the shoulders of her suit jackets bore the remnants of baby spit-up.</p>
        <p>The walls of her office are filled with her own paintings and photographs. ''I once thought I'd be an artist, but I wasn't good enough,'' she said. ''There are so many things I love -- theater, reading, old movies. But family is always first. And with a career in medicine, you can put your family first.''</p>
        <p>I couldn't resist asking: With all the discontent about managed care, how exactly do people get good doctors in New York if they don't have a well-connected friend like ours? ''There's no magic but money, connections and luck, if your company is in a plan with good doctors,'' she said ruefully. ''Unfortunately, that's the sad reality.''</p>
        <p>I saved another hard question for Naomi, 39, who lives outside of Boston and is less hyper than her older sister. ''Laura's very Manhattan,'' she said. Naomi is an endocrinologist and hypertension specialist who is an assistant professor of medicine at the Harvard Medical School. She is also on the staff at Brigham and Women's Hospital. The mother of four children, ages 3 to 10, she is married to Ashley Davidoff, a radiologist.</p>
        <p>Does she think her mom lives vicariously through her daughters?</p>
        <p>''She always told us, 'You can have a big family and a small career or a small family and a big career,' '' Naomi said. ''She sees us doing it and appreciates that you can't have it both ways and be superb at it. She made the family -- and giving us an academic bent -- her priority. I remember her saying we had to be 'second to none.' ''</p>
        <p>''My own kids think everyone's a doctor,'' she went on, amused. ''Mom, Dad, their aunts and uncles. I have to put tradition as a large part of why we all became doctors. My dad was idolized by the community. When he retired, it was like the end of the world.''</p>
        <p>David, 37, was the family jock. He combined his interests in sports and medicine and is now a radiologist and the director of diagnostic imaging at ProHealth Care Associates, a group practice on Long Island that works with the Jets, the Islanders and the U.S. Open.</p>
        <p>''When athletes are injured, they see a radiologist for X-rays, ultrasound, CAT scans or M.R.I.'s,'' he said. ''Twenty years ago we'd have to do arthroscopic surgery. Now we can take a look inside the body without using a knife.''</p>
        <p>Though he does not teach, David edits medical references for Academic American Encyclopedia/Grolier Multimedia Encyclopedia. ''From my mother correcting us, I'm critical of other people's writing,'' he said. He has three children, ages 3 to 6. ''For me, with three, we're only halfway there,'' he said, grinning. ''But my wife, Tammy, is overloaded. We're looking into getting a puppy next.''</p>
        <p>After the first overachieving bunch, the youngest three Fishers seem to take the pressure to succeed more in stride. Andrea, 35, came closest to not becoming a doctor. At the University of Michigan she majored in art history and pre-med. ''It's so hard to become a curator,'' she said, as if becoming a doctor were easy. ''We definitely had to go to graduate school, though we all had the option to do what we wanted as long as we would be successful.'' Following David's lead, she became a radiologist and is now an assistant professor at New York Hospital-Cornell University Medical Center, where she is also on the staff. As befits her visual bent, her specialty is body imaging.</p>
        <p>Andrea is single and said: ''Yes, I want to get married and have kids, but not seven. Even one would be nice.'' The undisputed dish of the family, she showed up to eat deli wearing black silk mules.</p>
        <p>''I'm definitely an underachiever compared to my sisters, who were both valedictorians,'' she said. ''It was hard. At an early age I realized I couldn't do it, too, and I didn't put all the effort in that I could. But as we all get older, I'm learning it's not about keeping up. I just have to be the best person and the best doctor I can be.''</p>
        <p>Daniel, 33, recently became engaged to a lawyer, whom he met through his Hamptons share. He seems to have modeled his career on Eddie's; also a cardiologist, he teaches at New York University Medical Center. He is a staff physician at Tisch Hospital and at Bellevue Hospital Center, where he is the co-director of its cardiology clinic.</p>
        <p>''Eddie was a big influence,'' he said. ''But as the sixth child, I have a different perspective, to include more of my own interests, make more time for play. Eddie's a role model, he's stoic and responsible, but I've learned that I can do that and something else, too. If you want to know what's on MTV, I can tell you.''</p>
        <p>Jonathan, 28, single and dating, is completing his final year of residency in internal medicine at Brigham and Women's Hospital in Boston; he will start a fellowship at Mount Sinai next July, having decided also to specialize in cardiology.</p>
        <p>''A big part of my happiness is being close to my brothers and sisters,'' he said. ''I used to see it as a weakness, needing the family. As the youngest, it's been a struggle to develop my own identity, as you can imagine.''</p>
        <p>He has put his mind to doing just that, teaching himself to juggle and performing magic at children's birthday parties or hospitals. ''I performed at the V.A. Hospital in Boston last Christmas,'' he said. ''One guy told me, 'If you could make my chest pain disappear, I'd have more interest.' ''</p>
        <p>Jonathan is also fluent in Spanish; at Williams, where he studied Latin American civilizations in Spanish, he recalled, ''it wasn't a popular decision with my parents, since I might not have gotten a good grade, and messed up my chances of getting into medical school.''</p>
        <p>The group chat turned out to be a bust; as in most large families, everyone talks at once. Most of them speak to each other almost daily anyway, about everything from patient referrals to child raising.</p>
        <p>''A lot of us have kids the same age,'' David said. ''When my kids are sick, I call Laura. She's the phone pediatrician.''</p>
        <p>''When Laura's pregnant, I do her sonograms,'' Andrea said.</p>
        <p>''We also have a family Web site,'' David said. ''We send pictures, and the nieces and nephews communicate with each other. Andrea does that. She's the Web mistress.''</p>
        <p>She made a big face. ''That sounds terrible,'' she protested.</p>
        <p>They all kissed Naomi goodbye when she left to catch the shuttle; their next get-together is on Thanksgiving: 2 parents, 7 children, 4 spouses, one fiancee and 12 grandchildren (unless the 13th is early). The rest of the group stayed, demolishing an enormous chocolate mousse cake (on top of corned beef and pastrami, for anyone wondering what doctors really eat while telling you to lay off the cholesterol).</p>
        <p>Before long, it was time to leave. As blind dates go, I considered this one a resounding success. Each person was smart and interesting and I would definitely want to see them all again.</p>
        <p>Just with luck, not anytime soon.</p>
        <p>AT HOME WITH/THE FISHER FAMILY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
