<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>School Improvements Are Cited in California</title>
    <meta content="Y05CAL$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/05/national/05CALI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236197"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cheating</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">California</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Whitaker, Barbara</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eastin, Delaine</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cheating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001005T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E3DA1F3DF936A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="570" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>School Improvements Are Cited in California</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA WHITAKER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Whitaker, Barbara</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, Oct. 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>California education officials report two-thirds of public schools showed improvement in program that ties performance on standardized test to financial rewards for schools and educators and are in line for about $660 million in awards; Delaine Eastin, superintendent for public instruction, plays down cheating incidents at few schools; agrees performance index should be based on criteria beyond one test (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the first year of a California program that ties academic performance to financial rewards for public schools and educators, two-thirds of the state's public schools showed improvement on tests that provide the basis of the program, officials announced today.</p>
        <p>Seventy-one percent of the 6,815 schools eligible to participate met their targets, and 67 percent of those are now in line for about $660 million in awards.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the first year of a California program that ties academic performance to financial rewards for public schools and educators, two-thirds of the state's public schools showed improvement on tests that provide the basis of the program, officials announced today.</p>
        <p>Seventy-one percent of the 6,815 schools eligible to participate met their targets, and 67 percent of those are now in line for about $660 million in awards.</p>
        <p>''This shows that if you give people a real target, they'll reach it,'' said Delaine Eastin, state superintendent for public instruction.</p>
        <p>Although officials said the improvements were encouraging, the program resulted in incidents of  cheating at a few schools and concerns about the limited criteria on which the performance index is based.</p>
        <p>Ms. Eastin played down the cheating, noting that irregularities were investigated at 51 schools, with tampering confirmed at 5 of those and a dozen of those still under investigation. But she agreed with critics who said the index should be based on criteria beyond one standardized test.</p>
        <p>''We are at the very first step of a longer journey and, honestly, I would have waited until there was more than one indice in the index,'' Ms. Eastin said. ''But when life gives you lemons, you make lemonade.''</p>
        <p>The Academic Performance Index is the cornerstone of the 1999 Public Schools Accountability Act, which established a statewide system examining schools and gauging their improvement.</p>
        <p>The index is tied to the results of  Stanford 9 achievement tests, pegging them to a scale of 200 to 1,000. A statewide performance target of 800 was established, and every school below that level must improve its performance by 5 percent and show comparable improvement for ethnic and socio-economically disadvantaged groups within the school. Those over 800 must show a one-point gain to be eligible for awards.</p>
        <p>Those who meet the goals are eligible for three types of awards. The Governor's Performance Award offers up to $150 a student to schools that meet their goal. The School Site Employee Performance Bonus divides $350 million, half to schools and half to all school employees who meet improvement targets. A third program provides an additional $100 million to go to certified teachers and administrators.</p>
        <p>Certified teachers and administrators at those schools with the biggest gains will receive the most money, with 1,000 teachers eligible to receive $25,000 each, followed by 3,750 getting $10,000 each and 7,500 others receiving $5,000 until the money is gone. The law says these awards will be decided upon by local district officials in negotiation with the local teachers unions.</p>
        <p>But some education experts voiced concern about the concept.</p>
        <p>Bruce Fuller, a professor of education and public policy at the University of California and co-director of an education policy think tank, noted that in approving the governor's plan, the Legislature had suggested that four criteria be used in the index, including high school graduation rates and school attendance rates.</p>
        <p>''It just makes a lot of educators nervous that cash bonuses of up to $25,000 for an individual teacher are going to flow based upon a single measure that is not even linked to the curriculum,'' Mr. Fuller said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fuller said the broader issue to examine was how schools in poor areas improved compared with those in more affluent areas.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
