<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Oracle's Stock Falls Again, But It Maintains Forecasts</title>
    <meta content="Y05ORA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/05/technology/05ORAC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236191"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TECHNOLOGY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trade Shows and Fairs</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Oracle Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Henley, Jeffrey O</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Richtel, Matt</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trade Shows and Fairs</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001005T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03EEDC1F3DF936A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="690" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Oracle's Stock Falls Again, But It Maintains Forecasts</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATT RICHTEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Richtel, Matt</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO, Oct. 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Oracle Corp's chief financial officer, Jeffrey O Henley, says that analysts gathered at company's OpenWorld trade show in San Francisco were mistaken if they understood his comments on Oct 3 to suggest company is lowering its revenue and earnings projections; drop in Oracle's stock for second consecutive day is linked to Henley's comments (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the Oracle Corporation's stock price dropped for the second consecutive day, company officials scrambled to clarify remarks made earlier in the week by an executive that apparently led to the selloff.</p>
        <p>Oracle's chief financial officer, Jeffrey O. Henley, said today that analysts gathered at the company's OpenWorld trade show here were mistaken if they understood his comments on Tuesday morning to suggest that the company was lowering its revenue and earnings projections.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As the Oracle Corporation's stock price dropped for the second consecutive day, company officials scrambled to clarify remarks made earlier in the week by an executive that apparently led to the selloff.</p>
        <p>Oracle's chief financial officer, Jeffrey O. Henley, said today that analysts gathered at the company's OpenWorld trade show here were mistaken if they understood his comments on Tuesday morning to suggest that the company was lowering its revenue and earnings projections.</p>
        <p>''There is no news and I have not changed my guidance,'' he said in an interview today, declaring that he was ''shocked'' at how some analysts had taken his comments. ''It's a very nervous tech market,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Oracle's shares closed today at $68.13, down $1.38, after falling $9.25 on Tuesday. Over the two days, the company lost $30 billion in market capitalization.</p>
        <p>The stock fell at a time when Oracle was expecting renewed optimism among its customers, given its new flagship database software, called 9i. Lawrence J. Ellison, Oracle's chief executive, introduced the product in a keynote speech on Tuesday, declaring with typical showmanship that it would be inconceivable if every existing customer did not gravitate to it.</p>
        <p>Analysts who follow Oracle's products agreed that the new database software had a lot to offer. Richard Winter, a database industry consultant, said that the software offered significant advances but that an outstanding question was whether the company would be able to deliver on all the features it had promised it would include.</p>
        <p>But Oracle's troubles on Tuesday and Wednesday came from the financial, not the product, side.</p>
        <p>Mr. Henley, meeting with financial analysts at a hotel here, reiterated projections made Sept. 14 in an earnings conference call. He said he was not changing his expectations for revenue growth of 15 to 25 percent in the database business and 50 to 100 percent in the applications business.</p>
        <p>And he said that the company would improve profit margins in line with projections made in the earlier conference call.</p>
        <p>Rick Sherlund, a software analyst with Goldman, Sachs, said Mr. Henley's comments were in line with the guidance given to analysts two weeks ago. He said rumors flowing around the convention that the applications business would not grow as projected were ''totally bizarre.''</p>
        <p>''A lot of us walked away saying, 'Were we all in the same meeting?' '' Mr. Sherlund added.</p>
        <p>He speculated that some analysts might have interpreted Mr. Henley's remarks -- that it might take the applications business two or three quarters to really take off -- to mean that he was ''backing off'' from earlier projections.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sherlund and Chuck Phillips, a managing director at Morgan Stanley Dean Witter, agreed that there was probably a different explanation for the falling stock price. Both noted that technology investors had been feeling skittish and said that they essentially jumped on an excuse to unload Oracle shares.</p>
        <p>Mr. Phillips said the drop in the stock price was related less to the company's fundamentals than to factors like the volatility of the euro, reports of slowing in capital spending and concerns about the near-term future of the business-to-business market.</p>
        <p>''If we had a more positive environment,'' he said, ''this wouldn't be happening. It's environment-  and sentiment-related.''</p>
        <p>On Sept. 14, the company reported first-quarter profit of $501 million, compared with $237 million for the first quarter a year earlier. The per-share earnings of 17 cents beat analysts expectations of 13 cents.</p>
        <p>''We doubled our earnings,''Mr. Henley said today. ''What earnings problem do we have?'' He said he was concerned that Oracle was being unfairly lumped with other, struggling, technology companies at a time Oracle is ''on a tremendous roll.''</p>
        <p>Moreover, Mr. Henley said Oracle did not see any weakness among its customers that would hamper growth. ''Everything in our space is terrific,'' he said.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday, Oracle issued a press release stating that nothing had changed in its outlook. ''Contrary to some erroneous press reports earlier today,'' the statement said, ''the company did not issue a sales or earnings warning during the meeting.''</p>
        <p>TECHNOLOGY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
