<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Carom Sends Bell Hobbling To Bench</title>
    <meta content="MB021849" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236307"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL: METS NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">San Francisco Giants</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kepner, Tyler</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bell, Derek</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/San Francisco Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001005T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E2DE163CF936A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="679" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Carom Sends Bell Hobbling To Bench</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kepner, Tyler</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO, Oct. 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Mets outfielder Derek Bell discusses his injuring ankle during loss to San Francisco Giants in first game of National League division series (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>His right leg was propped up on a folding chair, his ankle was bandaged and Derek Bell's heart, it seemed, was heavy. The Mets' right fielder did not want to talk -- ''I'm in pain right now; I don't want to talk,'' he said -- and he may not do much playing anytime soon.</p>
        <p>Bell sprained his right ankle going after a triple by Barry Bonds in the third inning of today's 5-1 division series loss to the Giants. X-Rays on the ankle were negative, but General Manager Steve Phillips said it was doubtful Bell would play in Game 2 on Thursday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>His right leg was propped up on a folding chair, his ankle was bandaged and Derek Bell's heart, it seemed, was heavy. The Mets' right fielder did not want to talk -- ''I'm in pain right now; I don't want to talk,'' he said -- and he may not do much playing anytime soon.</p>
        <p>Bell sprained his right ankle going after a triple by Barry Bonds in the third inning of today's 5-1 division series loss to the Giants. X-Rays on the ankle were negative, but General Manager Steve Phillips said it was doubtful Bell would play in Game 2 on Thursday.</p>
        <p>''He's probably unlikely for tomorrow,'' Phillips said. ''We'll get a better read in the morning on his status, see what the swelling is, and we'll go from there.''</p>
        <p>Bell appeared to suffer the injury as he tried to change his direction when Bonds's hit caromed toward mid-right field instead of rolling into the corner. He may have slipped on grass that center fielder Jay Payton described as ''kind of slick.''</p>
        <p>Ellis Burks, the Giants' right fielder who followed two batters later with a home run, felt for Bell.</p>
        <p>''A couple of weeks ago I had the same thing happen to me,'' Burks said. ''I slipped and hurt my knee and I was out three or four games due to that. I definitely know how tricky it is, considering how the ball comes of the wall. You definitely have to careful in the right field corner, because it seems a little moist over there, also.''</p>
        <p>With Bell injured and the Giants pitching left-hander Shawn Estes in Game 2, the Mets could turn to right-handed hitting outfielder Bubba Trammell. Another right-handed hitting outfielder, Joe McEwing, was a somewhat surprising addition to Bobby Valentine's postseason roster.</p>
        <p>As expected, the Mets took 10 pitchers, with long reliever Pat Mahomes left off the roster. But infielder/outfielder McEwing, used sparingly down the stretch, was one of the 15 position players to make it. The left-handed pinch-hitter Matt Franco, who played 101 games this season despite spending three weeks in the minors, was not.</p>
        <p>Bobby Valentine's lineup for Game 1 against the San Francisco Giants included another twist: he removed Bell from the No. 2 hole for the first time since May, and batted Payton second because Payton is swinging better.</p>
        <p>''Jay's just been swinging it better,'' Valentine said. ''Maybe we'll get on the board early.''</p>
        <p>McEwing's inclusion was partly because of his ability to ''rise to the occasion,'' said Valentine. McEwing batted .222 but had a few big hits, especially against Arizona Diamondbacks' overpowering left-hander Randy Johnson.</p>
        <p>More important, though, is McEwing's ability to play every position but pitcher. ''Joe adds versatility, both in the outfield and the infield,'' Valentine said. ''We had three left-handed pinch-hitters in Darryl Hamilton, Lenny Harris and Timo Perez, and as good as Matt Franco is -- I can't predict all this stuff. I'm just guessing that we're protected most in this grouping.''</p>
        <p>Teams can change the roster for the League Championship Series and World Series. Mahomes is hoping the Mets do should they win this series.</p>
        <p>''It's kind of hard to swallow, being here all year and when the time comes for the rewards, to be on the side and cheering,'' Mahomes said. ''But from the baseball side of it, if they're going with 10 pitchers, then I understand what they're doing.''</p>
        <p>The Mets' fifth starter, Glendon Rusch, came in from the bullpen today, striking out two to thwart a bases-loaded rally in the eighth.</p>
        <p>The right-handed starter Bobby J. Jones was unavailable today because he had thrown a side session on Tuesday, and Valentine said he was still not announcing his starter for a potential Game 4 on Sunday. Hampton threw only 73 pitches today and conceivably could come back on short rest.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL: METS NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
