<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Camby Is Looking to Stay Healthy (and Put)</title>
    <meta content="05KNIC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/05/sports/05KNIC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236208"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Broussard, Chris</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Camby, Marcus</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001005T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E2D91F3DF936A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="870" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Camby Is Looking to Stay Healthy (and Put)</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRIS BROUSSARD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Broussard, Chris</byline>
      <dateline>PURCHASE, N.Y., Oct. 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Knickerbockers forward Marcus Camby discusses his preparations for upcoming season; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>He will not lead the Knicks in scoring, but Marcus Camby could make a big impact this season. If he is healthy -- as he was during the playoffs in 1999 -- Camby could help catapult the Knicks toward a long postseason run. If he is hobbled by injury -- as he has been for most of the last eight months -- Coach Jeff Van Gundy's perimeter-heavy team could be in for a bottom-rung playoff seeding.</p>
        <p>After two days of training camp, the early signs are unfortunate. The sprained right knee that he injured in February and that transformed him into an also-ran during last spring's playoffs is still bothering him. The injury has forced Camby to sit out certain drills, and when he does join his teammates, he runs with a slight limp.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>He will not lead the Knicks in scoring, but Marcus Camby could make a big impact this season. If he is healthy -- as he was during the playoffs in 1999 -- Camby could help catapult the Knicks toward a long postseason run. If he is hobbled by injury -- as he has been for most of the last eight months -- Coach Jeff Van Gundy's perimeter-heavy team could be in for a bottom-rung playoff seeding.</p>
        <p>After two days of training camp, the early signs are unfortunate. The sprained right knee that he injured in February and that transformed him into an also-ran during last spring's playoffs is still bothering him. The injury has forced Camby to sit out certain drills, and when he does join his teammates, he runs with a slight limp.</p>
        <p>Both the Knicks' doctor, Norman Scott, and the Mets' doctor, David Altchek, told Camby over the summer that although there was no structural damage in the knee, he should expect to feel pain throughout training camp and perhaps even into December. Still, after resting the knee and avoiding even so much as a treadmill until September, Camby expected to enter training camp pain-free.</p>
        <p>Camby insists that the knee will not hinder him once the regular season begins Oct. 31, even if he is still hurting.</p>
        <p>''I don't think it'll be a factor,'' Camby said after running somewhat gingerly through today's practice at SUNY-Purchase. ''I think come opening night I'll be ready to go. It's not that frustrating because I know I can go out there and still do some things. I'm just looking forward to hopefully having a healthy season.''</p>
        <p>If the Knicks are to prosper in the wake of trading Patrick Ewing, they will need Camby -- a tremendous offensive rebounder -- to finally realize the potential that led the Toronto Raptors to make him the second pick of the 1996 draft.</p>
        <p>While his game is not without flaws -- Camby lacks a go-to move, for one -- his greatest impediment is his inability to stay healthy. In four seasons, he has never played more than 63 games, and last season, he missed 23 games because of injury. The question with Camby is not so much is he capable of playing effectively but rather is he capable of staying healthy.</p>
        <p>''To me, it's all about Marcus's health,'' Van Gundy said. ''If Marcus can have a career-best year in games played, I think he'll have a great year. I think it's difficult to develop consistency if you don't play in the majority of the games.''</p>
        <p>Camby's problems with his right knee began in February when he injured his anterior cruciate ligament in a game against the Miami Heat. To determine if the ligament was torn, Dr. Scott operated on Camby but found only a strain.</p>
        <p>Camby returned in March after missing 17 games but reinjured the knee, spraining the medial capsule, with two games remaining in the regular season. He tried to compete in the playoffs but was a shell of himself, unable to dominate around the basket and change the tone of a game. Under doctor's orders, Camby rested for most of the summer, participating in shooting drills and working out in a swimming pool.</p>
        <p>When the news that Camby had been advised not to run got out, the Knicks were angered because it hindered their ability to trade him. Camby further upset the Knicks by asking Altchek for a second opinion.</p>
        <p>The Knicks' anger was matched by Camby's disappointment at the team's willingness to trade him. He is clearly bothered by the fact that the Knicks shopped him throughout the summer and that no one in the organization has yet told him not to worry about being traded.</p>
        <p>Now, though he is hopeful of remaining in New York. Camby seems to have accepted the fact that the Knicks are not entirely committed to keeping him.</p>
        <p>''I'm to the point right now where I have to just go out there and just play,'' he said. ''I can't worry about anything else, just worry about the present not the future. I'd be discouraged if I hadn't gotten traded before and it was my first time going through the experience. But now having been traded once; I pretty much know what to expect and that's the approach I'm taking.''</p>
        <p>While Camby's fears of being traded are well founded, his latest brush with injury all but assures him that he will start the season with the Knicks, if only because no team will be willing to risk trading for what may be damaged goods.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
