<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>All Politics Are Local, but Look at These Stakes</title>
    <meta content="Y05OHI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="32" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/05/politics/05OHIO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236287"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: AN OHIO RACE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Ohio</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">House of Representatives (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clines, Francis X</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'Shaughnessy, Maryellen (Councilwoman)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tiberi, Pat (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kasich, John R (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gephardt, Richard A (Repr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Ohio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Ohio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Ohio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001005T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E4DE163CF936A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1032" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>All Politics Are Local, but Look at These Stakes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANCIS X. CLINES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Clines, Francis X</byline>
      <dateline>COLUMBUS, Ohio, Sept. 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Democratic Councilwoman Maryellen O'Shaughnessy and Republican State Rep Pat Tiberi vie for House set from Columbus, Ohio, being vacated by Republican Rep John R Kasich, key seat in Democratic battle to regain control of House; O'Shaughnessy is being boosted by House Minority Leader Richard A Gephardt and outside pro-Democratic groups; Kasich boosts Tiberi; map; tables; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As she runs for Congress here in Ohio's principal battleground district, City Councilwoman Maryellen O'Shaughnessy takes care to maintain her role in the family funeral home on East Town Street that has been the downtown anchor for generations of Democratic politicking by her kin.</p>
        <p>''I'm on night call,'' Ms. O'Shaughnessy proudly notes of this postscript duty to her 18-hour days of campaigning as ''the working mom working for us,'' in the words of her new television commercial.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As she runs for Congress here in Ohio's principal battleground district, City Councilwoman Maryellen O'Shaughnessy takes care to maintain her role in the family funeral home on East Town Street that has been the downtown anchor for generations of Democratic politicking by her kin.</p>
        <p>''I'm on night call,'' Ms. O'Shaughnessy proudly notes of this postscript duty to her 18-hour days of campaigning as ''the working mom working for us,'' in the words of her new television commercial.</p>
        <p>She lives this theme as a single mother of a 10-year-old boy and the main caretaker of her terminally ill mother. ''I can tell people respond to me because we talk about very personal issues,'' she says of her strategy of personifying the Democrats' showcase issues of health care and education, prescription drugs and Social Security.</p>
        <p>But when it comes to grass-roots authenticity, her Republican opponent, State Representative Pat Tiberi, concedes nothing. ''I was in the Ohio State marching band,'' he casually notes across the university-steeped district in underlining his credentials as the striving son of working-class immigrants.</p>
        <p>Indeed, Mr. Tiberi's college trumpet was at the ready for the Italian street feast the other day at St. John the Baptist Church, where he shook every hand not wielding cannoli.</p>
        <p>''Bring on the debate about working families, because I've lived it,'' he said, describing the help he gave his father with ''the federal bureaucracy'' that he complains Democrats have created around retirement and Medicare benefits.</p>
        <p>''And if you want to talk constituent services, I lived that for eight years,'' Mr. Tiberi added, referring to what he is playing as his ace in the hole: his former district job in serving voter needs on the staff of the congressman he now wants to succeed, Representative John R. Kasich.</p>
        <p>The popular, irrepressible Mr. Kasich is retiring after nine terms, and  national Democrats are seizing on his departure as a golden opportunity in their drive for a net gain of seven seats, which would allow them to retake control of the House.</p>
        <p>This Congressional district, Ohio's 12th, has been visited and singled out as a ''must win'' by Representative Richard A. Gephardt of Missouri, the House minority leader. Outside advertisements and other aid are being funneled in by pro-Democratic groups. Party workers say the Gore campaign is pouring resources into the district, making Columbus second only to Scranton, Pa., in the swing-state investment strategy of the national Democrats.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Kasich's potent voice is still being heard on the hustings. In a television advertisement, the congressman gives blessings to Mr. Tiberi and his immigrant roots. ''It's a wonderful story,'' Mr. Kasich warmly pronounces as the Tiberi forces salivate over the 65 percent share of the vote that the congressman regularly scored at election time.</p>
        <p>To which Ms. O'Shaughnessy, fighting a double-digit deficit in a  Columbus Dispatch poll, resolutely replies, ''I don't believe the voters will allow an anointment.''</p>
        <p>Her trust is rooted in the fact that 55 percent of the district's voters call themselves independents. But many of these traditionally vote Republican, in a state where recent polls show the Bush campaign maintaining a slender lead, perhaps five percentage points.</p>
        <p>Ms. O'Shaughnessy's television advertising campaign is just now beginning, and she concedes that ''I won't be real to the voters until they see me on TV,'' fond though she is of the old door-to-door handshake style of campaigning taught to her by her father, who was a state senator.  ''More and more, voters wait for TV to shape their ideas.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Tiberi is already complaining that a Democratic advertisement  grossly mis-shapes his record, by attacking him on the prescription drug issue as the beholden defender of insurance company political contributors out to deny fair drug prices to the elderly. Ms. O'Shaughnessy insists she had nothing to do with that advertisement, run by the state party. But a rapid-fire Tiberi counterattack ad accuses her of ''waging a negative campaign with special interests calling the shots.''</p>
        <p>Thus, in brutally long days and increasingly aggressive campaigning, the two candidates are having it out, with a level of energy that seems up to the national stakes they are playing for.</p>
        <p>Studded with yard signs, friendly with fish fries and senior socials, the district presents a picturesque mix of urban boom here in Columbus, where Democrats are on the rise, and bucolic bedrock in Delaware and Licking Counties, to the north and east, where the state's Republican tide surges forth. Councilwoman O'Shaughnessy was elected at large in this city, which accounts for 41 percent of the district's population, but Mr. Tiberi is contesting it as his beloved hometown.</p>
        <p>Both candidates admit to a certain exhaustion from the need, even here in a ground-level contest, to be spending four hours or more each day on the telephone begging for donations to feed the TV-commercial maw. By the end of the race, each campaign is expected to have cost a minimum of $1.2 million.</p>
        <p>''Right now I see it as Tiberi's race to lose,'' said Amy Walter, the House editor for The Cook Political Report, a Washington newsletter that tracks campaigns. ''Maryellen's a good candidate, with the money to still make a race of it. But she's running a kind of year-of-the-woman campaign that's a throwback to the early 90's.''</p>
        <p>Ms. O'Shaughnessy is far from apologetic. ''My personal experiences speak to the voters,'' she emphasizes, ''and I'll take their issues forward.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Tiberi hardly dismisses the personal touch, either, in this year-of-the-Kasich-successor campaign. ''I was the first high school graduate in my family, and was eligible for reduced-cost lunch in public school,'' he tells voters. ''My mom's still a seamstress.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: AN OHIO RACE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
