<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Avalanche and Stars Tie in Opener</title>
    <meta content="MB023142" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236376"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PLUS: N.H.L."/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Colorado Avalanche</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Dallas Stars</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001005T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE6DC143CF936A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="379" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Avalanche and Stars Tie in Opener</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jason Diamos</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Dallas Stars and Colorado Avalanche played to a 2-2 tie last night in a penalty-filled season opener matching two of the National Hockey League's best goalies and the teams that played in the last two Western Conference finals.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Dallas Stars and Colorado Avalanche played to a 2-2 tie last night in a penalty-filled season opener matching two of the National Hockey League's best goalies and the teams that played in the last two Western Conference finals.</p>
        <p>Ed Belfour stopped 26 Colorado shots and Patrick Roy, who remains four triumphs shy of breaking the N.H.L. record for career victories, made 19 saves.</p>
        <p>There were 21 penalties, 11 against Dallas. The visiting Avalanche was 1 for 10 on power plays and Dallas was 1 for 9.</p>
        <p>RANGERS SIGN MOTTAU FOR TWO YEARS: The Rangers challenged Mike Mottau to come to camp without a contract and prove he deserved a better offer. Mottau did exactly that, and yesterday the 22-year-old rookie defenseman was rewarded with a two-year deal that included a signing bonus of $575,000.</p>
        <p>''I knew something was going to get done today,'' Mottau said after the Rangers practiced in Rye, N.Y., in preparation for their season opener in Atlanta on Saturday. ''It's a great relief. Now, I can get in and get settled and just concentrate on playing, instead of the negotiation headaches I've had since April.''</p>
        <p>That was when Mottau, who won the Hobey Baker award - college hockey's equivalent of the Heisman Trophy - at Boston College last season, turned down a $650,000 signing bonus. He also opted to play in the world championships instead of for the Rangers' top minor-league affiliate in Hartford during Hartford's American Hockey League playoff run last season.</p>
        <p>After Glen Sather took over as Rangers' president and general manager this summer, the Rangers lowered their bonus offer to Mottau to $550,000. Then, after Mottau excelled in camp following a two-week holdout, the Rangers sweetened the pot.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, Mottau agreed to a contract with a base National Hockey League salary of $425,000 this season and $500,000 next season. It Mottau plays in the Minors, his base salary will be $75,000 this season, $82,500 next season.</p>
        <p>(Jason Diamos)</p>
        <p>PLUS: N.H.L.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
