<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TV Audience for Debate Is Smaller Than Expected</title>
    <meta content="05RATI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/05/politics/05RATI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20001006T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236279"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE RATINGS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nielsen Media Research</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Fox Broadcasting Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Broadcasting Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rutenberg, Jim</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001005T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE6DE163CF936A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="735" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TV Audience for Debate Is Smaller Than Expected</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JIM RUTENBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rutenberg, Jim</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Nielsen Media Research data show 46.6 million people watched presidential debate between Vice Pres Al Gore and Gov George W Bush, far less than 67 million average audience for all debates shown on networks from 1976 to 1992; good-government groups blame decisions of Fox and NBC networks not to show debate live and to offer other programming instead; graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The debate on Tuesday night between Vice President Al Gore and Gov. George W. Bush was watched by at least 46.6 million people, a fairly meager audience for a presidential debate, data from Nielsen Media Research shows.</p>
        <p>That was slightly larger than the audience of 46.1 million people that watched the first debate between President Clinton and Bob Dole in 1996, and considerably larger than the lowest-rated debate ever, the second debate between Mr. Clinton and Mr. Dole. That debate, on Oct. 16, 1996, was seen by an estimated 36.3 million people.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The debate on Tuesday night between Vice President Al Gore and Gov. George W. Bush was watched by at least 46.6 million people, a fairly meager audience for a presidential debate, data from Nielsen Media Research shows.</p>
        <p>That was slightly larger than the audience of 46.1 million people that watched the first debate between President Clinton and Bob Dole in 1996, and considerably larger than the lowest-rated debate ever, the second debate between Mr. Clinton and Mr. Dole. That debate, on Oct. 16, 1996, was seen by an estimated 36.3 million people.</p>
        <p>Still, the audience for the first debate between Mr. Gore and Mr. Bush was far smaller than the average audience for all the debates that were shown on the networks from 1976 to 1992: 67 million.</p>
        <p>The largest audience for a presidential debate on record was for the 1980 confrontation between Ronald Reagan and Walter F. Mondale. Shown on ABC, CBS and NBC, it was watched by more than 80 million people.</p>
        <p>Tuesday's presidential debate was the first to compete with both a network entertainment show and a major sporting event, the American League playoffs. Good-government groups were quick to say that responsibility for the relatively low ratings fell to the decisions of the Fox and NBC networks not to show the debate live and to offer other programming instead.</p>
        <p>Vidya Krishnamurthy, a spokeswoman for the Alliance for Better Campaigns, said that even though the debate on Tuesday fared better in the ratings than the first one between Mr. Clinton and Mr. Dole, it should have done much better considering that it took place in a far closer contest. She attributed the fall-off to NBC and Fox.</p>
        <p>''There was a lot of hype going into this and the polls had them in a dead heat,'' Ms. Krishnamurthy said. ''You would expect it to be higher.''</p>
        <p>On Tuesday, William E. Kennard, the Federal Communications Commission chairman, rebuked NBC and Fox for their decisions on the debates in an Op-Ed article in The New York Times.</p>
        <p>Instead of showing the debate live, Fox showed the first installment of ''Dark Angel,'' a new, one-hour drama about a woman with super-human strength. The move seemed to pay off. According to Nielsen, the program was watched by 17.4 million people, placing it among the top-rated Fox programs.</p>
        <p>Under pressure, Fox did agree to show the debate on tape on the 22 stations it owns after ''Dark Angel.''  Those showings of the debate were estimated to have been watched by about 1.1 million people, though Fox executives questioned that number last night. The Fox News Channel did show the debate, and it was watched by 1.9 million people.</p>
        <p>NBC slightly altered its plans. It had intended to show the first game of the American League Division Series, between the New York Yankees and Oakland Athletics, on all of its 222 affiliated stations. Instead, it gave those stations the option of showing the debate instead of the game or on tape after the game.</p>
        <p>Ultimately, NBC said, the debate was watched in some form or another by 6.2 million people on 78 percent of its stations. WNBC, NBC's New York station, carried the baseball game live, then later broadcast the debate on tape.</p>
        <p>That clearly hurt the ratings for the baseball game, which was watched by an estimated 4.8 million people, which is quite a small audience for a major sporting event carried by a major network.</p>
        <p>The ABC network had the largest audience. Apparently because of the audience for its hit game show ''Who Wants to be a Millionaire,'' more than 19 million people watched the debate on that network. ABC executives said the audience stayed constant througout the 90-minute debate.</p>
        <p>On CBS, 13.9 million people watched the debate, while on CNN, it was seen by 3.2 million people and on MSNBC by about 1 million. Audience figures for PBS and C-Span were not available.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE RATINGS  Correction:  October 6, 2000, Friday  An article yesterday about the number of people who watched the televised debate on Tuesday between Vice President Al Gore and Gov. George W. Bush of Texas referred incorrectly in some copies to Ronald Reagan's opponent in 1980, when the largest audience for a presidential debate was recorded. He was Jimmy Carter; Walter F. Mondale ran for vice president that year, and for president four years later.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: October 6, 2000, Friday</p>
        <p>An article yesterday about the number of people who watched the televised debate on Tuesday between Vice President Al Gore and Gov. George W. Bush of Texas referred incorrectly in some copies to Ronald Reagan's opponent in 1980, when the largest audience for a presidential debate was recorded. He was Jimmy Carter; Walter F. Mondale ran for vice president that year, and for president four years later.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
