<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Day in the Life of the Wired School</title>
    <meta content="05SKOO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Circuits" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Education" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/05/technology/05SKOO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236123"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Suffern (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Morris, Bonnie Rothman</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Circuits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001005T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE2DD1E3DF936A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="2146" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Day in the Life of the Wired School</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BONNIE ROTHMAN MORRIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Morris, Bonnie Rothman</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Viola Elementary School in Suffern, NY, is loaded with computers and illustrates the variety of ways in which schools can use technology; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE noise level in Jen Butler's fifth-grade language arts class in Viola Elementary School in Suffern, N.Y., was more fitting for a gymnasium than a class dedicated to reading and writing. But seven days into the school year, the children  could not contain their excitement.</p>
        <p>In groups of two and three, they poked away at new wireless iBook laptop computers, navigating through three Web sites chosen by their teacher to prepare a report on Gary Paulsen, a popular author of books for young readers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE noise level in Jen Butler's fifth-grade language arts class in Viola Elementary School in Suffern, N.Y., was more fitting for a gymnasium than a class dedicated to reading and writing. But seven days into the school year, the children  could not contain their excitement.</p>
        <p>In groups of two and three, they poked away at new wireless iBook laptop computers, navigating through three Web sites chosen by their teacher to prepare a report on Gary Paulsen, a popular author of books for young readers.</p>
        <p>Down the hall, third graders in Ashley Schuck's class were learning how to scan photos into the computer and waiting to use the three digital cameras that float from class to class in the school. Upstairs, Patty Marina's sixth-grade science class was peering into the world of weather, comparing information culled from a weather satellite receiver on the school's roof with data from weather Web sites on the six computers in the back of the classroom.</p>
        <p>''We're tracking tropical storm Florence, and we just predicted it won't hit land,'' Ms. Marina said. Jacob Morales, 10, pointed to a map on the Weather Channel Web site. ''See,'' he said, ''the storm is going here.'' To emphasize his point, Jacob held up an actual globe, pointed to a spot somewhere off the Florida coast and said, ''It's right here.''</p>
        <p>Viola Elementary, in Rockland County, is just one of thousands of wired schools in the United States, as the Clinton administration nears its goal of connecting all public schools to the Internet by the end of this year.</p>
        <p>But while at least 96 percent of public schools now have Internet access, according to the National Center for Education Statistics, it is often unclear how that access is being used to enhance learning. At some schools, the problem is that there is little else besides an Internet connection -- only out-of-date computers running antiquated software. At other schools, teachers have been reluctant to adopt computers. And some educators and parents question how much computers and the Internet really help children learn.</p>
        <p>But then there are schools like Viola Elementary, which is loaded with computers and seems to love it. Along with construction paper and crayons, computers are front and center at Viola, not buried in a separate lab to be used once a week to learn word processing and graphics programs.</p>
        <p>The Ramapo Central School District has a technology budget of about $1 million a year for 4,200 students. At Viola, which has 544 students in kindergarten through sixth grade, 22 iBooks are lodged on a cart and make their way into various classrooms for use throughout the day. Six PC's sit in neat rows in every classroom. There are 12 computers in the school library, a computer lab with 20 PC's, and a digital video camera that students can use with the Macintosh iMovie program.</p>
        <p>Viola Elementary and schools like it are unusually saturated with technology, but that makes them good places to examine the variety of ways in which computers are used. Students as young as kindergartners may be doing research on the Internet and using e-mail. They learn desktop publishing, use Microsoft Excel to create spreadsheets and use PowerPoint to make slide shows to supplement reports.</p>
        <p>In the best-case scenarios, experts say, computers in elementary school classrooms can create learning experiences that help students see the relevance of their studies. These lessons are meant to encourage children to develop what educational theorists call higher-order thinking. Parents may refer to this as fostering plain old imagination and problem-solving skills. The goal, at least for now, seems to be to keep children excited about learning in school.</p>
        <p>In many schools, the impetus for computer use comes from outside, from what the students and families are learning at home.</p>
        <p>''As early as kindergarten, kids often come to us with computer skills they've learned at home,'' said Roger Woehl, superintendent of the wired West Linn-Wilsonville School District in Clackamas County, Oregon. ''It's a challenge to keep up with the kids. In those early years, students are defining their world, and the environment creates that identity. If technology isn't a part of how they perceive the world, they're going to be at a disadvantage.''</p>
        <p>David T. Gordon, editor of The Harvard Education Letter and its book ''The Digital Classroom,'' published this year, said: ''Kids are growing up with the assumption that technology and all its wondrous forms is part of how we communicate. Introducing computers into the classroom is not just a case of going along with some fad. It's a case of responding, in some way, to what students expect and want.''</p>
        <p>But the integration of computers in the classroom is still slow, often because of technophobia among teachers. Teachers, as a group, have little time to apply themselves to learning how to use computers and often have even less support from the school districts when they seek training.</p>
        <p>Even in districts with a well-conceived technology plan, educators say, the process of adaptation can run off course. Sometimes computer programs are introduced before the students are able to grasp the basic concepts of the lessons. And in many classrooms, computers may still be used to reward students for finishing work early, or to allow students to do drills to prepare them for standardized tests.</p>
        <p>No set of teachers is more primed to use computers as a powerful educational tool than are those at the elementary school level.</p>
        <p>''Elementary school has been historically the best place to introduce computers,'' said Barbara Kurshan, executive vice president and chief education officer at bigchalk.com, which provides educational tools for teachers, parents and students. ''The curriculum allows teachers to have some flexibility about how to present a topic. When you get to high school, computers are used much more as an application device.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Kurshan said elementary school teachers were the most creative people she had ever met. ''They're scavengers who know how to make things come to life,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Diane Waud, a kindergarten teacher at the Brookwood Forest Elementary School in Mountain Brook, Ala., a suburb of Birmingham, taught kindergarten for 5 years before taking a 12-year hiatus to rear her children. She returned to the classroom four years ago. ''I feel like the children are more grown today,'' she said, adding that with the introduction of four computers in her classroom and a small lab down the hall, her teaching had changed along with the children's sophistication level.</p>
        <p>Like many kindergarten classes nationwide, Mrs. Waud's celebrates the 100th day of school. Last year, instead of carrying in, say, 100 lollipops, their assignment was to collect 100 e-mail messages. Within a week, students received messages from 42 states and from people on five continents, including a governor. Ms. Waud used the e-mail for lessons in math, maps and social studies. She will repeat the exercise this year.</p>
        <p>Computer use is well entrenched at Brookwood Forest, part of a district that is well ahead of the technology curve. Those districts that are advanced have the same explanation for their programs' successes: districtwide support, from the schools' superintendents on down. That support includes not only the proper hardware and software but also a well-established policy of teacher training. These efforts require a great deal of money. The Mountain Brook City Schools district started a private foundation five years ago that now has $5 million earmarked for technology training and integration, said Sharon Mumm, technology coordinator at Brookwood Forest.</p>
        <p>The $1 million in the Ramapo Central School District, which includes Viola Elementary, for technology includes salaries for technology coordinators.</p>
        <p>The Mountain Brook school district has a technology academy for teacher training. Ramapo Central's teachers have a contract that includes a clause requiring technology training, said Phyllis Brown, Viola's principal.</p>
        <p>Still, integrating technology into the classroom creates challenges. ''I think you can be a good teacher and teach kids well,'' said Jamie Burton, a sixth-grade science teacher at Brookwood Forest, ''and you can be good at computers, but putting those thing together is a challenge. It takes time to become proficient at being able to do the things you need to do on the computer and do it as well as the kids.'' Last year, using special software from the National Aeronautics and Space Administration, his students tracked the movement of Jupiter by viewing data from NASA's radio telescope in California on their computers in Alabama. The students, who showed up at 10:30 at night to do their work, recorded their findings, graphed them on the computers and shared the information with NASA scientists.</p>
        <p>''I've done computers long enough I don't draw a great distinction between when I'm using it and not,'' said Mr. Burton, who added that computers were simply a tool in the learning process.</p>
        <p>Teachers new to the process face a different challenge. Technology has to be easy to use so lessons are not stalled while teachers try to get balky computers to work. And teachers need to understand how computers enhance learning, said Dr. Robert MacNaughton, superintendent of the Ramapo Central School District.</p>
        <p>And that, it seems, is where even the most advanced and wired schools may be overstepping their technological boundaries. However stimulating computers are, there is a common trap that even the best-thought-out curriculum plan can fall into, and that is using the computer just for the sake of using it.</p>
        <p>Back in Mrs. Butler's fifth-grade language arts class, some students were using pencils to copy the information they found on the Gary Paulsen Web sites into three-ring binders. Most, however, were simply cutting and pasting blocks of text and pictures from the Web directly into documents that would become their reports.</p>
        <p>In those classrooms where computers are as ubiquitous as Magic Markers, computers are sometimes used in much the same way: to put presentations together. The computers can be used to create polished, professional-looking documents and PowerPoint slides. In fact, using PowerPoint is a skill that now appears to be as critical as mastering the cursive capital Q used to be. The reports look less quaint than the old-fashioned pasted variety. But even advocates of computers in the classroom say that this focus on the bells and whistles of technology is diluting what computers can really do.</p>
        <p>''Using PowerPoint has no real thinking or content or rigor involved,'' said Jamie McKenzie, a former school superintendent who is now a consultant and speaker on educational technology issues. ''It's mostly about flash and special effects and sound effects. It's not advancing the cause of student learning.'' Mr. McKenzie said that many schools would necessarily move through stages, starting off enamored of computers' flashiest functions, then eventually realized that ''it's about teaching, not technology.''</p>
        <p>Sometimes it's about both. Last year, Rob Hoisington's second graders at the Boeckman Creek Elementary School in West Wilsonville, Ore., went to Mars. For a unit on the solar system, the students first went to the NASA Web site to study the Mars Sojourner. Working in teams, the children built a model of the Mars environment and a computerized robot replica of the Sojourner.</p>
        <p>The models were then hooked up to a video camera, and the students moved their modules to mimic the scientists' experience of controlling the space module from Earth. The exercise brought the solar system to life for the young students, who took to referring to themselves as ''scientists'' at the family dinner table. Many continued to do research about astronomy on the Web throughout the year, sharing their findings with their teacher.</p>
        <p>''I want to be able to give kids experiences and have them come to their own learning when I can,'' said Mr. Hoisington, who views computers as a way to make learning ''more real and alive'' for his students. ''Kids are more self-directed and more motivated to find what they need on the computer.''</p>
        <p>But even technologically literate teachers recognize the value of powering down the computers.</p>
        <p>At Brookwood Forest, Ms. Waud reported that her kindergarteners spent as much time singing, dancing and putting on plays as they did on their computer activities. ''I don't want the computer to replace what I do,'' she said. ''Human contact is the most important thing, but it's the world where they are today.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
