<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Moving Heaven With Earth</title>
    <meta content="05KILE$30" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/05/living/05KILE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236124"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HUMAN NATURE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Landscaping</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">American Society of Landscape Architects</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Raver, Anne</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kiley, Dan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Manning, Warren</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olmsted, Frederick Law (1822-1903)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Saarinen, Eero (1910-61)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Landscaping</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001005T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E7DC1E3DF936A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="2051" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Moving Heaven With Earth</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNE RAVER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Raver, Anne</byline>
      <dateline>CHARLOTTE, Vt.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dan Kiley, 88-year-old master landscape architect in Charlotte, Vt, is link to history, having apprenticed with Warren Manning, who founded American Society of Landscape Architects with Frederick Law Olmsted, and collaborated with Eero Saarinen; for more than 60 years his work has revealed almost mystical sense of land; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DAN KILEY trudged slowly up the hill and across the green meadow. ''We just cut the hay,'' he said. ''It was this high.'' His hand floated just above his hip. ''Of course, it's a lot of work. Next year, I'm going to mow a path close to the woods, and just let the rest go.''</p>
        <p>The master landscape architect, at 88, is a link to history, from his apprenticeship to the great horticulturist Warren Manning, who founded the American Society of Landscape Architects with Frederick Law Olmsted, to his collaborations with Eero Saarinen. For more than 60 years, his work has revealed an almost mystical sense of the land, and here, in the country, he knows what to leave alone.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DAN KILEY trudged slowly up the hill and across the green meadow. ''We just cut the hay,'' he said. ''It was this high.'' His hand floated just above his hip. ''Of course, it's a lot of work. Next year, I'm going to mow a path close to the woods, and just let the rest go.''</p>
        <p>The master landscape architect, at 88, is a link to history, from his apprenticeship to the great horticulturist Warren Manning, who founded the American Society of Landscape Architects with Frederick Law Olmsted, to his collaborations with Eero Saarinen. For more than 60 years, his work has revealed an almost mystical sense of the land, and here, in the country, he knows what to leave alone.</p>
        <p>''How could I do better than that?'' he asked, staring across the meadow to the Green Mountains, and headed up for lunch at Camp David.</p>
        <p>That's the name Anne, his wife of 58 years and mother of their eight children, gave to the little house they built on the brow of the hill that overlooks their 400-acre farm in this village just south of Burlington, Vt. ''We wanted to get away from each other,'' he said.</p>
        <p>They used to live in an old farmhouse on the property, where Mr. Kiley was continually knocking out walls, until he built a new office and house even deeper into the woods in 1975.</p>
        <p>Then Mrs. Kiley, who has a great need to read and write, and smoke her one Camel cigarette for the day in solitude, started building little houses of her own, carrying the materials right across the stream.</p>
        <p>''Emerald City was beautiful,'' Mr. Kiley recalled. ''But it collapsed a while ago.''</p>
        <p>Their son Gus, an editor in Cambridge, Mass., compares his clan to ''slash-and-burn agriculturists just moving to the next available spot.'' He added, ''When you came home from school in the afternoon, you literally didn't know where the dining room table would be.''</p>
        <p>Still, he loved their free-spirited life. Building rafts and boats to float on Lake Champlain, cutting down pine trees for a tepee village. ''Mother would come out there all day long, playing her violin,'' Gus said. And they didn't bother with clothes. ''Everybody in the village thought we were a nudist colony,'' he added.</p>
        <p>The rambling nature of both office and home, with narrow boardwalks snaking through the forest (to keep from trampling the plants) and towers rising into the trees, is in striking contrast to the elegance of the designer's most famous public works, which marshal allees of trees, grids of stone and grass and long rills of water to extend the planes of modern buildings. They work together beautifully at Lincoln Center and Rockefeller University in Manhattan; the Nationsbank Plaza in Tampa, Fla.; the Air Garden (which has been demolished) at the United States Air Force Academy, where flat pools and walkways rushed to meet the vastness of the Rocky Mountains.</p>
        <p>These classical elements are used with a modernist's sensibility, like the honey-locust allee at the Miller garden, set parallel, not perpendicular, to the house Eero Saarinen designed for J. Irwin and Xenia Miller on the edge of Columbus, Ind. The effect is to frame the rolling flood plain and trees beyond -- though Mr. Kiley, a problem solver at heart, says he was just shading the house.</p>
        <p>Here at home, his proportions and rhythms -- like the sugar maples spaced along the long, curving unpaved drive -- feel perfectly right. Mr. Kiley's works are about moving through space, expanding toward the infinite.</p>
        <p>''To build is to imagine fresh possibilities,'' he told an audience gathered at Rockefeller University this spring. ''Like a butterfly emerging from the chrysalis. I'm always searching for the purest connection that holds us all together. Some form of sacred geometry. Sometimes the prevailing order is unseen, unknown.''</p>
        <p>Building, then, is a way of staying alive. Mr. Kiley pauses halfway across the soft meadow to rest for a minute. ''Just a year ago, I was skiing,'' he recalled. ''Now I don't have any energy. It's really frustrating.''</p>
        <p>Recovering from a minor stroke last year, he still finds the point he was making, or the name of a bird, dissolve into the clear Vermont air. ''I can't think very well,'' he said with a sense of profound surprise. ''I think we didn't realize we were old until this year.''</p>
        <p>Over lunch -- tender chicken and mushrooms -- the Kileys told how they met in their mid-20's, when Dan  came up from Boston to ski in the White Mountains of New Hampshire.</p>
        <p>''Oh, my God, that was extraordinary,'' said Mrs. Kiley, now 87, who taught skiing in Franconia, N.H., and ran a little inn with her sister. ''He stopped at one of the lodges, but they charged 75 cents a room, and he said that was too much. So they told him, 'There are a couple of girls who will take you for cheaper.' All that Irish pomp! His Irish setter jumped out and scared all the cats.''</p>
        <p>But she was so genteel, Mr. Kiley murmured, ''I agreed to pay 75 cents.''</p>
        <p>And what did she think of him? ''Not bad,'' she said.</p>
        <p>She had eight children in nine years, raising them alone much of the time because Dan was often traveling. ''Better to ask how they raised me,'' she said. ''The first three were not brought up very well. Then I got the hang of it.''</p>
        <p>Husbands are a different matter. ''I wasn't good at being a wife,'' she added. ''I never practiced on more than one.'' She has decided that ''Dan and I aren't married anymore.'' She continued, ''I discovered Dan Kiley was married to Dan Kiley.''</p>
        <p>Dan Kiley looked at his visitor and impishly stuck out his tongue. They both have the same snow-white hair.</p>
        <p>Later she lets him take her hand, as trusting as a schoolgirl. ''Since Dan and I lead very independent and individual lives, I think that our best times together have been lived in moments,'' she wrote in a note to this reporter. ''Just as the other evening we sat on the terrace gazing out over the flowers to the mountains. Bathed in the lovely light we seemed to float free of ourselves, and then it seemed we were like two leaves that drifted and touched together, a moment of homecoming which can in that instant make up for any separation.''</p>
        <p>Camp David is a friendly labyrinth of rooms opening out on other rooms, with windows on all sides and a hodgepodge of chairs set to take in the light, or the view. Books are scattered everywhere, like the Tao Te Ching, left on a table by a black canvas 1960's butterfly chair turned to face a patch of electric-red bee balm blooming in a pool of sunshine.</p>
        <p>There are dusty pictures of Mrs. Kiley's ancestors, merchants who helped found the city of Fairfield, Conn.; a painting of clipper ships in the Boston Harbor; a Queen Anne chair (worth $18,000, Mr. Kiley mentions), which no one appears to sit in; old plans and models, like the proposal he made for Columbus Circle in a 1998 competition. And pictures of the children, of course.</p>
        <p>''That's Gracie,'' Mrs. Kiley said, popping from the kitchen as we peered at a pretty young woman in a white dress, on the arm of her father, who is dressed in a tuxedo. ''Dan always said he'd see the children through two marriages, but this is the third, and it's the best yet.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kiley grew up in the Roxbury section of Boston, in a cityscape of once-elegant homes and three-deckers with porches and alleyways. His father was a construction manager who taught him how to box, to move in a graceful dancing way that he translated to skiing and golf and the fluid, dynamic qualities of his best designs.</p>
        <p>He roamed Olmsted's Emerald Necklace of parks along the Charles River, caddied on golf courses, where he grew to love sculptured green hills, and walked to school across the Arnold Arboretum, where he learned the names and dignity of trees. But it was in New Hampshire, visiting his grandmother, that he was struck by the architectural beauty of ''a thousand sugar maple trunks on a leaf-strewn slope,'' he said, ''or a snowy field with just two ski tracks.''</p>
        <p>Graduating from high school in 1930, at the height of the Depression, he apprenticed himself to Warren Manning, the famed plantsman who had worked with the Olmsted brothers on such projects as Biltmore, the Vanderbilt estate in North Carolina, and knew how to match the needs and habits of a plant to the site.</p>
        <p>''He gave me two pieces of advice,'' Mr. Kiley said. ''Not to join the society and not to go to Harvard.'' He never joined the society, but he did matriculate as a part-time student in Harvard University's department of landscape architecture. ''I would run in the day before the deadline and paint from my head,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Along with two other students, James Rose and Garrett Eckbo, who were bored with ''the dry symmetries of the Beaux-Arts,'' he wrote a series of articles for Architectural Record that called for a new kind of landscape architecture, a functional one that answered the needs of people in cities and suburbs, and looked to nature for clues to harmonious and workable design.</p>
        <p>When Manning died in 1938, Mr. Kiley left Harvard without a degree and made his way to Washington, where he worked with Louis Kahn on housing projects, and then enlisted in the Army, where he worked for Saarinen in the Office of Strategic Services. After the war, Saarinen got him the job designing the courtroom for the Nuremberg trails.</p>
        <p>That's when he first set eyes on the real gardens that had looked so dull in slide talks at Harvard.</p>
        <p>''I loved Versailles and Sceaux and Vaux-le-Vicomte,'' he said. ''I loved all of Le Notre's work,'' he added, referring to the 17th-century landscape builder Andre Le Notre, whose bosques and allees would work their way into the young designer's vision.</p>
        <p>Conversely, he has always scorned Olmsted's pastoral parks as ''fake'' nature.</p>
        <p>''Man is nature,'' he is fond of saying. ''When we shape the land, we are nature, too. But, he adds, ''we must be attuned to the systems of nature.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kiley has been maddeningly loath to analyze his own work. At a symposium two years ago at Harvard, where scholars traced his modernist design for the Miller house back to early drawings for Hollin Hills, a 1950's veterans' suburban housing community, Mr. Kiley was invited to the podium to illuminate the debate.</p>
        <p>He faced the audience in a sky-blue silk tie and began to slalom down an imaginary ski slope. ''Life is design,'' he said. ''It's like skiing down a mountain.''</p>
        <p>The Miller house has become an icon. Scholars hail its honey-locust allee as the beginning of modern landscape architecture. But Mr. Kiley is bored by all this theorizing. ''I planted those trees to shade the west side of the house,'' he said. ''There needed to be an allee there, so why avoid it?''</p>
        <p>Design is part of nature here in Vermont. ''We don't have any rules at our office,'' he said. ''The only rule is to be open-minded.''</p>
        <p>HUMAN NATURE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
