<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Just as They Did in '99, Mets Send a Signal</title>
    <meta content="05CHAS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/05/sports/05CHAS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236265"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">San Francisco Giants</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chass, Murray</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/San Francisco Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001005T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE3DF163CF936A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1054" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Just as They Did in '99, Mets Send a Signal</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Murray Chass</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chass, Murray</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses New York Mets loss to San Francisco Giants in first game of National League division series; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A year ago  a year ago today, to be precise -- Edgardo Alfonzo slugged a two-out grand slam in the ninth inning of a tied postseason opener, catapulting the Mets to a stunning 8-4 victory in the Arizona Diamondbacks' ballpark and igniting a scintillating playoff run that would be derailed two victories short of the World Series.</p>
        <p>The Mets served notice yesterday that their playoff run this year might not be so scintillating. Alfonzo gave it another shot, but this one fell far short of catapulting the Mets anywhere. They lost to the San Francisco Giants, 5-1, as Mike Hampton and Mike Piazza continued their personal postseason problems.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A year ago  a year ago today, to be precise -- Edgardo Alfonzo slugged a two-out grand slam in the ninth inning of a tied postseason opener, catapulting the Mets to a stunning 8-4 victory in the Arizona Diamondbacks' ballpark and igniting a scintillating playoff run that would be derailed two victories short of the World Series.</p>
        <p>The Mets served notice yesterday that their playoff run this year might not be so scintillating. Alfonzo gave it another shot, but this one fell far short of catapulting the Mets anywhere. They lost to the San Francisco Giants, 5-1, as Mike Hampton and Mike Piazza continued their personal postseason problems.</p>
        <p>The Giants are not the nouveau riche Diamondbacks. They play in a new park, but they are one of three playoff teams in the bottom half of the payroll standings. The Mets pay their players more than 50 percent more than the Giants pay theirs. But the Giants compiled the major leagues' best record, and they played yesterday like a team befitting that status.</p>
        <p>The Mets played like a team that doesn't have the right ingredients to advance beyond their consolation (wild-card) status. They scored a third-inning run on a sacrifice fly, and one of their few other scoring opportunities was a momentary gift. That instance was the one involving Alfonzo.</p>
        <p>With two out and runners at first and second in the fifth inning, Alfonzo came to bat. This year he did not hit a home run; rather, he lofted a routine fly to center field. Instead of easily catching the ball for the third out, Marvin Benard nearly played it into a critical Mets hit. Misjudging its trajectory, Benard charged in for the ball, then realized that he had come in too far. It seemed for a second as if the ball might land behind him and produce at least one Mets run, if not two, in what was then a 5-1 game.</p>
        <p>Benard recovered in time. He stopped on the proverbial dime (though his catch could be worth much more to the Giants), retreated several steps and snared the ball for the third out. Had the ball fallen safely, Alfonzo would still not have been the Mets hero he was a year ago; misjudged fly balls, no matter how productive they are, don't equal two-out, ninth-inning grand slams.</p>
        <p>But Alfonzo's fly ball could have put the Mets back in the game. That's not something Piazza could do, and his batterymate, Hampton, had already taken them out of it.</p>
        <p>Piazza was not instrumental in any of the Mets' five postseason victories last year. He tied Game 6 against Atlanta in the league series with a two-run home run in the seventh inning, but it didn't lead to a series-tying victory. He hit harmless pop fouls in his final two at-bats as the Braves won, 10-9, in 11 innings.</p>
        <p>In his first three times at bat yesterday, he led off each time and hit three more pop-ups, though fair, giving him a Mets postseason record of 6 hits in 36 at-bats for a .167 average. Add in two brief postseason visits with the Los Angeles Dodgers, and he is hitting .200.</p>
        <p>''All you can do is keep going out there doing the best you can,'' said Piazza, not one to bare his soul in discussing his shortcomings. ''That's the bottom line. You can't go out and put more pressure on yourself. You have to have confidence in yourself. You can't go out there and try to make things happen. You have to be patient.''</p>
        <p>The Mets certainly have to be more robust than they were against Livan Hernandez, collecting only five hits. Their effort was frighteningly reminiscent of the period last month when they scored few runs and lost many games.</p>
        <p>''It's frustrating, obviously,'' Piazza said of the team's offensive shutdown. ''We've had some tough games this month and today was no different. We weren't trying to get it back with one swing, but we couldn't get the flow going, moving runners over and getting them in. You have to manufacture runs as well as getting the big hits. I just felt like we were in neutral today.''</p>
        <p>Hampton's start was his fourth in four successive division series. The first three were with the Houston Astros, and he didn't win with them, either. Neither did they with him. In his four starts Hampton, a left-hander, has a 0-2 record and a 5.87 earned run average.</p>
        <p>''It's not frustrating,'' Hampton said, responding to a question. ''I go out and do the best I can regardless. I'm not ashamed of anything. I pitch as hard as I can. I pitch my guts out and leave everything on the field.''</p>
        <p>Manager Bobby Valentine chose Hampton to start Game 1 over Al Leiter, and now Leiter will try to pitch the Mets even before the three-of-five series goes to New York. He will be in a different position from the one he was in last year when he made his first start of that post-season. Last year the Mets were ahead two games to one when he pitched against Arizona.</p>
        <p>''In the case of being up 2-1,'' Leiter said, ''I was excited thinking I was going to be the one on the mound when we clinched. It took a couple innings more for us to clinch.''</p>
        <p>Now that the Mets are behind 1-0, he added, he doesn't intend to change his thinking or his approach.</p>
        <p>''I continue to think I have to be aggressive, make good pitches,'' he said, ''and not think of where I'm playing, the fans, the media, the fact we're down 1-0. All of those things will not make me release my slider out in front with the right amount of pressure and bury a slider in on Jeff Kent.''</p>
        <p>ON BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
