<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. DETECTS BIAS IN POLICE SEARCHES</title>
    <meta content="05POLI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/05/nyregion/05POLI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236281"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hispanic-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police Brutality and Misconduct</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Firearms</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weiser, Benjamin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Firearms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hispanic-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police Brutality and Misconduct</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001005T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E5DE163CF936A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1365" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. DETECTS BIAS IN POLICE SEARCHES</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BENJAMIN WEISER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Weiser, Benjamin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Federal probe of New York City Police Department's Street Crime Unit has found officers engaged in recial profiling, disproportionately searching blacks and Hispanics in aggressive drive to stop people suspected of crimes or carrying guns; Federal prosecutors are now in talks with Mayor Rudolph W Giuliani's administration in bid to negotiate set of changes that could avoid civil rights suit (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A federal investigation of the New York Police Department's Street Crime Unit has determined that its officers engaged in racial profiling in recent years as they conducted their aggressive campaign of street searches across the city, officials said.</p>
        <p>Federal prosecutors in Manhattan, who began their investigation in the weeks after the 1999 shooting death of Amadou Diallo, are now in talks with the Giuliani administration to discuss their findings and perhaps to negotiate a set of changes that would avert a lawsuit, the officials said.</p>
        <p>If the talks fail, prosecutors could seek authorization from the Justice Department to go to court under civil rights law and ask a judge to order broad changes in the operations of the Street Crime Unit and possible oversight by a federal monitor.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A federal investigation of the New York Police Department's Street Crime Unit has determined that its officers engaged in racial profiling in recent years as they conducted their aggressive campaign of street searches across the city, officials said.</p>
        <p>Federal prosecutors in Manhattan, who began their investigation in the weeks after the 1999 shooting death of Amadou Diallo, are now in talks with the Giuliani administration to discuss their findings and perhaps to negotiate a set of changes that would avert a lawsuit, the officials said.</p>
        <p>If the talks fail, prosecutors could seek authorization from the Justice Department to go to court under civil rights law and ask a judge to order broad changes in the operations of the Street Crime Unit and possible oversight by a federal monitor.</p>
        <p>Prosecutors have based their findings on a statistical analysis of the Street Crime Unit's searches of people its officers had stopped because they were suspected of committing crimes or carrying guns, one official said. Prosecutors told the city that their analysis concluded that blacks and Hispanics in the city were disproportionately singled out in the searches, and that the imbalance could not be explained by the fact that the city's minority neighborhoods typically had higher crime rates, the official said.</p>
        <p>Mary Jo White, the United States attorney for the Southern District of New York, whose office has conducted the inquiry, would not comment other than to say that her office's investigation was continuing. Officials with the city corporation counsel's office also would not comment.</p>
        <p>Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani and police and city officials have in the past adamantly rejected allegations that any officers engaged in racial profiling. They did so, for example, when the New York State attorney general, Eliot L. Spitzer, issued a report late last year saying that the department's street search tactics unfairly singled out the city's black and Hispanic residents.</p>
        <p>The Street Crime Unit -- squads of elite undercover officers that were sent into high-crime sections of the city -- was seen by the department as one of its great successes, the unit's ability to get guns off the street having played a large role in the broader reductions in violent crime.</p>
        <p>But the performance and conduct of the unit came under intense scrutiny after Mr. Diallo, an unarmed African immigrant, was shot to death on a Bronx street by four members of the unit. Although the four officers were ultimately acquitted of any crime, the Police Department did significantly reorganize the Street Crime Unit, and ordered many of its officers into uniform.</p>
        <p>Justice Department officials in Washington have yet to announce whether they will seek criminal civil rights charges against the four officers who shot Mr. Diallo.</p>
        <p>The federal investigation into the Street Crime Unit is not the only inquiry into problems within the department. Since 1997, after Abner Louima was tortured in a Brooklyn station house, federal prosecutors for the Eastern District of New York have been investigating patterns of brutality within the department and deficiencies in disciplining problem officers. Negotiations between the prosecutors and the city aimed at avoiding a formal lawsuit have dragged on for months.</p>
        <p>The full scope of Ms. White's investigation and its findings could not be learned. When prosecutors first announced the inquiry, in March 1999,  they said the investigation would focus on whether officers with the Street Crime Unit systematically deprived people of their rights through their ''stop and frisk'' tactics and other practices.</p>
        <p>But it is for the moment unclear what reforms Ms. White is seeking and whether they would address only the Street Crime Unit or more generally deal with the training and policies of officers throughout the department who conduct stop-and-frisk operations.</p>
        <p>The Justice Department has addressed concerns of racial profiling in other cities. In one recent example, Los Angeles city officials negotiated a series of reforms with the Justice Department to address allegations of systemic abuse by the police. That tentative settlement includes a requirement that the Los Angeles Police Department, in an effort to assess the extent of racial profiling, collect data on the race of people who are stopped by officers.</p>
        <p>In another case, the New Jersey State Police entered into a consent decree with the Justice Department barring police officers from using race as a basis for making traffic stops. That settlement also requires troopers to document the race, sex and ethnicity of all drivers who are stopped, and provides oversight with a computer tracking system and a federal monitor.</p>
        <p>Ms. White's findings came after her office obtained thousands of forms documenting stop-and-frisk searches conducted by New York City police officers over the last several years. The forms, known as UF-250's, are supposed to be filled out by officers when they stop and frisk someone on the street, and are often used as an investigative tool.</p>
        <p>The city spent about $1.5 million over many months to enter about 320,000 UF-250 reports into a computerized database, and then turned over the database to prosecutors for analysis. Searches conducted by the Street Crime Unit accounted for roughly 10 percent of the total reports.</p>
        <p>Although it is not known what the city's response has been to the findings of prosecutors, Mayor Giuliani and other city officials have repeatedly dismissed previous allegations of racial profiling against the department.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Spitzer, the state attorney general, asserted last year that his study of stop-and-frisk incidents had indicated a bias against the city's minority citizens, the mayor and police officials attacked the findings and the methodology behind them as flawed. They said Mr. Spitzer's report failed to adequately take into account the fact that a disproportionate number of the city's violent crimes took place in minority neighborhoods.</p>
        <p>And when a group of blacks and Hispanics filed a class-action lawsuit last year, asking a federal judge in Manhattan to halt the operations of the Street Crime Unit because, the suit said, the unit was illegally stopping and frisking people because of their race, the city's corporation counsel, Michael D. Hess, said: ''The plaintiffs are asking the court to stop a practice that does not exist. Therefore, there is nothing to stop.''</p>
        <p>Mayor Giuliani has also asserted that the Clinton Justice Department has been responding to political pressure in its investigations, most recently after the Rev. Al Sharpton met with Attorney General Janet Reno in August, urging her to to seek federal oversight of the Police Department.</p>
        <p>It is possible, too, that city officials could argue that steps have already been taken to improve the fairness of street searches. The Police Department last summer began a pilot program in different commands across the city that required officers to fill out much more detailed reports on their searches, a step that department officials said would make it easier for officers to explain and justify their actions.</p>
        <p>Moreover, the Street Crime Unit today is structured very differently from the way it was when Mr. Diallo was killed. Instead of an autonomous unit that operated across the city under its own chain of command, the Street Crime Unit has been divided into eight separate teams that report to the police chiefs responsible for the eight patrol sectors in which the city is divided.</p>
        <p>Police officials who announced the change last year described it as a redeployment. Officers, however, flew a white flag of surrender that day outside their headquarters in the Bronx.</p>
        <p>Officers still stop and frisk people they suspect of carrying guns, and focus much of their attention on violent criminals, but the mission has broadened.</p>
        <p>Many of the officers are assigned to prevent crimes against livery-cab drivers by patrolling in unmarked cars and stopping cabs when they suspect a driver might be in trouble. Others are put in a variety of settings in which the police need to expand their plainclothes presence, like in the stands at Shea Stadium when John Rocker of the Atlanta Braves takes the mound.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
