<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Braves, Still Confident, Are Relying on Glavine</title>
    <meta content="05CARD$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/05/sports/05CARD.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236187"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Atlanta Braves</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">St Louis Cardinals</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brown, Clifton</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Atlanta Braves</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/St Louis Cardinals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001005T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E4DC1F3DF936A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="829" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Braves, Still Confident, Are Relying on Glavine</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFTON BROWN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brown, Clifton</byline>
      <dateline>ST. LOUIS, Oct. 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Atlanta Braves discuss losing first game of National League division series against St Louis Cardinals and their preparations for second game (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>October is a bad time to play bad baseball, and the Atlanta Braves have paid the price.</p>
        <p>First the Braves blew home-field advantage for the opening round of the playoffs with a sloppy loss Sunday in their regular-season finale. Then the Braves opened the playoffs Tuesday by making two first-inning errors and misplaying a fly ball, fueling a six-run outburst by the St. Louis Cardinals that carried them to a 7-5 victory.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>October is a bad time to play bad baseball, and the Atlanta Braves have paid the price.</p>
        <p>First the Braves blew home-field advantage for the opening round of the playoffs with a sloppy loss Sunday in their regular-season finale. Then the Braves opened the playoffs Tuesday by making two first-inning errors and misplaying a fly ball, fueling a six-run outburst by the St. Louis Cardinals that carried them to a 7-5 victory.</p>
        <p>With Atlanta trailing, 1-0, in the three-of-five-game division series, the Braves have put themselves in a pressure-packed situation for Thursday afternoon's Game 2 at Busch Stadium. A victory would pull the Braves even in the series, with Game 3 and Game 4 at Turner Field, where the Braves were 51-30 this year. But if the Braves lose Game 2, the defending National League champions will be one defeat away from an embarrassing early exit.</p>
        <p>While a lesser team might be reeling, the Braves still had their bravado following the Game 1 defeat, and for good reason. With the 20-game winner Tom Glavine on the mound for Game 2, and nine consecutive years of postseason experience on their side, the Braves figured the momentum could turn quickly in their favor.</p>
        <p>''We're still confident,'' said Chipper Jones, who has made costly fielding errors in each of Atlanta's last two losses. ''The only reason we're down is because of the mistakes we've made. The last few games have been very uncharacteristic for us, but we expect to play better.''</p>
        <p>They will have to play better to beat the Cardinals, who won the season series from Atlanta, 4-3, and who believe they are not getting enough respect.</p>
        <p>''Everyone is writing us off as just a bump in their road,'' said Jim Edmonds, the Cardinals' center fielder, who has been outstanding after being traded by the Anaheim Angels during the off-season. ''This team has been great. To go from an underachieving team in Anaheim to a team that does everything right is fun. We don't have the problems as in Anaheim, the jealousy, bickering. This team is a team. They play hard. We've made a lot of things go our way. That's why we are where we are.''</p>
        <p>Edmonds was a star in Game 1, going 3 for 5 with a home run, but he injured his tailbone after falling hard on his back in the outfield. But Edmonds was at the Cardinals' workout today, and he plans to play in Game 2.</p>
        <p>''I'm still sore, but I've played with worse,'' said Edmonds. ''I'm just going to go home, relax, get some rest, and get ready.''</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the Braves hoped for a better performance from Glavine than they got from Greg Maddux in Game 1. While the fielding errors hurt Maddux, he was pounded for nine hits in just four innings, one of his worst outings of the season.</p>
        <p>Glavine was 21-9 this year, and he knows Atlanta needs another strong game. He was looking forward to the challenge.</p>
        <p>''There is pressure that goes along with being in the postseason, because you do not have the room to recover from mistakes like in the regular season,'' said Glavine. ''I think having played in the postseason as much as we have is definitely a plus. You know what you will have to deal with, you know what your preparation needs to be, and those things should help you to be successful.''</p>
        <p>But the Cardinals will have their ace on the mound for Game 2, the 20-game winner Darryl Kile. St. Louis Manager Tony La Russa gambled in Game 1, starting the 21-year-old rookie Rick Ankiel, and saving Kile (20-9) for Game 2. So far, the decision has paid off. Although Ankiel was shaky, tossing a major league-record five wild pitches in one inning, the Cardinals still won, allowing Kile to be available for Game 2, as well as Game 5 on Monday if necessary.</p>
        <p>So leading the series, and with their best pitcher ready to go, the Cardinals hoped to keep the momentum, while the Braves hoped to eliminate mistakes.</p>
        <p>''We have to stop giving teams extra outs and extra chances to hurt us,'' said Jones. ''If we do that, I think we'll be O.K.''</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>The weather forecast for Thursday called for a chance of showers and cooler temperatures. . . . TONY LA RUSSA, the Cardinals' manager, celebrated his 56th birthday Wednesday, and a huge sign wishing him a happy birthday flashed on the outfield scoreboard as the Cardinals worked out. La Russa already knew what he wanted for a present. ''I'd love to catch that plane to Atlanta leading 2-0 in the series,'' he said.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
