<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lucent Spinoff of Avaya May Offer Clues for AT&amp;T Proposal</title>
    <meta content="Y05AVAY" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/05/business/05AVAY.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236172"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">At&amp;t Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Avaya Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Lucent Technologies</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Romero, Simon</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001005T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE6DD1F3DF936A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="557" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lucent Spinoff of Avaya May Offer Clues for AT&amp;T Proposal</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SIMON ROMERO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Romero, Simon</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lucent Tecnologies' spinoff of Avaya Inc may not bode well for AT&amp;T Corp shareholders if AT&amp;T goes through with spinoff off its residential long-distance business; shares of Avaya Inc have declined more than 37 percent since they began trading separately from Lucent on Oct 2 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>According to recent news accounts, AT&amp;T is considering spinning off its residential long-distance business to its shareholders in a move that would free the company to focus on faster-growing areas. The question naturally arises as to whether investors would benefit from such a strategy.</p>
        <p>A glance at Avaya Inc., which was spun off to shareholders this week from Lucent Technologies, the world's largest manufacturer of telephone equipment, may offer insight.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>According to recent news accounts, AT&amp;T is considering spinning off its residential long-distance business to its shareholders in a move that would free the company to focus on faster-growing areas. The question naturally arises as to whether investors would benefit from such a strategy.</p>
        <p>A glance at Avaya Inc., which was spun off to shareholders this week from Lucent Technologies, the world's largest manufacturer of telephone equipment, may offer insight.</p>
        <p>Since Avaya began trading separately from Lucent on Monday, its share price has declined more than 37 percent, to $14.38.</p>
        <p>Avaya (pronounced uh-VIGH-uh) is the flashy new-economy name that Lucent gave to its enterprise networks group, a division focused on some decidedly old-economy areas. Avaya, for example, is a leader in selling PBX systems -- the electronic switchboards that control a corporation's telephone lines and voice-mail systems.</p>
        <p>While revenue from such businesses makes Avaya a $7.4 billion company, it is expected to grow a lot less, and less quickly, than Lucent, which is looking to focus on potentially faster-growing areas like fiber optic equipment and network systems. Lucent also plans to spin off its microelectronics division. Avaya's limited growth potential may explain why, so far, investors cannot seem to get rid of the shares quickly enough.</p>
        <p>Although AT&amp;T focuses on telecommunications services, not equipment, it is considering an overhaul similar to Lucent's. AT&amp;T's management is floating the idea of breaking up its divisions to focus more on fat-growing areas like broadband communications. Although its long-distance business still produces billions of dollars in revenue, that business is shrinking.</p>
        <p>At Avaya, the company's management hopes to allay concern over its share price by noting that Lucent shareholders were given one share of Avaya for every 12 shares of Lucent they own. The holders of Avaya shares need to be patient, Avaya's chief executive, Don Peterson, said.</p>
        <p>Morgan Stanley Dean Witter, the investment bank that advised Lucent and Avaya on the transaction, also tried to soothe investors. ''I'm surprised by the magnitude of the drop,'' George Kelly, a managing director at Morgan Stanley who assisted Avaya on the spinoff, said in a telephone interview from London.</p>
        <p>So far, Morgan Stanley is the only Wall Street firm that comprehensively covers Avaya.</p>
        <p>Spinoffs in the telecommunications industry like Avaya, of course, have produced some stellar results. After Lucent was spun off from AT&amp;T in 1996, it surpassed profit forecasts for 15 consecutive quarters as it became a powerhouse in markets for telecommunications.</p>
        <p>But this year, concern about inroads by competitors like Nortel Networks and Cisco Systems has pushed Lucent's price down 53 percent.</p>
        <p>But since Avaya began trading separately, Lucent's stock price has climbed about 15 percent. Just yesterday, shares in Lucent rose $2.38 to end the day at $32.38.</p>
        <p>So what, if anything, might this portend for AT&amp;T, as it considers spinning off its atrophying residential long-distance business?</p>
        <p>''Avaya is a relatively small piece of Lucent's pie, while the long-distance business is a much larger piece of AT&amp;T,'' said Michael Eggly, co-manager of the Northern Trust Corporation's $85 million Northern Global Communications Fund. ''Spinning off long-distance would totally redefine AT&amp;T as we know it.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
