<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Defining Themselves, Gore and Bush Drew Traditional Portraits</title>
    <meta content="Y05ASS$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/05/politics/05ASSE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236250"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: PARTY POSITIONS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rosenbaum, David E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001005T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E0D61F3DF936A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1201" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Defining Themselves, Gore and Bush Drew Traditional Portraits</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID E. ROSENBAUM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rosenbaum, David E</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Presidential debate underscored degree to which Vice Pres Al Gore and Gov George W Bush are standing fast on principles and policies that have divided their parties for generations; candidates not only took tried and true stands of their predecessors over many elections past, but even often used same words and phrases (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The debate Tuesday night underscored the degree to which Vice President Al Gore and Gov. George W. Bush are standing fast on the principles and policies that have divided their parties for generations.</p>
        <p>So much for the notion that the candidates are moving toward the center. So much for Ralph Nader's view that they are Tweedledum and Tweedledee.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The debate Tuesday night underscored the degree to which Vice President Al Gore and Gov. George W. Bush are standing fast on the principles and policies that have divided their parties for generations.</p>
        <p>So much for the notion that the candidates are moving toward the center. So much for Ralph Nader's view that they are Tweedledum and Tweedledee.</p>
        <p>Voters who intend to decide on the basis of where the candidates stand on the issues were presented with a clear choice between a traditional Democrat and a traditional Republican.</p>
        <p>On the role of government in the society, on taxes and spending, on Social Security and Medicare, on energy and the environment, on abortion, on public and private schools, and on choices for the Supreme Court, the presidential candidates not only took the tried and true positions of their predecessors over many elections past, they even often used the same words and phrases.</p>
        <p>When, for instance, Mr. Gore repeated over and over that the wealthiest 1 percent of taxpayers would be the main beneficiaries of the tax cuts Mr. Bush has proposed, he sounded just like his Democratic forefathers.</p>
        <p>This was Jimmy Carter expounding on Gerald R. Ford's tax policies in their first debate on Sept. 23, 1976: ''It's just a welfare program for the rich. As a matter of fact, 25 percent of the total tax deductions go for only 1 percent of the richest people in this country.''</p>
        <p>And this was Michael S. Dukakis addressing George Bush's tax plan in their first debate on Sept. 25, 1988: ''What he's proposing is a tax cut for the wealthiest 1 percent of people in this country.''</p>
        <p>When the younger Mr. Bush said on Tuesday that ''the vice president thinks it's the government's money; the payroll taxes are your money,'' he could have been quoting Ronald Reagan.</p>
        <p>This was Mr. Reagan in 1981 shortly after he became president: ''Are you entitled to the fruits of your labor or does the government have some presumptive right to spend and spend and spend?''</p>
        <p>In 1992 and 1996, Bill Clinton advocated a ''third way,'' something between the historical positions of Democrats and Republicans, and his opponents, George Bush and Bob Dole, were forced to defend political compromises they had struck as president and Senate majority leader, respectively.</p>
        <p>But the candidates this year have reverted to form. They have been able to do so for one main reason: money is available. As long as there was a large budget deficit, Republicans had to restrain their impulse to advocate large tax cuts, and Democrats were forced to rein in their desire to spend more money.</p>
        <p>''The surplus,'' said Charles O. Jones, professor emeritus of political science at the University of Wisconsin, ''has allowed a return to the clarity of the traditional two-party positions.''</p>
        <p>But it is much more than the matter of taxes and spending -- with Mr. Bush advocating deep, across-the-board tax cuts and Mr. Gore proposing heavy new spending for social programs -- where this year's campaign reflects long-held party positions.</p>
        <p>On the question of the proper role of the federal government, Mr. Bush accused Mr. Gore of wanting to ''increase the size of government dramatically,'' a plan that Mr. Bush said, ''empowers Washington.'' For his part, Mr. Bush went on, ''My passion and my vision is to empower Americans to be able to make decisions for themselves and their own lives.''</p>
        <p>This is the core of Republican dogma -- that an all-powerful Washington is something to be feared. It has been the stand taken by nearly every important Republican politician for the last 70 years.</p>
        <p>By the same token, Mr. Gore's insistence that social insurance -- Social Security and Medicare -- should be universal, available to the same degree to all Americans, rich and poor, has been the operating principle of the Democratic party since the New Deal.</p>
        <p>Republicans, for the most part, voted against Social Security in the 1930's and against Medicare in the 1960's and have never fully accepted the doctrine of social insurance. Mr. Bush's advocacy of partial privatization of the two programs fits that mold.</p>
        <p>On energy, Mr. Bush's solution to high oil prices is more domestic production, Mr. Gore's is conservation. This is the same dispute Mr. Carter and Mr. Reagan had in 1980.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Gore accused Mr. Bush of threatening to ''destroy precious parts of America's environment'' by drilling for oil in the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge, he was taking a cue from Mr. Dukakis, who in his second debate with Vice President George Bush called him ''the charter member of the environmental wrecking crew.''</p>
        <p>The division between the parties on abortion goes back at least to 1980, when Mr. Reagan won the backing of conservative Christians and Republicans by initiating an assault on Roe v. Wade, the Supreme Court decision that recognized a constitutional right to abortion.</p>
        <p>In the debate, Mr. Gore succinctly stated the Democratic principle: ''I think a woman's right to choose ought to be protected and defended.''</p>
        <p>Though Mr. Bush has mostly adopted the usual Republican stand against legalized abortion, he did some bobbing and weaving on Tuesday night. He spoke generally about ''promoting a culture of life'' and protecting ''every child born and unborn.''</p>
        <p>But while he said he was disappointed in the Food and Drug Administration's approval of the abortion pill, RU-486, he insisted he would be powerless as president to do anything about it. He also pledged again not to make the abortion issue a litmus test for his judicial nominees.</p>
        <p>The dispute over public and private schools is also a perennial. Republicans have long favored giving government money to parents who are dissatisfied with public schools to help offset private school tuition. Democrats maintain this would undermine the public schools.</p>
        <p>Polls show public disdain for vouchers, so Mr. Bush avoids the word, but his position is little different from that of his father, who was a strong advocate of vouchers.</p>
        <p>In the debate, Mr. Bush said, ''I believe that if we find poor children trapped in schools that won't teach, we need to free the parents.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore replied in time-tested Democratic fashion: ''I don't think private schools should have a right to take taxpayer money away from public schools.''</p>
        <p>The arguments over qualifications for the Supreme Court have hardly changed since Earl Warren was chief justice in the 1950's and 1960's. On Tuesday night, Mr. Bush said, ''I believe in strict constructionists, and those are the kind of judges I will appoint.''</p>
        <p>Sound familiar? Here is what Richard M. Nixon said in 1968 toward the end of his campaign against Hubert H. Humphrey: ''We need more strict constructionists on the highest court in the United States.''</p>
        <p>And Mr. Gore's response was the same one Democrats were making then: ''In my view, the Constitution ought to be interpreted as a document that grows with our country and our history.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: PARTY POSITIONS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
