<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Reality Of War, Traffic Jams And All</title>
    <meta content="05KIPP" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/05/arts/05KIPP.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236136"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FILM FESTIVAL REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">New York Film Festival</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Scott, A O</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gitai, Amos</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Kippur (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews/By A. O. Scott</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New York Film Festival</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New York Film Festival</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001005T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E0DA1E3DF936A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="733" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Reality Of War, Traffic Jams And All</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By A. O. SCOTT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Scott, A O</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>A O Scott reviews Kippur, new film by Amos Gitai being shown at New York Film Festival; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Twenty-seven years ago tomorrow, Egypt and Syria launched a surprise attack against Israel. The brief, intense war that followed -- called the Yom Kippur War, after the Jewish holiday on which the fighting started -- is the subject of Amos Gitai's new film, ''Kippur,'' which will be shown tonight at the New York Film Festival. The battlefield action in the film is bloody and relentless; Mr. Gitai is working in the close-to-the-ground, hyper-realist mode of Sam Fuller's ''Big Red One'' and the opening battle sequences of Steven Spielberg's ''Saving Private Ryan.'' War, according to this style of filmmaking, is an existential rather than a political event. The causes -- and even, in this case, the outcome -- of the conflict matter less than the experiences of the men who fight.</p>
        <p>''Kippur'' might be described as an anti-war movie. Not because it takes a stand against the Yom Kippur War, or war in general -- the soldiers in the film accept the necessity of fighting, and the film never questions their commitment -- but because Mr. Gitai, who wrote the screenplay with Marie-Jose Sanselme, does his utmost to resist the conventions of the genre. Yes, there is male camaraderie and wistful talk of girlfriends left behind, but the sentimental payoffs and narrative quiet spots that usually shape combat pictures are left out.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Twenty-seven years ago tomorrow, Egypt and Syria launched a surprise attack against Israel. The brief, intense war that followed -- called the Yom Kippur War, after the Jewish holiday on which the fighting started -- is the subject of Amos Gitai's new film, ''Kippur,'' which will be shown tonight at the New York Film Festival. The battlefield action in the film is bloody and relentless; Mr. Gitai is working in the close-to-the-ground, hyper-realist mode of Sam Fuller's ''Big Red One'' and the opening battle sequences of Steven Spielberg's ''Saving Private Ryan.'' War, according to this style of filmmaking, is an existential rather than a political event. The causes -- and even, in this case, the outcome -- of the conflict matter less than the experiences of the men who fight.</p>
        <p>''Kippur'' might be described as an anti-war movie. Not because it takes a stand against the Yom Kippur War, or war in general -- the soldiers in the film accept the necessity of fighting, and the film never questions their commitment -- but because Mr. Gitai, who wrote the screenplay with Marie-Jose Sanselme, does his utmost to resist the conventions of the genre. Yes, there is male camaraderie and wistful talk of girlfriends left behind, but the sentimental payoffs and narrative quiet spots that usually shape combat pictures are left out.</p>
        <p>Like many war stories, this one is about the disillusionment of brash young men: ''War, real war,'' exults one character, speeding toward the front in a broken-down car. ''This time it's ours.'' The smashing of this idealism is quick and brutal. In its place comes not any deep, consoling knowledge of human nature but a state of dazed cynicism.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gitai, himself a veteran of the 1973 war, has apparently followed his own experiences closely. His hero, Weinraub (Liron Levo), is an earnest young bohemian who lectures his friend Ruso (Tomer Ruso) on Herbert Marcuse and, in the opening and closing scenes, smears paint on his girlfriend while they're making love. The arty eroticism of these sequences stands in visual and emotional contrast to the rest of the movie, which shows men writhing in pain and covered in mud.</p>
        <p>At first, though, war is experienced as eerie silence punctuated by almost comical chaos. Audiences used to the square-jawed, crew-cut discipline on display in American combat movies may be surprised at the informality -- and the shagginess -- of the Israeli Army. Ruso and Weinraub set off in search of their reserve unit, but they encounter traffic jams and desolate highways before finally joining up with a helicopter rescue squad. In the company of a perpetually unshaven doctor named Klauzner (Uri Ran Klauzner), they slog through battlefields dodging Israeli tanks and Syrian mortar fire and trying to evacuate the wounded.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gitai is clearly intent on capturing the tedium and frustration of battle and its aftermath, as well as the sheer horror of burned faces and severed limbs. In the movie's most wrenching sequence, the team tries to extricate an unconscious soldier from a boggy ditch. They keep losing their footing as he slides off the stretcher back into the mud. It's almost unbearable, but Mr. Gitai refuses to cut away.</p>
        <p>The relentless attention to the sheer awfulness of war, which is the film's great strength, is also something of a shortcoming. Mr. Gitai reproduces the numb horror of wading through fields of gore almost too well: the self-protective response is to shut down your emotions, as the characters do. ''Kippur'' immerses you in violence and agony, but it may leave you with a curious feeling of detachment.</p>
        <p>KIPPUR</p>
        <p>Directed by Amos Gitai; written (in Hebrew, with English subtitles) by Mr. Gitai and Marie-Jose Sanselme; director of photography, Renato Berta; edited by Monica Coleman and Kobi Netanel; music by Jan Garbarek; production designer, Miguel Markin; produced by Laurent Truchot; released by Kino International. Running time: 117 minutes. This film is not rated. Shown tonight at 6 and Saturday at 9 P.M. at Alice Tully Hall as part of the 38th New York Film Festival.</p>
        <p>WITH: Guy Amir (Gadassi), Noach Faran (Rescue Commander), Shai Gani (Army Doctor), Keren Gitai (Young Soldier), Liat Glick Levo (Dina), Yoram Hattab (Pilot), Ran Kauchinsky (Shlomo), Uri Ran Klauzner (Doctor), Liron Levo (Weinraub), Kobi Livine (Kobi), Juliano Merr (Officer), Pini Mittleman (Hospital Doctor) and Tomer Ruso (Ruso).</p>
        <p>FILM FESTIVAL REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
