<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NO DEAL REACHED IN TALKS TO QUELL MIDEAST FIGHTING</title>
    <meta content="05DIPL$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/05/world/05DIPL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236282"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Israel-International Relations-US</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">France-International Relations-Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Anti-Semitism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Foreign Service</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Egypt</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">France</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Cairo (Egypt)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Syria</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Damascus (Syria)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Jordan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Amman (Jordan)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perlez, Jane</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barak, Ehud (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arafat, Yasir</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Albright, Madeleine K (Sec)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mubarak, Hosni (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chirac, Jacques (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Annan, Kofi (Sec Gen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Jordan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Syria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Egypt</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Egypt</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Jordan/Amman</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Jordan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Egypt/Cairo</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Syria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Syria/Damascus</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Anti-Semitism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Service</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Foreign Service</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001005T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E5DE163CF936A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1336" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NO DEAL REACHED IN TALKS TO QUELL MIDEAST FIGHTING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE PERLEZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Perlez, Jane</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, Thursday, Oct. 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Israeli Prime Min Ehud Barak, Palestinian leader Yasir Arafat and State Sec Madeleine K Albright fail to agree on plan to end continuing Israeli-Palestinian clashes in talks, Paris; Barak heads home, declining invitation from Pres Hosni Mubarak to host further talks in Egypt; Albright plans to meet with Mubarak and Arafat; Paris talks also involved French Pres Jacques Chirac and United Nations Sec Gen Kofi Annan; major sticking point reportedly was how probe should be conducted into fighting, with Barak resisting Arafat's demand for international probe; violence spreads to Cairo, where some 1,500 students protesting Palestinian deaths stone supermarket run by reportedly Jewish-owned British company; Syrian students stone United States Embassy, Damascus; Jordanian police use tear gas to disperse some 800 people who try to march on Israeli Embassy, Amman (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After more than 12 hours of stormy talks and with clashes continuing in the Middle East, the Israeli and Palestinian leaders and Secretary of State Madeleine K. Albright struggled into the early morning today to find a way to stop the violence, but failed to reach an overall agreement, a senior Clinton administration official said.</p>
        <p>Prime Minister Ehud Barak of Israel headed home from Paris this morning, declining an invitation from President Hosni Mubarak to hold further negotiations in Egypt. An American official said Dr. Albright was going to the meeting with Mr. Mubarak and Yasir Arafat, the Palestinian leader, to ''lock things down'' and pin down Mr. Arafat.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After more than 12 hours of stormy talks and with clashes continuing in the Middle East, the Israeli and Palestinian leaders and Secretary of State Madeleine K. Albright struggled into the early morning today to find a way to stop the violence, but failed to reach an overall agreement, a senior Clinton administration official said.</p>
        <p>Prime Minister Ehud Barak of Israel headed home from Paris this morning, declining an invitation from President Hosni Mubarak to hold further negotiations in Egypt. An American official said Dr. Albright was going to the meeting with Mr. Mubarak and Yasir Arafat, the Palestinian leader, to ''lock things down'' and pin down Mr. Arafat.</p>
        <p>Israeli officials were reported to have agreed to withdraw heavy armaments from the West Bank and Gaza, but that part of the overall accord that Dr. Albright was aiming for was not formalized by the parties, American officials said.</p>
        <p>There were also reports that the Palestinians would agree to stay away from two flash points in the West Bank and the Gaza Strip.</p>
        <p>But the State Department spokesman, Richard A. Boucher, said that despite continuing ''intense discussions'' that began at 10 a.m. Wednesday and ended not long before 3 a.m. today, the United States was not ''laying claim to any agreement.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Albright had summoned Mr. Barak and Mr. Arafat to Paris to try to dampen the violence that has resulted in the deaths of more than 60 Palestinians and threatens to unravel many of the gains made in seven years of Middle East peacemaking by the Clinton administration.</p>
        <p>According to accounts from diplomats involved in what turned into a chaotic flurry of talks that also involved the French president, Jacques Chirac, and the United Nations secretary general, Kofi Annan, the major sticking point was how an investigation should be conducted into the bloodletting. Mr. Arafat stood by his insistence that an investigation should be international, preferably involving the United Nations, while Mr. Barak was opposed to that, diplomats said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mubarak has been one of Mr. Arafat's key allies but also heads the first Arab country to have signed a peace treaty with Israel. It was clear, diplomats said, that Mr. Arafat needed the ''cover'' of a fellow Arab leader -- whose participation in the talks would make it easier to sell an agreement to Palestinians -- and would wait until the session in Egypt to complete an overall accord to stop the violence.</p>
        <p>[After Mr. Barak flew back to Israel, The Associated Press quoted some American officials as saying that Mr. Arafat might not go to Egypt either. But Agence France-Presse quoted a Palestinian spokeswoman, Leila Shahid, as saying that Mr. Arafat had left Paris and flown to Egypt to attend the talks.]</p>
        <p>The violence continued in the Palestinian territories Wednesday and spread beyond the borders of Israel and the Palestinian territories. In Mr. Mubarak's capital, Cairo, and in the Syrian capital, Damascus, thousands of university students protested the deaths of Palestinians.</p>
        <p>In Cairo about 1,500 students stoned a supermarket belonging to the British retail company Sainsbury's, asserting that the owner was Jewish. In Damascus, university students pelted the United States Embassy with stones, branches and rubbish. And in the Jordanian capital, Amman, the police fired tear gas and used batons to disperse about 800 people who tried to march on the Israeli Embassy.</p>
        <p>Where just last week she was playing peacemaker trying to mediate an overall accord between the Israelis and Palestinians, Dr. Albright found herself in Paris trying to extinguish the flames of the worst violence between the two sides since 1996.</p>
        <p>She was accompanied by the director of the Central Intelligence Agency, George J. Tenet, who worked out the security cooperation arrangement between the Israelis and the Palestinians in 1998.</p>
        <p>At one point on Wednesday evening, the talks became so heated that Mr. Arafat stormed out of a meeting at the residence of the American ambassador, saying, according to reporters who overheard the incident: ''This is humiliation. I cannot accept it.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Albright was heard in the same dialogue to order the security guards to ''shut the gates,'' so that the Palestinian leader could not leave the compound in central Paris.</p>
        <p>According to the account of a Reuters correspondent, Dr. Albright ran after Mr. Arafat, urging him not to leave. The gates closed in front of Mr. Arafat's car, and he got out and returned to the meeting.</p>
        <p>The two leaders arrived in defiant moods. Mr. Arafat, whose people are at a boiling point over the visit last Thursday of the right-wing Israeli opposition leader, Ariel Sharon, to the Muslim holy sites atop the Old City of Jerusalem, and over the killings since, was under pressure not to come at all.</p>
        <p>Mr. Barak, who was accompanied by the deputy chief of staff of the Israeli Army, Moshe Yaalon, announced on arrival that he would have no part of an international investigation into the violence.</p>
        <p>During the meetings, the general forcefully defended the use of live ammunition by Israeli security forces, officials said.</p>
        <p>Earlier, Mr. Chirac met separately with the two leaders. The French president, who has been the most critical of any Western leader of Mr. Sharon's visit, said he strongly supported an international inquiry into the latest violence.</p>
        <p>But expressing Israeli opposition to the idea, Justice Minister Yossi Beilin said: ''I think that if there are questions and if there are queries, we can answer them ourselves. We don't need a committee biased against Israel to investigate things.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Albright suggested that the Palestinians and the Israelis separately investigate what happened. American diplomats would help mediate the findings, she said, thus lending an international character to the proceedings.</p>
        <p>Diplomats said Wednesday's sessions had been taken up by considerable posturing. In his first meeting with the secretary this morning, Mr. Barak went into long descriptions of how the Palestinians were violating the agreements with Israel by acquiring illegal arms and shooting at Israeli soldiers.</p>
        <p>This evening, too, in a three-way meeting among Mr. Barak, Mr. Arafat and Dr. Albright, the Israelis stressed what they called the Palestinian violations, diplomats said. Mr. Arafat complained bitterly at the session about the use of helicopter gunships and anti-tank weapons by Israelis against his people.</p>
        <p>A charged atmosphere characterized the talks right from the start, with Mr. Barak releasing a statement after meeting with Mr. Chirac saying that Mr. Arafat could ''choose between the road to an agreement or the sliding down to violence,'' for which he said Mr. Arafat bore the responsibility.</p>
        <p>After his session with Mr. Chirac, the Palestinian leader set out three demands: the withdrawal of Israeli troops to their positions before Sept. 28, a cease-fire and an international investigation.</p>
        <p>At different points during the day, the various delegations were holed up in luxury hotels, plotting strategy and waiting their turns with the principle mediators. Mr. Arafat, who was at the Meurice Hotel on the Rue de Rivoli, spent much of the afternoon there, debating whether to take part in the three-way meeting.</p>
        <p>At another point, Mr. Annan was at the Bristol Hotel waiting to have dinner with the French foreign minister, Hubert Vedrine. Then, around midnight, sirens wailed as all the dignitaries -- Israelis, Palestinians, Americans and the United Nations delegation -- got into motorcades and descended on Elysee Palace to meet with Mr. Chirac.</p>
        <p>In her invitation to the Palestinian and Israeli leaders to come to Paris, Dr. Albright said she wanted to return them to the ''psychology of peace-making,'' apparently a reference to the Camp David meeting in July. But the tone was so severe here that several diplomats said the administration might have waited too long to intervene. At Elysee Palace,  Dr. Albright invited the Israelis and the Palestinians to each send a negotiator for peace talks to Washington next week, diplomats said. But the suggestion was not greeted warmly, they said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
