<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rethinking Police Dept. Recruitment</title>
    <meta content="05MATT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/05/nyregion/05MATT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236226"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="METRO MATTERS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hispanic-Americans</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Purnick, Joyce</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kerik, Bernard B (Comr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Metro Matters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hispanic-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001005T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEED81F3DF936A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="769" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rethinking Police Dept. Recruitment</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOYCE PURNICK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Purnick, Joyce</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>METRO MATTERS: Rethinking Police Dept. Recruitment**Joyce Purnick Metro Matters column discusses NYC Police Commissioner Bernard B Kerik, faced with crisis in attracting police recruits, especially among blacks and Latinos, relaxing some standards; criticism of move discussed (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LAST week, Police Commissioner Bernard B. Kerik, facing a crisis in attracting police recruits, especially among blacks and Latinos, relaxed some standards. Applicants can be 21 years old instead of 22, and more of them may use work credits in place of college credits.</p>
        <p>The changes are modest ones that probably will not hurt the quality of the Police Department. But they are, in the estimation of people as ideologically different as the Rev. Jesse Jackson and Thomas A. Reppetto of the Citizens Crime Commission, a bad idea.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LAST week, Police Commissioner Bernard B. Kerik, facing a crisis in attracting police recruits, especially among blacks and Latinos, relaxed some standards. Applicants can be 21 years old instead of 22, and more of them may use work credits in place of college credits.</p>
        <p>The changes are modest ones that probably will not hurt the quality of the Police Department. But they are, in the estimation of people as ideologically different as the Rev. Jesse Jackson and Thomas A. Reppetto of the Citizens Crime Commission, a bad idea.</p>
        <p>''One does not have to dumb down recruits to make better police,'' Mr. Jackson said in a speech at the John Jay College of Criminal Justice.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reppetto, president of the crime commission, said in an interview that ''rather than reducing standards marginally, the right direction is to try to attract more college graduates by selling policing as a human services occupation.''</p>
        <p>Several other criminal justice experts said much the same thing this week -- that the department should be elevating the nature of the job, in effect investing in, not cutting back on, standards.</p>
        <p>As they see it, New York is suffering from a national trend: the blue-collar job market is shrinking, and the relatively low salary and difficulties of being police officers are hurting recruitment.</p>
        <p>It's not that the modest changes announced by Mr. Kerik will make a big difference, goes the argument, but that the direction is wrong. In addition to lowering the age, he broadened the number of recruits permitted to waive a requirement for 60 college credits; those with two or more years of honorable military service were already exempt. Now, traffic enforcement and school safety agents with at least two years on the job won't have to take the 60 college credits either.</p>
        <p>That may help recruitment, but will it help in the long run? The nationwide difficulty in attracting more police officers is widely attributed to competition from more lucrative professions and the damaged image of the police because of everything from the corruption scandal in Los Angeles to the shooting death of Amadou Diallo in New York.</p>
        <p>In New York City, the newest class of police recruits is 355 short of its goal of 1,589, and though the percentage of minority recruits is growing, the department is still two-thirds white in a diverse city with a large black and Hispanic population. And police shortages could get worse as the hundreds of officers who joined the expanding police force in the early 1980's, after the hiring doldrums of the fiscal crisis, become eligible for retirement. Mr. Reppetto champions an alliance between the Police Department and the City University of New York.</p>
        <p>The city tried that in the mid-1990's, creating a ''cadet'' program for about 200 college students. Some got four-year degrees, some got two-year associate degrees. All took specialized classes in law, sociology, history and cultural diversity at John Jay,  which is part of the City University, and worked a minimum of three days a month at nonenforcement jobs in station houses, for about $7,000. After college, the cadets entered the police academy.</p>
        <p>THE program was successful, in the judgment of James T. Curran, dean of special programs at John Jay. Students learned from civilian instructors, were closely monitored (a third flunked out because of behavior problems or failing grades) and theoretically could free up police officers from desk jobs. The program also drew from City University's diverse student body.</p>
        <p>''It made a lot of sense,'' Mr. Curran said. ''There are some things you don't learn in six months at the police academy. Professions take awhile to shape people.''</p>
        <p>But it cost the city at least $1.2 million a year, much of it going to CUNY, and there were turf problems. The Police Department has its own cadet program, now with 538 students and moving toward twice that number: high school seniors and college students who work part time in police jobs. After two years in college they may attend the police academy, and if they serve two years, their college loans are forgiven.</p>
        <p>The CUNY program is quite different: students go to any college and do not take specialized courses focusing on criminal justice matters. Nor does a coordinated team at John Jay monitor their progress. But the Police Department found the two approaches working at cross purposes. So the link to John Jay and the rest of the City University ended in 1997.</p>
        <p>Maybe it's time, Mr. Reppetto says, for the new commissioner to rethink an old decision.</p>
        <p>METRO MATTERS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
