<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Justices Questions Congress's Limits on Legal Aid Arguments</title>
    <meta content="Y05SCOT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/05/politics/05SCOT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236175"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Welfare (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Legal Aid for the Poor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Federal Aid (US)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Supreme Court (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Legal Services Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greenhouse, Linda</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Federal Aid (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legal Aid for the Poor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Welfare (US)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001005T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E5DD1F3DF936A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="939" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Justices Questions Congress's Limits on Legal Aid Arguments</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LINDA GREENHOUSE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Greenhouse, Linda</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Supreme Court hears appeal of lower court ruling overturning 1996 law that barred lawyers in federally financed legal services program from challenging existing welfare laws; Legal Services Corp, which accepted restriction as alternative to being driven out of business by hostile Republican majority in Congress, and Clinton Administation defend law (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Supreme Court has permitted Congress to attach many strings to the use of federal money over the years. But pointed questioning by the justices today indicated that in restricting the type of legal arguments that lawyers in the federally financed legal services program can make on behalf of welfare clients, Congress might have gone too far.</p>
        <p>A 1996 appropriations measure for the Legal Services Corporation barred any ''effort to amend or otherwise challenge existing law'' in welfare cases; lawyers supported by the program could seek benefits on behalf of their clients but even while using money from private sources could not challenge the regulation or law under which the benefits had been denied. The restriction has been carried forward each year since then.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Supreme Court has permitted Congress to attach many strings to the use of federal money over the years. But pointed questioning by the justices today indicated that in restricting the type of legal arguments that lawyers in the federally financed legal services program can make on behalf of welfare clients, Congress might have gone too far.</p>
        <p>A 1996 appropriations measure for the Legal Services Corporation barred any ''effort to amend or otherwise challenge existing law'' in welfare cases; lawyers supported by the program could seek benefits on behalf of their clients but even while using money from private sources could not challenge the regulation or law under which the benefits had been denied. The restriction has been carried forward each year since then.</p>
        <p>The Legal Services Corporation has accepted the restriction as an alternative to being driven out of business by a hostile Republican majority in Congress. Joined by the Clinton administration, the corporation defended the policy before the justices today in an appeal of a lower court ruling that found it to be an unconstitutional restriction on criticism of government policy. The suit to lift the limitation was brought in New York City by individual legal services lawyers, their clients and a coalition of nonprofit organizations.</p>
        <p>''Congress itself has the power to decide what policies and programs it will promote,'' Alan Levine, a lawyer for the corporation, told the justices, adding that the limitation ''made perfect sense'' for a Congress that wanted to keep federally financed lawyers from challenging the substantial changes brought about by the 1996 welfare law. And Edwin S. Kneedler, a deputy solicitor general, told the court that the case concerned not speech but only ''what type of professional services is the government going to pay for.'' Lawyers who represent a client are not engaging in ''self-expression'' in any event, he said.</p>
        <p>But the court was deeply, even surprisingly skeptical. Challenging a government policy in court was ''the paradigm of free speech, a petition to the government,'' Justice Anthony M. Kennedy told Mr. Kneedler.</p>
        <p>The justices' concern seemed animated by their own experience as lawyers, and they were troubled by the notion of having to represent a client with certain arguments foreclosed.</p>
        <p>Under intense questioning by Justices Ruth Bader Ginsburg, Sandra Day O'Connor and David H. Souter, Mr. Levine conceded that a legal services lawyer could not make a type of argument that is the bread and butter of administrative law: that a regulation should be interpreted in a certain way because, interpreted another way, it might well be unconstitutional. Even the suggestion that a regulation was invalid would fall under the prohibition, the corporation's lawyer said.</p>
        <p>The restriction means in effect that the law is whatever the government says it is, Justice Souter said, adding, ''It limits more than I thought.''</p>
        <p>To Mr. Kneedler, the deputy solicitor general, Justice Souter said, ''You're getting just about to the molten core of the First Amendment'' when the government ''disfavors speech'' that disagrees with existing government policy. ''There's something very risky going on here.''</p>
        <p>Justice Souter's comments and active participation today drew particular notice because, as nearly everyone in the courtroom was aware, his view of the case, Legal Services Corporation v. Velazquez, No. 99-603, could well determine the outcome. In 1991, during his first term on the court, he joined the 5-to-4 majority that upheld a ban on abortion counseling by family planning clinics that received federal money. Nine years later, Justice Souter often appears notably more skeptical of government policy, and there has been considerable speculation that his vote would be different if he were deciding that case today.</p>
        <p>Burt Neuborne, the lawyer for the plaintiffs in the case today, said that the abortion case, Rust v. Sullivan, was wrongly decided but did not have to be overturned for his clients in the legal services case to prevail. In the earlier case, he said, the government had in effect hired the doctors who worked in the family planning clinics and given them the job of ''disseminating one point of view and not another'' on abortion as a method of family planning.</p>
        <p>But in the context of legal services, he said, the lawyer hired to give the government's message was not the legal services lawyer, but rather the government's own lawyer who appeared in court to defend a government policy in a lawsuit. The legal services lawyer ''doesn't speak for the state,'' Mr. Neuborne, legal director of the Brennan Center for Justice at New York University Law School, told the justices.</p>
        <p>''The government has hired one lawyer for the government's message and commandeers the voice of the other lawyer as well,'' he said. The restriction was ''a core interference with what attorneys ordinarily do for clients,'' he said, noting that it was very difficult for a lawyer to know in advance what kinds of arguments would serve a client's case. ''Legal services clients don't appear on your doorstep color-coded by argument,'' he said.</p>
        <p>In his 1999 opinion striking down the restriction, Judge Pierre N. Leval of the United States Court of Appeals for the Second Circuit found it an example of ''viewpoint discrimination'' that ''clearly seeks to discourage challenges to the status quo.'' Granting that Congress was free to finance some activities and not others, he said this case had a First Amendment dimension that placed it in a different category than abortion counseling or indecent art, the subjects of the Supreme Court's recent precedents.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
