<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>WORLD BRIEFING</title>
    <meta content="Y05BRI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/05/world/05BRIE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236161"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001005T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800EEDF1F3DF936A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1737" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>WORLD BRIEFING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by Barth Healey</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>RUSSIA: ACCORD ON NAZI LOOT -- Deputy Treasury Secretary Stuart E. Eizenstat said the United States and Russia had reached extensive agreement on opening archives to help find property looted by the Nazis. He declined to give details before addressing a conference this week in Vilnius, Lithuania, on Holocaust restitution. Nazi booty totaled about 220,000 artworks, according to estimates by the State Department, of which 60,000 have been recovered.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>RUSSIA: ACCORD ON NAZI LOOT -- Deputy Treasury Secretary Stuart E. Eizenstat said the United States and Russia had reached extensive agreement on opening archives to help find property looted by the Nazis. He declined to give details before addressing a conference this week in Vilnius, Lithuania, on Holocaust restitution. Nazi booty totaled about 220,000 artworks, according to estimates by the State Department, of which 60,000 have been recovered.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>ITALY: MUSSOLINI'S FORUM IN LIMBO -- The sale of Foro Italico, a Mussolini-era sports complex in Rome with distinctive Fascist architecture, was suspended by an Italian administrative court after the University Institute of Motor Sciences argued that it had a contract for free and permanent access. The Treasury Ministry could appeal.</p>
        <p>Alessandra Stanley (NYT)</p>
        <p>ITALY: DAMAGED CHURCH REOPENS -- Santo Stefano al Ponte in Florence, an artistic jewel that was severely damaged by a bomb in 1993, is reopening today after a $1.6 million restoration. The bombing, aimed at the Uffizi gallery, killed five people; it was attributed to the Mafia.</p>
        <p>(Agence France-Presse)</p>
        <p>MIDDLE EAST</p>
        <p>JORDAN: QADDAFI COMES CALLING -- In a sign of improving ties, the Libyan leader Muammar el-Qaddafi, near left, arrived in Aqaba for his first visit to Jordan since 1983. He and King Abdullah II, far left, planned talks on Libyan assistance for a major project to provide Amman with drinking water. Libya has offered $100 million for the project, which is estimated at $730 million. Relations have improved since Abdullah succeeded his father, King Hussein, 20 months ago. Colonel Qaddafi had been critical of Hussein's close ties with Israel.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>IRAQ: TUNISIAN PLANE ARRIVES -- A Tunisair plane carrying 20 surgeons and eye doctors and Tunisia's national soccer team arrived in Baghdad, another chink in the United Nations embargo against Iraq. Recent flights from Russia, France, Jordan, Yemen and Morocco prove Washington is isolated in its insistence on sanctions, Deputy Prime Minister Tariq Aziz said.  (Agence France-Presse)</p>
        <p>THE AMERICAS</p>
        <p>CUBA: PROGRESS ON DEBT REPORTED -- After years of deadlock, creditor nations in the so-called Paris Club are willing to try to reschedule the estimated $3.5 billion debt Cuba has with them, diplomats said. Central bank officials, who worry that higher oil prices could double Cuba's balance of payments deficit to close to $1 billion this year, are to meet these creditors in November. Cuba's total hard-currency foreign debt at the end of 1999 was just over $11 billion.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>AFRICA</p>
        <p>SOUTH AFRICA: PLEA TO TIGHTEN IMMIGRATION -- The home affairs minister, Mangosuthu Buthelezi, said South Africa must tighten immigration laws to discourage false asylum claims and marriages of convenience. One-third of the 75,000 asylum seekers currently in the country are not genuine, Chief Buthelezi said during a parliamentary committee hearing. Almost two-thirds of migration applications were by spouses involved in marriages of convenience, according to Mr. Buthelezi's chief adviser, Mario Oriani-Ambrosini.</p>
        <p>(Agence France-Presse)</p>
        <p>LIBERIA: U.N. INQUIRY ON DIAMONDS -- United Nations experts have arrived to investigate Liberia's reported involvement in smuggling diamonds from Sierra Leone. President Charles Taylor has denied profiting from Sierra Leone's civil war by encouraging the trade, and asked the United Nations to investigate.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>ZIMBABWE: RADIO STATION RAIDED -- Security agents raided Capital Radio, the nation's first independent radio station, which had begun broadcasting on Friday, said one of the station's owners, Mike Auret Jr. He said that the police had search warrants, but that lawyers for the station had served papers on the police, the attorney general and the Information Ministry prohibiting them from interfering in the station. So far, no arrests have been made, and the station remains on the air.</p>
        <p>(Agence France-Presse)</p>
        <p>ASIA</p>
        <p>INDIA: PUTIN URGES TALKS ON KASHMIR -- Russia's president, Vladimir V. Putin, addressing a special session of Parliament, said India's long dispute with Pakistan over Kashmir can be decided only ''on a bilateral basis'' between the two nations. New Delhi has consistently opposed any foreign mediation. During Mr. Putin's visit, India signed contracts with Russia to acquire tanks, fighter jets and an aircraft carrier, and an agreement to cooperate in ''peaceful uses of nuclear energy.''</p>
        <p>Barry Bearak (NYT)</p>
        <p>NORTH KOREA: NERVOUS ABOUT FOREIGN AID -- United Nations agencies are urging donors to send food to North Korea to avert famine, but such aid could prove dangerous, an official newspaper warned. ''The imperialists' aid is a tool of aggression, a dangerous toxin that brings about poverty, famine and death, not prosperity,'' said Rodong Sinmun, the official daily of the Workers Party of Korea.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>AFGHANISTAN: OPPOSITION ADAMANT -- Despite recent defeats, the opposition leader Ahmad Shah Massoud has vowed to fight on and blamed ''Pakistani intervention'' on the side of the ruling Taliban for the setbacks that have bottled up his army near the Tajikistan border. He appealed for ''the support of the international community'' to force Pakistan to disengage.</p>
        <p>Barry Bearak (NYT)</p>
        <p>CHINA: MANNED SPACE FLIGHTS PLANNED -- The director of the State Aerospace Bureau, Luan Enjie, said China plans manned space flights to the moon. In a speech commemorating International Space Week, Mr. Luan said China would start with unmanned flights, but he did not offer a timetable.</p>
        <p>Craig S. Smith (NYT)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
