<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Teacher Is Accused of Duping Boy to Make a Sexual Video</title>
    <meta content="05WEB" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/05/nyregion/05WEB.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236216"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Extortion and Blackmail</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chen, David W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bauer, Frank</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Extortion and Blackmail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001005T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E4D81F3DF936A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="772" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Teacher Is Accused of Duping Boy to Make a Sexual Video</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID W. CHEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chen, David W</byline>
      <dateline>NEW ROCHELLE, N.Y., Oct. 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Westchester County, NY, authorities arrest Salesian High School teacher Frank Bauer on charges of extortion and use of child in sexual performance; Bauer allegedly posed as older woman on Internet who demanded that boy, student in school, make explicit home video of himself (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It seemed to be a risque online relationship between a high school boy and an older woman that had spiraled out of control. The woman demanded that the boy make a sexually explicit home video of himself, or else she would distribute images, doctored to show him engaged in sexual activities, to his classmates at Salesian High School here.</p>
        <p>After the student made the video, she forced him to make a second one. Desperate, he confided in Frank Bauer, his art teacher, a well-liked man who wears Disney ties and allows students to loosen their own ties in class at Salesian, an all-male Roman Catholic school.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It seemed to be a risque online relationship between a high school boy and an older woman that had spiraled out of control. The woman demanded that the boy make a sexually explicit home video of himself, or else she would distribute images, doctored to show him engaged in sexual activities, to his classmates at Salesian High School here.</p>
        <p>After the student made the video, she forced him to make a second one. Desperate, he confided in Frank Bauer, his art teacher, a well-liked man who wears Disney ties and allows students to loosen their own ties in class at Salesian, an all-male Roman Catholic school.</p>
        <p>But a few days ago, the teenager learned that the woman was not a woman, but Mr. Bauer posing as one behind an America Online screen name, the police said. Today, the Westchester County authorities arrested Mr. Bauer, 29, and charged him with extortion and use of a child in a sexual performance.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bauer, a Bronx resident, pleaded not guilty at his arraignment today in New Rochelle City Court, said Jeanine F. Pirro, the Westchester district attorney. If convicted, Mr. Bauer, who was immediately suspended, could be sentenced to up to 15 years in prison.</p>
        <p>And while Mr. Bauer's case was the latest in what seems almost a weekly roundup of Internet pedophile cases prosecuted by Mrs. Pirro's office, this one, she said, was particularly chilling because it involved a teacher and his student.</p>
        <p>''This case is the ultimate betrayal of trust,'' Mrs. Pirro said. ''It's very disturbing, it's very distressing, and it demonstrates that parents need to know what their children are doing.''</p>
        <p>Late today, Mr. Bauer was still jailed, with bail set at $50,000. No one answered the phone at his Bronx home, and it was not known whether he had hired a lawyer.</p>
        <p>But according to the district attorney's office, Mr. Bauer's scheme began in September 1999, when he posed as a woman online and got in touch with the student, exchanging e-mail and pictures with the boy, who was identified as a Westchester resident under 16 at that time.</p>
        <p>Investigators released few details about the chronology leading to the teacher's arrest. In November 1999, the teenager tried to end the online relationship. That was when the woman, actually Mr. Bauer, threatened to use a picture of the boy to create fake images of him engaged in sex unless he agreed to make an  explicit video, law enforcement officials said. The boy was told to leave the video under a trash can at the high school, they said. He complied.</p>
        <p>Later, the teenager was told to make four more videos of himself, all to be left under the same trash can. And while he did make a second one, he also confided in Mr. Bauer, who told the boy, according to Mrs. Pirro, that he would intervene and send an e-mail message to the woman.</p>
        <p>Eventually, the boy also told his parents what was happening, and he recently notified the New Rochelle Police Department. With the help of Mrs. Pirro's high-technology crimes bureau and America Online, the police traced the messages to Mr. Bauer.</p>
        <p>At the high school today, officials convened an assembly to inform the 450 students, who live in Westchester and the Bronx, of the arrest. A prayer was said. In addition, the Rev. John Nazzaro, the school's president and director, wrote a letter to parents, asking them to get in touch with the school if anything had gone on that had made their children ''uncomfortable in their relationship with Mr. Bauer.''</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, students expressed disbelief at the accusations against a popular teacher. They described Mr. Bauer as an avid fan of animated Disney movies, taking a class during the previous school year to see ''Fantasia 2000'' at New Roc City, New Rochelle's new entertainment complex. They said he had a passion for theater, plastering his classroom with Playbills and supervising students in school musicals like last year's ''You're a Good Man, Charlie Brown.''</p>
        <p>But above all, they said that Mr. Bauer, who wore ties decorated with characters like Mickey Mouse, was a good man who was much more approachable than other teachers.</p>
        <p>''He was a very cool guy,'' said a former student of Mr. Bauer's, a junior from the Bronx, who also knew Mr. Bauer as a neighbor. ''If you had a problem, you could talk to him, or have him talk to a teacher. He was different. That's why everyone liked him.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
