<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Unfinished Business in Ivory Coast</title>
    <meta content="28SAT3" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/28/opinion/28SAT3.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242436"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Ivory Coast</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Ivory Coast</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001028T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E2D71F31F93BA15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="338" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Unfinished Business in Ivory Coast</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial holds that political and religious tensions threaten to consume popular revolt that ousted military dictator in Ivory Coast; contends that for democracy to prevail, new presidential elections must be organized in which all important political leaders are free to participatea</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Political and religious tensions threaten to consume the popular revolt that ousted a military dictator in Ivory Coast earlier this week. For democracy to prevail, new presidential elections must quickly be organized in which all important political leaders are free to participate.</p>
        <p>Wednesday's Belgrade-style insurrection was sparked by Gen. Robert Guei's attempt to perpetuate himself in power by stealing this week's presidential election. Supporters of the front-runner in that election, Laurent Gbagbo, took to the streets, won the support of key army and police commanders and installed their man in the presidency.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Political and religious tensions threaten to consume the popular revolt that ousted a military dictator in Ivory Coast earlier this week. For democracy to prevail, new presidential elections must quickly be organized in which all important political leaders are free to participate.</p>
        <p>Wednesday's Belgrade-style insurrection was sparked by Gen. Robert Guei's attempt to perpetuate himself in power by stealing this week's presidential election. Supporters of the front-runner in that election, Laurent Gbagbo, took to the streets, won the support of key army and police commanders and installed their man in the presidency.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Gbagbo's claim to the presidency rests on an election whose flaws ran deeper than General Guei's attempted rigging of the final vote count. Some of Ivory Coast's leading political figures, including Alassane Ouattara, the most prominent representative of the country's 40 percent Muslim minority, were unfairly excluded from the ballot. Deadly clashes erupted Thursday between Gbagbo supporters and backers of Mr. Ouattara. Yesterday Mr. Gbagbo met with Mr. Ouattara, an encouraging step. But the new president wrongly resists international calls for a new presidential vote.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gbagbo should move quickly to restore peace. The national unity government he is forming must be broadly inclusive. Its first tasks must be calming ethnic and religious unrest, re-establishing civilian control over the armed forces and preparing for credible new democratic elections early next year. An impartial judiciary must ensure that no legitimate candidate is wrongfully excluded. There should also be international oversight of the campaigning and balloting.</p>
        <p>Under its autocratic founding president, Felix Houphouet-Boigny, Ivory Coast became one of Africa's rare economic success stories, with unusual ethnic and religious harmony. In the early 1990's it enjoyed a brief period of multiparty democracy. This week thousands of ordinary Ivoirians risked their lives to chase a dictator from power. Mr. Gbagbo should honor their bravery by completing the transition to democratic rule.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
