<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Playing Again, 2 Partners Find That Hearts Are Trump</title>
    <meta content="28CARD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Ideas/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242399"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BRIDGE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bridge (Card Game)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Truscott, Alan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cooper, Steve</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Munson, Kitty</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Crossword and Games/Bridge</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bridge (Card Game)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001028T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E4DD1F31F93BA15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="504" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Playing Again, 2 Partners Find That Hearts Are Trump</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Alan Truscott</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Truscott, Alan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>bridge: playing again, 2 partners find that hearts</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The world of tournament bridge can be considered an enormous club, in which members come and go, perhaps resuming acquaintance after a lapse of many years.</p>
        <p>Slightly more than a quarter of a century ago, Kitty Munson was the Novice Player of the Year in Boston, and had met Steve Cooper, who held the same title in New York. Since then she has been active on the tournament scene, winning many titles,  including one at world level: the 1989 Venice Cup in Perth, Australia. He gave up the game to concentrate on his career as a law professor.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The world of tournament bridge can be considered an enormous club, in which members come and go, perhaps resuming acquaintance after a lapse of many years.</p>
        <p>Slightly more than a quarter of a century ago, Kitty Munson was the Novice Player of the Year in Boston, and had met Steve Cooper, who held the same title in New York. Since then she has been active on the tournament scene, winning many titles,  including one at world level: the 1989 Venice Cup in Perth, Australia. He gave up the game to concentrate on his career as a law professor.</p>
        <p>Both have recently retired, and when he returned to the bridge scene this year they played together. They will be married tomorrow in East Hampton, N.Y., will live in Albuquerque, N.M., and will be active on the tournament circuit.</p>
        <p>At the Summer Nationals in Anaheim, Calif., in August, they finished second in the Mixed Team Championship with Steve and Betty Bloom of Duanesburg, N.Y., and Mel and Janet Colchamiro of Merrick, N.Y. They had some help from the diagramed deal, which featured an unusual bid.</p>
        <p>Munson's three-spade cue bid with the North hand is commoner for the responder, directly following an overcall. It means a strong desire to play three no-trump if partner has a stopper in the opponent's suit, and is usually based on a solid minor suit.</p>
        <p>Cooper could not provide the required stopper, and passed East's double. When his partner retreated to four diamonds he ventured four hearts. This suggested a strong five-card suit, since he would have presumably bid four hearts a round earlier holding six.</p>
        <p>South had now reached a game that was unbeatable after the normal lead of the spade queen, but he had a hurdle to surmount in the play. West led the spade queen and noted his partner's discouraging play of the deuce. He accordingly shifted to a low diamond, confident that his partner would ruff.</p>
        <p>But Cooper had also seen the spade deuce, and knew what was going on. He played low from the dummy, and East ruffed. The defense took a spade trick, but that was the end. South scored a spade ruff, drew trumps, and threw his club losers on dummy's diamonds, making his game.</p>
        <p>The game could have been defeated by an improbable opening lead in a minor suit. As it was, after the lead, no defense could succeed.</p>
        <p>After a shift to a low club, South can play low from dummy and score a ruff in a black suit. After a weird shift to the club king, South would have to win and lead a black suit to set up a ruff.</p>
        <p>BRIDGE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
