<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Devils Are Sloppy, But Rally 3 Times to Tie</title>
    <meta content="28DEVI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/28/sports/28DEVI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242504"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Jersey Devils</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Carolina Hurricanes</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nobles, Charlie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Carolina Hurricanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New Jersey Devils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001028T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E6DA1630F93BA15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="512" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Devils Are Sloppy, But Rally 3 Times to Tie</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLIE NOBLES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nobles, Charlie</byline>
      <dateline>RALEIGH, N.C., Oct. 27</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New Jersey Devils and Carolina Hurricanes skate to 3-3 tie (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Stanley Cup is proving heavy for the Devils this season, but the champions appear to be up to the challenge.</p>
        <p>''Everywhere we go you can see teams are ready for us,'' goalie Martin Brodeur said after the Devils played to a 3-3 tie with the Carolina Hurricanes tonight at the Entertainment and Sports Arena. ''Everybody wants to beat the champions.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Stanley Cup is proving heavy for the Devils this season, but the champions appear to be up to the challenge.</p>
        <p>''Everywhere we go you can see teams are ready for us,'' goalie Martin Brodeur said after the Devils played to a 3-3 tie with the Carolina Hurricanes tonight at the Entertainment and Sports Arena. ''Everybody wants to beat the champions.''</p>
        <p>But they have not been so obliging. The Devils, who play at Pittsburgh on Saturday, moved to 4-2-2 with tonight's tie and are on a modest 2-0-1 streak.</p>
        <p>''These guys were really fast and they came after us tonight,'' said Brodeur, who had 26 saves. ''We didn't play really smart, but we played well enough to get a point.''</p>
        <p>Each time the Hurricanes scored tonight, the Devils found a rejoinder.</p>
        <p>''We had some sloppiness out there  and we weren't in good position at times,'' defenseman Scott Stevens said. ''But I think it was a good tie for us because we won the third period.''</p>
        <p>Carolina scored first, and Stevens had an inadvertent foot in it. Center Josef Vasicek scored on a power play 6 minutes 18 seconds into the game. Vasicek controlled the puck deep on the right side, moved toward Brodeur and shot. The puck ricocheted off Stevens's foot and caught Brodeur off guard.</p>
        <p>Brodeur kept the game close by spearing a 15-foot laser by right wing Sami Kapanen near the midway point in the first period. Jeff O'Neill also had a long, open shot that Brodeur muffled.</p>
        <p>Outshot by 8-3 early in the game, the Devils began to pick up the offensive pace as the period wore on. And they tied the score at the 18-minute mark. Right wing Alexander Mogilny, set up by Patrik Elias, flicked a shot past goalie Arturs Irbe into the right corner of the net.</p>
        <p>Carolina regained the lead 2:32 into the second period, as left wing Bates Battaglia managed a crossing pass under defenseman Sascha Goc's stick and led center Ron Francis, who had a step on Ken Sutton. Francis scored from just outside the crease.</p>
        <p>Ever resilient, the Devils again tied the game. Left wing John Madden took a pass from Scott Gomez  and, while being jostled by two defenders and moving away from the net, scored his first goal.</p>
        <p>The Hurricanes regained the lead when a slick pass from center Rod Brind'Amour set up Shane Willis's score with 2:54 remaining in the period.</p>
        <p>The Devils produced an answer 5:39 into the third period. Elias and Randy McKay had a two-on-one against Irbe, and McKay held the puck long enough to force Irbe to slide to his left, then passed to Elias for the score.</p>
        <p>The goal was Elias's third of the season, and enough to salvage a tie for the Devils.</p>
        <p>SLAP SHOTS</p>
        <p>Devils center PETR SYKORA, tied for second on the team in scoring with 7 points, was scratched from Friday's game with a pulled groin. Left wing JAY PANDOLFO missed his fifth straight game with a bruised shoulder.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
