<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rangers Are No Match For Jagr and Penguins</title>
    <meta content="28RANG$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/28/sports/28RANG.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242513"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Rangers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pittsburgh Penguins</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Diamos, Jason</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Pittsburgh Penguins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001028T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE5DA1630F93BA15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="755" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rangers Are No Match For Jagr and Penguins</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JASON DIAMOS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Diamos, Jason</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pittsburgh Penguins defeat New York Rangers, 4-1; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The best hockey player in the world and the worst team money can buy collided at Madison Square Garden last night. The result was all too predictable.</p>
        <p>Jaromir Jagr collected a Gordie Howe hat trick -- a goal, an assist, and a fight -- to lead the Pittsburgh Penguins to a 4-1 victory over the swooning Rangers. The defeat was the Rangers' fourth straight and sixth in seven games; they are 1-4 at home.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The best hockey player in the world and the worst team money can buy collided at Madison Square Garden last night. The result was all too predictable.</p>
        <p>Jaromir Jagr collected a Gordie Howe hat trick -- a goal, an assist, and a fight -- to lead the Pittsburgh Penguins to a 4-1 victory over the swooning Rangers. The defeat was the Rangers' fourth straight and sixth in seven games; they are 1-4 at home.</p>
        <p>After nine games, this season is beginning to look a lot like last season -- and the two before that.</p>
        <p>That is because this season's Rangers are much like the last three versions, all of which missed the playoffs. The Rangers are old, slow, small and overpaid.</p>
        <p>Against a quick team like the Penguins and a player like Jagr, that can spell disaster, as it did last night.</p>
        <p>Ron Low, the Rangers' new coach, can switch his lines and his defensive pairings all he wants. It doesn't seem to matter.</p>
        <p>''It's hard for me to keep talking about positives when we're getting our rear ends nailed to the wall every night,'' Low said.</p>
        <p>Even Mark Messier is getting disgusted. He fought his longtime nemesis, Darius Kasparaitis, after elbowing him (Messier threw two punches, Kasparaitis none) at 4 minutes 37 seconds of the second period. It was already 3-0 for Pittsburgh.</p>
        <p>''There was just nowhere to turn, nowhere to hide out there,'' Messier said. ''You've got to make a stand at some point.''</p>
        <p>The Rangers have allowed the first goal five times this season and have lost all five games.</p>
        <p>Last night the rookie goaltender Johan Holmqvist was pressed into emergency service because Kirk McLean was experiencing back spasms. Mike Richter, who was in goal for Thursday's 3-0 loss in Philadelphia, has yet to be cleared to play on successive nights. So the Rangers recalled Holmqvist and Jean-Francois Labbe from Hartford of the American Hockey League.</p>
        <p>Jagr opened the scoring at 14:26 of the first period, victimizing the rookie defenseman Mike Mottau (playing his second National Hockey League game), then Holmqvist (making 29 saves in his N.H.L. debut).</p>
        <p>Jagr swooped down the right wing, deked past Mottau, then toyed with Holmqvist -- faking forehand, backhand, forehand -- before beating him with a backhand shot from just off the right post for his ninth goal.</p>
        <p>A little more than two minutes later, Jagr descended on Holmqvist again. This time, he came in on a breakaway. With Kim Johnsson chasing, Jagr crossed everyone up and left a drop pass for Martin Straka, who was being chased by Mike York. Straka batted in his own shot inside the crease at 16:44, his fourth goal of the season.</p>
        <p>Just before the period ended, a familiar face made it 3-0: Aleksei Kovalev, who lives for games against the Rangers. With the Penguins on a five-on-three advantage, Kovalev shook off Brian Leetch in the right circle, then beat Holmqvist -- who was screened by Johnsson -- to the stick side with a wrist shot from the slot.</p>
        <p>For the third time in five home games, the Rangers had fallen behind by 3-0.</p>
        <p>It stayed that way through a penalty-filled second period, in which Messier fought Kasparaitis and Jagr ''fought'' Rich Pilon. (Jagr punched at Pilon repeatedly, though never dropped his gloves, before turtling on the ice.)</p>
        <p>Messier cut the lead to 3-1 on a power play at 2:46 of the third period, scoring from a difficult angle off the right post on a rebound. It was Messier's fourth goal of the season and the Rangers' first goal in more than five periods.</p>
        <p>Jan Hrdina added Pittsburgh's fourth goal on a power play with 1:06 to play.</p>
        <p>SLAP SHOTS</p>
        <p>As he threatened to do after Thursday night's 3-0 loss in Philadelphia, Rangers Coach RON LOW broke up the Czech line. PETR NEDVED skated with JAN HLAVAC and THEO FLEURY. MARK MESSIER centered VALERY KAMENSKY and RADEK DVORAK. And MIKE YORK centered TIM TAYLOR (playing left wing) and MICHAL GROSEK. Low reunited the Czechs in the third period.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
