<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Subway Series Ride</title>
    <meta content="28SAT2" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/28/opinion/28SAT2.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242434"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001028T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E3D71F31F93BA15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="491" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Subway Series Ride</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial on New York Yankees defeating New York Mets in World Series; holds that rivalry between Mets and Yankees did not divide city, it united it</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Somehow, this World Series has seemed too short. It probably would have seemed too short to New Yorkers even if it had gone to seven games, each one of them as long as the record-breaking first game. But if it had to end, it could hardly have ended in a finer, more emblematic manner than the contest that took place on Thursday night between the Yankees' pitcher, Andy Pettitte, and the Mets' pitcher, Al Leiter, who seemed, until his final moments on the mound, to be growing stronger and stronger. All of the Yankees' usual heroes -- Bernie Williams, Paul O'Neill, Mariano Rivera and Derek Jeter, who was named M.V.P. -- made it possible for the unusual hero, Luis Sojo, to win Game 5, and with it the 26th World Series in the history of this remarkable team.</p>
        <p>Few of the fans and probably none of the players have made the pilgrimage directly from Yankee Stadium to Shea, or vice versa. But during this Series we all imagined making it: taking the 4 train to the 7 and out to Willets Point, or driving the Deegan to the Grand Central to 126th Street, or paddling down the Harlem River and along the East River and into Flushing Bay. The landscape of these two stadiums, and their teams, is what Carl Sandburg would have called big-shouldered, though perhaps that adjective should be reserved for some eventual October when the Cubs at last take on the White Sox.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Somehow, this World Series has seemed too short. It probably would have seemed too short to New Yorkers even if it had gone to seven games, each one of them as long as the record-breaking first game. But if it had to end, it could hardly have ended in a finer, more emblematic manner than the contest that took place on Thursday night between the Yankees' pitcher, Andy Pettitte, and the Mets' pitcher, Al Leiter, who seemed, until his final moments on the mound, to be growing stronger and stronger. All of the Yankees' usual heroes -- Bernie Williams, Paul O'Neill, Mariano Rivera and Derek Jeter, who was named M.V.P. -- made it possible for the unusual hero, Luis Sojo, to win Game 5, and with it the 26th World Series in the history of this remarkable team.</p>
        <p>Few of the fans and probably none of the players have made the pilgrimage directly from Yankee Stadium to Shea, or vice versa. But during this Series we all imagined making it: taking the 4 train to the 7 and out to Willets Point, or driving the Deegan to the Grand Central to 126th Street, or paddling down the Harlem River and along the East River and into Flushing Bay. The landscape of these two stadiums, and their teams, is what Carl Sandburg would have called big-shouldered, though perhaps that adjective should be reserved for some eventual October when the Cubs at last take on the White Sox.</p>
        <p>If you were alive and breathing this week, you got a glimpse of Gotham that is not often revealed, to strangers or to itself. The rivalry between the Mets and the Yankees did not divide the city. It united it. These breathless games, so much closer in score than in the final tally of games won and lost, drew fans of both teams into a single vortex. No matter how much they claim to differ from each other, it became clear this week just how much Mets and Yankees fans truly share. Who cares whether the rest of the country was watching or not? We were watching, and New York loves nothing better than watching itself.</p>
        <p>Everyone had ideas of how this Series should have worked out -- the Mets in 7, the Yankees in 4, a home-run battle, a defensive duel. But those ideas have all been replaced by what has actually happened, by 47 1/2 innings of impeccable baseball, marred only by one strange moment in the first inning of the second game. Somehow what actually happened is even better than what we imagined. That, perhaps, is one of the things that sports are really for, to replace daydreams with actuality and thereby to fuel new daydreams.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
