<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Two Flutists Explore the 20th-Century Repertory</title>
    <meta content="28FLUT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Ideas/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/28/arts/28FLUT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242395"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sequitur (Ensemble)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kozinn, Allan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stillman, Mimi</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Monson, Patti</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001028T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E0DE1F31F93BA15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="688" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Two Flutists Explore the 20th-Century Repertory</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALLAN KOZINN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kozinn, Allan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Allan Kozinn reviews Young Concert Artists performance by flutist Mimi Stillman at Weill Recital Hall, and flutist Patti Monson, performing with ensemble Sequitur at Merkin Concert Hall; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It has been a busy week for fans of contemporary flute music. At Weill Recital Hall on Monday, Young Concert Artists presented one of its recent audition winners, Mimi Stillman, in a program devoted mostly to 20th-century works. Ten blocks uptown, at Merkin Concert Hall on Tuesday evening, the new music ensemble Sequitur presented its flutist, Patti Monson, in a recital that largely duplicated the program of ''Conspirare,'' her just-released debut recording for CRI Records.</p>
        <p>Together, the concerts conveyed an impression of the breadth of the modern flute repertory, with Ms. Stillman offering a more conservative, melody-oriented view, and Ms. Monson pushing the edges of contemporary technique in works that asked the unaccompanied flutist to create the impression of performing in an ensemble.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It has been a busy week for fans of contemporary flute music. At Weill Recital Hall on Monday, Young Concert Artists presented one of its recent audition winners, Mimi Stillman, in a program devoted mostly to 20th-century works. Ten blocks uptown, at Merkin Concert Hall on Tuesday evening, the new music ensemble Sequitur presented its flutist, Patti Monson, in a recital that largely duplicated the program of ''Conspirare,'' her just-released debut recording for CRI Records.</p>
        <p>Together, the concerts conveyed an impression of the breadth of the modern flute repertory, with Ms. Stillman offering a more conservative, melody-oriented view, and Ms. Monson pushing the edges of contemporary technique in works that asked the unaccompanied flutist to create the impression of performing in an ensemble.</p>
        <p>Three of the pieces accomplished this by setting the flute against a recorded or computer-processed soundtrack. Mr. Reich's familiar ''Vermont Counterpoint'' (1982), for one, offered a consonant, chirpy, rhythmically interlocked backdrop flute and piccolo lines, against which Ms. Monson's live solo line danced, moving into the harmonies and around the rhythms. In Kaija Saariaho's ''NoaNoa'' (1992), elements of Ms. Monson's flute line took on lives of their own as they were processed by a computer. A trill, for example, would continue into an echoic haze, augmented by vocalizations (fragments from Gaugin's Tahitian travel diary) as the live flute line worked its way into an expansive, haunting melody. Mr. Bresnick's piece presents a thicker texture: both the recorded and live flute parts are built of fluttering lines, multiphonics (chordlike sounds) and distortions, but the dialogue between them has a forceful, dramatic quality, abetted by Mr. Bresnick's use of space as a compositional element.</p>
        <p>Other works used illusion to suggest an ensemble's breadth. Robert Dick's ''Afterlight'' is a study in controlled multiphonics, in which the over- and undertones had an almost chorale-like quality. Mr. Dick's ''Piece in the Gamelan Style'' (1978) used multiphonics as well but was mostly about color, with the gracefully bent line approximating that of an Asian wooden flute giving way for the harmonic thorniness of the modern Western style.</p>
        <p>In ''Rapidfire'' (1992) Jennifer Higdon used dynamics to suggest counterpoint between a sharp-edged melody and a burbling obbligato. And Harold Meltzer, in an amusing collection called ''Rumors,'' provided a dictionary of colorful effects, the most notable being the percussive and breathy sounds that animated ''Trapset'' (1999), for alto flute, and the illusion of an almost whispered duet in ''Bel Canto'' (2000), for bass flute.</p>
        <p>Ms. Monson seemed fully at ease with the demands these works made, but the most compelling aspect of her performance was the degree to which she let musicality take over. A listener noted her technique as a means, not an end.</p>
        <p>That was generally the case in Ms. Stillman's concert as well, although the only work that made unusual demands was Mason Bates's ''Elements.'' A picturesque suite commissioned for the occasion, the work's movements describe ''Earth,'' ''Water,'' ''Air'' and ''Fire,'' and if the colors and effects were often predictable (bent notes for ''Wind,'' a rippling piano accompaniment for ''Water'') they showed Ms. Stillman to be both technically agile and imaginative in her use of color.</p>
        <p>Mostly, Ms. Stillman's program demanded a more conventional kind of beauty, which she supplied amply, with Hugh Sung as a supportive piano accompanist. Erwin Shulhoff's Sonata (1923) let her put a lovely, rounded tone at the service of graceful melodies in a French Impressionistic style. Ms. Stillman drew on those qualities again in her own transcriptions of Faure, Ginastera and Debussy songs, and filtered them through a chromatic prism in an appealing account of Lowell Liebermann's Sonata (1987).</p>
        <p>She showed the livelier side of her technique and interpretive sensibilities in the one antiquity on the program, Bach's A minor Suite (BWV 1013) for unaccompanied flute, and a modern echo of Bach's style, Villa-Lobos's ''Bachianas Brasileiras'' No. 6 (1938), a duet for flute and bassoon in which Ms. Stillman's partner was Darryl Hartshorne.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
