<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Abroad at Home; Why It Matters</title>
    <meta content="28LEWI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/28/opinion/28LEWI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242468"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Third-Party Moves (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lewis, Anthony</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nader, Ralph</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Third-Party Moves (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001028T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E6DD1630F93BA15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="757" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Abroad at Home; Why It Matters</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY LEWIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lewis, Anthony</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anthony Lewis Op-Ed column disputes Ralph Nader's contention that there is no real difference between Al Gore and George W Bush; predicts that meaningful campaign finance reform would be put off indefinitely if Bush is elected (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If George W. Bush is elected, one probable result will be to put meaningful campaign finance reform off indefinitely. That is not only because Governor Bush is opposed to serious change in the system. It is because of the appointments he is likely to make to the Supreme Court, which has the last word on whether and how campaign spending can be limited.</p>
        <p>That reality poses a hard question for Ralph Nader and his supporters. Mr. Nader has quite rightly called for an end to the obscene race for money that now marks political campaigns in this country. Yet he tells his rallies that there is no real difference between Governor Bush and Al Gore, ignoring the profound impact a Bush-appointed Supreme Court would have on the chance for reform.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If George W. Bush is elected, one probable result will be to put meaningful campaign finance reform off indefinitely. That is not only because Governor Bush is opposed to serious change in the system. It is because of the appointments he is likely to make to the Supreme Court, which has the last word on whether and how campaign spending can be limited.</p>
        <p>That reality poses a hard question for Ralph Nader and his supporters. Mr. Nader has quite rightly called for an end to the obscene race for money that now marks political campaigns in this country. Yet he tells his rallies that there is no real difference between Governor Bush and Al Gore, ignoring the profound impact a Bush-appointed Supreme Court would have on the chance for reform.</p>
        <p>Campaign finance is one example, among many, of large issues on which a future Supreme Court could make a great difference -- and on which Mr. Nader has hypocritically ignored reality in saying that the two major candidates are the same. I say hypocritically because he is too smart not to know what he is doing.</p>
        <p>The environment is another telling example. Mr. Nader is the candidate of the Green Party, and his calls for protecting the environment mean a lot to his audiences.</p>
        <p>But conservative legal theory advanced by judicial appointees of Presidents Reagan and Bush is a forbidding obstacle to national environmental regulation. Some of those judges, in the Federal Courts of Appeals, have found regulations invalid either because Congress delegated rule-making power to administrative agencies -- which is the only way regulating gets done -- or because the rules went beyond federal power over interstate commerce.</p>
        <p>Campaign finance reform would be impossible if the views of Supreme Court Justices Antonin Scalia and Clarence Thomas -- whom Governor Bush has called his models -- prevailed. They wrote last January that any limits on either campaign spending or contributions violated the First Amendment's guarantee of free speech.</p>
        <p>I do not believe that there is only one possible answer to questions that are put to the Supreme Court. Justice William J. Brennan Jr. used to say that his colleagues, agreeing or disagreeing, had the same commitment to the Constitution that he did. The questions are hard, and the answers -- all in good faith -- are bound to differ.</p>
        <p>Nor do I believe that George W. Bush has fixed, extremist views on the law. He does not seem to have thought deeply about the kinds of questions that go into the appointment of Supreme Court justices. In Texas, judges are elected. Governor Bush has filled vacancies, however, and his appointees on the whole are respected judges, conservative but eschewing the extreme.</p>
        <p>But the realities of the Republican Party these days -- the highly conservative party it has become -- will severely limit a President George W. Bush's choices if and when Supreme Court vacancies arise. The right will expect nominees who reliably embrace its views.</p>
        <p>Governor Bush is surely aware of the bitterness on the right about one of his father's choices, Justice David Souter. In the primary campaign Steve Forbes, opposing Governor Bush, said, ''America simply cannot afford another Supreme Court justice like David Souter.''</p>
        <p>Abortion is the prime issue for the right. Mr. Bush has said he would not make it a litmus test that his nominees would overrule Roe v. Wade. But in practice that will surely be a consideration. A leading anti-abortion figure, Gary Bauer, said on NBC's ''Today'' show the other day that if Mr. Bush became president and had more than one vacancy to fill on the Supreme Court, it was likely that ''Roe v. Wade would be overturned.''</p>
        <p>All this makes Ralph Nader's performance cynical. He knows better than most people what a difference a Bush or Gore presidency could make in the Supreme Court. Yet he gives the impression, as a Wall Street Journal report put it, that ''he would be happy to cause a Gore defeat.'' And Mr. Nader is campaigning hard in states where his support could cost Mr. Gore the electoral vote. Yesterday he was in Iowa, a toss-up state.</p>
        <p>The fundamental domestic issue in this election, I believe, is the future of the Supreme Court. Policy on taxes and the like is transitory; it can be quickly changed. The justices may be there for decades.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
