<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On Each Side, Accusing Fingers Over Nasty Turn in Campaign</title>
    <meta content="28MESS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/28/politics/28MESS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242476"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: IN THE TRENCHES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marks, Peter</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001028T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE1DD1630F93BA15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1203" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On Each Side, Accusing Fingers Over Nasty Turn in Campaign</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER MARKS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Marks, Peter</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vice Pres Al Gore and Gov George W Bush campaigns accuse each other of using dirty advertising techniques to try to win election, including inflammatory telephone calls to voters and incendiary television spots; both sides had been keeping fairly tight lid on invective in close race; Republicans and Democrats are beginning to accentuate negative to mobilize their partisans and stir up as much doubt as possible about opposition among undecided voters (M)d</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>From inflammatory telephone calls to voters by allies of Vice President Al Gore, to incendiary new television spots by supporters of Gov. George W. Bush, the presidential race reached a new level of mean-spiritedness yesterday. And each side sought to portray the other as the one dragging the campaign into the mud.</p>
        <p>In Michigan, the state Democratic Party placed calls to thousands of voters, with recorded messages from two women relating stories of death and illness in Governor Bush's Texas. In Wisconsin and the Northwest, a Republican group planned to begin running commercials showing footage of Ralph Nader, the Green Party candidate, attacking Mr. Gore's environmental record.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>From inflammatory telephone calls to voters by allies of Vice President Al Gore, to incendiary new television spots by supporters of Gov. George W. Bush, the presidential race reached a new level of mean-spiritedness yesterday. And each side sought to portray the other as the one dragging the campaign into the mud.</p>
        <p>In Michigan, the state Democratic Party placed calls to thousands of voters, with recorded messages from two women relating stories of death and illness in Governor Bush's Texas. In Wisconsin and the Northwest, a Republican group planned to begin running commercials showing footage of Ralph Nader, the Green Party candidate, attacking Mr. Gore's environmental record.</p>
        <p>Both sides had been keeping a fairly tight lid on invective in this close, tense race, but now, it seems, the seal is coming apart. With just a week and a half until Election Day -- a time when competitive races often turn nasty -- Republicans and Democrats alike are beginning to accentuate the negative to mobilize their partisans and stir up as much doubt as possible about the opposition among undecided voters.</p>
        <p>Attack advertisements from outside groups are multiplying, and the automated phone campaigns are reported to be spreading to states like Florida, Illinois and Pennsylvania. One phone message, recorded for the Democrats by the actor Ed Asner, warns listeners that Mr. Bush's plans for reforming Social Security could threaten ''current benefits.''</p>
        <p>At the same time, the campaigns, aware that polls show voters increasingly disgusted with personal attacks, are becoming more aggressive in painting each other as the offending party.</p>
        <p>''They want the advantage of going on the attack without being blamed for negativity,'' said Darrell West, a political science professor at Brown University who studies campaign advertising. ''It's like two tarantulas in a bottle: you have to strike before you get hit yourself.''</p>
        <p>In one recorded call, a Texas woman, Ann Friday, implies that Mr. Bush's failure to improve nursing home care in Texas contributed to the death of her husband, who died ''from an illness that his nursing home attendants failed to notice.'' In another, a woman from Houston, Charlotte Cherry, says of Mr. Bush's ''terrible record on the environment'': ''Governor Bush has accepted $1.3 million from corporate polluters, and he's allowed them to keep polluting while my kids suffer.''</p>
        <p>Republicans denounced the Michigan messages as ''despicable,'' and Karen P. Hughes, the Bush campaign communications director, said of the Ann Friday message, ''It is wrong for Vice President Gore to try to use a tragedy involving an elderly woman for his own political purposes.''</p>
        <p>The Democrats countered that the spot by the Republican Leadership Council using Mr. Nader's words against Mr. Gore was the true low blow. In the advertisement, which begins running on Monday in Oregon, Washington and Wisconsin, states in which Mr. Nader has substantial support, a sound bite is played in which Mr. Nader says, ''Al Gore is suffering from election-year delusion if he thinks his record on the environment is anything to be proud of.''</p>
        <p>The Nader campaign did not think much of the commercial, either. ''The ad fails to mention that George W. Bush also has an abysmal environmental record,'' said Laura Jones, a Nader spokeswoman.</p>
        <p>The new moves came as criticism mounted of a Texas group backing Mr. Bush that began running an anti-Gore commercial yesterday modeled on the notorious ''Daisy'' spot that the Democrats ran against Barry Goldwater in 1964. The spot, which ran in small and medium-sized cities in swing states like Florida, Missouri and Ohio, shows a young  girl counting the petals of a flower and then switches to the countdown to a missile launching. Its message is that the United States is vulnerable to a nuclear attack from China because the Clinton administration traded away national security in return for campaign contributions.</p>
        <p>The commercial drew a furious condemnation by the Gore campaign. Senator Joseph I. Lieberman, the vice-presidential nominee, described the spot as ''the kind of sneak attack that we adopted legislation to stop, where moneyed interests come in at critical moments.''</p>
        <p>Even Mr. Bush's advisers distanced themselves from the commercial; Ms. Hughes called the spot an ''anonymous attack ad that is in no way associated with our campaign'' and the kind the governor would seek to have abolished.</p>
        <p>Ms. Hughes added that Karl Rove, Mr. Bush's chief strategist, called the group sponsoring the ''Daisy'' commercial, Aretino Industries, yesterday to ask that it be pulled.</p>
        <p>Carey Cramer, a political consultant and spokesman for Aretino, confirmed that the nonprofit organization had spoken to Mr. Rove and had agreed to take the commercial off the air. The obscure group, which Mr. Cramer has said was formed to produce commercials for this campaign, had raised $60,000 for the initial purchase of television time.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cramer said Aretino's members, whom he has declined to name, decided to withdraw the spot because ''they did not want to hurt the Bush campaign.'' He added that the news media's reporting on the spot was drowning out its message.</p>
        <p>Despite the modest size of the advertising ''buy,'' the Gore campaign went to great lengths yesterday to spread the word about the spot. In e-mail messages to reporters, the campaign identified Mr. Cramer as an executive of the Meridian Group, ''a consulting firm with ties to Newt Gingrich.'' The message continued,  ''Cramer is a follower of Machiavellian principles.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Cramer confirmed that Machiavelli, known for his assertion that the ends can justify the means, was a major influence for him, but he said he was not sure why that was relevant to a political commercial.</p>
        <p>The Republicans were equally engaged in drawing attention to the telephone calls by the Michigan Democratic Party. Sage Eastman, spokesman for Michigan's Republican Party, said the office was being flooded with calls from voters angry at receiving the messages.</p>
        <p>Democratic officials were unapologetic.</p>
        <p>''These are real people leaving a message that is not scary,'' said Jennifer Backus, a spokeswoman for the Democratic National Committee, adding that they follow the Democrats' established practice of questioning Mr. Bush's record.</p>
        <p>Ms. Cherry, whose voice is heard in the phone call warning about pollution in Texas, said in an interview yesterday that she taped her message for the Democrats on Wednesday, but that partisanship was not her motivation. A secretary who lives in Houston, Ms. Cherry said that she and her neighbors had long been trying to get Mr. Bush to address their concerns about emissions from chemical plants near her home.</p>
        <p>''After I did that message, I had a chill down my spine,'' she said. ''I probably made some people mad, but I can't help it. I'm not trying to destroy the man, I'm just saying he had a chance to do something positive and he didn't.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: IN THE TRENCHES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
