<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Michigan, a Swing State, Bush Picks Words Carefully</title>
    <meta content="Y28BUS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/28/politics/28BUSH.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242474"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE TEXAS GOVERNOR"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Pennsylvania</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Ohio</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Michigan</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dao, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Michigan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Ohio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Pennsylvania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Michigan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Pennsylvania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Ohio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001028T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E3DD1630F93BA15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="919" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Michigan, a Swing State, Bush Picks Words Carefully</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES DAO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dao, James</byline>
      <dateline>BENTON HARBOR, Mich., Oct. 27</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gov George W Bush has conveyed conservative ideas without using conservative buzzwords that might turn off centrist Democrats and independent voters as he barnstorms through Pennsylvania, Ohio and Michigan (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>At a private Christian high school in this conservative region of southwest Michigan, Gov. George W. Bush brought an overflow crowd of faithful Republicans to their feet today -- though he often sounded like a Democrat.</p>
        <p>''We're a nation that says that when somebody can't help themselves, we will as a government,'' he said in Kalamazoo. ''We're a nation that says any time anybody has to choose between food and medicine, that's not right.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>At a private Christian high school in this conservative region of southwest Michigan, Gov. George W. Bush brought an overflow crowd of faithful Republicans to their feet today -- though he often sounded like a Democrat.</p>
        <p>''We're a nation that says that when somebody can't help themselves, we will as a government,'' he said in Kalamazoo. ''We're a nation that says any time anybody has to choose between food and medicine, that's not right.''</p>
        <p>As he has barnstormed through Pennsylvania, Ohio and Michigan in recent days, Mr. Bush has succeeded in firing up huge rallies of dyed-in-the-wool Republicans, energetically conveying conservative ideas without using conservative buzzwords that might turn off the centrist Democrats and independent voters he also needs to win.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush has called for big tax cuts, but he has spent almost as much time strongly defending two Democratic programs, Social Security and Medicare. He has endorsed the idea of school vouchers, but talks much more passionately about helping low-income students. He has praised the work of anti-abortion organizations without uttering the word abortion.</p>
        <p>In part, Mr. Bush's ability to rally his conservative base has stemmed from the potent combination of his personal charm and his supporters' gnawing hunger to put a Republican in the White House after eight years of the Clinton administration. But it also comes from choosing his words carefully.</p>
        <p>Thus, though he supports vouchers, he does not use the word, talking instead about school choice for students ''trapped'' in bad schools. ''When we find failure, we can challenge failure by giving parents more choice and more options and better opportunities for every child,'' he said in Kalamazoo today, sparking an appreciative roar from the crowd of several thousand people packed into a sweltering gymnasium.</p>
        <p>Rather than mentioning abortion, which he opposes, Mr. Bush praises the work of crisis pregnancy centers, organizations typically staffed by abortion opponents, who counsel pregnant women against having the procedure.</p>
        <p>''These are places of deep compassion,'' Mr. Bush said in Kalamazoo, as the audience whooped its approval.</p>
        <p>And instead of condemning efforts by government officials to stop private groups like the Boy Scouts from barring gays from their ranks, he described the Scouts as the kind of civic-minded organization that government should help, instead of trying to regulate.</p>
        <p>''The role of government is to rally the armies of compassion which exist all across America,'' he said. ''We want you to be involved without our bureaucracies throttling your compassion and trying to change your mission.''</p>
        <p>Political scientists contend that Mr. Bush has little choice but to sidestep many of the contentious issues that divide Republicans from Democrats because the race is so close and he is competing in several states that have voted Democratic in recent years.</p>
        <p>In Pennsylvania, Mr. Bush's positions on abortion, gun control and school vouchers all play well in the conservative western end, where he campaigned yesterday. But they turn off many moderate Republicans and centrist Democrats, particularly women, in the suburbs outside Philadelphia. So he barely mentioned them, or mentioned them only obliquely, in his most recent visit on Thursday.</p>
        <p>''This is Bush's way of raising morality issues without going down a road that offends suburban Republican women,'' said G. Terry Madonna, a political scientist at Millersville University in Pennsylvania.</p>
        <p>And while the rural regions of southwestern Michigan, where he stumped today, would be very receptive to strong talk about restricting abortion and protecting the rights of gun owners, such positions would probably hurt him in the Detroit suburbs.</p>
        <p>''He's using coded words he thinks Republicans understand,'' said Michael Traugott, a professor of political science at the University of Michigan. ''But he doesn't want to be picked up on national television talking about abortion.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Bush's message has clearly been getting through to its intended audiences. At each of his stops in recent days, Mr. Bush has been drawing huge, enthusiastic audiences, usually of several thousand people. They have stamped their feet, waved little flags and stood in wild ovation for their candidate.</p>
        <p>''He doesn't have to talk about abortion,'' said Anna May Conelley, 65, who heard Mr. Bush in Kalamazoo. ''We know where he stands.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's ability to communicate his conservative message to conservative voters has also been greatly abetted by the work of independent groups that support him, like the National Right to Life Committee, the National Rifle Association and Americans for Tax Reform. All have financed commercials, mailings, Web sites and newsletters to their members, which have praised Mr. Bush's positions on the military, tax cuts, abortion or gun control.</p>
        <p>And today, his appearance at the private Kalamazoo Christian High School drove home his message that religious institutions, private organizations and civic groups are often better than the government at helping solve society's problems.</p>
        <p>''This great land must understand that our strength lies not in the halls of government,'' he told the high school audience. ''Our strength lie in the hearts and souls of our citizens.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush has also avoided directly attacking President Clinton, who won in both Pennsylvania and Michigan in 1996.</p>
        <p>But political analysts say his focus on religion, family, character and values this week seems an effort to draw a sharp moral contrast to both Mr. Clinton and his Democratic rival, Vice President Al Gore.</p>
        <p>''Conservative voters can be fickle,'' said Ed Sarpolus, an independent pollster based in Lansing. ''If they don't think he's talking to them, they won't turn out.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE TEXAS GOVERNOR</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
