<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lincoln Center Chief Dusts Off Welcome Mat</title>
    <meta content="28DAVI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Ideas/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/28/arts/28DAVI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242409"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Lincoln Center for the Performing Arts (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blumenthal, Ralph</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Davis, Gordon J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leventhal, Nathan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001028T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E7DB1F31F93BA15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1012" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lincoln Center Chief Dusts Off Welcome Mat</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RALPH BLUMENTHAL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Blumenthal, Ralph</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gordon J Davis is named president of Lincoln Center for the Performing Arts and will preside over its renovation, project which could take 10 years and cost $1.5 billion; he succeeds Nathan Leventhal, who is retiring after 17 years; Davis, citing his own childhood steeped in performing arts, says he wants to extend Lincoln Center's reach to more diverse audience; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''I can assure you I will not hit the ground running,'' said Gordon J. Davis, who was formally named yesterday as the next president of Lincoln Center for the Performing Arts. ''I will walk in and take careful steps.''</p>
        <p>It is not just caution growing out of his long experience in city government and law, or his 22 years of affiliation with Lincoln Center, the world's biggest and busiest arts complex. Rather, said Mr. Davis, 59, his 6-foot-5-inch form splayed in a chair in a borrowed office overlooking his domain, he remembered what it was like taking over as Mayor Edward I. Koch's first parks commissioner in 1978.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''I can assure you I will not hit the ground running,'' said Gordon J. Davis, who was formally named yesterday as the next president of Lincoln Center for the Performing Arts. ''I will walk in and take careful steps.''</p>
        <p>It is not just caution growing out of his long experience in city government and law, or his 22 years of affiliation with Lincoln Center, the world's biggest and busiest arts complex. Rather, said Mr. Davis, 59, his 6-foot-5-inch form splayed in a chair in a borrowed office overlooking his domain, he remembered what it was like taking over as Mayor Edward I. Koch's first parks commissioner in 1978.</p>
        <p>''I thought there was nothing I didn't know about my new job,' he said, ''till I got there.''</p>
        <p>So, he said, he would not even hazard a guess about where many of Lincoln Center's 13 constituent groups -- the New York Philharmonic and the New York City Ballet and City Opera, among them -- might relocate when work begins in earnest on a vast renovation of the arts campus, a project that could take 10 years and cost $1.5 billion.</p>
        <p>Some events, Mr. Davis said, might be staged at the new $115 million quarters being built at Columbus Circle for Jazz at Lincoln Center, of which he is the founding chairman. But even upon its scheduled completion in 2003, the jazz complex's three performance spaces -- of 1,300, 600 and 150 seats -- would be unable to accommodate large productions.</p>
        <p>''If they knew the answer, they wouldn't need me,'' he said, smiling and stirring artificial sweetener into a cup of coffee with the temple of his eyeglasses.</p>
        <p>But he does know, he said, that after taking over on Jan. 1, he wants to extend Lincoln Center's reach to new audiences. ''Black people and Hispanic people and a whole cross section,'' he said, citing the Brooklyn Academy of Music as a model of success in attracting a hip, diverse audience.</p>
        <p>His own interest in the arts, he said, was bred into him as a child growing up in a black neighborhood in Chicago near a university campus that fostered rich offerings of music, theater and poetry. He played the drums -- badly, he confessed -- and became enamored of jazz, gospel and opera, once cutting classes at Williams College in Massachusetts to see Leontyne Price perform in ''Don Giovanni'' at the old Metropolitan Opera House on West 39th Street before the company moved to Lincoln Center.</p>
        <p>Now, he said, he wants to do the same for other youngsters. As a real estate lawyer who helped bring the new Rose Center for Earth and Space to the American Museum of Natural History, he said, he carries away the vision of the planetarium ringed with dozens of yellow school buses and cherishes a similar vision for Lincoln Center.</p>
        <p>''I don't know, it may be this,'' he said, slapping a computer on the desk and speculating vaguely that the digital revolution might transform the performing arts in ways that would attract new audiences.</p>
        <p>He does not come, he said, with plans for new festivals and events. ''My judgment is, at the moment we're chock full of programming,'' he said. ''We have to maximize what exists.''</p>
        <p>He said he had no concerns about getting the sometimes fractious constituents to work together, taking as his model the cooperation that produced the mixed-use Samuel B. and David Rose building, Lincoln Center's administrative headquarters, for which he did much of the legal work.</p>
        <p>That Mr. Davis is no stranger to Lincoln Center was a big factor in its board's decision yesterday to accept its screening committee's recommendation and name him to succeed Nathan Leventhal, who is retiring as president next month after 17 years and who will join the board. The vote for Mr. Davis was ''enthusiastically unanimous,'' said a spokeswoman.</p>
        <p>Mr. Davis described the intertwining of his career with that of Mr. Leventhal as bizarre. They worked side by side at City Hall for Mayor John V. Lindsay, ended up working at the same law firm, were colleagues in the Koch administration and -- ''It gets worse,'' he said -- both ended up in the president's office at Lincoln Center.</p>
        <p>As parks commissioner, Mr. Davis served as an ex-officio member of the Lincoln Center board, and when he left public service in 1983, he joined the board as a member. He began leading what became Jazz at Lincoln Center in 1989, and under his leadership the jazz entity became, in 1996, the first new Lincoln Center constituent in a quarter-century.</p>
        <p>Wynton Marsalis, artistic director of Jazz at Lincoln Center, yesterday called Mr. Davis ''the backbone and the guiding vision'' of the group. ''He will be sorely missed, but he has provided us with the tools to continue in our development,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Rob Gibson, the jazz unit's executive producer and director, also voiced regret over Mr. Davis's departure but said, ''We're gaining a great friend as president.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Davis recalled that after he had spent a year as parks commissioner, Mayor Koch offered to name him chairman of the City Planning Commission, a job he coveted. But he decided to turn it down, he said, when he realized how attached he was to the parks. Similarly, he said, it crossed his mind to pass up the Lincoln Center presidency in favor of keeping the jazz chairmanship, but this time he felt he could tear himself away.</p>
        <p>Like the parks, he said, Lincoln Center erases traditional divisions among people and creates new coalitions of interests. ''Somehow barriers melt away,'' he said. ''The arts are a way to greater democracy, a way for human beings to have their humanity confirmed.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
