<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Religion Journal; With Texas Group's Proposal, Struggle Among Baptists Enters a New Phase</title>
    <meta content="28RELI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/28/national/28RELI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20001031T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242483"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Endorsements</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Political Action Committees</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Texas</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Baptist Churches</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Southern Baptist Convention</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">American Muslim Political Coordinating Council</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Niebuhr, Gustav</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Columns/Religion Journal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001028T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE6DC1630F93BA15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="867" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Religion Journal; With Texas Group's Proposal, Struggle Among Baptists Enters a New Phase</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GUSTAV NIEBUHR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Niebuhr, Gustav</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gustav Niebuhr column notes that 7,000 Texas Baptists are considering taking step toward financial separation from Southern Baptist Convention; also notes that Muslim political action committee affiliated with American Muslim Political Coordinating Council is endorsing Gov George W Bush for president (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A week ago, former President Jimmy Carter made the unexpected announcement that he was severing his lifelong ties to the Southern Baptist Convention. He would remain active in his church in Plains, Ga., he said, but he would no longer consider himself a member of the denomination itself, which he said had become ''increasingly rigid'' theologically under a conservative leadership.</p>
        <p>Mr. Carter made news nationwide, but another decision, to be made next week, could have a greater impact on the denomination, which has nearly 16 million members.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A week ago, former President Jimmy Carter made the unexpected announcement that he was severing his lifelong ties to the Southern Baptist Convention. He would remain active in his church in Plains, Ga., he said, but he would no longer consider himself a member of the denomination itself, which he said had become ''increasingly rigid'' theologically under a conservative leadership.</p>
        <p>Mr. Carter made news nationwide, but another decision, to be made next week, could have a greater impact on the denomination, which has nearly 16 million members.</p>
        <p>On Monday afternoon, as many as 7,000 Texas Baptists will gather in Corpus Christi for their statewide annual meeting, where they will decide whether to take a step toward financial separation from the denomination. The question before the Texas group, which tends to be more moderate than the denomination over all, will be whether to redirect $5.4 million in contributions from the Southern Baptists' national budget and give it instead to Baptist causes in Texas.</p>
        <p>Previously, most of that money was channeled to six Southern Baptist seminaries. But if a proposal by a special committee is approved at the meeting, the amount given to those seminaries would be cut sharply and the balance used to help three other seminaries in Texas, all run by Baptists, but none under the control of the denomination.</p>
        <p>There is another proposal, too, to redirect $1.1 million away from two of the denomination's agencies and use it to finance Spanish-language churches and other causes in Texas.</p>
        <p>On the surface, this may seem an in-house matter, but it signals a new stage in one of the most remarkable developments in recent  religious history: the fight among Southern Baptists for control of their denomination, the largest Protestant body in the nation.</p>
        <p>In 1979, a deeply conservative group won control of the denomination and began shifting seminaries, missionary boards and other agencies toward the right -- where the new leaders said most Baptists had always been.</p>
        <p>The leaders hold that Scripture is ''inerrant,'' literally true in all respects, and that the Bible forbids women to serve as pastors.</p>
        <p>For several years, a more theologically moderate faction struggled to reverse the tide, saying Baptist tradition did not permit anyone to tell another how to interpret Scripture or whom a congregation may hire as pastor.</p>
        <p>In annual meetings, the conservatives prevailed. But moderates never lost control of a few state conventions, as Baptist organizations are called, most notably the biggest one, the General Baptist Convention of Texas.</p>
        <p>In June, the rift between the two sides has deepened. Then, Southern Baptists, following their leaders' request, revised the denomination's statement of faith to include provisions supporting inerrancy and arguing against women as pastors. The document is important because seminary professors and Southern Baptist agency employees are expected to affirm it.</p>
        <p>Since then, some moderate congregations have left the denomination. Mr. Carter, in a letter announcing his decision, denounced the revised statement as a ''creed'' -- a word anathema to Baptists, who have prided themselves on not having a specific formula of faith.</p>
        <p>Given how long the division has existed, the proposals in Texas have generated sharply conflicting responses.</p>
        <p>The current issue of The Baptist Standard, the Texas Baptist newspaper, carries differing advertisements on facing pages, one appealing to Texas Baptists to continue giving money to denominational seminaries, the other supporting the proposal to redirect the money to the three seminaries in Texas.</p>
        <p>The Southern Baptist Convention's Internet site, in a section called ''Baptist2Baptist,'' carries an essay by R. Albert Mohler, a seminary president, denouncing the proposal on the seminaries as a ''propaganda effort'' to split Texas from the denomination.</p>
        <p>But David Currie, a rancher who is coordinator of Texas Baptist Committed, a group that supports the proposals, said they would help support new seminaries in Texas.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Currie also said, ''Obviously, there's been a dramatic change in 20 years in Baptist life. Many of us in Texas feel there's been a dramatic move away from traditional Baptist theology, far to the right.''</p>
        <p>Muslim Group Backs Bush</p>
        <p>Earlier this week, a Muslim political action committee, affiliated with the American Muslim Political Coordinating Council, which represents four Islamic organizations in the United States, said it was endorsing Gov. George W. Bush of Texas, the Republican presidential candidate.</p>
        <p>Coincidentally, that decision followed by less than a week the publication of a broad, though unscientific, survey of political opinion among American Muslims, a group that may number as many as six million. The survey, undertaken by the Council on American-Islamic Relations, an advocacy organization that belongs to the coordinating council, found Mr. Bush ahead of the pack.</p>
        <p>Forty percent of respondents favored Mr. Bush, while 25 percent supported Ralph Nader, the Green Party candidate, and 24 percent backed Vice President Al Gore, the Democratic candidate.</p>
        <p>The council said it had distributed its survey by hand, fax and e-mail ''to Muslim individuals and organizations nationwide,'' and received 1,022 responses.</p>
        <p>The council's spokesman, Ibrahim Hooper, said, ''I see it as an accurate poll of politically engaged Muslims in America.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  October 31, 2000, Tuesday  The Religion Journal column on Saturday, about efforts by some Texas Baptists to end contributions to the Southern Baptist Convention because of its conservative policies, misstated the name of the denomination's Texas organization. It is the Baptist General Convention of Texas, not the General Baptist Convention.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: October 31, 2000, Tuesday</p>
        <p>The Religion Journal column on Saturday, about efforts by some Texas Baptists to end contributions to the Southern Baptist Convention because of its conservative policies, misstated the name of the denomination's Texas organization. It is the Baptist General Convention of Texas, not the General Baptist Convention.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
