<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="28FSUM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242481"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001028T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CEFDD1630F93BA15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1170" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-7</p>
        <p>4 Die in Mideast Clashes On Arab 'Day of Rage'  Israeli soldiers fatally shot four Palestinians as violence flared across the West Bank and Gaza Strip after several days of relative calm. Several Arab organizations had declared it a ''day of rage.'' The casualties brought the death toll in the month of protests to at least 137, with all but 8 being Arabs.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>AIDS and Rural China  Doctors familiar with rural parts of Henan Province say small towns there are experiencing an AIDS epidemic. But Chinese officials deny there is AIDS in Henan. The local news media and government health workers are barred from discussing the issue, and outside researchers are blocked from studying it.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-7</p>
        <p>4 Die in Mideast Clashes On Arab 'Day of Rage'  Israeli soldiers fatally shot four Palestinians as violence flared across the West Bank and Gaza Strip after several days of relative calm. Several Arab organizations had declared it a ''day of rage.'' The casualties brought the death toll in the month of protests to at least 137, with all but 8 being Arabs.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>AIDS and Rural China  Doctors familiar with rural parts of Henan Province say small towns there are experiencing an AIDS epidemic. But Chinese officials deny there is AIDS in Henan. The local news media and government health workers are barred from discussing the issue, and outside researchers are blocked from studying it.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Talks in Ivory Coast  The new president, Laurent Gbagbo, and his opponents held meetings, suggesting a truce in the political crisis a day after tensions erupted in deadly clashes in the port city of Abidjan.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Diamond Shipments Resume  Industry executives and traders said Sierra Leone had resumed exporting diamonds, accompanied by certificates of origin, under a United Nations plan to stamp out a $700 million-a-year trade in illicit diamonds that has fueled conflicts in Angola, Congo and Sierra Leone.</p>
        <p>A7</p>
        <p>Arrests in 1985 Jet Bombing  Canadian authorities arrested and charged two Vancouver-area men in the deaths of 329 people aboard an Air-India flight that blew up near Ireland 15 years ago. The downing is considered to have been the deadliest act of sabotage in aviation history.</p>
        <p>A7</p>
        <p>Taiwan Nuclear Plant Dispute  President Chen Shui-bian halted construction of a nuclear plant that had been championed by the previous, Nationalist government and had come to symbolize the wide gulf between the Nationalists and the new president. Mr. Chen's decision enraged the Nationalist Party.</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A7</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A8-13, 16</p>
        <p>As Race Nears Final Phase, Charges of Mudslinging Fly  The Gore and Bush campaigns accused each other of using dirty advertising techniques to try to win the election, including inflammatory telephone calls to voters and incendiary television spots.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Republicans in Washington, Oregon and Wisconsin prepared to broadcast a television commercial featuring Ralph Nader criticizing Vice President Al Gore in a recent speech. Campaigning in Iowa last night, Mr. Nader assailed Mr. Gore as being ''unbelievably subservient'' to corporations.</p>
        <p>A13</p>
        <p>Clinton Being Kept in Check  The Gore campaign has told President Clinton to steer clear of closely contested states like Michigan and Pennsylvania to avoid alienating the swing voters who will play a crucial role in choosing his successor, Democratic officials said.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore returned to Pennsylvania to promote his economic plan, to shore up support among traditional Democrats and to convince undecided voters that his election would assure a prosperous future. Recent polls show his lead narrowing over Gov. George W. Bush in Pennsylvania.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>Bush Picking Words Carefully  Gov. George W. Bush continued a barnstorming tour through Pennsylvania, Ohio and Michigan, often sounding like a Democrat as he conveyed conservative ideas without using conservative buzzwords that might turn off the centrist Democrats and independent voters he needs to win.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's energy policy contains a proposal nearly identical to one of Vice President Al Gore's that Mr. Bush has ridiculed -- tax credits for homeowners who install solar power panels.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Senate Passes Spending Bill  The Senate approved a $37.7 billion spending bill for the Commerce, Justice and State Departments and the federal courts. President Clinton has said he will veto it because its lacks a broad amnesty for certain illegal immigrants.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Religion Journal</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-8</p>
        <p>A Raucous Last Debate In New York Senate Race  Representative Rick A. Lazio and Hillary Rodham Clinton engaged in a quarrelsome hour of bickering and badgering as they attacked each other's ethics, commitment to Israel and proposals for ways to improve the nation's education system.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>The New York Republican State Committee is conducting a telephone campaign attacking Mrs. Clinton's record on issues of importance to Jewish voters. One recipient of a call described it as push-polling -- a technique disavowed by reputable pollsters in which a caller claims to be doing a survey but asks loaded questions. Republican officials said they did not engage in push-polling.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Giuliani's War Chest  A strategist for Mayor Giuliani's disbanded Senate campaign said it would transfer ''hundreds of thousands of dollars'' to committees for state Republican candidates. But Mr. Giuliani still has about $3.5 million in the bank.</p>
        <p>B6</p>
        <p>Nassau Fiscal Plan Refused  The county executive, Thomas S. Gulotta, rejected the Legislature's four-year fiscal rescue plan, saying he could not accept its 15.4 percent property tax rise next year, but he would try for a compromise.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>Scientist Sought for School  Schools Chancellor Harold O. Levy has blocked William J. Stark, a veteran social studies teacher and administrator, from heading the Bronx High School of Science. Mr. Levy, a graduate of the school, was said to be seeking someone on the order of a Nobel Prize-winning scientist.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>ARTS &amp; IDEAS</p>
        <p>B11-20</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-10</p>
        <p>No Thanks, Mets Say  The Mets declined the mayor's invitation to join the parade on Monday celebrating the Yankees' victory over them in the Subway Series.</p>
        <p>D4</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-16</p>
        <p>Economy Slowed in Summer  The pace of economic activity slowed sharply in the summer quarter, the Commerce Department reported, as higher interest rates took their toll on growth. But the latest numbers suggested that the dip might be temporary.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Hackers Breach Microsoft  Unidentified intruders had access to Microsoft computers for about six weeks and were able to view some of the source code -- a programmer's basic instructions -- for a future software product, the company said. The culprits did not view or steal the source code for Windows and Office software, officials said.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Bargain Price for Publisher  Reed Elsevier and the Thomson Corporation are buying Harcourt General for $4.4 billion in cash and the assumption of $1.2 billion of debt, a lower-than-expected price for one of the largest acquisitions in publishing.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Shareholders Grip Gazprom  Shareholders in the world's biggest natural gas company voted in Moscow to tighten control over management.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>B9</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A14-15</p>
        <p>Editorials: A sharper warning on warming; the Subway Series ride; unfinished business in Ivory Coast; unfair car loans.  Columns: Anthony Lewis.</p>
        <p>Bridge</p>
        <p>B19  TV Listings</p>
        <p>B20  Crossword</p>
        <p>B18  Weather</p>
        <p>D10  Public Lives</p>
        <p>A8</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
