<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="28DIGE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242459"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001028T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E5DE1630F93BA15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1189" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Higher Interest Rates Slowed Economic Growth  The pace of economic activity slowed sharply in the third quarter, the Commerce Department reported, as higher interest rates took their toll on growth.</p>
        <p>But in these boom times, even a relatively modest increase in the nation's gross domestic product at a annual rate of 2.7 percent, is still healthy growth, and the numbers suggest that the dip might only be temporary. Government outlays dropped, particularly as census takers left the payroll, and retailers sold stockpiled merchandise. [Page A1.]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Higher Interest Rates Slowed Economic Growth  The pace of economic activity slowed sharply in the third quarter, the Commerce Department reported, as higher interest rates took their toll on growth.</p>
        <p>But in these boom times, even a relatively modest increase in the nation's gross domestic product at a annual rate of 2.7 percent, is still healthy growth, and the numbers suggest that the dip might only be temporary. Government outlays dropped, particularly as census takers left the payroll, and retailers sold stockpiled merchandise. [Page A1.]</p>
        <p>Hackers in Microsoft Computers  Unidentified intruders had access to Microsoft Corporation computers for about six weeks and were able to view some of the source code -- a programmer's basic instructions -- for a future software product, the company said. Speaking to reporters during a seminar in Stockholm, Steven A. Ballmer, the company's chief executive, said, ''It is clear that hackers did see some of our source code.'' Several people close to the investigation said the company believed that the intruders had taken advantage of vulnerabilities in the computer of an employee working from a remote location, possibly in his or her home. [A1.]</p>
        <p>Judge Thomas Penfield Jackson says he knows his rulings in the Microsoft antitrust case are controversial, but he has no regrets, even though, as he put it, ''virtually everything I did may be vulnerable on appeal.'' [C14.]</p>
        <p>Prudential Said to Plan Some Cuts  Three weeks after a shake-up of its top management, Prudential Securities is preparing to stop trading bonds for institutional clients and to lay off a few hundred traders and other employees, people close to the firm said. [C3.]</p>
        <p>Sanyo Replaces Refrigerator Parts  Sanyo Electric, one of Japan's largest home electronics manufacturers, said that it was providing replacement parts for 180,000 refrigerators because the doors might fall off. In its second announcement of a defective product in a week, Sanyo said it had received complaints from 104 people about the refrigerators, which were made between 1995 and 1996. All of the refrigerators were sold in Japan. [C2.]</p>
        <p>Dow Soars on Renewed Confidence  The Dow Jones industrial average rose 210.50 points, or 2 percent, to 10,590.62, as a government report showed a gentle slowdown in economic growth, which calmed fears of inflation and interest rate increases. Broader indicators were also higher. The Nasdaq composite index ended with a gain of 6.18 points, to 3,278.36, after moving in and out of positive territory during the day. The Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index increased 15.14 points, or 1.1 percent, to 1,379.58. [C3.]</p>
        <p>Jetta and Audi Sales Bolster VW Net  Volkswagen said third-quarter profit rose 50 percent because of the weakness of the euro and strong demand in the United States for Jetta sedans and Audi TT coupes. Net income increased to 984 million marks ($417.3 million) from 657 million marks ($278.7 million) in the period a year earlier. [C2.]</p>
        <p>I.B.M. Plans Chip Plant in Shanghai  I.B.M. plans to build a $300 million computer chip packaging plant in Shanghai in expectation of heavy demand in China. It said the new plant, part of a $5 billion global plan to expand its semiconductor business, would make advanced chip packaging, components on which chips are mounted for use in high-technology devices like digital phones and camcorders. The plant is scheduled to begin production in early 2002 with a work force of 1,800. [C3.]</p>
        <p>Slowdown in Production in Japan  Industrial production in Japan lost steam in September after reaching record levels the month before. The Ministry of International Trade and Industry said output fell 3.4 percent after a 3.3 percent rise in August. [C2.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
