<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lazio Shifts Campaign Focus to Women's Issues</title>
    <meta content="28LAZI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/28/politics/28LAZI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242512"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE SENATE CAMPAIGN: THE APPEAL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lazio, Rick A (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lazio, Patricia</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Archibold, Randal C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001028T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E5DA1630F93BA15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1098" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lazio Shifts Campaign Focus to Women's Issues</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RANDAL C. ARCHIBOLD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Archibold, Randal C</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Rep Rick A Lazio, his wife, Patricia, and other surrogates, take part in flurry of events focusing on women as polls show Hillary Rodham Clinton, his New York Senate rival, gains ground among women; Lazio has also begun running more television comercials presumably aimed at women, particularly white women; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As independent polls show Hillary Rodham Clinton gaining ground among women, her opponent, Rick A. Lazio -- and his wife and other surrogates -- have embarked on a flurry of events focusing on women, including breakfasts, luncheons and tours of breast cancer treatment centers.</p>
        <p>The pinnacle of this effort may come late next week, when Mr. Lazio is expected to march in Manhattan with hundreds of women in a show of support for his candidacy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As independent polls show Hillary Rodham Clinton gaining ground among women, her opponent, Rick A. Lazio -- and his wife and other surrogates -- have embarked on a flurry of events focusing on women, including breakfasts, luncheons and tours of breast cancer treatment centers.</p>
        <p>The pinnacle of this effort may come late next week, when Mr. Lazio is expected to march in Manhattan with hundreds of women in a show of support for his candidacy.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio has also begun running more television commercials that are presumably aimed at women, particularly white women, in the belief that women of color overwhelmingly vote Democratic and are therefore solidly in Mrs. Clinton's camp.</p>
        <p>With women about 52 percent of the electorate, gender has played a role throughout the campaign.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton had a lot of trouble early on with some blocs of female voters, like professionals, who reacted negatively to her decision to stay with her husband and who expressed complicated sentiments about her modern-day role as supportive wife.</p>
        <p>Her opponent early in the race, Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani, had an edge among white women. But more recent polls, including two this week, suggested that Mrs. Clinton was now ahead of Mr. Lazio among white women, with many still undecided.</p>
        <p>''Clinton was expected to be the candidate to mobilize the gender gap,'' said Kerri Andersen, a professor of political science at Syracuse University who has written on women and politics. ''That gender gap would work to her advantage because women tend to favor women candidates and Democratic candidates.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio lost some support among women after the first debate, on Sept. 13, when he approached Mrs. Clinton's lectern and, pointing and waving a piece of paper, demanded that she sign a a pledge on campaign financing, a stunt Mrs. Clinton's spokesman called ''menacing.'' Mr. Lazio also answered a question on Mrs. Clinton's role in the president's affair with an intern by suggesting that Mrs. Clinton's character and trust had been tarnished by her response to the accusations against her husband.</p>
        <p>Since then, a round of polls, including one on Thursday, has suggested that Mrs. Clinton's support among women is inching up.</p>
        <p>Mike Murphy, Mr. Lazio's chief strategist, said that whatever support Mrs. Clinton had received among women was soft and that there remained a sizable number who had not made up their minds. ''They are moving to us; we just want to move them quicker,'' Mr. Murphy said of the spate of events, including forums called Women for Lazio, which he said had been ''marvelous to get the message out.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio has also sought to rehabilitate his image. In the second debate, on Oct. 8, Mr. Lazio softened his demeanor and avoided delving into Mrs. Clinton's personal life, saying such questions should not play a role in the race. In their third and final debate yesterday, he once again showed a feisty side but avoided personal barbs, often preceding verbal jabs by saying ''with all due respect.</p>
        <p>In an advertisement released on Thursday, a woman is shown talking about Mr. Lazio to a friend in a suburban yard. ''Sure, he's a scrappy guy,'' the woman says, ''but, hey, that's New York. I like that.''</p>
        <p>In another advertisement released this week, Mr. Lazio is shown with his family at the kitchen table and other settings, like a classroom. At one point his wife, Patricia, appears and says, ''I'm not asking you to vote for Rick because he's a good father and husband. I just want you to know that you can count on Rick to always do what's right for New York.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Andersen said that with the homey images the Lazio campaign was ''playing to the same sort of feelings Gore evoked with the kiss at the convention, the good family man.''</p>
        <p>But he added, ''Research, as far as I'm familiar with, shows women voters are not any more swayed than men by these things.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Andersen said references to certain issues, like health care and education, had proved effective.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Lazio, normally reticent, is venturing out onto the campaign trail more and more, to tour breast cancer treatment centers, speak at party dinners and appear in ads. She sometimes appears with Libby Pataki, the wife of Gov. George E. Pataki, and has had one event with Mr. Pataki's mother, Margaret.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio has stacked his schedule in recent weeks with events related to issues that appeal to women, including several highlighting his record on health care and a string of town-hall-style school visits.</p>
        <p>He has toured breast cancer treatment centers, marveling at the latest machines and sometimes chatting with patients.</p>
        <p>In Amsterdam, N.Y., on Monday, after touring a private clinic, Mr. Lazio stood before half a dozen people in the waiting room and talked about his accomplishments on the issue, including co-sponsoring a bill that helps poor women finance treatment of breast and cervical cancer. President Clinton signed the measure into law this week.</p>
        <p>In New Rochelle on Tuesday, he stood in front of a poster promoting breast and cervical cancer treatment for a news conference before touring the Sound Shore Medical Center, a hospital outpatient center.</p>
        <p>On the same day he appeared at one of the five Women for Lazio forums, allowing cameras to capture Mr. Lazio speaking before several hundred women and answering questions, which had been submitted by the women in advance and chosen by a moderator.</p>
        <p>The first three forums were held this week in Albany, Syracuse and Buffalo. The last is scheduled for Tuesday in Rochester.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Lazio appeared with her husband yesterday at a Women for Lazio event at the Sheraton New York in Midtown.</p>
        <p>How much ground Mr. Lazio is gaining is a matter of debate. Most of the women at these events appear to be Republicans already committed to him.</p>
        <p>''In some ways I have some respect for Mrs. Clinton,'' said Sarah J. Oliver, a sales manager who attended the Women for Lazio event in Syracuse, ''but I don't think she can have a greater grasp of New York issues than Rick Lazio.''</p>
        <p>THE SENATE CAMPAIGN: THE APPEAL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
