<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Marceau, Stuck Inside a Hat, Says, '  '</title>
    <meta content="28BOWL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Ideas/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/28/arts/28BOWL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242396"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nouvelle Compagnie de Mimodrame Marcel Marceau, La</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dewitt, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marceau, Marcel</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Bowler Hat, The (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001028T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E0DE1F31F93BA15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="758" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Marceau, Stuck Inside a Hat, Says, '  '</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID DeWITT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dewitt, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>David DeWitt reviews play in mime, The Bowler Hat, featuring Marcel Marceau with La Nouvelle Compagnie de Mimodrame Marcel Marceau, presented at Kaye Playhouse at Hunter College, Joseph A LoSchiavo, executive and artistic director; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There's pleasure in any show that depicts a panorama of gentleman's hats advancing ominously across a lovely blue sky. The image -- ridiculous, loaded and acutely entertaining -- is one of the climactic joys of ''The Bowler Hat,'' which completes its United States premiere run tomorrow at the Kaye Playhouse.</p>
        <p>Did I mention that the show's star is Marcel Marceau? It is, and at 77 Mr. Marceau remains a legendary, charming presence. But he is far from the only appeal of this drama in mime, performed by members of his Paris company, la Nouvelle Compagnie de Mimodrame Marcel Marceau.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There's pleasure in any show that depicts a panorama of gentleman's hats advancing ominously across a lovely blue sky. The image -- ridiculous, loaded and acutely entertaining -- is one of the climactic joys of ''The Bowler Hat,'' which completes its United States premiere run tomorrow at the Kaye Playhouse.</p>
        <p>Did I mention that the show's star is Marcel Marceau? It is, and at 77 Mr. Marceau remains a legendary, charming presence. But he is far from the only appeal of this drama in mime, performed by members of his Paris company, la Nouvelle Compagnie de Mimodrame Marcel Marceau.</p>
        <p>''The Bowler Hat'' doesn't involve Bip, Mr. Marceau's familiar, befuddled character with face painted in clown white. Here his makeup suggests the exaggerated humanity of comic melodrama, just one of the theatrical styles in this ensemble performance that mixes commedia dell'arte, surrealism, farce, dance, shadow shows and allegorical pathos.</p>
        <p>The central character, the program tells us, is Jonathan Bowler, a civil servant living in London between the world wars. His appearance -- with, yes, a bowler hat -- recalls Charlie Chaplin's Tramp.</p>
        <p>Jonathan lives a life of modest rituals -- he wakes, he has tea, he goes to work -- until he is bowled over by love. He flips for the barmaid at his regular pub. Jonathan hopes that changing fashions will help him get the girl, so he trades his respectable hat for a more romantic wide-brimmed version with a splash of red.</p>
        <p>But in a life measured in teaspoons, should Jonathan dare disturb the universe? His bowler becomes attached to his head. He can't remove it, not to adhere to his professional dress code nor to finesse polite society. He is mortified when he cannot tip his hat to show respect for a funeral procession.</p>
        <p>After a series of comic misadventures to remove his hat, Jonathan has it surgically detached, making him a celebrity across London. But identities cannot be shed so easily; his hat begins to grow. It shows up at parties. It multiplies itself. It fills the sky.</p>
        <p>The conceit sounds markedly similar to that of Mr. Marceau's ''Overcoat,'' another ensemble mime drama that had a New York run in 1995. In that show Mr. Marceau is menaced by a beloved fur coat that becomes an animated, gigantic threat. In ''The Bowler Hat'' Jacques Noel's costume and scenic design suggests a world increasingly inspired by Salvador Dali, in which familiar charms are bent by a playful absurdity.</p>
        <p>The beleaguered Jonathan, driven by his protean hat, does not escape his fate. With arms outstretched and head thrown back, he falls into the waiting body of a destiny figure  whose dress and theme music recall Mozart's ''Don Giovanni.'' It is an emotionally textured conclusion for a broadly theatrical play.</p>
        <p>Mr. Marceau still performs with a whole-bodied sense of completion for each flourish. Yet his Jonathan has less snap than soul, a sweet, confused yearning that centers a production that looks to its 12-mime supporting cast for more inventive physical effects.</p>
        <p>These cast members, noticeably younger than their mentor, take to their many roles with creative gusto. A series of scenes in an amusement park offer the mimes chances to portray roller-coaster riders, mechanical puppets and fun-house mirror images, among other treats for the audience, and Mr. Marceau seems at ease in letting his colleagues shine.</p>
        <p>The master will have his own chance to shine from Tuesday through Nov. 12, when he will present Bip and other characters in short solo performances, also at the Kaye Playhouse.</p>
        <p>THE BOWLER HAT</p>
        <p>Featuring Marcel Marceau with La Nouvelle Compagnie de Mimodrame Marcel Marceau. Lighting by Didier Girard; sound by Philippe Lacroix; costumes and sets by Jacques Noel; music by Isabelle Serrand; stage director, Jacques Deliot. Presented by the Kaye Playhouse, at Hunter College, Joseph A. LoSchiavo, executive and artistic director, and Micocci Productions, L.L.C., in association with the Marcel Marceau Foundation for the Advancement of the Art of Mime Inc. At the Kaye Playhouse, 68th Street between Park and Lexington Avenues.</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
