<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Speech, Bush Says It's Time for Leader Who Will Do the People's Business</title>
    <meta content="Y28BTE$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/28/politics/28BTEX.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242451"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Knoxville (Tenn)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Text</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Tennessee</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Tennessee</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Tennessee/Knoxville</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Tennessee</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001028T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E3DF1630F93BA15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="2362" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Speech, Bush Says It's Time for Leader Who Will Do the People's Business</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Excerpts from Gov George W Bush speech in Knoxville, Tenn (M)h</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Following are excerpts from a speech that Gov. George W. Bush delivered at a school in Knoxville, Tenn., on Tuesday as recorded by The New York Times:</p>
        <p>I know this is going to be a close election, and one of the reasons I come is not only to ask for your vote but to ask for your help. During the next two weeks -- I know you vote early here in Tennessee. So do we in Texas. Sometimes we vote early and sometimes we vote often. I just want to make sure those folks voting often are for us. But turn out the folks. Don't be afraid to turn to those independent-minded voters or some of those open-minded Democrats, because you know what? Like us, they know we can do better in Washington, D.C.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Following are excerpts from a speech that Gov. George W. Bush delivered at a school in Knoxville, Tenn., on Tuesday as recorded by The New York Times:</p>
        <p>I know this is going to be a close election, and one of the reasons I come is not only to ask for your vote but to ask for your help. During the next two weeks -- I know you vote early here in Tennessee. So do we in Texas. Sometimes we vote early and sometimes we vote often. I just want to make sure those folks voting often are for us. But turn out the folks. Don't be afraid to turn to those independent-minded voters or some of those open-minded Democrats, because you know what? Like us, they know we can do better in Washington, D.C.</p>
        <p>It doesn't have to be that way in Washington where you're pitting one group of people against another, where there's finger pointing and name-calling and bitterness. No, Washington doesn't have to be that way. You see, this country can have a fresh start after a season of cynicism. We can lift this nation's spirit, and we can focus on doing what's right for the people of this country. We can do what's right for America.</p>
        <p>There's a lot of talk about the so-called projected surplus. Let me tell you about the surplus. Let me tell you about it. First of all, it is going to exist not because of the ingenuity and the hard work of the federal government. It exists because of the ingenuity and the hard work of the people of America. That's why the surplus exists. And that money -- if you listen to my opponent, he lost some of the lessons he learned here in Tennessee, evidently -- because that money is not the government's money, Mr. Vice President. That money is the people's money. And that is one of the big differences in this campaign, and that's what you've got to tell our fellow independents and Democrats.</p>
        <p>This is a man who trusts government, and we trust the people. He trusts the federal government, and I trust the people with your own money to make your own decisions for your family. It's a fundamental difference of opinion, and it's one of the reasons why, when the people go to vote, when we get them out to vote, they're going to come our way on Nov. 7.</p>
        <p>Here's what I think we ought to do with the surplus. First I'm going to tell you what we ought not to do with the surplus -- spend it all and more. Listen, I'm running against a man who's going to define the history books about big spending. He's going to be the biggest spender, if he gets elected, in history. He'll be three times bigger than that which President Clinton proposed. His budget proposals, truthfully, are bigger than those of Walter Mondale and Michael Dukakis combined. Now that's saying something, folks. That's a man who trusts Washington. It's a man who wants Washington to have the power over our lives. That's not the way Tennessee thinks, and that's not the way America thinks either. So here's what we ought to do.</p>
        <p>We ought to take half of that surplus and set it aside for one purpose: Social Security. We need to be able to say to seniors loud and clear, a promise that this country has made will be a promise that this country will keep. Our seniors are going to get their Social Security checks, and we're not going to let the other side scare them. They're running ads that are trying to scare the seniors, and that's old-style politics. Not this time and not this year. This is the year we're going to say to the seniors: You can trust us. We're going to do what we say we're going to do. . . . We need to let younger workers take some of their own money and put it in the private market to get a better rate of return on their investment dollars.</p>
        <p>But they don't want you to do that in Washington. Because they want the government making decisions for everybody. See, I trust people. I want you to have your own assets to call your own, assets you can pass on from one generation to the next, assets that are real assets, not i.o.u.'s. And assets that will get a better rate of return on your money than the paltry 2 percent the federal government is getting on your behalf. No, it's time for new thinking in Washington, D.C., to make sure we save Social Security.</p>
        <p>There's some important projects. There's some important things we've got to do with some of that surplus. About a quarter of the surplus needs to go for important priorities. One of them is to rebuild our military to keep the peace. I want to tell the moms and dads and grandparents here that Dick Cheney and I will do what it takes to keep the peace. But I want a strong hand. I want a strong hand when it comes to keeping the peace.</p>
        <p>Now you've heard the debates about how our military is the strongest in the world. It is. But the role of a leader is to anticipate. The role of a leader is to be looking down the road and when you see warning signals, do something about it. I worry about the captains leaving our ranks. I worry about the fact that a recent survey showed that a lot of personnel in the military are not going to re-up. I worry about our military trying to be too many things to too many people around the world.</p>
        <p>Not only are we going to restore morale by paying our women and men in uniform more money, and house them better, and make sure they're better trained and better equipped. You're going to have a commander in chief who respects the men and women in uniform and a commander in chief who in turn earns the respect of the men and women in uniform.</p>
        <p>Education will be a priority, but I assure you I don't want to be the federal superintendent of schools. I believe in local control of schools. I believe we ought to trust parents and teachers and principals to make the right decisions. The people who care more about the children in Knoxville, Tenn., are the citizens of Knoxville, Tenn.</p>
        <p>My view of compassionate conservatism says any time we find somebody who cannot help themselves, we will. We're a compassionate nation. People should not go without in America. One of the big concerns in our society today is the fact that some of our seniors are having to choose between prescription drugs and food. And that's not right. That's not our vision for America.</p>
        <p>So I've got a plan that says we're going to spend the money necessary to modernize and strengthen Medicare. We're going to have a Medicare system that includes prescription drugs for all. We'll give seniors the choices they need, if they want to have a different plan. We're going to have an immediate helping hand for seniors. That means drugs and money for prescription drugs for poor and moderate-income seniors. This is going to require a leader who brings people together, someone who does not use Medicare as a political issue but someone who sees it as an important priority for our nation.</p>
        <p>Now I know you've heard the debate and all the numbers and all the language, but one thing is for certain that they cannot escape. In 1992 they went around the country saying 'we're going to do something about Medicare and prescription drugs.' In 1996, if you think about the echoes from the past, they said the same thing. And here we are now four years later, and they're still saying the same thing. Here's our answer, Mr. Vice President. You had your chance. You have not led, and we will.</p>
        <p>It's time for new leadership in Washington. It's time to get somebody up there to get the people's business done. It's time to send power out of Washington for our schools, save and strengthen Social Security, do something once and for all on Medicare, do something about the military so we can make the world more peaceful, keep our promises to our veterans. But let me tell you what else we have an opportunity to do. We have an opportunity to, once we fund our priorities, remember whose money the surplus is, and send some of it back to the people who pay the bills.</p>
        <p>They've been telling me all along during the campaign -- the pundits -- the pundits have been saying, you know, that people don't want tax relief. The polls say they don't want tax relief. You know what my answer is? I really don't care what the polls say. I'm standing before you because I do what I think is right. And what I think is right, what I think is right, is to hear the voices of those who work hard to make a living.</p>
        <p>I want to tell you the facts: people pay more in federal, state and local taxes than they do for food, clothing and housing combined. Now you think about that load on the people who work for a living. The pundits may not think people want tax reform, but I hear they do all across the country. I hear they do all across the country. We're going to use this moment now in American history, seize this moment, to make our tax code more fair and to give people some of their own money back.</p>
        <p>The death tax is unfair. It's unfair to Tennessee farmers, it's unfair to small-business people, and we need to get rid of the death tax. The marriage penalty is unfair; what kind of tax code is it that says if you get married, you'll pay more in taxes than if you're single? It's a bad tax. It's a bad tax.</p>
        <p>We're going to drop the top rate to 33 percent for two reasons: one, there ought to be a principle involved. The federal government should take no more than a third of anybody's income. But two, I understand how capitalism works. The role of the federal government is not to create wealth but an environment in which entrepreneurs flourish, in which small businesses can grow to become big businesses. Our economy is strong today not because of Al Gore, I might add, our economy is strong today because we're a land of dreamers and doers, but also because of the tax cuts, Ronald Reagan's tax cuts in the 80's.</p>
        <p>We need an insurance policy against an economic downturn by giving people some of their own money back, and I want you to remind our friends who haven't made up their minds yet, that people are paying more as a result of failed leadership in Washington. Those gasoline prices are going up. You know why? There's been no energy plan. They're going up and so are the heating bills, the heating oil bills, up in the Northeast. There's no energy plan. Their own energy secretary got caught, if I might use a Texas phrase, sleeping at the switch. They were caught unaware. We're more dependent than ever before. I think Americans ought to be asking, where's all the capital we earned overseas after defending some of our OPEC nation friends? Where are they?</p>
        <p>They're pulling 30 million barrels out of what they call the Strategic Petroleum Reserve. Sounds like they're using that as the Strategic Political Reserve. They're trying to cover up the fact that they've had a failed energy policy.</p>
        <p>No, our people need tax relief. And therefore, we're going to cut the taxes not on a few, but on everybody who pays taxes. We're going to drop the bottom rate from 15 percent to 10 percent and increase the child credit from $500 to $1,000 per child and here's why. I want you to hear why and tell your friends this. This tax code we have today is unfair for people at the bottom end of the economic ladder. If you're a single mother in Tennessee, trying to raise two children and making $22,000 a year, one, you're working the hardest job in this state. That's the toughest job. And two, for every additional dollar she earns above the $22,000, because of this tax code, justified by the agents of the status quo in Washington, D.C., she pays a higher marginal rate on that dollar than someone making $200,000 a year.</p>
        <p>In fact, this nation has put a toll booth right square in the middle of the road to the middle class. If you stand on one side of the toll booth, you pay the rates we've been telling you, and the other side, for those struggling to get ahead, for those working their heart out to put food on the table, you pay a higher marginal rate. And that's not right, folks. You're looking at a man who hears the voices of the entrepreneurs, but our plan also addresses the inequities of the system that hurts the hard-working people at the bottom of the economic ladder.</p>
        <p>It's time to knock down that toll booth on the road to the middle class. I've heard all the talk about rich people versus poor people. That's class warfare that Mr. Gore likes to put onto people. That's not how you lead. That's not what this nation needs. This nation needs somebody to bring us together. This nation needs a healer, not a divider. This nation needs somebody, somebody, who's going to stop the bickering and fighting and name-calling in Washington, D.C. . . .</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
