<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mets Tell the Mayor: We'll Sit This One Out</title>
    <meta content="28SHEA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/28/sports/28SHEA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242488"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL: SUBWAY SERIES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parades</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hermoso, Rafael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parades</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001028T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E7DB1630F93BA15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="835" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mets Tell the Mayor: We'll Sit This One Out</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RAFAEL HERMOSO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hermoso, Rafael</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Mets decide not to participate in ticker-tape parade after losing World Series to New York Yankees; players and manager say they do not want to detract from Yankees' victory but were pleased to be invited (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Any chance for a two-team, ticker-tape parade up Lower Broadway ended yesterday when the Mets essentially told the city, Thanks but no thanks. So the Yankees, who won the first Subway Series in 44 years on Thursday, will have the celebration to themselves on Monday.</p>
        <p>General Manager Steve Phillips of the Mets called Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani's offer of a dual celebration ''a wonderful gesture'' but said the Yankees ''deserve the stage themselves.'' Rather than a parade, Phillips said the city would recognize the Mets at City Hall in the future.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Any chance for a two-team, ticker-tape parade up Lower Broadway ended yesterday when the Mets essentially told the city, Thanks but no thanks. So the Yankees, who won the first Subway Series in 44 years on Thursday, will have the celebration to themselves on Monday.</p>
        <p>General Manager Steve Phillips of the Mets called Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani's offer of a dual celebration ''a wonderful gesture'' but said the Yankees ''deserve the stage themselves.'' Rather than a parade, Phillips said the city would recognize the Mets at City Hall in the future.</p>
        <p>Nobody in the Mets' clubhouse yesterday was in the mood to celebrate after losing Game 5 of the World Series, 4-2, Thursday. Some lockers, like Mike Hampton's, were already emptied and the name plates removed.</p>
        <p>Not that a dual parade was ever on the minds of the Mets' players. Most of them planned to leave town by Monday.</p>
        <p>''We appreciate the ideal thoughts, but some team has to lose, and when you have the Subway Series, some New York team is going to lose and some New York team is going to win,'' Mets outfielder Darryl Hamilton said. ''When you win, you should have all the glory. You're happy they're thinking about you, but how are you going to get excited about sitting on a car, waving to fans, after you just lost the World Series? I think it was a gesture they knew we were going to say no to.''</p>
        <p>Manager Bobby Valentine of the Mets did not want to detract from the Yankees' celebration and said his players ''felt that the mayor making us go there is rubbing it in our face.''</p>
        <p>The mayor, who is an unabashed Yankees fan, appeared in the Mets' clubhouse after Thursday's game clad in Yankees attire, offering his congratulations. Valentine is all for free expression and does not mind the mayor showing his colors, but he added that he thought the gesture was out of place.</p>
        <p>''It struck me as odd,'' Valentine said. ''I didn't think that it was necessary.''</p>
        <p>Instead, the Mets will begin working on their future. They have eight potential free agents, and the contracts of both Valentine and Phillips are about to expire. But catcher Mike Piazza, Todd Zeile, Edgardo Alfonzo, Robin Ventura, Al Leiter and the closer Armando Benitez are each signed through at least 2002. As for the outfield, Benny Agbayani, Jay Payton and Timo Perez are young and inexpensive players.</p>
        <p>''We have some important decisions to make this off-season,'' Phillips said. ''No matter where those go, the core of this team will remain. It's made of the right stuff.''</p>
        <p>Phillips refused to characterize his interest in Alex Rodriguez, the Seattle Mariners' All-Star shortstop, who has said he is fond of New York but will test free agency.</p>
        <p>Phillips also said the Mets did not necessarily need to improve their offense. Concerning their shortstop situation, he noted that the Mets have Rey Ordonez, who broke his forearm in late May and was lost for the season, under contract for three more years. Mike Bordick, who replaced Ordonez, filed for free agency yesterday.</p>
        <p>Phillips said he hoped to get more offense from Ventura and from the maturing outfield.</p>
        <p>Of the players present yesterday, Hamilton seemed the most confused about his role next season. He is under contract for next season but missed most of this year with a sore toe.</p>
        <p>Hamilton twice met with Valentine in the past month to discuss his role and was told that it would be expanded. But he was used strictly as a pinch-hitter during the postseason. Hamilton was 2 for 9 in the playoffs, including 0 for 3 in the World Series.</p>
        <p>''You wait 12 years to get there and to get three at-bats, obviously, it's frustrating,'' Hamilton said, adding that he anticipated a greater role in the division series, especially after Derek Bell was injured. ''That went all the way back to what I was told. I guess it's the old saying, don't believe what you hear.''</p>
        <p>Hamilton tried not to make an issue of his playing time, but said: ''When things didn't go well, obviously then you think there might be some type of change. But that didn't happen.''</p>
        <p>Hamilton said he was excited to be returning with the Mets but planned to speak with Phillips.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, as the Mets packed boxes and bags, they relived their emotional end to the season.</p>
        <p>Luis Sojo's single off Al Leiter's 142nd pitch of Game 5 scored the decisive runs in the top of the ninth inning for the Yankees, and yesterday the pain was only beginning to dissipate for the Mets.</p>
        <p>Rick Reed, who would have pitched a seventh game, if one were necessary, said: ''Why say, What if? You just drive yourself nuts.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL: SUBWAY SERIES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
