<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Giants Are Forced to Adjust on Defense Again</title>
    <meta content="28GIAN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/28/sports/28GIAN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242412"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Giants</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Philadelphia Eagles</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pennington, Bill</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Philadelphia Eagles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001028T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E7DA1F31F93BA15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="752" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Giants Are Forced to Adjust on Defense Again</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL PENNINGTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pennington, Bill</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., Oct. 27</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses upcoming game between New York Giants and Philadelphia Eagles (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Giants have been the second-best team defending the run in the National Football League this season. They rank 27th in pass defense.</p>
        <p>Over all, those are numbers that please John Fox, the team's defensive coordinator.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Giants have been the second-best team defending the run in the National Football League this season. They rank 27th in pass defense.</p>
        <p>Over all, those are numbers that please John Fox, the team's defensive coordinator.</p>
        <p>''From a purely statistical standpoint,'' Fox said, ''you want to be good against the run and not the pass. It means you're a winner.''</p>
        <p>That's because team rankings are based on total yardage gained. Teams that fall behind in games have to spurn the run and turn to the pass to catch up, often against prevent defenses. They gain passing yards, skewing the opposition's pass defense totals, even if they usually do not make up the point deficit.</p>
        <p>''They may get passing yards, but eventually we can get interceptions, sacks, maybe fumbles,'' said Fox, whose defense ranks 12th over all. ''You want your opponent to have to turn to the pass.''</p>
        <p>Fox will apparently get his wish on Sunday when the Philadelphia Eagles visit Giants Stadium, although this week he may find it a mixed blessing.</p>
        <p>Since Philadelphia lost running back Duce Staley for the season with a broken foot, the Eagles have put the offense almost entirely in the hands of quarterback Donovan McNabb. The Eagles will likely drop back to pass 40 times or more on Sunday. The question is whether this is the best time for the Giants to play a team averaging 225.4 passing yards in their last five games.</p>
        <p>The Giants have been busy plugging holes in their secondary and adjusting to changing roles. Emmanuel McDaniel, who had been the nickel cornerback, will start at right cornerback in place of Jason Sehorn, who is out with a cracked rib. McDaniel's substitute in the nickel was supposed to be Reggie Stephens, who appears headed to the bench with a sprained ankle. The Giants will instead dress the second-year cornerback Andre Weathers, who has not played since knee surgery a year ago.</p>
        <p>Another change in the mix is that Sehorn used to take on the opposition's top receiver. Do the Giants put Dave Thomas, the left cornerback, in that featured role?</p>
        <p>Most likely, they will not and will instead play the secondary fairly straight, unless someone is exposed as a weak link. That was what Fox did after Sehorn went out on the first play against Dallas two weeks ago.</p>
        <p>''We've got a good, flexible plan,'' Fox said of the Giants' scheme for the Eagles.</p>
        <p>But can Fox blitz as much as he likes without Sehorn to protect at least one portion of the field?</p>
        <p>''There are a lot of questions when it comes to the pass rush just because of the kind of quarterback we're facing,'' Fox said of McNabb. ''This is a guy who has been their leading rusher in some games since Staley went out. They use him on bootlegs, play action, quarterback draws.</p>
        <p>''Even when we send just four guys in the pass rush, we have to be careful. We have to fill lanes because if there are any chasms in the pass rush -- any lanes for him to escape -- he's gone. He's a better athlete than the people chasing him.''</p>
        <p>McNabb has completed 60.1 percent of his passes for the Eagles, who have won four of their last five games and are 5-3 over all. He has thrown 10 touchdown passes and 7 interceptions. He has made 43 rushing attempts and gained 277 yards.</p>
        <p>''He's been doing everything for them,'' Giants defensive end Michael Strahan said. ''He's carrying the load.''</p>
        <p>If the Giants have their way, McNabb will not be carrying the football too often on Sunday. They may be willing, within reason and late in the game, to let him pad his passing statistics.</p>
        <p>EXTRA POINTS</p>
        <p>Coach JIM FASSEL did not announce his decision on whether BRAD DALUISO or JARET HOLMES would do the place-kicking against the Eagles. But Holmes, who has a sprained ankle, did not kick in practice on Friday. . . . Fassel was aware that the 2000 World Series ended Thursday night. ''It's football season around here now,'' he said after Friday morning's practice. . . . The Giants are having a food drive and asking fans to bring canned, nonperishable food items to the game on Sunday. The items will be collected at entrance gates.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
