<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Vanbiesbrouck Helps Isles Secure First Home Victory</title>
    <meta content="28ISLE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/28/sports/28ISLE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242495"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Islanders</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Montreal Canadiens</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kellner, Jenny</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Montreal Canadiens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Islanders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001028T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E0DB1630F93BA15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="452" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Vanbiesbrouck Helps Isles Secure First Home Victory</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNY KELLNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kellner, Jenny</byline>
      <dateline>UNIONDALE, N.Y., Oct. 27</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Islanders defeat Montreal Canadiens, 2-1 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The way goaltender John Vanbiesbrouck sees it, winning does not come down to just talent. It takes something more.</p>
        <p>''There was a lot of willpower out there tonight, and not just in the final minutes,'' Vanbiesbrouck said after the Islanders beat the Montreal Canadiens, 2-1, tonight at the Nassau Coliseum.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The way goaltender John Vanbiesbrouck sees it, winning does not come down to just talent. It takes something more.</p>
        <p>''There was a lot of willpower out there tonight, and not just in the final minutes,'' Vanbiesbrouck said after the Islanders beat the Montreal Canadiens, 2-1, tonight at the Nassau Coliseum.</p>
        <p>''We're only seven games into it, but I feel like this was a good effort by everyone,'' Vanbiesbrouck said of the Islanders (2-3-2-0), who were coming off a five-day layoff.</p>
        <p>The victory, the Islanders' first at home after two losses, established a three-game unbeaten streak, matching the high of last season, when they had three such streaks. The victory also gave the Islanders 6 points, putting them in a fourth-place tie with the Rangers in the Atlantic Division.</p>
        <p>Vanbiesbrouck, in earning his first victory as an Islander, had what Coach Butch Goring called his best performance, putting on a show for the 11,261 fans. Vanbiesbrouck had a season-high 38 saves last Saturday in a 4-4 tie with the Capitals. Tonight he stopped 37 Canadiens shots, including 20 in the second period. He lost the shutout with just more than a minute remaining when Martin Rucinsky scored a power-play goal from the left face-off circle.</p>
        <p>''Unfortunately, they were able to zip one in, and things got a little dicey,'' Vanbiesbrouck said.</p>
        <p>The Islanders managed to stop the Canadiens, who used a sixth skater in the frenzied final seconds. The Canadiens (4-4-2-0) lost their five-game unbeaten streak. The teams meet again Saturday night in Montreal.</p>
        <p>''It feels great to win our first home game,'' Goring said. ''The guys were excited about it. We would love to become a threat at home.''</p>
        <p>Goring had voiced concern about how sharp his team would be after not playing since last Saturday night. But the Islanders showed no signs of rust, peppering Canadiens goaltender Jose Theodore with seven shots through the first nine minutes while holding the Canadiens to none.</p>
        <p>The Islanders' Mike Stapleton scored at 12 minutes 29 seconds of the first period, poking the rebound of Roman Hamrlik's shot past Theodore from a few feet out on his left side. The rookie Taylor Pyatt earned his first National Hockey League point with an assist.</p>
        <p>''You have to have a winning season at home,'' said Mark Parrish, who scored at 8:44 of the second period on an assist from Tim Connolly to put the Islanders up, 2-0. ''You win at home, and you do your best on the road.''</p>
        <p>The Canadiens, who had four shots on goal in the first period, two in the final minute, outshot the Islanders, 34-17, the rest of the game.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
