<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fujimori Takes Oath as Protests Blanket Area in Smoke</title>
    <meta content="Y29PER$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218456"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Peru</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Lima (Peru)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Krauss, Clifford</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fujimori, Alberto K (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Peru</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Peru/Lima</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Peru</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000729T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE5DC153DF93AA15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="812" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fujimori Takes Oath as Protests Blanket Area in Smoke</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFFORD KRAUSS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Krauss, Clifford</byline>
      <dateline>LIMA, Peru, July 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Alberto K Fujimori of Peru is inaugurated to third term as police and demonstrators engage in running battles that engulf downtown area of Lima in tear gas and smoke; demonstrators believe Fujimori was elected in fraudulent vote; as Fujimori takes oath of office, opposition congressmen jeer and walk out of congressional chamber; Peru has become increasingly polarized in two years since Congress dismissed three judges who ruled that Fujimori was disobeying Constitution by seeking third five-year term (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Alberto K. Fujimori was inaugurated to a third term today as the police and demonstrators engaged in running battles that engulfed the downtown area in tear gas and smoke.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fujimori, on his 62nd birthday, enjoyed the pomp of military marches and a special Mass. But waves of demonstrators, angered by their belief that he was elected in a fraudulent vote, tried to interrupt the proceedings, only to be turned back by police officers firing water cannon, tear gas and bullets.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Alberto K. Fujimori was inaugurated to a third term today as the police and demonstrators engaged in running battles that engulfed the downtown area in tear gas and smoke.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fujimori, on his 62nd birthday, enjoyed the pomp of military marches and a special Mass. But waves of demonstrators, angered by their belief that he was elected in a fraudulent vote, tried to interrupt the proceedings, only to be turned back by police officers firing water cannon, tear gas and bullets.</p>
        <p>The demonstrations were far smaller in size and more violent than organizers expected. The protesters threw rocks and sticks at the police, set bonfires at the gates of the presidential palace and vandalized several government offices. They threw homemade gasoline bombs and set fire to the building that houses the Supreme Court.</p>
        <p>Three people were wounded by gunfire and at least six others were reported to have died in fires set today. About 100 others were injured and scores of protesters were dragged away in handcuffs.</p>
        <p>As President Fujimori took the oath of office, opposition congressmen -- some wearing gas masks in a rebuke to the president -- jeered and walked out of the congressional chamber. But Mr. Fujimori made scant reference in his 40-minute address to the turbulence that has followed two rounds of balloting during which, international observer teams and opposition leaders have charged,  there were irregularities and dirty campaign tricks perpetrated by his intelligence agency. ''Many of our people are not in agreement with our program,'' Mr. Fujimori said. ''That's democracy.''</p>
        <p>But he stopped short of asking for a reconciliation in a nation that has become increasingly polarized in the two years since Congress dismissed three judges who ruled that Mr. Fujimori was disobeying the Constitution by seeking a third five-year term.</p>
        <p>In a speech short on rhetorical flare and delivered in a business-like fashion, he reminded Peruvians of his past successes at halting years of hyperinflation and in making peace with Ecuador. He also pledged to ''fortify democracy and generate employment and well-being, with discipline, prudence and realism.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Fujimori outlined promises that he would work to improve the judicial system and reorganize the security services now that two terrorist groups have been virtually defeated. But he did not address complaints by the Clinton administration, the Organization of American States and several Latin American and European governments that he has governed in an increasingly authoritarian manner.</p>
        <p>''Let's remember that in no country in the world does the minority govern, and certainly not in Peru,'' he said defiantly.</p>
        <p>Even as civilian democracy has progressed in Latin American countries like Mexico, Argentina and Chile, Mr. Fujimori has become the symbol of a counter-trend that disturbs many officials in Washington and around the region. One elected president was overthrown in a coup this year in Ecuador, and President Hugo Chavez of Venezuela has appeared to take lessons from Mr. Fujimori as he led a populist crusade.</p>
        <p>But Washington has been reluctant to take tough action against Mr. Fujimori because of his commitment to root out drug trafficking and for fear that the leadership of the opposition is too erratic to govern.</p>
        <p>Alejandro Toledo, the opposition presidential candidate who dropped out of the race a week before the May 28 runoff, originally said the demonstrators would block the inauguration altogether. But with his support flagging, Mr. Toledo lowered expectations and called for a longer-term strategy to force democratic change.</p>
        <p>''This march will not end until the dictatorship falls,'' Mr. Toledo told a rally of 40,000 protesters in downtown Lima on Thursday night. ''Mr. Fujimori must understand that the people will not stop demonstrating until there are new elections.''</p>
        <p>Tonight, Mr. Toledo blamed the government for the violence at the marches, saying intelligence agents infiltrated the demonstrations to discredit them. The government had no immediate response.</p>
        <p>The demonstrators, mostly students and young workers, traveled to Lima from around the country by bus, train and even boat down Amazonian tributaries.</p>
        <p>In his speech, Mr. Fujimori tried to bolster his base of rural Indians and shantytown residents with repeated promises that he would make new jobs his first priority. To promote development in the Andean highlands, he pledged to foster projects to improve irrigation and wool production from alpacas and llamas.</p>
        <p>He vowed to build 3,000 schools, pave roads in urban shantytowns and expand supplies of clean water and electricity. He also pledged to expand a public school breakfast program to include lunch.</p>
        <p>''The highlands must be transformed into something where more than despair grows,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Fujimori also tried to reassure investors, who in recent weeks have grown alarmed by his increasingly populist rhetoric. He promised to curb an expanding government deficit and to keep the annual inflation rate under 4 percent.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
