<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>F.B.I. Files Wound Up at White House by Error, Report Finds</title>
    <meta content="Y29FILE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218396"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Bureau of Investigation</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Secret Service</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lewis, Neil A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ray, Robert W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000729T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E1D9143DF93AA15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="561" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>F.B.I. Files Wound Up at White House by Error, Report Finds</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NEIL A. LEWIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lewis, Neil A</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Report by Robert W Ray, independent counsel, states that Clinton administration improperly acquired hundreds of FBI files through series of errors committed by Secret Service and, most of all, by incompetent, low-level employee in White House office of personnel security; Ray had announced last March that there was no criminal wrongdoing involved in acquisition of files; his report was released July 28 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Clinton administration improperly acquired hundreds of F.B.I. files through a series of errors committed by the Secret Service and, most of all, by an incompetent investigator in the White House, according to a report by the independent counsel that was released today.</p>
        <p>Robert W. Ray, the independent counsel, announced publicly last March that he had concluded his investigation of the acquisition of the files and that there was no criminal wrongdoing involved. He filed the full report with a special judicial panel that oversees independent counsel investigations, and that report was made public today by the panel's judges.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Clinton administration improperly acquired hundreds of F.B.I. files through a series of errors committed by the Secret Service and, most of all, by an incompetent investigator in the White House, according to a report by the independent counsel that was released today.</p>
        <p>Robert W. Ray, the independent counsel, announced publicly last March that he had concluded his investigation of the acquisition of the files and that there was no criminal wrongdoing involved. He filed the full report with a special judicial panel that oversees independent counsel investigations, and that report was made public today by the panel's judges.</p>
        <p>The report concluded that the files, many of which involved prominent Republicans, were acquired by the White House office of personnel security mainly through the mistakes of Anthony Marceca, a low-level employee there.</p>
        <p>Mr. Marceca, described by the report as a former Democratic political advance person, was hired by the head of the office, Craig M. Livingstone, to help get its files in order. Mr. Livingstone had no experience in security but was also a political advance aide.</p>
        <p>Mr. Marceca requested that the Federal Bureau of Investigation provide him with confidential personnel files on any person who worked at the White House. From the time he started his work in August 1993 until he left the next year, he requisitioned more than 1,100 such files. The independent counsel report said that at least 726 of them were for people who no longer worked at the White House.</p>
        <p>Because many of those were of prominent Republicans, suspicions were raised in news reports and in Congress that the acquisition was an effort by Clinton officials to gather political intelligence.</p>
        <p>In explaining why Mr. Ray concluded that was not so, the report said investigators found that Mr. Marceca requisitioned the files using an inaccurate list provided by the Secret Service. Although the Secret Service has denied that it was responsible for preparing such a list, Mr. Ray found that the Secret Service had in fact prepared a list that was ''unlabeled and overinclusive.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Ray's report said that Mr. Marceca admitted lying to Congress and to a federal grand jury but that he could not be prosecuted because he had been given immunity by federal prosecutors. In any event, the report said, nothing in his testimony affected the conclusion that there was not any conspiracy to obtain Republican files.</p>
        <p>The report said the Secret Service was flatly mistaken and gave misleading testimony when senior officials told Congress and the press that its computer system was incapable of producing an outdated list of White House passholders</p>
        <p>Because it denied any responsibility, the prosecutor said, the Secret Service greatly contributed to the suspicions that the acquisitions of the files could not have been an innocent mistake as the White House had claimed.</p>
        <p>The report said the Secret Service testimony ''plainly magnified public concerns regarding Mr. Marceca's conduct.''</p>
        <p>In an appendix to the report, a lawyer for three Secret Service officials disputed the conclusion blaming the Secret Service. Warren L. Dennis, a lawyer for Lewis Merletti, the former director of the service, and for John Libonati and Jeffrey Undercoffer, two former special agents, said the report was unfair because it misinterpreted their comments about the agency's computer system.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
