<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Clinton Hints That He Is Ready To Move Embassy to Jerusalem</title>
    <meta content="29MIDE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218472"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Foreign Service</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Jerusalem</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United States Foreign Service</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kifner, John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barak, Ehud (Prime Min)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel/Jerusalem</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Service</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000729T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E7DB153DF93AA15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1087" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Clinton Hints That He Is Ready To Move Embassy to Jerusalem</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN KIFNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kifner, John</byline>
      <dateline>JERUSALEM, July 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Clinton, hoping to shore up Prime Min Ehud Barak's shaky political base, goes on Israeli television to promise concrete rewards for peace, hinting he might move United States Embassy to Jerusalem; that move would be major triumph for Israel and Jews around world who have long sought international recognition for Jerusalem as capital of Jewish state; United States and most other nations keep their embassies in Tel Aviv, on argument that status of Holy City remains unresolved; Clinton, in television interview, says Barak has never compromised Israel's vital interests; interview said to be result of telephone call Barak made to White House, asking Clinton's help with his political problems (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Acting to help shore up Prime Minister Ehud Barak's shaky political base, President Clinton went on Israeli television tonight promising concrete rewards for peace, hinting that he was ready to move the United States Embassy to Jerusalem.</p>
        <p>That move would be a major triumph for Israel and Jews around the world who have long sought international recognition for Jerusalem as the capital of the Jewish state. The United States and most other nations have kept their embassies in Tel Aviv, on the argument that the status of the Holy City remains unresolved.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Acting to help shore up Prime Minister Ehud Barak's shaky political base, President Clinton went on Israeli television tonight promising concrete rewards for peace, hinting that he was ready to move the United States Embassy to Jerusalem.</p>
        <p>That move would be a major triumph for Israel and Jews around the world who have long sought international recognition for Jerusalem as the capital of the Jewish state. The United States and most other nations have kept their embassies in Tel Aviv, on the argument that the status of the Holy City remains unresolved.</p>
        <p>The newspaper Haaretz reported that Mr. Barak, who lost his majority in Parliament when three parties bolted his coalition to protest the talks and who faces no-confidence votes on Monday, had telephoned the White House and asked the president's help with his political problems. Interviewed for half an hour on Israeli television, Mr. Clinton himself introduced the issue of moving the embassy while answering a question about the relationship between United States and Israel, calling it ''very strong.'' [Excerpts, Page A5.]</p>
        <p>After talking about a long-term commitment to help modernize the Israeli Army and provide more security assistance now that Israeli troops have been withdrawn from Lebanon, the president said:</p>
        <p>''You know, I have always wanted to move our embassy to West Jerusalem. We have a designated site there. I have not done so because I didn't want to do anything to undermine our ability to help broker a secure and fair and lasting peace for Israelis and for Palestinians.</p>
        <p>''But in light of what has happened, I've taken that decision under review and I'll make a decision sometime between now and the end of the year on that.'' Congress called for moving the embassy five years ago, but the Clinton administration has not gone along, arguing that the peace effort came first.</p>
        <p>Once again, Mr. Clinton spoke highly today of Mr. Barak, saying the prime minister ''in no way ever compromised the vital interests of the state of Israel.''</p>
        <p>Though the interview was pegged to the Camp David talks and Mr. Barak's political needs, the issues of Jerusalem and American support for Israel have also featured strongly in the Senate campaign of Mr. Clinton's wife, Hillary Rodham Clinton, especially since she was accused of once making an anti-Semitic slur. Mrs. Clinton has declared that Jerusalem should be ''the eternal and indivisible capital of Israel.''</p>
        <p>Once Mr. Clinton broached the subject, the Israeli interviewer asked: ''You mentioned the relocation of the Israeli -- of the American Embassy and put it in Jerusalem.  Would you consider it in any circumstances, even if there is no agreement?'' The president replied ''Well, I think I should stand on the words I said.''</p>
        <p>''I have always wanted to do it,'' he continued. ''I've always thought it was the right thing to do. But I didn't want to do anything to undermine the peace process, our ability to be an honest broker, which requires that we be accepted by both sides.''</p>
        <p>''But it's something I've taken under review now because of the recent events,'' he said. ''And I think that's all I should say about it now.''</p>
        <p>There was no immediate official reaction here because the interview was broadcast on the 8 o'clock news, after sirens had sounded the start of the Jewish sabbath, during with the country largely shuts down.</p>
        <p>In response to a question, Mr. Clinton warned Yasir Arafat, the Palestinian leader, not to carry out his intention to unilaterally declare a Palestinian state by Sept. 13 even without a peace agreement. If that happens, the president said, ''there will inevitably be consequences. Not just here, but throughout the world. And things will happen. I would review our entire relationship.''</p>
        <p>Asked what Israel could expect to get if it signed a peace agreement, Mr. Clinton replied: ''I will do my best to get the maximum amount of support. One of the reasons that I wanted very much to get the agreement this time is that it would give us more time to pass an aid package through Congress.''</p>
        <p>He went on to mention an issue often raised by Israelis whenever the question of compensating Palestinian refugees arises -- that of also paying compensation to Jews who fled or were evicted from Arab lands since the creation of Israel.</p>
        <p>''There is some interest, interestingly enough on both sides, in also having a fund which compensates the Israelis who were made refugees by the war which occurred after the birth of Israel,'' he said. ''Israel is full of people, Jewish people, who lived in predominantly Arab countries who came to Israel because they were made refugees in their own land.''</p>
        <p>''That's another piece of the good news that I think I can reveal that came out of the summit,'' he said. ''The Palestinians thought those people should be eligible for compensation as well.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton said there would have to be an ''international fund'' for the refugees, but he did not indicate who would be expected to contribute.</p>
        <p>But the idea of such compensation was likely to be of special interest to Jews from Arab countries, whose support is crucial to Mr. Barak.  Many of them are supporters of Shas, a religious party with 17 seats in Parliament that broke from Mr. Barak's coalition before the talks.</p>
        <p>The return of Shas, whose central  interest is to protect and expand the government benefits it has accumulated, would be of major help to Mr. Barak in his efforts to regain a comfortable majority in Parliament.</p>
        <p>Its withdrawal from the coalition, along with that of two smaller parties, dropped Mr. Barak's support in the 120-seat legislature from 69 to 42.</p>
        <p>Shas has been moderate on issues of peace, and its spiritual leader, Rabbi Ovadia Yosef, has ruled that it would be acceptable to have a Palestinian flag fly over the Temple Mount in Jerusalem if the effect was to save Jewish lives. Giving the Palestinians control over the mount was one of the possible arrangements reportedly discussed at Camp David.</p>
        <p>Mr. Barak's immediate goal is to survive the no-confidence votes on Monday, after which Parliament adjourns for a three-month vacation.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
