<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Con Ed Runs Tests in Bid to Restart Indian Point Plant</title>
    <meta content="29NUKE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218431"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Indian Point Nuclear Power Plant (NY)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Consolidated Edison Co of New York Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hu, Winnie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Indian Point Nuclear Power Plant (NY)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000729T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907E6DE153DF93AA15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="897" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Con Ed Runs Tests in Bid to Restart Indian Point Plant</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WINNIE HU</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hu, Winnie</byline>
      <dateline>BUCHANAN, N.Y., July 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Consolidated Edison renews claims that Indian River 2 power plant can be safely restarted with existing steam generators; runs preparatory tests; engineers defend inspection procedures during public meeting with NRC (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Despite mounting criticism of its inspection procedures, Consolidated Edison renewed its claims today that the Indian Point 2 power plant could be safely restarted with its existing steam generators and even ran heat and pressure tests in preparation for the restart.</p>
        <p>Con Edison engineers elaborately defended their inspection procedures with charts and numbers during a five-hour public meeting with the Nuclear Regulatory Commission at the plant site, 35 miles north of New York City. Last week, the commission sent a letter to plant managers requiring further, extensive analysis of the steam generators before it could be reopened.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Despite mounting criticism of its inspection procedures, Consolidated Edison renewed its claims today that the Indian Point 2 power plant could be safely restarted with its existing steam generators and even ran heat and pressure tests in preparation for the restart.</p>
        <p>Con Edison engineers elaborately defended their inspection procedures with charts and numbers during a five-hour public meeting with the Nuclear Regulatory Commission at the plant site, 35 miles north of New York City. Last week, the commission sent a letter to plant managers requiring further, extensive analysis of the steam generators before it could be reopened.</p>
        <p>The commission delivered another blow yesterday in a second letter that cited Con Edison's lax inspection of the steam generators in 1997 as a contributing factor in the Feb. 15 radioactive leak that shut down the plant. In that leak, a tiny amount of radioactive steam escaped after a tube carrying superheated radioactive water cracked from corrosion. No injuries were reported, but the accident was the worst in the 26-year history of the plant.</p>
        <p>James S. Baumstark, vice president of nuclear engineering for Con Edison, said he disagreed with the nuclear commission's findings in the 1997 inspection. He also emphasized that the company had improved its methods since then to include an  electronic probe that is better able to spot minute cracks in the tubes.</p>
        <p>''We've made significant improvements in both equipment and processes,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But Nuclear Regulatory Commission officials said today that they would need more time to review the company's responses and study the processes involved before making a final decision. Still, Jack R. Strosnider, director of the division of engineering at the commission, said that the Indian Point 2 plant could reopen in a matter of weeks.</p>
        <p>''It's possible,'' he said. ''If they provide the right engineering answers. We haven't reached a final decision at this point.''</p>
        <p>Although Con Edison officials have pledged to replace the plant's aging steam generators by the end of the year, they want to restart the existing generators to increase the company's power reserves during the hot summer months, when energy use rises. Today, workers raised the temperature of the nuclear reactor in a routine test to check for leaks or other problems. A few weeks ago, they performed a similar test after receiving permission from the nuclear commission, said Michael Clendenin, a spokesman for Con Edison.</p>
        <p>In recent months, local government officials, advocacy groups and others have petitioned the nuclear commission to demand that Indian Point 2 remain closed until the new generators are installed.</p>
        <p>State Assemblywoman Sandra R. Galef, a Democrat from the nearby town of Ossining, was one opponent at today's public meeting. ''I think it was a waste of time, money and talent to debate whether these steam generators should be allowed to run for a few months,'' she said. ''I just don't understand why they let the engineers argue about this when they're going to change it anyway. Just get it done.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Baumstark said it could take nine months to a year before the new generators are fully operational because of the detailed preparations involved. During that period of transition, he said, the existing generators could supply power that is currently being bought from other power companies. Since the shutdown, the company has passed on the cost of that arrangement -- about $600,000 a day -- to its utility customers.</p>
        <p>''We're very concerned about the ability to get some reserve power on the grid,'' he said. ''The grid's done well to this point, but we haven't had a lot of very demanding days, and we could have a backup for our customers.''</p>
        <p>But still others today raised the possibility that the most economical decision for Con Edison may be to keep the Indian Point 2 plant closed  permanently.</p>
        <p>Edward A. Smeloff, executive director of the Pace University Energy Project, said that replacing the plant's four existing steam generators would cost between $150 million and $250 million. He said that Con Edison should undertake a comparative cost analysis to determine whether it would be cheaper in the long run to keep buying energy from other companies.</p>
        <p>Mr. Smeloff said that two power plants, one in Oregon and one in Maine, were closed by their owners in the mid-1990's because it was cheaper than replacing the costly steam generators. ''So the question becomes: Can that investment be recovered in future operations of the plant through the market?'' he said. ''If it can't, then the plant wouldn't be economical and should be shut down.''</p>
        <p>But Con Edison officials today dismissed the idea of shutting down the plant to save money. The company is in the process of selling the power plant, which has been licensed by the nuclear commission to operate until 2013. ''We believe it's less costly to have the plant running than to have to go purchase power from other sources,'' Mr. Clendenin said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
