<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Both Parties Are Fiddling With New York Ballot Lists</title>
    <meta content="29BALL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218420"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Endorsements</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Working Families Party</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perez-Pena, Richard</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000729T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E6DF153DF93AA15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="875" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Both Parties Are Fiddling With New York Ballot Lists</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD PEREZ-PENA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Perez-Pena, Richard</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, July 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Political operatives are reviving New York's old tradition of trying to manipulate who is or is not on ballot; seven Republican state senators facing tough challenges sue to push tiny Working Families Party off ballot after it endorses Democrats; Democrats on Board of Elections block effort to knock four little-known names off US Senate primary ballot, in hopes of diluting anti-Hillary Clinton vote (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Politicians of all stripes are charging that the last few days have marked a revival of one of New York's least proud political traditions: trying to gain advantage by manipulating who is or is not on the ballot.</p>
        <p>Seven Republican state senators facing tough challenges have sued the tiny Working Families Party, making a fairly novel argument that it is not a legally functioning party. Not incidentally, all seven Republicans tried to get the Working Families nomination but failed, and the party's line went to their Democratic challengers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Politicians of all stripes are charging that the last few days have marked a revival of one of New York's least proud political traditions: trying to gain advantage by manipulating who is or is not on the ballot.</p>
        <p>Seven Republican state senators facing tough challenges have sued the tiny Working Families Party, making a fairly novel argument that it is not a legally functioning party. Not incidentally, all seven Republicans tried to get the Working Families nomination but failed, and the party's line went to their Democratic challengers.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, on Thursday, the Democrats on the Board of Elections blocked an effort to knock four little-known Democrats off the United States Senate primary ballot, even though they clearly had not collected enough signatures to qualify. This means that in the Sept. 12 primary, Hillary Rodham Clinton could face five obscure challengers rather than one, diluting the anti-Hillary vote and making her all-but-certain victory seem more resounding.</p>
        <p>''It's embarrassing,'' a state elections official said of the two disputes. ''You don't see this kind of garbage happening in other states.''</p>
        <p>New York is, of course, famous for such maneuvering. Just this year, Gov. George E. Pataki and the state Republican Party tried to keep Senator John McCain off the state's presidential primary ballot, a move for which they were vilified, and that ultimately failed.</p>
        <p>The rules for entering a presidential primary have been eased, and Mr. Pataki has proposed relaxing them further, but the rules for other offices remain among the toughest in the country.</p>
        <p>In the case of the Working Families party, seven Republican state senators filed suit in their respective counties on Wednesday and Thursday, challenging not only the nominating petitions for their opponents -- a commonplace tactic in New York -- but the party's right to nominate any candidates at all. The senators are Roy M. Goodman of Manhattan; Guy J. Velella of the Bronx; Frank M. Padavan of Queens; Michael A. L. Balboni, Kemp Hannon and Carl L. Marcellino of Nassau County; and Thomas P. Morahan of Rockland County.</p>
        <p>None of the senators would discuss their suits on the record. But some acknowledged, on the condition that their names not be used, that they knew nothing about the legal arguments behind their suits, and that the idea had come not from them but from the Senate Republican Campaign Committee.</p>
        <p>The complaints note that the Working Families Party, first created in 1998 and with fewer than 5,000 registered voters, does not yet have an elected state committee, only an interim committee. Working Families officials say they are in the process of electing a state committee for the first time, following the timetable set by the Board of Elections.</p>
        <p>''This is just pure harassment, and hypocritical beyond belief,'' Dan Cantor, executive director of the party, said of the lawsuits.</p>
        <p>The Working Families Party did give its line to one Republican state senator, George D. Maziarz of western New York, but the Republicans have not challenged that nomination.</p>
        <p>''The law says they had to elect a state committee within their first year of existence,'' said John Ciampoli, the lawyer for the seven Republican senators who sued. ''They didn't do it. It's that simple.''</p>
        <p>All seven Republican state senators are seen as vulnerable this year, leading to unusually heated struggles for minor-party lines that could provide the margin of victory in a close race.</p>
        <p>A judge in Albany and a judge in Nassau County ordered that the seven suits be consolidated into one.</p>
        <p>In Mrs. Clinton's race, it became certain in recent days that she would face a primary, as Mark McMahon, a Manhattan doctor, filed far more than the 15,000 signatures needed to get on the ballot. Four other Democrats also filed petitions to appear on the primary ballot, but all fell well short of the requirements.</p>
        <p>Yet when the matter went before the state Board of Elections on Thursday, and the two Republican commissioners voted to disqualify the four challengers, the two Democratic commissioners abstained. Three votes are needed to knock someone off the ballot.</p>
        <p>''This is obviously an attempt to jam Hillary down the throats of Democratic voters,'' said Dan Allen, spokesman for the state Republican Party. ''They like to talk about a united party, but clearly it's not.''</p>
        <p>Carol Berman, the Democratic chairwoman of the Board of Elections, denied that her abstention had anything to do with Mrs. Clinton's prospects. But she admitted that ''the petitions are in no way in compliance with the election law.''</p>
        <p>But she pointed to Mr. McCain's case this year, when Judge Edward R. Korman, in Federal District Court in Brooklyn, ruled that the petition-gathering rules were too onerous. She noted that he not only ordered that Mr. McCain be placed on the presidential primary ballot, but also ordered the inclusion of Alan Keyes, who had not filed any petitions.</p>
        <p>Judge Korman explicitly limited his ruling to presidential primaries, but Ms. Berman said the same rule should apply in the Senate race.</p>
        <p>Mr. McMahon's campaign has signaled that it will go to court to challenge the board's decision and have the other four Democrats thrown off the ballot. Republican officials said today that they might join such a suit.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
