<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Mets Get More for Less</title>
    <meta content="29BORD$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218482"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trades (Sports)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Baltimore Orioles</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Tampa Bay Devil Rays</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kepner, Tyler</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Trammell, Bubba</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mora, Melvin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bordick, Mike</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tyner, Jason</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wilson, Paul</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">White, Rick</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Baltimore Orioles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Tampa Bay Devil Rays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Tampa Bay Rays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trades (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000729T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E2DB153DF93AA15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1165" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Mets Get More for Less</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kepner, Tyler</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Mets trade utility player Melvin Mora, infielder Mike Kinkade and two minor league pitchers to Baltimore Orioles for shortstop Mike Bordick; they also trade outfielder Jason Tyner and Class AAA pitcher Paul Wilson to Tampa Bay Devil Rays for outfielder Bubba Trammell and relief pitcher Rick White; photo; graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>One week after agreeing to deal the organization's top prospect for the All-Star shortstop Barry Larkin, the Mets yesterday traded for another All-Star shortstop, a right-handed setup reliever and a power-hitting outfielder without giving up one of their six top prospects.</p>
        <p>When Larkin rejected a trade and stayed with Cincinnati, the Mets focused on acquiring Mike Bordick from Baltimore. They got Bordick yesterday, then traded for reliever Rick White and outfielder Bubba Trammell from Tampa Bay.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>One week after agreeing to deal the organization's top prospect for the All-Star shortstop Barry Larkin, the Mets yesterday traded for another All-Star shortstop, a right-handed setup reliever and a power-hitting outfielder without giving up one of their six top prospects.</p>
        <p>When Larkin rejected a trade and stayed with Cincinnati, the Mets focused on acquiring Mike Bordick from Baltimore. They got Bordick yesterday, then traded for reliever Rick White and outfielder Bubba Trammell from Tampa Bay.</p>
        <p>The Orioles had insisted that the Class AA outfielder Alex Escobar be included in the deal, as he was in the proposed trade for Larkin. The Mets refused, and General Manager Steve Phillips thought there would be no trade.</p>
        <p>But late Thursday night the Orioles backed off Escobar and accepted a four-player package that included Melvin Mora, infielder Mike Kinkade and two minor league pitchers, Lesli Brea and Pat Gorman. The Orioles showed no interest in taking on the expensive contract of the Mets' injured shortstop, Rey Ordonez.</p>
        <p>After trading for Bordick and realizing he could not meet Milwaukee's demands for the closer Bob Wickman -- who was dealt to Cleveland yesterday for a package fronted by the slugging outfielder Richie Sexson -- Phillips turned to the Devil Rays. To get Trammell and White, the Mets traded outfielder Jason Tyner and the Class AAA starter Paul Wilson, both former No. 1 draft picks.</p>
        <p>While the Mets landed neither of the players they wanted most for shortstop and the bullpen, they filled several holes while keeping Escobar, the minor league pitchers Grant Roberts, Ken Chenard, Jae Seo and Pat Strange, and the minor league outfielder Brian Cole, considered the six best prospects in the system.</p>
        <p>''We feel like we've protected the top echelon of our prospect pool, hopefully to play for us but also for consideration for other big deals that could be out there now and this off-season,'' Phillips said.</p>
        <p>Bordick is an outstanding defensive shortstop who is enjoying his finest season at the plate. He is batting .297 with 16 home runs and 59 runs batted in, and he has a .979 fielding percentage.</p>
        <p>Mora, playing regularly for the first time in the majors, had a .958 fielding percentage at short.</p>
        <p>Bordick played seven years for Oakland before signing with Baltimore before the 1997 season. St. Louis Manager Tony La Russa, who managed Bordick with the Athletics, said Bordick was ''tied for first on the list'' of his favorite players.</p>
        <p>''He's a 10,'' La Russa said. ''He might be the perfect player, and he's a perfect person. He's ideal. You can't look at anything he does and say, 'I wish he did that differently.'</p>
        <p>''He plays as well defensively as anyone in the big leagues. Day in and day out, he's very consistent. He makes all the plays.''</p>
        <p>Bordick can be a free agent after the season, and the Mets, who covet another free-agent shortstop, Seattle's Alex Rodriguez, do not plan to talk about a contract extension with him now.</p>
        <p>Bordick had hoped to remain with the Orioles but said he was excited to be in a pennant race. He said he strives for consistency and has proven it in his career, making between 7 and 16 errors in each of his 10 full major league seasons, with a career fielding percentage of .981.</p>
        <p>''I was very confident in Melvin Mora, personally,'' Mets Manager Bobby Valentine said. ''That doesn't mean he was going to make all the plays Bordick's going to make. I think Mike will make more plays than Melvin would have made.''</p>
        <p>It is still possible that the Mets can make more moves before Monday's nonwaiver trading deadline, but Phillips said he would be satisfied heading into the final two months of the season if he made no more deals.</p>
        <p>''Absolutely; there's no question about that,'' he said. ''We're an improved team significantly at shortstop. I think we've addressed that need in the bullpen to have a complement to Turk from the right side late in the game. Trammell gives us some of that right-handed power that we wanted to have.''</p>
        <p>The 31-year-old White is durable, in the Turk Wendell style. He ranks first in the American League with 71 1/3 relief innings, after ranking second last year. Phillips said White was ''a combination of Wendell and Pat Mahomes.'' He can throw fastballs and sliders the way Wendell does and is able to pitch in long relief, the way Pat Mahomes does. White is especially tough on right-handers, who are hitting .172 off him.</p>
        <p>White, who has a 3.41 earned run average, will primarily be used in the late innings, giving the Mets two capable right-handed setup men to go with their left-handed tandem of Dennis Cook and John Franco.</p>
        <p>Trammell, 28, has had success for Tampa Bay as a part-time player, hitting .285 with 33 home runs in 671 at-bats over the last three years. With Benny Agbayani starting, the Mets have had only one right-handed power hitter in reserve, Todd Pratt, but he is a catcher and thus pinch-hits infrequently.</p>
        <p>Trammell fits in nicely as a reserve, Phillips said, and he could also start.</p>
        <p>To make room for Bordick, White and Trammell, the Mets sent down infielders Mark Johnson and Jorge Toca and designated the struggling reliever Rich Rodriguez for assignment. The Mets have 7 to 10 days to option Rodriguez to the minors, or to release or trade him.</p>
        <p>The prospects the Mets traded for Bordick -- Brea and Gorman -- are hard throwers who will probably be relievers if they reach the major leagues. Brea, 21, was 5-8 with a 4.24 E.R.A. as a starter at Class AA Binghamton. The 22-year-old Gorman, whom the Orioles' vice president for baseball operations, Syd Thrift, said was the pivotal player in the deal, had 15 saves for Class A Columbia.</p>
        <p>The more recognizable prospects the Mets traded were Tyner and Wilson, who will join Tampa Bay's major league roster, at least initially.</p>
        <p>While the Mets believed Tyner, their top pick in the 1998 draft, would hit in the majors, they were unsure of his defense. They have been impressed by Timoniel Perez, another Class AAA Norfolk outfielder, who has speed and more power.</p>
        <p>Wilson, picked first over all in the 1994 draft, was a sentimental favorite. The 27-year-old right-hander has come back from serious elbow and shoulder surgeries to have a solid season at Norfolk, going 5-5 with a 4.23 E.R.A.</p>
        <p>But Phillips also believed Wilson was more likely to pitch at the end of a major league rotation. He added: ''I just absolutely motivated him to prove me wrong.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
