<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Unions Angered by City's Proposal That Police Officers Defer Two Weeks' Pay</title>
    <meta content="29PBA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218400"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Contracts</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Patrolmen's Benevolent Assn (Pba)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lynch, Patrick</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greenhouse, Steven</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000729T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E4D8143DF93AA15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1069" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Unions Angered by City's Proposal That Police Officers Defer Two Weeks' Pay</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN GREENHOUSE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Greenhouse, Steven</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Giuliani administration proposes that New York City's 27,000 police officers accept two-week deferral of pay as part of any new labor contract; PBA president Patrick Lynch calls suggestion insulting (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Giuliani administration has proposed that the city's 27,000 police officers accept a two-week deferral of pay as part of any new labor contract, a demand that has angered leaders of the Patrolmen's Benevolent Association.</p>
        <p>Patrick Lynch, the P.B.A.'s president, assailed City Hall's proposal, saying it was insulting because it comes when crime is down, the city has a budget surplus and the city's police salaries are behind those in the suburbs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Giuliani administration has proposed that the city's 27,000 police officers accept a two-week deferral of pay as part of any new labor contract, a demand that has angered leaders of the Patrolmen's Benevolent Association.</p>
        <p>Patrick Lynch, the P.B.A.'s president, assailed City Hall's proposal, saying it was insulting because it comes when crime is down, the city has a budget surplus and the city's police salaries are behind those in the suburbs.</p>
        <p>''It's an embarrassment,'' Mr. Lynch said. ''We're dealing with a salary that makes police officers work two and three jobs and doesn't enable us to put food on the table for our families.''</p>
        <p>Deputy Mayor Robert Harding, who is overseeing the city's labor negotiations, would not discuss the wage-deferral proposal, which was part of a larger package of demands that the city presented to the police last week as part of its initial bargaining offer. The P.B.A.'s current five-year contract expires Monday.</p>
        <p>Union leaders were puzzling over whether the demand was just an opening bid that would soon be dropped or whether it signaled that the Giuliani administration was intent on hard-nosed bargaining.</p>
        <p>Under the city's proposal, police officers would miss two weeks' pay over the first year of any new contract. They would recoup those wages only when they retired or left the police force. The plan, if accepted, could save the city as much as $50 million.</p>
        <p>The proposal would not cause police officers to miss paychecks two weeks in a row, one official involved in the negotiations said. Instead, every two weeks police officers might be paid for 9 days of work rather than the 10 they actually worked, until two weeks of missed pay was accumulated.</p>
        <p>City officials would not discuss details of any other aspects of their contract proposals. Nor would Mr. Lynch detail the P.B.A.'s opening demands, except to say that the union wanted ''a substantial wage increase.''</p>
        <p>One city official sought to play down the importance of the wage-deferral proposal, sometimes called a lag payroll, saying it was merely part of the city's opening offer. He added that labor leaders should not make a big deal out of the proposal because the city's unions had accepted wage deferrals in the past, namely during the city's 1970's fiscal crisis.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, many union leaders condemned the proposal, saying it would amount to an effective 4 percent cut in pay. Labor leaders voiced anger that the city made the proposal to the P.B.A. in particular, because many unions are looking to the talks with the police union to set the pattern for other negotiations.</p>
        <p>Many municipal labor leaders were already fuming over Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani's proposal not to have across-the-board wage increases for city employees. Instead, he is insisting on individual merit increases, with some workers getting raises and others receiving none.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lynch and other union leaders called the administration's proposal especially galling because it came at the same time an arbitration panel awarded the Suffolk County police a raise of just under 20 percent over four years. That award will bring the average base pay of Suffolk police to more than $80,000 a year, far higher than in New York City, where police begin at $31,305 a year, with pay rising to $55,268 after 20 years.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lynch said he hoped that City Hall's wage deferral proposal was just part of the city's ''wish list,'' and that the city would quickly abandon it as negotiations progressed.</p>
        <p>Randi Weingarten, the teachers' union president and chairwoman of the Municipal Labor Coalition, which coordinates bargaining for the city's nearly 300,000 unionized workers, called the city's wage deferral proposal ''mind-boggling.''</p>
        <p>''It is a pretty funny thing,'' Ms. Weingarten said, ''that the Suffolk County arbitrator has come up with a four-year deal of 5 percent each year and the city, which talks about how valuable and important their cops are and how critical they are to the turnaround in crime, has called for a deferral of pay when it has its biggest budget surplus in years.''</p>
        <p>The city's demand is similar to one made by deficit-plagued Nassau County, which pushed its police officers and other unions to forgo two weeks' pay -- deferring that money until their retirement.</p>
        <p>But several union leaders said the city's proposal came across as callous because the city is in far better financial shape than Nassau.</p>
        <p>''We're talking about a time when there's a $2.9 billion surplus in the city,'' Mr. Lynch said. ''The reason there is a surplus in the city is that tourism is up because of the safety factor. People want to do business in the city. That can be directly attributed to the work of New York City police officers. All we're asking for is our fair share.''</p>
        <p>Deputy Mayor Harding denied that the city had a budget surplus, saying the city had used up last year's surplus by budgeting it to reduce deficits in future years.</p>
        <p>''We're in the new fiscal year,'' Mr. Harding said. ''We don't have a surplus. It's been used to reduce out-year gaps. There is no surplus in fact or law.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Weingarten said the proposal indicated that Mayor Giuliani was not serious about wanting to reach new contracts with the city's unions.</p>
        <p>''I don't think the city has an end game that gets to a contract,'' she said. ''I think the city is thinking, 'This is a headache for us. I don't want to deal with these issues. I'm going to try to avoid it.' And the best way to avoid it is to be so polemical in one's rhetoric that they'll scare the unions away.''</p>
        <p>Lt. Anthony Garvey, the president of the New York City Lieutenants Benevolent Association, said it would be wrong for unions to get angry about the city's wage deferral demand.</p>
        <p>''I think it might be just a preliminary offer,'' he said. ''I don't think they're at the serious stage of negotiations yet. I'm sure the P.B.A. has offered some demands that are unrealistic.''</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, he added: ''The city is in very good shape financially. There's certainly no need for any wage deferral.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
