<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Jazzy Jesus Raps, and Street People Reply in Chorus</title>
    <meta content="29MOOR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Ideas/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000801T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218370"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="OPERA REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nuyorican Poets Cafe</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Moore, Carman</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reed, Ishmael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tommasini, Anthony</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Gethsemane Park (Opera)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000729T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E2DC143DF93AA15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="577" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Jazzy Jesus Raps, and Street People Reply in Chorus</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY TOMMASINI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tommasini, Anthony</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anthony Tommasini reviews new gospel opera Gethsemane Park, with music by Carman Moore and libretto by Ishmael Reed; work is performed at Nuyorican Poets Cafe; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The composer Carman Moore and the librettist Ishmael Reed call their new gospel opera, ''Gethsemane Park,'' a ''gospera.'' It's a hodgepodge term,  but it indicates how consciously the creators of this earnest work -- an updated retelling of the story of Jesus'last days among his disciples set amid inner-city poverty -- have tried to mix musical styles, not just gospel and opera, but jazz, rap and popular song.</p>
        <p>Yet, in being so stylistically eclectic, ''Gethsemane Park,'' which is receiving its New York premiere at the lively Nuyorican Poets Cafe on East Third Street between Avenues B and C, winds up lacking a clear profile and diminishing its potential impact.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The composer Carman Moore and the librettist Ishmael Reed call their new gospel opera, ''Gethsemane Park,'' a ''gospera.'' It's a hodgepodge term,  but it indicates how consciously the creators of this earnest work -- an updated retelling of the story of Jesus'last days among his disciples set amid inner-city poverty -- have tried to mix musical styles, not just gospel and opera, but jazz, rap and popular song.</p>
        <p>Yet, in being so stylistically eclectic, ''Gethsemane Park,'' which is receiving its New York premiere at the lively Nuyorican Poets Cafe on East Third Street between Avenues B and C, winds up lacking a clear profile and diminishing its potential impact.</p>
        <p>The work's strongest point is its dramatic conception. The story is set in Gethsemane Park, the inner-city headquarters of a coalition of street people, social workers and intrepid mothers determined to protect their youngsters from crime and despair, all in colorful ragtag costumes designed by Barba-Ra Register and Charles Thomas. Jesus does not appear as a character, but his spirit is everywhere. In the opening scene, an indomitable woman brings her traveling soup kitchen, a shopping cart, to a bench in the park.</p>
        <p>As with the original disciples, the coming of Jesus has caused as much confusion as hope. There is a moving moment when Anne, played affectingly by Dee Dixon, tells the story of Jesus having raised her son Lazarus from the dead. ''It's not right to bring back the dead,'' she sings. And when a man huddling under a blanket reveals himself to be Lazarus, played by Charles Thomas, he is a haunted figure living on both sides of the door between life and death.</p>
        <p>The story of ''Gethsemane Park'' centers on the efforts of Beelzebub, played by an actor called Jamie, to get Mary Magdalene and the disciples to expose Jesus so Beelzebub and his thug followers can reclaim turf that was theirs until now.</p>
        <p>Mr. Moore's score is at times engaging, but stylistically confused. At least as performed here, the operatic components of the music seemed out of place. Much of the dialogue is delivered in heavy-handed dramatic recitation, and there are many needlessly complex choruses that this cast, which had some weak singers in it, struggled hard to execute.</p>
        <p>The best musical moments were the simplest, especially some of the solo songs. Eunice Newkirk, who dominated every scene she was in as Mary, the mother of Jesus, a proud black woman in a turquoise turban, was moving in the soulful ''Guilty as Charged.''</p>
        <p>The musical direction was by Nicole Becker. The stage director Rome Neal, working with a cast of clearly variable experience, still manages to create a disarming portrait of a scrappy community. Sometimes the work lapses into caricature, as when a trio of well-dressed taxpayers castigate the denizens of the park to take baths and find work.</p>
        <p>''Gethsemane Park'' has undeniable spirit. But it might have worked better had it simply been a gospel drama and left out the opera. It plays at the Nuyorican Poets Cafe, a vital venue for the arts in Alphabet City, through Aug. 13.</p>
        <p>OPERA REVIEW  Correction:  August 1, 2000, Tuesday  A Pop/Jazz music listing in the Arts &amp; Leisure section on Sunday for the City Parks Foundation Concerts carried an outdated schedule. Ray, Goodman and Brown is the performing group for three concerts: today at Fort Greene Park in Brooklyn; Wednesday at Linden Park in East New York; and Thursday at Von King Park in Bedford-Stuyvesant, Brooklyn. The concerts begin at 7 and are free.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: August 1, 2000, Tuesday</p>
        <p>A Pop/Jazz music listing in the Arts &amp; Leisure section on Sunday for the City Parks Foundation Concerts carried an outdated schedule. Ray, Goodman and Brown is the performing group for three concerts: today at Fort Greene Park in Brooklyn; Wednesday at Linden Park in East New York; and Thursday at Von King Park in Bedford-Stuyvesant, Brooklyn. The concerts begin at 7 and are free.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
