<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fleisher Shoots 63 To Lead Quigley</title>
    <meta content="29GLF" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218494"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF: ROUNDUP"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lightpath Long Island Classic (Golf)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cavanaugh, Jack</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fleisher, Bruce</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000729T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEFDB153DF93AA15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="849" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fleisher Shoots 63 To Lead Quigley</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CAVANAUGH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cavanaugh, Jack</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bruce Fleisher leads after second round at Lightpath Long Island Classic Senior PGA golf tournament (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The saying in sports that it is not how you start but how you finish was borne out again yesterday when Dana Quigley birdied the first three holes but still trailed Bruce Fleisher by a stroke after the opening round of the Lightpath Long Island Classic Senior PGA tournament.</p>
        <p>En route to his eight-under-par 64 at the Meadow Brook Club in Jericho, Quigley had eight birdies and a bogey. Fleisher, the defending champion, also had eight birdies during a bogey-free round, and three came on the final three holes as he fired a course-record 63.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The saying in sports that it is not how you start but how you finish was borne out again yesterday when Dana Quigley birdied the first three holes but still trailed Bruce Fleisher by a stroke after the opening round of the Lightpath Long Island Classic Senior PGA tournament.</p>
        <p>En route to his eight-under-par 64 at the Meadow Brook Club in Jericho, Quigley had eight birdies and a bogey. Fleisher, the defending champion, also had eight birdies during a bogey-free round, and three came on the final three holes as he fired a course-record 63.</p>
        <p>Two strokes off the lead was David Lundstrom, who, like Quigley, is 53 years old and in his third year on the Senior PGA Tour. Lundstrom shot a 66 with no bogeys.</p>
        <p>The 51-year-old Fleisher won only once in more than 400 tournaments on the PGA Tour from 1969 through 1998. As a rookie on the Senior Tour last year, Fleisher became a dominant player, winning seven tournaments, player of the year and rookie of the year honors, the Byron Nelson trophy for low-scoring average (69.19), and earning more -- $2,515,705 -- than any other player.</p>
        <p>This year, Fleisher has not let up. He has won three events and only Hale Irwin has won as many. Fleisher has also finished second five times, including a tie for second at the Instinet Classic in Princeton, N.J., last weekend.</p>
        <p>After Quigley, the iron man of the Senior PGA Tour with appearances in 101 consecutive tournaments, birdied the first three holes, he landed his 5-iron tee shot about 18 feet from the flag on the par-3 fourth hole. But he three-putted for his only bogey. That turned out to be the difference in the first-round lead.</p>
        <p>Gene Littler, at 70 the oldest player in the field of 78, had a one-under-par 71, as did Tom Longo, the head professional at the Seawane Club in Hewlett Harbor, who is a qualifier.</p>
        <p>JACK CAVANAUGH</p>
        <p>BLAND LEADS BY TWO STROKES: John Bland shot a four-under-par 67 yesterday to take a two-stroke lead over the defending champion, Christy O'Connor Jr. of Ireland, in the Senior British Open in Newcastle, Northern Ireland.</p>
        <p>Bland recovered from a bogey at the third hole to pick up birdies at the 8th, 9th, 12th, 15th and 16th to go to seven under for the tournament.</p>
        <p>O'Connor had birdies at the last three holes for a 68, moving him to six under for two rounds. The Irishman also birdied the last three holes on Thursday. (AP)</p>
        <p>FROST LEADS BY THREE: David Frost, stringing together two runs of four consecutive birdies, shot a nine-under-par 62 yesterday for a three-stroke lead after the second round of the John Deere Classic yesterday in Silvis, Ill.</p>
        <p>Frost, who won the tournament in 1992 and 1993, finished the day 15 under at 127.</p>
        <p>Tim Herron shot a 65 for the second day in a row and was at 130. (AP)</p>
        <p>LEAD SHARED: Dominating a course yet to mature after extensive reconstruction, Helen Alfredsson and Se Ri Pak each shot a seven-under-par 65 yesterday to share the lead after the opening round of the Giant Eagle L.P.G.A. Classic in Howland, Ohio.</p>
        <p>Heavy rains Thursday night, patchy spots in the fairways and freshly sodded greens forced the L.P.G.A. to invoke the lift, clean and place rule for the 140-player field. As a result, 75 players were at par or better.</p>
        <p>Alfredsson birdied the first six holes and eight of the first nine. Pak did not have a bogey against seven birdies. Both shot their lowest opening rounds of the year.</p>
        <p>A shot back were Pat Hurst, Dale Eggeling, Michelle Redman and Michelle Murphy. (AP)</p>
        <p>NEW SPONSOR IS NEEDED: For the first time in nearly 20 years, the L.P.G.A. Tour might have only three major championships on its schedule unless it can find a new sponsor for the du Maurier Classic in Canada, Commissioner Ty Votaw said yesterday.</p>
        <p>Ideally, it would be better to have four, and we might very well have four,'' Votaw said. But we also might have three.</p>
        <p>He expects to announce a decision in the next 45 days.</p>
        <p>The du Maurier Classic, a major championship since 1979, rotates among the top courses in Canada. But it ran into trouble three years ago when legislation banned tobacco companies from sponsoring sports and cultural events.</p>
        <p>Du Maurier is a leading cigarette brand for Imperial Tobacco.</p>
        <p>Jean-Paul Blais, a former du Maurier president, has been trying to find a sponsor to keep the tournament in Canada and to retain its major championship status.</p>
        <p>Votaw said the only thing certain is that the final du Maurier Classic will be played Aug. 10 to Aug. 13 at Royal Ottawa. (AP)</p>
        <p>GOLF: ROUNDUP</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
