<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Now It's Haydl-Didl in 'Vini-der-Pu'</title>
    <meta content="29POOH" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Ideas/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218369"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Yiddish Language</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Milne, A A (1882-1956)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wolf, Leonard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carvajal, Doreen</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Winnie the Pooh (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Faroe Islands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Language and Languages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000729T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E2DC143DF93AA15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="959" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Now It's Haydl-Didl in 'Vini-der-Pu'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DOREEN CARVAJAL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Carvajal, Doreen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Yiddish edition of Winnie the Pooh, Vini-der-Pu, is published with permission of London-based trust that controls rights to A A Milne classic; translator Leonard Wolf comments; cover photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>He is the familiar bear of very little brain with a penchant for hummy days and honey and singing birds and Cottleston pies. But oh my -- or rather, Oy gevalt! -- this Winnie-the-Pooh answers to the name of Vini-der-Pu, and his tastes run to honik and Varshever torts.</p>
        <p>Almost 75 years after the chubby bear and his playmates emerged from the fertile imagination of the very British upper-middle-class author A. A. Milne, the classic children's tale has become Pooh's corner for Yiddish.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>He is the familiar bear of very little brain with a penchant for hummy days and honey and singing birds and Cottleston pies. But oh my -- or rather, Oy gevalt! -- this Winnie-the-Pooh answers to the name of Vini-der-Pu, and his tastes run to honik and Varshever torts.</p>
        <p>Almost 75 years after the chubby bear and his playmates emerged from the fertile imagination of the very British upper-middle-class author A. A. Milne, the classic children's tale has become Pooh's corner for Yiddish.</p>
        <p>The Hundred Acre Wood is inhabited by Kristofer Robin and Iya (Eeyore) and Khazerl (Piglet), who mix their choruses of tra-la-las with haydl-didl, haydl-didl dams.</p>
        <p>For years the London-based trust that presides over the rights to Winnie-the-Pooh properties had permitted the publication of the classic children's book in a stable collection of more than 30 major languages. But in the last two years Pooh has been roaming for readers in obscure new corners -- with translations planned in Faroese, Luxembourgish and Sorb, which is spoken by no more than 2,000 people in the hamlets south of Hamburg, Germany.</p>
        <p>''Vini-der-Pu'' was translated by Leonard Wolf, 77, a Romanian immigrant and former professor of English at San Francisco State University, whose goal was to publish a whimsical version of the Pooh story to counteract what he considers a widespread misperception that Yiddish is a language linked with tragedy.</p>
        <p>''All my other Yiddish translations deal with disaster,'' said Mr. Wolf, who has translated works in Yiddish by Isaac Bashevis Singer and Israel Rabon for publishers like Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux and Schocken Books. ''With the Hitler years, Yiddish came to be associated with sorrow and grief,'' he said. ''I think it will be good for people to discover that Yiddish can be used in such an affectionate way and not only as a historical demonstration of pain.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Wolf persuaded the very particular executives of the trust for the Pooh properties that a market existed for a Yiddish translation. The London-based trust had already rejected his proposal to write an annotated version of ''Winnie-the-Pooh'' because of nagging fears that his views would reflect too much of an American perspective.</p>
        <p>''Vini-der-Pu'' was published in June and soon will be followed by another exotic version, in Romansch, a dialect spoken in the Swiss canton of the Grisons, as well those in Sorb, a language similar to Serbian; Luxembourgish, a cross between Flemish and French; and Faroese, which is spoken in the Faroe Islands north of Scotland.</p>
        <p>''These translations seem to underline the fact that there is a universal appeal of the bear as an archetype,'' said John Tyerman Williams, who has made a second career of pondering the deeper meaning of Winnie-the-Pooh in books with grandiose titles like, ''Pooh and the Philosophers: In Which It Is Shown That All of Western Philosophy Is Merely a Preamble to Winnie-the-Pooh.''</p>
        <p>''I think I've got to do some more research on that,'' he added, noting that he was looking for new material after completing a third book that examines ''Winnie-the-Pooh'' and its characters as a series of psychological case studies. ''There's something in a bear as a subject,'' Mr. Williams said. ''He's British and very beloved to the upper middle class of the 1920's and 1930's, and yet he's got this appeal across classes and languages.''</p>
        <p>Yiddish presented some thorny issues for Mr. Wolf, the translator, who said that initially his literary interest in Winnie-the-Pooh grew out of his own role as a grandfather of four.</p>
        <p>The grandfather of Piglet -- Trespassers W., which stands for William -- presented a dilemma because there is no W in Yiddish. So Mr. Wolf settled on the name Maseg-gvul V., with the V standing for Velvel, a common name that he considered close enough because the V looks like one-half of W.</p>
        <p>''All translations are difficult, but that's one of the charming nuances that hang over this,'' Mr. Wolf said. ''After I did it, I was struck by how lovely it sounds in Yiddish and how it can serve people as a sign of hope that Yiddish will not be forgotten and that it has a presence that is genial.''</p>
        <p>The accuracy of these new versions is to a certain extent backed by the trust's faith in their translators.</p>
        <p>''Are these translations accurate?'' asked Peter Jenson-Smith, an executive of the Pooh Properties Trust. ''The really good translations are not literal, but they get the sense of it -- like translating Cottleston Pie to Varshever tort'' (Warsaw cake).</p>
        <p>Mr. Wolf's publisher in the United States, Dutton, has shipped a first printing of about 10,000 copies to bookstores and is preparing a second printing. It's a modest bet on the demand for ''Vini-der-Pu,'' although editors there remain optimistic that it will sell steadily over the years. Some remember when there was a burst of sales in 1991 for two Latin versions, ''Winnie Ille Pu'' and ''Winnie Ille Pu Sember Ludet'' (''The House at Pooh Corner'').</p>
        <p>Mr. Wolf's ambitions, naturally, are much grander. ''Oh, listen, with the right approach we could sell two million,'' he said. ''The right approach is to recognize a beautiful book in a beautiful language that will comfort people with memories of when they were young.''</p>
        <p>So convinced is Mr. Wolf of the demand for classics in Yiddish that he is already considering new projects, including ''Alice in Wonderland.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
