<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Economy Grew at a Robust 5.2% Rate in the Second Quarter</title>
    <meta content="Y29ECON" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218409"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Consumer Behavior</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Uchitelle, Louis</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000729T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E5D7143DF93AA15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1004" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Economy Grew at a Robust 5.2% Rate in the Second Quarter</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LOUIS UCHITELLE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Uchitelle, Louis</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>US economy exhibits surprising robustness, growing at 5.2 percent annual rate during second quarter, Commerce Department reports; slowdown in economic growth had been widely expected; investment in business, increased federal spending and manufacturing of consumer merchandise sustained economic growth; demand by consumers, however, weakened; chart (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Despite a pullback in consumer spending, the American economy grew at a surprisingly robust 5.2 percent annual rate in the second quarter, the Commerce Department reported yesterday.</p>
        <p>A widely expected slowdown failed to materialize. In fact, the economy actually grew faster in the second quarter than in the first. But for all its strength, the second quarter offered just enough signs of weakness to raise doubts about the future of the longest economic expansion in the nation's history.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Despite a pullback in consumer spending, the American economy grew at a surprisingly robust 5.2 percent annual rate in the second quarter, the Commerce Department reported yesterday.</p>
        <p>A widely expected slowdown failed to materialize. In fact, the economy actually grew faster in the second quarter than in the first. But for all its strength, the second quarter offered just enough signs of weakness to raise doubts about the future of the longest economic expansion in the nation's history.</p>
        <p>Business investment, particularly in computers and software, sustained the growth, and so did corporate willingness to churn out consumer merchandise, although consumer sales weakened. Goods piling up unsold in warehouses and stores accounted for nearly a percentage point of the 5.2 percent growth.</p>
        <p>A surge in federal government spending, mainly for the military and for the now largely completed 2000 Census, added nearly another percentage point to the growth of the gross domestic product, which is the value of all new goods and services.</p>
        <p>But the economy's future path is in the hands of consumers, whose spending accounts for most of the now $9 trillion economy.</p>
        <p>''The real question is what happens next to consumer demand; will it rebound,'' said Richard D. Rippe, chief economist at Prudential Securities. ''My guess is that it will.'' Wall Street seemed to agree that economic growth in the second half of the year would remain well above the 4 percent level. That is the maximum growth rate that the economy can sustain, in the Federal Reserve's view, before shortages of goods and services appear and prices rise. Stock prices fell in expectation that the Fed will raise interest rates again to slow the economy, if not at its next policy-making meeting on Aug. 22, then later on. Higher rates encourage investors to shift their money from stocks into interest-bearing securities.</p>
        <p>The Commerce Department also issued a revision yesterday of economic growth rates going back to the fourth quarter of 1996. The average quarterly growth rate since then was nudged up to 4.6 percent from 4.5 percent. The revisions helped President Clinton to declare that economic growth since he took office in 1993 has averaged 4 percent a year, ''the best growth America has had since the Kennedy-Johnson years.''</p>
        <p>There were big revisions for last year's fourth quarter and this year's first quarter, mostly because of inventory swings. Stockpiles swelled in the fourth, particularly stockpiles of farm produce, and as a result the growth rate was revised to 8.3 percent from 7.3 percent. In the first quarter, however, inventories were drawn down, and growth was reduced to a 4.8 percent annual rate, instead of the originally reported 5.5 percent.</p>
        <p>An upward revision in business investment also played a role in swelling economic growth in the fourth quarter. In the first quarter, however, investment in new equipment and software turned out to be weaker than originally reported, partly because of a strike at the Boeing Company, which reduced aircraft production.</p>
        <p>Business held up its end handsomely in the second quarter. There was robust spending for equipment, software, office buildings, warehouses and other commercial buildings. And the federal government raised its spending by nearly 18 percent in the second quarter, after a fall of 14 percent in the first quarter.</p>
        <p>Some of that swing reflected quirks in government accounting, but the Commerce Department reported a significant increase in military spending, not for new weaponry but for various support functions, including research, weapons repair and personnel services.</p>
        <p>Rising investment holds out the hope of rising productivity. The new equipment, in effect, helps workers increase their output and their employers' revenue. The additional revenue is then available to feed profits or raise wages, or both, without an increase in prices. Labor costs, in fact, rose at a fairly mild 4.6 percent annual rate in the second quarter -- edging up from last year's rate of increase, but unchanged from the first quarter, the Labor Department reported on Thursday.</p>
        <p>Inflation has also risen slowly. The gross domestic product report includes a price measure that is far broader than the Consumer Price Index, covering almost every price change in the economy. This price measure showed inflation rising at a 2.5 percent annual rate in the second quarter. While that rate was higher than last year's levels, partly because of gasoline prices, it declined from a rate of 3.3 percent during the first quarter.</p>
        <p>The consumers, however, will determine the pace of economic growth in the future, and the second-quarter gross domestic product report suggests they are pulling back. Consumer spending in the second quarter increased at a rate of only 3 percent, or less than half the 7.6 percent growth rate registered for the first quarter.</p>
        <p>''Consumer spending slowed for basically everything, but the really big slowdown was in motor vehicle sales,'' said Brent Moulton, associate director of national economic accounts in the Bureau of Economic Analysis in the Commerce Department.</p>
        <p>As a result, inventories of unsold goods built up at almost double the pace in the first quarter, with most of the increase in motor vehicles parked in dealers' back lots. The auto buildup almost certainly will result in a production slowdown until the inventories are worked down, said Wynn Van Bussman, corporate economist at the DaimlerChrysler Corporation.</p>
        <p>''What you will probably see is a delay or a cutback in the production of new models,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
