<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dated? Perhaps, But His Insights Remain Powerful</title>
    <meta content="29TRIL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Ideas/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218366"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Trilling, Lionel (1905-75)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rodden, John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rothstein, Edward</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Lionel Trilling and the Critics: Opposing Selves (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000729T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E3DD143DF93AA15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1446" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dated? Perhaps, But His Insights Remain Powerful</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWARD ROTHSTEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rothstein, Edward</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Edward Rothstein comment on literary criticism of Lionel Trilling 25 years after his death, in light of new essay collection, Lionel Trilling and the Critics: Opposing Selves, edited by John Rodden; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>How quaint the literary criticism of Lionel Trilling can seem, now that successive waves of structuralism, deconstruction, cultural studies, postcolonialism and other literary technologies have transformed university departments of literature. It has been a quarter-century since Trilling died, and more than a half century since he published ''The Liberal Imagination,'' his first collection of essays -- and most important book. Who now would think to write essays called ''Art and Neurosis'' or ''Manners, Morals and the Novel'' -- except to question whether the words ''art,'' ''neurosis,'' ''manners,'' ''morals'' or ''novel'' have any permanent meaning?</p>
        <p>In fact, in the 1940's, when Trilling first became a prominent intellectual as an English professor at Columbia University, the most fashionable approach to literature was known as the New Criticism. It boasted an abstract, furiously modern vision: each literary work could be analyzed without reference to the author, his life or time. Criticism was to become a science. Trilling insisted on just the opposite. Criticism, like literature, had to engage with the full mess of human life, most notably the customs and beliefs we call ''politics.'' He got more than he bargained for: politics can now seem to be a main point of literary studies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>How quaint the literary criticism of Lionel Trilling can seem, now that successive waves of structuralism, deconstruction, cultural studies, postcolonialism and other literary technologies have transformed university departments of literature. It has been a quarter-century since Trilling died, and more than a half century since he published ''The Liberal Imagination,'' his first collection of essays -- and most important book. Who now would think to write essays called ''Art and Neurosis'' or ''Manners, Morals and the Novel'' -- except to question whether the words ''art,'' ''neurosis,'' ''manners,'' ''morals'' or ''novel'' have any permanent meaning?</p>
        <p>In fact, in the 1940's, when Trilling first became a prominent intellectual as an English professor at Columbia University, the most fashionable approach to literature was known as the New Criticism. It boasted an abstract, furiously modern vision: each literary work could be analyzed without reference to the author, his life or time. Criticism was to become a science. Trilling insisted on just the opposite. Criticism, like literature, had to engage with the full mess of human life, most notably the customs and beliefs we call ''politics.'' He got more than he bargained for: politics can now seem to be a main point of literary studies.</p>
        <p>In a new collection of essays about Trilling -- ''Lionel Trilling and the Critics: Opposing Selves'' -- even the editor, John Rodden, acknowledges that for many contemporary readers Trilling may seem ''little more than a curiosity of literary history, a period piece.'' His prose style can only accentuate the impression of things long past: it is almost baroque in its winding, hesitating, qualifying, venturing gestures. The words ''variety,'' ''difficulty,'' ''modulation,'' ''complexity'' abound. Each phrase is limpid, but the arguments themselves are tentative, often ambiguous.</p>
        <p>So faded has his intellectual aura become that it provides no immunity from the recent biographical accounts by members of his family. His widow, Diana Trilling, in her 1993 memoir, ''The Beginning of the Journey,'' recalled his anguished depressions, petty squabbles and nasty outbursts. In the journal The American Scholar, his son, James Trilling, recently suggested that his father's behavior and intellectual style were consistent with a psychological diagnosis of attention deficit disorder.</p>
        <p>Yet Mr. Rodden's anthology reminds a reader that Trilling was complicated enough to be hailed by such disparate figures as Edmund Wilson and Irving Kristol. A second, more significant, new anthology, ''The Moral Obligation to Be Intelligent,'' edited by Leon Wieseltier, shows just how much is at stake. It is the most capacious and pungent single volume of Trilling's work ever published, with writings spanning his entire career: classic essays on the Kinsey Report, on Wordsworth, on Jane Austen and on Kipling. It also includes Trilling's magisterial discussion of Henry James's novel ''The Princess Casamassima.''</p>
        <p>What gives these pieces enduring importance is not Trilling's judgment that the Kinsey Report fetishizes science or that Kipling gave nationalism a bad name. The essays' subjects really were occasions for Trilling to brood on much larger themes that, far from being dated or quaint, have lost none of their urgency.</p>
        <p>''The Liberal Imagination,'' for example, was partly a critical response to the Stalinism that tinged the era's liberalism. But in the book's influential preface Trilling uncovered deeper tensions within liberalism itself. One of the great achievements of modern times, he suggested, was the liberal conception of humanity: the view that there were universal and inalienable human rights, and that the powers of reason could both honor those rights and eradicate the world's evils.</p>
        <p>The problem, Trilling went on, was that liberalism, in its search for freedom and justice, had to exert power; it required legislation and organization. Stalinism was an extreme oversimplification of liberalism, one in which the social engineering was ruthless. But even democratic liberalism, Trilling believed, exhibited a simplified view of the world and an unwavering conviction about how the world might be regulated. Since these qualities of simplification and certainty were themselves illiberal, the enlargement of freedom risked producing a contraction of freedom. ''Some paradox of our natures,'' Trilling wrote, ''leads us, when once we have made our fellow men the objects of our enlightened interest, to go on to make them the objects of our pity, then of our wisdom, ultimately of our coercion.''</p>
        <p>The impact on the mind could be even more baleful. The ambition of rationally reforming society tended to minimize the importance of the inner life, shrinking the conception of the mind. All dark desires, untamable impulses, ambivalent feelings and contradictory thoughts would then be considered failures of the outside world, imperfections in the social order that could be controlled or legislated away. In this way, liberalism risked evolving into doctrinaire puritanism -- or worse.</p>
        <p>Such was liberalism's great temptation, in Trilling's view (a view he shared with Isaiah Berlin). ''Life presses us so hard,'' he wrote, ''time is so short, the suffering of the world is so huge, simple, unendurable -- anything that complicates our moral fervor in dealing with reality as we immediately see it and wish to drive headlong upon it must be regarded with some impatience.'' And while liberalism was, in its adversary position toward the world, a transforming force, it was also, in its adversary position toward the mind, a limiting force.</p>
        <p>This is where literature came in. Trilling suggested that the variousness of literature could help shape the liberal imagination, that it could temper impatient liberal objectives with reminders of the complexities of the inner life and encourage a ''moral realism'' that could soften the demands of ''moral righteousness.'' Literature would not serve the adversary culture; it would humanize it.</p>
        <p>Because of this extended skepticism about liberalism, Trilling was often attacked by liberals for being a conservative and attacked by conservatives for not being sufficiently forthright. During the 1960's, for example, he grimly but cautiously criticized the counterculture for turning liberalism's adversary position into sweeping orthodoxies. His arguments for rejecting the simple formulations of radical liberalism did indeed have conservative implications, emphasizing limits more than possibilities. But Trilling would also have objected to the conservative impulse to simplify the relationships he perceived. Who in the midst of such complexity could afford the certainty of self-righteousness, let alone a declaration of allegiance? Complexity was Trilling's prescription for all political positions; ambiguity was the solution. Moral realism is a balancing act.</p>
        <p>The sociologist Richard Sennett once accused Trilling of refusing to take a stand during the tumult of the 1960's and the crises at Columbia University.</p>
        <p>''You have no position,'' Mr. Sennett declared. ''You are always in between.''</p>
        <p>''Between,'' Trilling replied, ''is the only honest place to be.''</p>
        <p>However honest, though, it does not make things easy. In Trilling's brilliant examination of ''The Princess Casamassima,'' the hero, Hyacinth, poor and ill-educated, is drawn to two different worlds -- one of political radicalism in which great personal sacrifice is required in the name of moral good, the other of aesthetic refinement in which the greatest achievements of Europe are presented for his delectation. He realizes that there is no separating the inequities from the great works, but then how can he be true both to his radicalism and to his aesthetic perceptions? The novel's greatness, in Trilling's view, comes from its refusal to answer the question clearly; the tension is potentially tragic. Trilling saw Hyacinth as a version of Henry James, but he may have also seen him as a reflection of himself, desperately trying to stake out a ''between.''</p>
        <p>This is one reason that reading Trilling remains so unsettling. He provides no firm place to stand. Despite his powerful analysis of liberalism, his emphasis on complexity often becomes too sweeping a response to every belief. It is partly a retreat from the world, a declaration of its untenable tensions. But his portrait of the American democratic mind, imperially pious one minute, queasily unsteady the next, illiberally making demands in the name of virtue and liberally tolerating virtue's ambiguities, celebrating reason while distrusting its demands -- this mind remains as current now as it was then. It is as familiar and as strange as Trilling's prose.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
