<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Abortion Ban Kept as Plank By the G.O.P.</title>
    <meta content="Y29PLAT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218413"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE PLATFORM"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Toner, Robin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000729T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE6D6143DF93AA15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="773" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Abortion Ban Kept as Plank By the G.O.P.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBIN TONER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Toner, Robin</byline>
      <dateline>PHILADELPHIA, July 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Republicans fight passionately over abortion, with anti-abortion forces eaily prevailing, as platform committee makes its way through document intended to balance party's core conservatism with Gov George W Bush's effort at more centrist appeal; Bush had earlier indicated that he wants no changes in abortion plank, which calls for ban on abortion without exception; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Republicans fought passionately today over abortion, with the anti-abortion forces easily prevailing, as the platform committee made its way through a document intended to balance the party's core conservatism with Gov. George W. Bush's effort at a more centrist appeal.</p>
        <p>Abortion rights supporters tried to remove the platform's abortion plank, which called for a ban on the procedure, and tried to insert a provision declaring that the party recognized differing views on the issue. Both amendments were overwhelmingly defeated in subcommittee votes, and later by the full committee, in a debate that highlighted the party's continuing fault lines.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Republicans fought passionately today over abortion, with the anti-abortion forces easily prevailing, as the platform committee made its way through a document intended to balance the party's core conservatism with Gov. George W. Bush's effort at a more centrist appeal.</p>
        <p>Abortion rights supporters tried to remove the platform's abortion plank, which called for a ban on the procedure, and tried to insert a provision declaring that the party recognized differing views on the issue. Both amendments were overwhelmingly defeated in subcommittee votes, and later by the full committee, in a debate that highlighted the party's continuing fault lines.</p>
        <p>After an abortion rights supporter read a letter from 11 members of the House and Senate, asking for change in the platform, Meribelle Bolton of New Mexico declared: ''You have to understand that many of us are under a higher authority than the Congress of the United States, the Supreme Court or any state. I am under the authority of the creator of the universe, and he is pro-life -- always has been, always will be.''</p>
        <p>Toni Casey of California, who offered the amendment to remove the abortion plank, said, ''We need a platform that recognizes and understands that abortion is a sensitive, it is a delicate, and it is a personal, moral issue between a woman and her own religion, when she is faced with that very, very difficult and complex decision.''</p>
        <p>Today's vote was not surprising; Mr. Bush and Republican leaders had indicated early on that they wanted no changes in the abortion plank, which called for a ban on abortion without exception, and the appointment of judges who respected ''the sanctity of innocent human life.'' They were keenly aware that four years ago, the party's nominee, former Senator Bob Dole, sought to add a ''tolerance'' clause, only to suffer an embarrassing defeat at the hands of the anti-abortion forces.</p>
        <p>Today, abortion rights supporters said they were disappointed but not defeated, still holding out the hope that they could get the support of a majority of six state delegations, the first step toward bringing the issue to the floor of the full convention, or perhaps getting a minority report reflecting their views out of the committee.</p>
        <p>''We're working on it,'' said Susan Cullman, head of the Republican Pro-Choice Coalition.</p>
        <p>Conservatives pushed back on other issues, including gay rights. They reinserted language, dropped in an initial draft, that declared, ''We do not believe sexual preference should be given special legal protection or standing in law.'' They declared their support for the ''traditional definition of marriage'' and denounced efforts to ''force states to recognize other living arrangements as marriages.''</p>
        <p>The day's deliberations reflected a party acutely aware of Mr. Bush's political needs, and his efforts to appeal to swing voters on issues like education, but also unwilling, at times, to compromise on core beliefs.  Some of the biggest fights, for example, came on the platform's section on education, with conservatives resisting a strong federal role on what they argued should be a matter for state and local communities and families.</p>
        <p>The 1996 platform, for example, called for the abolition of the Department of Education; the draft developed by party leaders and the Bush forces did not. But conservatives amended that draft in subcommittee today to say that the role of the federal government in education ''must be progressively limited,'' and were clearly resistant to much of the detailed education agenda put forward by the Texas governor.</p>
        <p>The platform committee, pushed hard by its chairman, Gov. Tommy G. Thompson of Wisconsin, was reading and voting on the platform into the night, and expected to finish its work on Saturday. The full convention will act on the platform on Monday. The committee is working so fast that part of the ''tolerance'' provision on abortion was passed tonight, until several delegates said they were confused about what they were voting on and asked to reconsider their vote. It then was defeated.</p>
        <p>Ann Stone of Republicans for Choice said, ''Just think, we were welcome for 10 or 15 minutes; that's real progress.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE PLATFORM</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
