<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Postseason Is Agreeing With Edmonds</title>
    <meta content="10CARD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/10/sports/10CARD.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237640"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="2000 PLAYOFFS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">St Louis Cardinals</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Atlanta Braves</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brown, Clifton</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Edmonds, Jim</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Atlanta Braves</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/St Louis Cardinals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001010T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E0DC113CF933A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="840" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Postseason Is Agreeing With Edmonds</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFTON BROWN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brown, Clifton</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Play of St Louis Cardinals outfielder Jim Edmonds in sweep of Atlanta Braves in National League division series discussed; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Great players do not always enjoy great postseasons. Ask Barry Bonds or Frank Thomas.</p>
        <p>But as the St. Louis Cardinals prepare to face the Mets for the National League pennant, Jim Edmonds knows he followed a terrific regular season by raising his game in the playoffs. Leading the Cardinals to a stunning three-game sweep of the Atlanta Braves, Edmonds batted .571 with two homers and seven runs batted in while setting a division-series record with six extra-base hits.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Great players do not always enjoy great postseasons. Ask Barry Bonds or Frank Thomas.</p>
        <p>But as the St. Louis Cardinals prepare to face the Mets for the National League pennant, Jim Edmonds knows he followed a terrific regular season by raising his game in the playoffs. Leading the Cardinals to a stunning three-game sweep of the Atlanta Braves, Edmonds batted .571 with two homers and seven runs batted in while setting a division-series record with six extra-base hits.</p>
        <p>Just as containing the Giants' Bonds was a priority for the Mets in their last series, stopping Edmonds will be priority No. 1 for their pitchers when the four-of-seven-game N.L. Championship Series begins tomorrow night at Busch Stadium.</p>
        <p>Is Edmonds, in his first postseason, surprised by his playoff success? In a season in which Mark McGwire has been slowed by injuries, Edmonds led the Cardinals in home runs (42), runs batted in (108), runs scored (129), walks (103) and game-winning R.B.I. (19) while playing spectacularly in center field. Why should he be shocked by his performance?</p>
        <p>''Jimmy Edmonds has been this team's M.V.P.,'' said Will Clark, who bats cleanup behind Edmonds in the lineup, giving the Cardinals a dangerous 1-2 left-handed punch. ''All season long, he carried the load, and he has really stepped it up, not only offensively but defensively.''</p>
        <p>The Mets won their season series with St. Louis, six games to three, but Edmonds hit .278 with four home runs and six R.B.I. against them. And in a three-game sweep of the Mets in September, Edmonds ended two of the games with solo homers, a ninth-inning shot on Sept. 1 against Pat Mahomes and an 11th-inning shot on Sept. 3 against Rick White.</p>
        <p>That type of clutch hitting has made Edmonds a hero in St. Louis, and more fans have begun to chant ''M.V.P., M.V.P.'' whenever he steps into the batter's box. For Edmonds, the off-season trade that brought him to St. Louis from the Anaheim Angels -- for Kent Bottenfield and Adam Kennedy -- has been a godsend. Edmonds played six seasons for the Angels and was one of their most productive players, yet he earned a reputation as being a selfish player and a difficult teammate.</p>
        <p>Edmonds calls that portrayal unfair, fueled by only a few former teammates and the news media. But there is no doubt that Edmonds has felt more accepted with the Cardinals, and his comfort level has been reflected in his performance.</p>
        <p>''To go from an underachieving team to a team that has everything going is pretty fun,'' Edmonds said. ''We do not have the problems as in Anaheim, the jealousy, the bickering. This team is a team.''</p>
        <p>Edmonds has become the heart of the team, a player who can alter a game with his bat, his glove, his legs or his arm. Edmonds routinely makes spectacular catches while playing a shallow and daring center field. Few outfielders get a better jump on a ball than Edmonds does, and his signature catch has become the over-the-shoulder grab with his back turned to the infield. Edmonds made one of those catches against the Braves, changing direction at the last moment to rob Rafael Furcal of an extra-base hit.</p>
        <p>''If you see us play, you will see him do at least one of those every series,'' Manager Tony La Russa of the Cardinals said. ''He is a complete center fielder because he has range in four directions. And he is probably the most accurate thrower with a strong arm that I have seen.''</p>
        <p>The biggest negative regarding Edmonds this year was his strikeouts. He had 167 of them, second most in the National League, and he struck out 17 times in 36 at-bats against the Mets. But he struck out just twice in 17 at-bats in the division series with the Braves after making an effort to make better contact.</p>
        <p>''We did not go up there trying to swing for the fences,'' Edmonds said. ''We tried to peck away, get a run here and there, and we got big hits.''</p>
        <p>The Cardinals scored at least seven runs in all three games against Atlanta, hammering one of baseball's best pitching staffs, 24-10. Now the Cardinals have turned their attention to the Mets. And while it is hard to imagine Edmonds playing any better than he did against Atlanta, he saw no reason he wouldn't.</p>
        <p>''You have to understand you're in a big situation, but it's still baseball,'' Edmonds said. ''Never be surprised by success. This is a great time of year, and we have a chance to go to the World Series. We've worked hard to get in this situation, and we've been winning all year. If we play our best baseball, we're going to be difficult to beat.''</p>
        <p>2000 PLAYOFFS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
