<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ex-Transit Chief Takes On London's Ailing Subway</title>
    <meta content="10KILE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/10/nyregion/10KILE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237672"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Subways</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">London (Eng)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Metropolitan Transportation Authority</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kennedy, Randy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kiley, Robert R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England/London</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Subways</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001010T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04EED9113CF933A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1017" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ex-Transit Chief Takes On London's Ailing Subway</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RANDY KENNEDY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kennedy, Randy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Robert R Kiley, who as chairman of Metropolitan Transportation Authority from 1983-1990 is credited with rebuilding New York City's subway system, is named to head London's ailing subway system; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>By British tabloid standards, the reception yesterday was almost like a hero's welcome: ''New York Tough Guy to Run Tube,'' announced the headline in The Evening Standard.</p>
        <p>It might seem strange, from a country that has long prided itself on its fastidiously punctual train service. But England now has among the worst commuter and subway lines in Europe.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>By British tabloid standards, the reception yesterday was almost like a hero's welcome: ''New York Tough Guy to Run Tube,'' announced the headline in The Evening Standard.</p>
        <p>It might seem strange, from a country that has long prided itself on its fastidiously punctual train service. But England now has among the worst commuter and subway lines in Europe.</p>
        <p>Web sites have even sprung up to lambaste the London Underground, or the Tube, one bearing this motto: ''I am not a sardine. No, by God, I am a human being.''</p>
        <p>So when London officials announced yesterday that they would try to fix the New York-esque problems of their subway system by importing an American -- Robert R. Kiley, who helped rebuild the crumbling New York subway in the 1980's -- very little wounded British pride was on display.</p>
        <p>While London's subway, the oldest in the world, is still considered cleaner and faster than New York's, it has recently fallen on relatively hard times, with investment in repairs lagging even as ridership and crowding have increased sharply.</p>
        <p>In fact, delays and breakdowns have grown so prevalent that public transportation became the most important issue in the race for the first elected mayor of London. And the candidate who won in May, Ken Livingstone, ran on a platform that included bringing the system back to a more Victorian efficiency.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kiley, who served as chairman of the Metropolitan Transportation Authority from 1983 to 1990, will become commissioner of an agency called Transport for London, which was created this summer to oversee not only subway operations, but also bus service, taxis, traffic lights, ferries and some light rail and roads.</p>
        <p>The London Underground will not be under the agency's direct control for several months, until the new city government decides whether to privatize parts of the subway system. But it was clear that Mr. Kiley, 65, was chosen because of the role he played in revitalizing New York City's subway lines.</p>
        <p>During his seven years on the job, he was instrumental in winning state approval to put billions of dollars in bond-backed investment into New York's transit system, a rebuilding program that had started under Mr. Kiley's predecessor, Richard Ravitch. The rehabilitation addressed decades of official neglect and brought about the virtual elimination of graffiti, the repair of miles of tracks and the replacement or rebuilding of thousands of subway cars.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kiley, who will step down as president and chief executive of the New York City Partnership, an alliance of major businesses, will be paid slightly more than $360,000 a year for the London post. But as part of the deal, he can double his salary with bonuses if bus and subway service improves, meaning he could earn about $2.9 million over four years, Mr. Livingstone said.</p>
        <p>In a written statement, he acknowledged that the pay was high by British public service standards. But he added that ''if Transport for London is able over this period to make real progress in solving the capital's transport crisis, Londoners will consider this cheap at the price.''</p>
        <p>In a telephone interview yesterday, Mr. Kiley said he made up his mind on Sunday to take the offer. His decision followed three weeks of talks with Mr. Livingstone and other officials, and a trip to London with his wife in early October to discuss  the job.</p>
        <p>He said the offer came about almost by accident: Mr. Kiley was first called as a reference for another candidate for the post. But the leaders of the search committee then began to ask him whether he was interested.</p>
        <p>''I was relucant in no small part because I've become very implanted in New York, and the idea of pulling up the roots was very difficult to deal with,'' Mr. Kiley said. But he added that he grew excited about the challenge of trying to turn around another ailing transit system, especially one as storied as the London Underground.</p>
        <p>''There has clearly been a decline in investment and maintenance in the system, and it's beginning to show,'' Mr. Kiley said. ''It may not be as bad as it was New York in the mid-80's, but it's getting there.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kiley, who once headed Boston's transit system and was an unsuccessful candidate for mayor there, will immediately have to confront several problems reminiscent of those that plagued the New York system in the early 1980's.</p>
        <p>The London system, which has an annual ridership of about 900 million, is not as busy as New York's, which carries about 1.3 billion a year.</p>
        <p>But the systems are roughly equal in size, New York's with 238 route miles and London's with about 243.</p>
        <p>Escalators, crucial in London because of the depth of many of the subway lines, have been breaking down frequently, so often that the transit agency now posts a weekly escalator update on its Web site. Crime, especially pickpocketing and other nonviolent crimes, has been increasing. (A notice on the Tube Web site yesterday announced that one subway station had been closed because its platforms had been vandalized.) And breakdowns are much more frequent than in the past..</p>
        <p>The sentiment among typical London Underground riders seems to be one of weariness. So a comment by one rider yesterday on a Web site devoted to criticizing the subways -- www.tubehell.com -- might be taken as representative of the feeling about Mr. Kiley's imminent arrival: ''Sounds promising. He certainly can't make things any worse.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
