<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tragedy in Israel and Vandalism Here Darken Yom Kippur</title>
    <meta content="10KIPP$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/10/nyregion/10KIPP.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237708"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Anti-Semitism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vandalism</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Waldman, Amy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Anti-Semitism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vandalism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001010T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E0D7113CF933A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="936" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tragedy in Israel and Vandalism Here Darken Yom Kippur</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AMY WALDMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Waldman, Amy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Yom Kippur worshipers at Conservative Synagogue Adath Israel in Riverdale section of Bronx discuss their sorrow over act of vandalism against their synagogue as well as increase in violence in Middle East; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As Yom Kippur worshipers at Conservative Synagogue Adath Israel in the Riverdale section of the Bronx filed out of services at midday yesterday, two police detectives and an agent from the federal Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco and Firearms combed the building's perimeter and the woodsy area around it.</p>
        <p>They examined windows and poked through leaves and climbed an outcropping just north of the synagogue, which is on West 250th Street and the Henry Hudson Parkway. They were looking, one detective said, ''for anything and everything.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As Yom Kippur worshipers at Conservative Synagogue Adath Israel in the Riverdale section of the Bronx filed out of services at midday yesterday, two police detectives and an agent from the federal Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco and Firearms combed the building's perimeter and the woodsy area around it.</p>
        <p>They examined windows and poked through leaves and climbed an outcropping just north of the synagogue, which is on West 250th Street and the Henry Hudson Parkway. They were looking, one detective said, ''for anything and everything.''</p>
        <p>Over the weekend, a vandal hurled a bottle of purplish liquid at the synagogue, shattering a glass door. Given the escalating violence in the Middle East, the rise in street protests here and several possibly anti-Semitic incidents across the city in recent days, it was enough to prompt a round-the-clock presence by the police, and sentiments both anxious and mournful by worshipers.</p>
        <p>''This is minor, but it has its effect,'' said Richard Newberger, 33, standing outside the synagogue after the morning's services. ''You just don't know what will happen next.''</p>
        <p>Across the region yesterday, a holiday already somber by ancient tradition was for many layered with additional seriousness and worry. Yom Kippur is the holiest day of the year for Jews, a time for contemplation, reflection on the year past, and of atonement to God for vows not kept. This year, as a startling chill descended on the city, it was also an occasion for reflecting on a situation edging perilously close to war.</p>
        <p>''Rosh Hashana and Yom Kippur are days of thinking, of reaching into yourself to correct the mistakes you make,'' said Ralph Davidson, 82, waiting for the evening service to begin at Ansche Chesed,'' a Conservative synagogue on West 100th Street in Manhattan. ''Yet people on these days are creating torment, torture and destruction. This should be incomprehensible to all people.''</p>
        <p>A specific torment was heavy on the minds of the members of Congregation Beth Torah in Brooklyn's Midwood neighborhood. Over the weekend, Hillel Lieberman, the son of  Rabbi Sidney Zvulun Lieberman, was killed after being abducted by Palestinian militants.</p>
        <p>Scores of families trudged, heads  low, past police cars to Yom Kippur services at the synagogue, at 1061 Ocean Parkway. Most chose not to speak with reporters, and some wept openly. A few spoke of both their rabbi's loss and their own mounting fears for loved ones in Israel.</p>
        <p>''It's a horror for all of us,'' said Rhonda Baum, 50, who lives in Midwood and worships at Beth Torah. ''I think we were all hoping that the violence over there wouldn't touch us so directly.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Baum said she worried that the violence could touch her even more directly: she has nieces and nephews living in Elon More, the Jewish West Bank settlement where Hillel Lieberman had lived since immigrating to Israel 14 years ago.</p>
        <p>''You can't help but wonder if your family will be next,'' she said. ''I don't know if my nieces and nephews are safe traveling in and out of the area or if they're in the middle of it. We're just praying for them and for Rabbi Lieberman, even for the Arabs who are also losing their loved ones.''</p>
        <p>Israeli officials said Mr. Lieberman was found in a gully near the Palestinian-controlled town of Nablus, which is about three miles from his village. Mr. Lieberman had apparently been trying to rescue artifacts from the Jewish holy site known as Joseph's Tomb.</p>
        <p>Rabbi Lieberman said on Sunday that he was a distant cousin of Senator Joseph I. Lieberman. The Democratic vice-presidential campaign said yesterday that it was still trying to determine what, if any, family connection existed.</p>
        <p>Police cars were parked along Ocean Parkway and plainclothes officers lined the entrance to the synagogue. Meant to allay fear, Ms. Baum said the increased police presence actually increased it.</p>
        <p>''It's a little frightening,'' she said. ''You see them and you're reminded that anything can happen, even in this neighborhood.''</p>
        <p>Police officers on patrol were told to pay close attention to both synagogues and mosques, the police said. Police officials added that they had no indication that the incident in Riverdale and what appeared to be anti-Semitic incidents in Brooklyn last week were the work of a coordinated group.</p>
        <p>Members at Adath Israel were perturbed, but calm, in part because this is not the first time the synagogue has been struck by vandals.</p>
        <p>One member and Riverdale resident, Jeremy Newberger, said his jeep had also been painted with anti-Semitic slurs a year ago. ''There's no safe place,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Steven Ungar, 54, said that the attack on Adath Israel was disturbing, but should be kept in perspective. ''I think we can go overboard about these things,'' he said, saying he suspected local youths were responsible. ''Everyday on the news you see kids throwing rocks. If you're a kid maybe it gives you an idea.''</p>
        <p>But, he said, the incident ''scared a lot of old people here. They are Holocaust survivors. They don't see things in the context I see it.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, for Ruth Jacobs, 72, a member of Adath Israel for 31 years, context was everything. ''We have lost a lot,'' she said, her accent giving away her Czech roots. ''Maybe it affects us more than other people.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
