<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Onetime Milosevic Mouthpiece Remakes Itself</title>
    <meta content="Y10BEL$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/10/world/10BELG.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237639"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Propaganda</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom of the Press</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Serbia</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Politika (Newspaper)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cohen, Roger</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Milosevic, Slobodan (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Antic, Dragan Hadzi</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom of the Press</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Propaganda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001010T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E1DC113CF933A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1300" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Onetime Milosevic Mouthpiece Remakes Itself</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROGER COHEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cohen, Roger</byline>
      <dateline>BELGRADE, Serbia, Oct. 9</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Politika, Belgrade daily newspaper that was once a party organ of Slobodan Milosevic, is adjusting to an abruptly changed political landscape in Serbia; Dragan Hadzi Antic, newspaper's editor, appears to be in hiding; the new Politika promises objectivity, but whether its journalists, who long churned out Milosevic's propaganda, can really reinvent themselves overnight as spokesmen of a free press remains to be seen; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the government of Slobodan Milosevic tottered last Thursday, the editor of the newspaper Politika quietly slipped out the back door of his huge office and disappeared, leaving five half-drunk glasses of whiskey on a table, cold coffee in a pot and one of post-revolutionary Serbia's greatest political prizes up for grabs.</p>
        <p>Dragan Hadzi Antic, the editor of the daily that was the fallen government's mouthpiece and a former boyfriend of Mr. Milosevic's daughter, Marija, is believed to be in hiding in Belgrade. Meanwhile, a fierce battle has begun for control of Politika, which has reinvented itself with mind-bending abruptness.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As the government of Slobodan Milosevic tottered last Thursday, the editor of the newspaper Politika quietly slipped out the back door of his huge office and disappeared, leaving five half-drunk glasses of whiskey on a table, cold coffee in a pot and one of post-revolutionary Serbia's greatest political prizes up for grabs.</p>
        <p>Dragan Hadzi Antic, the editor of the daily that was the fallen government's mouthpiece and a former boyfriend of Mr. Milosevic's daughter, Marija, is believed to be in hiding in Belgrade. Meanwhile, a fierce battle has begun for control of Politika, which has reinvented itself with mind-bending abruptness.</p>
        <p>''Democracy comes to Serbia,'' screamed the first post-revolutionary edition, cobbled together after Mr. Antic fled. Days earlier, the front page had been devoted to a Chinese analysis of the ''ruthless interference of the West'' in Yugoslavia, describing how the ''worst anti-Yugoslav forces'' wanted to manipulate the presidential election to achieve ''what NATO did not get by bombing.''</p>
        <p>The new Politika promises objectivity. But can the journalists, minus Mr. Antic, who long churned out Mr. Milosevic's often preposterous propaganda, really reinvent themselves overnight as ardent admirers of a free press?</p>
        <p>The question goes to the heart of the quandary facing a country where huge numbers of long-compliant or conniving people -- in the media, the police, the military and elsewhere -- are scurrying to garb themselves in once scorned democratic attire that may save their skins as Vojislav Kostunica takes power.</p>
        <p>The paper is run under a labyrinthine shareholding structure that benefited cronies of Mr. Milosevic, including the directors of a major bank and of the largest Serbian oil company. Its ownership also poses the central question of how best to undo the huge vested economic interests built up under Mr. Milosevic's state-sponsored thuggery.</p>
        <p>Slavica Cedic, the national editor and now one of the 20 members of a  ''crisis committee'' running Politika, has been at the paper for 22 years. She says that she is committed to the policy of ''true and full information'' that it announced Saturday, adding that she was often uncomfortable with the line Mr. Milosevic dictated.</p>
        <p>''Twice I even did think of resigning,'' she said, ''but I was always thinking of how to survive and earn money and there are not so many papers in Serbia.''</p>
        <p>And on what occasions, in the 13 Milosevic years, did she want to quit? ''It was more of an accumulation of discontent,'' Ms. Cedic continued. ''But when I was instructed to write that state pensions would be paid but not say for which month, so that the long delays in payments would not be clear, I thought I could not go on writing this way.''</p>
        <p>She paused and smiled wanly: ''But then you remember your children, and the many unemployed, and you shrug. And you think, well, perhaps, this will change one day and you hope that one day Milosevic will go.''</p>
        <p>Things have changed and Mr. Milosevic has gone, and Ms. Cedic, who shrugged, now finds herself in the small team running the paper. The upheaval began a week ago, three days before the revolution, when 56 journalists -- close to half the journalistic staff -- signed a petition to Mr. Antic demanding that the paper be ''democratized.''</p>
        <p>Radovan Lazarevic, the journalist now running the Politika company, which includes several other publications, said Mr. Antic did not respond to the petition. ''So last Thursday morning, before Parliament was stormed, 48 of us went on strike. But then events overtook us.''</p>
        <p>As those events removed Milosevic cronies, they revealed some extraordinary things. The circulation of the paper had been ''top secret'' under Mr. Antic's direction. That may seem surprising in a nominally ''privatized'' company with shareholders, but then Mr. Milosevic's Serbia was a surprising sort of place.</p>
        <p>What Mr. Lazarevic and Ms. Cedic discovered was that the print run of Politika was 170,000 copies, but 100,000 of those were distributed to the police, the army, members of Mr. Milosevic's Socialist Party of Serbia, members of his wife's leftist party and the bureaucracy.</p>
        <p>''We are now on a fact-finding mission to find out the nature of the company,'' Ms. Cedic said. ''Before people were paralyzed with fear and did not dare ask anything, even though employees did pay from their salaries for 'shares' in Politika.''</p>
        <p>The so-called privatization of the paper was completed this summer, with 35 percent of shares formally left in state hands, and the rest divided among present and former employees, private companies and state companies. The net result is hard to judge, but it appears that more than 50 percent of Politika remains in state hands.</p>
        <p>What is clear is that Mr. Milosevic had absolute control of this officially private enterprise. Among the shareholders are the Commercial Bank, run by Ljuba Mihailovic, one of Mr. Milosevic's closest associates, and the Nis oil company, run by Dragan Tomic, the speaker of the Serbian Parliament and another leading Milosevic ally.</p>
        <p>In addition, Mr. Antic was known as one of the people closest to the former ruler, often being photographed next to him at public occasions and long courting Mr. Milosevic's daughter, whose own television station, Kosava, has been off the air since Thursday. Her whereabouts are also unknown.</p>
        <p>''In the area of politics, the line was dictated 100 percent by Mr. Milosevic,'' said Ms. Cedic. From that came the endless front-page atricles on the fraternal nations like Belorussia and Libya that, with Yugoslavia, would one day lead the charge against American imperialism.</p>
        <p>The tangled ownership of Politika points to a central problem facing  the new president. The soft dictatorship of Mr. Milosevic's later years involved the fabulous enrichment of close associates given effective control over whole sectors of the economy. Privatization amounted to state control by other means.</p>
        <p>Ousting the people in control of that system will not be easy because huge interests are at stake. At Politika, founded in 1904 in Serbia, 14 years before the creation of the state that would become Yugoslavia, those interests center not on money but on political control of a paper whose name is still hugely resonant. Politika's reputation was solid until it was purged by Mr. Milosevic when he gained power in 1987.</p>
        <p>Already, some political parties, including the Radical Party of Vojislav Seselj, a sometime ally of Mr. Milosevic, have announced moves to control the paper. Mr. Seselj has proposed a ''nationalization'' of the paper that would formally recognize that 51 percent of Politika remains in state hands.</p>
        <p>In the Serbian Parliament, the parties of Mr. Seselj, Mr. Milosevic and his wife hold a majority, making them a potentially formidable force.</p>
        <p>''We reject these proposals,'' said Ms. Cedic, ''because our commitment is now to printing all points of view, and to objectivity.'' But she seemed unsure as to what ownership structure would best suit those aims.</p>
        <p>As she spoke, officials from one of the main parties backing Mr. Kostunica were visiting Politika, an indication that the new president's team is watching the paper closely. It has made a strong new start, selling all 140,000 copies printed on Saturday.</p>
        <p>Ms. Cedic was asked how the new government and Serbian society should respond to people like herself becoming overnight enthusiasts for democracy. ''I believe the opposition knew what we really thought,'' she said. ''We all know how we lived under Milosevic and have understanding for each other, for why we had to be silent at certain times. The Serbian people forgive easily.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
