<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Doctor Like This? You Should Be So Lucky</title>
    <meta content="10JAME" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/10/arts/10JAME.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237596"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">James, Caryn</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Braugher, Andre</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">McGill, Bruce</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Gideon's Crossing (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001010T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DEFD7103CF933A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1153" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Doctor Like This? You Should Be So Lucky</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CARYN JAMES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">James, Caryn</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Caryn James reviews ABC television program Gideon's Crossing; photo of Andre Braugher and Bruce McGill (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Near the end of the powerful opening episode of ''Gideon's Crossing,'' the camera closes in on Andre Braugher as Ben Gideon, the head of experimental medicine at a Boston hospital. Jogging on a foggy road at night, he is explaining to a friend how he argued with his wife as she was dying of ovarian cancer. ''Bitter fights,'' Mr. Braugher says with restraint, shaking his head and allowing pain to flicker across his face as if it had risen from the depths of his soul. He had wanted her to resist death longer; she was ready to let go. ''Things I said to this poor dying woman,'' he says slowly, his subtle performance capturing all the shades of Gideon's emotions.</p>
        <p>By then it is clear that ''Gideon's Crossing'' is not just another hospital series. With a deep and perplexing hero, a wide social reach and uncommon eloquence, it instantly takes a place among the best dramas on television.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Near the end of the powerful opening episode of ''Gideon's Crossing,'' the camera closes in on Andre Braugher as Ben Gideon, the head of experimental medicine at a Boston hospital. Jogging on a foggy road at night, he is explaining to a friend how he argued with his wife as she was dying of ovarian cancer. ''Bitter fights,'' Mr. Braugher says with restraint, shaking his head and allowing pain to flicker across his face as if it had risen from the depths of his soul. He had wanted her to resist death longer; she was ready to let go. ''Things I said to this poor dying woman,'' he says slowly, his subtle performance capturing all the shades of Gideon's emotions.</p>
        <p>By then it is clear that ''Gideon's Crossing'' is not just another hospital series. With a deep and perplexing hero, a wide social reach and uncommon eloquence, it instantly takes a place among the best dramas on television.</p>
        <p>Gideon is a hero for an age so cynical about doctors that it needs to believe in heroic healers more than ever. In this episode he has already treated an arrogant businessman who has a rare and vicious disease. (''I'm not a wizard,'' Gideon warns. The patient snaps, ''You better be 'cause I need one.'') He has wrestled with the reasons for taking on this apparently hopeless case. How much is for his ego and reputation? How much to try to save a life? How can he ever tell the difference?</p>
        <p>He has dealt with his three small children as well as a half-dozen interns and residents who are scarcely more mature. One examines the dog of a hospital benefactor and admits the pooch for treatment.</p>
        <p>Even as the series casts a harshly realistic light on the medical profession, it balances that toughness with an idealistic glow. It does, after all, need to draw viewers back every week. Paradoxically, part of Gideon's nobility is his self-awareness; he wouldn't be so heroic if he weren't so hard on himself.</p>
        <p>The show's alchemy owes a lot to the combination of Mr. Braugher's portrayal and the intelligent approach of its creator and writer, Paul Attanasio. He was a creator of the series ''Homicide,'' on which Mr. Braugher gained his reputation as the intense, morally questioning Frank Pembleton. Just as ''Homicide'' was less about solving a crime than about the workings of the detectives' minds, so ''Gideon's Crossing'' is about how the doctors feel and think.</p>
        <p>A doctor's mind can be a scary place. Gideon's colleagues range from the high-minded to the mercenary. His friend and confidant is the solid Dr. Max Cabranes (Ruben Blades), the head of the hospital and so far the only other person who seems to be keeping his sanity.</p>
        <p>The residents and interns so dread failure that their insecurity is matched only by their budding God-complexes. One compares the hospital's power structure to a medieval kingdom. Maybe he's not imagining that, but his extended metaphor offers a glimpse of the sparing, effective literary touches that give the dialogue a poetic tone. ''A lab report is like free verse,'' the chief resident instructs an intern in a future episode. ''It's just words until you interpret it.''</p>
        <p>The businessman whom Gideon treats in tonight's episode is forced to assess his life, which leads to a stunning emotional twist. Whether the patient lives or dies, the series resists finding hope in pat endings. Its uplift comes in sidelights, like Gideon making breakfast for his children, or less effectively here in the strained comic relief of the dog.</p>
        <p>And it seems that the show will keep its edge. In one future episode a man goes to the emergency room and faces everyone's medical nightmare, a chain of human mistakes. ''A patient comes in healthy, we send him out dead,'' as Gideon puts it.</p>
        <p>Tonight's premiere will be shown with no breaks, just commercials before and after from Johnson &amp; Johnson, apparently hoping that all this medical talk will make viewers hanker for a Band-Aid. The gimmick allows the episode to run about 10 minutes longer than it would have, but the places for commercials are obvious. The show does not break the mold for television drama; it recasts it into a bold new shape.</p>
        <p>Yet ABC's banal promo for the show, ''Where television goes to get better,'' is so out of sync with the series' grace that it makes you fear for its life. Next week the show moves to its regular slot, Wednesdays at 10 against the fierce competition of ''Law and Order.'' It takes nothing away from the smart, streamlined entertainment that is ''Law and Order'' to say that ''Gideon's Crossing'' belongs to a different, higher realm of drama.</p>
        <p>THE GEENA DAVIS SHOW  ABC, tonight at 9:30  (Channel 7 in New York)</p>
        <p>As the stupidest stepmom in the world, Geena Davis glides around her new sitcom with a huge grin that says, ''Aren't I cute?'' That attitude is not likely to endear her to the stepchildren or television viewers. The message she ought to be sending is: ''Help! I'm an Oscar-winning movie star trapped in a pathetic, cliched series.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Davis plays a sophisticated woman from Manhattan named Teddie who owns a public relations company. In little more than a month (a brief opening flashback tonight) she falls for a widower with two children and finds herself living in the suburbs. In real life he would have been divorced; the series has cut out the pesky ex-wife, but otherwise the idea of ''Sex and the City'' moving to the burbs has possibilities.</p>
        <p>But the inane writing makes Teddie a throwback to the birdbrained housewife character, even if she does have a career. Suddenly she turns so idiotic she forgets it's a good idea to wear pants when there's a teenage boy in the house. Next week she bakes a cake; a risque punch line does not make that tired premise any funnier. No one around Teddie has developed a personality either, including Peter Horton as the man who, inexplicably, is charmed by her routine.</p>
        <p>GIDEON'S CROSSING  ABC, tonight at 10  (Channel 7 in New York)</p>
        <p>Paul Attanasio, creator; based on the book ''The Measure of our Days'' by Jerome Groopman, M.D.; Mr. Attanasio, Katie Jacobs and Eric Overmyer, executive producers; Randy Zisk, co-executive producers; produced by Touchstone Television Productions.</p>
        <p>WITH: Andre Braugher (Dr. Ben Gideon), Ruben Blades (Dr. Max Cabranes), Russell Hornsby (Dr. Aaron Boies), Hamish Linklater (Dr. Bruce Cherry), Eric Dane (Dr. Wyatt Cooper), Rhona Mitra (Dr. Ollie Klein), Ravi Kapoor (Dr. Sid Shandar), Sophie Keller (Dr. Maya Stiles), Marianne Muellerleile (Mrs. Henna), Brian Wiltshire (Charlie Gideon), Jascha Washington (Eli Gideon), Meagan Gregory (Rose Gideon) and Kevin J. O'Connor (Dr. Michael Pirandello).</p>
        <p>TELEVISION REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
