<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Morton Zolotow, 69, Manager of Leading Theaters</title>
    <meta content="Y10ZOLO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Obituaries" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/10/arts/10ZOLO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237626"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Deaths (Obituaries)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zolotow, Morton A</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Obituary (Obit)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Obituaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Deaths (Obituaries)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001010T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E2DD113CF933A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="343" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Morton Zolotow, 69, Manager of Leading Theaters</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Morton A Zolotow, theater manager, dies at age 69 (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Morton A. Zolotow, a theater manager who administered the backstage traffic at some of the nation's grandest auditoriums, died on Sept. 15 at a hospital in Chicago. He was 69.</p>
        <p>The cause was pancreatic cancer, said Kathy Zolotow, his wife.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Morton A. Zolotow, a theater manager who administered the backstage traffic at some of the nation's grandest auditoriums, died on Sept. 15 at a hospital in Chicago. He was 69.</p>
        <p>The cause was pancreatic cancer, said Kathy Zolotow, his wife.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zolotow, a native New Yorker, graduated from Columbia University in the early 1950's with a degree in fine arts. But his show business education had begun much earlier: his father was Sam Zolotow, longtime theater columnist for The New York Times, and the family was friendly with celebrities like Jack Benny and Groucho Marx.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zolotow's first job was in public relations, setting up lavish post-screening parties for films like ''Around the World in 80 Days.'' But his life, like his father's, quickly gravitated toward the theatrical.</p>
        <p>During the next two decades, Mr. Zolotow managed several Broadway theaters, including the Helen Hayes and the Morosco, both now demolished. In the 1960's, he was manager at one of New York's biggest showcases, Carnegie Hall. He oversaw the booking and handling of everything from solo acts by the likes of Harry Belafonte and Vladimir Horowitz to a production of ''South Pacific'' with Mary Martin.</p>
        <p>In 1969, he moved to Chicago, where he was manager of that city's Blackstone Theater (now known as the Merle Reskin Theater) and the Shubert Theater. There, too, Mr. Zolotow handled an array of shows -- ballet, rock concerts, touring musicals. And with each, he often attended the cast parties, rubbing elbows and sharing backstage anecdotes with the likes of Ella Fitzgerald and Ethel Merman.</p>
        <p>In 1977, he took over management of the Auditorium Theater, where he worked until his retirement in 1989.</p>
        <p>In addition to his wife, Mr. Zolotow is survived by his children, Jonathan, and Amy; two sisters, Leah Levy of Boston and Suzanne Berman of Boca Raton, Fla., and a brother, David Zolotow of Key West, Fla.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
