<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Continental Makes Bid for US Air Assets</title>
    <meta content="Y10AIR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/10/business/10AIR.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237660"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ual Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Continental Airlines</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">US Airways</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Airlines</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">DC Air</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bethune, Gordon</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnson, Robert (Black Entertainment TV)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gilpin, Kenneth N</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001010T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E4D9113CF933A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="733" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Continental Makes Bid for US Air Assets</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KENNETH N. GILPIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gilpin, Kenneth N</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Continental Airlines offers $215 million for assets that US Airways Group plans to spin off in Washington as part of its proposed purchase by parent of United Airlines; offer represents premium of more than 50 percent above $141 million offer by Robert Johnson, member of US Airways board and founder of Black Entertainment Television; Johnson plans to create regional carrier called DC Air (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Continental Airlines offered yesterday to buy the assets that the US Airways Group plans to spin off in Washington as part of its proposed purchase by the parent of United Airlines.</p>
        <p>In letters made public yesterday, Gordon Bethune, the chairman and chief executive of Continental, the nation's fifth-largest carrier, offered to pay $215 million for the assets. That would be a premium of more than 50 percent above the $141 million offer made by Robert Johnson, a member of the US Airways board and the founder of Black Entertainment Television. Mr. Johnson plans to create a regional carrier called DC Air.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Continental Airlines offered yesterday to buy the assets that the US Airways Group plans to spin off in Washington as part of its proposed purchase by the parent of United Airlines.</p>
        <p>In letters made public yesterday, Gordon Bethune, the chairman and chief executive of Continental, the nation's fifth-largest carrier, offered to pay $215 million for the assets. That would be a premium of more than 50 percent above the $141 million offer made by Robert Johnson, a member of the US Airways board and the founder of Black Entertainment Television. Mr. Johnson plans to create a regional carrier called DC Air.</p>
        <p>The offer by Continental, which could complicate the proposed merger, was first made by Mr. Bethune in an Oct. 2 letter to James Goodwin and Rakesh Gangwal, who respectively head United's parent, the UAL Corporation, and US Airways. After receiving no response, Mr. Bethune repeated his offer yesterday in a second letter to the same executives.</p>
        <p>Analysts said they were not surprised that an existing airline had expressed interest in the Washington assets, which include gates as well as takeoff and landing slots at Ronald Reagan National Airport.</p>
        <p>But they said Continental's offer was likely to prove merely the latest move in a series of negotiations on the $11.6 billion US Airways/United merger.</p>
        <p>United proposed spinning off DC Air as a way of addressing Federal antitrust concerns. But since the merger was announced in late May analysts said further concessions would almost certainly be needed to get the deal approved.</p>
        <p>''It has been clear from the outset the DC Air divestiture is a starting point, and not an end point in what will be an active dialogue on possible remedies to competitive issues raised by the merger,'' said Samuel C. Buttrick, an airline industry analyst at PaineWebber.</p>
        <p>''Even with the proposed DC Air divestiture, a combined United Airlines and US Airways has a commanding revenue share in the Washington area and would remain the largest carrier at each of its three airports. That is not in the consumers' best interest.''</p>
        <p>United is still in discussions with the Department of Justice about the merger.</p>
        <p>''I am not surprised someone has stepped forward'' to bid for the assets, said Kevin Murphy, an airline analyst at Morgan Stanley Dean Witter. ''And when all is said and done I would not be surprised to see some more carve-outs from the United-US Airways presence at Reagan National Airport.''</p>
        <p>US Airways shareholders are scheduled to vote on Thursday on the proposed merger. Yesterday, the airline said it did not plan to consider other offers for the Washington assets that it planned to sell.</p>
        <p>''The agreement with Mr. Johnson prohibits discussions with third parties regarding any alternative to the DC Air transaction,'' said David Castelveter, a US Airways spokesman.</p>
        <p>The assets Continental seeks include 119 jetliner takeoff and landing slots at Reagan, 103 slots for smaller commuter planes, leases for 8 gates and other operations.</p>
        <p>''A sale of the DC Air assets to a strong and well-funded competitor like Continental Airlines would provide sustainable competition and real benefits to consumers,'' Mr. Bethune wrote in yesterday's letter. ''This should be the objective of United and US Airways as part of your divestiture strategy, and certainly of the regulatory bodies reviewing your transaction.''</p>
        <p>In his letter yesterday, Mr. Bethune also raised doubts about Mr. Johnson's ability to run an airline.</p>
        <p>''While we have the utmost respect for Mr. Johnson's success in the entertainment business, he has no expertise in the airline business,'' Mr. Bethune wrote. ''DC Air will be totally dependent on United Air Lines to operate the business for it, thus bringing no real competition to this crucial market.''</p>
        <p>United stood its ground, saying the deal with Mr. Johnson addresses those concerns.</p>
        <p>''United has recognized from the beginning the need to maintain and enhance competition at Washington, D.C., by a divestiture of US Airways assets at the Washington Reagan National Airport,'' said Andy Plews, a United spokesman. ''DC Air will bring added competition to the marketplace and will provide service to those communities currently served by US Airways from Reagan National Airport.''</p>
        <p>On the New York Stock Exchange, Continental Airlines shares closed at $46.13, down $1.88. UAL stock fell $1.19, to $41.19. And US Airways was unchanged at $31.44 a share.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
