<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Unidentified Floating Objects: Not Quite Stars or Planets</title>
    <meta content="10PLAN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/10/science/10PLAN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237588"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stars and Galaxies</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Orion Nebula</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wilford, John Noble</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stars and Galaxies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001010T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE3D7103CF933A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="875" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Unidentified Floating Objects: Not Quite Stars or Planets</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN NOBLE WILFORD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wilford, John Noble</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Astronomers observe a large number of low-mass objects drifting free in a cluster of young stars in constellation Orion, some 1,150 light-years from Earth (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Astronomers have found themselves a seemingly new phenomenon: a large number of low-mass objects drifting free in a cluster of young stars in the constellation Orion, some 1,150 light-years from Earth.</p>
        <p>These mystery objects are too small and dim to be stars. They also appear not to fit the usual description of failed stars, known as brown dwarfs. And they do not meet the standard definition of planets, for they are not orbiting any star.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Astronomers have found themselves a seemingly new phenomenon: a large number of low-mass objects drifting free in a cluster of young stars in the constellation Orion, some 1,150 light-years from Earth.</p>
        <p>These mystery objects are too small and dim to be stars. They also appear not to fit the usual description of failed stars, known as brown dwarfs. And they do not meet the standard definition of planets, for they are not orbiting any star.</p>
        <p>So what are they?</p>
        <p>An international team of astronomers working at telescopes in the Canary Islands and Spain has detected at least 18 of these free-floating objects, which they describe as ''a new kind of giant planet.'' They are huge gas spheres estimated to have 5 to 15 times the mass of Jupiter, the solar system's largest planet. Jupiter's mass is 318 times as great as Earth's.</p>
        <p>''This kind of isolated giant planet, which apparently forms on time scales of less than a few million years, offers a challenge to our understanding of the formation processes of planetary mass objects,'' the discovery team, led by Dr. Maria Rosa Zapatero Osorio of the Astrophysics Institute of the Canary Islands, wrote in the current issue of the journal Science.</p>
        <p>Other astronomers said they found the observations convincing and exciting. Similar studies of other young star clusters, including recent observations by the Hubble Space Telescope, have produced evidence that such objects may be a common phenomenon.</p>
        <p>But there was much less agreement on what to call these objects. Several astronomers objected to calling them planets or planetlike bodies, because planets are customarily defined as large objects orbiting a star -- not drifters with no direct stellar ties. By contrast, the 50 or more planets that have been detected around other stars in recent years are firmly linked by gravity to their host stars.</p>
        <p>Dr. Alan P. Boss, a theoretical astrophysicist at the Carnegie Institution in Washington, said the free-floaters might well represent the discovery of a new class of brown dwarfs -- ''sub-brown dwarfs,'' he called them.</p>
        <p>''It's clear that brown dwarfs are out there, and many of them have very low masses,'' Dr. Boss said.</p>
        <p>Brown dwarfs are dim starlike objects lighter than 75 times the mass of Jupiter. They never amassed enough material to fuel the thermonuclear processes that cause real stars to shine. The existence of these failed stars, long theorized, was finally confirmed five years ago, but only now are astronomers detecting especially low-mass brown dwarfs in abundance.</p>
        <p>Dr. Joan R. Najita, an astronomer at the National Optical Astronomy Observatory in Tucson, reported in the Oct. 1 issue of The Astrophysical Journal the detection of more low-mass brown dwarfs than high-mass ones in a star field in the Perseus constellation. Several of the objects were no bigger than 15 Jupiter masses.</p>
        <p>Any doubts about these findings were apparently laid to rest by the Orion observations.</p>
        <p>To the surprise of most astronomers, Dr. Boss said, the size range for brown dwarfs now seemed to run all the way from 5 to 75 Jupiter masses.</p>
        <p>Some astronomers, however, question whether a 5 Jupiter-mass object is really a brown dwarf and not something previously unrecognized, perhaps deserving of an entirely new name.</p>
        <p>''Nature is not making things easy for us,'' Dr. Boss sighed.</p>
        <p>Dr. Zapatero Osorio, now at the California Institute of Technology in Pasadena, conceded that the discovery by her team of Spanish, American and German astronomers had created a ''nomenclature problem'' and a need for theorists to reconsider their ideas about planets and brown dwarfs. ''The formation of young, free-floating planetary-mass objects is difficult to explain by our current models of how planets form,'' she said.</p>
        <p>It is generally thought that brown dwarfs are formed, like stars, in the collapse of a heavy molecular cloud. If its mass is great enough -- more than 75 Jupiter masses -- the pressure inside will be sufficient to fuse hydrogen atoms and start the nuclear furnace of a full-fledged star.</p>
        <p>If there is less than enough mass, the best that failed star, or brown dwarf, may be able to manage is to produce some heat and light by fusing atoms of deuterium, a heavier form of hydrogen.</p>
        <p>Some of the newest low-mass objects may be too small for even feeble deuterium fusion.</p>
        <p>Planets are thought to be formed by dust and gas left over from a star's birth.</p>
        <p>Planets coalesce in the spinning disks of material extending out from the star's equator. If the newly discovered objects are indeed planets, scientists must figure out how they became free-floaters.</p>
        <p>One possibility is that gravitational disturbances caused by massive planets or passing stars ejected the bodies from their home planetary systems. But scientists questioned whether this could account for 18 such objects in one small sector of space.</p>
        <p>Dr. Zapatero Osorio's group said its findings suggested that such unbound planetary objects could be formed in less than a few million years, in contrast to the slower evolution of regular planets.</p>
        <p>The 18 objects, observed in visible and infrared light, occupied a region known as the Sigma Orionis star cluster, where stars are forming in profusion and none of them are more than five million years old, which is just yesterday in cosmic time.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
