<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Democrats' Bid To Win House Gains Strength</title>
    <meta content="10HOUS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/10/politics/10HOUS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20001014T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237709"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: PROSPECTS IN THE HOUSE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Florida</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">House of Representatives (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Congress (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clymer, Adam</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccollum, Bill (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Canady, Charles T (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shaw, E Clay Jr (Repr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001010T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E0D7113CF933A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1388" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Democrats' Bid To Win House Gains Strength</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM CLYMER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Clymer, Adam</byline>
      <dateline>LAKELAND, Fla., Oct. 9</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Democrats appear to be gaining strength in battle to win control of House; nationwide, about two dozen Republican seats seem to be vulnerable, while 10 or fewer are competitive on Democratic side; situation does not guarantee the net gain of seven seats that Democrats need for a majority, but it does put it clearly in reach; races in Florida and other states discussed; map and chart of Florida races for seats now held by Republicans Bill McCollum, Charles T Canady and E Clay Shaw Jr; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mike Stedem, a car dealer and community leader in central Florida, was an afterthought as a Democratic Congressional candidate after bigger names turned the party down.</p>
        <p>But the surprisingly strong run here by Mr. Stedem, 50, in the 12th District against State Representative Adam Putnam, 26, an eager Republican who emphasizes his ''conservative philosophy and values,'' reflects a striking change over the summer in the battle for control of the House. More Republican seats, like the one in the 12th where a Republican incumbent is retiring, now seem vulnerable, and more Democratic seats seem safe.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mike Stedem, a car dealer and community leader in central Florida, was an afterthought as a Democratic Congressional candidate after bigger names turned the party down.</p>
        <p>But the surprisingly strong run here by Mr. Stedem, 50, in the 12th District against State Representative Adam Putnam, 26, an eager Republican who emphasizes his ''conservative philosophy and values,'' reflects a striking change over the summer in the battle for control of the House. More Republican seats, like the one in the 12th where a Republican incumbent is retiring, now seem vulnerable, and more Democratic seats seem safe.</p>
        <p>The result is that nationally, about two dozen Republican seats seem to be in play, while 10 or fewer are competitive on the Democratic side, extensive interviews with politicians in Washington and around the country show.</p>
        <p>That change hardly guarantees the net gain of seven seats the Democrats need for a majority. But it puts it clearly in reach.</p>
        <p>With six of those vulnerable Republican seats on the West Coast, a long election night is guaranteed. Even counts and recounts may not be enough to decide which party fills the speaker's seat and committee chairmanships. Bargaining and possible party switches could leave the results in doubt until Congress convenes at noon on Jan. 3.</p>
        <p>As one could expect, the two parties offer very different analyses of the situation. Ed Goeas, a Republican pollster, called a three-seat Republican loss the ''worst case'' he could imagine.</p>
        <p>David Plouffe, executive director of the Democratic Congressional Campaign Committee, said that  strong fund-raising by the party and its candidates enabled Democrats to go on television earlier than in past campaigns and that ''four weeks out from the election, I'd rather be us than them.''</p>
        <p>Florida, with three Republican seats in play, exemplifies most of the factors that have improved Democrats' chances. Few states have seen as much unexpected strength from the ticket of Vice President Al Gore and Senator Joseph I. Lieberman, and Florida's continuing status as a presidential tossup guarantees that they will keep coming to stir up the party faithful.</p>
        <p>The Eighth District around Orlando has been an obvious battleground all year. It opened up when Representative Bill McCollum decided to run for the Senate after 10 terms in the House.</p>
        <p>The Democrats settled early on Linda Chapin, the Orange County clerk of courts, who had all year to raise money, while Republicans battled through a primary in September and a runoff last Tuesday. Republicans from Washington have been running advertisements against Ms. Chapin and began raising money for Ric Keller, the primary winner, as soon as the results were clear. Stuart Rothenberg, a nonpartisan analyst, sees ''an edge to Chapin.''</p>
        <p>The 22nd District, an ungainly 91-mile strip along the Atlantic Coast from Fort Lauderdale to Palm Beach, came onto both parties' radar screens gradually, though by registration it is a 57 percent Democratic district. The reason is simple. The incumbent is Representative E. Clay Shaw Jr., a Republican elected in 1980 who has generally been seen as a credible lawmaker and is untouched by the kind of scandal usually needed to oust a veteran.</p>
        <p>But for the first time in recent years, he has a serious opponent, who seems to be campaigning harder than he is. State Representative Elaine Bloom has raised enough money to advertise in the expensive markets of Miami and Palm Beach. As a Ways and Means Committee member, Mr. Shaw has access to whatever contributions he can use, so the race is expensive.</p>
        <p>Here in the 12th District, a sprawling area of orange groves, cattle ranches and phosphate mines with Lakeland as its hub, the Republican incumbent, Representative Charles T. Canady, kept his promise to retire after eight years. Democrats went after various prominent legislators and other local politicians, but when they were rejected by all of those people, Mr. Stedem entered the race in late spring.</p>
        <p>Republicans in Washington dismissed him, and for a time, so did Mr. Putnam, who said early in the race that he saw no need for television commercials.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Stedem has made a race of it, arguing that his ''life'' experience outweighs Mr. Putnam's four years in Tallahassee. Mr. Stedem tells of working his way through college, spending 70 hours a week on his Ford dealership, organizing community leaders to build a clinic to attract doctors after Fort Meade's last three physicians died or retired, running the hospital board and a welfare-to-work operation and founding Citrus Cars, a charity which rebuilds automobiles and leases them for $25 a month to people getting off welfare so they can get to work.</p>
        <p>In Washington, he said, ''the biggest difference between us is that someone who is interested in establishing a career is going to go along to get along.'' In contrast to Mr. Putnam, whom he predicted would be lackey for Republican leaders, ''I can run my mouth.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Putnam argues that the experience edge is his, because of his work on water policy in the Legislature. He ran for the Legislature as soon as he graduated from college and is now one year over the constitutional minimum age for the House membership, 25. He says his experience ''will allow me to hit the ground running.'' He is a polished street campaigner, talking easily as he goes from store to store, and he has raised more money than Mr. Stedem.</p>
        <p>The Democrat released a poll last month showing that the race was neck and neck, and party leaders have flocked in to support him. Today, Representative Charles Stenholm of Texas, who would head the Agriculture Committee if Democrats take over, came through Bartow and Dade City to emphasize his empathy with the citrus industry. Still, this is a tough district for a Democrat.</p>
        <p>But it is only one of many blooming opportunities. Regardless of how many of them materialize as Democratic victories, for now Republican defensive lines are being stretched.</p>
        <p>In western North Carolina, for example, no one considered Representative Charles H. Taylor vulnerable earlier this year. Charles Cook, another nonpartisan analyst, called his 11th District in the Asheville area ''solid Republican.'' But that was before Mr. Taylor got into a row with local property tax assessors, eventually paying his taxes ''reluctantly'' while Sam Neill, a Democratic lawyer, capitalized on the dispute.</p>
        <p>In Kentucky, Representative Anne M. Northup also seemed too formidable, though the Third District around Louisville, tends Democratic. But State Representative Eleanor Jordan's challenge seems to have grown stronger in the face of negative, though truthful, advertising against her by the National Republican Congressional Committee.</p>
        <p>On the other side, several vulnerable Democratic freshmen no longer seem like good Republican targets. In the Kansas City, Kan., suburbs, Representative Dennis Moore seems to have solidified his grip on the Third District. So have Jay Inslee in Washington's First District in Microsoft country and Joseph M. Hoeffel in Pennsylvania's 13th in the Philadelphia suburbs.</p>
        <p>To be sure, Republicans are solidly favored to win some of the Democratic seats they consider a firewall against loss of control because of defeats elsewhere. When Michael P. Forbes lost the Democratic primary in New York's First District, Felix Grucci became the favorite, and in Virginia's Second District, State Senator Ed Schrock is likely to succeed a retiring Democrat. And Republicans also have realistic opportunities for gains in Pennsylvania, New Jersey, Michigan and Missouri.</p>
        <p>At the same time, Democratic targets for turnovers in Utah, Oklahoma and California have moved out of the tossup column, as Democrats established leads, and perhaps seven more Republican seats are now tossups.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: PROSPECTS IN THE HOUSE  Correction:  October 14, 2000, Saturday  A front-page article on Tuesday about Democratic efforts to regain control of the House of Representatives incorrectly summarized statements from Adam Putnam, a Republican candidate in the 12th District of Florida, about the use of commercials in the race. While Mr. Putnam said television commercials had never been used in elections in the 12th District, he did not say he saw no need for them in his race against Mike Stedem.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: October 14, 2000, Saturday</p>
        <p>A front-page article on Tuesday about Democratic efforts to regain control of the House of Representatives incorrectly summarized statements from Adam Putnam, a Republican candidate in the 12th District of Florida, about the use of commercials in the race. While Mr. Putnam said television commercials had never been used in elections in the 12th District, he did not say he saw no need for them in his race against Mike Stedem.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
