<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>OBSERVATORY</title>
    <meta content="10OBSE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/10/science/10OBSE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237584"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Meteors and Meteorites</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Asteroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mars Global Surveyor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mars (Planet)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mercury (Metal)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sierra Nevadas (US)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United States Geological Survey</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fountain, Henry</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Columns/Observatory</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Meteors and Meteorites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mars (Planet)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Asteroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Metals and Minerals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001010T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E3D9103CF933A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="750" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>OBSERVATORY</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HENRY FOUNTAIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fountain, Henry</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Scientists in Czech Republic and Italy deepen understanding of how some asteroid fragments travel all the way to Earth, where they become meteorites; NASA officials announce that mission formerly known as Mars Surveyor 2001 will now be known as 2001 Mars Odyssey, in honor of book and film 2001: A Space Odyssey; scientists with United States Geological Survey study mercury contamination of fish in Sierra Nevadas (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Meteorite Mystery</p>
        <p>On the long transit from Earth to Moon, the Apollo spacecraft were put into what was known as ''barbecue mode'' -- a slow rotation so that no part of the ship got too hot from exposure to sunlight.</p>
        <p>A rock in space -- like a fragment knocked off one asteroid in a collision with another in the belt between Mars and Jupiter -- does not normally roll like a rack of ribs on a rotisserie spit. So one side gets more sunlight than the other and gives off more heat in return. This difference, the Russian engineer I. O. Yarkovsky suggested a century ago, can be enough to cause the rock to drift slightly in its orbit.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Meteorite Mystery</p>
        <p>On the long transit from Earth to Moon, the Apollo spacecraft were put into what was known as ''barbecue mode'' -- a slow rotation so that no part of the ship got too hot from exposure to sunlight.</p>
        <p>A rock in space -- like a fragment knocked off one asteroid in a collision with another in the belt between Mars and Jupiter -- does not normally roll like a rack of ribs on a rotisserie spit. So one side gets more sunlight than the other and gives off more heat in return. This difference, the Russian engineer I. O. Yarkovsky suggested a century ago, can be enough to cause the rock to drift slightly in its orbit.</p>
        <p>Scientists in Italy and the Czech Republic have now used this ''Yarkovsky effect'' to explain one of the remaining mysteries of how some of those asteroid fragments travel all the way to Earth, where they become meteorites.</p>
        <p>It has long been known that asteroid fragments in two narrow orbital bands can, under the gravitational effects of Jupiter and Saturn, be kicked out of the asteroid belt and head toward Earth. But this supposes that only a few asteroids, situated on the edges of these bands (which are known as resonance gaps) produce the fragments. And the numbers do not add up: a few asteroids are not enough to produce the number of fragments that hit Earth.</p>
        <p>Using computer modeling, the scientists found an explanation in the Yarkovsky effect. A fragment from a far-off asteroid, they reported in the journal Nature, can slowly drift into one of the resonance gaps due to the differential heating.</p>
        <p>Enough of these rocks can drift in this way to explain the number of meteorites hitting Earth. And the phenomenon also explains the age of many meteorites (as measured by cosmic ray exposure): they have been drifting for millions of years before entering the resonance gap, rather than quickly entering from nearby.</p>
        <p>'A Space Odyssey' Rerun</p>
        <p>NASA's promised rethinking of its ''faster, cheaper, better'' strategy for exploring Mars, instituted after the loss of two spacecraft last year, has already brought some changes in the way the agency is pursuing future missions, the most notable being a total review of all missions in the works (which has resulted in delays and cancellations for some).</p>
        <p>But in addition to rethinking, NASA has been engaged in some renaming. Never one to pass up a chance to increase the appeal of its projects to the general public, the agency announced last week that the mission formerly known as Mars Surveyor 2001 would now be known as 2001 Mars Odyssey, in honor of the book and film ''2001: A Space Odyssey.''</p>
        <p>The renaming follows a decision in May, amid all the rethinking, to eliminate a lander portion of the mission. The 2001 Mars Odyssey will now consist only of an orbiter, to be launched next April. It will carry instruments to detect the planet's surface composition, any water or shallow buried ice, and radiation. NASA has since announced a plan to send two landers to Mars in 2003.</p>
        <p>A Gold Rush Legacy</p>
        <p>The California Gold Rush may be long over, but the environmental and ecological effects remain, more than 150 years after James Marshall first found flakes of gold at Sutter's Mill.</p>
        <p>The latest evidence for this is a study by scientists with the United States Geological Survey of mercury contamination of fish in the Sierra Nevadas. Mercury is a potent neurotoxin, and it accumulates in the food chain.</p>
        <p>During the Gold Rush, millions of pounds of mercury were used to extract gold from its ore (it is still used this way in some developing countries). Much of the mercury was lost to the environment.</p>
        <p>The federal researchers found that bass and other fish from two watersheds in former gold mining areas showed significant levels of mercury in their tissues. The researchers have given their data to state health officials, who can decide whether to issue a public advisory against eating certain fish from these areas.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
