<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In His Arrest, Chinese Editor Sees Success Of His Journal</title>
    <meta content="10HUAN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/10/arts/10HUAN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237605"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Business and Finance</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Huang Beiling</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bohlen, Celestine</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Huang Beiling</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001010T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEFD6103CF933A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1212" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In His Arrest, Chinese Editor Sees Success Of His Journal</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CELESTINE BOHLEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bohlen, Celestine</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of and interview with Boston-based poet and editor Huang Beiling, Chinese dissident who was arrested on Aug 11 outside his Beijing apartment, charged with illegal publishing; Huang has spent several months each year in China hand-delivering his journal Tendency, quarterly Chinese literary journal; Chinese authorities released Huang and deported him back to United States after protests from the West; Huang has permanent resident status in US although he is Chinese citizen; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As he was being questioned by the political security department of the Beijing police in August, Huang Beiling suddenly realized that he had achieved literary success.</p>
        <p>For six years Mr. Huang, 40, a Boston-based poet and editor who also uses the pen name Bei Ling, had spent several months a year in China hand-delivering Tendency, a quarterly Chinese literary journal he edits. The 2,000 to 3,000 copies were printed in Hong Kong or Taiwan and ferried across the border by Mr. Huang and his friends in bulging suitcases.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As he was being questioned by the political security department of the Beijing police in August, Huang Beiling suddenly realized that he had achieved literary success.</p>
        <p>For six years Mr. Huang, 40, a Boston-based poet and editor who also uses the pen name Bei Ling, had spent several months a year in China hand-delivering Tendency, a quarterly Chinese literary journal he edits. The 2,000 to 3,000 copies were printed in Hong Kong or Taiwan and ferried across the border by Mr. Huang and his friends in bulging suitcases.</p>
        <p>On Aug. 11, Mr. Huang was arrested outside his apartment in Beijing. A day later he was charged with illegal publishing and put in a crowded city jail. Two weeks later, after protests from the West, the Chinese authorities collected $2,400 of a $24,000 fine and deported him back to the United States, where he has permanent residence status although he is a Chinese citizen.</p>
        <p>Mr. Huang, recounting his experience in a recent interview in New York, said he realized during his initial 10-hour interrogation just how successful his efforts had been.</p>
        <p>''I understood that the Chinese government was more and more angry that this issue was everywhere in the country, in the cities and outside,'' he said. ''They said they saw it everywhere, even in bookstores, and they didn't like it.''</p>
        <p>What they didn't like, it seems, was his lack of concern that the Communist Party did not officially approve his journal.</p>
        <p>Before his arrest Mr. Huang had a reception in Beijing to welcome the latest edition and was planning a colloquium to discuss its contents, which include an interview, poems and essays by the Irish poet Seamus Heaney and a collection of Chinese underground poetry written during the Cultural Revolution. Mr. Huang even opened a Beijing office, included its address on the journal's last page and decided to have it printed at a small official printer in Beijing who agreed to take the risk (and, Mr. Huang later found out, was interrogated and fined).</p>
        <p>Tendency was first published as an underground poetry magazine in 1988, and its fourth issue, which honored two Chinese poets who died in the tumultuous year of 1989, was seized by the police in Shanghai. The journal started up again in 1994 as a more literary, intellectual publication based in Boston. When its editors decided to print one third of the run in Shenzhen, in southern China, the authorities stepped in again and confiscated all 1,000 issues.</p>
        <p>This year the authorities went further, although their action against Mr. Huang backfired. His arrest and jailing and the jailing of his brother and partner, Huang Feng, caused a stir. The PEN American Center published an open letter calling for Mr. Huang's release, and it was signed by Arthur Miller, Susan Sontag, Czeslaw Milosz and Nadine Gordimer. The United States government also protested.</p>
        <p>Mr. Huang said that the government was showing increased nervousness about China's publishing boom. He said 15 publishing houses had been closed, a handful of them permanently, and he cited a ban on the writing of two Shanghai feminists. Some Western books, including photography books about the Clinton presidency and about high fashion, that were printed in China for Western markets have been confiscated recently on grounds of being politically offensive or overtly sexual.</p>
        <p>''What we are seeing is a tightening of the rules,'' said Michael Roberts, executive director of the PEN American Center. ''Before, certain things were allowed for economic reasons, and now there seems to be concern about how to control the printing business.''</p>
        <p>It is still not clear which invisible wire Mr. Huang tripped with his latest issue of Tendency. It may have been the photograph of Wang Dan, a leader of the student movement that was crushed in Tiananmen Square in June 1989, which he printed with Mr. Wang's pledge to ''continue his struggle against the Communist Party regime.''</p>
        <p>In a last-minute decision, Mr. Huang dropped one of the two Chinese characters that form the word ''against'' as well as Mr. Wang's family name in hopes of avoiding official anger. The authorities were aware of the sleight of hand and chided Mr. Huang for trying to ''play games.'' Regular readers say it is not the first time Tendency has tiptoed across the line into quasi-political activity.</p>
        <p>''The journal is ostensibly literary, but Huang Beiling has published Havel, he has published underground literature, '' said Merle Goldman, a professor of Chinese history at Boston University. ''He really does push the edge.''</p>
        <p>When it started in 1988, Tendency wanted to give underground or alternative Chinese writers a place to publish, and to be a forum for authors to ''bear witness'' to events in China.</p>
        <p>To his list of firsthand experiences, Mr. Huang can now add time in a Chinese prison. ''In China, the situation in the jails is very bad,'' he said. ''Someday, I have to write about it.''</p>
        <p>He spent his first night in a cell jammed with men, women and infants, mostly out-of-towners rounded up as illegal migrants. Mr. Huang said that many of his cellmates had been held for more than the authorized 24 hours without food or water and were subject to beatings.</p>
        <p>Later he was transferred to a city jail where he shared a room with 16 to 25 men who slept in shifts and were assigned times to use the single toilet and wash basin in the cell. When they were taken out for interrogation, prisoners had to squat on their heels and keep their hands behind their necks, he said.</p>
        <p>The only inmate to escape this treatment was the manager of the cell, a convicted prisoner appointed by the authorities as their spy. ''He lived like a king,'' Mr. Huang said. ''There were two people assigned to give him a massage in the morning. He had a double space to sleep.''</p>
        <p>When he tried to warn the guards that they were dealing with the holder of a United States green card, they laughed, he said. ''They said, 'Who cares,' '' he said. '' 'Here you are a small potato.' ''</p>
        <p>Toward the end of his second week, Mr. Huang was moved to a hostel, and a higher-ranking police official came to question him, pressing him to admit that he had violated regulations by publishing an unregistered journal. Mr. Huang said he refused to use the word criminal but did agree to sign a statement saying that he was not in compliance with regulations.</p>
        <p>When he was told that he was to be released and deported, he said he could sense frustration on the part of his jailers. ''They just want to stop this magazine,'' he said. ''They don't want to see it anywhere in China. And they know if they release me, this magazine will continue. And it will.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
