<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Small Bookstores Breathe Easier, After Break in Price War</title>
    <meta content="10BOOK$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Books; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/10/technology/10BOOK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237686"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Day, Sherri</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001010T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E0D8113CF933A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="802" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Small Bookstores Breathe Easier, After Break in Price War</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SHERRI DAY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Day, Sherri</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Independent bookstore owners express relief that price war, in which they were forced to fight back against chain stores and online vendors by meeting price discounts and by making stores more attractive to shoppers with cafes and gardens, has eased; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Three years ago, when Susan Scioli heard that Barnes &amp; Noble was opening a store six blocks from her own, more modest establishment in Park Slope, Brooklyn, she got busy.</p>
        <p>Ms. Scioli has owned the Community Bookstore at 143 Seventh Avenue since 1971, and for her, staying competitive amounted to nothing short of war. She drew up a serious battle plan. She matched Barnes &amp; Noble's discounts on hardcover books penny for penny; she started a book club giving members discounts on purchases; and she took steps to make the store more attractive: down came the back wall and from the dust rose a cafe and outdoor garden.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Three years ago, when Susan Scioli heard that Barnes &amp; Noble was opening a store six blocks from her own, more modest establishment in Park Slope, Brooklyn, she got busy.</p>
        <p>Ms. Scioli has owned the Community Bookstore at 143 Seventh Avenue since 1971, and for her, staying competitive amounted to nothing short of war. She drew up a serious battle plan. She matched Barnes &amp; Noble's discounts on hardcover books penny for penny; she started a book club giving members discounts on purchases; and she took steps to make the store more attractive: down came the back wall and from the dust rose a cafe and outdoor garden.</p>
        <p>Ms. Scioli said the struggle was about her ''sense of will to survive.'' But she did more than survive. Now business is booming, and the store shows consistent growth.</p>
        <p>''It took a little while to see that things were going to be O.K.,'' Ms. Scioli said. ''And they're very good.''</p>
        <p>She is one of many owners of independent bookstores in New York and throughout the country who have been confronted by a competitive onslaught from bookstore chains like Barnes &amp; Noble and online giants like Amazon.com. Those larger companies offered big discounts and bigger selections, and there were plenty of independent bookstores that had to close because they could not stand the competition.</p>
        <p>Now, after getting the word that chain stores and online book merchants are scaling back their discounts, discontinuing them altogether or in some cases actually raising prices, little-guy survivors like Ms. Scioli are breathing a collective sigh of relief and smiling just a bit.</p>
        <p>''In some ways I think that they might be under more threat from us,'' said Ms. Scioli, adding that the chain stores lack friendly and knowledgeable workers and book selections geared to a local clientele.</p>
        <p>Linda Marotta, the head buyer for Shakespeare &amp; Company Booksellers, agrees that the chain stores may be in trouble.</p>
        <p>''People suspect that a lot of these stores are doing pretty poorly,'' said Ms. Marotta from her small office in the basement of the Shakespeare &amp; Company store in Greenwich Village, on Broadway at Waverly Place. ''People would not be surprised if a lot of these stores closed when the leases came up.''</p>
        <p>She was not always so confident. In 1997, when Barnes &amp; Noble opened an outlet next door to Shakespeare &amp; Company's store on Broadway near 80th Street and another near Lincoln Center, the smaller company closed its Upper West Side store. It kept open the Greenwich Village store, though, and since has opened two stores in Manhattan and a gift shop in Brooklyn and plans to open another store near Brooklyn College, between Flatbush and Ocean Avenues.</p>
        <p>Ms. Marotta says her company has endured because it provides better customer service and sells books that the neighborhood wants.</p>
        <p>''It was impossible to believe that independent bookstores would disappear,'' she said. ''There's absolutely no way that chain stores could fulfill everybody's needs.''</p>
        <p>The owners of St. Mark's Bookshop, at Third Avenue and Stuyvesant Street, said they never felt threatened by chain stores or their online counterparts.</p>
        <p>The small store could not afford book discounts or slick advertising campaigns, but when Barnes &amp; Noble moved nearby the owners cut expenses, listened to what the neighborhood wanted and relied on the store's neo-bohemian identity to keep customers coming in.</p>
        <p>''We have a Barnes &amp; Noble within shouting distance,'' said Terence McCoy, a co-owner. ''You can see it from our window. People would still buy the books from us. It's very heartening. I cannot explain it, other than people just wanted to buy the books from us.''</p>
        <p>It does not surprise Mr. McCoy that chain stores are no longer offering deep discounts.</p>
        <p>''I knew that they'd have to stop eventually if they had to show a profit,'' he said. ''At some point they can't discount. It's fairly simple arithmetic to me.''</p>
        <p>The future looks more uncertain to George Leibson, who owns Coliseum Books on Broadway at 57th Street. Although he has survived to see a break in the book price war, he does not expect his own business picture to improve.</p>
        <p>He has been losing money since the chain stores opened, he said, but his greatest problem is a lease that is soon to expire.</p>
        <p>''The rents in this area are too high currently, and they're asking three times the rent I'm paying now,'' Mr. Leibson said. ''I don't know what's going to happen.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
