<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Israelis Extend Deadline for Arafat to Quell Violence</title>
    <meta content="10ISRA$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/10/world/10ISRA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237710"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="WHOSE HOLY LAND? THE OVERVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Middle East</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Egypt</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sontag, Deborah</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arafat, Yasir</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barak, Ehud (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Annan, Kofi (Sec Gen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mubarak, Hosni (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Egypt</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Egypt</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001010T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E0D7113CF933A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1563" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Israelis Extend Deadline for Arafat to Quell Violence</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DEBORAH SONTAG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sontag, Deborah</byline>
      <dateline>JERUSALEM, Tuesday, Oct. 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Deadline set by Israeli Prime Min Ehud Barak for Palestinians to quell violence expires with riots still raging, but Israeli cabinet decides to avoid exploding a tense situation and gives Yasir Arafat 'last chance' to quiet protests; government also says it would agree, if invited, to attend US-sponsored summit meeting; as anxiety increases about regionwide violence, international intervention intensifies with arrival of United Nations Sec Gen Kofi Annan; Pres Clinton talks by phone to Barak, Arafat and Egyptian Pres Hosni Mubarak; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After the deadline set by Prime Minister Ehud Barak of Israel for the Palestinians to quell violence expired with riots still raging, the Israeli cabinet decided early this morning to avoid exploding a tense situation and gave Yasir Arafat a ''last chance'' to quiet protests.</p>
        <p>In the face of a concerted international effort to prevent the conflict from escalating and spreading, the government also said that it would agree, if invited, to attend an American-sponsored summit meeting in the region this week.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After the deadline set by Prime Minister Ehud Barak of Israel for the Palestinians to quell violence expired with riots still raging, the Israeli cabinet decided early this morning to avoid exploding a tense situation and gave Yasir Arafat a ''last chance'' to quiet protests.</p>
        <p>In the face of a concerted international effort to prevent the conflict from escalating and spreading, the government also said that it would agree, if invited, to attend an American-sponsored summit meeting in the region this week.</p>
        <p>''We will act to restore calm to the extent that it depends on us, while also giving Yasir Arafat a certain additional time to do what he needs to do,'' said Nachman Shai, a government spokesman. ''There is intense international diplomatic activity that we cannot reject or ignore.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, as anxiety increases about the possibility of regionwide violence, the international intervention intensified with the arrival in the region on Monday of the United Nations secretary general and Russia's foreign minister.</p>
        <p>''Time is short, the stakes are high and the price is greater than we are willing to pay,'' Secretary General Kofi Annan said in Tel Aviv on Monday before heading to Gaza City to meet with Mr. Arafat, the Palestinian leader.</p>
        <p>As the high-stakes Israeli cabinet meeting got under way at the Defense Ministry in Tel Aviv on Monday night, a man draped in an Israeli flag zoomed through the gates on a motor scooter. He reached Mr. Barak's car before he was tackled by a dozen secret service agents.</p>
        <p>President Clinton had proposed on Sunday that the Egyptian president, Hosni Mubarak, hold a meeting in Cairo with Mr. Barak and Mr. Arafat. On Monday, before the Israeli Cabinet meeting began, a senior administration official in Washington said the president would make a decision in the next 24 hours on whether to go ahead with an emergency summit meeting.</p>
        <p>''We have to make a judgment whether some intervention on our part is sensible, whether the fever can be broken,'' the official said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton, who has concentrated on the Middle East crisis since last Friday night, spoke again by telephone on Monday to Mr. Barak, Mr. Arafat and Mr. Mubarak.</p>
        <p>The president still had to be convinced that both sides were willing to take steps to ''tamp down the violence'' before he takes part in a summit meeting, the official said.</p>
        <p>Israeli officials had said they considered it premature to contemplate holding a meeting in the Middle East this week, as President Clinton had suggested. They demanded an end to the violence first.</p>
        <p>Similarly, the Palestinians said the Israelis must pull back their troops from reinforced positions in the West Bank and Gaza and accede to their demand for an international inquiry into the recent violence.</p>
        <p>The new moves came after a 12th day in which, in addition to clashes that pitted Palestinians against Israeli soldiers, vigilante-style revenge raids increased between Israeli and Palestinian civilians.</p>
        <p>The death toll continued to rise, with at least 89 reported dead.</p>
        <p>And the Jewish-Arab relationship continued to deteriorate inside Israel, particularly in Nazareth.</p>
        <p>Thousands attended funerals there on Monday for two Israeli Arabs killed on Sunday night, by Israeli riot police, after Jews rampaged through the heart of the Arab town.</p>
        <p>On Monday, Mr. Barak, saying that he was particularly concerned about ''the delicate fabric'' of Jewish-Arab coexistence inside Israel, issued an unusual appeal for internal peace after the Jewish Day of Atonement, Yom Kippur, ended at sunset.</p>
        <p>''I urge our Jewish citizens to refrain from attacking Arabs and their property under any circumstances,'' he said. ''And I urge our Arab citizens to refrain from being dragged along behind a radical minority that wants to destroy the fabric of life in Israel.''</p>
        <p>Although not explicitly in all three cases, Mr. Barak had threatened on Saturday to disengage from the peace effort, to bomb Syria and Lebanon and to form an emergency government with Ariel Sharon, the right-wing opposition leader.</p>
        <p>In a sign of the intensifying international effort to pull Mr. Barak and Mr. Arafat back from the brink of war, the two leaders were expected to meet on Monday and today with Mr. Annan, Foreign Minister Igor Ivanov of Russia and Javier Solana, the European Union's foreign policy chief.</p>
        <p>While in the region, Mr. Annan is expected to try to negotiate the release of three Israeli soldiers kidnapped on Saturday by Lebanese guerrillas who pierced Israel's northern border under cover of fire.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ivanov, too, is playing a role. He visited Lebanese officials on Monday.</p>
        <p>The Shiite Muslim guerrillas, who are demanding that Israel release Lebanese and Palestinian detainees in exchange for the soldiers, have indicated that they will allow an International Red Cross representative to visit the hostages today.</p>
        <p>Despite Mr. Barak's threat to resort to greater force if the Palestinians did not restrain their people, clashes defiantly continued throughout the West Bank on Monday.</p>
        <p>''There is no sign in the field that there has been a halt to the violence by the Palestinians,'' Shlomo Ben Ami, the acting foreign minister, said before the cabinet meeting.</p>
        <p>The clashes proved particularly intense in Ramallah, where the Monday incidents offered a glimpse into warring perceptions of reality.</p>
        <p>Palestinians began gathering in the city center for a protest against Mr. Barak's ultimatum. Then, the demonstration-in-the-making collided with a funeral procession for a rioter who had just died of wounds sustained last week.</p>
        <p>Already combative, the protesters and mourners became enraged by the announcement of an alleged brutal killing of a Palestinian by settlers. The 40-year-old man's skull was crushed, his bones broken and his body burned, the crowd was told. Palestinian television repeatedly showed pictures of the charred and mutilated body, which drove more people into the streets, and offered the opinion of some Palestinian officials that the killing justified an open season on settlers.</p>
        <p>''The settlers must now be a target by every Palestinian in order to stop their terrorism and they must be uprooted from our Palestinian occupied lands,'' said Hassan Asfour, a cabinet minister, according to Reuters. The reaction catapulted a large crowd toward a confrontation with Israeli troops at a junction between Israeli and Palestinian territories.</p>
        <p>Israeli military officials, however, disputed the Palestinian account of how the man had died. They contend that the man, Isam Hamad, 36, died in a car crash north of Ramallah and that the Palestinians chose to exploit the terrible condition of his body.</p>
        <p>''I suggested to my Palestinian counterpart earlier today that we make a combined investigation and take the body to a pathological institute,'' said Col. Gal Hirsch, the Israeli commander for the Ramallah area. ''He did not want it. Instead, they went with the body to the TV, and said the settlers had killed him.''</p>
        <p>The demonstrators threw rocks and firebombs at the soldiers, and taunted them over loudspeakers.</p>
        <p>In Hebrew, they praised Shiite Muslim guerrillas in Lebanon for the soldiers' kidnapping.</p>
        <p>Colonel Hirsch said his soldiers were under strict instructions to fire only when fired at. He said they used more tear gas -- canisters frequently hurled back at them -- and fewer so-called rubber bullets. Witnesses say the soldiers retreated as the crowd advanced several times, and with each retreat, the crowd whistled, clapped and flashed victory signs.</p>
        <p>There were fewer casualties from the confrontation, which also included short-lived gun battles, than from similar ones last week. One Israeli soldier was shot by a live bullet.</p>
        <p>Palestinian medics said about 22 Palestinians had been injured.</p>
        <p>--------------------</p>
        <p>Security Scare at Cabinet Meeting</p>
        <p>TEL AVIV, Tuesday, Oct. 10 (Reuters) -- Israeli security men drew their weapons and wrestled to the ground a man on a motor scooter who drove up to the entrance of a heavily guarded Defense Ministry building where the cabinet was meeting early today.</p>
        <p>The identity and motive of the man were not immediately known.</p>
        <p>Israeli television said he had been part of a group of protesters -- for and against peacemaking with the Palestinians -- demonstrating outside the compound while the cabinet met.</p>
        <p>Minutes after the incident, a second man, identified by Armed Forces Radio as the first gate-crasher's brother, entered the compound and was apprehended by security men. His face was badly scraped as they knocked him to the pavement.</p>
        <p>The government, after releasing a statement that cabinet ministers had ''made light'' of the incident, later said it viewed the matter ''with extreme seriousness'' and would review security procedures.</p>
        <p>WHOSE HOLY LAND? THE OVERVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
