<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: CAMPAIGN BRIEFING</title>
    <meta content="MB002125" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/10/politics/10CAMP.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237711"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001010T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504EFD7113CF933A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="735" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: CAMPAIGN BRIEFING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by B. Drummond Ayres Jr.</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE STATES</p>
        <p>G.O.P. PLANS CALIFORNIA BLITZ -- Despite polls showing Vice President Al Gore holding on to a comfortable lead over Gov. George W. Bush in California, the Republican Party says it will begin a $1 million-a-week television advertising blitz in the Los Angeles area in the next few days that, as party officials describe it, will be a ''serious'' effort to contest the Golden State.</p>
        <p>At that expenditure level, modest for the California television market, a typical viewer might see an advertisement 10 times a week.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE STATES</p>
        <p>G.O.P. PLANS CALIFORNIA BLITZ -- Despite polls showing Vice President Al Gore holding on to a comfortable lead over Gov. George W. Bush in California, the Republican Party says it will begin a $1 million-a-week television advertising blitz in the Los Angeles area in the next few days that, as party officials describe it, will be a ''serious'' effort to contest the Golden State.</p>
        <p>At that expenditure level, modest for the California television market, a typical viewer might see an advertisement 10 times a week.</p>
        <p>Gore campaign and Democratic Party officials say they are not impressed. They have spent no money for commercials in California, and they dismiss the Republican move as a feint to prompt them to start spending.</p>
        <p>California has been a tough state for Republicans in recent years, and Mr. Bush's father, President George Bush, drew sharp criticism in 1992 after he abandoned any effort to compete there against Bill Clinton.</p>
        <p>Governor Bush has vowed to run hard in the state. But so far he has mostly raised money there, not spent it.</p>
        <p>Todd S. Purdum (NYT)</p>
        <p>SURPRISE CAMPAIGN IN TEXAS -- Nowhere in the United States is the death penalty administered more often or defended more staunchly than in Texas. Yet Bill Vance, 60, a Democrat and a state appeals court judge, is running for presiding judge of the Texas Court of Criminal Appeals, the state's highest criminal court, on an idea that once would have seem blasphemous, a moratorium on executions.</p>
        <p>Judge Vance has promised to support a moratorium on any death penalty cases in which DNA technology could possibly prove a defendant's innocence or confirm his or her guilt.</p>
        <p>Recent polls in Texas show support for DNA testing and even a moratorium on death row cases in which DNA testing could prove innocence. But Judge Vance's position also is an intentional reminder of a controversy surrounding his Republican opponent, Judge Sharon Keller, 47, who joined the Court of Criminal Appeals in 1995 but has resigned to run for presiding judge.</p>
        <p>Judge Keller was criticized in 1998 for her majority opinion in which the court refused to order a new trial for Roy Wayne Criner, who in 1990 was sentenced to 99 years in prison on a rape charge. A DNA test administered after Mr. Criner's conviction concluded that sperm found inside the victim's body had come from someone else.</p>
        <p>His lawyers sought to have the verdict overturned or to win a new trial. But Judge Keller and the majority of the appeals court refused.</p>
        <p>This year, however, another DNA test further proved Mr. Criner's innocence, and local prosecutors and the local judge joined defense lawyers in asking that Mr. Criner be freed. Gov. George W. Bush did just that.</p>
        <p>Jim Yardley (NYT)</p>
        <p>DEMOCRAT LEADS IN NORTH DAKOTA -- When Heidi Heitkamp, a Democrat running for North Dakota governor, announced several weeks ago that she would undergo surgery for breast cancer, the first concern was, of course, for her health. But the inevitable speculation soon began about what effect her illness might have on her campaign.</p>
        <p>Ms. Heitkamp, the state attorney general, was in a tight contest with a well-known Republican, John Hoeven, former president of the Bank of North Dakota.</p>
        <p>The surgery has now been completed, and Ms. Heitkamp is back on the campaign trial, almost full time. And if a new poll is any indicator, she is faring well. Conducted by The Fargo Forum, the poll found her leading Mr. Hoeven by six percentage points.</p>
        <p>Most voters told the poll takers that Ms. Heitkamp's medical condition would not affect their vote. But Mr. Hoeven's campaign manager, Carol Olson, said, ''I think Heidi received a good deal of publicity in papers and TV and radio stations that probably had something to do with it.''</p>
        <p>While Ms. Heitkamp's campaign manager, Denise Lawson, concedes that Ms. Heitkamp's condition brought increased publicity, she said she thought the poll results were more directly related to Ms. Heitkamp's recent advertising and her stance on issues.</p>
        <p>''I wouldn't call it sympathy vote,'' Ms. Lawson said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
