<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Mrs. Clinton, One Topic on Voters' Minds Stays Taboo</title>
    <meta content="10MARR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/10/politics/10MARR.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237675"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bumiller, Elisabeth</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001010T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E6D8113CF933A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1796" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Mrs. Clinton, One Topic on Voters' Minds Stays Taboo</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELISABETH BUMILLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bumiller, Elisabeth</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Hillary Rodham Clinton, as she campaigns across New York State, refuses to discuss her marriage to President Clinton; current relationship between couple, who will mark their 25th wedding anniversary tomorrow, discussed; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As Hillary Rodham Clinton campaigns across New York State, she talks about everything from gasoline prices to the Buffalo economy to her first experience hunting ducks. But there is one taboo subject, always on the minds of voters, that came up yet again in Mrs. Clinton's debate with Representative Rick A. Lazio on Sunday. Why, she was asked, did she stay in her marriage?</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton, who will mark her 25th wedding anniversary tomorrow, responded that ''the choices that I've made in my life are right for me,'' then cited her daughter, her religious faith and her ''strong sense of family.'' What she did not do was bow to the suggestion that the state of her marriage was anybody's business.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As Hillary Rodham Clinton campaigns across New York State, she talks about everything from gasoline prices to the Buffalo economy to her first experience hunting ducks. But there is one taboo subject, always on the minds of voters, that came up yet again in Mrs. Clinton's debate with Representative Rick A. Lazio on Sunday. Why, she was asked, did she stay in her marriage?</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton, who will mark her 25th wedding anniversary tomorrow, responded that ''the choices that I've made in my life are right for me,'' then cited her daughter, her religious faith and her ''strong sense of family.'' What she did not do was bow to the suggestion that the state of her marriage was anybody's business.</p>
        <p>Both Clintons do talk readily about their work together on her campaign and have joked about their role reversal and its effects on their marriage. ''She had so many people who wanted her to run and wanted her to do it that she really decided that she ought to try,'' Mr. Clinton said at a reception with his wife in Little Rock, Ark.</p>
        <p>''And then I just practically beat her up time and time again, working on this announcement speech. She said, 'I've given a zillion speeches, why do you keep doing this?' I said, 'Because an election is a job interview, and if you get the job it helps to have decided in advance what you intend to do when you get there.' ''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton responded: ''I'm trying to do the very best job I can, but I want to take back every time I ever said to Bill, 'You know, you could have said it like this.' And there was that delicious role reversal when he was working on my announcement speech and making me practice in front of him, and saying, 'No, no, say it like this.' And it was a great moment for both of us.''</p>
        <p>Last weekend, the president had planned to be with his wife in Chappaqua on Saturday night and then was to watch her Sunday morning debate from the couple's home on Old House Lane. Violence in the Middle East changed his plans, but Mr. Clinton still flew up to Chappaqua at 6:15 p.m. on Sunday, stayed overnight with his wife, then left late yesterday morning for Washington with the Clintons' daughter, Chelsea.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton has, in fact, stayed overnight with his wife at the Clintons' Chappaqua home at least 20 times since the couple moved in on Jan. 5, or an average of two or three nights a month. Although many of the trips were tied to Mrs. Clinton's campaign events or to presidential meetings and fund-raising in New York, at other times the president quietly left the White House at 9 or 10 p.m. after work, then returned to Washington late the next morning.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton also spends some nights with her husband in Washington, and talks with him up to six times a day on the phone.</p>
        <p>Although it is impossible to know whether the president made those 40-minute flights on Air Force One to work on his marriage or simply to turn up for the cameras at Chappaqua coffee shops, he did publicly address the subject of his betrayal in August. ''I'm now in the second year of a process,'' he said, ''of trying to totally rebuild my life from a terrible mistake I made.''</p>
        <p>The president also speaks in glowing terms of the wife he humiliated, and who is now the Clinton with a political future and the potential for carrying on the family legacy.</p>
        <p>''When we first met and fell in love, I actually felt guilty about it because I thought I was robbing her of the career I felt she should have,'' Mr. Clinton said at a Silicon Alley fund-raiser for his wife last month in SoHo, one of some two dozen he has attended in the last year to raise $5 million for her campaign.</p>
        <p>''I thought she was better organized than me. I thought she understood things about public policy I didn't know. I thought she had more talent as a public servant than anybody I ever met. I want to see this seat occupied by someone, yes, that I happened to have loved for three decades, but more important, whose love can change the future of America and New York in a positive way.'' Then he kissed her forehead.</p>
        <p>Despite such displays of affection, Mrs. Clinton and her advisers have, as a matter of tactics, made a decision not to discuss publicly her relationship with the president, seeing it as an explosive topic. If Mrs. Clinton were to speak of her love for Mr. Clinton, her advisers say, she might be greeted with skepticism or even derision. If she were to talk of the difficulties in her marriage, they say, she would distract from a campaign that she is trying to win with her positions on issues.</p>
        <p>Although the advisers acknowledge that in largely ignoring her marriage the first lady risks appearing cold and opportunistic -- and bolsters the view of many voters that she has remained in the marriage purely for political power -- they say that any discussion of the relationship would hurt more than help. ''We don't want to talk about it, because she's the one running, not him,'' said one of Mrs. Clinton's senior campaign advisers.</p>
        <p>The president may in any case do enough talking for everyone. At a Washington fund-raiser last month at the home of the Clintons' longtime friend, Vernon Jordan, Mr. Clinton effusively described the first-time experience of voting for his wife in the Sept. 12 New York primary. ''I was happy as a kid on Christmas morning,'' Mr. Clinton said. ''It was amazing. We got to go in and shake hands with all the election officials. And I got into this little voting booth and I realized what I was doing and it was just an unbelievable feeling.''</p>
        <p>At another Washington fund-raiser for his wife, in June, Mr. Clinton recalled his wife's entry into the Senate race. ''I was surprised she'd even think of it,'' he said. ''I said, 'Do you know how much this is going to cost you?' She said, 'You're talking to me about money?' She laughed at me. She said, 'You, who have never cared if we had a nickel in the bank?' ''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton, who declined to be interviewed for this article, returns the coziness with an almost detached admiration for her husband's presidency, although she has on occasion been more personal. ''I would not be standing here tonight were it not for Bill and were it not for all he has done for me,'' she said to a hushed audience in Albany on May 16 after the New York State Democratic Party nominated her for the Senate.</p>
        <p>Longtime friends of the Clintons, who adamantly insisted that their names not be used, say that although the first lady in effect froze out the president for six months after he admitted to his relationship with a White House intern, he begged for forgiveness and told his wife that he would do anything for her. The Senate campaign, they say, presented an ideal opportunity.</p>
        <p>David Gergen, the former Republican adviser to Mr. Clinton and three other presidents, basically agreed with that view by arguing in his new book, ''Eyewitness to Power: The Essence of Leadership: Nixon to Clinton,'' that the president would not challenge his wife once her health care plan was failing -- in part out of guilt.</p>
        <p>''The president asked the first lady in part because he believed in her talents, which was justified,'' Mr. Gergen writes. ''He acted, too, because he wanted to promote women as national leaders, which was welcome. He also liked to share with his wife, which was generous. But does anyone doubt that he also wanted to placate her? Had it not been for his own past, I doubt he would have placed his presidency so fully in her hands.''</p>
        <p>After news articles first appeared about Paula Corbin Jones, Mr. Gergen writes, ''it became obvious that the stories had privately humiliated Mrs. Clinton and her husband was deep in her doghouse.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gergen adds that ''perhaps I am wrong, but over the next several weeks, I sensed that he was in no mood -- and no position -- to challenge her on anything.''</p>
        <p>Whatever the case, Mr. Clinton has at times seemed like half of a classic New York-Washington commuter marriage. On April 5, after spending the day at an economic conference at the White House and entertaining Jimmy and Rosalynn Carter and six of their grandchildren over dinner, the president flew up to Chappaqua. He lifted off in a helicopter from the South Lawn as the Carters, who were to spend the night in their old home, waved to him from the White House.</p>
        <p>A week later, the president returned to Washington about 8 p.m. on Air Force One after a trip to Denver, dropped off the press and much of his staff at Andrews Air Force Base, then switched to a smaller plane, a C-9, for a flight that night to Chappaqua. (The larger Air Force One, a 747, cannot land at the small Westchester County Airport.) Mr. Clinton had no public schedule in New York, and was back in Washington the next day in time to speak to a gathering of the American Society of Newspaper Editors.</p>
        <p>In some of the more intimate fund-raisers the president attends on behalf of Mrs. Clinton, he speaks freely about his wife. ''Not much gets me mad anymore, I'm feeling pretty mellow, but one of the things that still kind of steams me is when I hear somebody say, well, why is she doing this,'' Mr. Clinton said at the fund-raiser at Mr. Jordan's house. ''She wouldn't be doing this if she wanted to be his wife and the first lady.</p>
        <p>''The truth is, if she hadn't decided to spend the last 30 years helping me, helping other people, being a public servant as well as a private lawyer, she could've been doing this 25 years ago.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
