<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Reporter's Notebook; Fashion Magazines In 3 Dimensions</title>
    <meta content="10NOTE$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/10/living/10NOTE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Fashion Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237623"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Milan (Italy)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Trebay, Guy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy/Milan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001010T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E5DD113CF933A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="841" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Reporter's Notebook; Fashion Magazines In 3 Dimensions</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GUY TREBAY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Trebay, Guy</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, Oct. 9.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article describes scene at 10 Corso Como, fashion emporium in Milan, Italy; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''They make your ankles look really good,'' a fashion editor said the other day in Milan, speaking to a colleague who was trying on a pair of $2,000 black crocodile Manolo Blahniks.</p>
        <p>''What about heel height?'' the potential buyer asked.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''They make your ankles look really good,'' a fashion editor said the other day in Milan, speaking to a colleague who was trying on a pair of $2,000 black crocodile Manolo Blahniks.</p>
        <p>''What about heel height?'' the potential buyer asked.</p>
        <p>''Good,'' the first editor said. ''But I do question whether you need them when you just bought the same pair in brown.''</p>
        <p>That settled it. Out came the platinum card, and a salesman was summoned. Since when was necessity an issue? The sale was made.</p>
        <p>The women were busy playing lire Lotto at 10 Corso Como, the Milanese shop where the style flock descends en masse during the runway shows, most recently to avail themselves of an exchange rate that, as one editor put it, makes all of Italy seem ''like a sample sale.''</p>
        <p>Opened in September 1991 by Carla Sozzani, a former fashion journalist, 10 Corso Como is a so-called concept store, a mini lifestyle emporium assembled -- some would say edited -- with the same wide range of suppliers and dictatorial hipness that has traditionally been what makes good magazine editors worth their salt. Over the past several years, such stores have taken hold in Europe, bringing a variety of fascinating goods to a label-dominated market and fresh theater to the depleted urban marketplace.</p>
        <p>A poorly kept secret for almost a decade, 10 Corso Como seems to have been an inspiration, if not the template, for many similar stores. In London, for instance, there is both the Cross and Joseph. Paris has Stella Cadente Living Room, Bernie (where all the goods are color-themed), two boutiques named after their owner, Jean-Charles de Castelbajac, and, pre-eminently, a three-story establishment on the Rue St.-Honore named Colette.</p>
        <p>''I think of the Colette as a magazine,'' said Sarah, its director, who goes by a single name. It is probably no accident that Ms. Sozzani had earlier made the same observation about her place in Milan.</p>
        <p>In Ms. Sozzani's case, the magazine in question is probably Italian Vogue, where she was once a special-issues editor and where her sister, Franca, is editor in chief. Among important fashion magazines, there are few whose editorial pages function with as little apparent commercial consideration as does Italian Vogue, or exert as much influence. Designers with big ad budgets are well accommodated between its covers, of course, but it is not rare to come across 10-page spreads devoted to an obscure designer or an insider's pet photographer.</p>
        <p>Likewise at 10 Corso Como. A visitor will always find clothes from Prada, and alongside them a leopard-print trilby from Philip Treacy, the mad English hatter, or a John Galliano cardigan with oversize stitches seemingly knitted by a stoned-out Madame Defarge, or an assortment of designer clothes in the outlandish shapes for which the right hanger has never been found. There are caviar palettes, too, candles from Comme des Garcons, a variety of useless but chic household items and a smattering of kitsch (''Shanghai Seduction Love Kits'').</p>
        <p>Located in a revamped warehouse a 10-minute walk from Milan's central shopping district, 10 Corso Como encompasses a cafe, bar, art bookshop and gallery. ''For a long time, I had no clue of commercial things,'' Ms. Sozzani said at a gasping-room-only opening of pictures by Ugo Mulas, a photographer, at the gallery. ''I kept going, because I wanted very much a place where you can communicate in all areas of taste and get an immediate response.''</p>
        <p>The editorial model for Colette is likelier to be a magazine with a passionate readership and a fraction of Italian Vogue's ad base; France's Self Service, a fashion insiders' bible, comes to mind. At Colette, a nondescript space on a retail speedway dominated by Gucci -- and other examples of what one French magazine derided as ''the inescapable temples of luxury'' -- was reconfigured in 1997 by Arnaud Montigny, an architect, into an emporium organized along what Sarah called ''simple but not minimalist'' lines.</p>
        <p>Sarah said of the store, ''We wanted to do something similar to what journalists do, showing new designers and ideas.'' In Colette's weekly changing window displays, you might see $150 baby caps from Gucci or disk handbags from the New York collective As Four; rumpled clown dresses from Marni or orchids from Marianne Robic's in-store Flower Bar; 1,000 copies of Juergen Teller's book ''Go-Sees''; or a single $4,000 Fendi patchwork pony coat.</p>
        <p>You will also see inside the store the kind of hordes you might associate with supermarket coupon day.</p>
        <p>The reason for the success of 10 Corso Como and Colette is simple, said Stephen Gan, creative director of Visionaire magazine, at Junya Watanabe's spring 2001 show on Sunday: fashion has become too mainstream for fashionable people to consider it hip. ''People aren't interested in celebrities endorsing fashion anymore,'' Mr. Gan said. For now, he added, ''it's experts and tastemakers'' who are in the ascendancy.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
