<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tap the Oil Reserve, and Entrepreneurship Flows</title>
    <meta content="Y10OIL$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/10/business/10OIL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237624"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Strategic Petroleum Reserve</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Futures and Options Trading</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Energy Department</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Stroud, Lance, Enterprises</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Burhany Energy Enterprises</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Euell Energy</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Banerjee, Neela</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kripowicz, Robert S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Futures and Options Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001010T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E5DD113CF933A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1119" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tap the Oil Reserve, and Entrepreneurship Flows</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NEELA BANERJEE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Banerjee, Neela</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Third of oil from Strategic Petroleum Reserve is going to little-known companies, including Lance Stroud Enterprises, Burhany Energy Enterprises and Euell Energy, a surprising turn of events that has ignited speculation that small companies were front for mysterious entrepreneurs or shams to prop up auction; traders speculate that government in effect sold 20 million barrel, not 30 million, because little guys do not know what to do with it, and that those barrels will never move; Lance Stroud Enterprises plans to to sell oil to large company in hopes that commodity price of oil will fall, allowing it to pay less to return allotment to government (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Four stories above the streets of central Harlem, Lance Stroud has created a one-man oil company that, after going head to head with the multinationals, may now play a role in the nation's energy agenda.</p>
        <p>Lance Stroud Enterprises, a corporate 97-pound weakling, elbowed into the midst of oil giants last week when it was chosen as one of 11 companies that will receive a total of 30 million barrels of oil from the nation's Strategic Petroleum Reserve. With winter and the elections approaching, the White House decided to release the oil to replenish low supplies of heating oil in the Northeast and Midwest. Mr. Stroud, in his oil deal, offered to buy four million barrels worth more than $120 million.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Four stories above the streets of central Harlem, Lance Stroud has created a one-man oil company that, after going head to head with the multinationals, may now play a role in the nation's energy agenda.</p>
        <p>Lance Stroud Enterprises, a corporate 97-pound weakling, elbowed into the midst of oil giants last week when it was chosen as one of 11 companies that will receive a total of 30 million barrels of oil from the nation's Strategic Petroleum Reserve. With winter and the elections approaching, the White House decided to release the oil to replenish low supplies of heating oil in the Northeast and Midwest. Mr. Stroud, in his oil deal, offered to buy four million barrels worth more than $120 million.</p>
        <p>''I feel like I'm the front of the boat and the government is the rest of the boat,'' said the 35-year-old Mr. Stroud, relishing his luck. ''I'm parting the waters of this energy crisis with the weight of the government behind me.''</p>
        <p>Based in a room more college dormitory than executive suite, with a flooring of sweat socks, sneakers, soup cans and literary anthologies, Lance Stroud Enterprises received the second-largest allotment from the government's oil reserve, just behind BP Amoco, one of the world's huge oil companies.</p>
        <p>The Energy Department structured the release of the oil as a swap, which means that the companies will take 30 million barrels now and return 31.56 million barrels between August and November 2001. A third of the oil is going to little-known companies, which besides Lance Stroud Enterprises include Burhany Energy Enterprises of Tallahassee, Fla., and Euell Energy of Aurora, Colo. -- a surprising turn of events that has ignited speculation in an oil market driven as much by juicy rumor as dry numbers.</p>
        <p>Traders speculated that the small companies were fronts for mysterious entrepreneurs or shams to prop up the auction. ''Really and truly what it says is that the government sold 20 million barrels and not 30 because those little guys don't know what they will do with it,'' a longtime trader said. ''My best theory is that those barrels will never move.''</p>
        <p>But many of those same traders and big companies are now sidling up to Mr. Stroud, as if he were an orphan come into a kingly inheritance, hoping to buy his oil.</p>
        <p>''The oil industry is like a close-knit family,'' Mr. Stroud said. ''I don't have any animosity toward them. Besides, they might need some heating oil.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Stroud's intention is simple: he plans to sell the oil to a larger company in hopes that the commodity price of oil will fall, allowing him to pay less to return his allotment to the government and pocket the difference.</p>
        <p>Robert S. Kripowicz, the Energy Department's acting deputy secretary for fossil energy, said that start-up companies had previously received oil from the reserve. This time, ''after the small companies got their bids, major traders and oil companies called our contract people at D.O.E. to say they were in serious negotiations with all three of them,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Stroud thinks that selling the oil should be easy. Sitting in his office overlooking an air shaft, he said he was negotiating with several concerns to buy the oil, including BP Amoco, which confirmed that it was in talks.</p>
        <p>The challenge, he said, may be in finding enough oil to repay the Strategic Petroleum Reserve. To speed the flow of crude oil to refineries in time for the winter heating season, the Energy Department did not require financing up front, which it has in the past, thus providing entry to small players like Mr. Stroud. It instead tapped businesses that extended the most favorable swap terms. Mr. Stroud's offer of 12 percent more oil than he will receive, about 4.5 million barrels, placed him at the upper range of bidders, the Energy Department said.</p>
        <p>''Why 12 percent?'' he said. ''Because I don't have bricks-and-mortar or 70,000 employees I need to pay every week. And I don't need to earn enough for 60 generations to live on off this one contract. I just want this to be my coming out.''</p>
        <p>For Mr. Stroud to make money on the deal, the price of oil would have to fall by at least 12 percent over the next year, which traders said was probable.</p>
        <p>To protect against default on the swap, the winning bidders have to secure letters of credit by Thursday, and Mr. Stroud said he was talking to a major European lender about providing the guarantee. If he fails to get the letter, the Energy Department must decide whether it will auction the oil once more.</p>
        <p>Little in his life prepared Mr. Stroud, whose two-year-old company is not even listed in the phone book, for such wheeling and dealing. After four years in military intelligence, he said, he worked as a bus driver, a security guard, a computer programmer and recently, to make ends meet as he set up his business, a census taker. He shares an apartment with his mother and keeps a second office in his sister's apartment two flights up, where his computer keyboard sits on an upturned drawer and a lamp with Winnie the Pooh and Eeyore, taken from his son's nursery, illuminates a small corner.</p>
        <p>A math buff with a front tooth missing from basketball, Mr. Stroud was attracted to the oil market because, he said, ''everything that moves, moves by vehicle, and that needs oil; I wanted my hand in everything that moves.''</p>
        <p>By following the weekly statistics that traders, economists and oil companies use, he saw that supplies of heating oil were growing tight worldwide, especially in the Northeast. Then he received an e-mail message from the Energy Department soliciting bids for the oil from the reserve. ''I was ready to participate in remedying the energy crisis in New York,'' he said, ''and this fell into my lap.''</p>
        <p>He understands that trading in millions of barrels of oil could ''make or break'' him. But like the winner of any lottery, he holds on tightly to his ticket out of a life of odd jobs and bleak fourth-floor views.</p>
        <p>''If this works out,'' he said, ''I'll have to move. If someone around here makes a lot of money, something could happen. See, when one crab tries to climb out of the box, all the others will pull him back in.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
