<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Editorial Observer; Why the St. Louis Cardinals Could Be Trouble for the Yankees and Mets</title>
    <meta content="10TUE3$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/10/opinion/10TUE3.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237680"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">St Louis Cardinals</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Semple, Robert B Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001010T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E2D8113CF933A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1018" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Editorial Observer; Why the St. Louis Cardinals Could Be Trouble for the Yankees and Mets</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT B. SEMPLE Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Semple, Robert B Jr</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>editorial observer: why the</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ever since 1989, the year of its founding (with me as a charter member), I have been looking for a way to mention the Stan Musial Society in the pages of The New York Times. The society was named after the best all-around player in the history of the St. Louis Cardinals, and now numbers 300 members, all upright citizens who also happen to be terminally weird on the subject of the Cardinals. There has been no reason to mention the society because, with the exception of 1996, the Cardinals have not appeared in the post-season playoffs. Now here they are, having conquered the Atlanta Braves in three straight, with only the New York Mets standing between them and their sixth World Series encounter with the New York Yankees. The Yankees themselves must first overcome the Seattle Mariners, but that they will do, for reasons of historical necessity to be explained in a moment.</p>
        <p>As Tyler Kepner of The Times noted yesterday, the fans in New York are dreaming of having the World Series all to themselves, the way they used to before Horace Stoneham and Walter O'Malley did the unthinkable and transported the  Giants and Dodgers to the West Coast in the late 1950's. Nobody can begrudge them this dream, and if the Yankees and Mets do meet, it should be a whale of a series. One team is trying to salvage a dynasty, the other is trying to begin one, and both are loaded with high-priced talent. But the Cardinals have not only high-priced talent but something else that neither the Yankees nor the Mets can claim -- a fan base of vast geographical and political reach. In fact, if the Cardinals were running for president, nobody could touch them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ever since 1989, the year of its founding (with me as a charter member), I have been looking for a way to mention the Stan Musial Society in the pages of The New York Times. The society was named after the best all-around player in the history of the St. Louis Cardinals, and now numbers 300 members, all upright citizens who also happen to be terminally weird on the subject of the Cardinals. There has been no reason to mention the society because, with the exception of 1996, the Cardinals have not appeared in the post-season playoffs. Now here they are, having conquered the Atlanta Braves in three straight, with only the New York Mets standing between them and their sixth World Series encounter with the New York Yankees. The Yankees themselves must first overcome the Seattle Mariners, but that they will do, for reasons of historical necessity to be explained in a moment.</p>
        <p>As Tyler Kepner of The Times noted yesterday, the fans in New York are dreaming of having the World Series all to themselves, the way they used to before Horace Stoneham and Walter O'Malley did the unthinkable and transported the  Giants and Dodgers to the West Coast in the late 1950's. Nobody can begrudge them this dream, and if the Yankees and Mets do meet, it should be a whale of a series. One team is trying to salvage a dynasty, the other is trying to begin one, and both are loaded with high-priced talent. But the Cardinals have not only high-priced talent but something else that neither the Yankees nor the Mets can claim -- a fan base of vast geographical and political reach. In fact, if the Cardinals were running for president, nobody could touch them.</p>
        <p>Being a fan, I have to think that the fan base will be the deciding factor. I myself am a natural-born fanatic, born in St. Louis, essentially raised on the Cardinals (my younger brother got the woeful American League Browns by virtue of a coin flip). I saw my first home run in 1946, a towering fly ball over the Alpen Brau beer sign in left field hit by Whitey Kurowski, and my second one a few weeks later by Musial himself over the Griesedieck Bros. beer sign in right field. (St. Louis produced at  least a half-dozen different brands in those days, along with Buster Browns -- hence the slogan ''First in Shoes, First in Booze, and Last in the American League'').</p>
        <p>But the two founders of the Stan Musial Society, like many Cardinal fans, were not home-grown -- far from it. One is Frank Mankiewicz, a Californian. The other is Victor Gold, who hails from New Orleans. You could not find a politically odder couple. Mr. Mankiewicz served as Robert F. Kennedy's press secretary and George McGovern's campaign manager. Mr. Gold worked for Barry Goldwater and was Spiro T. Agnew's press secretary. Their real common ground has been a baseball team. When they founded the society, they expected to sign up maybe a dozen hard-core cases like themselves. They got many more than that, most of whom come to one big lunch a year in Washington, attended by the likes of William Webster, a Republican and former director of the C.I.A., and Richard Gephardt, the most powerful Democrat in the House.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mankiewicz and Mr. Gold adopted the Cardinals for the same reasons. First, the Cardinals were the only major league team located west of the Mississippi until the Giants and Dodgers moved to the Coast. For a while after that, they were also Major League Baseball's southernmost city, by a latitudinal hair over Cincinnati and Washington (you could look it up). They were thus a magnet for young fans in more than half the country that was not then served by a major league team.</p>
        <p>The second reason was KMOX, which has long broadcast the Cardinal games. KMOX was one of a handful of ''clear'' radio channels set aside years ago for national defense purposes. That meant that after sundown, when other stations on the same frequency were forced to go off the air, the voices of Cardinal announcers like Harry Caray and Jack Buck could be heard thousands of miles away. Of course, you sometimes had to sit in your car to pick them up. Mr. Mankiewicz reminded me the other day that that was how we met back in 1964 -- not in the pursuit of some journalistic business, but because we had both driven our cars to Washington's National Cathedral, at one of the highest points in the city, so we could hear a game. (I recount this stirring anecdote just to indicate what the Yankees and Mets fans are up against).</p>
        <p>In any event, the combination of geographical location and a strong radio signal built an unusually broad fan base, and accounts for the fact that even today, in this age of television and baseball expansion, Busch Stadium in St. Louis is filled not only with home-grown St. Louisans but with people from Iowa and Nebraska and Kansas and Arkansas and points south and west.</p>
        <p>Now for my predictions. Frankly, I'm terrified of the Mets, and the reasons have as much to do with the old Brooklyn Dodgers as anything else. Any time we came close to a pennant in the 1950's, there were the Dodgers, and to my way of thinking the Mets inherited some of the Dodgers' mystique. But if we can get past them, and the Yankees beat Seattle, then we have only the Yankees. And history says we should beat them. You could look it up. I did, and the Cards have won three of five.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
