<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mets and Yankees Turn a Bay Area Double Play</title>
    <meta content="Y09YAN$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/09/sports/09YANK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237535"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="2000 PLAYOFFS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Oakland Athletics</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olney, Buster</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Oakland Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001009T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E5D9103CF93AA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1337" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mets and Yankees Turn a Bay Area Double Play</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olney, Buster</byline>
      <dateline>OAKLAND, Calif., Oct. 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Yankees defeat Oakland Athletics, 7-5, to win American League division series, 3-2; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Yankees are old and slow and ragged and flawed, and they are alive, through their force of will and experience and shared labor. After scoring six runs in the first inning tonight, the Yankees spent the rest of the evening circled around that lead, protecting it against repeated attacks, and they hung on to beat the Oakland Athletics, 7-5, in Game 5 of their American League Division Series.</p>
        <p>''It was about as intense a game as I've ever played in,'' center fielder Bernie Williams said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Yankees are old and slow and ragged and flawed, and they are alive, through their force of will and experience and shared labor. After scoring six runs in the first inning tonight, the Yankees spent the rest of the evening circled around that lead, protecting it against repeated attacks, and they hung on to beat the Oakland Athletics, 7-5, in Game 5 of their American League Division Series.</p>
        <p>''It was about as intense a game as I've ever played in,'' center fielder Bernie Williams said.</p>
        <p>When Mariano Rivera -- the last of four relievers called upon by Manager Joe Torre after Andy Pettitte was knocked out in the fourth inning -- retired Eric Chavez for the elusive 27th out, the Yankees charged the field in celebration. Having shrugged off their crippling late-season slump to defeat the Athletics, three games to two, the Yankees advanced to play the Seattle Mariners in the A.L. Championship Series, which begins Tuesday night at Yankee Stadium.</p>
        <p>When the celebration moved to the Yankees clubhouse, the players sprayed Champagne for about 10 minutes, but left four cases of it unopened.</p>
        <p>''Two more to go,'' right fielder Paul O'Neill shouted, referring to the number of playoffs rounds standing between the Yankees and their third consecutive World Series title.</p>
        <p>Relief pitcher Mike Stanton screamed out, ''Who said we were too old?''</p>
        <p>Torre said he did not know whom he would start in Game 1 of the A.L.C.S., but after crisscrossing the country before finally putting away the Athletics, he did not care -- not tonight, anyway.</p>
        <p>The Yankees arrived here about 3:30 this morning. They lost Game 4 by 11-1 on Saturday night in Yankee Stadium, and they were tired and in need of a boost -- and it came from an unexpected source.</p>
        <p>Before tonight's game, Chavez, Oakland's third baseman, was asked to field questions in the interview room, and he prattled breezily about his weariness after the overnight travel and about big games he had played in his career. What Chavez did not know is that for some reason, his image was being projected on the two giant scoreboards that loom over Network Associates Coliseum, his words echoing around the ballpark that would have been mostly empty if not for the fact that the Yankees were taking batting practice.</p>
        <p>Then Chavez was asked if he had any thoughts on the possible end of the Yankees' dynasty. ''I don't mind at all,'' he began cheerily. ''I mean, they've won enough times. It's time for some other people to have some glory here.''</p>
        <p>Derek Jeter and O'Neill and others on the field tilted their heads, looking up at Chavez's 30-foot smile. They were tired, yes; his words were caffeinated, and he continued. ''But, no, they've had a great run,'' Chavez said. ''It's hard to stay No. 1. Everybody's gunning for you; everybody's trying to beat you. They're going to throw their best at you. They've done a phenomenal job as it is.''</p>
        <p>Some of the Yankees looked at one another incredulously. A 22-year-old with a couple of years in the big leagues was talking about them as if they had already lost. O'Neill finished batting practice and on his way to the field, stopped and shared his disbelief with Scott Brosius. Chavez had innocently infuriated them.</p>
        <p>''So he's dropping the past tense on us, was he?'' Brosius said, as he picked up his helmet and bat. ''Did you see that? O.K., we'll see how it goes.''</p>
        <p>Chavez's words were still resonating when Chuck Knoblauch led off the game and smashed Gil Heredia's first pitch for a single to right. Heredia was immediately on the defensive and walked Jeter, before O'Neill bounced an infield single high off home plate. Bases loaded and nobody out. Williams lined to right and Knoblauch tagged up and scored, and after Heredia walked David Justice, Tino Martinez launched a high drive to the base of the center-field wall; Terrence Long was fooled by the late-afternoon shadows and sun; the ball fell at his feet. Jeter, O'Neill and Justice all scored, their teammates jumping and shouting happily, the first-base coach Lee Mazzilli going all the way from his box to greet the runners.</p>
        <p>Jorge Posada laced a ball against Heredia's thigh for an infield hit, and although Heredia technically departed because of an injury, Oakland Manager Art Howe probably would have relieved him anyway. Jeff Tam finished the inning, and the Yankees added two more runs -- the second run scoring on Knoblauch's second hit of the inning. The Yankees had scored six runs, more than in any inning in a month.</p>
        <p>''You can't beat us with your mouth,'' Jeter said of Chavez's comments after the game. ''You have to beat us on the field.''</p>
        <p>Chavez said he meant no disrespect.</p>
        <p>''All I was trying to say was you have to give them credit and I hoped our organization would follow in their footsteps,'' he said. ''If that's past tense, it's past tense. I apologize.''</p>
        <p>The drawback to the big inning was that the whole thing had taken so long, 23 minutes, and as the rally dragged on, Pettitte went down to throw in the bullpen, to stay warm.</p>
        <p>If the Yankees had been playing well, if they were dominant like they were the last two years, six runs would have been enough. The Yankees would have had a deep rotation and Pettitte would have been pitching with his full complement of rest.</p>
        <p>But Pettitte had only three days' rest, rather than four, and whether it was nerves or weariness, he was not himself, his fastballs loitering in the strike zone. The A's got a couple of hits in the first inning, a couple more in the second; Randy Velarde smacked a two-run single, cutting the Yankees' lead to 6-2. When Chavez smashed a run-scoring double in the third, the Yankees began to look like marathoners who had gone out too fast and were now looking over their shoulders.</p>
        <p>Justice launched a homer in the fourth, the Yankees' first homer in 66 innings. But Oakland responded immediately, sandwiching two hits around a walk to open the bottom of the fourth, bringing the tying run to the plate. Mike Stanton and Jeff Nelson, relievers who usually pitch in the seventh and eighth innings, started warming up.</p>
        <p>Torre wanted Pettitte to go as long as possible, to protect his thin bullpen from stress. But Pettitte was talking to himself, baffled by his own ineffectiveness, and both Jason Giambi and Olmedo Saenz blistered sacrifice flies to score two runs, and after Miguel Tejada singled, Torre  pulled his starter.</p>
        <p>The Yankees had a 7-5 lead and had 16 outs to go. Torre could assume that he could call on his closer, Rivera, for the last six. He needed some way to get those other 10 outs, to somehow carry the lead to Rivera.</p>
        <p>Stanton relieved Pettitte, finishing the fourth inning with the lead intact, striking out two batters and retiring the Athletics in order in the fifth, getting two outs in the sixth. Ten outs to go, only four to reach Rivera.</p>
        <p>Giambi singled in the sixth, and Torre summoned Nelson, who struck out Saenz, punctuating the whiff by pumping his right hand and rushing off the field. Orlando Hernandez, who had thrown 130 pitches Friday, began warming up in the Yankees' bullpen; Torre intended to use everybody necessary to get to Rivera.</p>
        <p>Hernandez continued to warm up as the seventh inning began. Nelson retired the side in order in the seventh, his control problems of July and August forgotten. Hernandez  jogged in to pitch the eighth, struck out Ben Grieve, and Rivera started throwing in the bullpen.</p>
        <p>2000 PLAYOFFS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
