<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Economy; Finding some middle ground in a world obsessed with the new and impatient with the old.</title>
    <meta content="09NECO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/09/technology/09NECO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20001027T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237427"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schwartz, John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brown, John Seely</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Social Life of Information, The (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/World Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Columns/New Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001009T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900EED9133CF93AA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1133" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Economy; Finding some middle ground in a world obsessed with the new and impatient with the old.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By John Schwartz</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schwartz, John</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>John Schwartz New Economy column discusses the future of computers as foreseen in John Seely Brown's book The Social Life of Information (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HERE comes that darned future again, threatening to tear everything up. Take a look, for instance, at the latest issue of Fortune, which puts the star power of Ben Affleck on the cover and declares, ''The future of the Internet: Everything is about to change -- again.''</p>
        <p>The world is obsessed with the new, and impatient with the old. Our futurists have taken the undeniable changes wrought by the computer and the Internet -- changes that justify the overused word ''revolutionary'' -- and try to take the concept farther, into some kind of technological Reign of Terror. It is not enough to have a revolution, they seem to say: the past must be wiped out as well.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HERE comes that darned future again, threatening to tear everything up. Take a look, for instance, at the latest issue of Fortune, which puts the star power of Ben Affleck on the cover and declares, ''The future of the Internet: Everything is about to change -- again.''</p>
        <p>The world is obsessed with the new, and impatient with the old. Our futurists have taken the undeniable changes wrought by the computer and the Internet -- changes that justify the overused word ''revolutionary'' -- and try to take the concept farther, into some kind of technological Reign of Terror. It is not enough to have a revolution, they seem to say: the past must be wiped out as well.</p>
        <p>The Internet, the seers have boldly asserted, will be the end of the retailer, as brick-and-mortar stores give way to clicks. The end of the university, because online learning will bring the Ivory Tower down. Of the newspaper (say it isn't so!). The end of taxation, because electronic payments will be untraceable. And geography? So yesterday, now that the Net allows you to be anywhere.</p>
        <p>But there are other voices, people who say the end is NOT nigh, and they aren't just professional neo-Luddites. John Seely Brown has surfed technology's long wave for decades as the head of Xerox's famed Palo Alto Research Center, the birthplace of such innovations as the mouse-driven computers. And while the company famously fumbled in bringing its scientists' brainchildren to market -- we use Macintoshes and Windows PC's today, not Xeroxes -- no one can deny that Xerox has served as one of the most creative centers for technology the world has ever known.</p>
        <p>And from that, Mr. Brown, 60, has learned a measure of humility. He has been at the forefront and recognizes that evolution is more common than revolution -- and that what's really interesting about the new economy might be what's old about it.</p>
        <p>The Internet can transmit information, but conveying knowledge is a much bigger job. Knowledge comes from understanding the context of information, seeing it in practice and learning the things that are tacitly understood but rarely stated. And so change is less radical than we might expect.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brown has laid out his views in a recent book, ''The Social Life of Information,''  co-written by Paul Duguid, a researcher at the University of California at Berkeley. The book takes on the facile predictions -- especially the strain of prophesy he calls ''endism.'' He recounts ruefully that his own company was part of the group in the mid-1970's that predicted the ''paperless office.''</p>
        <p>''That was a great idea, we thought, 20 years ago, until we grew up,'' he said in an interview. Paper, he noted, is genuinely useful and dependable. ''A piece of paper never runs out of power. You never have to reboot a piece of paper. A piece of paper never turns blue and says 'sorry: unrecoverable error.' '' Most of all, he observed, ''paper has infinitely better resolution than the world's best displays today.''</p>
        <p>We don't just read the data in a book. We do, indeed, judge a book by its cover, and from other cues. We feel its weight, espy the cut and texture of its pages, and assess the underlinings and wear it may have gotten from its last reader.</p>
        <p>Geography, too, remains important, because the world is not just made up of bits of information. Silicon Valley flourishes because it is a physical community. And Mr. Brown, who projects a slightly old-world look with his beard and maroon suspenders, asks for a face-to-face meeting to hash out his ideas most effectively.</p>
        <p>To explain what he means by the ''social life'' of information, Mr. Brown points to a Xerox project to build a database of information about fixing copying machines. To begin with Xerox did something smart: it hired an anthropologist to study how its copier repair staff really did their jobs.</p>
        <p>What Xerox discovered was that they were often most productive over coffee before work started in the morning. They would toss around stories and build a living database. So Xerox tried to augment that kaffeeklatsch by equipping the workers with two-way radios, and then created a database of stories, not just procedures, that were grounded in practice. The process turned out to be so useful that, at a convention of copier repair staff, the one who contributed the most useful tips received a standing ovation.</p>
        <p>Since he published the book in February, the world has only served up more and increasingly desperate warnings of endism -- culminating, perhaps, in an essay earlier this year from the technoseer Bill Joy, a founder of Sun Microsystems and one of the world's truly certified Smart Guys. Mr. Joy predicted that the combination of unregulated technologies such as exceedingly miniature nanotechnology could lead to biological disaster and the end of, well, everything.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Joy's thesis was widely read and highly regarded, to Mr. Brown it just looked like the same endist pitch but with a bigger ball. He describes it with one of his favorite aphorisms about the futurist class -- that they count ''one, two, three, one million.'' Life is more gradual than that, the graybeard sighs.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brown left Xerox in June and has created a new investment company, Twelve Entrepreneuring, with some star entrepreneurs: Halsey Minor, the chairman of Cnet; the former McKinsey &amp; Company e-commerce expert John Hegel, and Eric Greenberg, founder of Scient. They are trying to figure out what makes a company, in Mr. Brown's words, ''truly transformative.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Brown is not saying much about the new company yet, but suggests that the key is making sure that knowledge is shared throughout the enterprise -- that it ''leaks'' across the boundaries that separate, say, the researchers who dream up new technologies from the engineers who manufacture the company's products, and that the knowledge is ''sticky'' enough that trade secrets stay within the company.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brown says he is looking to new models, but within traditional bricks-and-mortar businesses, because he says the lessons of the new age are not only for callow dot-coms. ''How do you use the clicks to deeply augment the bricks?'' he asked, saying he hopes ''to replace this ridiculous mind-set that the e-world is everything.''</p>
        <p>It feels good just to hear somebody say that out loud.</p>
        <p>Correction:  October 27, 2000, Friday  The New Economy column in Business Day on Oct. 9 about the views of John Seely Brown, former director of the Xerox Palo Alto Research Center and the author of ''The Social Life of Information,'' misstated his role at the investment firm Twelve Entrepreneuring. He joined the firm after it was created by Eric Greenberg, Halsey Minor and Benchmark Capital; he did not create it with them. The article also misspelled the surname of the firm's chief strategy officer. He is John A. Hagel III, not Hegel.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: October 27, 2000, Friday</p>
        <p>The New Economy column in Business Day on Oct. 9 about the views of John Seely Brown, former director of the Xerox Palo Alto Research Center and the author of ''The Social Life of Information,'' misstated his role at the investment firm Twelve Entrepreneuring. He joined the firm after it was created by Eric Greenberg, Halsey Minor and Benchmark Capital; he did not create it with them. The article also misspelled the surname of the firm's chief strategy officer. He is John A. Hagel III, not Hegel.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
