<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Putting the Focus on Trust</title>
    <meta content="Y09ADB$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/09/politics/09ADBO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237529"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE AD CAMPAIGN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marks, Peter</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001009T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E1DA103CF93AA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1010" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Putting the Focus on Trust</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER MARKS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Marks, Peter</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gov George W Bush's presidential campaign runs a new commercial that seeks to connect Bush's stands on a variety of issues to a single notion: trust; its accuracy and effectiveness assessed; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Bush campaign on Thursday began running a new 60-second commercial that seeks to connect Gov. George W. Bush's stands on a variety of issues to a single notion: trust. The spot is to run in 19 states, from the Pacific Northwest to the Southeast, that have been identified as having close races.</p>
        <p>PRODUCER -- Maverick Media</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Bush campaign on Thursday began running a new 60-second commercial that seeks to connect Gov. George W. Bush's stands on a variety of issues to a single notion: trust. The spot is to run in 19 states, from the Pacific Northwest to the Southeast, that have been identified as having close races.</p>
        <p>PRODUCER -- Maverick Media</p>
        <p>ON THE SCREEN -- A serene-looking Mr. Bush in an open-neck shirt speaks directly to the camera. Interspersed are portraits of the governor interacting with workers, young children and businesspeople, each episode intended to underline one of the issues the spot highlights.</p>
        <p>SCRIPT -- Mr. Bush: ''I believe we need to encourage personal responsibility so people are accountable for their actions. And I believe in government that is responsible to the people.</p>
        <p>''That's the difference in philosophy between my opponent and me. He trusts government. I trust you.</p>
        <p>''I trust you to invest some of your own Social Security money for higher returns.</p>
        <p>''I trust local people to run their own schools. In return for federal money, I will insist on performance. And if schools continue to fail, we'll give parents different options.</p>
        <p>''I trust you with some of the budget surplus. I believe one-fourth of the surplus should go back to the people who pay the bills. My opponent proposes targeted tax cuts only for those he calls the right people. And that means half of all income tax payers get nothing at all.</p>
        <p>''We should help people live their lives, but not run them. Because when we trust individuals, when we respect local control of schools, when we empower communities, together we can ignite America's spirit and renew our purpose.''</p>
        <p>ACCURACY -- The positions outlined are restatements of policies that Mr. Bush has been emphasizing for months. Speaking here in the most general terms, the governor makes another pitch for his proposal to allow workers to take charge of the investment of some of their Social Security money. He also promotes his plan for broad-based tax cuts, a platform that has been attacked by Vice President Al Gore as overwhelmingly favoring the wealthiest 1 percent of the population. Though the federal government has little direct control over education, Mr. Bush says once again that he will demand greater accountability from schools in return for federal aid. And the declaration about giving parents ''different options'' seems a veiled reference to his support for charter schools and school vouchers, the latter a politically charged phrase he has stopped using of late.</p>
        <p>SCORECARD -- The Bush campaign rather cleverly uses Mr. Bush's stands on the issues to demonstrate he is a man of character. The governor uses the word trust six times in the spot, and it also materializes on the screen. (''Trust'' is, in fact, the title of the spot.) It is no accident that the nominee himself invokes the name of his opponent -- a rarity for Bush commercials. The idea he seems to want to convey in this thematic comparison is that only one candidate in the race is truly a man of his word.</p>
        <p>PETER MARKS</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE AD CAMPAIGN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
