<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Democracy Arrives in Corporate News Releases</title>
    <meta content="09WIRE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237426"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">PR Newswire</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Businesswire (Co)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bloomberg Business News</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berenson, Alex</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001009T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06EFD9133CF93AA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="896" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Democracy Arrives in Corporate News Releases</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEX BERENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Berenson, Alex</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>PR Newswire and Businesswire, premier corporate news distributors, are now making information simultaneously available to public and news media, which have had a 15-minute lead over the public until now; gap gave professional traders who spend more than $1,000 each month for access to Bloomberg and other financial wire services a valuable edge over individual investors, because wires carried headlines on the releases before the full releases actually appeared; shift further erodes the informational advantage professional investors once enjoyed over individuals (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For decades, corporate press releases have been sent to the news media 15 minutes before everyone else gets them.</p>
        <p>That gap gave financial wires like Bloomberg News a monopoly on crucial information about earnings and mergers. And it gave the professional traders who spend more than $1,000 each month for access to Bloomberg and other financial wire services a valuable edge over individual investors, because the wires carried headlines on the releases before the full releases actually appeared.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For decades, corporate press releases have been sent to the news media 15 minutes before everyone else gets them.</p>
        <p>That gap gave financial wires like Bloomberg News a monopoly on crucial information about earnings and mergers. And it gave the professional traders who spend more than $1,000 each month for access to Bloomberg and other financial wire services a valuable edge over individual investors, because the wires carried headlines on the releases before the full releases actually appeared.</p>
        <p>But no more. The 15-minute gap officially ended yesterday, when PR Newswire and Businesswire, the two services that distribute the vast majority of corporate news releases in the United States, began sending those releases to Web sites like Yahoo at the same time they offer them to financial news organizations. So an individual investor looking for corporate news on Yahoo will now see a release at the same time as a reporter for Dow Jones News Service would.</p>
        <p>''What we've eliminated was a rather unfair avenue of information,'' said Lorry I. Lokey, chief executive of Businesswire, which distributes an average of 1,300 releases each day. ''Now it's really wide open.''</p>
        <p>The shift further erodes the informational advantage professional investors once enjoyed over individuals. It also offers more evidence of the impact of Regulation FD, a new rule from Securities and Exchange Commission mandating the widest possible disclosure of important corporate information to investors.</p>
        <p>But it also presents this irony: that the wires, once viewed as the most efficient way to distribute company news, are now seen as a potential barrier to the widest possible spread of that information.</p>
        <p>''The Internet is the reason,'' said David Armon, senior vice president of PR Newswire. ''The Internet has changed all of our worlds. There's no question that this is a big deal for us and the members of PR Newswire -- there will be clearly more people looking at this information as it comes out.  It's a transformation from an indirect disclosure vehicle to a direct disclosure vehicle.''</p>
        <p>But Bloomberg, Dow Jones News Service, and Reuters, the most important financial wire services, say they do not expect simultaneous distribution to cost them subscribers, because they do much more than regurgitate the facts in press releases.</p>
        <p>''I like to think that just like The New York Times, what you put on your front page requires some critical thinking and judgment, and press releases are not news stories,'' said Matthew Winkler, editor-in-chief of Bloomberg News. ''People don't know how many big stories we do every day, and how many anecdotes, and how much news we break.''</p>
        <p>Richard Tofel, spokesman for Dow Jones &amp; Company, whose wires had more than 330,000 subscribers worldwide as of June 30, said investors will continue to depend on financial wires to sort through releases quickly and find the most important facts, which companies bury inside their releases.</p>
        <p>''What people, particularly in the financial markets want, is not two pages or 10 pages that they have to sift through,'' Mr. Tofel said. ''What they want in the first seconds is two or three numbers. And then they want to know why. And the press release makes it hard to do A and impossible to do B.''</p>
        <p>Even Mr. Lokey of Businesswire agreed. ''The news media definitely add value in looking for buried leads or putting two and two together,'' he said. ''They also clarify -- they're a very important source.''</p>
        <p>The 15-minute delay began in the 1960's after PR Newswire began offering its feed directly to brokerage houses. The Newswire's move  posed a threat to Dow Jones, which had previously been the main distributor of releases on Wall Street. In addition it gave brokerage firms an advantage in seeing those releases. So regulators pressed for a delay, theoretically so that the information could be disseminated more widely and democratically.</p>
        <p>The new change means less than it would have a few years ago, since the news wires themselves are now increasingly widely distributed across the Internet. Reuters stories, for example, can be read on about 1,000 Web sites, including Yahoo, according to a Reuters spokeswoman. In addition, anchors at CNBC, the financial news channel, often read headlines with important news as soon as they appear on the wires.</p>
        <p>The move to simultaneous distribution comes only six weeks after a fake press release on Internet Wire, a smaller news release service, caused shares in Emulex, a California high-technology company, to fall more than 50 percent in a matter of minutes. That incident has sparked fears that more bogus releases will roil the markets. But Mr. Armon said PR Newswire checks to make sure that the releases are actually from the companies that supposedly wrote them.</p>
        <p>Some professional investors also worry that the change may lead individuals to mistake news releases for news stories, since the releases will now be distributed widely before the wires have time to react. To prevent confusion, PR Newswire is encouraging sites that carry its releases to identify them prominently as news releases, Mr. Armon said.</p>
        <p>''There's about 1,400 portals that carry our copy, and we're asking them that they move up something called the source line,'' Mr. Armon said. He cited Yahoo, which has added a ''Press Release'' tag in bold letters to the top of all releases, as a model for other sites.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
