<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>One Germany</title>
    <meta content="09MON2$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/09/opinion/09MON2.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237512"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Germany, Reunification of</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Unemployment</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Germany</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Unemployment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001009T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E6DA103CF93AA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="641" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>One Germany</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial says German commitment to rule of law, democracy and European integration has put to rest the concerns about German reunification that were raised 10 years ago; says task of reunification remains incomplete, with the east's per-capita gross domestic product still only two-thirds of the west's and its unemployment twice as high; says German society must also strive to become more tolerant and welcoming of foreigners (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Germans last week celebrated the 10th anniversary of their nation's reunification, an event once as inconceivable as it is now uncontroversial. Contrary to the initial concerns of wary neighbors, Germany did not turn inward or resuscitate threatening ambitions in the aftermath of reunification. The nation remains a responsible advocate for continued European integration and a strong champion of the Atlantic alliance. Germany still faces formidable challenges in bringing together east and west, but from the perspective of the international community, a united Germany of 83 million people has proved a rousing success.</p>
        <p>After the unexpected fall of the Berlin Wall in November 1989, it was not only neighbors who were apprehensive about the prospect of a reunified Germany. So were plenty of thoughtful Germans. Arguing against the rush by Helmut Kohl, then chancellor, to incorporate East Germany into the Federal Republic (which is what ultimately took place on Oct. 3, 1990), Gunter Grass, who has since been awarded the Nobel Prize for literature, wrote on the Op-Ed page of this newspaper: ''No one of sound mind and memory can ever again permit such a concentration of power in the heart of Europe.'' He added that a reunited Germany would block the path to European unity. This was a fairly typical view among German intellectuals.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Germans last week celebrated the 10th anniversary of their nation's reunification, an event once as inconceivable as it is now uncontroversial. Contrary to the initial concerns of wary neighbors, Germany did not turn inward or resuscitate threatening ambitions in the aftermath of reunification. The nation remains a responsible advocate for continued European integration and a strong champion of the Atlantic alliance. Germany still faces formidable challenges in bringing together east and west, but from the perspective of the international community, a united Germany of 83 million people has proved a rousing success.</p>
        <p>After the unexpected fall of the Berlin Wall in November 1989, it was not only neighbors who were apprehensive about the prospect of a reunified Germany. So were plenty of thoughtful Germans. Arguing against the rush by Helmut Kohl, then chancellor, to incorporate East Germany into the Federal Republic (which is what ultimately took place on Oct. 3, 1990), Gunter Grass, who has since been awarded the Nobel Prize for literature, wrote on the Op-Ed page of this newspaper: ''No one of sound mind and memory can ever again permit such a concentration of power in the heart of Europe.'' He added that a reunited Germany would block the path to European unity. This was a fairly typical view among German intellectuals.</p>
        <p>These concerns were backed by history, but in retrospect clearly underestimated the transformation of West German society in the postwar generation. Over time, a reverence for the rule of law, democratic ways and European integration, first imposed on it by occupying powers, had been internalized, and had become a part of the ethos of the new, more humble Federal Republic.</p>
        <p>A united Germany has not strayed from its commitment to deepen European integration, as evidenced by the momentous steps since reunification toward a single market and a monetary union. This focus on deepening the European Union may have delayed the entry of new member nations from Eastern Europe, it is true, but that cannot be pinned on German reunification. The welcome participation of German troops in NATO's Kosovo campaign last year is also indicative of the extent to which a reunified Germany has allayed its neighbors' initial concerns.</p>
        <p>While the rest of the world may now be at peace with German reunification, at home the task itself remains incomplete. The transfer of $540 billion from west to east in the past decade has been an extraordinary effort to raise a people's standard of living, but the east's per-capita gross domestic product remains only two-thirds of the west's, and its unemployment rate is twice as high. Still, more than 9 out of 10 easterners would not go back to the days of Communism.</p>
        <p>As it breaks down economic and psychological barriers between east and west, German society must also strive to become more tolerant and welcoming of foreigners. In this regard, last year's liberalization of citizenship laws was a heartening step. Likewise, the German people's continued recognition of the uniqueness of their nation's history suggests that reunification has not eroded the moral sensibility of the Federal Republic, even if Berlin is once again its capital.</p>
        <p>Plenty of challenges lie ahead for Germany, but they are the challenges of a mature nation. For the first time in modern history, a unified Germany is a peaceful, prosperous nation surrounded by allies in the heart of Europe, and not a troubling powder keg. The ''German problem'' is no more.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
