<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>House Race Important to Control of Congress Draws Outside Interest and Money</title>
    <meta content="Y09CAL$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/09/politics/09CALI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237475"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: CALIFORNIA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">California</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">House of Representatives (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kuykendall, Steven T (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Harman, Jane</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ayres, B Drummond Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001009T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E7DE103CF93AA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1216" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>House Race Important to Control of Congress Draws Outside Interest and Money</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By B. DRUMMOND AYRES Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ayres, B Drummond Jr</byline>
      <dateline>MANHATTAN BEACH, Calif., Oct. 3</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Rep Steven T Kuykendall, Republican, and his Democratic challenger, Jane Harman, are battling it out in California's 36th Congressional District in an election that is expected to go down the wire and and play an important role in deciding which party ends up controlling the House; each candidate has raised well over $1 million in campaign money, and considerable outside money is also being spent by special interest groups and by campaign committees of national political parties; photo; graph; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Except for a few placards and a scattering of advertisements on cable television, there is almost no readily visible evidence that an election is being held this fall in California's 36th Congressional District, the  sunny ocean-side strip of Beach Boys country, from just south of Santa Monica to just north of Long Beach.</p>
        <p>Still, a hot political battle is being waged in the 36th, one that is expected to go down to the wire and play an important role in deciding which party ends up controlling the House. The two candidates -- Steven T. Kuykendall, the Republican incumbent, and Jane Harman, his Democratic challenger -- are having at each other daily, trying to gain traction, even if little attention is being paid.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Except for a few placards and a scattering of advertisements on cable television, there is almost no readily visible evidence that an election is being held this fall in California's 36th Congressional District, the  sunny ocean-side strip of Beach Boys country, from just south of Santa Monica to just north of Long Beach.</p>
        <p>Still, a hot political battle is being waged in the 36th, one that is expected to go down to the wire and play an important role in deciding which party ends up controlling the House. The two candidates -- Steven T. Kuykendall, the Republican incumbent, and Jane Harman, his Democratic challenger -- are having at each other daily, trying to gain traction, even if little attention is being paid.</p>
        <p>Available polls indicate that of the 52 House races in California this year, this one might be the closest and might be decided by many of the same tax, health care, education and Social Security issues that are at play in the presidential race.</p>
        <p>The district is roughly 40 percent Republican, 40 percent Democrat and 20 percent independent and has a history of swinging from one side to the other in elections. It tends to be moderate on social, cultural and environmental issues, and conservative on fiscal issues. For decades it was heavily dependent on the defense and aerospace industries, and on sun-and-surf tourism, but in recent years it has added a balancing and economically stabilizing mix of entertainment and communications industries, along with numerous ventures related to trade around the Pacific Rim.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kuykendall, more moderate than many California Republicans because of the moderate tilt of the 36th, won the seat two years ago by just two percentage points, all but guaranteeing he would face a strong challenge this year. Ms. Harman, also a moderate, held the seat for three terms from 1992 to 1998, giving it up in 1998 to run for governor, unsuccessfully.</p>
        <p>National Democratic leaders pressed hard to get her to jump back into the fray this year. She says she agreed because, in her view, Mr. Kuykendall has been little more than a status-quo legislator and is too wedded to Republican plans for huge tax cuts and privatization of some of the investment aspects of Social Security and some of the prescription drug provisions in Medicare.</p>
        <p>''The role of a member of Congress is to be a leader,'' she declared a few days ago in the campaign's first debate. ''Steve Kuykendall and I stand in very different places.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kuykendall readily agreed with the latter point, asserting that  little happened on Capitol Hill to help the residents of the 36th ''in the six years that Jane Harman was in Congress.''</p>
        <p>He contends she is too liberal for the district and out of touch with its residents.</p>
        <p>''She's a big-government person and she's out of touch because she's never really bothered to get down on the ground and work the district,'' he said the other day. ''The people of this district have needs, and they want answers to them, reasonable answers like good health care and good jobs and fair taxes. But they are not big-government people.''</p>
        <p>Each candidate has raised well over $1 million in campaign money. Both say they easily could spend more than $2 million each, about double what House candidates usually spend in California. Certainly spending $2 million would be no great challenge for Ms. Harman, since there is great wealth in her family and she did not hesitate to dip deeply into it in her losing run for governor -- a run in which she failed to carry the 36th District, Mr. Kuykendall likes to point out.</p>
        <p>Considerable outside money also is being spent on the race by special interest groups and by campaign committees of the national political parties, and national party figures have been visiting to help the candidates raise even more money. If the contest stays close, along with the overall race for control of the House, still more outside money and visitors almost certainly will flow in.</p>
        <p>The Los Angeles-area television market is one of the country's most costly, so neither Mr. Kuykendall nor Ms. Harman has started to run television advertisements, preferring to husband money for blitzes in the final weeks. But the A.F.L.-C.I.O., the Natural Resources Defense Council and the state and national Democratic and Republican parties have been running commercials.</p>
        <p>One of the hardest hitting is a labor federation advertisement contending that Mr. Kuykendall ''voted against guaranteeing seniors prescription medicine under Medicare and backed a private insurance plan that will leave millions without coverage.'' Mr. Kuykendall says that the advertisement is ''completely off-base'' and that he has a solid history of supporting comprehensive medical care programs for older people.</p>
        <p>Neither Vice President Al Gore nor Gov. George W. Bush of Texas has campaigned recently in the district, but Mr. Gore's running mate, Senator Joseph I. Lieberman of Connecticut, caused a splash when he showed up to help Ms. Harman, as did Senator John McCain of Arizona when he came in to help Mr. Kuykendall. In fact, Mr. McCain is due for a return visit in the final days of the campaign.</p>
        <p>''What happens here will have great bearing on whether the Republicans maintain control of the majority in the House,'' he said in his first visit. ''A lot is at stake here.''</p>
        <p>In March, when Mr. Kuykendall and Ms. Harman ran in the state's open primary, he got 42 percent of the vote and she got 41 percent. No independent polls have since been conducted in the district, but each candidate is polling and each says the race remains too close to call.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kuykendall says that the polls he has conducted have all shown him and Ms. Harman ''running about even, sometimes with me up a couple of points, sometime with her up by a couple.'' Ms. Harman says her polls have all shown the race ''essentially a tie when you factor the possible sampling error.''</p>
        <p>Nonpartisan political analysts consider the contest a tossup, too.</p>
        <p>''The slightest political breeze over the next month could nudge either candidate to victory,'' said Amy Walter, who follows House contests for the Cook Political Report. ''Both sides will be pouring in the television and the mass mailings and working the streets, such as you can work streets in California. If Bush eventually pulls out of the presidential competition in the state to concentrate his efforts elsewhere, that just might give Harman the edge she needs. But then again, suppose Bush hangs in?''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: CALIFORNIA</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
