<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Roots of Prosperity Reach Past Clinton Years</title>
    <meta content="Y09ECO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/09/politics/09ECON.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237483"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE ECONOMY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sack, Kevin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001009T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E6DD103CF93AA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1717" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Roots of Prosperity Reach Past Clinton Years</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD W. STEVENSON</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Any claim that Pres Clinton and Vice Pres Al Gore have to credit for long run of prosperity dates to Aug 6, 1993, when Gore cast tie-breaking vote in Senate on administration's plan to reduce budget deficit by raising taxes and restraining spending, but many economists say it is a considerable stretch to suggest, as Gore often does, that powerful expansion of 1990's was born with the passage of that plan; graphs (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Any claim that President Clinton and Vice President Al Gore have to credit for the country's long run of prosperity dates to the evening of Aug. 6, 1993. That was when Mr. Gore cast the tie-breaking vote in the Senate on the administration's plan to reduce the budget deficit by raising taxes and restraining spending, a move fraught with political as well as economic risks.</p>
        <p>Republicans, not one of whom voted for it, predicted that the legislation would choke what had been a fragile recovery from the 1990-91 recession. Mr. Clinton and Mr. Gore asserted that it would unlock the economy's potential by easing the pressure on interest rates, and they say history has proved them correct.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Any claim that President Clinton and Vice President Al Gore have to credit for the country's long run of prosperity dates to the evening of Aug. 6, 1993. That was when Mr. Gore cast the tie-breaking vote in the Senate on the administration's plan to reduce the budget deficit by raising taxes and restraining spending, a move fraught with political as well as economic risks.</p>
        <p>Republicans, not one of whom voted for it, predicted that the legislation would choke what had been a fragile recovery from the 1990-91 recession. Mr. Clinton and Mr. Gore asserted that it would unlock the economy's potential by easing the pressure on interest rates, and they say history has proved them correct.</p>
        <p>''Twenty-two million new jobs and the greatest prosperity ever,'' Mr. Gore said in touting the outcome in his debate with Gov. George W. Bush of Texas on Tuesday night.</p>
        <p>Even critics of the administration acknowledge that the 1993 budget plan did not have the dire effects Republicans had warned of, and there is a widespread consensus that it helped support the wave of business investment that has characterized the economy in recent years.</p>
        <p>But many economists say it is a considerable stretch to suggest, as Mr. Gore often does, that the powerful expansion of the 1990's was born with the passage of that plan.</p>
        <p>For one thing, they say, other policy decisions played a role in straightening out the government's finances. Among them were a deficit-reduction bill signed by President George Bush in 1990 and a deal between Mr. Clinton and the Republican Congress in 1997 that cut capital gains taxes while further restricting spending.</p>
        <p>Moreover, economists and business executives say, much of what happened to the economy in the 1990's had little to do with Washington and was part of a process that began before Mr. Clinton and Mr. Gore took office.</p>
        <p>At the same time that the administration was setting out to address the fiscal mess, the Federal Reserve Board's decision to hold interest rates at rock-bottom levels throughout 1992 and 1993 was giving the economy a kick as it emerged haltingly from the recession that ended in March 1991.</p>
        <p>In the private sector, companies were starting to see the benefits of painful steps to make themselves more competitive at home and abroad, including plant closings and layoffs of previously secure middle managers.</p>
        <p>And perhaps most important, years of technological progress were beginning to click into place in a way that promised tremendous benefits, most notably through a pickup in productivity, the basic measure of efficiency and the best predictor of long-term economic potential.</p>
        <p>By acting as a brake on inflation, the surge in productivity allowed the Fed more flexibility in holding down interest rates in the mid- and late-1990's, and helped generate profits and wealth that in turn created huge new tax revenues for the government and turned budget deficits into surpluses.</p>
        <p>''Clinton came in at a time when technological innovation was at a sweet spot,'' said William C. Dudley, chief economist at Goldman Sachs, the investment firm. ''He's gotten the benefits of technical innovation that other presidents didn't benefit from. But he didn't do anything to squelch it, and undertook policies to encourage not squelching it.''</p>
        <p>Jerry Jasinowski, the president of the National Association of Manufacturers, said the economy's recovery in the early years of the administration was mostly driven by the Fed's low interest rates, and that the economic strength in the second half of the 1990's primarily came from investments by business in technology.</p>
        <p>''The Clinton administration merits credit for some early deficit reduction and for letting the Federal Reserve have its independence, and that's it,'' Mr. Jasinowski said. ''The amount of credit the administration gets is a bronze medal behind the Federal Reserve and the private sector's expansion of productivity.''</p>
        <p>When it comes to the economy, the administration often points to its success in opening foreign markets to trade and in helping low-income workers through increases in the minimum wage and an expansion of the tax credit for the working poor. But inside the White House, the 1993 budget plan is seen as the single most crucial turning point.</p>
        <p>At the urging of Mr. Gore, as well as advisers like Robert E. Rubin, then chairman of the White House's National Economic Council, and outsiders like Alan Greenspan, the Fed chairman, Mr. Clinton decided as he took office in 1993 that the economy was being held back largely by the dead weight of the budget deficit, which at that time was projected to grow inexorably.</p>
        <p>The administration's 1993 proposal to raise taxes infuriated Republicans, and its plan to restrict spending frustrated Mr. Clinton, who had pledged to increase spending in areas like education. But the administration was betting that there would be an economic payoff in that narrowing the deficit would reduce the government's borrowing needs and would therefore increase the pool of capital available for private investment.</p>
        <p>More capital means downward pressure on interest rates. Lower rates would make it more affordable for companies to expand and modernize, and for consumers to buy houses and cars.</p>
        <p>There was considerable debate among economists and on Wall Street about whether the strategy would work. In the end, administration officials say, things unfolded just as they had predicted.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Gore put it on Tuesday night, the ingenuity of the American people should get credit for the strong economy, but the American people also had plenty of ingenuity eight years ago when the economy was in the doldrums and the deficit was out of control.</p>
        <p>''The difference is we've got a new policy,'' Mr. Gore said in the debate. At times he has been even more explicit about claiming the credit. ''I voted and we won and then we've had an economic recovery since then,'' he said in a speech on the economy late last year.</p>
        <p>But while the administration tends to credit the improving fiscal situation with igniting the technology and productivity revolution, many economists and business executives think it was the other way around.</p>
        <p>Indeed, there were already powerful forces reshaping the economy before the deficit reduction plan passed.</p>
        <p>Five months before Mr. Gore's tie-breaking vote in the Senate that August, engineers at the Intel Corporation in Silicon Valley had introduced their new Pentium chip.</p>
        <p>The Pentium was the latest in a string of advances in semiconductor technology and software throughout Silicon Valley that within a few years would help bring the Internet to every desktop while driving computing power up and computer prices down.</p>
        <p>And even as the Pentium was being introduced, engineers at Intel, under intense competitive pressure from equally fast and innovative rivals, were halfway through development of a successor that would cram 75 percent more transistors onto a chip and run three times as fast.</p>
        <p>''That's when everything really came together,'' said Albert Yu, a senior vice president at Intel, describing the atmosphere of rapid-fire progress in the technology business in 1993.</p>
        <p>Dana G. Mead, who through most of the decade held the No. 1 or No. 2 jobs at Tenneco, a sprawling conglomerate, said that by 1993 his company and others were seeing the combined effects of more aggressive management efforts to cut costs and years of investment in automation and information technology.</p>
        <p>''In the early 1990's, after a decade of this investment, we were finally beginning to see real improvement,'' Mr. Mead said.</p>
        <p>So convinced was Mr. Mead that businesses were operating in a fundamentally more efficient way that he took his message directly to Mr. Greenspan at the Fed in 1995. If the Fed could be convinced that corporate America was better at absorbing costs and producing more for less, Mr. Mead said, then perhaps the Fed would not be so quick to raise interest rates when economic growth picked up.</p>
        <p>Unbeknownst to Mr. Mead, Mr. Greenspan was already thinking along the same lines. In early 1994, even as the Fed enacted the first in a yearlong series of rate increases, Mr. Greenspan told a closed meeting of the Fed's top policy makers that ''something different'' was going on.</p>
        <p>Long before other analysts noticed anything, Mr. Greenspan raised the possibility of an extraordinary pickup in the growth rate of productivity, which had mysteriously tapered off in the early 1970's and to that point had shown no clear signs of revival, according to transcripts of the meeting made public this year.</p>
        <p>Over the next five years, as the Fed chairman became increasingly convinced he was correct, it led him to allow far higher levels of growth in the economy than traditional economic theory held was prudent.</p>
        <p>But while Mr. Greenspan had helped convince Mr. Clinton that there would be an economic payoff for deficit reduction, the Fed chairman has always stopped well short of suggesting that there was a direct link between the upturn in productivity and the 1993 budget plan.</p>
        <p>Mr. Greenspan takes a much longer view. He often traces today's prosperity to the development of the transistor after World War II, and a whole series of technological advances since then that converged in the 1990's to supercharge the economy in a way that has happened periodically but infrequently throughout history.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE ECONOMY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
