<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Harry Potter Faces Challenge in China</title>
    <meta content="Y09POT$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/09/world/09POTT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237470"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Marketing and Merchandising</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Translation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Chinese Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Copyrights</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Book Trade</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rowling, J K</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, Craig S</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Harry Potter (Book Series)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chinese Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Translation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Copyrights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Language and Languages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Book Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001009T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E6DF103CF93AA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="943" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Harry Potter Faces Challenge in China</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CRAIG S. SMITH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smith, Craig S</byline>
      <dateline>SHANGHAI, Oct. 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Three books in J K Rowling's Harry Potter series are published in China, but copyright pirates beat the state-owned publisher to the bookshelves, and anemic marketing fails to generate the excitement that Rowling's publishers drummed up in the West; translators make good use of China's rich idiomatic language; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Harry Potter has arrived in China, riding the biggest initial print run for a work of fiction here since the Communist Party came to power 51 years ago. It may take a bit of Hogwart's magic to make those books disappear.</p>
        <p>The People's Literature Publishing House, which still offers selected works of Mao Zedong's poetry, has printed 600,000 copies of the first three books in J. K. Rowling's elaborate fantasy, betting that the tale of youthful wizardry will appeal to the country's growing literary appetite for lively foreign fare.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Harry Potter has arrived in China, riding the biggest initial print run for a work of fiction here since the Communist Party came to power 51 years ago. It may take a bit of Hogwart's magic to make those books disappear.</p>
        <p>The People's Literature Publishing House, which still offers selected works of Mao Zedong's poetry, has printed 600,000 copies of the first three books in J. K. Rowling's elaborate fantasy, betting that the tale of youthful wizardry will appeal to the country's growing literary appetite for lively foreign fare.</p>
        <p>But conquering China isn't without challenges. Copyright pirates beat the state-owned publisher to the bookstore shelves with illegal copies of a Taiwanese edition. And anemic marketing has failed to generate the excitement that Ms. Rowling's publishers drummed up in the West.</p>
        <p>Prospective Potterphiles lined up halfway around the block at Wangfujing Bookstore in Beijing's main shopping district on Friday, when the official edition went on sale. But at Shanghai's bustling Book City, few people scratched up the relatively rich $2.50 for a copy, slimmed considerably from its English-edition heft by the compactness of Chinese characters. ''It's not selling well,'' said a clerk watching the display. ''There aren't any pictures.''</p>
        <p>Only about 30 books had been sold by late afternoon on Harry Potter's first day in the largest book store in China's largest city, despite a national holiday extended to encourage retail sales.</p>
        <p>Wang Ruiqin, the editor behind the Chinese Harry Potter series, hopes that giving away colorful Harry Potter ballpoint pens will help entice buyers, and that printing the books on pale green paper will discourage counterfeiters, whose books sell for about half the price of the official edition. She also hopes that Chinese book reviewers will create enough buzz to burn through the inventory.</p>
        <p>''Chinese literature lacks imagination,'' said Ms. Wang. ''You can't easily find a book as good as these.''</p>
        <p>True or not, decades of pressure for writers to serve the party's political ends sapped much of the country's literary vigor, which has only recently begun to return. And a desire among the country's educated class to feel a part of the global community has increased the demand for foreign books here -- China bought the copyrights to 6,461 foreign titles last year.</p>
        <p>After being shut off from foreign ideas for so long, many Chinese are hungry for a taste of the exotic. ''The Horse Whisperer,'' ''The English Patient'' and ''Sophie's World'' have been best-sellers. More recently, Shanghai Translation Publishing House has sold 310,000 copies of ''Tuesdays with Morrie,'' Mitch Albom's recounting of conversations with a dying professor.</p>
        <p>The People's Literature Publishing House hopes to repeat the success it had with the international best-seller, ''Bridges of Madison County,'' of which it sold a total of 700,000 copies during the 1990's. The current huge print run, 200,000 each of J. K. Rowling's first three books, is a bet that the Harry Potter series will have at least as much appeal.</p>
        <p>It might. The Chinese have a long tradition of supernatural stories and a fascination with the paranormal. Wizards are standard fare in the country's kung fu novels. And one of China's most enduring folk epics follows the adventures of a magical monkey king, a monk and a mischievous talking pig.</p>
        <p>Many Chinese, meanwhile, are tired of the same characters and the old tales. Walt Disney's animated film ''Mulan,'' for example, was a disappointment at the box office here because the well-known story of an ancient Chinese girl warrior did not excite much interest.</p>
        <p>''I read that the book is all the rage overseas and so I came here just to buy it,'' said Han Pingqi, a pimpled 19-year-old high school senior poring over a Harry Potter book beside a stack of the freshly printed paperbacks. He said he and his friends have already devoured the popular Hong Kong science fiction writer Wei Sili and are ready for something new.</p>
        <p>Ms. Wang says Ha-li Bo-te, as Harry Potter's name is rendered in Chinese, ''teaches ethics that are universal, but does so in a very humorous and emotional way,'' unlike the flat melodrama of many children's books in China. ''Harry Potter books don't have such lines as 'you should be brave,''' she said.</p>
        <p>Each of the three Harry Potter books had a different translator, all of them women. Chinese equivalents for the books' quirky names and magical incantations were decided by committee. Many translations have meanings that resonate in China's rich idiomatic language.</p>
        <p>The Leaky Cauldron, a London hangout for witches and wizards, becomes Po Fu Jiu Ba, or the Broken Cauldron Bar. 'Broken cauldron' in Chinese means something akin to 'burnt bridges' in English because of a legendary tale of soldiers who destroyed their cooking pots before going into battle to show their determination not to return defeated.</p>
        <p>Harry Potter's archenemy, Lord Voldemort, is Fu Di Mo in Chinese, meaning 'demon hiding underground,' and the wraithlike dementors are called She Hun Gui, or 'soul snatching ghosts.'</p>
        <p>The People's Literature Publishing House said it beat a crowd of other Chinese publishers bidding for the right to publish Ms. Rowling's books. It wouldn't say how much it paid for the rights, though Chinese regulations prohibit the publisher from paying royalties in excess of 10 percent of the retail price of every book sold.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
