<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Giants' Defense Gets the Falcons, and Credit for an Ugly Victory</title>
    <meta content="09FALC$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/09/sports/09FALC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237510"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Giants</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Atlanta Falcons</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">George, Thomas</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Atlanta Falcons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001009T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E7DA103CF93AA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="991" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Giants' Defense Gets the Falcons, and Credit for an Ugly Victory</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Thomas George</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">George, Thomas</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTA</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>On Pro Football column discusses New York Giants victory over Atlanta Falcons (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The offense dropped balls. There were plenty of turnovers. The flow, the rhythm, just was not there. It was mostly hit and then miss, a gain and then a loss.</p>
        <p>More dropped balls.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The offense dropped balls. There were plenty of turnovers. The flow, the rhythm, just was not there. It was mostly hit and then miss, a gain and then a loss.</p>
        <p>More dropped balls.</p>
        <p>These were the Falcons. These were the Giants.</p>
        <p>Two offenses in the Georgia Dome yesterday kept falling short, sometimes by a yard, often by much more.</p>
        <p>But the Giants offense managed a scoop more than Atlanta's. And the Giants defense? Now that was the show. The Giants defense kept answering every call, and believe me, there always seemed to be a knock, a ring, a plea.</p>
        <p>Save us. Do it one more time. Stop them. Smash them. Protect that lead.</p>
        <p>And the Giants' defense did, over and over, for the final 50 minutes of the game, all the way to the final seconds when the Falcons took four shots from inside the Giants' 20-yard line and could not score. The Giants won, 13-6, in a game in which their defense rose and defended its honor.</p>
        <p>Here is a quick recap, from start to finish:</p>
        <p>The special teams gains a turnover early and deep in Atlanta territory. Jason Sehorn intercepts a pass in the Atlanta end zone that chokes an Atlanta drive that had reached the Giants' 5. A nice combination blitz by Michael Strahan and Shaun Williams gets there. Uh-oh -- there goes Falcons quarterback Chris Chandler out for the game with pounded and bruised ribs. Sehorn races across the field and makes a third-down tackle on a running back running free. Jessie Armstead gains an interception. Pow! What a hit by Shaun Williams! Sehorn breaks up another pass. Cornelius Griffin gains a sack. Strahan gets another sack. Cedric Jones tips a pass. And Sehorn ends the final Atlanta play in the Giants' end zone by batting down a pass.</p>
        <p>There. Nice, neat, a package delivered by the Giants' defense.</p>
        <p>And how fitting. They were rattled by Washington and smacked by Tennessee and the criticism surfaced, the respect wavered. The Giants noticed. Especially Strahan.</p>
        <p>''When we were 3-0, I didn't get those questions,'' Strahan said. He was talking about questions about the defense in general and his lack of quarterback pressures and sacks in particular in the Giants' consecutive losses before this game.</p>
        <p>''No one played well against Tennessee,'' he continued. ''But everyone was looking at me like I am the problem. So be it. I used to be a media darling, the golden boy. But gold turns to bronze and bronze sometimes becomes tarnished.''</p>
        <p>And that can lead to disappointment and anger. Strahan and his teammates on defense played that way today, first against Chandler and then against his replacement, the former Giant Danny Kanell.</p>
        <p>''We wanted this game put in our hands and the more it went on that was how it turned out,'' Armstead said. ''Atlanta tried a lot of different things -- isolations, bootlegs -- but we prepared hard and we were ready because we knew the team that lost this game was going to take some real heat.''</p>
        <p>And that is what happened to the Falcons, a 2-4 team now that plays at the St. Louis Rams on Sunday.</p>
        <p>The Falcons talked about shocking the world and winning there. A more modest achievement would be keeping their quarterback alive.</p>
        <p>''Chris is real sore; it's his rib cage on his left side,'' Atlanta Coach Dan Reeves said of Chandler. ''A lot of bad things happened to us on offense. When you are struggling, the mistakes are magnified.''</p>
        <p>The Falcons made so many, magnification was not required.</p>
        <p>Two interceptions. One lost fumble. A missed field goal. Thirteen net rushing yards. Drops, missed blocks, out of sync, just a complete grind. Again, the Giants were only slightly better. But oh, that Giants defense.</p>
        <p>''They played pretty tough today,'' Kanell said. ''They blitzed us a lot and had a good plan. I think teams can sense that we are having trouble with the blitz. They sure did, and they threw more and more at us.''</p>
        <p>Sehorn traveled with receiver Terance Mathis and shut him down -- Mathis made 3 catches for 25 yards. He was frustrated.</p>
        <p>''They took me out of the game,'' Mathis said. ''We did some things to help them, but they are aggressive -- he was aggressive.''</p>
        <p>Sehorn was better than that. He sparkled.</p>
        <p>''I take my job seriously and our reputation seriously,'' he said.</p>
        <p>All of the Giants on defense, from coordinator John Fox on down, did.</p>
        <p>Two immobile quarterbacks helped the Giants' defense zero in and punch them out. Chandler and Kanell are pure pocket passers, so, the Giants viewed both like blocks of concrete. The pass rush rolled. The run defense swelled. The secondary feasted on receivers running rushed routes because their quarterbacks were being hounded.</p>
        <p>What will the Giants' defense do against more mobile quarterbacks like Steve McNair, who tripped them last week? And will the Giants' offense contribute enough on a steady basis to make their season more worthwhile?</p>
        <p>''Armstead, Strahan, Sehorn -- those are the three guys that give their defense a name and an identity,'' Falcons cornerback Ray Buchanan said. ''They join with the other role players to form a unit and together their defense is able to keep them in a lot of games. Sometimes they can really pressure the quarterback. Can they win their division or make the playoffs? It's up in the air. A lot of things are being decided right now.''</p>
        <p>Like which Giants' defense will ultimately stand. Yesterday, it was one intent or reclaiming its honor.</p>
        <p>ON PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
