<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>General Motors drops Ayer in favor of McCann-Erickson as agency for corporate advertising.</title>
    <meta content="09ADCO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/09/business/09ADCO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237428"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">General Motors Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ayer, N W, &amp; Partners</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mccann-Erickson Worldwide Advertising</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Elliott, Stuart</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001009T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CEED9133CF93AA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="841" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>General Motors drops Ayer in favor of McCann-Erickson as agency for corporate advertising.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Stuart Elliott</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Elliott, Stuart</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Advertising column reports that General Motors Corp has terminated its relationship with ad agency N W Ayer &amp; Partners after 28 years; will move its corporate campaign to McCann-Erickson's Detroit office (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AN era in automotive advertising is coming to a close as the General Motors Corporation ends its relationship with N. W. Ayer &amp; Partners after 28 years.</p>
        <p>Since 1972, Ayer had been creating corporate campaigns that sought to stimulate the sales of G.M. cars and trucks by burnishing the reputation of the General Motors brand rather than by promoting specific products or divisions. But on Friday, General Motors said it would shift the responsibilities for corporate advertising and marketing from the Ayer office in the Detroit suburb of Troy, Mich., which had G.M. as its only client, to another agency that has worked for General Motors for many decades, McCann-Erickson Detroit, also based in Troy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AN era in automotive advertising is coming to a close as the General Motors Corporation ends its relationship with N. W. Ayer &amp; Partners after 28 years.</p>
        <p>Since 1972, Ayer had been creating corporate campaigns that sought to stimulate the sales of G.M. cars and trucks by burnishing the reputation of the General Motors brand rather than by promoting specific products or divisions. But on Friday, General Motors said it would shift the responsibilities for corporate advertising and marketing from the Ayer office in the Detroit suburb of Troy, Mich., which had G.M. as its only client, to another agency that has worked for General Motors for many decades, McCann-Erickson Detroit, also based in Troy.</p>
        <p>''While we have had a long and productive client-agency relationship'' with Ayer, said John G. Middlebrook, vice president and general manager for vehicle brand marketing and corporate advertising at General Motors in Detroit, ''we believe this consolidation with McCann will integrate our strategic and tactical efforts.''</p>
        <p>G.M.'s spending on corporate image ads has varied in recent years, rising and falling in a range estimated from $15 million to $60 million. The most familiar campaign from Ayer, a unit of the B Com3  Group, celebrated the G.M. logo as a ''mark of excellence''; the most recent centered on the loyalty of owners of General Motors vehicles as demonstrated by repeat purchases.</p>
        <p>The dismissal of Ayer, which will lead B Com3  to close the Ayer office in Troy, was reported late Thursday night by the Web site of the trade publication Adweek. It is the most recent in a series of consolidations that have altered the advertising landscape in the competitive automotive industry.</p>
        <p>In July, G.M. made the largest assignment in the history of Madison Avenue when it consolidated duties for media planning -- deciding where to run ads with an annual budget of $2.9 billion -- at a new agency to be formed by B Com3 . And the DaimlerChrysler Group in Auburn Hills, Mich., part of DaimlerChrysler A. G., is considering the consolidation of creative and media tasks for all Chrysler, Dodge, Jeep and corporate ads -- with an annual budget of $1.8 billion -- at units of either the Omnicom Group or True North Communications.</p>
        <p>The G.M. decision to remove Ayer from its agency roster means that McCann-Erickson Detroit will add Ayer's tasks to its G.M. accounts, which include creative duties for the Buick division, developing corporate brand strategy and creative duties for what is called cross-divisional retail advertising, encouraging shoppers to visit dealers for the mainstay G.M. brands: Chevrolet, Pontiac, Oldsmobile, Buick and Cadillac.</p>
        <p>McCann-Erickson Detroit, part of the McCann-Erickson Worldwide Advertising unit of the McCann-Erickson World Group, has worked for G.M. continuously since 1958; its first assignment came in 1930.</p>
        <p>The dismissal of Ayer is only the second time in 42 years that General Motors has taken a big assignment from a roster agency -- and both times, McCann-Erickson Detroit was involved. In 1997, the agency lost creative duties for GMC trucks to Ammirati Puris Lintas in New York, now the Lowe Lintas &amp; Partners unit of the Lowe Group. Both McCann and Lowe are owned by the Interpublic Group of Companies.</p>
        <p>Ayer's dismissal was not entirely unexpected. Eyebrows were raised last year when the assignment to create a corporate campaign to appear during the 2000 Summer Olympics -- promoting the G.M. sponsorship of the United States Olympic team in conjunction with the United Auto Workers union -- was awarded to a different shop on the General Motors agency roster, Berlin Cameron &amp; Partners in New York.</p>
        <p>And after B Com3  landed the consolidated G.M. media planning assignment, in a review that also included the Initiative Media Worldwide unit of Interpublic, it was not too surprising that Interpublic would be favored the next time General Motors made an agency change. Interpublic units like Lowe, McCann-Erickson and Campbell-Ewald share the bulk of the G.M. account with B Com3  units like Leo Burnett Worldwide and D'Arcy Masius Benton &amp; Bowles Worldwide.</p>
        <p>The loss of G.M. costs Ayer a prestigious account from one of its three major national clients, leaving Continental Airlines and the Kitchenaid division of Maytag along with assignments from smaller marketers like Charming Shoppes; all that work is handled from the Ayer headquarters in New York. The accounts of other major national clients like Avon Products and Procter &amp; Gamble left Ayer when they were transferred to a sibling, D'Arcy.</p>
        <p>Most of the eight Ayer employees in Troy will be transferred to other units of B Com3  there, said Tricia Kenney, a spokeswoman for Ayer in New York, including G.M. Planworks, which will handle the newly consolidated media planning duties for General Motors.</p>
        <p>In addition, Ms. Kenney said, Ayer ''has just been awarded an undisclosed new business assignment for two consumer products from a major brand, which will more than replace the G.M. business financially.'' Details are to be disclosed in a week or two, she added.</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
