<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Once Again, Us vs. Them</title>
    <meta content="09ISRA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/09/world/09ISRA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237502"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="WHOSE HOLY LAND? NEWS ANALYSIS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sontag, Deborah</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001009T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E2DB103CF93AA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1049" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Once Again, Us vs. Them</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DEBORAH SONTAG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sontag, Deborah</byline>
      <dateline>JERUSALEM, Oct. 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ten days of violence between Palestinians and Israelis dissolves internal differences in both camps, reducing conflict to barest essence: Jew against Arab, Arab against Jew; many Israelis, especially doves, are staggered by swift tumble from what seemed to be the brink of a resolution back down into depths of an elemental ethnic hatred; there is no such disillusionment among Palestinians because for an overwhelming majority of them, the peace felt only skin-deep, not bone-deep, and very fragile; unity throughout Arab world has not been so strong for quite some time; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the degenerative violence of the last 10 days, the conflict that had been so elaborately dressed in the civilizing cloak of a peace effort has been stripped to its barest essence: Jew against Arab, Arab against Jew.</p>
        <p>The internal differences in each camp have been pushed aside, uniting right and left in Israel, government and opposition in the Palestinian world, and Arabs throughout a region that had been deeply divided. The old, familiar notion of us against them has been sharpened and pushed to the front once again.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the degenerative violence of the last 10 days, the conflict that had been so elaborately dressed in the civilizing cloak of a peace effort has been stripped to its barest essence: Jew against Arab, Arab against Jew.</p>
        <p>The internal differences in each camp have been pushed aside, uniting right and left in Israel, government and opposition in the Palestinian world, and Arabs throughout a region that had been deeply divided. The old, familiar notion of us against them has been sharpened and pushed to the front once again.</p>
        <p>Many Israelis, especially the doves, are staggered by this swift tumble from what seemed to be the brink of a resolution back down into the depths of the elemental ethnic hatred at the root of their blood-soaked conflict. But the Palestinians are not. For an overwhelming majority of them, the peace felt only skin-deep -- not bone-deep -- and very fragile.</p>
        <p>The visible conflict now pits the nationalist Palestinian youths against the soldiers who represent the Israeli occupation, would-be state against state.</p>
        <p>But from underneath, the longer the battle rages, a more primal conflict surfaces, too, tribe against tribe.</p>
        <p>A Jewish settler kills a Palestinian; a Palestinian kills a Jewish motorist. This is not exactly the ''people to people'' component envisioned by the peace effort. Stabbing for stabbing, stoning for stoning, an eye for an eye. The Israeli right is glumly smug; this is what they had been warning against.</p>
        <p>In Israel, tensions between Israeli Jews and Israeli Arabs have also been laid bare and are so raw right now that at a mall outside Nazareth they hurled rocks at each other this weekend. After Palestinians sacked the shrine known as Joseph's Tomb on Saturday morning, Israeli Jews vandalized an Israeli-Arab house of worship, an old mosque in Tiberias, on Saturday night.</p>
        <p>Israeli newspapers, even liberal ones, have been grouping the dead ethnically, not by nationality: the Israeli casualties do not, by their count, include the Arabs born in Israel who were shot dead by their own police force. It is, some have remarked, as if Israel and the Palestinian territories had returned to the time of the British mandate.</p>
        <p>In the Arab world, pan-Arab unity has not been so strong for quite some time. The Hezbollah guerrillas have hitched their Katyusha-filled wagon to the Palestinian cause, erasing borders. ''Hezbollah joins the fight for Palestine,'' a Lebanese daily proclaimed in a headline today.</p>
        <p>Kuwait has agreed to attend an Arab summit meeting in Cairo at the end of the month, without raising objections to the expected presence of Iraq, which invaded its southern neighbor in 1990, because suddenly the Jewish-Arab conflict has transcended internal Arab ones.</p>
        <p>For many outsiders, it would be difficult to understand how Prime Minister Ehud Barak of Israel could contemplate forming a national emergency government with Ariel Sharon, the right-wing leader. To many, it looks as if Mr. Sharon -- in his visit to a contested holy site in Jerusalem, which the Palestinians call the provocation for their uprising -- sabotaged the peace effort and Mr. Barak, the would-be peacemaker, too.</p>
        <p>But what matters most to Israelis now, no matter what their political stripe, is finding a common ground against a common enemy. For Yasir Arafat, the Palestinian leader, it is a confirmation of what he has been saying all along: that it does not matter who runs Israel, because they are all Zionists.</p>
        <p>That, of course, is disputed not only by Israelis but also by the American and European leaders who have endorsed Mr. Barak's peacemaking efforts as courageous.</p>
        <p>For many Israelis, peace, recently, meant a gradual sloughing off of fear, fear of terrorism and existential fear. To them, it did not matter so much that it was an interim peace and not a permanent one.</p>
        <p>For many Palestinians, however, the interim period went on too long and did not change their lives enough. They were still hemmed into refugee camps, and impoverished. They still faced Israeli checkpoints, and settlers still encroached on what they considered their land; nothing essential to them like the return of relatives, the refugees or the future of Jerusalem had been resolved.</p>
        <p>''I don't know why Israelis should be so surprised,'' said Khaled Tomer, a Ramallah resident. ''We kept saying we were frustrated, dissatisfied and ready to burst.''</p>
        <p>To many Israelis, staggered to find themselves at the brink of what could be war, there is a disconcerting sense of time collapsing on itself. ''Yom Kippur 2000 is one link in a chain that is connected to Yom Kippur 1973,'' Nahum Barnea, a longtime columnist, wrote, referring to the October war that began on the holy day. ''It seems as if the circle of Arab hostility around the country was never broken.''</p>
        <p>Tonight, many Israelis began their retreat into Yom Kippur, the Day of Atonement, with a very edgy feeling, especially in Jerusalem, where tanks were positioned on the edge of the city and sirens cut the night. They were scared for their personal security, scared for their nation and scared of going backward after so much cocksure talk of normalization and its effects on society.</p>
        <p>''What's going on here?'' Sever Plotzer wrote in the newspaper Yediot Ahronot. ''It was only two weeks ago that we were buying furniture in Ramallah, gambling in Jericho, importing vegetables from the West Bank villages, and reading about the Palestinians' intention to build six new duty-free malls for Israelis along the border with the autonomous areas.''</p>
        <p>''How does all that sit with the outburst of the horrible hatred that flooded the territories and the Arab sector?'' he continued. ''Where did we make the wrong assumption? Where was this concealed so that we didn't see it? And what is the truth: the fire at Joseph's tomb or the casino in Jericho? War or peace?''</p>
        <p>WHOSE HOLY LAND? NEWS ANALYSIS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
