<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>METRO BRIEFING</title>
    <meta content="09MBRF$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/09/nyregion/09MBRF.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237489"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001009T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07EEDD103CF93AA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1797" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>METRO BRIEFING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by Anthony Ramirez</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NEW YORK</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: UNCONSCIOUS PATRONS AT NIGHTCLUB  A security guard at a Chelsea nightclub was charged with reckless endangerment for not reporting that three patrons were unconscious inside the club hours after closing time yesterday morning. The patrons had to be removed by ambulance from the club, Twilo, on West 27th Street, at 9 a.m. yesterday, apparently after having spent the night, the police said. The police said they believe the patrons had taken drugs while inside the club, which the city has previously accused of allowing open use of the drug Ecstasy. The three patrons were in stable condition at Manhattan hospitals. The employee, Joseph Murray, of Jamaica, Queens, was held pending arraignment. Two Twilo patrons have died apparently of drug overdoses since 1998.</p>
        <p>C. J. Chivers (NYT)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: NUDE PHOTO SESSION IN STREET  At dawn yesterday, about 200 nude people lay down on West 72nd Street in front on the Dakota apartment building to pose for a photographer known for shooting large groups of nudes in public places. The photographer, Spencer Tunick, had wanted to shoot at Grand Central Terminal but the city denied him a permit despite a Supreme Court ruling in his favor earlier this year. In protest, Mr. Tunick shot without a permit yesterday and moved the shoot to Central Park and the nearby Dakota apartment building, partly to honor the birthday today of John Lennon, who lived in the Dakota. The police did not interfere.</p>
        <p>Eun Lee Koh (NYT)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NEW YORK</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: UNCONSCIOUS PATRONS AT NIGHTCLUB  A security guard at a Chelsea nightclub was charged with reckless endangerment for not reporting that three patrons were unconscious inside the club hours after closing time yesterday morning. The patrons had to be removed by ambulance from the club, Twilo, on West 27th Street, at 9 a.m. yesterday, apparently after having spent the night, the police said. The police said they believe the patrons had taken drugs while inside the club, which the city has previously accused of allowing open use of the drug Ecstasy. The three patrons were in stable condition at Manhattan hospitals. The employee, Joseph Murray, of Jamaica, Queens, was held pending arraignment. Two Twilo patrons have died apparently of drug overdoses since 1998.</p>
        <p>C. J. Chivers (NYT)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: NUDE PHOTO SESSION IN STREET  At dawn yesterday, about 200 nude people lay down on West 72nd Street in front on the Dakota apartment building to pose for a photographer known for shooting large groups of nudes in public places. The photographer, Spencer Tunick, had wanted to shoot at Grand Central Terminal but the city denied him a permit despite a Supreme Court ruling in his favor earlier this year. In protest, Mr. Tunick shot without a permit yesterday and moved the shoot to Central Park and the nearby Dakota apartment building, partly to honor the birthday today of John Lennon, who lived in the Dakota. The police did not interfere.</p>
        <p>Eun Lee Koh (NYT)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: FOUR-ALARM FIRE  Two firefighters suffered minor injuries yesterday morning at a four-alarm fire on the West Side. The fire, on the ninth floor of a 26-story brick building at 250 West 57th Street, took nearly three hours to extinguish and tied up traffic until 9 a.m., the authorities said. James Spollen, a Fire Department spokesman, said the cause of the fire could not immediately be determined.</p>
        <p>C. J. Chivers (NYT)</p>
        <p>QUEENS: 2 KILLED IN CAR CRASH  Two people were killed and two others injured in a head-on collision in Flushing early yesterday. The police said a 27-year-old man lost control of a 1992 Acura while traveling west on Roosevelt Avenue at 1:30 a.m. and veered into the oncoming traffic near the intersection with 126th Street, striking a 1987 Acura head on. The driver, whose name was withheld by the police, and his passenger, Cindy Wong, 20, of 41-25 Kissena Boulevard, Queens, were killed. The driver and the passenger of the second car were both in serious condition yesterday but were expected to recover, the police said. The police issued no summonses in the case.</p>
        <p>C. J. Chivers (NYT)</p>
        <p>WHITE PLAINS: TEACHER CONVICTED OF ABUSE  A former fifth-grade teacher was convicted yesterday of sexually abusing two boys, ages 8 and 10. A Westchester County Court jury found the man, Steven Nowicki, 37, guilty on 22 counts of sodomy and other charges. The family had invited Mr. Nowicki, the teacher of the older boy, to a New Year's Eve party at their Dobbs Ferry home in 1998, and asked him to stay because he seemed too drunk to drive home. The boys testified that Mr. Nowicki had climbed into their beds and molested them. Mr. Nowicki faces up to 50 years in prison.</p>
        <p>Eun Lee Koh (NYT)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: NEW SUBWAY WEB SITE  The Straphangers Campaign, the advocacy group for riders, has begun a Web site -- www.straphangers.org -- that will try to make up for what the group sees as a deficiency in the way subway information is conveyed to the public. The site, said Gene Russianoff, a staff lawyer for the group, will simplify and explain information that is announced by New York City Transit every week about changes on the city's 20 subway lines. The group will also send that information every week by e-mail to riders who want it, at no charge.</p>
        <p>Randy Kennedy (NYT)</p>
        <p>NEW CITY: FEDERAL SHORTFALL ALLEGED  A Rockland County legislator has asserted that the county is being shortchanged by $600 million in state and federal money. The legislator, Ryan S. Karben, a Democrat from Ramapo, said last week that Rockland received only 1 percent of the federal dollars spent annually in New York even though it had 1.5 percent of the state's population. He also said that its share of state money for public schools and local government was smaller than that for counties with a similarly sized population.</p>
        <p>Winnie Hu (NYT)</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY</p>
        <p>WOODBRIDGE: MONEY FOR SEX-OFFENDER CENTER  Mayor James E. McGreevey, left, said he would demand that the state pay $1.3 million a year in exchange for Woodbridge's accepting a center for 300 sex offenders. The state is not obliged to make such a payment, but Mr. Greevey said it was needed to cover costs like expansion of the local sewer system. Pete McDonough, a spokesman for Gov. Christine Todd Whitman, said the state is open to discussing the issue. The center has prompted widespread local opposition.</p>
        <p>Steve Strunsky (NYT)</p>
        <p>NEWARK: NEW POLICE CHIEF FOR BRIDGE  The Port Authority of New York and New Jersey has named Charles Torres as police commander of the George Washington Bridge, which the authority calls the world's busiest because 53.4 million vehicles crossed it last year. Captain Torres, 46, succeeds Captain George Albin, who was commander for the last two years and will now head the police unit at the authority's New Jersey marine terminals.</p>
        <p>(NYT)</p>
        <p>CONNECTICUT</p>
        <p>HARTFORD: PRISON OVERCROWDING  A little-noticed provision in a new state law expanding victims' rights could lead to crowding in state jails, state officials say. The law took effect this month and says defendants convicted of threatening or using force are ineligible for release while awaiting sentencing. That means that even defendants who plead guilty in exchange for a suspended sentence would be forced to remain in jail during the weeks background reports for sentencings are prepared. John M. Bailey, the chief state's attorney, saying that the law would make defendants reluctant to plead guilty, said he would urge a change in the law when the Legislature reconvenes in January.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
