<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Niche Radio Finds Its Footing on the Internet</title>
    <meta content="09RADI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/09/technology/09RADI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237429"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MEDIA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television and Radio Programming</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Simon, Clea</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001009T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E6D8133CF93AA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1404" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Niche Radio Finds Its Footing on the Internet</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLEA SIMON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Simon, Clea</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Niche radio programming over Internet is growing thanks to absence of federal licensing restrictions and improved technology that makes the transmission of high-quality Web audio viable; another factor is consolidation of radio ownership and resulting trend toward homogeneous formats on broadcast bands; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In cyberspace, there is no fade out. No high buildings or mountains obscure the radio signals transmitted over the Internet. The geographical limits based on station power or on federal licensing restrictions have no relevance.</p>
        <p>No wonder many radio stations with loyal but small followings have in recent years expanded into Web broadcasting as a means of transcending their traditional boundaries. And not only have they found a market hungry for their idiosyncratic programming, but many have begun reaping financial benefits.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In cyberspace, there is no fade out. No high buildings or mountains obscure the radio signals transmitted over the Internet. The geographical limits based on station power or on federal licensing restrictions have no relevance.</p>
        <p>No wonder many radio stations with loyal but small followings have in recent years expanded into Web broadcasting as a means of transcending their traditional boundaries. And not only have they found a market hungry for their idiosyncratic programming, but many have begun reaping financial benefits.</p>
        <p>''There is no other station like this in the world,'' said Ken Freedman, station manager for WFMU-FM, a noncommercial station that broadcasts from Jersey City at 91.1 on the FM band and has been streaming its programming onto the Web at www.wfmu.org since 1997.</p>
        <p>WFMU, Mr. Freedman explained, is a small, independent station with a fairly weak signal. Its shows are aggressively eclectic, ranging from a morning Judaica program to home recordings. Such a station ''is perfect for the Internet,'' Mr. Freedman said. ''We fill this niche.''</p>
        <p>In the three years that WFMU has been on the Web, its list of listener-contributors has grown by about 1,000, raising the total to 9,000. Web listeners contributed about $90,000, or 15 percent, of the station's operating budget during the annual fund-raiser in March. And though the majority of listeners are in Brooklyn and Manhattan, Mr. Freedman said, the station has heard from people tuning in on their computers in San Francisco and Tanzania.</p>
        <p>Other niche stations are also on better financial footing as a result of their Web expansion since the beginning of 1998. They include WWOZ-FM, a New Orleans community radio station that can be heard on the Web at www.wwoz.org; WOXY-FM, a small commercial alternative-rock station in Ohio that can be heard at www.woxy.com; and KFAN, a commercial broadcaster of an eclectic mix of Texas music that uses the World Wide Web address www.texas rebelradio.com.</p>
        <p>The experience of these and other stations indicates that Web radio is no longer a semiaudible experiment, but a potentially viable business strategy for conventional broadcasters.</p>
        <p>Two trends may be in play here. The first is the increased use of high-speed Internet connections and rapidly improving technology, which make the transmission of high-quality audio viable.</p>
        <p>The second is the consolidation of radio ownership. A shrinking number of corporate owners control a growing share of the nation's radio stations and program them with proven, if homogeneous, formats. That means niche-format broadcasting has become much less common on the broadcast bands. Indeed, the radio-holding giant Clear Channel Communications took its adult-alternative station in Santa Monica, Calif.,  off the air in August, leaving it to sink or swim solely on the Web at WorldClassRock.com.</p>
        <p>But the small niche stations see the Web not as a last resort, but as a way to grow. ''Is Celtic music your choice?'' asked Peggy Miles. ''In a typical market, you can't find that.'' Ms. Miles runs Intervox Communications, a digital media consulting firm.</p>
        <p>''But if you can take a thousand people from Boston, a thousand people from Wales and a thousand people from Denver, you start to build a market,'' Ms. Miles continued. ''You can develop a brand. It's a novelty, and you get people listening.''</p>
        <p>That can be a boon for the small, independent stations that have long been eking out a living in conventional broadcasting with their regional or specialized formats.</p>
        <p>''Internet broadcasting has counteracted a really terrible trend,'' said Mr. Freedman, whose station has been on the air since 1958. ''Our FM coverage area has been getting smaller and smaller and smaller,'' he said. He cited competition in the New York-New Jersey metropolitan area from a growing number of licensed stations and from a higher transmitter power that larger stations have been authorized to use as the airwaves grow more congested.</p>
        <p>Dwayne Breashears, program director of WWOZ-FM (90.7) in New Orleans, tells a similar story. ''We're heard around the world,'' he said. ''We're getting 700,000 hits per month on our Web site.''</p>
        <p>The station, which has broadcast a mix of jazz, blues, zydeco and other traditional Louisiana musical styles since going on the air in 1980, is primarily supported by the station's license holder, the New Orleans Jazz and Heritage Foundation. But listener contributions help the station meet its budget, Mr. Breashears said, noting that nearly 10 percent of the $250,000 raised in last spring's semiannual fund drive came in listener donations from the Web audience, including contributors from China, New Zealand and Britain.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, for small commercial stations, like WOXY-FM (97.7) in Ohio, Internet broadcasting can help expand the advertising base. WOXY, an alternative rock station in Oxford, a semirural college town between Dayton and Cincinnati, has rarely shown up in the area's traditional ratings during the station's 19 years of broadcasting under the ownership of Doug and Nancy Balogh.</p>
        <p>Besides artists like Radiohead and Rancid, which are staples of alternative rock stations owned by big corporations, WOXY plays music by Matthew Sweet, Foil and Ladytron, smaller-label artists who are seldom heard elsewhere.</p>
        <p>But making money was never easy in the small market, which has about a million potential listeners, including a seasonal population of 130,000 students at colleges in the area. Since WOXY expanded into Webcasting two years ago, however, broadcast advertising revenue and online ad revenue have grown significantly, said Mr. Balogh, who declined to provide specific figures.</p>
        <p>But some industry analysts warn that the high costs of emerging technology could prove a barrier to the Web for some small stations. The small independents must ''keep up with the gazillions in Web development being spent by AOL and other big corporations,'' said Tom Taylor, editor of M Street Daily, a radio trade publication.</p>
        <p>To get on the Web, a small station usually contracts with an Internet service provider, which encodes the traditional broadcast signal for Internet distribution. Start-up fees for such service can run more than $10,000, said Jayson Fritz, owner and manager of the Texas-music station KFAN in Fredericksburg, Tex. Additional expenses, like the fees for the high-speed line that KFAN uses to carry the signal, can run $400 to $500 more a month.</p>
        <p>As Ms. Miles, the consultant, pointed out, Web broadcasters must also bear the expense of delivering the signal. In Web broadcasting, Internet service providers charge by the amount of information, or the bit rate, actually being encoded and transmitted.</p>
        <p>Roughly speaking, that amounts to to the station's being charged for the number of Web listeners who tune in. Prem Gill, a spokesman for GlobalMedia.com, an Internet service provider based in Vancouver, British Columbia, estimated the cost at $20 to $30 for every 100 users who listened for 100 minutes each.</p>
        <p>But the Internet service providers usually shoulder some of those expenses, which can also be offset by higher broadcast and Web advertising revenue.</p>
        <p>The Web site has also become an e-tailer. ''We've made money from the Web from Day 1,'' Mr. Fritz said. ''We probably sell $2,000 a month in merchandise,'' he added, describing the T-shirts, caps, key chains and jewelry that feature the station's call letters branded onto a map of Texas.</p>
        <p>Such merchandising sales may be the clearest example of the way a station can create a niche brand, and then capitalize on its cachet.</p>
        <p>''We're a very musically driven station,'' said Mr. Fritz, whose station stresses the music of Texas, whether the traditional yodelings of Don Walser or the rock of the Austin Lounge Lizards. Besides its weekly live performances, its features on unsigned local artists, and jazz and blues shows, KFAN plays a roster of songs much larger than is usually considered commercially viable.</p>
        <p>''As more and more stations practice safe radio,'' Mr. Fritz said, ''that's what sets us apart.''</p>
        <p>MEDIA</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
