<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Long a Sanctuary From Africa's Conflicts, Zambia Now Chafes in the Role</title>
    <meta content="Y09ZAM$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/09/world/09ZAMB.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237476"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Firearms</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Zambia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mayukwayukwa (Zambia)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Africa</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cauvin, Henri E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Zambia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Zambia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Firearms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001009T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E6DE103CF93AA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="927" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Long a Sanctuary From Africa's Conflicts, Zambia Now Chafes in the Role</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HENRI E. CAUVIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cauvin, Henri E</byline>
      <dateline>MAYUKWAYUKWA, Zambia</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Zambia is becoming less hospitable to fellow Africans seeking refuge from liberation struggles; country has given shelter to thousands of refugees from neighboring countries over the years; refugees now number almost a quarter of a million, and the influx is rising with no signs of abating; refugees are blamed for crime and arms smuggling in Mayukwayukwa in country's western province; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For nearly as long as this nation has been called Zambia, settlements like this enormous encampment in the country's western province have given shelter to thousands of refugees from neighboring African nations.</p>
        <p>In the early years after Zambia gained independence in 1964, fellow Africans sought refuge from liberation struggles; today, they are mostly fleeing post-colonial conflicts, particularly in Angola, the home of Africa's longest-running civil war.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For nearly as long as this nation has been called Zambia, settlements like this enormous encampment in the country's western province have given shelter to thousands of refugees from neighboring African nations.</p>
        <p>In the early years after Zambia gained independence in 1964, fellow Africans sought refuge from liberation struggles; today, they are mostly fleeing post-colonial conflicts, particularly in Angola, the home of Africa's longest-running civil war.</p>
        <p>For decades, Zambia has embraced all comers: from peasants fleeing fighting in their fields to future presidents seeking a haven from would-be assassins in countries like Mozambique, Namibia, South Africa or Zimbabwe. Freed from white rule years before those countries, Zambia became virtually the epicenter of the struggle for majority rule.</p>
        <p>Now, however, the Zambian welcome is wearing somewhat thin and many of the country's almost 10 million people are wondering when its role as the region's sanctuary of last resort will end. The anxiety among ordinary Zambians, while only occasionally approaching out-and-out anger, is nevertheless an increasing part of the social dynamic.</p>
        <p>''People here are asking what the little man has gained, how are ordinary Zambians benefiting from the refugees,'' said Angelline Rudakubana, who has worked with refugees for 30 years and is now working for the World Food Program in Zambia. ''They've suffered a lot for other countries. They did a lot for Africa, but the average Zambian did not benefit.''</p>
        <p>There is little sign that things will change soon: the number of refugees nationwide, almost a quarter of a million, is rising, and the influx is unlikely to abate.</p>
        <p>During the last year, the number of refugees here at Mayukwayukwa, established almost 35 years ago and the oldest of Zambia's refugee settlements, has increased almost fourfold, to 15,000. The settlement has grown from 10 camps over seven and a half square miles to 28 camps over about 10 square miles, and efforts to acquire more land from local chiefs are under way, said Samuel Mbumbi, the project coordinator for the Lutheran World Federation, which runs the settlement with the United Nations high commissioner for refugees.</p>
        <p>Angola's eastern provinces, which border this region of Zambia, have long been strongholds of the Angolan rebel movement led by Jonas Savimbi. In the last year, Angola's forces have won crucial ground from the rebels, driving columns of refugees into Zambian towns. Last month, with fighting raging near the border, a Zambian village was hit by two bombs in an Angolan attack on a nearby rebel position.</p>
        <p>The influx has transformed Mayukwayukwa. Last month, the settlement acquired a fixed police post to contend with a growing crime problem and to curb the flow of weapons that some refugees are suspected of smuggling into the camps.</p>
        <p>''The old settlements, they are O.K.,'' said Majeri Mayemba, 20, who lives in a village called Mapulanga, on the edge of the settlement. ''The newer ones, that's where the problem is. When there is a football match, these refugees come with knives, they fight with knives.''</p>
        <p>Besides the police post, the United Nations refugee agency runs a clinic that is only half-finished but already is seeing dozens of patients a day to alleviate the burden on the lone government clinic in Mayukwayukwa.</p>
        <p>The influx has started to take a toll on the amicable coexistence that prevailed for many years among Angolans and Zambians in this region, where many of them trace their ancestry to the same tribes.</p>
        <p>''Look at our local resources,'' said Simbuwa Mubita, a health worker at the government clinic here and a native of the western province. ''They cut wood. They cut trees. They're a burden on the resources.''</p>
        <p>Even in the corridors of the capital, Lusaka, government officials have been increasingly vocal about the refugees. At a September conference, the Ministry of Home Affairs exhorted refugees to obey Zambia's laws and vowed that refugees would not be treated any better than the ordinary citizens of Zambia, most of whom live in poverty.</p>
        <p>''All of a sudden you hear Zambians talking about refugees, especially the government,'' Ms. Rudakubana. ''They never used to. Now, everybody is talking about refugees. That means there is a problem.''</p>
        <p>One very real challenge is finding enough arable land for the refugees. Much of the land here in Mayukwayukwa, for example, is just sand.</p>
        <p>In the short term, many of the newcomers are eligible for aid from the World Food Program, which feeds about 70,000 of the refugees in Zambia. After two planting seasons, however, those people are supposed to support themselves -- a potential problem for a government already contending with over-farming of arable land.</p>
        <p>Even when land is made available, convincing some refugees to plant food and essentially settle is difficult.  ''They say, 'No, we're going back very soon,' '' said Mr. Mbumbi of the Lutheran World Federation.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mbumbi, himself a Zambian, is eager to provide proper care for the refugees. But even he worries that the influx of Angolans will eventually change the place in ways that Zambians may have never intended.</p>
        <p>''I feel the war in Angola is putting us in a very awkward situation,'' he said. ''We have allowed a situation where people are coming from Angola, and we don't even really know how many of them there are. I think that in the years to come, some of the Angolans will say, 'This is our country, and we can do what we want.' ''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
