<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In New Jersey Senate Debate, Compliments Seasoned With Scorn</title>
    <meta content="09JERS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/09/politics/09JERS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237496"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="CAMPAIGN 2000: NEW JERSEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Corzine, Jon S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Halbfinger, David M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Franks, Robert D (Repr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001009T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E2DC103CF93AA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1600" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In New Jersey Senate Debate, Compliments Seasoned With Scorn</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID M. HALBFINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Halbfinger, David M</byline>
      <dateline>EDISON, N.J., Oct. 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Representative Bob Franks and Jon S Corzine, in their first debate of United States Senate campaign in New Jersey, attack each other's records, campaign tactics and stands on various issues; debate is well mannered slugfest, with no talk of character or trust; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Representative Bob Franks and Jon S. Corzine jabbed at each other for nearly a full hour today in their first debate of the United States Senate campaign in New Jersey, attacking each other's records, campaign tactics and stands on issues like health care, the environment and gun control.</p>
        <p>The first public side-by-side confrontation between the two men, who are members of the same church, was a well-mannered slugfest. There was no talk of character or trust, and each man paid the other a compliment or two before deflating him with scorn or sarcasm.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Representative Bob Franks and Jon S. Corzine jabbed at each other for nearly a full hour today in their first debate of the United States Senate campaign in New Jersey, attacking each other's records, campaign tactics and stands on issues like health care, the environment and gun control.</p>
        <p>The first public side-by-side confrontation between the two men, who are members of the same church, was a well-mannered slugfest. There was no talk of character or trust, and each man paid the other a compliment or two before deflating him with scorn or sarcasm.</p>
        <p>Mr. Franks, who is trailing in the most recent polls by as much as 14 percentage points, took every opportunity to paint Mr. Corzine as a spendthrift liberal whose ambitious social programs would drive the nation into deficits, and said Mr. Corzine was contributing to public cynicism by refusing to release his tax returns.</p>
        <p>At the same time, Mr. Franks, a four-term Republican congressman who was all but unknown to most New Jerseyans before Mr. Corzine started vilifying him in campaign commercials two weeks ago, sought to portray himself as a common-sense, experienced defender of New Jersey's interests in Washington.</p>
        <p>''Everybody in America knows you've got the most liberal agenda of anyone running anywhere in the country today,'' Mr. Franks said at one point, describing Mr. Corzine's support for universal health insurance, long-term care for the elderly and the disabled, and free preschool and college tuition. ''There's only 100 cents in every dollar. I think you would've appreciated that from Wall Street. But I've had to make the tough decisions to finally balance the federal budget.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Franks, a career politician, bitingly referred to some of Mr. Corzine's statements as ''silly'' or ''unbelievable.'' But Mr. Corzine, the former co-chairman of Goldman, Sachs &amp; Company, showed he had improved greatly since the Democratic primary debates, when he frequently appeared nervous and inarticulate.</p>
        <p>Today, though he remained hard to follow at times, he seemed more relaxed and countered a number of Mr. Franks's barbs with his own critiques of Mr. Franks's tactics and voting record. He said, for example, that Mr. Franks was long on talk about saving the environment but short on money for conservation initiatives.</p>
        <p>At another point, Mr. Corzine said his proposal for free tuition at state colleges for students with at least a B average would cost $2.2 billion a year, but that Mr. Franks was claiming the price would be $58 billion. ''Sometimes I think that's one of the reasons that people are cynical about political debate,'' Mr. Corzine said.</p>
        <p>The debate, held at the studios of News 12 New Jersey, a cable station, was carried live on that station and a second local cable channel, as well as nationally on C-SPAN. Mr. Franks and Mr. Corzine, each in a dark suit and white shirt, sat in red leather armchairs before a black curtain. The audience of about 30 people included three prominent Democrats -- Senator Frank R. Lautenberg, whom the two candidates are hoping to succeed, and Senator Robert G. Torricelli, with Representative Robert Menendez separating them -- but none of the state's most prominent Republicans.</p>
        <p>It was a quick-paced encounter, with no opening statements, and the candidates' differences were starkly drawn right from the start.</p>
        <p>In the only question on foreign policy, the two men were asked if they agreed with the United States's abstention from a Security Council vote on Saturday condemning what a resolution called Israel's ''excessive use of force'' in clashes with Palestinians over the last two weeks.</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine, who says on his campaign Web site that the United States must ''veto, whenever possible, anti-Israel resolutions,'' nonetheless said he approved of the abstention, without explaining why.</p>
        <p>Mr. Franks called the vote ''a mistake.'' He added, ''When the rest of the world gangs up on Israel, we have no choice but to veto that type of anti-Israel resolution.''</p>
        <p>The two men also differed dramatically on social issues like gun control. Mr. Franks said he supported an assault weapons ban, trigger locks, and stiffer penalties for gun crimes,  but opposed Mr. Corzine's call for mandatory gun licensing and registration. Mr. Corzine complimented Mr. Franks for the measures he supported, but said that as a state lawmaker, Mr. Franks had tried to ''strip down'' a 1990 assault weapons ban, and that the 1994 ban Mr. Franks voted for in Congress ''allows people to own Uzis.'' He added, ''I don't think that's real gun control.''</p>
        <p>On abortion rights, both men said they supported the Roe v. Wade decision, which recognized a woman's right to choose an abortion. But Mr. Franks said he favored requiring parental notification for minors seeking abortions and banning the late-term procedure referred to by critics as partial-birth abortion, which he called ''a form of infanticide.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine, who supports no such restrictions, answered a hypothetical question by saying that if he had a pregnant 14-year-old daughter contemplating an abortion, ''Our family would have been open and we would have related to each other enough that we would have that kind of discussion.'' But he added that for girls with abusive parents, ''It is dangerous to try to put frameworks around this that might end up harming the health and life of a child.''</p>
        <p>Much of the debate focused on government spending for social programs, and quickly fell into a pattern in which Mr. Franks attacked, and Mr. Corzine defended his more ambitious proposals. On health care, Mr. Franks likened Mr. Corzine's ideas to Hillary Rodham Clinton's failed 1993 effort at a national health insurance system. He faulted Mr. Corzine for favoring a requirement that employers pay to insure their workers, using a favorite line, ''To me there's only one thing more unfortunate than an employee without health care insurance, and that's an employee without a job.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Corzine responded, ''The idea that this is going to cause unemployment is about like saying that raising the minimum wage in 1996 is going to throw us into a recession.'' He added that Mr. Franks's more modest approach, to make health insurance premiums 100 percent tax deductible for the self-employed and for employees of small businesses, would do little to help low-income workers ''who may not even be paying taxes.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine was the aggressor, however, when the men clashed over  environmental issues. Mr. Corzine, who was endorsed by two prominent environmental advocacy groups, criticized Mr. Franks for supporting a 1995 bill dubbed by its opponents the ''dirty water act,'' which died in the Senate but which would have removed federal protection from 80 percent of the nation's wetlands. ''It was a serious denigration of our environmental laws,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Franks conceded the 1995 bill was ''not an ideal piece of legislation,'' but defended his environmental record and said he had been leading efforts to ban the gasoline additive MTBE to protect ground water.  Mr. Franks attacked Mr. Corzine for failing to ''even bother to vote'' in a  1998 New Jersey bond referendum to preserve land. ''Your commitment to preserving New Jersey's open space is laudable,'' he said, ''but maybe we should vote some more.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Franks was most dismissive of his opponent when he accused Mr. Corzine of backpedaling since the Democratic primary; he said that Mr. Corzine had stopped calling for ''universal health insurance,'' and now speaks of ''universal access'' to health care. ''I was really looking forward to seeing which Jon Corzine would show up for today's debate,'' he said. ''Only now, when I guess his handlers have described to him just how expensive that would be, he's regrouped.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Franks repeatedly attacked Mr. Corzine for refusing to disclose his tax returns, and for at first refusing to disclose his charitable donations. When Mr. Corzine revealed those gifts last month, it turned out he had given more than $100,000 to groups whose leaders or sponsors later endorsed him.</p>
        <p>''You know, Jon says he'll take his personal wealth and put it in a blind trust after the election,'' Mr. Franks said. ''He won't tell us where the conflicts of interest may lie. He says, 'Elect me, then I'll do the right thing.' ''</p>
        <p>But when Mr. Franks tried to corner Mr. Corzine on his finances, he was sidetracked by the moderator, Tom Moran of The Star-Ledger.</p>
        <p>Mr. Franks began by telling Mr. Corzine that ''the idea that you're trying to buy a seat in the United States Senate'' was ''the lens through which the people of New Jersey are looking at this contest.''</p>
        <p>''I wish in order to tell people where all this money is coming from, that today you'd tell us that you're going to disclose finally your complete and unabridged income tax returns for the last 10 years,'' Mr. Franks said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Moran interrupted before Mr. Corzine could respond, asking Mr. Franks what, if anything, he expected to find in Mr. Corzine's tax returns. Mr. Franks refused to say.</p>
        <p>''This is a threshold issue,'' Mr. Franks said. ''Do you believe in full, unabridged public disclosure, or are you going to try to hide it?''</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine said again that he was prevented from releasing his returns by a confidentiality agreement with Goldman Sachs.</p>
        <p>CAMPAIGN 2000: NEW JERSEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
