<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The New York Times; The Roar of the Crowd Is a Pitcher's Reward</title>
    <meta content="09ANDE$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/09/sports/09ANDE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237534"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">San Francisco Giants</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Anderson, Dave</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jones, Bobby J</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Atlanta Braves</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/San Francisco Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001009T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E7D9103CF93AA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="856" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The New York Times; The Roar of the Crowd Is a Pitcher's Reward</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE ANDERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Anderson, Dave</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dave Anderson Sports of The Times column discusses performance of New York Mets pitcher Bobby J Jones in victory over San Francisco Giants in fourth game of National League division series; Jones hurled one-hit shutout; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FROM ''Benn-ee'' to ''Bobb-ee'' to the N.L.C.S.</p>
        <p>To know why the Mets soared into the National League Championship Series yesterday at Shea Stadium, all you had to do was listen.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FROM ''Benn-ee'' to ''Bobb-ee'' to the N.L.C.S.</p>
        <p>To know why the Mets soared into the National League Championship Series yesterday at Shea Stadium, all you had to do was listen.</p>
        <p>At first, you heard every so often the roar of ''Benn-ee, Benn-ee'' for Benny Agbayani, the Hawaiian left fielder whose 13th-inning homer for the 3-2 victory Saturday put the Mets in command of their N.L. division series with the Giants.</p>
        <p>On a short fly ball in the fifth inning, ''Benn-ee, Benn-ee'' was heard when he hit the cutoff man. When he was removed for a pinch-runner after a double in the eighth, you heard another ''Benn-ee, Benn-ee'' roar as his teammates greeted him.</p>
        <p>The roar soon changed to ''Bobb-ee, Bobb-ee'' as Bobby J. Jones walked up to hit, the loudest ''Bobb-ee, Bobb-ee'' he ever heard. He struck out, but he heard that roar again as the Mets rushed the mound after his career performance, a 4-0 one-hitter against the Giants.</p>
        <p>''It's an awesome feeling,'' Jones said of the roar, ''knowing that the fans are behind you and pulling for you.''</p>
        <p>Most of those 56,285 fans understood what yesterday's masterpiece meant to Jones, a 30-year-old right-hander out of Fresno, Calif., who was unavailable in last year's playoffs; he had bursitis in his pitching shoulder.</p>
        <p>In April he was on the disabled list with a damaged calf muscle. Some people wondered if he would ever be a useful pitcher again.</p>
        <p>''I told him,'' Bobby Valentine, the Mets' manager, recalled, ''that he could stay with us and not pitch because we had five starters, but the only way you're going to get better is to pitch. You have to pitch more to get better and if you get better, then you'll pitch more for this team.''</p>
        <p>Another experienced pitcher -- Jones was 15-9 in 1997, 12-9 in 1996 -- might have refused to go to the minor leagues, but Jones went quietly and willingly.</p>
        <p>In his four starts for Norfolk of the Class AAA International League, he won twice. On returning to the Mets, he finished with an 11-6 record to earn Valentine's trust against the Giants in the playoffs.</p>
        <p>''For this series I moved Glendon Rusch to the bullpen because I thought two left-handers would suffice,'' Valentine said, alluding to Mike Hampton and Al Leiter.</p>
        <p>''I also thought Bobby was the guy to go in this game since the beginning of the series. He's a pro. Look it up in the dictionary and you'll see his picture beside the word 'pro.' ''</p>
        <p>On the way out of Shea after Saturday's 13-inning theater, Valentine noticed Jones's wife, Kristi.</p>
        <p>''She says, 'Is Bobby pitching tomorrow?' '' Valentine recalled. ''I said, 'Yes, he is.' And she said: 'You won't be sorry that he is. He'll be pitching the game of his life.' I guess that was planned from the time they had breakfast a couple days ago. And indeed he did.''</p>
        <p>Jones doesn't throw that hard, but he knows how to change speeds, how to fool batters. Quite simply, he knows how to pitch.</p>
        <p>''People like to look at the speed gun,'' Valentine said, ''and say, 'He's only throwing 84, 86 miles an hour, and therefore he's not a top-echelon pitcher.'</p>
        <p>''But it's how he complements that with his changeup, curveball, cut fastball and a slider that torments hitters. He's why we're here.''</p>
        <p>In the N.L.C.S., which opens Wednesday night in St. Louis, Jones will surely be the fourth starter after Hampton, Leiter and Rick Reed.</p>
        <p>''Going to the minors to pitch was an easy decision for me,'' Jones said. ''After not being part of the playoffs last year, I wanted to have a great year and experience the playoffs. If I was pitching like I was earlier in the year, I would not be here.''</p>
        <p>And the Mets wouldn't be in the N.L.C.S., where they need not be concerned with having to dethrone their nemeses, the Atlanta Braves.</p>
        <p>''I think a lot of guys and myself, I was a little relieved,'' the reliever Turk Wendell said. ''That's a team that mentally puts a lot of pressure on other teams.</p>
        <p>''It puts pressure on guys to think they have to be perfect and if they make an error, in the back of their mind, they're going, 'Gosh, we've opened the floodgates.' That's a team that capitalizes on errors and you can't give teams like that four or five outs in an inning.</p>
        <p>''Mentally, it did a lot for our team,'' Wendell added. ''Whatever it is against the Braves, we don't have to contend with it and that's a definite plus for our ballclub.''</p>
        <p>Instead the Mets, who were 6-3 against the Cardinals during the season, know they need not be concerned with whatever psychological problems they had with the Braves. The Mets also know that, in this four-of-seven-game N.L.C.S., they have a fourth dependable starter in Bobby J. Jones.</p>
        <p>The ''Bobb-ee, Bobb-ee'' roar told them that.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
