<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pass Rush Finally Arrives</title>
    <meta content="09BLUE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/09/sports/09BLUE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237517"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL: EXTRA POINTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Giants</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Atlanta Falcons</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hermoso, Rafael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Atlanta Falcons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001009T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E5DA103CF93AA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="547" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pass Rush Finally Arrives</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RAFAEL HERMOSO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hermoso, Rafael</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTA, Oct. 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Giants victory over Atlanta Falcons discussed (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Coach Jim Fassel of the Giants has pleaded with his defense to provide more of a pass rush since the preseason. Today the team's defensive coordinator, John Fox, used a variety of blitzes for the first time this season. In fact, the Giants' game plan appeared to involve getting quarterback Chris Chandler out of the game, because once the Giants learned they could rush the pocket, they did not stop.</p>
        <p>The Giants collected four sacks, including the game-clincher by defensive end Michael Strahan with 1 minute 45 seconds remaining. Strahan hit the substitute quarterback Danny Kanell for a 7-yard loss when the Falcons had a second-and-10 at the Giants' 10-yard line. Atlanta could not score or get a first down, basically ending the game.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Coach Jim Fassel of the Giants has pleaded with his defense to provide more of a pass rush since the preseason. Today the team's defensive coordinator, John Fox, used a variety of blitzes for the first time this season. In fact, the Giants' game plan appeared to involve getting quarterback Chris Chandler out of the game, because once the Giants learned they could rush the pocket, they did not stop.</p>
        <p>The Giants collected four sacks, including the game-clincher by defensive end Michael Strahan with 1 minute 45 seconds remaining. Strahan hit the substitute quarterback Danny Kanell for a 7-yard loss when the Falcons had a second-and-10 at the Giants' 10-yard line. Atlanta could not score or get a first down, basically ending the game.</p>
        <p>Strahan was expected to have a good game against the Atlanta rookie right tackle Michael Thompson. But Thompson partly tore an Achilles' tendon early in the game and was replaced by another rookie, Travis Claridge. Strahan said he watched film of Thompson all week and it took him more than a half to adjust.</p>
        <p>''In my mind, I figured out that once I stop thinking I need to get a sack, I'll get one,'' Strahan said.</p>
        <p>That was a long time ago, because Strahan said he no longer worries about getting sacks. ''I had one last week,'' he said. ''I had one this week. Somebody asked if I was in a rut? I don't get it. What's expected, 20 a game?''</p>
        <p>Hamilton Injured</p>
        <p>Defensive tackle Keith Hamilton left the game in the third quarter with a sprained right knee and had X-rays taken after the game. The results were not immediately known.</p>
        <p>Plenty of Boos</p>
        <p>Whether it was directed at him or the play calling, Atlanta running back Jamal Anderson heard an unusual number of boos from the crowd. Anderson, coming back from a major knee injury, finished with 12 yards on 12 carries and was not a factor in the second half.</p>
        <p>Cleared for Action</p>
        <p>Giants linebacker Mike Barrow, who has a pinched nerve in his neck, was cleared to play by doctors but did not dress for the game.</p>
        <p>The injury also forced him to miss half of last week's game against Tennessee, but Jim Fassel said Barrow should return next Sunday against Dallas. Barrow, who had no history of neck problems, said last week that he had had the injury for four weeks.</p>
        <p>Pete Monty started for Barrow at middle linebacker and had five tackles and one sack.</p>
        <p>Solid Effort by Kicker</p>
        <p>With Brad Daluiso (stiff back) inactive for the second straight game, Jaret Holmes again served as the place-kicker and had two field goals and an extra point.  Holmes also did his part against Atlanta's vaunted kick returners, averaging 62 yards on kickoffs, although none reached the end zone.</p>
        <p>RAFAEL HERMOSO</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL: EXTRA POINTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
