<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>AMF Bowling Has 7 Weeks To Redo Debt</title>
    <meta content="Y16BOWL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222927"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Amf Bowling Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Goldman Sachs Group</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcgeehan, Patrick</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000816T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E7DE1F3FF935A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="500" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>AMF Bowling Has 7 Weeks To Redo Debt</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICK McGEEHAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mcgeehan, Patrick</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>AMF Bowling has been given seven weeks to come up with plan for reorganizing its debts or risk being pushed into bankruptcy court; AMF, which is controlled by Goldman Sachs Group, says its lenders agreed to waive some covenants of their loans and allow AMF to skip $13 million payment that is due on Sept 15 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AMF Bowling, the world's largest operator of bowling alleys, has been given seven weeks to come up with a plan for reorganizing its debts or risk being pushed into bankruptcy court.</p>
        <p>AMF, which is controlled by the Goldman Sachs Group, said on Monday that its lenders had agreed to waive some covenants of their loans and allow AMF to skip a $13 million payment that is due on Sept. 15. The company, which is based in Richmond, Va., also disclosed that the New York Stock Exchange had warned that AMF's depressed stock price could cause it to be delisted.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AMF Bowling, the world's largest operator of bowling alleys, has been given seven weeks to come up with a plan for reorganizing its debts or risk being pushed into bankruptcy court.</p>
        <p>AMF, which is controlled by the Goldman Sachs Group, said on Monday that its lenders had agreed to waive some covenants of their loans and allow AMF to skip a $13 million payment that is due on Sept. 15. The company, which is based in Richmond, Va., also disclosed that the New York Stock Exchange had warned that AMF's depressed stock price could cause it to be delisted.</p>
        <p>AMF has struggled for two years with slow growth and a staggering debt load it took on in a bowling alley buying spree. Its shares have traded for less than $1 for two months and closed yesterday at 50 cents, up 3 cents. Goldman Sachs owns 54 percent of the stock.</p>
        <p>Prices of the company's bonds have also sunk, and the Standard &amp; Poor's Corporation and Moody's Investors Service downgraded them yesterday on word of the plan to miss the debt payment. AMF said its lenders set a deadline of Sept. 30 for a reorganization plan and Oct. 15 for approval by creditors.</p>
        <p>S.&amp; P. lowered AMF's corporate credit rating to CCC- from CCC and lowered the rating on its subordinated debt two notches, to C, the lowest rating short of default, from CCC-.</p>
        <p>Moody's, citing ''AMF's continued poor returns and insufficient cash flow,'' cut its rating on the parent company's convertible bonds to C from Caa2 and on its main subsidiary's subordinated bonds to Ca from Caa1. The company owes more than $1.2 billion.</p>
        <p>''It's sort of a cat-and-mouse game,'' said Hal Diamond, an analyst at S.&amp; P. ''The company has 30 days to cure the default or the bondholders may choose to file the company into bankruptcy proceedings.''</p>
        <p>Yesterday, AMF's bonds, which are classified as ''junk'' by traders, were selling for about 25 percent of their face value, said Phelps Hoyt, an analyst with KDP Investment Advisors in Montpelier, Vt.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hoyt said he thought the company would work out an arrangement with bondholders to stave off a bankruptcy filing. That agreement would probably be structured as an exchange of existing bonds for new bonds that would carry smaller payments or no payments at all for some period, he said.</p>
        <p>''That would let the company see if they can turn it around,'' he said, and would ''let Goldman keep their equity, and if it's a home run, fine.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
