<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>White One Isn't Only House The Democrats Have Eye On</title>
    <meta content="Y16CON$11" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222978"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE DEMOCRATS: THE BATTLE FOR CONGRESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions, National (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clymer, Adam</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000816T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E7D81F3FF935A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1023" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>White One Isn't Only House The Democrats Have Eye On</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM CLYMER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Clymer, Adam</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, Aug. 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>More senators, representatives and Congressional candidates are speaking at Democratic Convention than can be found on floor of either chamber most of the time; incumbents and aspirants are tracking Al Gore's campaign issues in hopes of winning back control of narrowly Republican House and perhaps even Senate; Republican convention, in striking contrast, consigned its lawmakers, especially controversial conservatives, to few moments of throwaway time (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The stage does not look like the Capitol, but there have been more senators, representatives and Congressional candidates speaking at the Democratic National Convention than can be found on the floor of either chamber most of the time.</p>
        <p>With the convention half over, 40 present and perhaps future lawmakers have spoken about everything from campaign finance legislation to the environment to the minimum wage to health insurance -- tracking the issues Vice President Al Gore is campaigning on -- and hoping to win back control of the narrowly Republican House, and maybe even the Senate.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The stage does not look like the Capitol, but there have been more senators, representatives and Congressional candidates speaking at the Democratic National Convention than can be found on the floor of either chamber most of the time.</p>
        <p>With the convention half over, 40 present and perhaps future lawmakers have spoken about everything from campaign finance legislation to the environment to the minimum wage to health insurance -- tracking the issues Vice President Al Gore is campaigning on -- and hoping to win back control of the narrowly Republican House, and maybe even the Senate.</p>
        <p>Today, Senator Tom Daschle of South Dakota, the minority leader, promised to work with Al Gore, as president, on legislation dealing with school construction, a Medicare drug benefit and a patients' bill of rights, among other things. And Representative Martin T. Meehan of Massachusetts, arguing for a ban on the largely unregulated party donations known as soft money, said gun control, patients' rights and tobacco legislation had been halted because of ''millions of dollars in special-interest money spent to stop them dead in their tracks.''</p>
        <p>The contrast to the Republicans in Philadelphia is striking. While Speaker J. Dennis Hastert gave a short speech there, most Congressional and Senate incumbents and candidates were consigned to a few moments of throwaway time at midday on the first day of the convention. Controversial leaders like Representative Tom DeLay, the majority whip from Texas, were seen mainly at golfing fund-raisers.</p>
        <p>While Republicans said that was fine because it was Gov. George W. Bush's success that would help them retain Congress, it was clear that the Democrats thought political strength could trickle up as well as down.</p>
        <p>Democrats cannot stop talking about the ''closet'' in which Republicans confined their most conservative lawmakers. Jennifer Backus, press secretary of the Democratic National Committee, said Republicans treated their leaders, like Mr. DeLay and Representatives Dick Armey, the majority leader, and Henry J. Hyde of Illinois, chairman of the Judiciary Committee and leader of the effort to impeach President Clinton, ''like the crazy aunt in the attic.''</p>
        <p>''They wanted to hide them away,'' Ms. Backus said.</p>
        <p>Michael Whouley, a senior political strategist who went to the Democratic committee from the Gore campaign, put it positively, saying that Congressional figures amplified Mr. Gore's message and helped focus the convention on legislative issues.</p>
        <p>''It's a convention,'' Mr. Whouley  said, ''a Democratic Party convention.''</p>
        <p>The only candidate in a tough race to get national television exposure, however, has been Hillary Rodham Clinton, the New York Senate hopeful who adopted as her campaign motto the slogan of the Children's Defense Fund: ''Leave no child behind.''</p>
        <p>Another Senate hopeful, Representative Debbie Stabenow of Michigan, had a star turn with six female senators. She spoke on Monday night of the need for a prescription drug benefit under Medicare, a patients' bill of rights and insurance for all children. The networks did not carry her remarks; ABC correspondents were talking to each other, and the others were not yet broadcasting the convention. But the segment was shown on several Michigan stations.</p>
        <p>Representative Stabenow said today, ''It's wonderful the way that Al Gore and Joe Lieberman are willing to share the stage.'' She said she valued the chance to ''show who I'm all about and who I'm fighting for'' in the race against the incumbent Republican, Senator Spencer Abraham.</p>
        <p>Another challenger, Susan Bass Levin, the mayor of Cherry Hill, N.J., has been here all week, attending delegation meetings and other events, all of which, she said, emphasized the importance of regaining the House, where a net pickup of seven seats will bring Democratic control. She is running against Representative James H. Saxton, and has a brief speaking slot on Thursday afternoon. Her staff has organized three house parties in the district to watch her.</p>
        <p>But some candidates stayed away. Lauren Beth Gash, a candidate for an open seat in the Chicago suburbs, said, ''It's more important for me in this particular race to be right here in this district.'' She said, ''we were offered numerous opportunities to do things out there, including fund-raisers and other opportunities.''</p>
        <p>Instead, she said, she had done things like meeting ''with voters at a train station for several hours, going to union meetings and a rotary club, going door to door.''</p>
        <p>Candidates struck the themes they thought mattered in their races. Representative Jay Inslee of Washington, facing a stiff challenge in a swing district, used his three minutes to talk about privacy, saying he wanted to ensure ''that our genetic history is not used to discriminate against us in employment, that our health records are used by our doctors and not our bankers, and that our government protects privacy rather than threatens it.''</p>
        <p>Senator Edward M. Kennedy of Massachusetts, who has hardly any opposition in his race for his seventh full term, recalled in his remarks that John F. Kennedy was nominated here 40 years ago. Then the senator focused on his own special cause.</p>
        <p>''On the issue of health care,'' he said, ''we must heed my brother's words here in Los Angeles, which echo now across the years. He spoke of 'a choice . . . between the public interest and private comfort.' And that is our choice today.''</p>
        <p>Bill Nelson, Florida's insurance commissioner and a Senate candidate, spoke of his record on education and the environment and the need to ''cut down on fraud against seniors.''</p>
        <p>''The values Al Gore and I will campaign on are American's values, your values,'' Mr. Nelson said.</p>
        <p>Representative Richard A. Gephardt of Missouri, the minority leader who would become speaker if the Democrats win the House, said,  ''There is a real desire in the D.N.C. to not just elect a president and a vice president but to take back the House and the Senate, too.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gephardt said, ''The agenda of the presidential campaign is the same agenda as ours.''</p>
        <p>THE DEMOCRATS: THE BATTLE FOR CONGRESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
