<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="16FSUM$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222997"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000816T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE6D71F3FF935A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1222" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-18</p>
        <p>Russia Presses Effort To Save Sunken Sub's Crew  Russian seamen failed twice to hook up a rescue vehicle to the nuclear-powered submarine Kursk, lying broken and powerless with 116 men aboard about 400 feet below the surface of the Barents Sea. High seas, strong currents, poor visibility and the sub's position hampered the efforts. A third attempt was planned. Officials said oxygen supplies would probably last only until Friday.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Russian Church Sets Doctrine  The Russian Orthodox Church adopted a social doctrine that, among other things, condemned genetic engineering, homosexuality, euthanasia and abortion. It also approved of the concept of private property and reconfirmed the church's close relationship with the military.</p>
        <p>A13</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-18</p>
        <p>Russia Presses Effort To Save Sunken Sub's Crew  Russian seamen failed twice to hook up a rescue vehicle to the nuclear-powered submarine Kursk, lying broken and powerless with 116 men aboard about 400 feet below the surface of the Barents Sea. High seas, strong currents, poor visibility and the sub's position hampered the efforts. A third attempt was planned. Officials said oxygen supplies would probably last only until Friday.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Russian Church Sets Doctrine  The Russian Orthodox Church adopted a social doctrine that, among other things, condemned genetic engineering, homosexuality, euthanasia and abortion. It also approved of the concept of private property and reconfirmed the church's close relationship with the military.</p>
        <p>A13</p>
        <p>British Concordes Grounded  British Airways grounded its seven supersonic airliners after French and British investigators of the Air France crash said they would urge withdrawal of the aircraft's airworthiness certificate.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Indonesian Plan for Middle East  President Abdurrahman Wahid plunged into Middle East politics with a complicated power-sharing formula he said could resolve the deadlock over Jerusalem's status. His offer followed a meeting with Shimon Peres, Israel's former prime minister.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>Israeli Parliament Battle  The main opposition party, Likud, used a special legislative session to push through a resolution intended to impede new peace talks with the Palestinians, but Prime Minister Ehud Barak's government dismissed it as political grandstanding.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>U.S. Rejects Iraqi Claim  American military officials said a warehouse bombed by American and British warplanes on Friday in southern Iraq held anti-aircraft weapons and other military equipment, not food supplies.</p>
        <p>A5</p>
        <p>Congo Peace Talks End  African leaders wound up 18 hours of talks without reaching an agreement on how to revive the crumbling Congo peace accord, officials said.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A20-28</p>
        <p>Democrats Act to Reassure Liberals Skeptical of Goals  The Democratic Party devoted much of its convention day to reassuring its liberal base, which has grumbled about the centrist tone of the ticket and platform. The vice- presidential candidate, Senator Joseph I. Lieberman, met with black delegates to declare his unequivocal support for affirmative action.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>President Clinton symbolically ceded the stage to Mr. Gore.</p>
        <p>A23</p>
        <p>President John F. Kennedy's daughter, brother, niece and nephew recalled his legacy and linked Vice President Al Gore to it.</p>
        <p>A25</p>
        <p>Many of the same lobbyists who helped underwrite the Republican convention are out in force in Los Angeles, to cover both party bases.</p>
        <p>A23</p>
        <p>The convention's first night, which featured speeches by the Clintons, got more time on network television and pulled in more viewers, both on the networks and on the cable news channels, than did the first night of the Republican convention.</p>
        <p>A27</p>
        <p>The Los Angeles police defended their tactics, which included the use of rubber bullets, during violent protests on Monday, and Democratic officials who were on the roof watching backed them up. Demonstrations appeared more calm yesterday.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Lawrence C. Franco, 23, of Farmingdale, N.Y., was arrested after a caller to the Howard Stern radio show threatened Mr. Lieberman.</p>
        <p>B2</p>
        <p>DNA Does Not Clear Inmate  Ricky Nolen McGinn, 43, who received a stay from Gov. George W. Bush of Texas, was rescheduled for execution after DNA tests failed to exonerate him in the rape and murder of his 12-year-old stepdaughter.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>Ruling Limits Eavesdropping  A federal appeals court struck down parts of a government order that expanded the ability of law enforcement to monitor cell phone conversations of criminal suspects.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>Hearing for Nuclear Scientist  Lawyers for Wen Ho Lee, who is accused of mishandling nuclear weapons secrets, offered evidence suggesting that he had been singled out for prosecution largely because he is Chinese-American.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-8</p>
        <p>Parental Notification Law Is Ruled Unconstitutional  The New Jersey Supreme Court, ruling 4 to 2, struck down a law requiring that the parents of an unmarried girl under age 18 be notified before she can get an abortion. The court held that the requirement imposed a burden on minors seeking abortions that it did not impose on those who continue their pregnancies.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Dam Monitoring Found Flawed  A state-required inspection in 1991 of the Seneca Lake Dam, which gave way during intense flooding in northwestern New Jersey on Saturday, found that it was in need of repairs, but they were never made by its private owners, officials said. The dam is one of about half a dozen destroyed or damaged by flood waters. No one knows to what extent the dams' failure contributed to the damage.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Rise in Extraditions Foreseen  The inauguration today of Hipolito Mejia as president of the Dominican Republic is leading American officials, and the relatives of a New York City police officer slain more than a decade ago, to hope that fugitives from American justice will no longer find a haven on the island.</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>B7</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>B8</p>
        <p>City Blames Albany for Shortage  Schools Chancellor Harold O. Levy filed court papers blaming State Education Commissioner Richard P. Mills for the shortage of certified teachers in New York City's 99 lowest-performing schools.</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-8</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-8</p>
        <p>SCIENCE/HEALTH</p>
        <p>Warning on Money and Science  The huge influx of money into biomedical research creates conflicts of interest for scientists and erodes public trust, scientists and officials said at a federal conference.</p>
        <p>A28</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-22</p>
        <p>Fatal Rollovers After Blowouts  Government data showed that virtually all the 62 recent deaths linked to Firestone tires now being recalled occurred when sport utility vehicles, most of them Ford Explorers, rolled over after the tires failed.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Navistar Announces Layoffs  One of the world's largest makers of heavy trucks, buses and diesel engines will lay off 1,100 employees, or about 15 percent of its white-collar workers, because of a slowdown in truck orders in North America.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Accusations at BET Network  A former chief financial officer of Black Entertainment Television, Dwight Crawford, intends to file a lawsuit today asserting that the company, its chairman, Robert L. Johnson, and its president, Debra Lee, sought to evade some taxes. Mr. Crawford's wrongful-termination suit seeks $21 million in damages.</p>
        <p>C2</p>
        <p>Cendant Seeks to Acquire Avis  Henry Silverman, the chief executive of Cendant, made a bid to regain control of Avis, the nation's second-largest rental car company, for $29 a share, a nearly 14 percent premium over Avis's previous-day closing price but a price the market immediately deemed too low; investors bid up the shares of Avis $5, to $30.50.</p>
        <p>C2</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>DINING</p>
        <p>F1-10</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A30-31</p>
        <p>Editorials: Warring populisms; diversity in news and entertainment; Andres Martinez on Latinos in Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>Columns: Paul Krugman, Maureen Dowd.</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E4  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E8  Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2  Weather</p>
        <p>D8</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
