<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lox in a Cone: Sliced Thin It's Not</title>
    <meta content="16ICE.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222887"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ice Cream</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">max and mina's homemade ice cream and ices</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hyland, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ice Cream</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000816T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E4DB1E3FF935A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="687" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lox in a Cone: Sliced Thin It's Not</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN HYLAND</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hyland, John</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Max and Mina's Homemade Ice Cream and Ices in Flushing, Queens, infuses their products with unusual flavors, such as lox, blintz, pizza, and chocolate-covered potato chip fudge; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR many New Yorkers, a brunch without lox is like a candlelight dinner without matches. So when it was Ilya Grozovsky's turn to be the host of a brunch in his Midtown office, he thought he would impress his colleagues with lox. And sugar cones.</p>
        <p>What he served was vanilla ice cream studded with bits of nova lox, cream cheese and a secret ingredient: salt. ''I thought it would be a real kick -- kind of bagel and lox, minus the bagel and lox,'' said Mr. Grozovsky, who works for a division of Chase Manhattan Bank. ''The feedback that I got was that this took the cake, so to speak.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR many New Yorkers, a brunch without lox is like a candlelight dinner without matches. So when it was Ilya Grozovsky's turn to be the host of a brunch in his Midtown office, he thought he would impress his colleagues with lox. And sugar cones.</p>
        <p>What he served was vanilla ice cream studded with bits of nova lox, cream cheese and a secret ingredient: salt. ''I thought it would be a real kick -- kind of bagel and lox, minus the bagel and lox,'' said Mr. Grozovsky, who works for a division of Chase Manhattan Bank. ''The feedback that I got was that this took the cake, so to speak.''</p>
        <p>Or the cone. But such creations aren't all that unusual at Max &amp; Mina's Homemade Ice Cream and Ices in Flushing, Queens, where the rotating menu of more than 300 flavors includes blintz (sour-cream ice cream, pieces of blintz, cinnamon and graham crackers), pizza (mozzarella, tomato sauce and, yes, pizza) and chocolate-covered potato-chip fudge. (You get the idea.) And, of course, lox, a flavor suggested by Mr. Grozovsky, a customer.</p>
        <p>The business is owned by Bruce and Mark Becker, brothers who welcome newfangled ideas from patrons, or from anywhere. Anyone can do plain vanilla, after all.</p>
        <p>The Beckers were inspired by the more traditional recipes of their grandfather Max Sockloff, a chemist who lived in the Bronx with his wife, Mina, before moving to Coral Gables, Fla. Bruce Becker, 32, discovered the recipes while clearing out the Sockloffs' home after they died in the mid-1980's. Mr. Sockloff had been a freelance chemist for companies and ''had recipe books for toothpaste to shampoo,'' said Mark Becker, 27.  But what he also did well was ice cream.</p>
        <p>One of Mrs. Sockloff's favorites was vanilla almond fudge, but even it is not always among the 40 ice creams and 8 to 10 sorbets on the menu at the shop at any one time. ''It's very rare that we keep a flavor, except a few standard ones, on the menu,'' Bruce Becker said. A flavor like that, he said, reappears every two or three weeks in a roster that includes standbys like vanilla and chocolate next to newer entries like corn on the cob, peanut butter and jelly, ''cookie mess'' and vanilla pretzel fudge.</p>
        <p>Most of the ice creams use milk that is 16 percent butterfat or higher, though some are fat-free. All are kosher, a selling point for many customers. The Beckers are Orthodox Jews, although a lot of non-Jews are also regulars.</p>
        <p>Max &amp; Mina's sells ice cream by the cone or cup (from $1.50 for one scoop to $4 for three) and in larger quantities ($4.60 for a pint and $6.50 for a quart, with a second pint or quart at half price). The Beckers, who started four years ago selling other people's yogurt before branching out with their own creations, also operate a wholesale business, supplying restaurants and shops, like Carlton Cards in Pennsylvania Station.</p>
        <p>As for the lox ice cream, the taste is . . . well, loxy. ''You've got to take good lox,'' Mark Becker said, or ''it'll taste like a fish, and that's not what we want.''</p>
        <p>''We want it to taste like ice cream,'' he said, ''or as close to it as possible.''</p>
        <p>A recent group tasting of about 20 flavors inspired plenty of ''mmm''s, but only a few for the lox, which drew mostly gasps and groans. But the Beckers can safely say they  offer something that sets them apart.</p>
        <p>Some flavors haven't hit a cone yet, even at Max &amp; Mina's. When the Beckers' sister Debra Weinstock was pregnant, ''she was begging us to make a pickle one,'' Bruce Becker said.</p>
        <p>''But I tried it, and it was too sour,'' he said. ''I have to work on it again.''</p>
        <p>Can Alka-Seltzer ice cream be far away?</p>
        <p>Max &amp; Mina's Homemade Ice Cream and Ices is at 71-26 Main Street, Flushing, Queens; (718) 793-8629.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
