<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Where Few Bistros Have Gone Before</title>
    <meta content="16REST$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222877"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="RESTAURANTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Abajour (NYC Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Grimes, William</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Columns/Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000816T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEEDE1E3FF935A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1056" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Where Few Bistros Have Gone Before</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By William Grimes</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Grimes, William</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William Grimes reviews Abajour, Manhattan restaurant; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DINING on the lower reaches of the Upper East Side often seems an all-or-nothing proposition. It's either high-end restaurants like March, JoJo, Daniel and Aureole, or a sobering procession of limp trattorias, third-rate sushi shacks and the occasional Hunan house of horrors. In one of the world's most expensive swaths of real estate, it's easier to find pizza by the slice than a decent bistro. In culinary terms, this part of town is like a pillared mansion with a few rusty washing machines on the front lawn.</p>
        <p>Abajour comes as welcome news. It's not Cafe Boulud. It's not JoJo either. What it is, is a respectable neighborhood bistro with pleasing decor, an attractive menu and some well-priced wines. It's just what the neighborhood needs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DINING on the lower reaches of the Upper East Side often seems an all-or-nothing proposition. It's either high-end restaurants like March, JoJo, Daniel and Aureole, or a sobering procession of limp trattorias, third-rate sushi shacks and the occasional Hunan house of horrors. In one of the world's most expensive swaths of real estate, it's easier to find pizza by the slice than a decent bistro. In culinary terms, this part of town is like a pillared mansion with a few rusty washing machines on the front lawn.</p>
        <p>Abajour comes as welcome news. It's not Cafe Boulud. It's not JoJo either. What it is, is a respectable neighborhood bistro with pleasing decor, an attractive menu and some well-priced wines. It's just what the neighborhood needs.</p>
        <p>Abajour, which is in the former Tony MacGregor's, shines on the street with an extrovert's smile. The interior, obviously done on an Ikea budget, has a bright, summery look, with pale lemon walls, apricot banquettes, gauzy white drapes and slatted cabana shutters. Tall freestanding lamps with oversize shades allude to the restaurant's name, an adaptation of the French for lampshade (abat-jour).</p>
        <p>The menu fits the tone. It's not terribly ambitious, but it has enough smart little twists to lift Abajour above the standardized steak frites competition. A somewhat stingy shellfish platter is not one of them. Priced at $45, it offers four unimpressive oysters and dinky clams, along with less than memorable shrimp, lobster meat and crab claws. It's a missed opportunity, because the accompanying sauces are terrific, especially a rough-textured cocktail sauce, packed with little chunks of wonderfully sweet tomatoes.</p>
        <p>The humble-sounding country pate, fresh-tasting and generously portioned, shames the shellfish platter, let alone a lot of the higher-priced meat spreads in the city. It's on the lighter side, with chicken, chicken liver and firm blocks of pork, seasoned with restraint and lifted with fresh thyme and parsley. It's precisely the kind of pate you hope for in a bistro. And translucent slices of shaved fennel, crunchy and fragrant, pair beautifully with cremini mushrooms, a little olive oil and a sprinkling of salt and pepper.</p>
        <p>Jonathan Crean, the executive chef, knows when to stop, always a good sign. Even the dishes with a little complexity to them generally rely on a simple but well-judged opposition of flavors, like scallops in a thin crust of cumin, fennel, ginger and black pepper, which find a welcome touch of sweetness in endive braised in butter and sugar. Fish and frites, the cheapest of the entrees at $15, may be plain, but it makes a very good showing. The breading on the fish has just the right texture to brown nicely and pick up a good crunch without absorbing any oil, and its tartar sauce is exemplary. Grilled tuna is loved not wisely but too well by Mr. Crean. It gets a little lost in a sumptuous pillow of pureed parsnip, enriched with brown butter and cut with a touch of acidic citrus and capers. In the end, the tuna becomes a texture rather than a taste.</p>
        <p>Duck confit works better. The duck meat, halfway between chewy and creamy, meets its match in a suave, lightly garlicked bean puree, touched with red wine sauce. Even better is a grilled prime sirloin steak smothered in roasted-garlic herb butter. Abajour does not make a big fuss about this steak, but it's one of the juiciest, most flavorful pieces of meat I've come across in months. It threatens to overshadow a very worthy rack of Colorado lamb, served simply with a garlic flan and red wine sauce, accented with rosemary. All entrees on the menu appear with suggestions for matching wines, which can be ordered by the glass.</p>
        <p>Desserts do not make the pulse pound, and it's hard to see what is extraordinary about ''extraordinary strawberry shortcake,'' a very homey take on an American classic. It does just what it's supposed to do, except one evening when the strawberries were less than ripe. Chocolate pot de creme is a little grainy, but intensely flavored with a nice, bitter overlay, and the banana split hits the target, although its bowl-like glass makes for a messy presentation. When a banana split is billed as traditional, it should appear in an elongated barque, all the better to show off the caramel and chocolate sauces. Three little chocolate biscotti appear with the check. Seize them. They are as good as any of the desserts.</p>
        <p>Abajour seems to have struck a chord. On the night I visited, it drew a well-heeled, older crowd, which looked as though it had been siphoned from Le Perigord. Anyone in the place could have afforded a meal at twice the price. But at Abajour, they were getting a warm reception and better than decent food. The sense of surprise was palpable. Right here on First Avenue -- who would have thought?</p>
        <p>Abajour  *  [Rating: One Star]  1134 First Avenue (62nd Street); (212) 644-9757</p>
        <p>ATMOSPHERE: Updated American bistro dishes served in a bright, airy dining room.  SOUND LEVEL: Loud when full.  SERVICE: Eager to please but somewhat awkward.  RECOMMENDED DISHES: Four-spice scallops, shaved fennel with cremini mushrooms, grilled tuna with parsnip puree, duck confit with bean puree, sirloin steak with onion rings and peppercorn sauce, banana split.  WINE LIST: About 60 well-chosen American and French wines, seven by the glass, with four half bottles.  HOURS: Dinner, 5 to 11 p.m. daily. Late night menu, 11 p.m. to 1 a.m.  PRICE RANGE: Appetizers, $6.50 to $14; entrees, $15 to $29; desserts, $6.50. Prix fixe, $30.  CREDIT CARDS: All major cards.  WHEELCHAIR ACCESS: Restrooms on street level.</p>
        <p>WHAT THE STARS MEAN:</p>
        <p>(None) Poor to satisfactory  * Good  ** Very good  *** Excellent  **** Extraordinary</p>
        <p>Ratings reflect the reviewer's reaction to food, ambience and service, with price taken into consideration. Menu listings and prices are subject to change.</p>
        <p>Past restaurant reviews from The New York Times, with additional capsule reviews by Times critics, are available on New York Today:  www.nytoday.com</p>
        <p>RESTAURANTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
