<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Navistar Cuts 1,100 Jobs, Citing Truck Order Drop</title>
    <meta content="Y16TRUC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222934"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trucks and Trucking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Production</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Navistar International Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barboza, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Production</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trucks and Trucking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000816T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E2DE1F3FF935A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="647" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Navistar Cuts 1,100 Jobs, Citing Truck Order Drop</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID BARBOZA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barboza, David</byline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO, Aug. 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Navistar International Corp, responding to slowdown in heavy-truck orders in North America, says it will lay off 1,100 employees, or about 15 percent of its white-collar work force; graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Responding to a slowdown in heavy-truck orders in North America, the Navistar International Corporation said today that it would lay off 1,100 employees, or about 15 percent of its white-collar work force.</p>
        <p>The company, one of the world's largest makers of heavy trucks, buses and diesel engines, said that after several years of spectacular growth, orders for big trucks in North America had been falling steadily, largely because of higher interest rates, soaring fuel prices and a glut of used trucks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Responding to a slowdown in heavy-truck orders in North America, the Navistar International Corporation said today that it would lay off 1,100 employees, or about 15 percent of its white-collar work force.</p>
        <p>The company, one of the world's largest makers of heavy trucks, buses and diesel engines, said that after several years of spectacular growth, orders for big trucks in North America had been falling steadily, largely because of higher interest rates, soaring fuel prices and a glut of used trucks.</p>
        <p>The announcement by Navistar, which is based in Chicago, comes just a day after Freightliner, a unit of DaimlerChrysler A.G. and the world's biggest maker of heavy trucks, said that it would cut 3,475 jobs, or about 19 percent of its work force.</p>
        <p>Earlier this month, Paccar, the world's No. 2 truck maker, based in Bellevue, Wash., said that it would lay off 430 workers at a big-truck plant in Tennessee.</p>
        <p>Though the economy remains strong, and demand for diesel engines and buses is robust, Navistar and other truck makers are trying to head off a cyclical downturn after what some industry experts said were two years of ''excessive demand'' for heavy-duty rigs. Higher interest rates have made it more expensive to finance the purchase of a new truck, and higher diesel prices have forced some trucking companies to park their rigs.</p>
        <p>As a result, over the last year, orders for heavy-duty trucks -- which often cost $80,000 to $100,000 -- fell nearly 30 percent. Freightliner said yesterday that it expected heavy-duty truck sales in North America to drop about 25 percent from 1999.</p>
        <p>And earlier this year, Navistar laid off 800 employees in Canada, where its heavy-duty trucks are made, and the company says it may cut 500 more jobs. The company, which markets its big trucks under the International brand name, has 19,000 employees worldwide.</p>
        <p>The Navistar announcement was contained in its third-quarter earnings release, which reported profits excluding special items of $76 million, or $1.27 a share, compared with $77 million, or $1.17 a share, in the quarter a year earlier. Revenue edged up to $1.92 billion from $1.88 billion. The results slightly beat Wall Street projections of $1.24 a share, according to First Call/Thomson Financial.</p>
        <p>Shares of Navistar, which have been weak for much of the last year, fell $1.9375 yesterday, to $37.125.</p>
        <p>John R. Horne, the chairman and chief executive of Navistar, said in a statement that the company was working to become less cyclical.</p>
        <p>''The steps we plan will allow us to continue to build a healthy business in the downturn,'' he said, ''and come out even stronger when the market turns up again.''</p>
        <p>The company said it would also take a charge in the fourth quarter related to the 1,100 job cuts.</p>
        <p>Though heavy-truck orders, which make up about a quarter of Navistar's sales, are in decline, orders for medium-sized trucks are more stable, and sales of Navistar's diesel engines, which are used in U.P.S., U-Haul and pickup trucks, continues to grow. The company is also supplying diesel engines to the Ford Motor Company, which uses them in its sport utility vehicles. The company also said its school bus division was strong.</p>
        <p>Analysts said today that they were not surprised by the Navistar announcement. Many investors have been warned about a drop in orders going back more than a year, and the stock prices of many of the big truck and engine makers have fallen.</p>
        <p>''We're in the ninth inning in the stock prices,'' said Tobias M. Levkovich, an analyst at Salomon Smith Barney. ''This news has all been discounted, and we think we might see a recovery by next spring in the order patterns.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
