<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At 93, Texas Artist Gains National Spotlight Anew</title>
    <meta content="Y16ELP$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000818T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222913"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">El Paso (Tex)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lea, Tom</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yardley, Jim</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas/El Paso</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000816T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E2D61E3FF935A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1235" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At 93, Texas Artist Gains National Spotlight Anew</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JIM YARDLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Yardley, Jim</byline>
      <dateline>EL PASO, Aug. 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Tom Lea, 93-year-old muralist, painter and author, is in national spotlight after George W Bush quotes from his book, A Picture Gallery, about living on side of mountain in El Paso; Lea is now enjoying modest renaissance outside Texas, where his work hangs in several museums; interview; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The muralist, painter and author Tom Lea is probably the only person, dead or alive, who can say he has been threatened by Pancho Villa, interrupted by Chiang Kai-shek and regaled by Franklin D. Roosevelt. Oddly enough, Mr. Lea was mostly forgotten until he was quoted this month by Gov. George W. Bush.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lea, who is 93, is sitting in the living room of his house on the slope of the Franklin Mountains, the same simple home where he and his wife, Sarah, have lived for decades above the dun-colored streets of El Paso and its Mexican sister city, Ciudad Juarez. The Texas folklorist J. Frank Dobie once surveyed the desert terrain and complained that Mr. Lea did not even have a tree in his yard.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The muralist, painter and author Tom Lea is probably the only person, dead or alive, who can say he has been threatened by Pancho Villa, interrupted by Chiang Kai-shek and regaled by Franklin D. Roosevelt. Oddly enough, Mr. Lea was mostly forgotten until he was quoted this month by Gov. George W. Bush.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lea, who is 93, is sitting in the living room of his house on the slope of the Franklin Mountains, the same simple home where he and his wife, Sarah, have lived for decades above the dun-colored streets of El Paso and its Mexican sister city, Ciudad Juarez. The Texas folklorist J. Frank Dobie once surveyed the desert terrain and complained that Mr. Lea did not even have a tree in his yard.</p>
        <p>''But you don't have a mountain in yours,'' Mr. Lea answered.</p>
        <p>Like Mr. Lea, Mr. Bush was impressed with that mountain. Mr. Lea was spending an evening at home when the telephone rang from the Republican National Convention with the news that Mr. Bush planned to mention him in his speech. Mr. Lea switched on the television and watched the Texas governor quote a passage from his book ''A Picture Gallery,'' in which he wrote of living ''on the east side of the mountain.''</p>
        <p>''It's the sunrise side, not the sunset side,'' he wrote. ''It's the side to see the day that is coming, not to see the day that is gone.''</p>
        <p>The speech and subsequent national attention have sparked a happy, if modest, renaissance for Mr. Lea. He has always had passionate admirers, and his drawings and paintings are displayed in museums, including a gallery carrying his name at the El Paso Museum of Art. But he was largely forgotten outside Texas. Now, a national art magazine has inquired with his dealer, Adair Margo, about a profile. The wire services ran stories of his emotional response to the speech. Friends called with congratulations. ''I was very moved,'' Mr. Lea recalled.</p>
        <p>He is fiddling with a hand-carved cane embossed with his name, a gift from a fan. He can no longer see well enough to paint or read, and even when he could, he always kept his distance from the modern art world with its infatuation with introspection and experimentation. The world that inspired him lay outside his window.</p>
        <p>Asked what advice he would give an aspiring artist or writer, Mr. Lea responded without hesitation, ''I'd tell them I hope they'll study from life.''</p>
        <p>His own beginnings in El Paso, where he was born in 1907, came when the city was little more than a dusty passageway north from Mexico. Once, Mr. Lea's father, who served as mayor in 1915, jailed the wife of Pancho Villa for gun running. Infuriated, the Mexican bandit and revolutionary put a bounty on the mayor's head and promised to kidnap Tom and his brother, Joe -- a threat that got the boys a police bodyguard to and from school.</p>
        <p>El Paso sparked his imagination but offered Mr. Lea little in the way of artistic training, so he went to the Chicago Art Institute and studied under the muralist John Warner Norton. Mr. Lea illustrated for magazines and painted murals, like ''The Nesters,'' for the Benjamin Franklin Post Office in Washington. By World War II, his work attracted the attention of Henry Luce, the Life magazine publisher who hired him as an illustrator.</p>
        <p>He traveled more than 100,000 miles, painting the sinking of the aircraft carrier Wasp in the North Atlantic and landing with the marines on Peleliu Island in the Pacific.</p>
        <p>Luce once dispatched him to paint a portrait of Chiang Kai-shek, then the nationalist leader of China. Chiang, Mr. Lea recalled, arrived with a sofa pillow and a miniature Big Ben clock. He placed the pillow behind his back for support and set the clock ticking as Mr. Lea began  his profile. When 25 minutes passed, the clock rang clanged and Chiang abruptly left. Mr. Lea then went upstairs, where Madame Chiang Kai-shek proved a more willing subject. As she posed, Chiang entered the room in an evening robe, bowing toward his wife, then to an aide and then to Mr. Lea before leaving without a word.</p>
        <p>''You know,'' she told Mr. Lea, ''my husband would be quite handsome if he would keep his teeth in.''</p>
        <p>Late in the war, Luce dispatched Mr. Lea to the White House to present a collection of Life war paintings to President Roosevelt, who spent 20 minutes chatting about how such works too often ended up in the offices of one admiral or another.</p>
        <p>''He said, 'Henry Luce and I have solved that,' '' Mr. Lea recalled of the president's deal to take control of the works. His painting of the sinking of the Wasp remains on display at the United States Army Center of Military History in Washington.</p>
        <p>When the war ended, Mr. Lea returned to El Paso, where he has remained, even as interests broadened. He went to Mexico to study the fighting black bulls and wrote and illustrated his first novel, ''The Brave Bulls,'' which became a best seller and a movie. His subsequent novel of the border, ''The Wonderful Country,'' became a best seller in 1952. In the movie, which starred Robert Mitchum, Mr. Lea played the barber.</p>
        <p>He wrote other books, including ''The King Ranch,'' a two-volume account of Texas' most famous ranch that established him as a historian.</p>
        <p>Until 1992, when he joined with Ms. Margo, Mr. Lea never had an art agent or dealer. Patrons simply inquired, and he put their names on a list. When he finished a painting, Ms. Margo said, he would call the next person on the list and invite the person to El Paso to take a look. One painting not for sale, now or ever, is a portrait of his wife of 62 years, ''Sarah in the Summertime,'' that hangs in the living room.</p>
        <p>''I'll stand by that one,'' he says. ''Destroy all the rest.''</p>
        <p>The Leas were introduced to Mr. Bush and his wife, Laura, a few years ago by Ms. Margo. A friendship ensued, and Mr. Bush honored the couple at a dinner at the governor's mansion. Mr. Bush also quoted Mr. Lea's passage from ''A Picture Gallery'' in one of his State of the State addresses.</p>
        <p>The El Paso outside Mr. Lea's window is very different now. The cowboys are harder to find, and the dusty border town is part of a metropolitan area of more than two million people. Mr. Lea's yard now has a tree, an Arizona cypress, and a carpet of green grass. His only regret is that he can no longer paint.</p>
        <p>''Every time I ever lifted a brush, I hoped I would make a better painting,'' he said. ''That's my true wish: that I would be a better painter than I was.''</p>
        <p>But from the vantage point of the east side of the mountain, he was more than good enough.</p>
        <p>Correction:  August 18, 2000, Friday  An article on Wednesday about renewed interest in the painter and author Tom Lea misstated the site of an episode he painted -- the sinking of the aircraft carrier Wasp in World War II. It occurred in the Pacific Ocean, not the North Atlantic.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: August 18, 2000, Friday</p>
        <p>An article on Wednesday about renewed interest in the painter and author Tom Lea misstated the site of an episode he painted -- the sinking of the aircraft carrier Wasp in World War II. It occurred in the Pacific Ocean, not the North Atlantic.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
