<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Passenger Steers Bus to Safety After Driver's Heart Attack</title>
    <meta content="16BUS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222960"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Buses</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Metropolitan Transportation Authority</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wong, Edward</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lawrence, Shedrick</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Buses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000816T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E6DA1F3FF935A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="733" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Passenger Steers Bus to Safety After Driver's Heart Attack</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWARD WONG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wong, Edward</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Shedrick Lawrence takes over Metropolitan Transportation Authority bus on Long Island when driver collapses from fatal heart attack and steers it to safety; passengers suffer only minor injuries; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Shedrick Lawrence told his wife yesterday morning that he did not have time to cook his own sausage because he had to catch the bus to his new job. They yelled at each other. He ran out of their apartment in Baldwin, N.Y., on an empty stomach, clutching a brown bag lunch of leftover spaghetti.</p>
        <p>And because he made the bus, he very likely saved 19 fellow passengers on their Long Island M.T.A. bus from serious injuries in what could have been a major traffic accident, the authorities said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Shedrick Lawrence told his wife yesterday morning that he did not have time to cook his own sausage because he had to catch the bus to his new job. They yelled at each other. He ran out of their apartment in Baldwin, N.Y., on an empty stomach, clutching a brown bag lunch of leftover spaghetti.</p>
        <p>And because he made the bus, he very likely saved 19 fellow passengers on their Long Island M.T.A. bus from serious injuries in what could have been a major traffic accident, the authorities said.</p>
        <p>When the driver collapsed from a fatal heart attack about 8 a.m., Mr. Lawrence, 30, grabbed the wheel of the bus, which was headed east on Jerusalem Avenue in North Merrick. He steered it away from a concrete overpass, through one fence, over a patch of grass, into some saplings, through another fence and into a backyard, where it stopped after crashing into the aluminum awning of a suburban home, police and transit officials said. ''I didn't want to sit there and watch myself die,'' Mr. Lawrence said.</p>
        <p>Eleven of the 20 passengers were treated for minor injuries at Nassau County Medical Center and released. The bus driver, David Wiggins, 38,  was pronounced dead of cardiac arrest at 8:45 a.m., a hospital spokeswoman said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lawrence's ride yesterday on Route 54 began when he boarded the bus at the Hempstead terminal, headed to his second day at a stair-building company in Bellmore, after being out of work for a month. He would have asked his wife, Kisha, to drive him to work (he said his license had been suspended), but their Toyota Camry had brake problems.</p>
        <p>So he took the bus.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lawrence sat four seats behind the driver, his legs stretched out in the aisle, and daydreamed about his bed. The bus pulled out of the Jerusalem Avenue stop near Canton Drive. Mr. Lawrence looked up and saw the driver slumped over. Maybe he was looking for something under the wheel, Mr. Lawrence thought. But the driver's head was on the wheel. Mr. Lawrence sprinted up to the front.</p>
        <p>At first the bus was going around 5 m.p.h., Mr. Lawrence said. But then it began accelerating as the driver's foot slammed on the gas pedal. Mr. Lawrence grabbed the steering wheel and sat on the driver's lap. He tried hitting the brake, but could not get his foot between the driver's feet. The driver's leg was impossible to move.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lawrence looked up. The bus, now going about 30 m.p.h., was headed straight for the wall of a concrete overpass. Passengers screamed. Mr. Lawrence jerked the wheel to the left.</p>
        <p>The bus careered onto a field of grass. Mr. Lawrence said he wanted to crash it into a large tree, but he did not see any nearby. The bus barreled into one fence. Then another one. Then it shot into someone's backyard, and Mr. Lawrence saw a house coming up fast. He dived into the aisle and began praying.</p>
        <p>''I didn't want to go, not like this,'' said Mr. Lawrence, the father of two. ''I'm telling God I've got to live. I've got to live for my babies.''</p>
        <p>Then the bus screeched to a halt. Having slammed into the awning, it stopped six feet from the house.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lawrence and the other passengers scrambled out an emergency window. ''I thought the bus might blow up,'' he said. ''That's what happens in the movies.''</p>
        <p>Police cruisers and ambulances showed up, and Mr. Lawrence called his wife and said he was shaken up. She told him to go to work.</p>
        <p>''A lot of people expect him to be at work today,'' she said. ''How do you expect your rent to be paid?''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lawrence went to the hospital, then caught a ride to work with a reporter, not a scratch on him. But he had left his bag of leftover spaghetti on the bus. His boss treated him to lunch at a Chinese restaurant.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
