<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Negotiations Are Continuing As Telephone Strike Drags On</title>
    <meta content="16PHON" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222966"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Communications Workers of America</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Verizon Communications</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Romero, Simon</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000816T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DEFDA1F3FF935A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="543" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Negotiations Are Continuing As Telephone Strike Drags On</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SIMON ROMERO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Romero, Simon</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Communications Workers of America and International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers, which represent more than 86,000 customer service workers and technicians who are on strike at Verizon Communications, continue to wrangle with company over several issues, extending strike now in its 11th day (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Unions representing more than 86,000 customer service workers and technicians at Verizon Communications continued to wrangle with the company over several issues yesterday, extending a telephone strike now in its 11th day.</p>
        <p>Progress appeared to be made late yesterday, however, at a meeting between the company and union negotiators for the region that includes New York and New England. According to a person close to the talks, Verizon addressed some concerns over job security in a development that could lead to the end of the strike in the next several days.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Unions representing more than 86,000 customer service workers and technicians at Verizon Communications continued to wrangle with the company over several issues yesterday, extending a telephone strike now in its 11th day.</p>
        <p>Progress appeared to be made late yesterday, however, at a meeting between the company and union negotiators for the region that includes New York and New England. According to a person close to the talks, Verizon addressed some concerns over job security in a development that could lead to the end of the strike in the next several days.</p>
        <p>Verizon and the Communications Workers of America and the International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers are trying to resolve issues that include job-related stress, mandatory overtime and the transfer of work in response to the merger of Bell Atlantic and GTE, which formed Verizon.</p>
        <p>The unions and the company met for formal talks in Washington yesterday morning, people close to the negotiations said, and ancillary discussions continued into the night.</p>
        <p>The two sides are largely in agreement over wages, benefits and a concession from Verizon allowing the unions to organize more easily in the company's wireless division. But the differences over workplace stress and the possible loss of job security because of the merger emerged as sticking points.</p>
        <p>As the strike drags on, Verizon has tried to deal with a growing number of requests for telephone service, for repair of existing service and vandalism. The company said it had to focus on repair requests instead of installations of new service and had asked customers having problems receiving help from directory assistance to look up numbers on its Web site, www.bigyellow.com.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, though, Verizon had to shut down a separate site to which it had been directing customers who needed to report service problems. The shutdown came after an online magazine, SecurityFocus.com, alerted Verizon of a security breach that made it possible to use the site to get access to customers' unlisted telephone numbers.</p>
        <p>To deal with other problems, Verizon has deployed about 30,000 nonunion employees including managers and other staff members like secretaries and lawyers to fill in for the 86,000 striking workers.</p>
        <p>In the first few days of the strike, the company reported a rash of vandalism, including severed lines. Reports of such incidents have dwindled, but late Monday telephone service for 1,600 residential and business customers in Massachusetts was knocked out after vandals cut  cables at a pole in Tewksbury, Mass.</p>
        <p>The company, which managed to restore service by about noon yesterday, offered a $25,000 reward for information leading to the arrest and conviction of people involved in the cable cutting. ''Whoever did this knew what they were doing,'' said Jack Hoey, a Verizon spokesman.</p>
        <p>The company said it was receiving  80,000 requests a day for repair and dealing with as many of them as fill-in managers could handle.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
