<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Bit Baffled, Flushing Greets a Candidate</title>
    <meta content="16LAZI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222957"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Asian-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Subways</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Archibold, Randal C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lazio, Rick A (Repr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Asian-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Subways</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000816T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E0DB1F3FF935A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="613" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Bit Baffled, Flushing Greets a Candidate</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RANDAL C. ARCHIBOLD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Archibold, Randal C</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Repr Rick A Lazio takes subway to Flushing, Queens, to court Asian community; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With an eye toward reaching constituencies not traditionally thought of as Republican, Representative Rick A. Lazio yesterday took a subway line nicknamed the immigrant express to Flushing, Queens, a predominantly Asian community that his party is courting.</p>
        <p>When he stepped off the No. 7 line, he did not seem fazed that some people who shook his hand, like Huan Lee, a restaurant delivery man, did not know who he was; Mr. Lee, being a citizen of China, also cannot vote. But there were plenty of other people toting signs advertising Mr. Lazio's Senate candidacy who promised support in November.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With an eye toward reaching constituencies not traditionally thought of as Republican, Representative Rick A. Lazio yesterday took a subway line nicknamed the immigrant express to Flushing, Queens, a predominantly Asian community that his party is courting.</p>
        <p>When he stepped off the No. 7 line, he did not seem fazed that some people who shook his hand, like Huan Lee, a restaurant delivery man, did not know who he was; Mr. Lee, being a citizen of China, also cannot vote. But there were plenty of other people toting signs advertising Mr. Lazio's Senate candidacy who promised support in November.</p>
        <p>State Senator Serphin R. Maltese, chairman of the Queens County Republican Committee, and Mei Lin Tan, a real estate broker and vice chairwoman of the party, escorted Mr. Lazio as he strolled Roosevelt Avenue and adjacent streets in the heart of a Chinese immigrant neighborhood.</p>
        <p>He was also accompanied by supporters who tried to outshout a group of counterdemonstrators who back his Democratic opponent, Hillary Rodham Clinton.</p>
        <p>Once again, a young man dressed as Uncle Sam repeatedly barked at Mr. Lazio to release his income tax returns, reprising the role he played at a news conference on Monday. Again, Mr. Lazio said he would release the returns sometime this month.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio pressed on with a smile as Ms. Tan introduced him to residents, occasionally translated their remarks into English and did some cheerleading as well.</p>
        <p>''Yeah, come on!'' she shouted as she marched into a seafood restaurant, motioning diners to clap their hands for Mr. Lazio, which some did.</p>
        <p>''It's good to be in the community, to take the type of transportation every New Yorker takes here into the community and to be walked around and get this level of support,'' Mr. Lazio said afterward.</p>
        <p>The response from people, he added, was ''a terrific sign of support for who we are and the inclusive campaign that we have and the fact that our message is spreading.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Maltese said the party was aggressively courting Asian-Americans in Flushing, who, he said, were undergoing a political awakening as they developed stronger bonds to the United States.</p>
        <p>He said many shopkeepers enthusiastically agreed to wave placards and put campaign signs in their windows.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio's appearance was in line with what his campaign staff has said would be a serious effort to woo minority voters. Mr. Lazio has visited black and Hispanic neighborhoods and plans to begin a bus tour across the state today with a stop at the National Black Theater in Harlem.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio drew many well-wishers, though some offered no more than polite handshakes.</p>
        <p>''No, they don't know him,'' Ms. Tan said later of people's familiarity with Mr. Lazio.</p>
        <p>''But I tell them he will be the next senator.''</p>
        <p>Mei Jin, who works in a clothing shop on Roosevelt Avenue, said she had seen Mr. Lazio on television but had not formed an opinion of him or of Mrs. Clinton.</p>
        <p>''I don't know enough about either candidate, but it's good he came here to meet us,'' Ms. Jin said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
