<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>FOOTLIGHTS</title>
    <meta content="16FOOT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222885"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Festival of Music (Lucerne)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Jean Cocteau Repertory</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Machito Orchestra</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Lincoln Center Jazz Orchestra</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fuller, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marsalis, Wynton</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brome, Richard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Grillo, Mario</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Van Gelder, Lawrence</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blitzstein, Marc (1905-1964)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">World Upside Down, The (Play)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Cradle Will Rock, the (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000816T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E4DB1E3FF935A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="720" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>FOOTLIGHTS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAWRENCE VAN GELDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Van Gelder, Lawrence</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>63rd annual International Festival of Music Lucerne will open on August 17 in Lucerne, Switzerland; photo; The World Upside Down, comedy written by Richard Brome in 1638, will open at Globe Theater in London; Machito Orchestra directed by Mario Grillo will team up Lincoln Center Jazz Orchestra with Wynton Marsalis for free concert on Great Hill at Duke Ellington Boulevard in Upper Manhattan; photo; Jean Cocteau Repertory will open 30th anniversary season with new production of Marc Blitzstein play The Cradle Will Rock, directed by David Fuller (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NEWS</p>
        <p>Swiss Setting  With a lineup that includes the Maryinsky Orchestra led by Valery Gergiev, the Berlin Orchestra led by Claudio Abbado and the London Philharmonic led by Kurt Masur, the 63rd annual International Festival of Music Lucerne opens tomorrow in Switzerland. In all, 15 leading orchestras will participate in 26 concerts before the event ends on Sept. 16. This year's festival, commemorating the millennium, takes ''Metamorphosis'' as its theme. Isaac Stern, who made his European debut at the festival in 1948, will conduct his masterclass series.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NEWS</p>
        <p>Swiss Setting  With a lineup that includes the Maryinsky Orchestra led by Valery Gergiev, the Berlin Orchestra led by Claudio Abbado and the London Philharmonic led by Kurt Masur, the 63rd annual International Festival of Music Lucerne opens tomorrow in Switzerland. In all, 15 leading orchestras will participate in 26 concerts before the event ends on Sept. 16. This year's festival, commemorating the millennium, takes ''Metamorphosis'' as its theme. Isaac Stern, who made his European debut at the festival in 1948, will conduct his masterclass series.</p>
        <p>Topsy-Turvy  Imagine a world where lawyers beg not to be paid, deer pursue hounds, cats are protected from ravenous mice and women rule men. That world, imagined by Richard Brome in 1638, is brought to life in ''The Antipodes,'' or ''The World Upside Down,'' opening officially on Friday at the Globe Theater in London. The 17th-century screwball comedy spins around Peregrine Joyless, driven so mad by his obsession to travel the world that his family takes him to London for treatment. Brome was Ben Johnson's manservant, and much influenced by his work, though of warmer heart.</p>
        <p>All This Jazz  Dancing in the grass is in the forecast for Central Park on Saturday when the Machito Orchestra, directed by Mario Grillo, and the Lincoln Center Jazz Orchestra, with Wynton Marsalis, team up for a free concert on the Great Hill, at Duke Ellington Boulevard (106th Street) and Central Park West. Scheduled for 4 to 7:30 p.m. (with a rain date on Sunday), the concert starts with Afro-Cuban jazz compositions by the Machito Orchestra, followed by swing and the blues. It is the third in the Great Jazz on the Great Hill collaborations between Jazz at Lincoln Center and the Central Park Conservancy.</p>
        <p>Out of the Past  Written in a time of militant union activity, management backlash and repression from conservatives in Congress, ''The Cradle Will Rock,'' Marc Blitzstein's powerful ''play in music,'' directed by Orson Welles and produced by John Houseman, made history when it was first performed in 1937. Mounted as guerrilla theater in defiance of budget cuts and a suspension of Federal Theater Project productions, it attacked the American system as corrupt. On Friday the Jean Cocteau Repertory opens its 30th-anniversary season with a new production directed by David Fuller that runs through Oct. 19.</p>
        <p>LAWRENCE VAN GELDER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
