<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Woods Sets His Sights on Nicklaus's Record</title>
    <meta content="16GOLF$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222958"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pga Golf Championship</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brown, Clifton</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Woods, Tiger</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000816T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE0DB1F3FF935A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1146" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Woods Sets His Sights on Nicklaus's Record</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFTON BROWN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brown, Clifton</byline>
      <dateline>LOUISVILLE, Ky., Aug. 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Tiger Woods preparing for PGA Championship; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A year ago, Tiger Woods turned the P.G.A. Championship into a turning point in his remarkable career.</p>
        <p>Just 365 days ago, Woods had won just one major championship -- the 1997 Masters. For a player who measures his success by major championships, one was not enough.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A year ago, Tiger Woods turned the P.G.A. Championship into a turning point in his remarkable career.</p>
        <p>Just 365 days ago, Woods had won just one major championship -- the 1997 Masters. For a player who measures his success by major championships, one was not enough.</p>
        <p>He didn't win a major in 1998, and he didn't win the first three majors of 1999. Woods came to last year's P.G.A. Championship at Medinah Country Club in Illinois needing a victory to feed his insatiable appetite for majors, to begin his pursuit of Jack Nicklaus's 18 professional major championships in earnest.</p>
        <p>But after Woods won the P.G.A. last year, holding off Sergio Garcia in a riveting back-nine duel, Woods began distancing himself from everyone else, like a Ferrari with the gas pedal nailed to the floor. Starting with his victory at Medinah, Woods has won three of the last four majors, the last two by incredible margins -- 15 strokes at the United States Open, and 8 strokes at the British Open.</p>
        <p>He returns to defend his title this week at Valhalla Golf Club in the midst of an extraordinary run that has made him the world's most talked-about athlete. Should Woods win this weekend, he would become the second player to win three consecutive professional majors in one year, joining Ben Hogan, who won the Masters, the United States Open, and the British Open in 1953.</p>
        <p>Woods will be living in a fishbowl this week, as evidenced today, when hordes of fans followed him in the 90-degree heat during his practice round, getting a glimpse of a player who has single-handedly increased the importance of the event. Even Woods may never have another chance to win three majors in one year, or three majors in succession. It will be a draining week, but for Woods, winning makes everything worth it, and the possibility of winning 18 or more majors no longer looks as unlikely as it once did.</p>
        <p>''This is what I want to do, to win major championships,'' said Woods, who will try to become the first player to win back-to-back P.G.A. Championships since Denny Shute won in 1936 and 1937. ''This is going to be a long week. The golf course is set up very difficult, and the weather is going to be sapping a lot out of you. Hopefully, I can make a few putts and keep the trophy.</p>
        <p>''Am I pursuing Jack Nicklaus's records? He set the bar very high, and he won the biggest ones over and over again. Have I tried to chase him? I don't think it's realistic to think about that yet until you get into double digits, maybe the teens. It's going to take a long time. Hopefully, things will go well for a long period of time in my career.''</p>
        <p>It is fitting that Woods will be paired on Thursday and Friday with Nicklaus and Vijay Singh. Nicklaus, at age 60, may be playing his last P.G.A. Championship. Meanwhile, Singh won this year's Masters, the only major that Woods did not win.</p>
        <p>Imagine the galleries that will follow Woods and Nicklaus, in what could be their last pairing together in an official event.</p>
        <p>''It was a pleasant surprise,'' said Woods, of being paired with the player he admires the most. ''It's going to be quite an honor and a lot of fun to play with him.''</p>
        <p>If not for a first-round 75 at the Masters, where he settled for a fifth-place tie, Woods could have conceivably entered this week with a chance to win all four majors this year. If he were to win this weekend, however, he would have a chance to win four consecutive majors at next year's Masters, an idea that clearly intrigued him when it was mentioned to him last week.</p>
        <p>''Four in a row is four in a row,'' said Woods, his face lighting up. ''I came close at Augusta this year. And I already know I can win four tournaments in a one year. It's just a question of peaking at the right time. And that's something I'm getting better at doing.''</p>
        <p>The evidence that Woods can raise his game at majors is undeniable. He holds the scoring record in relation to par at three majors -- the Masters (18 under par), the United States Open (12 under par), and the British Open (19 under par). The P.G.A. Championship record is 17 under par, set by Steve Elkington and Colin Montgomerie in 1995 at Riviera Country Club, where Elkington won in a playoff.</p>
        <p>Does Woods want that record, too? Of course he does, but he is more concerned with winning. He worked hard last week with Butch Harmon, his coach, to perfect the shots he will need at Valhalla, which requires a much higher ball flight than the British Open, where the wind and links style of play required lower ball flight.</p>
        <p>When Harmon looks at Woods, he sees a player who is as enthusiastic as he was when he was 17 years old, which is when they began working together.</p>
        <p>''Tiger thinks he can get better, and I think he's going to get a lot better,'' Harmon said.</p>
        <p>Harmon did not back off when he saw the raised eyebrows on the face of the person asking him questions.</p>
        <p>''I know that sounds scary,'' Harmon said. ''But I think he can get a lot better.''</p>
        <p>Based on the last two majors, everyone in the locker room knows who the player to beat is this week. And it will be interesting to see who rises to the challenge of a player who holds a psychological edge over some players even before play begins.</p>
        <p>''I heard Nicklaus say this year that the other guys are running up the white flag,'' said Steve Jones, winner of the 1996 United States Open, who strongly disagreed. ''I've only won eight tournaments in my life, but I enter every tournament to win. Hal Sutton beat Tiger at the Players Championship, Phil Mickelson beat Tiger in San Diego. But the guy is good. In basketball, you heard guys complain that Michael Jordan got all the calls. Out here, we don't have any refs. Tiger is making history. Whether he wins 23 majors, or whatever, we'll see. But everyone knows who the best player is.''</p>
        <p>So with the world watching, again, Woods looked forward to another memorable week.</p>
        <p>''I'm going to give it everything I've got,'' Woods said. ''Hopefully, it will come together by Thursday.''</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
