<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Getting Away With Murder (Probably)</title>
    <meta content="16BERN$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222884"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bernstein, Richard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Motion, Andrew</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Wainewright the Prisoner (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000816T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E6DB1E3FF935A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1100" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Getting Away With Murder (Probably)</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD BERNSTEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bernstein, Richard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Richard Bernstein reviews Andrew Motion book Wainewright the Prisoner; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WAINEWRIGHT THE POISONER  By Andrew Motion  Illustrated. 276 pages. Alfred A. Knopf. $26.</p>
        <p>Thomas Griffiths Wainewright was a minor English painter of the first half of the 19th century who was convicted of forgery and transported to Australia, where he did hard labor for seven years. He was an unusual criminal in that he knew people like Samuel Taylor Coleridge, William Blake and Lord Byron, and when his term of hard labor was finished, he gained recognition in Tasmania as a portrait painter. He was called ''an insufferable fop'' by one person who knew him, ''a daring and impudent braggart'' by another.</p>
        <p>Most important as background to Andrew Motion's unusual biography of Wainewright, he probably murdered his uncle, his mother-in-law and his sister-in-law, though he was never convicted of those crimes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WAINEWRIGHT THE POISONER  By Andrew Motion  Illustrated. 276 pages. Alfred A. Knopf. $26.</p>
        <p>Thomas Griffiths Wainewright was a minor English painter of the first half of the 19th century who was convicted of forgery and transported to Australia, where he did hard labor for seven years. He was an unusual criminal in that he knew people like Samuel Taylor Coleridge, William Blake and Lord Byron, and when his term of hard labor was finished, he gained recognition in Tasmania as a portrait painter. He was called ''an insufferable fop'' by one person who knew him, ''a daring and impudent braggart'' by another.</p>
        <p>Most important as background to Andrew Motion's unusual biography of Wainewright, he probably murdered his uncle, his mother-in-law and his sister-in-law, though he was never convicted of those crimes.</p>
        <p>Mr. Motion's ''Wainewright the Poisoner'' is an ambitious and unusual undertaking, a scrupulously factual fiction that puts Waine wright's story into an imagined confession. It is in this sense an imagined biography that aims, by having Wainewright speak for himself, at bringing us closer to the man than standard biography would allow.</p>
        <p>Mr. Motion buttresses his approach with many pages of explanatory notes providing the historical basis for every one of his imaginative gestures. Helped along in this way by Mr. Motion, a literary biographer who was named poet laureate of Britain in 1999, Wainewright tell the ''truth'' of his life and his crimes even as we understand that crucial elements in that ''truth'' are self-serving falsehoods, or at least convenient omissions aimed at restoring a tattered reputation.</p>
        <p>This is certainly an intriguing exercise, and it does succeed in bringing the reader into the troubled mind of a figure who would otherwise be known only through a few fragmentary historical leftovers. We get a kind of insider's look into early-19th-century dandyism, art criticism and Wordsworthian nature worship. Still, one reads this book wondering why it isn't more gripping, more narratively powerful, more redolent of the spice of human iniquity or at least enlivened by more mordant wit. The explanation would seem to be ''Wainewright's'' very stylistic and historical plausibility and the scholarly care that Mr. Motion has taken undermine the literary and psychodramatic potential of his story.</p>
        <p>The early chapters, in which Wainewright introduces us to his tragedy and describes the world of writers and artists he inhabited in the London of the first third of the century, have a kind of pre-Victorian vaporousness that makes them slow going. (''But while we are passing from moment to moment, we are tossed in the torrent of a thousand accidents and chances.'') When he gets to the heart of the story -- the strange deaths of his intimate relations -- Wainewright accounts for himself the way he might have had he really written this probably dishonest confession.</p>
        <p>But if Wainewright was guilty of those poisonings, he isn't going to let us into his malevolent heart; and if he isn't guilty, his ''confession'' is false and not wittily false enough to give it much more than an antiquarian interest.</p>
        <p>The critical episode in Waine wright's story has to do with the death of Helen, the younger sister of his wife, Eliza. Eliza herself -- first Wainewright's nurse, then his wife -- never comes across in this confession as anything other than a stock character described with an earnest sort of 19th-century boilerplate. (''The nurse who had lifted me from the black waters of my unhappiness with so sore a struggle had become the whole object of my wish to please.'') Helen has even less of a profile here, and while this is historically necessary, given the absence of information about her very colorlessness, it undermines Mr. Motion's purpose in inventing Wainewright's confession in the first place.</p>
        <p>Helen bought several life insurance policies, making Eliza and Wainewright (or Wainewright's creditors) her beneficiaries. The idea, Wainewright says, was this: ''While Helen was still in health, it had been my proposal that she, and I, and all of us, would escape to the Continent, where eventually we would rescue our fortunes by redeeming our policies.'' Helen's death would be faked, and the insurance money collected. But Helen dies a slow and painful death soon after the policies are bought, a death medically similar to those of Wainewright's uncle and mother-in-law not long before.</p>
        <p>In other words, Helen, having witnessed these earlier deaths, nonetheless agreed to give Wainewright a large financial stake in her demise. But Mr. Motion's historical excavation prevents us from delving speculatively into the relationship of Wainewright, Eliza and Helen, even though that would seem to be at the savory crux of the story.</p>
        <p>Instead, Wainewright moons with romantic-era heartfulness over her death. (''Our one reality was the fair head of Helen upon the pillow, her skin blanched to a deadly pallor, and her forehead sprinkled with the beads of her distress.'') We are left to ponder whether this mooning is fake or sincere. That is an interesting question, but Mr. Motion's choice of approaches to Wainewright's life doesn't shed much light on it.</p>
        <p>Much of the second half of Waine wright's narrative recounts his escape to France, his return to England, his trial for fraud (the murder charges could not be proved) and his dispatch to Australia. Again Mr. Motion provides an entirely plausible account, bolstered with footnotes, and it becomes strangely more absorbing than the earlier episodes. One senses that the Wainewright of these later pages, having less to hide, becomes more open and straightforward. He tells a story, about the killing of an albatross on board the ship that took him to Australia, that strips away his usual veneer of calculation and springs him into genuine passion, real feeling.</p>
        <p>Mr. Motion's notes on later opinions of Wainewright from the likes of Edward Bulwer Lytton, an all but forgotten writer, and Oscar Wilde, provide an absorbing epilogue. We never know for sure whether Wainewright was a poisoner, though the circumstantial evidence strongly indicates he was. Certainly he was a colorfully dubious figure, and we learn a great deal about him and his times from this book, which reveals Wainewright and at the same time coats him with a layer of prose thick enough to test the reader's patience.</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
