<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Prelates Of Russia Set Doctrine On Issues</title>
    <meta content="Y16MOS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222975"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Orthodox Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Genetic Engineering</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Church-State Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Death and Dying</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Russian Orthodox Church</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Roman Catholic Church</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Death and Dying</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Orthodox Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Genetic Engineering</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Church-State Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Church-State Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Death and Dying</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000816T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E0D91F3FF935A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="539" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Prelates Of Russia Set Doctrine On Issues</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>MOSCOW, Aug. 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Russian Orthodox Church hierarchy adopts social doctrine that condemns genetic engineering, homosexuality, euthanasia and abortion, approves concept of private property and reconfirms church's close relationship with the military; second document on relations with other faiths condemns conversion efforts but calls for continued dialogue, particularly with Roman Catholic Church (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Russian Orthodox Church adopted a social doctrine today that condemns genetic engineering, homosexuality, euthanasia and abortion, approves of the concept of private property and reconfirms the church's close relationship with the military.</p>
        <p>The doctrine was approved by the approximately 150 hierarchs of the Russian church, who are sitting as the Council of Bishops. On Monday, the council elevated the last czar, Nicholas II, and his family to sainthood, a move that had been sought by conservatives within the church.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Russian Orthodox Church adopted a social doctrine today that condemns genetic engineering, homosexuality, euthanasia and abortion, approves of the concept of private property and reconfirms the church's close relationship with the military.</p>
        <p>The doctrine was approved by the approximately 150 hierarchs of the Russian church, who are sitting as the Council of Bishops. On Monday, the council elevated the last czar, Nicholas II, and his family to sainthood, a move that had been sought by conservatives within the church.</p>
        <p>The doctrine is the first of its kind for the church, which is still establishing its place in Russian society after 70 years of atheist Soviet rule.</p>
        <p>The council, the church's second highest body, has been meeting since Sunday in the Cathedral of Christ the Savior, rebuilt recently after Stalin ordered the earlier building blown up in 1931.</p>
        <p>Bishops at today's gathering said that theirs is the only such doctrine they know about from an Orthodox church. Eastern Orthodox churches are less likely than the Roman Catholic Church to set out the church's position on social issues in such a way.</p>
        <p>In another document issued today, the Russian church defined its relationship to other religions. It condemned attempts to win over Orthodox believers by other religions, including Roman Catholicism. The Russian church has expressed anger in the past at what it considers the Vatican's expansion in its canonical territory.</p>
        <p>But the document also defended the Russian Orthodox Church's involvement in the ecumenical movement, which has been reviled by right-wing forces in the church.</p>
        <p>Metropolitan Kirill of Smolensk, leader of the church's external relations department, was in charge of developing the social doctrine.</p>
        <p>In comments today after the release of the doctrine, he said that the  Orthodox churches showed solidarity during the NATO bombing of Yugoslavia, which he condemned. But he also called for continued dialogue with Western churches, especially the Roman Catholic Church.</p>
        <p>The text of the social doctrine does not explicitly condemn the former Soviet rule, but it calls for a clear separation of church and state and says that Christians must avoid accepting government authority as absolute and must recognize its purely earthly bounds.</p>
        <p>It warns the state against interfering in the life of the church -- in its teachings, its liturgical life and its spiritual practices.</p>
        <p>While there are strong forces within the church preaching views on property similar to those of Communists, the doctrine recognizes all forms of property and says that private property is a gift from God to be used wisely for the common good.</p>
        <p>In some cases however, market relations are described negatively. Doctors are urged to take patients' well-being into consideration without worrying about material rewards, although providing adequate pay for medical workers is described as a priority.</p>
        <p>The doctrine defines war as an evil, but does not mention the Russian operation in Chechnya.</p>
        <p>And it is approving about the church's increasingly close cooperation with the military, describing it as a means of returning servicemen to the time-honored Orthodox traditions of serving the homeland.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
