<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Where the Fieldworkers Wear Lab Coats</title>
    <meta content="16GARD$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222894"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vegetables</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Chef's Garden (Co)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hesser, Amanda</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vegetables</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000816T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E3DA1E3FF935A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="2686" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Where the Fieldworkers Wear Lab Coats</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AMANDA HESSER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hesser, Amanda</byline>
      <dateline>HURON, Ohio</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Chef's Garden, small farm in Huron, Ohio, that grows herbs and vegetables specifically for top restaurant chefs nationwide for whom it is laboratory, research and development center and, often, their trump card; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A GROUP of chefs from the Ritz-Carlton hotel chain were sitting on a flatbed pulled by a 1964 John Deere tractor. It plodded along the field, grumbling the entire way. Off in the distance, a woman was crouched over a row of herbs with a crisp white lab coat on her back and a wicker basket at her side. She was harvesting with scissors.</p>
        <p>The chefs, who had come from Washington, D.C., California and Cleveland, sat in silence, their heads wagging as they took in the spectacle before them: rows of low bushes, silvery like salmon skin; delicate pine-green plants; loud-pink flowers; leafy herbs. The farmer driving the tractor didn't say a word and didn't need to. This was not like any other farm they had seen before or would ever see again.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A GROUP of chefs from the Ritz-Carlton hotel chain were sitting on a flatbed pulled by a 1964 John Deere tractor. It plodded along the field, grumbling the entire way. Off in the distance, a woman was crouched over a row of herbs with a crisp white lab coat on her back and a wicker basket at her side. She was harvesting with scissors.</p>
        <p>The chefs, who had come from Washington, D.C., California and Cleveland, sat in silence, their heads wagging as they took in the spectacle before them: rows of low bushes, silvery like salmon skin; delicate pine-green plants; loud-pink flowers; leafy herbs. The farmer driving the tractor didn't say a word and didn't need to. This was not like any other farm they had seen before or would ever see again.</p>
        <p>The herbs the woman was harvesting were just one of more than 600 plant varieties on the 70-acre farm. In less than 24 hours those herbs, meticulously cleaned and gathered in bouquets -- clean, vibrant, impossibly perfect ones -- would be shipped overnight to one of the country's top kitchens. For years, Charlie Trotter has been buying from this farm. More recently, Jean-Georges Vongerichten and Alain Ducasse have begun ordering. Even Thomas Keller, whose restaurant rests in what many consider to be America's fertile crescent, the Napa Valley, orders vegetables from here.</p>
        <p>But this small, fecund plot, called the Chef's Garden, resists that kind of romance. It's on a flat, humid plain about an hour west of Cleveland. Here, wedged between vast farms carpeted with soybeans, corn and wheat, is an extraordinary collection of culinary delicacies: Mexican tarragon, Vietnamese houttuinia (looks like basil, tastes like fish sauce), ginger shoots, New Zealand spinach, purple beans, micro red shiso and melons so sweet you could cry.</p>
        <p>For chefs around the country, this small farm has become their laboratory, their research and development center and, often, their trump card. Many farms that sell at the Greenmarkets in New York City work with chefs to develop new crops and to revive old ones. But none in upstate New York, or around the country, do it on the scale that the Chef's Garden does.</p>
        <p>Every single sprout that emerges from the farm's rich lake-bed soil is there for a restaurant. And every one is grown with such scientific precision and artistic temperament that what comes from it is something a home cook, even one with a garden out back, will never see.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Ducasse calls in an order for 20 pounds of one-inch round turnips, the farm does not check to see if enough have been harvested. A team heads out to the field and picks through rows of turnips, sifting out just the one-inch round ones.</p>
        <p>When Douglas Rodriguez, the chef at Chicama, came back from Peru with a package of seeds for huacaty (a black mint that is as important to Peruvian cooking as basil is to Italian cuisine) and culantro (a flat-leaf form of cilantro), he sent them to the Chef's Garden to have them cultivated. When Andrew Carmellini, the chef at Cafe Boulud, went to Alsace last year and had a salad of yellow dandelion greens, he asked the Chef's Garden if it could figure out how to grow them. (It did.)</p>
        <p>Along with 56 varieties of pepper, 11 kinds of melon, 65 of tomatoes, 27 of lettuce and 16 of eggplant, the farm is developing varieties of lettuce from Hungary never before commercially grown in the United States, as well as a blanched mint and a horseradish shoot that is gentler than the root itself. And with a moderate climate and a number of greenhouses, it is harvesting year round.</p>
        <p>WITHOUT the farm's produce, Mr. Rodriguez's fluke ceviche would lack its beguiling herbal aroma. The Ecuadorean shrimp at Cello would not have the peppery snap of micro-watercress in the first few bites. And the roasted lupo di mare on braised celery at Felidia would not have the gentle, fresh flavor of chopped micro-celery and wiry garlic roots.</p>
        <p>But just as the location is unlikely, so are the farmers. ''We're just a bunch of dumb old farmers,'' said Bob Jones, who runs the business with his sons, Bobby and Lee. Very few dumb old farmers, however, have classical music and sharp advertising on their phone system and refer to their fieldworkers as team members, let alone do business with Charlie Trotter.</p>
        <p>''Chefs really run our business,'' Bob Jones said. ''If we don't grow it, we try to find it and learn how to grow it.'' Precisely the way the chefs want it.</p>
        <p>''Pickers need to know that a chef doesn't like flowers on the thyme but that another chef appreciates the bud,'' Lee Jones said. In packing miniature heads of curly red leaf lettuce, a team member washes and trims them one by one, so they are pristine and flawless. They are then spun dry, packed in a cushioned container and placed in a padded box. Ice packs are added if the weather at the destination warrants it.</p>
        <p>The Joneses didn't always farm this way. Two decades ago, they ran just another commercial farm, growing cabbage, sweet corn, peppers and soybeans on 1,500 acres. In July 1980, all that changed. What appeared to be a heavy rainstorm approaching out of the northwest turned out to be hail -- hail the size of quarters. It wiped out their entire crop, and ultimately their livelihood.</p>
        <p>''We lost everything,'' Lee Jones said. ''We moved out of our home. They sold my mother's car. We lost the whole thing.''</p>
        <p>Eventually they started over, but this time with just five acres. They grew vegetables -- zucchini, tomatoes, cantaloupes, beans -- but this time sold them at the farmers' market in Cleveland. In the first few years, they often had to borrow money for gas from their neighbors just so they could get to the market, and they painted the expired license plates on their market truck with mud so they wouldn't be pulled over.</p>
        <p>At the market, Iris Bailin, then a chef at Prescott Ball &amp; Turben, a brokerage firm in Cleveland, became a regular customer. One day, she asked Lee Jones if he would sell zucchini blossoms. ''I laughed,'' he said. ''I said, 'Ma'am, that isn't how you eat zucchini -- you eat the bulb, not the flower.' ''</p>
        <p>But Ms. Bailin was persistent, and after weeks of her requests, Mr. Jones finally took a bunch to her at the market.</p>
        <p>Ms. Bailin kept buying. And so did many of her chef friends, whom she told about the Joneses' produce. Pretty soon, half their business was with chefs.</p>
        <p>In 1984, Bob, Bobby and Lee held a family vote to decide whether they should continue going to the market or try to make a living selling only to chefs. Lee Jones was adamantly opposed to taking such a risk. But he was outvoted.</p>
        <p>Their farm has since grown to 70 acres, and they now have 65 employees. The family that owns the farm surrounding theirs has more than 3,000 acres and only a few people working the land, a ratio that is about average for a profitable farm today. ''They think we're nuts,'' Lee Jones said. ''We are, but we're very committed nuts.''</p>
        <p>What made their reputation nationally -- and gave them a weekly client base of over 200 restaurants -- was the relationship they developed with Mr. Trotter six years ago. Mr. Trotter, convinced that mesclun was passe, called to see if the Joneses could grow something different, perhaps a mixture of greens like mesclun, but much smaller. ''They came with their clipboards and tested and tasted,'' Lee Jones said of Mr. Trotter and his cooks. With their suggestions, microgreens were born. They are now the farm's largest selling crop.</p>
        <p>The old market truck, with dancing vegetables painted on its sides, is still around. It sits on the farm, bent and rusted, like an ancient ruin. Around it a cluster of greenhouses has sprung up, along with a collection of buildings -- offices, packing rooms, garages -- that is soon to be the world's most complex maze.</p>
        <p>During the day, it is like a beehive buzzing with bees. There are sales representatives and accountants in the offices, packers out back, maintenance workers, men welding and a group of young farmers, a number of them interns from Russia, Bulgaria, Slovakia and Romania, running the greenhouses where the microgreens are grown.</p>
        <p>Bobby Jones charts out the 2,800 plantings each year and works with the field crews. Lee Jones handles the chefs. Bob Jones, a round man with a face like an old apple, is the man behind the curtain, orchestrating it all. ''He's part scientist, he's part doctor and he's a great grower, and he reads and reads and reads,'' Lee Jones said. Not just farming manuals, but at least 10 management books a month.</p>
        <p>When they want to try something new, they turn to him. ''A lot of our information,'' Bob Jones said, ''a lot of our help comes from books about farming 100 years ago. They relate better to our farm today.'' When a former intern from Hungary sent them four lettuce seeds, they used old techniques of crop isolation and seed selection to increase the yield.</p>
        <p>They use old tractors, which they say are more gentle on the soil, and dated ways of creating microclimates. Being just a few miles from Lake Erie, they already enjoy a moist coastal climate, but by planting corn around their fields and rye between rows as natural wind barriers, they have been able to raise the average field temperatures by five to seven degrees. As a result, though the farm is nestled in Ohio, it has a growing season identical to that of Louisville, Ky.</p>
        <p>This year, Bob Jones found a way to force a horseradish root to grow shoots by planting it deep in the soil. The shoots, which grow out the sides of the root, have the sheen of corn silk and the texture of a water chestnut. They taste like horseradish without the bite.</p>
        <p>Based on that success, the Joneses did the same with ginger roots. Hops shoots are next. Last year, when they were transplanting young garlic, they noticed that a dense cluster of long tender roots had formed. They washed and tasted them. They were like a cross between garlic and scallion, with the thickness of a chive. Now, Mr. Ducasse buys the young plant -- greens, cloves and roots -- and uses the whole thing like a scallion with its root attached.</p>
        <p>Blanched popcorn shoots have also gone over well, so next year they are going to try blanching mint and pea shoots. An effort to grow an asparagus fern -- the frail plant that grows after the asparagus is finished -- has just begun. So far, it's turned up a small, needly plant that is chewy but sweet with a faint asparagus flavor and a dash of bitterness. They have done their own tasting, but the real test lies with the chefs to whom they will send the fern for comment. (The Joneses are not tossing microgreens and vinaigrette for dinner. They eat mainstream vegetables like carrots, tomatoes and corn.)</p>
        <p>This back-and-forth relationship with chefs has accounted largely for their success. When Mr. Rodriguez gave some of his Peruvian seeds to farms in upstate New York, the farmers didn't follow through. The Joneses, however, dedicated most of a row to his herbs and another to a crop of special peppers, which they sell to him several times a week.</p>
        <p>The Joneses will also grow something for a single occasion. If a chef knows he has a large party two months hence and he wants micro curly cress for one dish, the Joneses will grow a special crop just for the party.</p>
        <p>Now, many of the chefs who buy from them visit regularly to see what is growing, to talk about new ideas, to look for inspiration. The day after the Ritz-Carlton chefs toured the farm, Mr. Carmellini, from Cafe Boulud, stopped by for his annual visit.</p>
        <p>''We don't want to supply restaurants with their weekly produce,'' Bob Jones said. ''We want to be there to give them something that's going to set a dish apart.''</p>
        <p>Even for top restaurants, it's expensive. A 5-by-6-inch plastic container of microgreens, for instance, is $12 to $26 plus shipping. Fifty flowerettes of basil tops are $12 to $17.50, depending on the variety. Cantaloupes average $6 apiece. That's why, when Mr. Carmellini was going around, though he tasted and smelled everything in sight, he was interested in just a few items. For certain vegetables, like white asparagus, Mr. Carmellini buys as much as possible when it's in season. But generally, he orders from Chef's Garden just three or four times a month.</p>
        <p>At one point during his visit, Lee Jones took him to the end of a row where a group of black buckets were overturned. ''Here's an experiment that flopped,'' Mr. Jones said, lifting a bucket. Beneath was a tight bouquet of white pointy leaves, sad and limp.</p>
        <p>''This is it!'' Mr. Carmellini exclaimed. It was the blanched dandelion greens he had tasted in Alsace and asked the Joneses to grow. Weak as they looked, they tasted right. The leaves were bitter like green dandelion, but less aggressive, and as tender as a sprout.</p>
        <p>Almost giddily, they exchanged ideas on how to improve the growing method and get the greens going in time for the winter menu.</p>
        <p>In the meantime, Mr. Carmellini would stick with his short list of favorites: New Zealand spinach, heirloom tomatoes, baby basils and strong, earthy hickory nuts grown by a neighbor of the Joneses. He uses the hickory nuts with skate sauteed in beurre noisette and haricots verts. If price were no object, Mr. Carmellini said, he would buy the baby haricots verts from the Joneses, too.</p>
        <p>But at $45 a pound, they seemed too indulgent a flourish, even for New York.</p>
        <p>Soon, Mr. Carmellini will be serving the New Zealand spinach, a cultivar indigenous to New Zealand that has a small, velvety leaf with a rounder, less chalky flavor than regular spinach.</p>
        <p>He braises sweetbreads in a sauce scented with licorice root, at the very end tossing in the rigid, succulent leaves. They wilt, draping themselves over the sweetbreads, and maintain in every bite their identity -- a sturdy, minerally leaf that is as integral and memorable as any luxury should be. Without it, the dish wouldn't be nearly as good.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
