<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Flooding's Aftermath, a Slapdash System of Dam Repairs Emerges</title>
    <meta content="16DAMS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222986"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Floods</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dams and Dikes</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Lake Seneca (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Newman, Maria</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dams and Dikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Floods</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000816T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E3D81F3FF935A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1079" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Flooding's Aftermath, a Slapdash System of Dam Repairs Emerges</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARIA NEWMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Newman, Maria</byline>
      <dateline>SPARTA, N.J., Aug. 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>About half dozen dams gave way during recent intense flooding in northwestern New Jersey, highlighting slapdash system in which many dams never undergo state-mandated inspections or repairs; New Jersey regularly monitors condition of only 187 of state's 1,600 dams, about 800 of which are privately owned; no one knows to what extent dam failures contributed to flood damage, but officials are inspecting each of them, and say that they will not provide public money for repair of private dams; map of dams that were damaged, destroyed or overflowed; photo of Lake Seneca, which emptied after dam broke (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A state-required inspection in 1991 of the Seneca Lake Dam, which gave way during intense flooding in northwestern New Jersey on Saturday night, found that it was in need of repairs, but they were never undertaken by its private owners, state officials said today.</p>
        <p>The dam is one of about a half dozen in this part of the state that were destroyed or damaged by the raging flood waters. Some of those, like Seneca's, had not had required repair work in years, said John H. Moyle, chief of the dam safety section of the state's Department of Environmental Protection.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A state-required inspection in 1991 of the Seneca Lake Dam, which gave way during intense flooding in northwestern New Jersey on Saturday night, found that it was in need of repairs, but they were never undertaken by its private owners, state officials said today.</p>
        <p>The dam is one of about a half dozen in this part of the state that were destroyed or damaged by the raging flood waters. Some of those, like Seneca's, had not had required repair work in years, said John H. Moyle, chief of the dam safety section of the state's Department of Environmental Protection.</p>
        <p>No one was injured in the flooding, which an aide to Gov. Christine Todd Whitman told The Associated Press had caused more than $100 million in damage.</p>
        <p>But as cleanup crews continue to shore up fallen bridges and clear mudslides, environmental officials and private-lake owners are also focusing on how the creation of so many dams in this region may have contributed to the flooding.</p>
        <p>They are also finding a slapdash system in which many owners seldom inspect or repair dams, the state regularly monitors the condition of only 187 of New Jersey's 1,600 dams, and maintenance and inspection of the rest is largely arbitrary and unsupervised.</p>
        <p>Mr. Moyle said about half of the state's dams are built and maintained by private owners, many of them, like Seneca, for recreational purposes.</p>
        <p>''A lot of these dams are in need of repairs, and very few of them are up to current standards,'' he said.</p>
        <p>No one knows to what extent the failure of the dams contributed to the damage, but state officials are inspecting each of them and have said that they will not provide public money to help repair the private dams. For now, that leaves homeowners who bought properties for their lakeside views fronting mud holes that smell of dead fish.</p>
        <p>On Saturday night, as a persistent storm dumped 14 inches of rain on Sparta, the waters on Seneca Lake were rising steadily. But at about 6 p.m., they started going down, said Tammy Crimando, who lives with her family on the water's edge.</p>
        <p>''My husband said, 'Something does not look right,' '' she said. ''So he and my daughter hopped in the car and went down to check the dam, and he came back and said: 'It's gone. The water's gone.' ''</p>
        <p>''And in about 15 minutes, the entire lake was drained,'' she said, her eyes misting as she stood on her deck, looking out into a mud field. ''One day it's here and the next day it's not. Who would have believed it could happen so fast?''</p>
        <p>The earthen dam on 25-acre Seneca Lake broke during the storm, spilling its entire contents into Tomahawk Lake, where, domino-style, that lake's dam also broke.</p>
        <p>Ms. Crimando, a member of the board of the 140-member Seneca Lake Association, said members were at a loss about how to  repair the dam, who would pay for it and when the lake could be restored, if ever.</p>
        <p>''We obviously bought the house for the lake,'' Ms. Crimando said. ''We're just hoping it can be fixed, but there's a dispute about who owns the lake, and there's a matter of determining who is responsible.''</p>
        <p>Association members, many ignorant of their responsibility until this week, are still reeling from the flooding.</p>
        <p>Their primary concern is who is responsible for repairing the dam, although they are shuddering at rumors of how much it could cost to replace it.</p>
        <p>While Governor Whitman has declared parts of Sussex and Morris Counties disaster areas, and there could be federal aid if President Clinton follows her lead, such help would likely not help owners of private lakes.</p>
        <p>''The full responsibility of fixing these dams and lakes falls with the lake association and whoever else owns them,'' Mr. Moyle said.</p>
        <p>But the lake association members may have one final recourse. After Tropical Storm Floyd flooded central New Jersey last September, the State Legislature appropriated $3.5 million to help pay to repair private dams in that area, which suffered $8 million in damage, Mr. Moyle said.</p>
        <p>Today, United States Representative Marge S. Roukema, who represents parts of the region damaged in the floods, said she would look into the possibility of helping private-lake owners.</p>
        <p>Mr. Moyle said many of the state's dams were built in the early 1900's by private developers, not for flood control but to provide beachfront property for new developments. The state, which has since passed legislation that makes it virtually impossible to build private dams, classifies them in three categories: high hazard, significant hazard and low hazard.</p>
        <p>There are 187 dams in the first category, and if they were to fail, Mr. Moyle said, there is a potential for loss of life. There are 372 dams considered significant hazard, and damage to them would result in severe property damage. Those in the last category, which includes the balance of the 1,600 dams, have little impact to life or property, he said.</p>
        <p>Dams in the first two categories have to be inspected every two years, Mr. Moyle said, and those in the low hazard category every four years. The Seneca Lake Dam was considered a significant hazard dam,  because its collapse would affect Tomahawk Lake downstream.</p>
        <p>Owners of private lakes are required to hire their own engineers to conduct the inspections, Mr. Moyle said. But up until now, private-lake owners have barely understood their responsibilities, and there has been virtually no state enforcement.</p>
        <p>In 1991, the last inspection for Seneca Lake found that the dam spillway would not be able to handle major flooding, and repairs were recommended. Such repairs were never done, Mr. Moyle said.</p>
        <p>''The problem is we have concentrated on the major dams,'' he said. ''We've not really aggressively enforced that inspections be done in the lower category dams. I think maybe now we will.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
