<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Addition of Brisby Will Finally Give the Jets a Big Target</title>
    <meta content="16JETS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222981"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Jets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eskenazi, Gerald</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brisby, Vincent</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000816T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E6D81F3FF935A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="882" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Addition of Brisby Will Finally Give the Jets a Big Target</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GERALD ESKENAZI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eskenazi, Gerald</byline>
      <dateline>HEMPSTEAD, N.Y., Aug. 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Jets to sign free agent receiver Vincent Brisby (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Vincent Brisby, one of seven players from Bill Parcells's first New England draft still active, is headed for the Jets.</p>
        <p>At 6 feet 3 inches tall and almost 200 pounds, Brisby is the big wide receiver the Jets have been attempting to find in the aftermath of one of the most talked-about trades in club history -- Keyshawn Johnson to the Tampa Bay Buccaneers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Vincent Brisby, one of seven players from Bill Parcells's first New England draft still active, is headed for the Jets.</p>
        <p>At 6 feet 3 inches tall and almost 200 pounds, Brisby is the big wide receiver the Jets have been attempting to find in the aftermath of one of the most talked-about trades in club history -- Keyshawn Johnson to the Tampa Bay Buccaneers.</p>
        <p>Brisby's arrival Wednesday should elevate the team's depth at wide receiver. Yatil Green, the former Dolphins first-round pick who has been plagued by injuries, failed to impress the Jets in practice or in games until Monday, when he caught three touchdowns in practice, and then continued to look good today.</p>
        <p>Another surprise today was the return of Vinny Testaverde, who participated in drills only three days after spraining his left big toe against the Ravens in a preseason game last Saturday night. If there are no setbacks, Testaverde will start on opening day, Sept. 3 at Green Bay.</p>
        <p>Ray Lucas, though, will start the final preseason game, against the Giants on Friday night. His starting receivers will be Wayne Chrebet, who has stepped up his formidable game even more now that he is the main wideout, and Dedric Ward. Both players are under 6 feet tall. Behind them are two rookies in Laveranues Coles and Windrell Hayes. Neither appears to be ready to take on full-time duties.</p>
        <p>Brisby was a surprise cut by the Patriots late Monday, even though Patriots Coach Bill Belichick had named him the starter opposite Terry Glenn earlier in training camp. But Belichick said he wanted more speed and also wanted to see Troy Brown on the field more often.</p>
        <p>So Brisby, who has been injured so often in recent years that he has only 48 receptions in the last four seasons, became available. He will cost the Jets about $750,000 against the salary cap. Brisby was Drew Bledsoe's favorite receiver their first three years together, starting in 1993. Brisby, who has caught 217 passes for 3,142 yards and 14 touchdowns, has averaged about 14.5 yards a catch in his career.</p>
        <p>''When healthy, he's a good receiver,'' said cornerback Otis Smith, a former New England teammate of Brisby's. ''He works hard.''</p>
        <p>Tom Tupa, who used to throw to Brisby during Patriots practices, remembered him as a big guy who can help us. ''He's not very fast, but he's very good,'' Tupa said.</p>
        <p>Cornerback Ray Mickens, who has played against Brisby since 1996, described him as an excellent receiver. ''I'd like to have him,'' Mickens said. ''A tough receiver. We mixed it up a little bit. I respect his game.''</p>
        <p>The acquisition of Brisby gives the Jets a big, effective receiver to complement Chrebet's overall ability and Ward's speed. Chrebet could be even more impressive than in the past. He said today that had spent the off-season doing an unusual exercise to prepare for the increased action he will see.</p>
        <p>''Every night I swam to exhaustion in my pool,'' the tightly muscled Chrebet said. ''I don't have much buoyancy. For me to do 30 to 40 laps got my heart racing. After about a week I was playing basketball for a few hours and I didn't even feel it.''</p>
        <p>He did the cardiovascular exercise, he said, because ''I want to be in better shape now.''</p>
        <p>''Instead of being in 50 to 60 plays a game, I'll be in 70 or 80,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Although Coach Al Groh remembers Brisby from New England, he also knows what Chrebet can do.</p>
        <p>''I've told him there are ways to elevate his game even more,'' Groh said. ''He's got to study the field and take advantage of what he learns.''</p>
        <p>Both Groh and Chrebet declined to say why Chrebet was held out of last Saturday's game at Baltimore, although a television report said he had been kicked in the head at practice. Chrebet was at the game, though, and after Testaverde was injured he sat with the quarterback.</p>
        <p>''Don't do this to me again, Vinny,'' Chrebet said, reflecting on the season-ending Achilles' tendon injury the quarterback sustained last year. But today Testaverde showed that he may be back sooner than expected, and when he does return, he will have a big target to throw to in Brisby.</p>
        <p>EXTRA POINTS</p>
        <p>JUMBO ELLIOTT's appeal on his two-game suspension will take place Wednesday. But he will not learn anything until at least next week. Elliott received a small fine and did community service after pleading guilty to two violations stemming from a bar fight last year. . . . Offensive tackle JASON FABINI will appeal the $15,000 fine by the league for his involvement in the altercation. Fabini, however, will have his criminal charges dismissed in a few days. The Nassau County court said it would expunge his conviction if he stayed out of trouble for six months. . . . CARL BANKS, the Jets' director of player development, is a finalist for the Hall of Fame balloting for his career as a Giants linebacker. . . . DANNY FERRAUIOLA will leave the Jets, where he is a public relations assistant, to become a senior publicist with ESPN the Magazine.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
