<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Burmese Salads, With the Thermostat on Cool</title>
    <meta content="16BURM$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222881"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Burma</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Burros, Marian</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Myanmar</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000816T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02E0DD1E3FF935A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1166" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Burmese Salads, With the Thermostat on Cool</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARIAN BURROS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Burros, Marian</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Marian Burros article on Burmese salads; recipes; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ON my first day in most Southeast Asian countries I invariably have the following conversation:</p>
        <p>Guide: I have arranged for you to have dinner tonight in your hotel.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ON my first day in most Southeast Asian countries I invariably have the following conversation:</p>
        <p>Guide: I have arranged for you to have dinner tonight in your hotel.</p>
        <p>Me: Do they serve local food?</p>
        <p>Guide: You won't like that. Maybe you can have Chinese.</p>
        <p>A polite argument ensues.</p>
        <p>But sometimes I get lucky. Last year in  Myanmar (formerly Burma), the Strand Hotel in Yangon (formerly Rangoon) actually had a small menu of Burmese dishes, mostly salads. They were superb, with light, bright flavors and a wonderful mix of textures. As I later learned from Burmese cooks living in the United States, those dishes had been authentically seasoned and only slightly altered to suit Western tastes.</p>
        <p>I think of those salads when it's really hot, as it is in Myanmar, where the average year-round temperature is over 80 degrees.  Salads are always cooling, of course, and in countries with tropical climates hot spices are frequently used because they make people perspire, another technique for cooling off. The Burmese, like the Thais and Laotians, love raw vegetables and greens and eat them with a pungent dipping sauce that usually contains chilies. Their daily outdoor markets are filled with dazzling displays of small pale purple eggplants, tiny fiery green chilies, tomatoes, and green papayas and mangoes that are treated like vegetables. Markets also carry betel nuts, which produce a high as well as blackened teeth.</p>
        <p>Myanmar sits between India to the northwest and China to the northeast, with Thailand to the south, and its cooking has been shaped by its neighbors' ingredients: bamboo shoots and soy sauce; curry leaves and tamarind; fish sauce and lemon grass. Yet, the food is distinctly Burmese. Despite the use of chilies, the food is never as hot as it is in Thailand.</p>
        <p>Curries are a staple, but the Indian versions use a far more complex blend of spices. The Burmese rely on fresh ingredients like green chilies for additional seasoning.</p>
        <p>Rice is the mainstay of the diet, but the Burmese love noodles, too, a notable legacy from China. The Burmese national dish, if there is such a thing in a country with almost 70 indigenous groups, is a noodle soup called mohinga. Fish-based and made with rice noodles, it is served at breakfast, and it was one of the most appealing breakfasts I have ever eaten. Shan State in particular is noted for its noodle dishes, and I had a wonderfully savory version at a hotel on Inle Lake.</p>
        <p>But the specialty of Myanmar is lephet, or fermented tea leaf salad. Its appeal lies in the slight bitterness and smokiness of the leaves, which are mixed with a highly seasoned combination of fried garlic, roasted sesame seeds, peanuts, fish sauce and lime juice. In Burma it is served as a snack, a palate cleanser, a welcome to guests and a stimulant to ward off sleep.</p>
        <p>When tomatoes and cabbage are added, it is served as a salad. (That is how it is adapted in the United States. Both Irene Khin Wong, who owns Saffron59, a catering company in New York, and Pyu Pyu Win, who owns Myanmar Burmese Restaurant in Falls Church, Va., serve it that way.)</p>
        <p>Ginger salad is made of peeled, julienne of ginger with many of the same ingredients as the tea leaf salad, but the slightly hot ginger provides a completely different taste. The recipe is based on one from Ms. Win and Claudia Saw Lwin Robert, who lives in Yangon.</p>
        <p>The green papaya salad is similar, but once again, the papaya enhances the other flavors while adding texture if not taste.</p>
        <p>All three salads are easy to put together once you have made a trip to Indian and Asian markets for the staples, like fish sauce, ground roasted peanuts and ground dried shrimp. The fermented tea leaves are probably the most exotic ingredient, and they can be ordered from Myanmar Wholesale and Retail (212) 566-1851. The Chinatown business also sells packages of mixed fried garlic, peanuts, beans and sesame seeds in oil to use in the salad, for $6 plus shipping, but you can buy just the tea leaves (also $6) and make the salad following the recipe given here.</p>
        <p>PAPAYA SALAD  Adapted from the Strand Hotel  Time: about 20 minutes</p>
        <p>1 very large julienne green papaya  2 slices lime, plus extra for garnish  3 tablespoons ground roasted peanuts  1 to 2 tablespoons ground dried shrimp  1 large onion, very thinly sliced  1 tablespoon garlic-flavored oil</p>
        <p>1/4 cup lime juice  2 tablespoons fish sauce (nam pla or nuoc mam)</p>
        <p>1/4 to  1/2 teaspoon minced bird's-eye or  other very hot green chili  2 tablespoons chopped cilantro  Cilantro leaves and whole green chilies for garnish.</p>
        <p>1. Soak papaya julienne in water to cover with 2 slices of lime for 15 minutes or longer. Drain.</p>
        <p>2. Combine with other ingredients and mix well. Arrange on plate. Garnish with cilantro leaves, lime slices and green chilies.</p>
        <p>Yield: 4 servings.</p>
        <p>GINGER SALAD  Adapted from the Strand Hotel  Time: about 20 minutes</p>
        <p>2/3 cup peeled julienne ginger  2 tablespoons ground roasted peanuts  2 tablespoons whole roasted peanuts  2 tablespoons peanut oil  2 teaspoons fish sauce (nam pla or nuoc mam)  1 to 2 tablespoons ground dried shrimp  2 tablespoons toasted sesame seeds  2 plum tomatoes, halved and thinly sliced  1 cup very thinly sliced cabbage  2 teaspoons toasted yellow split pea flour  (see note)  2 teaspoons fried garlic slices  Serrano or other hot green chilies, chopped, for garnish.</p>
        <p>Combine all ingredients except chilies in a large bowl. Mix well. Divide among four plates, and serve, garnished with chopped chilies.</p>
        <p>Yield: 4 servings.</p>
        <p>Note: Split pea flour is available in Indian markets. Spoon desired quantity onto aluminum foil, and bake at 350 degrees until it begins to brown, just a few minutes.</p>
        <p>FERMENTED TEA LEAF SALAD  Adapted from the Strand Hotel  Time: about 20 minutes</p>
        <p>1/4 to  1/2 cup fermented tea leaves  1 tablespoon dry shrimp powder  1 tablespoon peanut oil  2 large julienne plum tomatoes  1 cup very thinly sliced cabbage  1 teaspoon fried garlic (see note)  2 tablespoons roasted peanuts  2 tablespoons fried dried peas  2 teaspoons toasted sesame seeds  2 to 3 teaspoons lime juice</p>
        <p>1/8 to  1/4 teaspoon minced bird's-eye chili or other hot chili, like a serrano  1 to 2 teaspoons fish sauce (nam pla or  nuoc mam)  Cilantro leaves, sliced fried garlic and whole green chilies, for garnish.</p>
        <p>Combine all ingredients in large bowl, and mix well. Divide between two plates, and  serve, with garnishes.</p>
        <p>Yield: 2 servings.</p>
        <p>Note: To make fried garlic, slice as many cloves of garlic lengthwise as desired. Saute slowly in peanut oil to cover until garlic is lightly browned on both sides. Remove from oil, and place on paper towels to dry. Refrigerate in tightly covered container.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
