<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Knoblauch Is Still Aching</title>
    <meta content="16PINS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222985"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Curry, Jack</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Knoblauch, Chuck</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000816T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E3D81F3FF935A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="410" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Knoblauch Is Still Aching</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Curry, Jack</byline>
      <dateline>ARLINGTON, Tex., Aug. 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Status of injured New York Yankees infielder Chuck Knoblauch discussed (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Chuck Knoblauch threw from the second-base hole to first base as part of his rehabilitation for his right elbow in Tampa, Fla., on Monday, a distance of about 60 feet. Then Knoblauch woke up this morning and felt lingering soreness in his elbow, so he did not even pick up a ball.</p>
        <p>That Knoblauch could not throw on two consecutive days was an ominous sign for the Yankees, who are anxiously waiting for Knoblauch to return to the leadoff position.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Chuck Knoblauch threw from the second-base hole to first base as part of his rehabilitation for his right elbow in Tampa, Fla., on Monday, a distance of about 60 feet. Then Knoblauch woke up this morning and felt lingering soreness in his elbow, so he did not even pick up a ball.</p>
        <p>That Knoblauch could not throw on two consecutive days was an ominous sign for the Yankees, who are anxiously waiting for Knoblauch to return to the leadoff position.</p>
        <p>Knoblauch, who has been plagued by elbow, wrist and forearm injuries, has not started at second since July 24 because of what he first called a small tear. The Yankees have since called it tendinitis.</p>
        <p>''I'm obviously concerned,'' Manager Joe Torre said. ''With all the results from the tests, you think you can let it go and it'll get better. We have enough time, but, for sure, I'm concerned.''</p>
        <p>Torre said that Knoblauch hit without any pain today, but the manager did not say whether Knoblauch would try to throw again on Wednesday. Torre said ''you don't realize how important'' Knoblauch is until he has his typically feisty and effective at-bats and creates problems for pitchers by walking, getting a hit or even getting hit with a pitch.</p>
        <p>While Knoblauch is on the disabled list for the first time in his 10-year career, Torre said he was comfortable using Derek Jeter as the leadoff batter. Though Jeter had three hits tonight, he is not as selective as Knoblauch and it is also difficult to replace Jeter in the second spot. Luis Sojo batted second tonight, but Torre has also used the switch-hitter Jorge Posada there.</p>
        <p>''It's not easy to place that guy behind Jeter,'' Torre said.</p>
        <p>There are more than six weeks left in the regular season, so the Yankees hope that Knoblauch will recover and be able to play second. Since Torre already has designated hitters Jose Canseco and Glenallen Hill and would like to start David Justice as a D.H. sometimes, the Yankees do not want Knoblauch as another D.H. When Torre was asked if he had thought about the possibility of not having Knoblauch for the postseason, he did not deflect the question.</p>
        <p>''There's not much we can do about it,'' Torre said. ''I'd sure as heck feel better with him. You do the best you can.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
