<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Disputes Iraqi Claims Over Damage In Bombing</title>
    <meta content="Y16IRA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/16/world/16iraq.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222916"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Samawa (Iraq)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Myers, Steven Lee</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000816T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE7DF1F3FF935A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="668" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Disputes Iraqi Claims Over Damage In Bombing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN LEE MYERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Myers, Steven Lee</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Aug. 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>American officials say that warehouse bombed by US and British warplanes in southern Iraq held antiaircraft weapons and other military equipment, and not supplies of food as Iraq claims; officials also dispute Iraqi claim that second attack damaged train station in Samawa; Russia joins Iraqi protests to UN (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>American officials said today that a warehouse bombed by American and British warplanes on Friday in southern Iraq held antiaircraft weapons and other military equipment, and not supplies of food as the Iraqis claimed.</p>
        <p>The officials also disputed Iraq's claims that a second attack on Saturday damaged a train station in the same town. In fact, they said, the Americans and British destroyed two antiaircraft batteries half a mile away.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>American officials said today that a warehouse bombed by American and British warplanes on Friday in southern Iraq held antiaircraft weapons and other military equipment, and not supplies of food as the Iraqis claimed.</p>
        <p>The officials also disputed Iraq's claims that a second attack on Saturday damaged a train station in the same town. In fact, they said, the Americans and British destroyed two antiaircraft batteries half a mile away.</p>
        <p>The airstrikes over the weekend, which the Iraqis said killed 2 and wounded more than 20, prompted a flurry of denunciations. Iraq's foreign minister, Muhammad Said al-Sahhaf, wrote to the United Nations Secretary General, Kofi Annan, and accused the United States and Britain of ''spitting their venom at innocent Iraqis.''</p>
        <p>Russia's foreign minister, Igor Ivanov, echoed those protests today, saying the strikes violated international law and should end immediately. ''Already suffering from an embargo, simple Iraqis are the first to suffer from the destruction of food depots,'' Mr. Ivanov said.</p>
        <p>The strikes were in Samawa, a city that is about 170 miles south of Baghdad and inside the no-flight zone that American and British aircraft have patrolled in the aftermath of the Persian Gulf war.</p>
        <p>To undercut the claims, American military officials took the unusual step today of discussing classified assessments of the bombing, including aerial photographs and other intelligence reports.</p>
        <p>Lt. Cmdr. Ernest L. Duplessis of the Navy, a spokesman for the United States Central Command, which overseas all American forces in the region, said there was no evidence that the warehouse in Samawa contained food or other routine supplies, but rather was being used by Iraqi forces. ''The building was used to store air defense equipment and weapons,'' Commander Duplessis said. ''We are very confident saying that facility was not used for humanitarian food stores.''</p>
        <p>Reuters reported that one of its photographers was escorted to the site after the bombing and did not see any Iraqi military units in the area. The photographer also reported seeing several nearby homes that were severely damaged.</p>
        <p>However, an administration official said that an aerial photograph taken in the hours before the attack showed an array of antiaircraft batteries surrounding the warehouse.</p>
        <p>Commander Duplessis and officials in Washington did not dispute the report that people were killed in the strikes or that homes may have been damaged but they said the pilots do not intentionally strike civilians or nonmilitary buildings.</p>
        <p>They also said the pilots attack only when Iraqi forces fire on them first as they course over the no-flight zones in northern and southern Iraq.</p>
        <p>The weekend strikes seemed to signal an intensification of fighting in the zones. American and British jets have regularly clashed with Iraqi forces there ever since December 1998, when the United States and Britain began four nights of airstrikes to punish Iraq for refusing to cooperate with United Nations weapons inspectors.</p>
        <p>In recent weeks, there had been something of a lull in what has become a low-intensity war of attrition. Before the most recent strikes, there had not been a clash in southern Iraq since July 22.</p>
        <p>In northern Iraq, American and British jets attacked Iraqi forces today for the first time since June 14, striking an air-defense site near the city of Mosul after Iraqi forces opened fire with antiaircraft weapons, according to a spokesman for the United States European Command, which overseas the patrols in northern Iraq.</p>
        <p>Neither the Americans nor the Iraqis mentioned any deaths in the strikes today, but the Iraqi News Agency said the warplanes attacked civilian installations.</p>
        <p>Iraq has not recognized the no-flight zones, but aside from firing antiaircraft weapons or surface-to-air missiles, it has done little to seriously challenge the patrols.</p>
        <p>The strikes followed a period of increasingly pointed accusations by Iraq, particularly against Saudi Arabia, Kuwait and Turkey, which provide bases for the American and British jets patrolling the zones.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
