<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Terms of Endearment in the Booth</title>
    <meta content="16SAND$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222923"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TV SPORTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sandomir, Richard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Miller, Dennis</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Monday Night Football (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000816T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E0DF1F3FF935A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="539" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Terms of Endearment in the Booth</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Richard Sandomir</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sandomir, Richard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>TV Sports column discusses performance of Dennis Miller as broadcaster on ABC's Monday Night Football (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If nothing else, Dennis Miller's presence on ''Monday Night Football'' is loosening up Al Michaels.</p>
        <p>Why else would Al be calling Dennis ''baby'' so often?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If nothing else, Dennis Miller's presence on ''Monday Night Football'' is loosening up Al Michaels.</p>
        <p>Why else would Al be calling Dennis ''baby'' so often?</p>
        <p>As in ''You're planting all these things in my head, baby.''</p>
        <p>He never called Frank Gifford ''baby.'' Or Dan Dierdorf.</p>
        <p>Certainly not Boomer Esiason, who already had a cute moniker.</p>
        <p>In return for being called ''baby,'' Miller called Michaels ''Albeeno.'' But only once.</p>
        <p>Dan Fouts, the third man in the booth, merits a ''Danny'' or a ''Dan-O.''</p>
        <p>But not a ''sweetie.''</p>
        <p>Terms of endearment aside, it looks like this Miller thing might work out.</p>
        <p>In his second game, working Monday's Tennessee-St. Louis preseason snoozer, Miller was more consistently funny and less prone to mundane analysis.</p>
        <p>Still, ABC may have to offer the complete works of Will and Ariel Durant as premiums to football fans unaccustomed to his brand of expression.</p>
        <p>His swath of references included vivisection, Gordon Gekko, Danny Bonaduce, S. J. Perelman, Hume Cronyn, the vampire Lestat and Nancy Sinatra.</p>
        <p>And there was this bizarre nugget about the former St. Louis coach Dick Vermeil -- ''an emotional man who seemed to cry more frequently than Sylvia Plath being pepper-sprayed,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Maybe all this name-dropping scares viewers away. The 6.6 Nielsen rating fell 27 percent from last year's comparable preseason contest. It started at 7 p.m. Eastern -- when fewer households watch television -- an hour earlier than last year.</p>
        <p>Miller's acme may have come in the third quarter, after Melissa Stark's interview with Bud Adams, the owner of the Tennessee Titans and a suspect head of hair. ''The field is grass,'' he said, ''but did we just see artificial turf?''</p>
        <p>He was more cynical than in his July 31 debut, acting more like the star of ''Dennis Miller Live'' on HBO. Noting that the Washington Redskins are charging fans to attend practice, Miller said: ''Now they're charging for the training camp experience. Because you can charge for an experience, but camp is free.''</p>
        <p>He made better use of his football knowledge. He knew enough to be able to compare the style of Frank Wycheck, the Tennessee tight end, to that of the former Raider Todd Christiansen. He noted that officials are ''throwing the flags more accurately this year; the specter of Johnnie Cochran hovers.''</p>
        <p>And he described Carl Pickens, the former Cincinnati wideout now employed by Tennessee, in this way: ''The Bengal stripes were prison stripes. Now he gets to come back and kick the warden's butt twice this year.''</p>
        <p>But the stand-up comic lives. In a gag begging to be used in Nashville, Miller said: ''I got out today and saw some of the local color. I went on a visit to the sequin mines. Just a beautiful operation. I was down in the Porter Wagoner shaft.''</p>
        <p>Miller is rapidly proving his worthiness. He has adapted his often crude one-man HBO act to the three-man booth. He shares his time well with his playmates; yet by being what he is, Miller is quickly becoming the defining member of the team, the one all the publicity is about. Isn't that true, baby?</p>
        <p>TV SPORTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
