<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Former Argentine President Warns of Economic Peril</title>
    <meta content="Y16ARG$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222959"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Currency</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recession and Depression</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Argentina</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Krauss, Clifford</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Menem, Carlos Saul</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">De La Rua, Fernando (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Argentina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Argentina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recession and Depression</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Currency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000816T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807EEDB1F3FF935A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="789" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Former Argentine President Warns of Economic Peril</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFFORD KRAUSS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Krauss, Clifford</byline>
      <dateline>BUENOS AIRES, Aug. 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Argentina's former Pres Carlos Saul Menem predicts that Argentina faces devaluation and depression unless Pres Fernando de la Rua either changes economic direction or adopts dollar as national currency; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>At a time of deepening concern about the Argentine economy, former President Carlos Saul Menem has predicted that Argentina faces a devaluation and a depression unless President Fernando de la Rua either changes economic direction or adopts the dollar as the national currency.</p>
        <p>Mr. Menem retains a strong reputation among some Argentine executives and Wall Street analysts for re-engineering the economy in the early 1990's, so his public comments Monday propelled a debate in the Argentine business press and sent shudders through the government.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>At a time of deepening concern about the Argentine economy, former President Carlos Saul Menem has predicted that Argentina faces a devaluation and a depression unless President Fernando de la Rua either changes economic direction or adopts the dollar as the national currency.</p>
        <p>Mr. Menem retains a strong reputation among some Argentine executives and Wall Street analysts for re-engineering the economy in the early 1990's, so his public comments Monday propelled a debate in the Argentine business press and sent shudders through the government.</p>
        <p>Since Mr. de la Rua took office eight months ago, he has concentrated on cutting government deficits. But with the prices of wheat and soybeans at record lows, and the Argentine peso tied one-to-one to a strong dollar, the country's exports and economy have stagnated.</p>
        <p>More tax revenue and a decline in public spending this year have pleased the International Monetary Fund, but unemployment has risen to 15.4 percent, a three-year high.</p>
        <p>Only five months ago, government officials said the economy would grow at least 4 percent this year -- after a 3 percent decline in 1999 -- but now most economists say the country will be lucky to reach a 2 percent growth rate.</p>
        <p>The weakness is especially startling when compared with the performance of Latin America's two other huge economies -- Brazil and Mexico. Last week, Brazil reported its best quarterly growth rate in three years at nearly 4 percent, and there are widespread expectations it will grow 4 percent for the year in a robust recovery. And today, Mexico, where the economy is in its best shape in years, said its second-quarter growth rate reached 7.6 percent, far above expectations.</p>
        <p>Argentina, by contrast, seems mired in bad economic news. Even Argentine beef, one of the country's most promising exports, is now jeopardized by fears of a possible outbreak of foot-and-mouth disease. Demand from new markets in Asia has fallen, and experts are predicting a loss of $130 million in foreign beef sales this year.</p>
        <p>With confidence sagging, President de la Rua is putting the final touches on a new $50 million jobs program to alleviate poverty in the provinces, but the plan is being greeted with skepticism since salaries would be as low as $200 a month. Analysts hope that a continued expansion in Brazil and an eventual strengthening of the European euro could help increase Argentine exports by the end of the year.</p>
        <p>''If we continue on this path, I think there will be a devaluation, or a dollarization of the economy,'' said Mr. Menem, who is the leader of the opposition Justicialist party and says he will run for president again in 2003. ''If things go on this way, we are heading into a depression that could be dramatic for Argentina.''</p>
        <p>Argentina long suffered from cycles of devaluations and hyperinflation until Mr. Menem's administration redesigned the currency system in 1991 pegging the peso one-to-one to the dollar. The policy quickly toppled inflation to a rate that is near zero, but growth has been slow and choppy in the last five years. Mr. Menem began floating the idea of a complete dollarization during his final year in office.</p>
        <p>Mr. Menem's peg, however, went a long way to dollarizing the Argentine economy on its own. Most large contracts and transactions are already stated in dollars, as well as the debts of most big corporations.</p>
        <p>Dario Loperfido, the government secretary of culture and communications, bitterly criticized the former president today for trying to ''create a bad image of the country abroad.'' He added, ''He's not doing the country any good.''</p>
        <p>The timing of the former president's dire prognosis came as Economy Minister Jose Luis Machinea traveled to Washington today to consult with international bankers and as Mr. de la Rua prepared to be host of a two-day visit by Secretary of State Madeleine Albright.</p>
        <p>Walter Molano, head of research for BCP Securities, a brokerage firm in Greenwich, Conn., said Mr. Menem's comment ''reflects a sense among the opposition that there is blood in the water'' and it is now time to begin attacking the government's economic policies in a more forthright manner.</p>
        <p>''Things are coming to a head in Argentina,'' Mr. Molano added. ''They are running out of rabbits to pull out of their hats.''</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
