<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Heading for the Hills With a Caribbean Beat</title>
    <meta content="16CARL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222891"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="POP REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pareles, Jon</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vives, Carlos</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000816T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E6DA1E3FF935A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="412" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Heading for the Hills With a Caribbean Beat</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JON PARELES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pareles, Jon</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jon Pareles reviews concert by Colombian pop singer Carlos Vives, at Radio City Music Hall; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Actors who play musicians sometimes hang on to the role afterward, the way Gary Busey and Dan Aykroyd did. But no one has followed through like the Colombian pop singer Carlos Vives, who played a sold-out concert on Saturday night at Radio City Music Hall.</p>
        <p>Mr. Vives, who had acted in Colombian soap operas, took a television role in 1990 as Rafael Escalona, a major figure in la musica vallenata, the accordion-driven songs from the Valledupar region of Colombia. Mr. Vives went on to record a million-selling album of electrified traditionalist vallenatos, ''Clasicos de la Provincia,'' in 1993, and since then he has become a standard-bearer for Colombian music, making pop hits that flaunt traditional sounds.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Actors who play musicians sometimes hang on to the role afterward, the way Gary Busey and Dan Aykroyd did. But no one has followed through like the Colombian pop singer Carlos Vives, who played a sold-out concert on Saturday night at Radio City Music Hall.</p>
        <p>Mr. Vives, who had acted in Colombian soap operas, took a television role in 1990 as Rafael Escalona, a major figure in la musica vallenata, the accordion-driven songs from the Valledupar region of Colombia. Mr. Vives went on to record a million-selling album of electrified traditionalist vallenatos, ''Clasicos de la Provincia,'' in 1993, and since then he has become a standard-bearer for Colombian music, making pop hits that flaunt traditional sounds.</p>
        <p>Onstage, he looked like a rock star: shoulder-length hair, T-shirt, muscles and a perpetually boyish grin. Girls rushed onto the stage to kiss him and dance with him. Yet by his side was Egidio Cuadrado, wearing the black-and-tan woven straw hat of a rural Colombian and playing a button accordion. Across the stage was Mayte Montero playing the gaita, a cane flute akin to those used in Peruvian and Bolivian music.</p>
        <p>Colombia stretches from the Caribbean to the Andes, and Mr. Vives's band, La Provincia, set out to do the same. Songs often began with the sustained sound of international pop: a synthetic keyboard tone, a big guitar chord. But as soon as Mr. Vives started singing, the music almost literally headed for the hills. His voice isn't spectacular; it's slightly nasal, while it preserves the tearful yelp of old-fashioned vallenato singers. But it's ebullient enough to ride the band's catchy, pan-Colombian arrangements.</p>
        <p>La Provincia stirred up the clip-clop beat of the Colombian cumbia with Afro-Caribbean cross-rhythms; it answered button accordion with gaita or with rock lead guitar. Mr. Cuadrado's accordion lines scampered and stuttered, taking brilliant liberties with the instrument's traditional role; the gaita leaped out of the music with breathy insistence. The frenetic scratching of another rural instrument, the guacharaca (scraper), drove the music the way a washboard drives a zydeco band.</p>
        <p>The songs were about love and, nearly as often, about Colombia's places, people and culture. ''El Amor de Mi Tierra'' (EMI Latin) the title song of Mr. Vives's most recent album, combined the two. Joyful flag-waving Colombians sang along, as Mr. Vives pulled the past into the present.</p>
        <p>POP REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
