<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Metro Briefing</title>
    <meta content="16MBRF$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223019"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000816T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E7D61F3FF935A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1896" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Metro Briefing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by Anthony Ramirez</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NEW YORK</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: POLICE DEPLOYMENT CRITICIZED  The Police Department should assign more of its new officers to precincts instead of to specialized squads like those investigating robberies, arson or auto thefts, according to a report released yesterday by City Councilman Sheldon S. Leffler, a Queens Democrat. The report said precinct assignments were promised by Police Commissioner Howard Safir last year. While the department has 809 more officers than it did last year, less than half, or 361, are assigned to precincts, the report said. Staffing is a ''dynamic situation'' and the commissioner makes adjustments, a police supervisor said in response to the report. ''But crime is still declining in almost all of these precincts.''</p>
        <p>C. J. Chivers (NYT)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NEW YORK</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: POLICE DEPLOYMENT CRITICIZED  The Police Department should assign more of its new officers to precincts instead of to specialized squads like those investigating robberies, arson or auto thefts, according to a report released yesterday by City Councilman Sheldon S. Leffler, a Queens Democrat. The report said precinct assignments were promised by Police Commissioner Howard Safir last year. While the department has 809 more officers than it did last year, less than half, or 361, are assigned to precincts, the report said. Staffing is a ''dynamic situation'' and the commissioner makes adjustments, a police supervisor said in response to the report. ''But crime is still declining in almost all of these precincts.''</p>
        <p>C. J. Chivers (NYT)</p>
        <p>WANTAGH: CRASH KILLS TEEN AND INJURES 2 OTHERS  An 18-year-old driver was killed and his two passengers were critically injured yesterday after he lost control of his car at the traffic circle at Jones Beach on Long Island, the police said. The car hit a bus shelter and burst into flames, the police said. The driver, David Pagliaroli, of Yonkers, was pronounced dead at Nassau County Medical Center. One passenger, Carla Delfina, 16, of Yonkers, had second- and third-degree burns, while the other, Vida Loey, 16, of Eastchester, N.Y., had multiple injuries, a hospital spokeswoman said.</p>
        <p>Andy Newman (NYT)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: DOCTOR'S LICENSE  A Park Avenue gynecologist charged with fraud, negligence and incompetence has asked a State Supreme Court justice to lift the suspension of his medical license so he can resume his practice. The doctor, Niels Lauersen, 63, said the State Health Department violated his right to due process when it suspended his license on Aug. 9 without a complete hearing after declaring that he posed an ''imminent danger to the public.'' In papers filed Monday, Dr. Lauersen asked the court to bar the state from acting until hearings in his case are complete. Justice Phyllis Gangel-Jacob is to hear arguments today on Dr. Lauersen's petition.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: LAWSUIT AGAINST KOCH DISMISSED  A Manhattan judge has dismissed a lawsuit by a man from Sierra Leone who claimed that he was defamed when former Mayor Edward I. Koch called him a kidnapper on ''The People's Court'' television show. The man, Idris Kabia, claimed that Mr. Koch had said during the show that Mr. Kabia had kidnapped his own son. But the judge, Norman Ryp of Manhattan Civil Court, said he could find no reference to kidnapping in a videotape of the show, and ruled that state law made Mr. Koch immune from lawsuits when acting as an arbitrator in a proceeding that the parties had agreed to in writing.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>BROOKLYN: LAND BOUGHT FOR PARK  A nonprofit conservation group, the Trust for Public Land, has paid $8.3 million for two blocks in Williamsburg for use as a state park. The property, a former industrial site between North Seventh and North Ninth Streets, lies on the East River across from Stuyvesant Town in Lower Manhattan. New York University lent the trust the money and agreed to pay for the site's restoration and maintenance. In return, N.Y.U. will build playing fields for students on about two-thirds of the site.</p>
        <p>Jim O'Grady (NYT)</p>
        <p>CONNECTICUT</p>
        <p>EAST HARTFORD: STADIUM PLAN HITS SNAG  Plans for the University of Connecticut's 40,000-seat football stadium here have met a complication: two endangered species of birds live on the proposed construction site. A state environmental study released yesterday reported that Rentschler Field, a 700-acre meadow, is home to the grasshopper sparrow and the upland sandpiper. Planners do not expect the birds to stop construction of the stadium, scheduled to hold its first game in August 2003. Officials plan to create a habitat for the birds elsewhere.</p>
        <p>(NYT)</p>
        <p>STRATFORD: $1 MILLION IN STORM DAMAGE  A quick-moving thunderstorm caused $1 million in flood damage to Stratford, according to the town manager's office. Yesterday, town officials and representatives from the Federal Emergency Management Agency and the Small Business Administration toured areas flooded by Saturday's storm, which dumped more than six inches of rain and damaged homes and businesses near a railroad viaduct on Main Street. Gov. John G. Rowland appealed to President Clinton on Monday for federal disaster aid, including low-interest loans.</p>
        <p>(NYT)</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY</p>
        <p>UNION TOWNSHIP: TRANSIT EXPANSION  New Jersey Transit plans to expand its Raritan Valley line. It broke ground here yesterday on a $30 million train station that is to serve 800 commuters, including 400 from congested stations in Roselle Park, Cranford and Westfield. The station, Union Township's first, will include a 3,000-square-foot terminal with restrooms and up to three shops, a 545-foot platform, a 484-car parking lot and a ''kiss and ride'' dropoff area. It will be called Union Station.</p>
        <p>Steve Strunsky (NYT)</p>
        <p>NEWARK: BRENNAN HEARING DELAYED  A contempt hearing for Robert E. Brennan, left, the disgraced financier, has been blocked pending review by a federal appellate court. The contempt hearing had been sought by Judge Richard Owen of Federal District Court, who in 1995 ordered Mr. Brennan to pay what is now more than $78 million to the Securities and Exchange Commission. The S.E.C. and New Jersey authorities maintain that Mr. Brennan has consistently sought to hide his assets overseas. It was unclear why the United States Court of Appeals for the Second Circuit blocked the hearing, which had been scheduled for today. Neither Mr. Brennan nor the S.E.C. had asked the court to consider the case.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>BURLINGTON TOWNSHIP: CRASH MEMORIAL  The National Transportation Safety Board has completed the first phase of what could be a yearlong investigation into the cause of a midair collision last week that killed 11 people and destroyed a house. Investigators have finished examining the site where a Piper Navajo carrying nine people and a Piper Seminole with a flight instructor and student pilot aboard collided Aug. 9. A memorial service is scheduled for tomorrow at Lakehurst Naval Air Station, where six of the victims had worked.  (AP)</p>
        <p>Compiled by Anthony Ramirez</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
