<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Police Arrest Suspect in East Side Sex Assaults</title>
    <meta content="16RAPE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223018"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dewan, Shaila K</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holmes, Ishmael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000816T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E7D61F3FF935A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="576" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Police Arrest Suspect in East Side Sex Assaults</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SHAILA K. DEWAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dewan, Shaila K</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Homeless man Ishmael Holmes, who police say has been haunting Upper East Side in search of women walking alone, is arrested for sexual assault and attempted robbery; Holmes is suspected in string of eight incidents; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A homeless man who the police said had been haunting the Upper East Side in search of women walking alone was charged last night with sexual abuse and attempted robbery.</p>
        <p>The man, Ishmael Holmes, 22, had stalked some women and assaulted others, and was on probation for a similar crime in the Bronx, the police said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A homeless man who the police said had been haunting the Upper East Side in search of women walking alone was charged last night with sexual abuse and attempted robbery.</p>
        <p>The man, Ishmael Holmes, 22, had stalked some women and assaulted others, and was on probation for a similar crime in the Bronx, the police said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Holmes, who the police said had been released from jail in early May and was living in a Wards Island homeless shelter, is suspected in a string of eight incidents of harassment, robbery or sexual assault that began on May 30 and took place between 83rd and 95th Streets and First and Fifth Avenues. The victims were 21 to 31 years old.</p>
        <p>Mr. Holmes would usually strike at midday, the police said, when he would follow a woman into her apartment building. Twice the victims were sexually assaulted, the police said, and other times they escaped or scared him away.</p>
        <p>Mr. Holmes was arrested in 1997 for sexual assault and in 1998 for public lewdness, Capt. Robert Iovino said.</p>
        <p>In October 1999, he was arrested in connection with two sex-related incidents in the Bronx, Captain Iovino said.</p>
        <p>Steven Reed, a spokesman for the Bronx district attorney, said that Mr. Holmes had asked a woman to disrobe and kneel but that the woman resisted and Mr. Holmes fled. Mr. Holmes reached a deal with prosecutors in which he pleaded guilty to unlawful imprisonment, a nonviolent felony, Mr. Reed said.</p>
        <p>Though he had not yet been sentenced, under the terms of the plea agreement he was released and was to have served four and a half years of probation in addition to the six months he had already spent in jail.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reed said Mr. Holmes's release was conditional on his living at the shelter, attending a sex offender's program and appearing regularly before the judge. Mr. Reed was not sure whether Mr. Holmes had begun attending the therapy, but said he had appeared before the judge at least twice since his release.</p>
        <p>In the Bronx incident, Mr. Reed said, no sexual acts were performed and no weapon was used.</p>
        <p>When a pattern of sexual abuse began to emerge on the Upper East Side, officers there were shown sketches of the attacker every morning during training sessions.</p>
        <p>They were on the lookout for him when they received a call about an attempted robbery in the vestibule of a building on 87th Street at 7 p.m. Monday, said Officer Chris Martinez, who responded to the call with Officer John Schretzman.</p>
        <p>The officers described the robber on the radio, and Mr. Holmes was picked up on 94th Street, Officer Martinez said. The victim identified him, and several other victims recognized him in lineups, the police said. ''He did fit the description,''  Officer Martinez said. ''We're not going to say we automatically knew it was the person.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
