<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Blazers' Play Forces The Lakers To Game 7</title>
    <meta content="03LAKE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204391"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Los Angeles Lakers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Portland Trail Blazers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Spousta, Tom</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Portland Trail Blazers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Los Angeles Lakers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E3DA1E3CF930A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="760" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Blazers' Play Forces The Lakers To Game 7</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TOM SPOUSTA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Spousta, Tom</byline>
      <dateline>PORTLAND, Ore., June 2</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Portland Trail Blazers defeat Los Angeles Lakers, 103-93, in sixth game of Western Conference Finals; series is tied 3-3; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>They wore determined looks and shook their heads from side to side, gesturing to the Los Angeles Lakers throughout Game 6 that the Western Conference finals would not end in their house.</p>
        <p>Tonight the Portland Trail Blazers protected the Rose Garden like pit bulls, stopping the Lakers at every key moment for a 103-93 victory to tie the series at 3-3 and force Game 7 on Sunday in Los Angeles.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>They wore determined looks and shook their heads from side to side, gesturing to the Los Angeles Lakers throughout Game 6 that the Western Conference finals would not end in their house.</p>
        <p>Tonight the Portland Trail Blazers protected the Rose Garden like pit bulls, stopping the Lakers at every key moment for a 103-93 victory to tie the series at 3-3 and force Game 7 on Sunday in Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>After falling behind by three games to one, the Trail Blazers are in position to become only the seventh team in National Basketball Association history to win a four-of-seven-game series after falling behind by three games to one.</p>
        <p>Steve Smith, the 31-year-old guard, fired daggers into the Lakers' hearts throughout the game and finished with 26 points. Rasheed Wallace added 18 and Damon Stoudamire 14. Scottie Pippen, quiet through three quarters, contributed 9 points and several clutch defensive plays.</p>
        <p>Kobe Bryant had 33 points and Shaquille O'Neal had 17, his lowest total against Portland this season, and 11 rebounds.</p>
        <p>''Our guys came out with a passion and the intensity that had been lacking in previous games,'' Portland Coach Mike Dunleavy said. ''There's no fear factor for us going down there. Everybody wanted a Game 7. Now we got one.''</p>
        <p>Bonzi Wells energized an already raucous home crowd with 20 points in 19 minutes. Wells, who played only six minutes in three quarters, hit back-to-back baskets to give the Trail Blazers a 79-68 lead with 9 minutes 11 seconds to play. Moments later, Brian Grant hit two free throws to put Portland ahead by 13 and force the Lakers to scramble.</p>
        <p>Unlike Games 3 and 4, when the Trail Blazers blew double-digit leads, they held steady in the third quarter tonight. The Lakers could chip only 2 points off Portland's lead and trailed by 71-63. A dunk and a jump shot by Wallace and two free throws each from Pippen and Smith held off a Los Angeles surge, before Bryant drilled a 3-pointer with 1.3 seconds left in the quarter to move the Lakers within 8 points.</p>
        <p>The Lakers cut their 10-point halftime deficit to 49-44 with a 3-point play by Ron Harper and a 3-point shot from Glen Rice. The Trail Blazers quickly countered, though, with a 10-5 run for some breathing space at 58-49 midway through the third quarter.</p>
        <p>The Trail Blazers' 49-39 halftime lead was earned without any offense from Pippen, who took only one shot, a 3-pointer in the second quarter. Pippen's presence was felt with three rebounds and two assists, but mostly he left the heavy lifting to Smith, Stoudamire and Wallace.</p>
        <p>Smith and Stoudamire scored 12 points each and Wallace added 11 as the Trail Blazers twice built 15-point leads early in the second quarter. Smith was 6 of 9 from the field and Stoudamire, easily surpassing his 8.8-point average for the series, hit 6 of 10 field-goal attempts.</p>
        <p>Wallace came alive late in the second quarter with 7 points. His short jump shot and dunk in the final 1:30 held off a Lakers' rally that had twice pulled them within 8 points.</p>
        <p>Bryant, nursing a sprained foot suffered early in Game 5, led the Lakers in the first half with 14 points.</p>
        <p>As for most of the series, O'Neal was ominously quiet in the first half. With the Trail Blazers sticking to him like lint, he made 4 of 8 field-goal attempts for 8 points and grabbed 5  rebounds.</p>
        <p>''I don't know if we got in their heads,'' Stoudamire had said before the tip-off. ''But we gave them something to think about. I definitely don't think they thought they were coming back to Portland.</p>
        <p>''A lot of people had buried us. Probably the only people in the country who thought we were going to win that last game was us.''</p>
        <p>Portland's mission was apparent from the start. Once again, the Trail Blazers flung themselves at the Lakers from all angles and set a blistering pace. Smith and Stoudamire were especially hot, carrying the Trail Blazers to a 26-15 lead through one quarter.</p>
        <p>Bryant was in the starting lineup despite his sprained foot, although concern about his injury caused the Lakers to make a defensive adjustment.</p>
        <p>Bryant had guarded Pippen for most of the series, but was switched to Stoudamire. Rice was assigned to Pippen, a matchup that the Trail Blazers did not need to exploit after they blitzed the Lakers early.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
