<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Motor Vehicles Chief Quits Amid Accusations on Tests</title>
    <meta content="03EMIS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204314"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Envirotest Systems</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Herszenhorn, David M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Salinas, Jose O</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rowland, John G (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blumenthal, Richard (Atty Gen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E0DA113CF930A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="499" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Motor Vehicles Chief Quits Amid Accusations on Tests</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID M. HERSZENHORN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Herszenhorn, David M</byline>
      <dateline>BRIDGEPORT, Conn., June 2</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Commissioner of Connecticut State Motor Vehicles Department, Jose O Salinas, resigns amid growing number of accusations of fraud in state's emissions testing program, which is run by outside contractor, Envirotest Systems Inc; emissions testing case began with arrests of three inspectors charged with falsifying emission test results in exchange for payments from car owners of $50 to $60; Attorney General Richard Blumenthal said he had received reports of corruption in program prompting Gov John G Rowland to order independent audit of Envirotest; Mr Salinas is not accused of wrongdoing but questions have arisen regarding improper contract oversight by Department of Motor Vehicles (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The commissioner of the Connecticut State Motor Vehicles Department, Jose O. Salinas, resigned on Thursday amid a growing clamor over accusations of fraud in the state's emissions testing program, which is run by an outside contractor, Envirotest Systems Inc.</p>
        <p>In a letter to Gov. John G. Rowland, Mr. Salinas said he planned to resign effective June 29. But Mr. Rowland, who has been described by aides as increasingly frustrated with the fraud accusations, asked that the resignation take effect Monday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The commissioner of the Connecticut State Motor Vehicles Department, Jose O. Salinas, resigned on Thursday amid a growing clamor over accusations of fraud in the state's emissions testing program, which is run by an outside contractor, Envirotest Systems Inc.</p>
        <p>In a letter to Gov. John G. Rowland, Mr. Salinas said he planned to resign effective June 29. But Mr. Rowland, who has been described by aides as increasingly frustrated with the fraud accusations, asked that the resignation take effect Monday.</p>
        <p>Bill Seymour, a spokesman for the Department of Motor Vehicles, said the resignation was unrelated to the  accusations. Mr. Salinas, a lawyer,  decided to return to a post in the attorney general's office, Mr. Seymour said, because ''his first real love was the practice of law.''</p>
        <p>The emissions testing case began  in March with the arrests of three inspectors here who were charged with falsifying emissions test results in exchange for payments from car owners of $50 to $60.</p>
        <p>A fourth inspector was arrested in April, in Darien, after officials from Envirotest told state police investigators that he had sold a passing sticker for $80. The emissions test, required every two years, costs $20;  cars that fail must be repaired and tested again.</p>
        <p>Last month, the attorney general, Richard Blumenthal, said he had received reports of widespread corruption in the emissions testing program and wrote to Mr. Salinas urging a broad investigation into allegations of bribery, fraud and theft.</p>
        <p>That same week, Governor Rowland ordered an independent audit of Envirotest, which has run the emissions inspection program since 1994 under a 10-year, $25 million contract from the state. The company, based in East Granby, operates 25 testing stations and inspects 1.5 million cars a year.</p>
        <p>Mr. Salinas has not been accused of any wrongdoing and is not a target of the audit or the state police investigation. But some people, including Governor Rowland, have questioned whether the Motor Vehicles Department exercised proper contract oversight. ''The governor obviously is very concerned about the integrity of the emissions testing program,'' said his spokesman, Dean Pagani. Mr. Pagani said the governor had instructed the auditors to look at both the private contractor and the motor vehicle agency.</p>
        <p>''He is seriously asking whether the management at D.M.V. has done a sufficient job in overseeing that contract,'' Mr. Pagani said.</p>
        <p>The fraud allegations relate to various automobile tests that are performed by more than 300 employees of Envirotest around the state, including exhaust-system emission tests and gas-cap tests that check fuel vapor emissions. The arrested inspectors have been accused of conducting multiple emissions tests on cars that they know will pass to generate an extra pass report and sticker for a car that would fail.</p>
        <p>Martha Sanders, a spokeswoman for Envirotest, said the company had cooperated fully with investigators and was vigilant about fraud.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
