<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Indonesia's Uphill War on Rule From the Top</title>
    <meta content="03INDO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204336"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Indonesia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wahid, Abdurrahman (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Suharto</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mydans, Seth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Indonesia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Indonesia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE3D8113CF930A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1154" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Indonesia's Uphill War on Rule From the Top</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SETH MYDANS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mydans, Seth</byline>
      <dateline>JAKARTA, Indonesia, May 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Indonesia clamors for democracy but is directed from the top by Pres Abdurrahman Wahid much as it was under Suharto until he was forced out in May 1998; Wahid's ability to enact his policies is dangerously limited, however, because Suharto eviscerated the nation's institutions; he rules through the force of his personality, through his moral authority, through the weakness of his rivals and through a sort of lighthearted bullying, but he can never be certain how his directives will be carried out; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Everything has changed in Indonesia since its strongman, Suharto, was pushed from office just two years ago. The clamor of democracy is everywhere, along with the violence and instability that accompany a time of unfettered transformation.</p>
        <p>And nothing has changed. For all the talk about democratic principles and local empowerment, Indonesia is still focused on the ideas, the directives -- even the whims -- of one man, its new president, Abdurrahman Wahid.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Everything has changed in Indonesia since its strongman, Suharto, was pushed from office just two years ago. The clamor of democracy is everywhere, along with the violence and instability that accompany a time of unfettered transformation.</p>
        <p>And nothing has changed. For all the talk about democratic principles and local empowerment, Indonesia is still focused on the ideas, the directives -- even the whims -- of one man, its new president, Abdurrahman Wahid.</p>
        <p>Will the country's separatist movements be crushed by force or courted with blandishments? Will its military leaders be the hard men fostered by Mr. Suharto or a new generation of liberal thinkers? Will its press remain open and free? Will Indonesia begin toying again with the idea of strict currency controls?</p>
        <p>These are all fundamental questions whose final answer lies with one man, the president.</p>
        <p>And yet, in sharp contrast to Mr. Suharto, who was forced to step down in May 1998 after 32 years in power, Mr. Wahid's ability to enact his policies is dangerously limited.</p>
        <p>As he built his top-down structure of personal control, Mr. Suharto so eviscerated the nation's institutions that his successors have inherited a hollow and nearly useless bureaucracy.</p>
        <p>''The government here is almost hydroponic,'' said a Western diplomat -- a floating structure with dangling, ineffectual roots.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wahid was a compromise president, the product of back-room deals seven months ago to replace Mr. Suharto's immediate successor, B. J. Habibie. Though Mr. Wahid is personally popular, he lacks a broad political base. Even his cabinet, the product of his deal-making, does not fully support him.</p>
        <p>So he rules through the force of his personality, through his moral authority, through the weakness of his rivals and through a sort of light-hearted bullying in which he pummels potential challengers with jokes, insults and impulsive personnel changes.</p>
        <p>But when he issues direct orders, one of his cabinet ministers said, he can never be sure what the result will be. His subordinates may be recalcitrant or incompetent or simply lack the bureaucratic machinery to act effectively.</p>
        <p>''This is a president from whom everyone expects too much,'' said Daniel S. Lev, an expert on Indonesia at the University of Washington in Seattle, who was visiting Jakarta.</p>
        <p>''He is a president without the institution of the presidency,'' Mr. Lev said. ''Every major administrative institution and political institution has essentially been destroyed, crushed. There is really nothing left to work with. It doesn't matter, in a sense, how good the people are that you appoint because the institutions are devastated. There's corruption everywhere.''</p>
        <p>And so, seven months into his presidency, Mr. Wahid finds his country in a slough of discontent, its reforms slowing, its leaders consumed by personal rivalries, shaken by outbreaks of religious violence and increasingly annoyed by the mannerisms of its quirky president.</p>
        <p>Several recent missteps have particularly shaken public confidence. They include the still-unexplained firing of a highly respected economic minister, Laksamana Sukardi, and his replacement by a political ally of the president. And they include scandals involving the president's youngest brother and his personal masseuse that have evoked fears of a return of the corruption and nepotism of the Suharto years.</p>
        <p>Most dangerously, the public restiveness grows out of a sharp economic downturn that has seen the currency, the rupiah, lose up to 18 percent of its value this year and the stock market plunge by 27 percent. Although the overall economy is growing and could exceed last year's increase by as much as 3 percent, the slump has caused a panic in this still-traumatized nation, where it was an economic crash that led to the forced resignation of Mr. Suharto.</p>
        <p>And so the Western diplomat offered a succinct analysis of the current challenges facing Indonesia: ''It's the economy, stupid.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Wahid is not a president who takes a great interest in the economy, and the economic team he has assembled -- skewed by his political deal-making -- is widely viewed as weak.</p>
        <p>The situation has not been helped by a series of ill-considered statements by government officials, most strikingly by Kwik Kian Gee, the president's chief economic minister.</p>
        <p>''If I were a foreign investor, I wouldn't come to Indonesia,'' Mr. Kwik said in a recent, and much quoted, interview with Dow Jones Newswires. ''The law enforcement is not there, but not only that, the whole thing is so confusing. How can you come here?''</p>
        <p>Like Mr. Wahid, Mr. Kwik spent much of his career in opposition to the Suharto government. Both men, like some other leaders, still speak and act as if they were in opposition rather than in charge.</p>
        <p>So Mr. Kwik -- the government's chief economic manager -- blamed ''the way the government is managed'' for the weak economy. He criticized his boss for appointing a welter of economic councils and advisory groups, leading to inconsistent policies.</p>
        <p>In response, Mr. Wahid told reporters he might just take over economic management himself, despite his lack of background. He then said he might take action to control currency fluctuations -- a seeming reference to the creation of a currency board, an eccentric idea of Mr. Suharto's that aroused shudders among investors.</p>
        <p>But while the surface of public life here drifts and sloshes in what sometimes seems a sea of incompetence, fundamental changes are being prepared in the structure of the nation and its governance.</p>
        <p>Donald K. Emmerson, a professor of political science at Stanford University, calls it ''the rebirth of the Indonesian political system.''</p>
        <p>Commissions are preparing constitutional amendments for a congress scheduled in August that would put in place a democratic system with striking similarities to that of the United States.</p>
        <p>With the support of Mr. Wahid, these changes are likely to include direct election of the president, a bicameral legislature, a system of judicial review, decentralization of some power to the provinces and even perhaps an American-style bill of rights.</p>
        <p>Mr. Emmerson suggested that there may be mirror images here.</p>
        <p>Mr. Suharto placed his emphasis -- and staked his legitimacy -- on economic development, while corrupting and bankrupting the political system. It appears that the new government of Mr. Wahid, while drifting economically, has embarked on an ambitious program of political development.</p>
        <p>Mr. Suharto took the easy way; he crushed dissent by force. Mr. Wahid has more faith in the ability of his countrymen to live together in peace; this is a time when that faith is being tested.</p>
        <p>It is rainy season in Jakarta, and the gray skies and occasional cracks of thunder speak to the national mood.</p>
        <p>All debates and rivalries and even outbreaks of violence are focused now on August, when the national assembly will meet to debate, to pass laws and to hear a state-of-the-nation report from the president. No one is sure if a storm is coming.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
