<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rusch and Zeile Brighten Mets On Stormy Night</title>
    <meta content="03METS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204387"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Tampa Bay Devil Rays</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Curry, Jack</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Tampa Bay Devil Rays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Tampa Bay Rays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E4DA1E3CF930A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="682" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rusch and Zeile Brighten Mets On Stormy Night</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Curry, Jack</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Mets defeat Tampa Bay Devil Rays, 5-3, in interleague play (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Glendon Rusch pitched one inning for the Mets after he was acquired from the Kansas City Royals last September, no chance for him to make any impression. Rusch was just another young left-hander who had been disappointing for three seasons in the major leagues, losing twice as many games as he won.</p>
        <p>But Rusch is only 25 years old and he realized that his chances with the Mets would come this year. So he journeyed to Venezuela to pitch last winter and paid to fly from his home in Seattle to New York to receive tutelage from the pitching coach Dave Wallace.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Glendon Rusch pitched one inning for the Mets after he was acquired from the Kansas City Royals last September, no chance for him to make any impression. Rusch was just another young left-hander who had been disappointing for three seasons in the major leagues, losing twice as many games as he won.</p>
        <p>But Rusch is only 25 years old and he realized that his chances with the Mets would come this year. So he journeyed to Venezuela to pitch last winter and paid to fly from his home in Seattle to New York to receive tutelage from the pitching coach Dave Wallace.</p>
        <p>Rusch developed an impressive changeup; he gained more confidence and the pitcher no one noticed has evolved into a superb starter.</p>
        <p>He was effective, not dominant, last night and Todd Zeile continued to dominate with a three-run homer that helped the Mets rumble by the Tampa Bay Devil Rays, 5-3, on the first night of interleague play at Shea Stadium.</p>
        <p>''I've had the confidence I could pitch at this level,'' Rusch said. ''There were tough times, but I'm still learning. I'll be learning until the last day I play this game.''</p>
        <p>Fred McGriff was gazing toward center field after his 400th career homer gave the Devil Rays a 3-2 lead in the sixth and Rusch was standing in front of the mound kicking at the dirt. But Zeile came back in the bottom of the sixth to put the Mets ahead with a homer to left center off Rick White. Zeile has four homers and 10 runs batted in over his last six games.</p>
        <p>''People always said Todd comes up big,'' Manager Bobby Valentine said. ''He came up big tonight. We needed that.''</p>
        <p>Zeile added: ''Rusch battled through the rain delay and kept us close. I'm glad I was able to help us.''</p>
        <p>Rusch had allowed two earned runs in six of his eight starts this season and had received only an average of two and a half runs of support a game.</p>
        <p>While Rusch yielded three earned runs in six innings, he pitched a gutsy game on a night the game was interrupted by rain for 1 hour 22 minutes and the Mets played without Mike Piazza. The Mets, who play 21 of their next 26 games in New York, have won 11 of 16.</p>
        <p>After winning his second straight start, Rusch, who has watched the Mets lose games he has started by scores of 2-0, 2-1, 3-0 and 1-0, moved to 3-4 with a 3.56 E.R.A.</p>
        <p>Rusch's E.R.A. is better than that of Mike Hampton, Al Leiter or Rick Reed. Pat Mahomes replaced Rusch in the seventh, created a bases-loaded jam and then retired Gerald Williams. Armando Benitez struck out Greg Vaughn with the potential tying runs on base in the ninth.</p>
        <p>Without Piazza, the reserve catcher Todd Pratt continued his Mark McGwire-like power pace by smashing a homer off Albie Lopez that gave the Mets a 2-1 lead in the fifth.</p>
        <p>Pratt has six homers in 58 at-bats, one every 9.7 at-bats, and, like someone who has been noticed, he was drilled with a pitch by White.</p>
        <p>When Pratt was asked about the Mets winning without Piazza, he said: ''Mike's not the whole team here. We got a bunch of millionaires. We've been doing it all year.''</p>
        <p>After the rain delay, Jay Payton homered on Lopez's second pitch in the third, his second in the last 46 games, to give the Mets a 1-0 lead. Williams led off the Tampa Bay fourth by doubling and scored on McGriff's single to make it 1-1.</p>
        <p>It had turned dark and windy and ugly at Shea very quickly as gusty winds whipped debris around the field like kernels bouncing in a popcorn machine.</p>
        <p>The skies turned from light gray to dark gray to black. Eventually, the rains vanished, play resumed and Rusch, Zeile and the Mets prevailed.</p>
        <p>''It was a good feeling,'' Rusch said.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
