<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Chipping Away at the Community of New York</title>
    <meta content="03FREE$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204315"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Privatization</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Health Insurance</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Empire Blue Cross &amp; Blue Shield</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Freeman, Joshua B (Prof)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Privatization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E0DA113CF930A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="525" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Chipping Away at the Community of New York</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Joshua B. Freeman</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Freeman, Joshua B (Prof)</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Joshua B Freeman Op-Ed article opposes conversion of Empire Blue Cross and Blue Shield from a nonprofit health insurer into a for-profit corporation; says its problems, which stem from both mismanagment and competition that picked off its healthiest customers, leaving the organization with the sickest, most expensive clients, can be addressed without privatization (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Few may have noticed, but last week saw another step in the dismantling of New York's pioneering social benefit system. Eliot Spitzer, the state attorney general, announced that he would no longer oppose converting Empire Blue Cross and Blue Shield to a for-profit corporation.</p>
        <p>Over the past decade, various government and nonprofit health, housing and cultural institutions have been turned into money-making entities outside of public control. Slowly, the city and state are giving away a civic patrimony that earlier generations of New Yorkers built with their money, imagination and political will.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Few may have noticed, but last week saw another step in the dismantling of New York's pioneering social benefit system. Eliot Spitzer, the state attorney general, announced that he would no longer oppose converting Empire Blue Cross and Blue Shield to a for-profit corporation.</p>
        <p>Over the past decade, various government and nonprofit health, housing and cultural institutions have been turned into money-making entities outside of public control. Slowly, the city and state are giving away a civic patrimony that earlier generations of New Yorkers built with their money, imagination and political will.</p>
        <p>In the 1930's, New York hospitals founded what became Empire Blue Cross to ensure themselves steady income while giving people a way to finance hospitalization. Individuals were the first subscribers, but the plan took off after it began signing up groups of workers. Unions, by demanding that employers provide coverage, helped fuel Blue Cross's meteoric growth after World War II.</p>
        <p>During the 1990's, some Blue Cross and Blue Shield plans in other states began turning themselves into for-profit companies. They argued that because of increased competition, they needed access to private capital and they needed to shed mandated responsibilities, like accepting all applicants or charging all customers the same fee. In some states, officials responded by allowing them to privatize but forcing them to finance nonprofit foundations, a route Empire Blue Cross is now trying to take.</p>
        <p>Empire Blue Cross has long been mired in problems, stemming from both mismanagement and competition that picked off its healthiest customers, leaving the organization with the sickest, most expensive clients. (Until recently, state regulations required Blue Cross to accept applicants that other plans could reject.)</p>
        <p>These problems are serious, but they can be addressed without privatization. For more than 60 years, Blue Cross has acted not for the benefit of stockholders, but for its customers. Isn't that model still important? A large nonprofit insurer provides a benchmark for private competitors and an alternative for coverage.</p>
        <p>The controversy over privatization is not unique. In 1996, debate raged over Co-op Village, a complex of cooperative apartments on the Lower East Side, which had originally been financed with government subsidies and union loans. After fierce debate, residents decided to abandon rules that required them, upon moving, to sell their shares back to the cooperative at the original price. Residents have profited from this plan, but the conversion has reduced opportunities for other working and middle-class families. In 1996, Mayor Rudolph Giuliani sold off the city's broadcast facilities. A public uproar forced the sale of WNYC radio to a nonprofit foundation, but the municipal television station went into private hands.</p>
        <p>Once public and quasi-public assets slip out of public control, it is almost impossible to retrieve or replace them. While privatizing any one might seem reasonable in the face of problems, the cumulative effect is to destroy a web of institutions that helped keep New York City livable and attractive during decades when many cities drastically declined. In good times, public services and safety nets do not seem so important. In bad times, it is too late to get them back.</p>
        <p>Joshua B. Freeman, a history professor at Queens College, is the author of ''Working-Class New York.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Joshua B. Freeman, a history professor at Queens College, is the author of ''Working-Class New York.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
