<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Yanks Play Their Best Against The Best</title>
    <meta content="03YANK$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204389"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Atlanta Braves</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olney, Buster</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Atlanta Braves</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807E3DA1E3CF930A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="996" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Yanks Play Their Best Against The Best</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olney, Buster</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTA, June 2</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Yankees defeat Atlanta Braves, 5-2, in interleague play; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Yankees have mastered their sport three of the last four years, and truth be told, the regular season bores the two-time defending World Series champions.</p>
        <p>A series in Detroit is like homework for them. What the Yankees love are the big tests, which is why they can flunk a pop quiz against the Oakland Athletics and then come back and stifle the Atlanta Braves.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Yankees have mastered their sport three of the last four years, and truth be told, the regular season bores the two-time defending World Series champions.</p>
        <p>A series in Detroit is like homework for them. What the Yankees love are the big tests, which is why they can flunk a pop quiz against the Oakland Athletics and then come back and stifle the Atlanta Braves.</p>
        <p>Maybe it's human nature to rise to challenges, David Cone said before Orlando Hernandez hushed the Atlanta bats tonight in a 5-2 victory.</p>
        <p>Ricky Ledee drove in all but one of the Yankee runs with an early three-run homer and a late double; Ledee has four runs batted in in each of his last two games. Mariano Rivera, the hero of the four-game sweep over Atlanta last October, registered the last four outs for his first save since May 8.</p>
        <p>The Yankees understand what big games are all about, know the difference between those and mundane May contests. After playing inconsistently for two months, they will be filled with adrenaline in the days ahead: Roger Clemens faces Atlanta's Greg Maddux on Saturday, the first duel of pitchers with nine Cy Young awards between them.</p>
        <p>After finishing a three-game series here Sunday against this year's best team, the Yankees play the Montreal Expos, the Mets, the Boston Red Sox and the Chicago White Sox at Yankee Stadium, then the White Sox and the Red Sox on the road.</p>
        <p>Seven straight series against teams with winning records. The Yankees rise to these challenges.</p>
        <p>''Sometimes you scratch your head and you wonder why,'' said Joe Torre, the Yankee manager. ''We play a team like the Braves and we go in and tend to business, and it's a mystery to me. I sure as heck would like us to be more consistent.''</p>
        <p>But Torre also appreciates the fact that his players embrace challenges. Hernandez (5-4) had something to prove.</p>
        <p>He had not won since April 23, had missed his last start with a strained muscle in his back, and yet El Duque pitched against the Braves the way he did last October, when he shut them down in the first game of the World Series.</p>
        <p>Hernandez got ahead in counts, threw mostly fastballs -- he had a little extra, the catcher Jorge Posada said, because he hadn't pitched in so long -- and mixed in breaking balls to keep the Atlanta hitters off balance.</p>
        <p>''He was very dominant,'' Torre said.</p>
        <p>Tino Martinez had something to prove. Torre made a point of chatting with the first baseman hours before the game in an attempt to soothe Martinez, who is on a pace to drive in 83 runs, woeful production for an American League first baseman in this era.</p>
        <p>Martinez frets when he is not hitting home runs, but Torre reminded Martinez that he was driving the ball to center and left-center when he was at his best.</p>
        <p>There was one out when Martinez batted in the fourth inning tonight, and with a 3-and-2 count, Kevin Millwood looked in for a sign from catcher Javy Lopez. Fastball inside, Lopez signaled, but Millwood did not want to throw that. Curveball inside, Lopez signaled. No, Millwood indicated.</p>
        <p>As Lopez gave another sign, Martinez stepped out, then stepped back in, and when Millwood finally agreed with Lopez and threw a fastball high and outside, Martinez smashed it against the center-field wall for a double.</p>
        <p>Posada reached a full count, as well, then ignored a changeup that was just a fraction high for ball four. That is what the Yankees do in big games, concentrate on each pitch. Ledee was next, and with two runners on base, Millwood did not want to dawdle. He wanted to pump a fastball past Ledee for a strike.</p>
        <p>Ledee hammered the fastball, lifting it high toward right field, where Brian Jordan slowly retreated, then  reached for the wall with his gloved left hand until he bumped into it. Jordan could go no farther. As soon as the ball landed in the seats, Clay Bellinger and then Jeter each lifted both hands in the Yankees' dugout.</p>
        <p>Ledee, who would lose his job if the Yankees traded for a slugger today, rounded the bases and smiled a bit as teammates congratulated him, but it wasn't until he returned to left field for the bottom of the fourth inning that he appeared to really relax.</p>
        <p>Warming up before the Braves batted, Ledee played catch with the relief pitcher Jason Grimsley, and when Grimsley began firing his nasty sinker and slider, Ledee laughed and waved a finger across his throat -- cut that out, please.</p>
        <p>Baseball was fun again for Ledee, who has something to prove.</p>
        <p>But all the Yankees seemed more intent, more focused, facing three weeks of big games, big challenges.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>NICK JOHNSON, one of the Yankees' top prospects, is probably about a week to 10 days away from taking full batting practice, and he could return to action late this month or in early July. Johnson who sprained his wrist in an exhibition game March 10 and has not played since, will play for Class AAA Columbus this year and is expected to get a chance to supplant TINO MARTINEZ as the Yankees' first baseman next season. . . . The Yankees are moving closer to completing the paperwork on the signing of the Cuban defector ADRIAN HERNANDEZ, and once the four-year deal is wrapped up, Hernandez is expected to pitch for Class A Tampa.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
