<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sprewell Muses About What Went Wrong</title>
    <meta content="03HOOP$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204390"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Indiana Pacers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Miami Heat</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Broussard, Chris</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sprewell, Latrell</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Indiana Pacers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Miami Heat</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E3DA1E3CF930A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="956" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sprewell Muses About What Went Wrong</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRIS BROUSSARD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Broussard, Chris</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Knickerbockers Latrell Sprewell reflects on his play and why Knicks were eliminated by Indiana Pacers in season-ending Game 6 of Eastern Conference Finals; attributes long series with Miami Heat to loss in Game 1 which set tone for remainder of series; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Injured foot and all, Latrell Sprewell had been carrying the Knicks all night. While his teammates appeared lifeless, lacking the pep that would seem to come automatically in a contest of such magnitude, Sprewell's game was in a stratosphere that only Reggie Miller could relate to.</p>
        <p>He had been dynamic in the first quarter, scoring 11 points to keep the Knicks from being left behind. Later, in the third, he scored 6 straight points to help erase Indiana's 9-point halftime advantage and sank a mid-range jumper to give the Knicks their biggest lead of the game with two minutes left in the quarter.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Injured foot and all, Latrell Sprewell had been carrying the Knicks all night. While his teammates appeared lifeless, lacking the pep that would seem to come automatically in a contest of such magnitude, Sprewell's game was in a stratosphere that only Reggie Miller could relate to.</p>
        <p>He had been dynamic in the first quarter, scoring 11 points to keep the Knicks from being left behind. Later, in the third, he scored 6 straight points to help erase Indiana's 9-point halftime advantage and sank a mid-range jumper to give the Knicks their biggest lead of the game with two minutes left in the quarter.</p>
        <p>Then, 20 seconds into what would become the final period of the Knicks' season, Sprewell buried a 3-pointer to break a tie and, for a moment, send the Madison Square Garden crowd into hysteria, giddy with thoughts of another great comeback.</p>
        <p>But then it stopped. As if there was room for only one burning hot swingman in the stratosphere, Sprewell fell from his peak and became mundane. But he didn't realize it, so he kept shooting. A 14-footer clanged off the rim. A 12-footer and a 13-footer became Pacer rebounds. His high was done, as were the Knicks.</p>
        <p>''I probably took some shots that I shouldn't have taken,'' Sprewell admitted after shooting 13 for 26 in the Knicks' 93-80 loss to the Indiana Pacers. ''But hey, as a player, you're going to go out and try and do what you can to win. And that was the only thing that was on my mind out there. There were two or three shots that if I could do it over I would've done different. After you miss a couple, you want to make sure that everybody else is getting involved too.''</p>
        <p>Sprewell, said his excessiveness speaks to the root of why the Knicks were eliminated, 4 games to 2, in the Eastern Conference finals. While he scored 32 points on a cracked bone in his left foot, his teammates shot a combined 18 for 48 (37.5 percent). Patrick Ewing was the only other Knick to have anything resembling a fine offensive game, scoring 18 points on 6-of-15 shooting. Allan Houston missed 10 of 15 shots in scoring just 10 points, and Larry Johnson, a postseason hero so many times, ended his season meekly with 7 points on 3-of-10 shooting. Sprewell said the Knicks' big scorers rarely played well together, unlike last season, when they won the conference title.</p>
        <p>''The difference in this team this year and last year is that it seems like in every game I could think of, it was at least myself and Allan or L.J. and Allan or me and L.J.,'' Sprewell said. ''We at least had two guys playing well and in most of the games in this series, minus Game 3, it seems like it was only one guy really carrying the team.</p>
        <p>''One night, it would be L.J. One night it would be Patrick or myself or Allan. It's hard to win that way.''</p>
        <p>While many observers will point to Game 5, when the Knicks blew an 18-point first-quarter lead, as the turning point of the series, Sprewell thinks that Game 2, when the Knicks were outscored by 6-0 in the final minute of an 88-84 loss, set a bad tone for the rest of the series.</p>
        <p>In that game, as well as the 102-88 Game 1 loss, Sprewell said the Knicks might have still been recovering from their tough seven-game series with Miami.</p>
        <p>''To be honest, I think the Miami series took a lot out of this team,'' Sprewell said. ''Going seven games with those guys was exhausting. It took us a game or two to switch gears and get ready for Indiana. That could've been the difference because playing that series with Miami was brutal.'' Sprewell thought that the Knicks should have double-teamed Miller, who made 5 of 7 3-pointers and scored 34 points (including 17 in the fourth quarter), more as soon as he caught the ball.</p>
        <p>''When a guy's going good like that, he's going to make shots like that no matter whether a guy's in his face or not,'' Sprewell said. ''Looking back, we probably could have doubled him on the catch more and forced other people to make plays. That's something we did last year and we didn't do that this year.''</p>
        <p>Sprewell, who had a similar game in last year's finale, scoring 35 points in the Game 5 championship series loss to the San Antonio Spurs, said last year's pain was harder to take.</p>
        <p>''That was more disappointing because you're so much closer to ultimately winning it all,'' he said.</p>
        <p>While reflecting on this season over the summer, Sprewell said he will not have surgery to repair the incomplete fracture of the fifth metatarsal in his left foot. He said that rest is all the foot will need to heel.</p>
        <p>Sprewell also realizes that changes might be in store for the Knicks, even though he said he thinks that they are good enough to win a championship as composed.</p>
        <p>''My job is to come here and play with the players that are here, whether there are no changes or a lot of changes,'' Sprewell said. ''Hopefully, I'll be here. If not, that's something that I can't control.''</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
