<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Population Shifts in the Southeast Realign Politics in the Suburbs</title>
    <meta content="03SUBU" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204343"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE ELECTORATE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suburbs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Population Shifts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Southeastern States (US)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Georgia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Atlanta (Ga)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Firestone, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Georgia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Georgia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Georgia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Georgia/Atlanta</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suburbs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Population</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E4D7113CF930A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2048" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Population Shifts in the Southeast Realign Politics in the Suburbs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID FIRESTONE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Firestone, David</byline>
      <dateline>SMYRNA, Ga., June 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Political shift to the left is under way in suburbs of Atlanta and other cities in Southeast as a result of influx of millions of people from other parts of the country who are far less conservative than longtime residents; suburbs once dominated by religious conservatives are increasingly home to moderate Republicans, and moderate Republican districts are teetering on the edge of a Democratic reascendancy; issues like lower taxes, welfare reform and crackdown on crime give way to new agenda: managing growth and transportation, bringing in technology jobs and, above all, improving education; photos; map; table (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When he was swept into the Georgia House of Representatives in 1994 at the crest of the Republican revolution, Randy J. Sauder seemed to personify Cobb County's reputation as one of the most conservative suburbs in the country.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sauder was in favor of mandatory execution for twice-convicted murderers, abolishing the state parole board and barring Atlanta's public transportation system from the county. He became an ally of fellow Cobb County resident Newt Gingrich, and a national Republican organization voted him the top freshman state legislator in the country.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When he was swept into the Georgia House of Representatives in 1994 at the crest of the Republican revolution, Randy J. Sauder seemed to personify Cobb County's reputation as one of the most conservative suburbs in the country.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sauder was in favor of mandatory execution for twice-convicted murderers, abolishing the state parole board and barring Atlanta's public transportation system from the county. He became an ally of fellow Cobb County resident Newt Gingrich, and a national Republican organization voted him the top freshman state legislator in the country.</p>
        <p>But last month, Mr. Sauder infuriated the Republican Party in Georgia with an audacious heresy. As he saw the future of his district, he became a Democrat.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sauder's conversion says much about the population changes that are transforming the suburbs of Atlanta and other cities in the Southeast, rearranging the political order along with the priorities of state leaders. Nearly 2.5 million Americans moved to the Southern states along the Atlantic Coast during the 1990's, by far the largest growth of any region in the country, and they have proven to be far less conservative than longtime residents.</p>
        <p>Suburbs once dominated by religious conservatives are increasingly home to moderate Republicans, and moderate Republican districts are teetering on the edge of Democratic reascendancy. As officials of both parties have begun to move away from divisive racial and social issues and toward the center, the effect on public policy has been dramatic.</p>
        <p>In state after state, conservative social issues that once monopolized the conversation of Southern suburbs -- lower taxes, welfare reform, crackdowns on crime -- have been supplanted by a new agenda: managing growth and transportation, bringing in technology jobs and above all, improving education. In a swath of states from the Carolinas to Mississippi, Democratic governors have made these issues their own, and Republicans are struggling to keep up.</p>
        <p>''My district has changed so dramatically since I was first elected,'' Mr. Sauder said recently, over biscuits at a Shoney's restaurant near his house. ''The people moving in want to see action on issues like education and sprawl, and it's the Democrats that have grabbed those themes and delivered. The Republicans around here are seen as bickering and obstructionist.''</p>
        <p>Even a matter as racially charged as the Confederate battle flag on the South Carolina Capitol, which comes down on July 1, has largely been resolved, mostly at the request of suburban voters who made it clear they had other priorities.</p>
        <p>At the same time as centrist Northerners, mostly white, moved South, an inner ring of Southern suburbs that were once nearly all white have become more diverse, attracting large and stable populations of black, Hispanic and Asian residents who do not as a rule support a conservative political agenda.</p>
        <p>In Cobb County, where blacks once had to sue to rent apartments, the number of black residents has grown fivefold since 1980, rising to 12 percent of the county's population from 4 percent 20 years ago, according to the Census Bureau and the county. There has been a similar shift in other Atlanta suburbs, like Clayton and Gwinnett Counties, along with suburbs of Charlotte and Raleigh-Durham in North Carolina and Columbia in South Carolina.</p>
        <p>The population shifts, driven by the South's quickening economy and the prosperity of a mobile middle class, do not necessarily presage a partisan realignment like the mass movement of white Southern Democrats to the Republican Party in the 1980's and 1990's. Nor are they necessarily good news for Vice President Al Gore's presidential campaign.</p>
        <p>Although two state legislators have switched to the Democratic Party in South Carolina, and more could do so in Georgia, the pendulum swing is more ideological than political. Its most lasting effect may be a race by officials of both parties to the center, mostly at the state level.</p>
        <p>In North Carolina, the explosion of new residents in the 1990's has actually produced a new breed of Republican in a state dominated for decades by Democrats and religious conservatives. They seem to be precisely the kind of voters singled out by the campaign of Gov. George W. Bush of Texas.</p>
        <p>''As North Carolina has filled up with cul-de-sacs, we have become simultaneously more Republican and far less conservative,'' said John N. Davis, executive director of the North Carolina Forum for Research and Economic Education, a nonprofit, research group supported by business that surveys newcomers.</p>
        <p>''These are pro-government Republicans, who want the best soccer fields, schools and police departments that government money can buy,'' Mr. Davis said. ''And suddenly you see formerly conservative candidates for office pushing education and environment programs that they would have tried to cut 10 years ago.''</p>
        <p>He said that many of the newcomers come from the Northeast where it is common to be Republican and moderate or Republican and left-of-center, a combination rare in the South.</p>
        <p>Native Southerners, whether Democratic or Republican, identify themselves as conservative far more often than newcomers in his organization's polls, he said. A similar survey by the University of North Carolina last year showed that 34 percent of non-native Southerners considered themselves conservative, compared with 42 percent of native Southerners.</p>
        <p>Newcomers are prodding elected officials to be more aggressive about spending tax money on their priorities. In the last three years, residents in 19 out of 20 counties in the Atlanta area have voted to raise their sales taxes to pay for schools and other projects, often by overwhelming margins.</p>
        <p>In Cobb County, where voters raised the sales tax in 1998 for new schools, the county commission has proposed a tax increase to buy parkland, and commissioners say they believe that residents will support the measure.</p>
        <p>Gwinnett County, a northeast Atlanta suburb that has been a developer's paradise, recently imposed a seven-month moratorium on rezonings. (The move is mostly symbolic, but coincides neatly with the re-election campaigns of most of the county commissioners.) Suburban politicians make it clear that in both substance and style, they are following a mellower electorate.</p>
        <p>''My district is still a conservative place, but the social issues of the 90's are not the fundamental foundation of people's politics anymore,'' said Representative Johnny Isakson, a Republican who replaced Mr. Gingrich in Georgia's Sixth Congressional District and whose easygoing moderation bears no resemblance to his predecessor's partisan fire.</p>
        <p>''We've taken care of matters like a balanced budget and welfare reform,'' Mr. Isakson said, ''and now people are more concerned about quality-of-life issues, education and transportation.''</p>
        <p>But just as Bill Clinton made an art out of appropriating Republican themes, Democratic governors in the Southeast have edged aside Republicans in seizing the issues at the top of suburban agendas.</p>
        <p>Republicans who have opposed Democratic initiatives to raise teacher salaries and hold schools accountable with testing regimens are gleefully painted as obstructionist, and the effects are visible. Both legislators in South Carolina who switched to the Democratic Party complained that Republican leaders tried to force them to vote against education programs that their constituents supported.</p>
        <p>Many Republicans insisted that the party switching did not represent a trend, and that deeply conservative values still prevailed in the South. Q. Whitfield Ayres, a Republican pollster in Atlanta, said the increased emphasis on quality-of-life issues was the result of an improved economy, not a political shift. But other Republicans said their party had fallen behind in the race to capture newcomers with unpledged loyalties.</p>
        <p>''This transformation is going on around the South, and the Republican leadership just does not get it,'' said Matt Towery, a Republican and former state representative from Cobb County who was Mr. Gingrich's campaign chairman for many years. ''They're still talking about tax cuts, but the Democrats now have the issues that appeal to presidential-year voters, the environment, gun safety. You can't win these counties as a gun-toting, anti-abortion Republican anymore.''</p>
        <p>But partisanship still prevails. All but 1 of the 16 Republican state legislators from Gwinnett County voted against the overhaul of Georgia's education system by Gov. Roy E. Barnes, a Democrat, which passed nonetheless. The law mandates many of the ideas that Republicans have championed: smaller class sizes, an end to teacher tenure and strict accountability of each school, as measured by comprehensive tests.</p>
        <p>When he signed the bill, Mr. Barnes deliberately chose a school in the district of the one Gwinnett Republican who had supported him.</p>
        <p>Mr. Barnes, in fact, has been one of the South's shrewdest observers of these demographic trends, assembling an agenda with pitch-perfect resonance for suburban voters -- the education bill, a powerful new transportation and planning authority, a managed-care bill of rights -- while also retaining his popularity among urban and rural residents.</p>
        <p>He has worked to strengthen the Democratic majority in the Georgia Legislature in anticipation of the redistricting that will follow this year's census, singling out districts like Mr. Sauder's in Smyrna. (If he had not switched parties, Mr. Sauder acknowledges, he would eventually have faced a Democratic opponent with the governor's strong backing.)</p>
        <p>Bobby Kahn, the governor's chief of staff and principal political strategist, said the population shifts in Georgia had been of significant benefit to the Democrats, and could make a difference in Mr. Gore's favor this November, although the state is considered a tossup.</p>
        <p>''The outer ring of suburbs are still very Republican,'' Mr. Kahn said, ''but some of the counties on the inner ring that had gone Republican are clearly trending back to the Democrats. I think Gore could do better in the suburbs than people expect, particularly with women. In a close state, you make an impact at the margin, and the suburbs are the margin now.''</p>
        <p>One of those swing districts is likely to be in Smyrna and south Cobb County, home to both Mr. Sauder and, before he moved to the governor's mansion, to Mr. Barnes. The district has become one of the fastest-growing integrated regions in Georgia, a leading destination for middle- and upper-middle-class white and black families buying homes in the $200,000 range and above. Mr. Kahn said the governor's hometown, Mableton, just southwest of Smyrna, is now about equally black and white.</p>
        <p>The welcome mat for black home buyers represents quite a turnaround for Smyrna. As recently as 1988, a restaurant with a slavery theme, Aunt Fanny's Cabin, could be found in Smyrna. But the restaurant closed in 1994, the city replaced its  decaying downtown with a landscaped civic center and professionals caught in rush hour began to appreciate Smyrna's easy access to downtown Atlanta.</p>
        <p>Keith De Cay, one of many black homeowners who recently bought a house in the affluent Austin Lake section of Smyrna, said he was impressed by the city's friendliness, selecting it after a transfer from New Orleans based on the number of residents who offered to give him directions when he pretended to be lost.</p>
        <p>''I'm a lifelong Democrat, and I had heard this was a very Republican area, so I didn't know what to expect,'' said Mr. De Cay, an executive with the Dataradio Corporation, which makes wireless modems. ''But I just haven't found that old-guard kind of politics here. They're building schools and community centers and parks, and that's what I want to see my elected officials do.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE ELECTORATE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
