<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Man Admits Making Illegal Campaign Gifts</title>
    <meta content="03FUND" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204316"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcfadden, Robert D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Torricelli, Robert G (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wolin, Alfred M (Judge)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chang, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E0DA113CF930A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="931" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Man Admits Making Illegal Campaign Gifts</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT D. McFADDEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mcfadden, Robert D</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>David Chang of Creskill, NJ, pleads guilty to five misdemeanor election-law violations before Judge Alfred M Wolin in US District Court in Newark; Chang is charged with illegally channeling $53,700 into 1996 campaign of Senator Robert G Torricelli by making contributions that exceeded individual limits, by making illegal corporate donations and by making clandestine contributions in others' names; Senator Torricelli has not been accused of wrongdoing and says he was unaware of improper contributions which have since been donated to charity (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A New Jersey political donor with mysterious sources of income and connections that reached into the White House and both political parties pleaded guilty in federal court in Newark yesterday to charges of illegally channeling $53,700 into the 1996 campaign of Senator Robert G. Torricelli.</p>
        <p>The donor, David Chang, 57, of Cresskill, N.J., pleaded guilty to five misdemeanor election-law violations by making contributions to the campaign that exceeded individual limits, by making illegal corporate donations and by making clandestine contributions in others' names.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A New Jersey political donor with mysterious sources of income and connections that reached into the White House and both political parties pleaded guilty in federal court in Newark yesterday to charges of illegally channeling $53,700 into the 1996 campaign of Senator Robert G. Torricelli.</p>
        <p>The donor, David Chang, 57, of Cresskill, N.J., pleaded guilty to five misdemeanor election-law violations by making contributions to the campaign that exceeded individual limits, by making illegal corporate donations and by making clandestine contributions in others' names.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chang, who was raised in South Korea and served on the Torricelli campaign's finance committee, also pleaded guilty to one felony count of obstructing justice by trying to persuade a potential witness to lie to a grand jury investigating accusations of campaign financing laws in the 1996 elections.</p>
        <p>Appearing before Judge Alfred M. Wolin four days before he was to go on trial on election-law, tax, perjury and other charges that could have sent him to prison for decades, Mr. Chang, as a condition of his plea, also agreed to cooperate with the Justice Department's investigation of campaign skulduggery. While he could be sentenced to 15 years in prison and fined up to $250,000 under federal sentencing guidelines, prosecutors said he might draw as little as two years behind bars if he provides ''substantial cooperation.''</p>
        <p>The guilty plea came one day after a Korean-born businessman, Cha-Kuek Koo, pleaded guilty in federal court in Newark to federal election-law violations by making illegal contributions to the Torricelli campaign and by aiding Mr. Chang in making secret contributions in the name of other people.</p>
        <p>Mr. Torricelli, a Democrat, has not been accused of any wrongdoing. While he has called Mr. Chang a friend, the senator has insisted that he was unaware of the improper contributions to his campaign, which have since been donated to charities. Among 25 people accused of election-law abuses by a Justice Department task force, Mr. Chang and 5 others from New Jersey have admitted wrongdoing, but none of them have implicated the senator.</p>
        <p>Mr. Torricelli, whose fund-raising skill led to his appointment as chairman of the Democratic Senatorial Campaign Committee, raised $9.2 million to defeat Representative Richard A. Zimmer in the 1996 Senate race. The senator did not comment yesterday on Mr. Chang's plea.</p>
        <p>Abbe David Lowell, a lawyer for Mr. Torricelli, noted that the Justice Department ''has confirmed that neither the senator nor anyone in the campaign are the focus of any investigation.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Chang made no statement after entering his plea. He remains under house arrest, pending a bail hearing on Monday. His lawyer, David Schertler, told The Associated Press that he would not comment on what other information Mr. Chang might provide the task force.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chang, who was born in Beijing, China, and raised in South Korea where his family moved when he was a boy, attended the University of London, worked in the oil business in the Middle East, came to New York in the early 1980's and has become a naturalized American citizen.</p>
        <p>Although he operates commodities trading and export businesses in Bergen County, they have never posted a profit, investigators say, and his only known sources of appreciable income have been wire transfers from unknown sources in Korea.</p>
        <p>Yet he lives in a $1.25 million home, drives a Rolls-Royce, has run up huge business debts and gambling losses, and has given nearly $300,000 to American election campaigns since 1993 -- $240,000 to Democrats and more than $50,000 to Republicans, according to investigators and election records.</p>
        <p>As one of the nation's most prolific campaign donors, he has had dinner at the White House, private discussions over pizza with President Clinton, a ride on Air Force One and personal references from President George Bush. He also has a history of prior campaign violations, including illegal contributions in 1992 to a California representative, Jay Kim, who later pleaded guilty to accepting $133,000 in donations from Korean corporations.</p>
        <p>Federal laws prohibit political donations by corporations and individual contributions exceeding $2,000 to a candidate during an election cycle. They also bar secret reimbursements to so-called ''straw donors'' -- a way of hiding political contributions by the person making the reimbursement.</p>
        <p>Both Mr. Chang and Mr. Koo admitted making such contributions. Mr. Chang, in his plea, acknowledged that he had reimbursed Berek Paul Don, a former Bergen County Republican leader, and Mr. Don's former law partner, Carmine Alampi, for $11,000 they had contributed to Mr. Torricelli's campaign in their own names. Mr. Don and Mr. Alampi pleaded guilty last year to related charges.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chang admitted that, as a member of Mr. Torricelli's campaign committee, he had collected $21,000 from donors and had illegally reimbursed them with money from one of his corporations, Bright &amp; Bright, based in Englewood Cliffs.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chang said he also used $1,700 from the same corporation to pay for flights for the Torricelli campaign -- an allegation Mr. Torricelli's aides have denied, saying that Bright &amp; Bright was reimbursed for all flights it paid for. Mr. Chang also admitted that he gave Mr. Koo $20,000 to reimburse other donors.</p>
        <p>While prosecutors agreed to drop other charges in the latest of several indictments, they noted in court papers that they anticipated filing additional charges against Mr. Chang ''with respect to payments made to a certain former government employee.'' They declined to provide details.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
