<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Great Big Engine That Simply Couldn't</title>
    <meta content="03KNIC$12" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204392"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Indiana Pacers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Roberts, Selena</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Indiana Pacers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE3DA1E3CF930A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1325" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Great Big Engine That Simply Couldn't</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SELENA ROBERTS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Roberts, Selena</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Indiana Pacers defeat New York Knickerbockers, 93-80, in Eastern Conference Finals; win series 4-2; photo; diagram (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The exits at Madison Square Garden were beginning to fill like evacuation routes as Reggie Miller stood at the edge of the Knicks' glossy logo and dribbled down the fleeting seconds on the clock. A hunched and weary Patrick Ewing was on his way out as well.</p>
        <p>He waited at the edge of the tunnel to the locker room, waved a hand in Miller's direction at the buzzer and then disappeared like a bear in a cave as he slipped through a canopy of fans. One hoarse-voiced heckler squeezed one barb in as he left: ''Don't come back, Ewing.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The exits at Madison Square Garden were beginning to fill like evacuation routes as Reggie Miller stood at the edge of the Knicks' glossy logo and dribbled down the fleeting seconds on the clock. A hunched and weary Patrick Ewing was on his way out as well.</p>
        <p>He waited at the edge of the tunnel to the locker room, waved a hand in Miller's direction at the buzzer and then disappeared like a bear in a cave as he slipped through a canopy of fans. One hoarse-voiced heckler squeezed one barb in as he left: ''Don't come back, Ewing.''</p>
        <p>There was no graceful way out for Ewing last night. There was only the helplessness of watching Miller whip his tinsel-tough body around screens, shake a variety of defenders with his step-back shots and pump fakes. On the perimeter, right in front of Spike Lee, Miller had undone Ewing's hopes for a title one more time.</p>
        <p>This time, it seemed harder to absorb. A year after the depleted and desperate Knicks summoned a star-aligned journey through Miller's Indiana Pacers and into the National Basketball Association finals with Ewing in a boot cast, they were unceremoniously eliminated last night in Game 6, 93-80, and lost the Eastern Conference finals, four games to two.</p>
        <p>There was so much behind this surprising collapse: Latrell Sprewell's panicked one-on-one forays, Allan Houston's untimely disappearance, Larry Johnson's inability to put his wounded body on Dale Davis (who had 16 rebounds), the Knicks' failure to decode Miller's 34-point performance. There was a lack of poise as Miller scored 17 fourth-quarter points while the Knicks managed just 18. There was a lack of the mental edge the Pacers had while the Knicks groped for the same inspiration that fed them last year.</p>
        <p>But ultimately, every Knick misery is traced back to Ewing. In each loss of the series, Ewing was the common thread. In each victory, he was out with an injury.</p>
        <p>''I feel for Patrick,'' said Sprewell, who scored 32 points but ended up taking 15 of the Knicks' 35 second-half shots. ''No one guy was at fault. But I know a lot will be made of how we won without him and how we lost with him. So I feel bad for him. I really do.''</p>
        <p>It was an inglorious end for Ewing. He scored 18 points and pulled down 12 rebounds but missed all four of his fadeaway jumpers in the fourth quarter. By the time Coach Jeff Van Gundy spared his wobbly body with 1 minute 42 seconds remaining, he looked like a shipwreck victim.</p>
        <p>''My leg, you know, my leg got a little tired, but by no means is that an excuse,'' said Ewing, who missed Games 3 and 4 with peroneal tendinitis in his right foot. ''It's just disappointing because of all the hard work we put in, all the frustration we got past and the pain that we overcame. You know, I feel that we're a better team than we showed. Nothing against them, but it's just hard.''</p>
        <p>His crestfallen moment was Miller's heaven. After all these years of waiting behind Michael Jordan -- just like Ewing -- he was going to the finals. Miller didn't leave miracles, or 4-point plays, to chance. When the Knicks took a 65-62 lead, he came back with a step-back 3-pointer over Chris Childs. When the Knicks closed to within 72-68, Miller pump-faked Sprewell and nailed another 3-pointer. He devastated every defender, from Houston to Charlie Ward.</p>
        <p>''I told the guys before the game, if the league called you up and said you guys have a chance to go to the finals, but you have to win one game and we will let you pick the venue, where would you want to play?'' said Miller, who hit 3 of 3 from 3-point range in the fourth and added a perfect 8-of-8 free throws. ''Everyone said the Garden. And who do you want to play? Of course, New York. This is our home away from home.''</p>
        <p>It wasn't last year. This was the place the Knicks leaned on Houston and Sprewell and Marcus Camby to capture lightning in a bottle, eliminate the Pacers and advance to the finals.</p>
        <p>The Knicks could not re-create the same magical atmosphere. They could not muster the same kind of percolating energy that propelled them last year when Ewing was injured. Unlike last year, Houston vanished and Camby never surfaced. Perhaps it was Sprewell's constant embrace of the ball, but Houston never found his groove with so few touches in the second half. Maybe it was his knee injury, but Camby never got off the ground. Houston scored just 10 points and Camby grabbed just 6 rebounds and did not score.</p>
        <p>More than Houston's inability to score, Camby's inability to soar devastated the Knicks. If there was any constant culprit against the Knicks -- even more than Miller -- it was rebounding. The Pacers ended the night with a 42-34 edge. That, more than anything, was a sign of how much the Pacers wanted this game.</p>
        <p>That was the little extra something that was missing in the Knicks. Are they more motivated without Ewing? Do they need to be the underdogs to thrive?</p>
        <p>''Last year, we did it the right way,'' said Houston, who seemed worn down by his futile chase of Miller and scored just 4 points after the first quarter. ''We won on the road, and won early. Tonight, waiting around until the last minute to pull off a series caught up to us. I don't know. Maybe we just thought it was going to happen to us because it's happened for us so many times before.''</p>
        <p>They thought they could snap their fingers or discover a four-leaf clover. They had always done that before.</p>
        <p>''I'm disappointed,'' said Sprewell, who also admitted to taking a series of rushed and awkward shots down the stretch. ''We never really played together well. We didn't get it together like we did last year. In that way, it wasn't the same.''</p>
        <p>Miller made sure of that. Someone thought they saw Miller a little misty-eyed afterward.</p>
        <p>''Reggie did what he had to do,'' Houston said. ''And we didn't. I know I didn't. In a way, even in the Miami series, we were hanging by a thread. We never gave ourselves any cushion. We made the last two series an uphill battle by falling behind, 3-2. I thought we had plenty of ammunition to do it this year. Last year was special because of everything we went through to do what we did. This year, I'll leave with no special thoughts. It's disappointing.''</p>
        <p>No one was more dispirited than Ewing. At the end of the night, as the last one to put on his suit, he threw his things in a garbage bag and made his exit. ''That's it,'' he told one ball boy as he left. ''Guess that's it.''</p>
        <p>REBOUNDS</p>
        <p>The Pacers will play for an N.B.A. title for the first time. They won American Basketball Association titles in 1970, '72 and '73. . . . JEFF VAN GUNDY has 35 career playoff victories, tying PAT RILEY for second place among Knick coaches. RED HOLZMAN is the leader, with 54.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
