<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>MAY'S LABOR DATA INDICATE ECONOMY COULD BE SLOWING</title>
    <meta content="03ECON$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000606T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204381"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Unemployment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hispanic-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Reserve System</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Uchitelle, Louis</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hispanic-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Unemployment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E6DA1E3CF930A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1289" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>MAY'S LABOR DATA INDICATE ECONOMY COULD BE SLOWING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LOUIS UCHITELLE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Uchitelle, Louis</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Nation's private-sector employers cut 116,000 jobs in May, the largest drop in more than eight years and the first since the economy began to soar in mid-1990's; unemployment rate edges up to 4.1 percent from 3.9 percent, with blacks and Hispanics absorbing most of the loss; job report comes on heels of a half-dozen other indications that a still very strong economy is beginning to cool off after six interest rate increases over the last year; Wall Street investors push up stocks across the board in anticipation that Fed will limit future rate increases; graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the strongest signal yet that the booming American economy is slowing, the Labor Department reported yesterday that the nation's private-sector employers, instead of hiring, shed 116,000 jobs in May. It was the largest drop in more than eight years and the first since the economy began to soar in the mid-1990's.</p>
        <p>The unemployment rate edged up to 4.1 percent from 3.9 percent, with blacks and Hispanics absorbing most of the loss. Wage increases, which had accelerated in the early spring, eased in May, reducing concerns about inflation. Jobs disappeared in almost every sector of the economy, except government, where the hiring of 357,000 census takers for the once-a-decade population count offset the decline in business jobs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the strongest signal yet that the booming American economy is slowing, the Labor Department reported yesterday that the nation's private-sector employers, instead of hiring, shed 116,000 jobs in May. It was the largest drop in more than eight years and the first since the economy began to soar in the mid-1990's.</p>
        <p>The unemployment rate edged up to 4.1 percent from 3.9 percent, with blacks and Hispanics absorbing most of the loss. Wage increases, which had accelerated in the early spring, eased in May, reducing concerns about inflation. Jobs disappeared in almost every sector of the economy, except government, where the hiring of 357,000 census takers for the once-a-decade population count offset the decline in business jobs.</p>
        <p>The jobs report came on the heels of a half-dozen other indications this week that a still very strong economy is beginning to cool off, responding to the Federal Reserve's six interest rate increases over the last year. Car sales and home sales have dipped recently, partly because of higher car loan and mortgage rates. Construction spending is off, and manufacturing production appears to have weakened in May.</p>
        <p>''We clearly have evidence now that the economy is slowing,'' said Jerry Jasinowski, president of the National Association of Manufacturers. ''The question is how much.''</p>
        <p>On Wall Street, investors pushed up stocks across the board yesterday -- as they have for much of the week -- in the belief that the accumulating evidence of a slowing economy would encourage the Federal Reserve to limit future rate increases aimed at keeping the inflation rate from rising.</p>
        <p>The Nasdaq index registered its largest weekly percentage gain in history and the Dow Jones industrial average had one of its best weekly performances this year. The Dow closed above 10,794 yesterday, up more than 142 points. The Nasdaq closed at 3,813, up more than 230 points.</p>
        <p>But the May employment report may overstate labor force weakness, some economists said, and may be encouraging too much euphoria.</p>
        <p>Until this week, Wall Street forecasters had expected another rate increase at the Fed's meeting in late June. That expectation had helped to damp stock prices, and had led many economists to predict that the robust consumer spending fostered by the so-called ''wealth effect'' of a rising stock market would begin to moderate, weakening the economy.</p>
        <p>But Wall Street's exuberance now creates a quandary for the Fed. ''The economy is probably slowing, but the markets are so excited about it that higher stock prices are already increasing the odds of a speed-up in the economy this summer,'' said John Makin, an economist at the American Enterprise Institute. A revived wealth effect, he and other economists argued, could swamp the Fed's efforts to slow the economy, or convince the policy makers to keep raising rates.</p>
        <p>''The irony is that when people believe the economy is slowing, the markets behave in a way that encourages people to spend more,'' Mr. Makin said.</p>
        <p>Not surprisingly, the Fed's policy makers, starting with Alan Greenspan, the chairman, have made no reference in recent speeches to the state of the economy -- one concern being that if they were to observe that the economy might be slowing, stock prices could really take off.</p>
        <p>The Clinton administration argued that the latest figures were nothing to worry about. ''The economy took a breather in May,'' said Alexis Herman, the labor secretary, ''but it remains robust.''</p>
        <p>Some economists lowered their forecasts yesterday for economic growth in the second quarter, which ends on June 30. For example, Macroeconomic Advisers, a consulting firm in St. Louis, predicted that growth would be closer to 3 percent than the 4.5 percent originally forecast.</p>
        <p>But the May report may have overstated the job losses. Just as the March and April reports seemed to exaggerate job growth, they said, the May numbers seemed unrealistically low. Indeed, job growth in the private sector averaged 182,000 a month from January through May, almost in line with last year's average of 202,000 jobs a month.</p>
        <p>Count all the census takers hired in May and jobs actually rose by 231,000, the Labor Department reported. But without them, the drop of 116,000 jobs in the private sector was the first loss since January 1996, when 61,000 jobs disappeared, and the largest since November 1991, when the work force shrank by 129,000 jobs as the nation emerged from its last recession.</p>
        <p>May was the last month in which census takers were hired in huge numbers; the estimate for June is only 11,000. Still, some economists argued that if the census takers had not gone to work for the government, at $8 to $18 an hour, many would have found employment in the private sector, swelling the rolls.</p>
        <p>''The private-sector employment numbers are definitely'' an anomaly, said Chris Varvares, a partner at Macroeconomic Advisers.</p>
        <p>Still, the cutbacks were widespread. Reversing course, 29,000 jobs disappeared in construction, 71,000 in wholesale and retail trade, 17,000 in manufacturing, and 11,000 in transportation, mostly trucking.</p>
        <p>''Jobs even fell for college graduates,'' said Lawrence Mishel, research director at the Economic Policy Institute.</p>
        <p>Labor Department statisticians offered various reasons for much of the drop, particularly for construction and retailing. Warm winter weather, for example, swelled construction rolls in April, so employers did not need to hire in May. Retailing exhibited a similar pattern.</p>
        <p>The wage and hours numbers were less equivocal. Average hourly earnings, covering 80 million production employees in a work force of 131.7 million in May, rose only a cent, to $13.65, the smallest increase in months. This number is the first on wage trends each month, and with the slight May increase, wage growth over the previous 12 months fell to 3.5 percent from 3.8 percent in April.</p>
        <p>The slight rise in joblessness hit hardest at blacks, whose unemployment rate rose to 8 percent from 7.2 percent. That was still well below the peak for the 1990's of 14.2 percent in June 1992. Hispanics, whose rate edged up to 5.8 percent from 5.4 percent, remained far from their peak of 12.1 percent, also in June 1992. By comparison, the unemployment rate for white adults remained at 3.5 percent.</p>
        <p>The pool of people available to take jobs -- those either actively seeking jobs or willing to work if a job came their way -- rose to 10.2 million from 9.9 million in April.</p>
        <p>The Labor Department's job numbers come from a monthly survey of 400,000 businesses. An annual revision, announced yesterday, resulted in small changes in earlier months, most of them upward.</p>
        <p>The unemployment rate, on the other hand, comes from a separate survey of 50,000 households. It also produces an estimate of the total work force, one considered less accurate. In May, according to the household survey, 991,000 jobs disappeared, the largest one-month drop since the survey began in 1948. To the Labor Department, that outsized decline reflected problems in the way the results are adjusted to account for seasonal variations.</p>
        <p>Whatever the statistical quirks, the new signals of a slowing economy suggested to William Dudley, director of domestic research at Goldman, Sachs, that ''it is going to be hard for the Fed to justify raising rates at the June meeting.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 6, 2000, Tuesday  A front-page article on Saturday about the Labor Department's employment report for May misstated the period for a forecast of economic growth made by Macroeconomic Advisers, a consulting firm in St. Louis. In predicting growth closer to 3 percent than to the 4.5 percent originally forecast, it referred to the second half of the year, not the second quarter.</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 10, 2000, Saturday  A front-page article last Saturday  about the Labor Department's employment report for May misstated the period for a forecast of economic growth made by Macroeconomic Advisers, a consulting firm in St. Louis, and misstated the recency of the forecast. And a correction in this space on Tuesday omitted a clarification of the recency. The firm predicted a decline in growth from 4.5 percent in the second quarter to around 3 percent in the second half of the year, not the second quarter. The forecast was the firm's existing one -- not revised as a result of May's employment data.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 6, 2000, Tuesday</p>
        <p>A front-page article on Saturday about the Labor Department's employment report for May misstated the period for a forecast of economic growth made by Macroeconomic Advisers, a consulting firm in St. Louis. In predicting growth closer to 3 percent than to the 4.5 percent originally forecast, it referred to the second half of the year, not the second quarter.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>Correction: June 10, 2000, Saturday</p>
        <p>A front-page article last Saturday  about the Labor Department's employment report for May misstated the period for a forecast of economic growth made by Macroeconomic Advisers, a consulting firm in St. Louis, and misstated the recency of the forecast. And a correction in this space on Tuesday omitted a clarification of the recency. The firm predicted a decline in growth from 4.5 percent in the second quarter to around 3 percent in the second half of the year, not the second quarter. The forecast was the firm's existing one -- not revised as a result of May's employment data.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
