<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>If Not Quite a 'New Rudy,' Baby Steps Toward Change</title>
    <meta content="03MAYO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204318"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hevesi, Alan G (Comptroller)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Green, Mark (Public Advocate)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fields, C Virginia (Boro Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bumiller, Elisabeth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907EEDA113CF930A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1206" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>If Not Quite a 'New Rudy,' Baby Steps Toward Change</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELISABETH BUMILLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bumiller, Elisabeth</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mayor Rudolph W Giuliani makes overtures to longtime antagonists, including Mark Green, public advocate, Comptroller Alan G Hevesi and C Virginia Fields, Manhattan borough president, apparently trying to become a better person and a better mayor; the 'new Rudy' has not fully arrived, however, for he has yet to approach New York's black leaders; Giuliani appears engaged and energetic as he sorts out his cancer treatment options and messy marital life, and he clearly does not miss Senate race (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The other day, something extraordinary happened at City Hall: the city's two top elected officials had a conversation with each other.</p>
        <p>To be specific, Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani had a private, cordial meeting with his longtime tormentor, Mark Green, the public advocate. At a bill-signing ceremony the same day, the mayor even patted Mr. Green on the shoulder and whispered in his ear, ''Good job, good job.'' Mr. Green, who has been a frequent target of the mayor's ire, said afterward that his new relationship with the mayor felt good but ''strange.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The other day, something extraordinary happened at City Hall: the city's two top elected officials had a conversation with each other.</p>
        <p>To be specific, Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani had a private, cordial meeting with his longtime tormentor, Mark Green, the public advocate. At a bill-signing ceremony the same day, the mayor even patted Mr. Green on the shoulder and whispered in his ear, ''Good job, good job.'' Mr. Green, who has been a frequent target of the mayor's ire, said afterward that his new relationship with the mayor felt good but ''strange.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani also initiated a meeting last week with Alan G. Hevesi, the city comptroller with whom he has been at war, and told him, according to Mr. Hevesi, that he ''wanted to take some steps to repair the relationship.'' Around the same time, Mr. Giuliani called C. Virginia Fields, the Manhattan borough president, and asked to meet with her as part of what he promises will be a new relationship with the city's minority communities.</p>
        <p>Two weeks after he dropped out of the race for United States Senate, saying that he wanted to be a better person and a better mayor, Mr. Giuliani has started to make some tentative overtures to former enemies. But as he continues to research his treatment for prostate cancer and sort out his messy personal life, it is clear that any mayoral transformation is just beginning.</p>
        <p>The ''new Rudy,'' if such a creature exists, is still in his cocoon. City Hall remains in limbo, waiting for the mayor to decide on his cancer treatment as well as the initiatives that he promised would redefine his mayoralty in its last 18 months.</p>
        <p>So far, Mr. Giuliani does not appear to have talked with many of the city's black leaders, even though he said in his withdrawal speech that he wanted to bring down the ''barrier'' that he had erected between himself and some communities he had alienated. Nor has he contacted the family of Patrick M. Dorismond, the unarmed black man shot dead by the police in March, although he said he wanted to find a way to belatedly express his sympathy to them. He has not reached out to Representative Charles B. Rangel of Harlem, the dean of New York's Congressional delegation, or to former allies like the Rev. Calvin O. Butts and the Rev. Michel Faulkner.</p>
        <p>''I've sent him a couple of messages,'' said Mr. Faulkner, the pastor of the Central Baptist Church on West 92nd Street, who went on a fast and prayer vigil to protest the mayor's repeated attacks on Mr. Dorismond. ''I haven't heard back from him. I don't know what it means, to be honest with you. To me it's not good. I know that his personal situation takes pre-eminence over what's going on, but I hope he would understand the seriousness of the condition of the city.''</p>
        <p>By all appearances, Mr. Giuliani remains an engaged and energetic mayor, with a schedule full of the substance and ceremony of his job. His main business the last two weeks has been directing negotiations with the City Council over a pending $37 billion city budget package, plus monitoring intense talks between his top deputies and officials in Albany over legislation that would affect the city's pension costs and ability to borrow money. He has also, in the 15 days since withdrawing from the race, given six speeches, held at least six news conferences, attended three funerals, marched in three parades, appeared on two radio shows, presided over two receptions, had one town hall meeting, sworn in two judges and cut one ribbon. His four deputy mayors, meanwhile, are said to be working on initiatives intended to revise his legacy, but short of race relations there is no indication of what form they might take.</p>
        <p>One thing is certain: Mr. Giuliani does not appear to miss the Senate race or his brief campaign trips upstate. Asked the other day whether he had followed the party nomination in Buffalo of Representative Rick A. Lazio, the Republican choice to replace him in the race against Hillary Rodham Clinton, Mr. Giuliani replied, ''somewhat -- not in great detail.'' Then he added offhandedly, ''I was doing other things yesterday.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani's personal life remains complicated. He has had quiet dinners in Midtown restaurants with his ''very good'' friend, Judith Nathan, a district sales manager for Bristol-Myers Squibb who is divorced and has a teenage daughter. Friends say he is in love with her. But he also celebrated his 56th birthday last Sunday at Gracie Mansion with his two children and his estranged wife, Donna Hanover, who recently hired a divorce lawyer to work out the couple's separation agreement as they live in the same house. ''She got him a gift, and they shared an ice cream cake with the children,'' said Joannie Danielides, Ms. Hanover's press secretary. Later that day, he was honored at a party with some 50 staff members and friends at Jennifer's, an Italian restaurant on West 58th Street.</p>
        <p>Publicly, Mr. Giuliani has largely kept to his new kinder, gentler demeanor, although his news conferences have shrunk from extravaganzas of lengthy introspection into short, no-nonsense events. On Wednesday, his briefing to about a dozen reporters in the City Hall Blue Room lasted no more than eight minutes. The mayor ignored a question about whether he had met with the Dorismond family, said he would describe any minority initiative ''when I'm ready to describe it'' and cut off a reporter who asked whether his fresh promises of reaching out to blacks were similar to those he made, with few results, in 1997.</p>
        <p>''Why don't we all try to be nice to each other, O.K.?'' the mayor replied. ''Why don't we make a pretense of being nice to each other?''</p>
        <p>Still, it was a long way from the old irascibility. Generally, it's very hard to get the mayor angry these days.</p>
        <p>The mayor's staff members and city officials say Mr. Giuliani is different in meetings, too. ''He was very mellow and sort of pensive,'' said Mr. Hevesi, talking about his 45-minute  conversation last week with Mr. Giuliani. Mr. Hevesi, who had surgery for prostate cancer in 1996, said the two discussed city business as well as Mr. Giuliani's illness. Mr. Hevesi said he told the mayor that he had decided that surgery was his own best option -- a decision he made about a week after his diagnosis. Mr. Giuliani, who announced five weeks ago that he had cancer, said last month that he was still wavering between treatment options.</p>
        <p>As for the ''new Rudy,'' Mr. Giuliani sometimes seems as skeptical as his critics. ''No, there isn't a new Rudy,'' he told Rich Lamb on the WCBS radio show ''Ask the Mayor'' on Thursday night. ''You grow from things. Things that happen to you make changes in you.'' He added that his illness ''has changed me in certain respects'' and is ''probably going to change me even more, but not into a totally different person.''</p>
        <p>Dropping out of the race ''was the right decision, oh yeah, sure,'' he said. ''I haven't looked back.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
