<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Finding a Real Job for Philosophy; Everyday Frustrations Can Yield to the Wisdom of the Ages</title>
    <meta content="03BOTT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Ideas/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204296"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Philosophy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lyall, Sarah</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">De Botton, Alain</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Consolations of Philosophy, the (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E2DC113CF930A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1566" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Finding a Real Job for Philosophy; Everyday Frustrations Can Yield to the Wisdom of the Ages</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SARAH LYALL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lyall, Sarah</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, June 2</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alain de Botton, author of The Consolations of Philosophy, theorizes that solutions for some of life's problems lie in writings of philosophers such as Socrates, Montaigne, Seneca and others; de Botton suggests that there are different philosophers for different times whose writings may apply to issues such as anger, disappointment, feelings of sadness or rejection; drawings, photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Suppose you were a writer whose book received an unfavorable review. Your response (depending on your temperament) might be to indulge in a paroxysm of self-loathing or to retreat to your cave of self-righteousness, railing at the reviewer's incompetence and mean spirit.</p>
        <p>Alain de Botton, the author of ''The Consolations of Philosophy,'' has a third suggestion. What you should do, he says, is take a deep breath, sweep aside your unuseful emotions and apply the eminently sensible reasoning of the Roman philosopher Seneca, a great expositor of Stoicism and a firsthand student of the cruel hand of fate. (Among other things, Seneca was forced to abandon his house and all his worldly goods on the spot and was sent to live by himself in exile.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Suppose you were a writer whose book received an unfavorable review. Your response (depending on your temperament) might be to indulge in a paroxysm of self-loathing or to retreat to your cave of self-righteousness, railing at the reviewer's incompetence and mean spirit.</p>
        <p>Alain de Botton, the author of ''The Consolations of Philosophy,'' has a third suggestion. What you should do, he says, is take a deep breath, sweep aside your unuseful emotions and apply the eminently sensible reasoning of the Roman philosopher Seneca, a great expositor of Stoicism and a firsthand student of the cruel hand of fate. (Among other things, Seneca was forced to abandon his house and all his worldly goods on the spot and was sent to live by himself in exile.)</p>
        <p>''One element of Stoicism is to think that you can survive, that what is essential for life is a lot less than you might think it is,'' Mr. de Botton explained in a recent interview as he absent-mindedly nibbled on a tuna sandwich. Tall, thin and delicate-looking, he presented a poised and thoughtful figure, his air of slight melancholy at war, perhaps, with his constant undercurrent of amusement.</p>
        <p>If you can use Seneca to cope with anger and disappointment, the 30-year-old Mr. de Botton argues in his book, there's no reason you can't turn to Socrates when you're discouraged by your unpopularity. Or to Montaigne to keep from feeling horrified by your physical appearance. Or to Epicurus to liberate yourself from feeling sad that you don't have more money.</p>
        <p>''There are different philosophers for different times,'' said Mr. de Botton, whose book examines six of them. ''There are moments when Nietzsche's heroic stance, bombastic and rather hysterical, is very nice. There are times when Montaigne's more gentle and accepting side seems relevant. To spend some time in the company of a philosopher like Montaigne is very pleasant, even if you don't become a committed Montaigne-ian.''</p>
        <p>Britain has had plenty of opportunity lately to take in Mr. de Botton's message. A best seller here, the book was made into a television series, one show per philosopher, with the author describing and illustrating his points about each one. When Mr. de Botton (who is sometimes called ''Dr. Love'' because of his three novels with love themes and his philosophical advice to the lovelorn) went to Manchester for the series, he told a shopaholic whose life was being ruined by his addiction that he might find solace in the teachings of Epicurus. In London he told a delivery man prone to terrible spasms of road rage how he might calm down by reading Seneca instead of The Sun, the popular downmarket newspaper.</p>
        <p>And when he visited the home of an attractive young woman whose boyfriend had just left her, Mr. de Botton, in the midst of applying the lessons of Schopenhauer found himself asking the heartbroken subject out to dinner. They are now dating.</p>
        <p>His book is only slightly less quirky than his approach to television. His elegant essays filter interesting biographical data about the philosophers through the prism of his playful mind. (Schopenhauer's closest relationships, we learn, were with a series of poodles, although Mr. de Botton writes of him, ''For the griefs of love, he may be the finest among philosophers.'') The author urges his readers to return to what he sees as the ancient purpose of philosophy: teaching people how to live. ''I wanted to write a book that would rescue a certain totally neglected tradition in philosophy, which is the pursuit of wisdom,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''The Consolations of Philosophy'' is written in an easygoing, accessible style and filled with whimsical illustrations that help make its points. But it is by no means a survey of philosophy in the manner, say, of the phenomenally popular novel ''Sophie's World'' by Jostein Gaarder. Mr. de Botton says he wanted to write in an engaging, persuasive way because he is easily bored when he reads, and he assumes others are, too. But it is his breezy approach, as much as anything else, that has unsettled some serious students of philosophy. Reviewing the book in The Observer of London, Peter Conrad said it ''wickedly veers between sagacity and silliness.''</p>
        <p>Maybe, Mr. de Botton suggests, they have misunderstood his intent.</p>
        <p>''I haven't written an introduction to philosophy or the complete guide to any of these philosophers,'' he said. ''What I've really done is simply written six essays looking at six different aspects of their thought.</p>
        <p>''I'm also trying to do a tricky thing which annoys some people. I'm not surrendering my claim to be accurate, to get all the facts right, to be quite scholarly. But at the same time I don't want to write in a scholarly way at all. I'm being rather brazen about this and standing up against the opposition, because it's my deepest belief that you can be at once serious and yet easy to read and playful. And however much I may fail in that attempt, I believe in that as a goal.''</p>
        <p>It is an approach that he used with much success in his three novels and, most notably in his last book, ''How Proust Can Change Your Life,'' a funny, robust and joyous argument for negotiating the daunting thickets of ''Remembrance of Things Past.'' At first overlooked in Britain, Mr. de Botton's book leapt into public consciousness and then on to best-seller lists on both sides of the Atlantic when John Updike raved about it in The New Yorker. (Sales of Proust increased, too.)</p>
        <p>''His curious, humorous, didactic and dazzling book bears the subtitle 'Not a Novel,' '' Mr. Updike said in the review. ''It contains, however, more human interest and play of fancy than most fiction.''</p>
        <p>Mr. de Botton is not a French aristocrat, though that is what Britons generally assume when they hear his name (which is pronounced in the French manner) and see his picture. He comes from a rich family -- his father is a successful financier -- but one that has always emphasized achievement above anything else, and Mr. de Botton has had to make his own way in the world. The family name was originally Spanish, but his father was born into a small, thriving community of Jews in Cairo. His mother comes from Switzerland, which is where Mr. de Botton spent his early years.</p>
        <p>He was sent to Harrow, a top-notch boys' boarding school in Britain, at the age of 8, and had to learn not only English but also how to thrive in a place that glorified athletes, something he is not in the least. He did it by being clever, he said, and by agreeing to do others' homework.</p>
        <p>After Cambridge University, from which he graduated with a double-starred first (roughly equivalent to summa cum laude), Mr. de Botton drifted into academia, looking to acquire a Ph.D., first at Harvard and then at King's College London. He dropped out of both. ''I was very confused,'' he said. ''I wanted to pursue the history of ideas, but I found myself not sitting comfortably in any one discipline. I didn't want to be a philosopher and didn't want to be a historian, and I got quite depressed by the whole thing. I thought, 'Oh, God, maybe I won't get a job at the end and it will all be quite miserable.' ''</p>
        <p>(Helpful tip from Nietzsche, according to Mr. Botton: Don't panic about panicking. Life is difficult, and angst is a normal human response.)</p>
        <p>Unfailingly charming and, one suspects, unlikely to lose his temper, Mr. de Botton has nonetheless had his share of sleepless nights and crippling self-doubt. He describes his 20's as an anxious time and says that for him, reading great thinkers is nothing but a comfort.</p>
        <p>''I don't want to make myself sound obsessive in this area, but I've always looked to figures from literature or history as sources of interesting ideas on how to live,'' he said. ''People come up with all sorts of responses about what to do about anxiety, and one of them is the quest for knowledge. I intellectualize things. That's my way of dealing with anxiety.''</p>
        <p>But he is only human. Before he intellectualizes, he frets, rages and sometimes wallows.</p>
        <p>''Seneca would say that one can't help but have emotions,'' he said. ''Philosophy is for an hour later.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
