<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>World Briefing</title>
    <meta content="Y03BRI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204351"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E6DF1E3CF930A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1013" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>World Briefing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled By Terence Neilan</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>GREECE: TURKS STORM BEACH -- In a dramatic display of the improved state of Greek-Turkish relations, about 160 Turkish troops, one of whom is at left, stormed a beach at Kyparissia, in the western Peloponnesus, as part of a NATO exercise in recapturing lost territory. Some 2,000 Greek, American and Spanish marines were also involved. Greece and Turkey came close to war in 1996 when Turks seized a disputed rocky islet about 310 miles west of Kyparissia.</p>
        <p>Anthee Carassava (NYT)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>GREECE: TURKS STORM BEACH -- In a dramatic display of the improved state of Greek-Turkish relations, about 160 Turkish troops, one of whom is at left, stormed a beach at Kyparissia, in the western Peloponnesus, as part of a NATO exercise in recapturing lost territory. Some 2,000 Greek, American and Spanish marines were also involved. Greece and Turkey came close to war in 1996 when Turks seized a disputed rocky islet about 310 miles west of Kyparissia.</p>
        <p>Anthee Carassava (NYT)</p>
        <p>NORTHERN IRELAND: HITCH OVER FLAG -- Ministers in the new government from Sinn Fein, the political wing of the Irish Republican Army, refused to permit the flying of the Union Jack from their office buildings, the official practice on June 2, the anniversary of Queen Elizabeth II's coronation. The pro-British Ulster Unionist Party accused Sinn Fein of violating the terms of the peace pact that created the new home rule government. First Minister David Trimble said the dispute would be debated when the Northern Ireland Assembly reconvenes Monday.</p>
        <p>Warren Hoge (NYT)</p>
        <p>CZECH REPUBLIC: 'MEIN KAMPF' SUIT -- The Czech publisher of Hitler's ''Mein Kampf'' has been charged with promotion of Nazism, the police said. Michal Zitko published the unabridged Czech translation in March, saying he wanted Czechs to be exposed to an important historical document. A first edition of 10,000 copies sold out. He faces up to eight years in prison if convicted.</p>
        <p>Steven Erlanger (NYT)</p>
        <p>SLOVAKIA: TOP U.N. JOB DENIED -- Prime Minister Mikulas Dzurinda and Foreign Minister Eduard Kukan conspired to keep a choice United Nations job offer from Finance Minister Brigita Schmognerova. Secretary General Kofi Annan suggested to Mr. Kukan that she become director of the United Nations Economic Commission for Europe, but Mr. Dzurinda decided he needed Ms. Schmognerova in his government and never told her about the offer. ''It would have been one of the greatest positions a Slovak official could hold,'' she told Radio Twist in Bratislava.</p>
        <p>Steven Erlanger (NYT)</p>
        <p>GERMANY: WOMEN'S ARMY ROLE -- Defense Minister Rudolf Scharping announced that women would have unrestricted access to all jobs in the armed forces starting in January. Until now, women in the German Army have been permitted to serve only as nurses and musicians. Mr. Scharping's decision follows a court ruling that said women could not be excluded from performing most military tasks.</p>
        <p>Alan Maimon (NYT)</p>
        <p>RUSSIA: POPE NOT WELCOME -- The Russian Orthodox Church, responding to reports that President Vladimir V. Putin plans to invite Pope John Paul II to visit Russia when they meet at the Vatican on Tuesday, said it is not ready to receive him until differences between the two churches are resolved. The Orthodox Church objects to missionary work by Catholics in Russia.</p>
        <p>(NYT)</p>
        <p>THE AMERICAS</p>
        <p>PERU: FINAL VOTE TALLY -- Election authorities released final results of last Sunday's presidential runoff showing President Alberto K. Fujimori winning 51.20 percent of the vote. Alejandro Toledo, the business professor who dropped out of the race charging fraud, won 17.68 percent. The remaining voters, 31.12 percent, canceled or left their ballots blank.</p>
        <p>Clifford Krauss (NYT)</p>
        <p>CANADA: VIETNAM TO FREE WOMAN -- Vietnam has told Canada it will release from a Hanoi jail a 74-year-old Canadian-Vietnamese woman convicted of heroin trafficking. Tran Thi Cam was convicted with her daughter, Nguyen Thi Hiep, in a case in which the Canadian police suspected they were tricked into trying to embark from Hanoi with art panels laden with heroin. The daughter was executed in Hanoi.</p>
        <p>James Brooke (NYT)</p>
        <p>ASIA</p>
        <p>JAPAN: PARLIAMENT DISSOLVED -- In the face of some of the worst-ever polling data, Prime Minister Yoshiro Mori dissolved the lower house of Parliament and announced national elections for June 25. The elections have been sparked by a series of controversies surrounding Mr. Mori, from the circumstances surrounding his arrival in power, to a remark calling Japan a divine country. Mr. Mori became prime minister on April 3 his predecessor, Keizo Obuchi, suffered a stroke. Mr. Obuchi died last month.</p>
        <p>Howard W. French (NYT)</p>
        <p>INDONESIA: SUHARTO SUIT -- Lawyers for former President Suharto filed an appeal of a government order placing him under house arrest during an investigation into his involvement in corruption and abuse of power. Court officials said the appeal would be heard next week.</p>
        <p>Seth Mydans (NYT)</p>
        <p>MIDDLE EAST</p>
        <p>ISRAEL: REJECTING RED CROSS -- Israel said it was rejecting a proposal by the International Committee of the Red Cross to allow it membership if it agreed to replace its red Star of David with a neutral symbol, like a diamond, in certain zones. The director of the Magen David Adom, or Red Star of David organization, said that since the symbol would be for Israel only, it would be ''like a yellow star,'' the Nazi insignia for the Jews.</p>
        <p>Deborah Sontag (NYT)</p>
        <p>AFRICA</p>
        <p>ETHIOPIA, ERITREA: TALKS RESUME -- The Organization of African Unity resumed talks in Algiers with Ethiopian and Eritrean delegations after a 24-hour break to allow the two countries to study proposals to end their border war. Officials said Justice Minister Ahmed Ouyahia of Algeria met Ethiopia's foreign minister, Seyoum Mesfin, left, and would hold talks with the Eritreans.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>ZIMBABWE: U.N. MISSION ON HOLD -- Secretary General Kofi Annan postponed a high-level mission to Zimbabwe this weekend after President Robert Mugabe's government published a list of 804 farms that authorities plan to seize under a new law aimed at expediting land redistribution.</p>
        <p>Henri E. Cauvin (NYT)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
