<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With Lebanon's Border Calm, New Threats Stand Out</title>
    <meta content="Y03MIDE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204363"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Lebanon</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Syria</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Golan Heights</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sachs, Susan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Lebanon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Syria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Syria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Lebanon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E1DE1E3CF930A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1045" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With Lebanon's Border Calm, New Threats Stand Out</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUSAN SACHS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sachs, Susan</byline>
      <dateline>BEIRUT, Lebanon, June 2</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pullout of Israeli troops from southern Lebanon redraws physical boundaries between two countries, but absence of a deal between Syria and Israeli on return of occupied Golan Heights leaves potential for instability and violence (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Every square inch of land counts in the reckoning of victory and defeat in the Middle East. And every inch along the Lebanese-Israeli border is going to be counted, probably twice, before anyone can say whether Israel's withdrawal from southern Lebanon last week will ultimately count as an installment on regional peace.</p>
        <p>In the nine days since the pullout, the frontier between the countries has remained tranquil for the first time in more than 25 years. The only spike in tension occurred on Sunday, when Israeli soldiers fired rubber-coated bullets at a few Lebanese men who, giddy with newfound bravado, plunged through a border fence to plant a Hezbollah flag under the noses of their longtime enemies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Every square inch of land counts in the reckoning of victory and defeat in the Middle East. And every inch along the Lebanese-Israeli border is going to be counted, probably twice, before anyone can say whether Israel's withdrawal from southern Lebanon last week will ultimately count as an installment on regional peace.</p>
        <p>In the nine days since the pullout, the frontier between the countries has remained tranquil for the first time in more than 25 years. The only spike in tension occurred on Sunday, when Israeli soldiers fired rubber-coated bullets at a few Lebanese men who, giddy with newfound bravado, plunged through a border fence to plant a Hezbollah flag under the noses of their longtime enemies.</p>
        <p>But it is still dangerous territory. Although the physical boundaries between Lebanon and Israel have been redrawn, the political map contains the same ambushes and obstacles as before the Israeli retreat.</p>
        <p>As long as Syria has not made its own deal with Israel to return the occupied Golan Heights, the potential for instability and violence remains.</p>
        <p>''Israelis may no longer wake up in the morning to hear of another soldier killed in southern Lebanon,'' said Joseph Samaha, a Lebanese expert who writes for Al Hayat, the pan-Arab daily newspaper. ''But still, each day, in terms of regional strategy, they will know they can never enjoy peace or integrate into the Middle East until they have an agreement with Syria.''</p>
        <p>Syria has been sending mixed signals about how it will behave in the new atmosphere. In the extreme, experts said, Syria could encourage guerrilla attacks on Israeli targets in Shabaa Farms, a strip of land abutting the Golan Heights that the Lebanese government, with mild Syrian backing, claims as its own.</p>
        <p>An outbreak of violence, with the expected Israeli reprisals, could ruin Syria's efforts over recent weeks to gain international approval by cooperating with the United Nations over the Lebanon withdrawal.</p>
        <p>Syria could also keep the temperature in the region turned up by more limited, and less bloody, means. It could permit Lebanon, which has so far refused to claim sovereignty over the liberated south and send its army into the liberated zone, to keep on arguing indefinitely with the United Nations over whether the withdrawal has been completed.</p>
        <p>''We've had years of low-intensity warfare here,'' said Simon M. Karam, a lawyer here and a former ambassador to the United States. ''Now we will have a low-intensity diplomatic imbroglio, a crisis that's always brewing at just over 98.6 degrees, like someone who is mildly sick.''</p>
        <p>Lebanon, a tiny nation of barely 4.5 million people, is effectively a satellite state to its bigger and more militarized neighbor, Syria. Some 30,000 Syrian soldiers are stationed in Lebanon, and the Lebanese government always toes the Syrian line on foreign policy.</p>
        <p>For years, the Syrian strategy, in peace negotiations with Israel and through the Hezbollah guerrillas it encouraged to attack Israeli occupation forces, has been to link the liberation of southern Lebanon to the recovery of the Golan Heights.</p>
        <p>Israel will not enjoy peace, Syrian officials have often said, until it leaves the Golan Heights and southern Lebanon. Lebanese officials, taking their cue from Damascus, refused to negotiate with Israel, insisting that the occupation of southern Lebanon has to end, but always adding that they could never sign a separate peace agreement before Syria regained its land.</p>
        <p>That stand was shaken when Israel announced three months ago that it would cut its losses and quit southern Lebanon, with or without a peace agreement with Syria.</p>
        <p>The Syrian reaction was summed up in a warning from Foreign Minister Farouk al-Shara that such a move would be suicidal. In Lebanon, the prospect of a unilateral Israeli pullout caused a shiver of panic, and officials immediately raised other issues.</p>
        <p>No Israeli pullout would comply with United Nations resolutions unless Lebanese prisoners in Israel were freed, the officials said. Palestinian refugees have to be given the right of return, and the United Nations has to disarm Palestinians in refugee camps in Lebanon so that they could not, in theory, attack Israel and provoke fresh Israeli retaliation against Lebanon.</p>
        <p>Since the withdrawal, Lebanon has repeated those demands and added new ones, like recovering Shabaa Farms.</p>
        <p>Although Syria has permitted Lebanon to act as its devil's advocate, Syrian officials have also tried hard to portray themselves as cooperative with the United Nations.</p>
        <p>This week, according to a United Nations envoy, the Syrian officials said they accepted the United Nations position that for purposes of verifying whether Israel has complied with United Nations Resolution 425, the pullout will be complete, even if it does not include Shabaa Farms.</p>
        <p>The resolution, from 1978, calls for Israel's complete withdrawal from the Lebanese territory that it occupied in that year. Most of the Shabaa Farms land was seized by Israel in 1967.</p>
        <p>But for their Lebanese clients, Syrian officials also left their position muddy by reassuring Lebanon this week that Shabaa Farms was also occupied Lebanese land. The murkiness of the Syrian stance has left the Lebanese government and the Syrian-backed Hezbollah militia floundering.</p>
        <p>A senior Hezbollah official, Muhammad Raad, said this week that the militia had a right to continue its armed struggle against Israel until Shabaa Farms had been returned to Lebanese control and the Lebanese government had verified that Israel had left every inch of Lebanese territory. But Mr. Raad would not say whether Hezbollah would exercise that right.</p>
        <p>''When we say we want to claim our land back, we are not going to act carelessly,'' he said. ''We will resist in the right time and the right place, so the resistance will be effective. It could take 20 years even. We are very patient, and we will not be in any dispute with Lebanon or with Syria.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
