<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cutting the Mustard</title>
    <meta content="28SEAR$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202869"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="IN SEARCH OF . . ."/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Delicatessens</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">D'agnese, Joseph</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E2DD143DF93BA15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1518" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cutting the Mustard</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSEPH D'AGNESE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">D'agnese, Joseph</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Jewish-style, New York-style and Kosher delis in New Jersey which, while not as well known as their New York City counterparts, have found their own niche; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LODGED solidly in the back of every deli lover's mind -- and possibly in his arteries as well -- is a vision of a flawless pastrami on rye: heavy on the spices, steamed to perfection, fatty and delicious. Its table companion, is that fountain classic, the egg cream: milk, chocolate syrup and seltzer whipped together to create a satisfying beverage topped by egg-white-like head.</p>
        <p>For a certain slice of the population, the two delights came together most often in Jewish-style delis of New York. In pastrami palaces like the Carnegie, the Stage,  Ratner's and Katz's, generations of American Jews noshed on knishes, oversized pickles, colossal franks and shippable beef salamis.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LODGED solidly in the back of every deli lover's mind -- and possibly in his arteries as well -- is a vision of a flawless pastrami on rye: heavy on the spices, steamed to perfection, fatty and delicious. Its table companion, is that fountain classic, the egg cream: milk, chocolate syrup and seltzer whipped together to create a satisfying beverage topped by egg-white-like head.</p>
        <p>For a certain slice of the population, the two delights came together most often in Jewish-style delis of New York. In pastrami palaces like the Carnegie, the Stage,  Ratner's and Katz's, generations of American Jews noshed on knishes, oversized pickles, colossal franks and shippable beef salamis.</p>
        <p>With time, the meeting places in the old neighborhoods changed as children grew up and took their own families elsewhere. Many moved to New Jersey. And while the old tastes never died, who had the time anymore to shlep to the city? Which led, in time, to the big question: Where are the great Jewish delis of Jersey, and how good can they possibly be?</p>
        <p>To answer the first part, they're out there. They're just not universally known. For example, uttering the names Larry's or Jack Cooper's or Jesse &amp; David's -- all longtime Jewish-style New Jersey delis -- is not going to elicit the same sighs from old-timers as the hallowed name of the Second Avenue Deli. Like all things worth fighting over, a neighborhood Jewish deli arouses passion and nostalgia. (Where else can you find a Dr. Brown's Cel-Ray soda?)</p>
        <p>Now, are these upstarts as good as the old places, or at least the same? That's a thornier question. You might as well ask after the snows of yesteryear.</p>
        <p>For one thing, the Jersey delis are not really upstarts. Most of the ones mentioned here have been around for at least a decade; a handful have been around for 50 years. A word on semantics is also in order: Americanized delis prefer to call themselves ''New York-style'' or ''Jewish-style'' as only establishments under rabbinical supervision, and thus subject to weekly inspections, may call themselves kosher (nor will you get the egg cream with the corned beef).</p>
        <p>One of the state's best delis -- Jack Cooper's Celebrity Deli in Edison -- got its start in 1949. That's when Morris Cooper opened a family luncheonette, Cooper's Sweet Shop, on Bergen Street in Newark. Jack Cooper, his son, joined him as a partner in 1953, and later moved the operation. Now 72, the younger Mr. Cooper seems exasperated when people ask him how his place compares with Manhattan delis.</p>
        <p>''I hear this all the time,'' Mr. Cooper said. ''It's not the same. It's not the same.' I say, it doesn't really matter that it's the same. You're not the same. This is food that's delicious, that we've all grown up with, but we don't eat it the way we used to.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Cooper realized, as all deli owners eventually do, that success in Jersey sometimes necessitates moving beyond the delectable trio of pastrami, corned beef and brisket.</p>
        <p>In the 1980's, when Cajun food was hot, Cooper's offered Cajun food. Today the restaurant offers a number of vegetarian dishes, and sliced turkey meals nearly always beat out corned beef orders.</p>
        <p>The deli promotes itself with a Web site and a newsletter, and by steadfastly adhering to an old deli tradition: it'll ship any meal anywhere, overnight. (Its most popular boxed treat, the Nosh, which includes corned beef, pastrami, pickles, cole slaw and rye bread for six to eight people, costs $100, air charges included.) ''We just don't have the foot traffic out here that New York does,'' said Mr. Cooper. ''If we weren't willing to change our way of doing business, we couldn't survive.''</p>
        <p>In fact, one could spend a whole night -- preferably over matzoh ball soup and a hefty sandwich topped with Russian dressing and cole slaw -- analyzing what Jersey delis have done to make themselves stand out.</p>
        <p>Some go big, as in gigantic, gargantuan, huge. ''Being that some of our sandwiches and dinners are of humongous proportions,'' warns a sign displayed in Harold's New York Style Deli, which is tucked into the Holiday Inn on Route 46 in Parsippany, ''we encourage you to share at no extra charge.''</p>
        <p>The average Harold's sandwich comes in one of two sizes: the 9- or 19-ouncer. A monstrous triple decker, also on the menu, feeds three and will set you back $23 to $27. Owner Tom Botsaris, a Greek-born Jew, said size was everything when it came to pleasing customers . ''Most people when they go out want to take something home,'' Mr. Botsaris said. ''Tomorrow they'll share it with their family. 'Hey, this is from Harold's.' ''</p>
        <p>Others focus on service -- catering parties, weddings, bar mitzvahs and synagogue functions -- and generally conjuring up a neighborhood feeling that so many patrons and owners sense is forever lost in the land across the Hudson.</p>
        <p>''It's the kind of thing where you get to know the customer more,'' said Jerry Feldstein, 57, who for 17 years has run the 75-seat Jerry and Harvey's Noshery in Marlboro with his wife, Marie. ''When we started out, our motto was, 'Bridging the Gap between Brooklyn and New Jersey.' We think we've been pretty successful at it.''</p>
        <p>In some cities, like Teaneck, a thriving  observant Jewish population supports numerous glatt kosher businesses (the strictest kosher designation). At a spot like Noah's Ark on Cedar Lane, where pictures of animals streaming two by two from the ark decorate the walls, chicken Creole, chicken Marsala, and chicken cordon bleu (stuffed with pastrami, not prosciutto, and omitting cheese entirely) share billing with chicken in the pot, a traditional dish of boiled chicken in broth with matzoh balls. You'd need never eat a deli item if you didn't want to, though you'd be a fool not to try the slab-sized french fries or onion rings.</p>
        <p>So please, come, sit, eat, and enough already with the comparisons to Manhattan. 'We're better than them anyway,'' said Mr. Botsaris, whose restaurant boasts the imprimatur any deli really needs: an autographed portrait of Henny Youngman hanging on the back wall.</p>
        <p>''The Stage is like a tourist attraction these days,'' he insisted. ''The Carnegie too. Real New Yorkers don't go there anymore.''</p>
        <p>And Eleanor Gordon, manager of Larry's Kosher Deli, a Plainfield institution opened by Harry Scheckner in 1946, agrees. ''People don't like to say it, but there's been a lot of changes in New York too,'' he said. ''Now even Ratner's is going out.''</p>
        <p>That should settle the issue, but of course it won't. Deli owners know they play to a tough crowd. Customers can be forever counted on to weigh in on anything, including the ambience. In the old days, deli decor was simple: you hung a few salamis and called it a day. Today it's a little more complicated. Just ask Abe Dankner, who runs Eppe Essen (the name means 'something to eat' in Yiddish) in Livingston, another Newark transplant. The logo of Eppe Essen is the fiddler on the roof; you'll find a life-sized fiddler statue inside -- and a little more.</p>
        <p>Some years ago, Mr. Dankner, a fan of American Indian art, transformed his banquet hall into a pantheon of Indian design, including a map depicting locations of various tribes in the United States. He was inspired, in part, by a long-gone diner in Newark, named after that city's Weequahic Park. That diner, said Mr. Dankner, had an Indian name but nevertheless played host to numerous Jewish patrons. But the Indian theme hasn't been warmly received at Eppe Essen; restaurant reviewers over the years always take swipes at the decoration.</p>
        <p>''So I put my art in there,'' said Mr. Dankner. ''So what? Decor has nothing to do with the food. If you think about it, the Jewish people are a minority and Indians are a minority, so why not have their art here?''</p>
        <p>So nix the kasha varnishkas, and pass the succotash.</p>
        <p>New York Style</p>
        <p>Eppes Essen, 105 East Mount. Pleasant Avenue, Livingston;, (973) 994-1120.</p>
        <p>Jack Cooper's Celebrity Deli &amp; Restaurant, 1199 Amboy Avenue, Edison;, (732) 549-4580, www.celebritydeli.com</p>
        <p>Jerry &amp; Harvey's Noshery, 96 Route 9, Marlboro; (732) 972-1122.</p>
        <p>Harold's New York Deli, Holiday Inn, 707 Route 46 East, Parsippany; (973) 335-3339.</p>
        <p>Richard's, 155 Brighton Avenue, Long Branch; (732) 870-9133.</p>
        <p>Kosher</p>
        <p>Jesse &amp; David's, Towne Pointe Shopping Center, 357 Route 9 South, Manalapan; (732) 972-7755.</p>
        <p>Larry's Kosher Deli &amp; Restaurant, 1353 South Avenue (Route 28); Plainfield, (908) 755-8013.</p>
        <p>Noah's Ark Glatt Kosher Restaurant-Deli, 493 Cedar Lane, Teaneck; (201) 692-1200 or 1 800 772-6624.</p>
        <p>IN SEARCH OF . . .</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
