<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Looking for the Right Man in Bridgeport</title>
    <meta content="28BISH$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202868"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Bridgeport (Conn)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Roman Catholic Church</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'Connor, John (Cardinal)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Egan, Edward Michael (Abp)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Musante, Fred</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E2DD143DF93BA15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1089" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Looking for the Right Man in Bridgeport</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRED MUSANTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Musante, Fred</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on concerns raised by parishioners and church officials as Roman Catholic Diocese of Bridgeport, Conn, searches for replacement for Bishop Edward Michael Egan, who has been chosen as Archbishop of New York to succeed Cardinal John O'Connor; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MANY Roman Catholics of the Diocese of Bridgeport were proud that their bishop, Edward Michael Egan, had been chosen as archbishop of New York to succeed Cardinal John O'Connor, but there were also sighs of regret.</p>
        <p>Bishop Egan is widely popular among many parishioners and clergy of the diocese, which consists of Fairfield County, for what they say are his gifts as a homilist, his support of Catholic charity and education, his attention to spiritual matters in the parishes, and for improving the financial condition of the diocese.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MANY Roman Catholics of the Diocese of Bridgeport were proud that their bishop, Edward Michael Egan, had been chosen as archbishop of New York to succeed Cardinal John O'Connor, but there were also sighs of regret.</p>
        <p>Bishop Egan is widely popular among many parishioners and clergy of the diocese, which consists of Fairfield County, for what they say are his gifts as a homilist, his support of Catholic charity and education, his attention to spiritual matters in the parishes, and for improving the financial condition of the diocese.</p>
        <p>According to several parish priests and church officials, what the 360,000 Catholics of the diocese want the most in their next bishop is a man who possesses many of the same qualities as Bishop Egan and is able to expand on his record.</p>
        <p>''The concern is that we continue the programs that we have,'' said Monsignor Alan Detscher, ecumenical officer for the diocese, ''and most bishops, when they come in, don't try to make too many changes right away.''</p>
        <p>Fairfield County is geographically small, but  complex, said Dr. Anthony Cernera, president of Sacred Heart University. Some parishes are poor and others wealthy, and throughout the parishes are enclaves of immigrants. ''It defies simple answers,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Cernera said that the next bishop would have to be ''someone who's going to understand the needs of that struggling immigrant in Bridgeport and also the corporate executive who's also a member of the diocese.''</p>
        <p>When Bishop Egan arrived in the diocese in 1988, he was fluent in Latin and Italian, but he soon learned Spanish and would frequently preach in Spanish and English when celebrating  Mass at predominantly Spanish-speaking parishes, said Monsignor Aniceto Villamide, the diocese's vicar for Hispanics. ''People were very happy with that,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The next bishop won't have to deal with many of the difficult problems that the diocese faced when Bishop Egan arrived. At that time, the economy was moving into recession and many of the parishes in poorer neighborhoods, and their schools, were feeling the pinch.</p>
        <p>Bishop Egan closed some Catholic elementary schools that were poorly attended or dilapidated, and regionalized the school system so that the remaining 33 elementary schools were supported by all the diocese's 88 parishes, not only by each one's individual parish.</p>
        <p>Along with his streamlining and reorganization of diocesan operations, this eventually put the diocese on firm financial ground.</p>
        <p>''Financially, he straightened the place out,'' said the Rev. Michael Jude Fay, pastor of St. John's Church in Darien.</p>
        <p>Bishop Egan also started the Inner City Foundation, a semi-autonomous fund-raising organization, to raise money in support of the parish schools and Catholic Charities of Fairfield County. The foundation's director, Richard Stone, said that since 1992, it has raised $9.5 million to help the poor in Fairfield County. The money has been used to open health clinics and job-training programs, and grant scholarships to families to send their children to Catholic schools.</p>
        <p>''People usually think of Fairfield County as a very wealthy county, but there are many needy people in the cities of Bridgeport, Norwalk and Stamford,'' Mr. Stone said.</p>
        <p>The reorganization of the diocese's parish schools made a big difference, and coming, as it did, just ahead of a resurgence of the school-age population in the state, it was fortuitous. In addition, Bishop Egan also raised a $55 million endowment for the diocese's five high schools and implemented improvements in school budgets.</p>
        <p>''He changed the paradigm from parochial to regional,'' Armand Fabri, the diocese's superintendent of schools, said. ''The demand was always there, but affordability was an issue.''</p>
        <p>As a result, the next bishop can look forward to leading the diocese's Catholic schools in an expansion drive. Mr. Fabri said plans are being made to reopen some of the schools that had been closed and to build additions on others to meet the demand for Catholic education.</p>
        <p>Another area in which Bishop Egan was very successful, and where there is a high interest in seeing a continuation, is in priesthood vocations. Six months after his appointment as bishop of the Diocese of Bridgeport, Bishop Egan started the St. John Fisher House, a residential seminary in Stamford, and he was responsible for attracting many of the seminarians who have trained there.</p>
        <p>Since 1965, said the Rev. Chris Walsh, the spiritual adviser at the seminary residence, there has been a 21 percent decline in the number of Catholic priests in the United States. The Diocese of Bridgeport has stayed even, but even at the current rate of increase Father Walsh said it doesn't have enough priests to meet the expansion of parish services that is foreseen in the coming years, something the next bishop will face. ''I hope for someone who will be identical in terms of his dynamism and commitment toward vocations,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Monsignor Villamide said Bishop Egan's success attracting men to the priesthood has been particularly helpful in expanding Catholic ministry to Hispanics and other immigrants in the cities in the diocese. When Bishop Egan came to the diocese there were only three Hispanic priests and seven parishes with Spanish ministries, and now there are eight Hispanic priests and a number of non-Hispanic, Spanish-speaking priests, and Spanish ministries at 12 parishes.</p>
        <p>He said three new Haitian priests were ordained in the last three years to preach to Haitian immigrants, and a Vietnamese priest was newly ordained as well .</p>
        <p>Until a new bishop is appointed, Monsignor Greg Smith, director of the Institute for Religious Education and Pastoral Studies at Sacred Heart University, said Pope John Paul II will probably appoint an administrator to run the diocese.</p>
        <p>Monsignor Smith said he doubted a new bishop would be appointed before September, because decisions like that are usually not made during the summer.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, a Vatican official will consult with American bishops to compile a list of names to submit to the Pope for consideration, Monsignor Smith said.</p>
        <p>He said he thought that the church's hierarchy would look for someone who is a leader, has shown loyalty to Pope John Paul, had demonstrated spiritual qualities, and has pastoral and administrative ability.</p>
        <p>But continuing those programs that Bishop Egan started, particularly with regard to Catholic education and the priesthood, would weigh heavily in Rome, he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
