<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Recombinations</title>
    <meta content="28BECK" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202768"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Beck, Martha</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bateson, Mary Catherine</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Full Circles, Overlapping Lives (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE1DF123AF93BA15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="918" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Recombinations</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Martha Beck</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Beck, Martha</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Martha Beck reviews book Full Circles, Overlapping Lives: Culture and Generation in Transition by Mary Catherine Bateson; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Full Circles, Overlapping Lives</p>
        <p>Culture and Generation in Transition.</p>
        <p>By Mary Catherine Bateson.</p>
        <p>262 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Random House. $25.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Full Circles, Overlapping Lives</p>
        <p>Culture and Generation in Transition.</p>
        <p>By Mary Catherine Bateson.</p>
        <p>262 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Random House. $25.</p>
        <p>If you aren't a fan of the excruciatingly politically correct genre known as women's studies, you'll be inclined to put down Mary Catherine Bateson's latest book before finishing the first 50 pages. Don't. After a middling start, ''Full Circles, Overlapping Lives'' grows into a thoroughly absorbing and enlightening book, one that deserves to be enjoyed by people of both sexes and all ages.</p>
        <p>Gender and age are the two factors that make up the bulk of Bateson's subject matter. ''Full Circles, Overlapping Lives'' is this anthropologist's look at a society that has ''arrived at a necessity for interdependence and empathy that goes beyond any selected for during evolution.'' Human culture did not emerge among people who routinely survived childhood and remained healthy and active into old age. Since World War II alone, more than 20 years have been added to the average human life span. At the same time, technological and political change has revolutionized both work and family, transforming virtually every social experience any of us is likely to have. Bateson sets out to articulate and analyze the problems and opportunities created by this new reality. She succeeds through a combination of impressive intellect, broad knowledge and genuine sensitivity.</p>
        <p>True, Bateson's sensitivity gets too much play early on. The first two chapters, rich in the argot of academic feminism, might be called touchy-feely by anyone wishing to be attacked as an oppressive, patriarchal, reactionary minion of evil. The book focuses on Bateson's experience at Spelman College in Atlanta, where she taught a seminar that included not only college-age students but several women closer to Bateson's own age (late 50's). In describing the seminar and its members, Bateson resorts to the self-conscious verbal tiptoeing that characterizes so much of contemporary social science.</p>
        <p>Bateson spends paragraphs agonizing over her choice of a label for the seminar's older participants (''auditors''? ''veterans''? ''oaks''?) before settling on ''elders,'' with an apology for any possible pejorative nuance. But what to call a student who once considered herself bisexual but has limited lesbian experience and sometimes waffles about her sexual orientation?</p>
        <p>Though this pressing question is left unanswered, we are firmly assured that the student in question is a ''womanist'' and has been oppressed accordingly. Bateson dutifully notes another participant's accusation that her seminar was ''adultist,'' and that courtesy is ''internalized oppression.'' She seems so anxious to let every voice be heard without prejudice that she lets the conventions of diversity-speak water down her own keen insights and felicitous prose. It may be true that every voice in the Spelman seminar deserves an equal hearing, but frankly Bateson's is by far the most interesting.</p>
        <p>This becomes fully apparent when Bateson stops fussing over nomenclature and digs into her subject. Her analyses of topics like the changing duration and definition of youth, the emergence of a ''second adulthood'' in developed societies and the chaos of new styles of interaction between people of different ages and sexes are fascinating and topical. Bateson offers educated commentary on a host of other subjects, as well. To give just a few examples:</p>
        <p>On depression: Bateson speculates that typical reactions to psychological stress may have been selected by an evolutionary process favoring docile women and aggressive men. ''More males respond to stress and alienation with aggression, more females sink into depression. . . . And just as controlled aggression makes good soldiers, mild depression may make obedient wives and daughters, resigned to circumscribed roles.'' However, today's culture requires quick thinking over traditional role enactment: ''We may be entering the first era in the history of civilization when a mild state of chronic unipolar depression . . . is not regarded as appropriate in the great mass of the populace.''</p>
        <p>On family structure: Comparing the nuclear family of modern Western cultures with the far more varied, multifaceted age and sex combinations typical of every other society in history, Bateson notes, ''Arguably we should see the nuclear family not as the ideal of family life but as a bare and fragile minimum.''</p>
        <p>On neoteny (an evolutionary quirk that gives humans small features and rapid learning curves throughout life, characteristics other apes lose after infancy): ''The ability to respond like a child may be the most precious inheritance of human evolution.''</p>
        <p>On death: Until recently, ''it has been relatively harmless for human beings to believe that death was somehow unnatural,'' since ''it was unnecessary to learn to welcome so reliable a guest.'' Today, however, we must include plans for dying into our plans for living, for medical science has placed more and more aspects of death under technological control, and ''wherever choice is possible, it is obligatory.''</p>
        <p>Toward the end of ''Full Circles, Overlapping Lives,'' Bateson recounts a struggle with chronic fatigue syndrome that temporarily rendered her unable to teach. Any effect on her writing must have been positive, for this book grows steadily more engrossing through the final page. It will leave readers feeling as though they're finishing a conversation with a wise and learned friend: satisfied, thoughtful and hoping to hear more from this perceptive observer of our continuing cultural transformation.</p>
        <p>Martha Beck is the author of ''Expecting Adam'' and ''Breaking Point.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Martha Beck is the author of ''Expecting Adam'' and ''Breaking Point.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
