<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Two Trees Grow in Brooklyn</title>
    <meta content="28QAQA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202787"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="Q &amp; A"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Q and A</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E3D71F3AF93BA15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="843" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Two Trees Grow in Brooklyn</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Q My mom lives in a Brooklyn condominium. She has owned her ground-floor apartment with a backyard for 12 years. She has two fruit trees: nectarine and mulberry. Both trees are big, and she loves them.  Recently, she got a letter from the board asking her to cut down one of the trees because it was ''imposing itself in the parking lot.'' The board added that if she did not respond to its request within 30 days the board would hire a tree-removal company to have the work done and then bill my mother. Can the board do this? . . . Christine Mark, Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>A Michael P. Graff, a Manhattan real estate lawyer, said that it is likely that when Ms. Mark's mother bought her apartment, the backyard space was described as a ''limited common element,'' or in some other way that would indicate that while the mother has the exclusive use of the space, the board retains some level of control over that use.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Q My mom lives in a Brooklyn condominium. She has owned her ground-floor apartment with a backyard for 12 years. She has two fruit trees: nectarine and mulberry. Both trees are big, and she loves them.  Recently, she got a letter from the board asking her to cut down one of the trees because it was ''imposing itself in the parking lot.'' The board added that if she did not respond to its request within 30 days the board would hire a tree-removal company to have the work done and then bill my mother. Can the board do this? . . . Christine Mark, Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>A Michael P. Graff, a Manhattan real estate lawyer, said that it is likely that when Ms. Mark's mother bought her apartment, the backyard space was described as a ''limited common element,'' or in some other way that would indicate that while the mother has the exclusive use of the space, the board retains some level of control over that use.</p>
        <p>Even if such a designation of the space was not stated, Mr. Graff said, the board would have a right to prohibit any use of the backyard that would detrimentally affect the common elements. ''This would include preventing a disturbance of the use of the parking lot,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Accordingly, Mr. Graff said, Ms. Mark's mother should respond to the board's letter by proposing a discussion of alternative methods of dealing with the problem. For example, he said, if the roots are damaging the pavement, it may be possible to solve the problem -- and save the trees -- by pruning the roots.</p>
        <p>If that is not possible, Mr. Graff said, and one or both trees have to be removed, it would appear that the board's threat to hold the unit owner responsible for the cost of removing the trees is somewhat harsh.</p>
        <p>''Their right to impose that charge is less clear than their right to require the removal,'' he said, explaining that the party ultimately responsible for the removal cost may depend on when the trees were planted.</p>
        <p>''If the trees were there when the condominium was originally declared, then I would argue that it would be the board's responsibility to bear the cost of removing them,'' Mr. Graff said. If they were planted later, with the express consent of the board, then it would seem fair to expect that the board should bear at least part of the removal cost, he said. If they were planted later, but without the consent of the board, he said, then the unit owner may indeed be responsible for their removal.</p>
        <p>Conflicts of Interest On Co-op Boards</p>
        <p>Q How do people in co-ops protect themselves from conflicts of interest among board members? Could a board oversee a renovation project if a board member was the contractor or architect for the project? What can a board do about abuses of this nature by board members? . . . M. B. Lee, Manhattan.</p>
        <p>A Howard Schechter, a Manhattan co-op lawyer, said that while the board is a co-op's first line of defense against improper conduct by individual board members, it is also responsible for awarding contracts that are in the best interests of the co-op.</p>
        <p>''It is possible that the contract described by the letter writer may be in the best interest of the corporation because of the unique talents or favorable price offered by the contractor or architect,'' Mr. Schechter said.</p>
        <p>And while a board would generally be better off avoiding the problems that could arise if the board member who acts as a contractor or architect does not perform the work as promised, there is nothing in the law that prohibits boards from awarding such contracts to board members.</p>
        <p>At the same time, Mr. Schechter said, the Business Corporation Law permits the board to revoke a contract between the co-op corporation and a company in which one of the co-op board members is a director or officer, or holds a substantial financial interest, unless certain formalities are followed.</p>
        <p>For example, he said, there must be full disclosure of the board member's interest in the company being hired, and the contract being awarded must be approved by the board without counting the interested board member's vote. Mr. Schechter said the bylaws of the co-op may include additional requirements.</p>
        <p>If the shareholders believe that the board is failing to act in good faith, he said, the primary remedy is to replace it at the next election. If a co-op has been damaged by a bad contract approved by the board, he said, the shareholders could initiate a suit against the board members who approved the contract, seeking to recover any money lost.</p>
        <p>Q &amp; A</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
