<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Where Boys Can Learn to Shape Up</title>
    <meta content="28LEIV$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202816"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Men</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">School of American Ballet</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York City Ballet</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leivick, Laura</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Men</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E1DC163DF93BA15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1774" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Where Boys Can Learn to Shape Up</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAURA LEIVICK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Leivick, Laura</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article profiles School of American Ballet, which has expanded its mandate from simply training dancers to also acting in loco parentis for students and has added special training program for male dancers; photos</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EVEN some of the harshest critics of Peter Martins's regime at New York City Ballet troop eagerly to the annual workshop performances of his company's academy, the School of American Ballet. Year after year, in the dancing of the latest crop of advanced students, the workshops present a glimpse of ballet's ideals.</p>
        <p>In the 17 years since Mr. Martins succeeded Balanchine as the company's ballet-master-in-chief and the school's chairman of faculty, his every move at the company has been debated. Changes at the school, however, go pretty much unremarked outside its sanctum in the Samuel B. and David Rose Building at Lincoln Center. The move in 1991 to those hushed new quarters, with dormitories for 64 students in the Meredith Willson Residence Hall above, marks the biggest institutional change in the Martins years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EVEN some of the harshest critics of Peter Martins's regime at New York City Ballet troop eagerly to the annual workshop performances of his company's academy, the School of American Ballet. Year after year, in the dancing of the latest crop of advanced students, the workshops present a glimpse of ballet's ideals.</p>
        <p>In the 17 years since Mr. Martins succeeded Balanchine as the company's ballet-master-in-chief and the school's chairman of faculty, his every move at the company has been debated. Changes at the school, however, go pretty much unremarked outside its sanctum in the Samuel B. and David Rose Building at Lincoln Center. The move in 1991 to those hushed new quarters, with dormitories for 64 students in the Meredith Willson Residence Hall above, marks the biggest institutional change in the Martins years.</p>
        <p>Today, this academy, established in 1934 to train ballet dancers, period, publishes its intention to act in loco parentis for the students and provides things like nutrition counseling. Beneath the recent revival of curiosity about the private lives of the school's students, triggered by scenes in Nicholas Hytner's new dance film, ''Center Stage,'' may lie plain dislike of what Lincoln Kirstein, co-founder of the school and company, celebrated as ballet's ''credo of self-denial at the moment when egos are inclined to feel their first selfhood.''</p>
        <p>The school under Mr. Martins has also been affected by the death of Kirstein, in 1996, and of teachers representing the full span of the Balanchine era -- Stanley Williams, Alexandra Danilova, Muriel Stuart and Elise Reiman. Mr. Martins has brought in guest teachers like Mikhail Baryshnikov; he recruited retired company dancers, including Peter Frame and Katrina Killian, and active dancers like Darci Kistler (his wife), Jock Soto and Peter Boal, for the faculty; and he asked others, like Kyra Nichols and Damian Woetzel, to pitch in as guest teachers. Mr. Martins himself teaches the advanced men on Wednesdays. ''When he walks into the studio and takes off the blazer, it's the most intimidating thing in the world,'' says one boy.</p>
        <p>Mr. Martins also made Kay Mazzo, a former partner who taught under Balanchine, his co-chairman of faculty. ''Kay is a woman whom I have always adored,'' Mr. Martins says. ''She has impeccable judgment, and she is a very, very fine person.'' The soft-spoken Ms. Mazzo loves her job but can't remember what it's called: ''Titles are for the birds,'' she says.</p>
        <p>As for the curriculum, such as it is -- the school has no written syllabus, just an oral tradition -- Mr. Martins has added classes in ballroom dance, mime, contemporary partnering techniques and weight training for the men. If he has a larger project in view, it seems to be evolving ad hoc: upgrading the training for men.</p>
        <p>In 1992, Mr. Martins began a special program for boys: the school announces its open auditions to 8- to 11-year-old boys in the city's public schools; classes in the children's division are no longer co-ed, and boys under 14 attend tuition-free (this year's tuition for girls ranged from $1,067 to $2,412); and they are allowed to wear shorts instead of tights. It is too soon to see the results of these changes, though for nearly a decade, most of the boys in the party scene in City Ballet's annual performances of ''The Nutcracker'' have been boys, not the disgruntled little girls of Christmases past.</p>
        <p>A dancer's training takes about 10 years, and S.A.B., unlike the state academies abroad, does not have a stable population: twice-weekly auditions are held at the school year-round, students outside the United States may send audition tapes, and an annual 25-city audition tour selects some 200 students for the summer session. There is a constant winnowing (perhaps 20 of the 200 summer kids will be invited to return in the fall). Of the current group of 29 advanced men, for example, only 7 have trained more or less exclusively at the school.</p>
        <p>This year, many of these hand-picked 14- to 19-year-olds will be featured in Balanchine's ''Stars and Stripes'' at the workshop performances Saturday and next Monday at the Juilliard Theater. One recent afternoon, Suki Schorer, one of Balanchine's appointees and a former City Ballet principal, was running a rehearsal for the all-male Second Regiment section (''Thunder and Gladiator'') like a high-strung drill sergeant.</p>
        <p>''I want to see the whole stage move!'' she shouted above the rousing Sousa march, sweeping her arm in a huge arc. The soloist leading the 12-boy regiment was Daniel Ulbricht, a cheerful 16-year-old from Florida now in his first term. He tore across the studio diagonally like a gymnast heading for a handspring, took off like a cannonball, hit a pose in midair -- knees tucked up, saluting briskly -- landed, ran to the far corner, turned smartly and did it again.</p>
        <p>The group ran the taxing six-minute dance straight through and marched off, eyes right. ''O.K.,'' said Ms. Schorer brightly; then she turned on a kid who showed up late, and didn't know the choreography, and was he chewing gum?</p>
        <p>Lincoln Kirstein likened S.A.B. to West Point with good reason. These boys work as if there's no tomorrow. Mr. Ulbricht describes his daily schedule: three academic classes at the Professional Performing Arts School (along with three independent-study classes); three S.A.B. classes; then rehearsals till as late as 9. Somehow the plan also accommodates appearances with the company, like his recent performances as one of the three Court Jesters in Mr. Martins's ''Sleeping Beauty.''</p>
        <p>For boys who like that sort of life, of course, that's just the sort of life they like: male enrollment at the school is at an all-time high, 82 out of a student body of 343. Yet ask Mr. Martins whether he's overhauling the boys' program at S.A.B., and he replies: ''I'm not. I'm just introducing our time, as one should, updating it.''</p>
        <p>Certainly there is nothing revisionist about sweetening the pot for young men in Balanchine's academy. Just as certainly, however, male dancing was not Balanchine's first priority; he was a ballerina man. ''Put 16 girls on a stage, and it's everybody -- the world,'' he said, famously. ''But put 16 boys, and it's always nobody.''</p>
        <p>Yet not only did important dancers like Edward Villella, Arthur Mitchell and Jacques d'Amboise emerge from S.A.B.; established stars from Mr. Martins himself to his teacher Erik Bruhn to Rudolf Nureyev and Mr. Baryshnikov beat down the door to dance for Balanchine.</p>
        <p>A belief in the stature of the Balanchine legacy lends both joy and anxiety to the school's task of preparing dancers to be civilized members of the ballet world. The charming Andrei Kramarevsky, a Balanchine hire known as Krammy, lets the top boys, a tuition-free class of 13 called ''special men,'' try the bravura steps one of them calls ''the things we see on the videotapes.''</p>
        <p>Looking sharp in shirts, slacks and jazz shoes, they join the other advanced and intermediate men to do the merengue with the advanced girls in ballroom class. Courtesy prevails: many teachers address the boys as ''Gentlemen''; in the courtly Mr. Boal's classes, you can hear a pin drop.</p>
        <p>The idea that the stylization variously called Balanchine technique and Balanchine style is enforced at the school is shrugged off by Ms. Mazzo. Hard-line classicists have long said that S.A.B. dancers overcross positions, overarticulate elbows and wrists, shift their hips out of alignment to raise the leg in extension and let their heels off the floor too soon in plie, the luxurious ready position that gives ballet steps their spring and lilt. ''I'd rather say it's a way of getting a dancer to move fast and make it look easy,'' she says. ''Details like how you use your arms are not even insisted on in Mr. B's choreography.''</p>
        <p>Everywhere you look at S.A.B., some danseur-in-the-rough is sorting out something, watching himself critically in the ubiquitous mirrors. Waiting for pas de deux class to begin, Mr. Ulbricht tries a pirouette and delivers eight perfect revolutions, then calmly closes fifth position. In Mr. Frame's weight-training class, intended to help the men avoid injury while partnering, he has them stand, face front and answer questions about their views on art. Asked which dancer inspires him, one boy chooses American Ballet Theater's Julio Bocca, whom he had just seen in the Broadway hit ''Fosse'': ''He was totally transformed. You can use your technique to do anything.'' And how would he apply this to his own work? ''You have to make every plie the most important thing in the world,'' he said.</p>
        <p>In a workshop ballet, he got a chance to make good. Nikolaj Hubbe, a City Ballet principal, was rehearsing ''Konservatoriet,'' an 1849 ballet by August Bournonville.</p>
        <p>The cast -- in this scene, 14 girls and 4 boys -- begins in first position, bras bas (their arms low and rounded), with a plie. To teach them the lovely Bournonville arm positions, Mr. Hubbe has them walk through whole passages of choreography, only indicating the dance steps, but doing the port de bras full-out. ''Don't allonger'' -- that is, elongate -- ''the arms and fingers,'' he tells them. They try again. ''Ah, when you do like this -- so, so soft and gentle -- it's heavenly,'' he responds. ''Now, let's try it with steps, but still elegant and gentle. Don't kick it!''</p>
        <p>Later, the four boys come forward, stand in fifth position and begin a difficult academic dance: brisk beats; quick, precise turns. One boy, a dark-haired, sober 15-year-old named David Blumenfeld, after a few corrections, executes a perfectly balanced triple attitude turn.</p>
        <p>''You're hired!'' Mr. Hubbe exclaims with a laugh, and the students join in. It's a joke with an edge because, for the older students, the workshop serves as an audition for City Ballet or the other companies that send scouts.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hubbe is called away for a moment, and while two boys start trying turns and coax a girl or two into partnering experiments, a few of the students take the opportunity to lie down on the floor, like puppies; one girl rests her head on a friend's flank, eyes open in plain fatigue.</p>
        <p>''We forget they are children,'' Mr. Hubbe says later. ''This is such a rigorous profession.''</p>
        <p>DANCE Laura Leivick is writing a book about ballet and literature for Yale University Press.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Laura Leivick is writing a book about ballet and literature for Yale University Press.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
