<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Sydney, First-Rate Fare in Casual Settings</title>
    <meta content="28TAB.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202778"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="CHOICE TABLES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sydney (Australia)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Santich, Barbara</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Columns/Choice Tables</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia/Sydney</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02EEDB1E3AF93BA15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2721" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Sydney, First-Rate Fare in Casual Settings</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA SANTICH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Santich, Barbara</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Barbara Santich Choice Tables article reviews casual eating places in Sydney; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SYDNEY, Australia's oldest, largest and arguably most vibrant and hedonistic capital, the Emerald City of David Williamson's play, could never be described as lacking in visitor attractions. From art to history -- Art Gallery of New South Wales, Museum of Contemporary Art, Hyde Park Barracks, Museum of Sydney -- the city offers a wealth of enriching experiences.</p>
        <p>But sometimes it's more pleasurable to simply stroll, with no particular purpose but perhaps a vague destination in mind, open to unexpected delights such as the sight and sound of tugs guiding a liner through the harbor, or an art installation in the empty ground floor of an office building.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SYDNEY, Australia's oldest, largest and arguably most vibrant and hedonistic capital, the Emerald City of David Williamson's play, could never be described as lacking in visitor attractions. From art to history -- Art Gallery of New South Wales, Museum of Contemporary Art, Hyde Park Barracks, Museum of Sydney -- the city offers a wealth of enriching experiences.</p>
        <p>But sometimes it's more pleasurable to simply stroll, with no particular purpose but perhaps a vague destination in mind, open to unexpected delights such as the sight and sound of tugs guiding a liner through the harbor, or an art installation in the empty ground floor of an office building.</p>
        <p>This selection of restaurants focuses on the more casual eating places, where reservations are not necessary and, in some cases, aren't taken. Each offers a taste of the city, starting with the gastronomic experience that is most quintessentially Sydney: a plate of rock oysters.</p>
        <p>Once plentiful around the rocky inlets of the harbor, where Aborigines feasted on them and 18th-century colonials enjoyed oyster picnics, today the Sydney rock oyster is cultivated in estuaries along the New South Wales coast. Typically smaller than the Pacific, its shell more convoluted, it demands nothing but a drop or two of lemon juice to bring out its intense, briny tang.</p>
        <p>Quay Bar</p>
        <p>At Quay Bar, across the street from Circular Quay and its harbor ferries, oysters are shucked to order and, most important, not rinsed, so that they still carry all the savor of the sea. Natural oysters come on a bed of sea salt with wedges of lemon, a bowl of the traditional mayonnaise-based cocktail sauce and warm slices of lightly toasted rye bread; or accompanied by a vodka-lime vinaigrette.</p>
        <p>Quay Bar occupies the forecourt of the gracious old Customs House, but around the corner in Loftus Street is its Oyster Bar, whose high ceilings, tall mirrors, old-fashioned palms and dark wood evoke the old oyster bars once clustered here. Both offer the same swift service and the same menu of sandwiches, salads and uncomplicated main courses, such as fish and chips or lamb cutlets. In addition to wines by the glass, a good selection of draft beers is available.</p>
        <p>Post Brasserie</p>
        <p>There is also an oyster bar at Post -- in this instance more accurately described as a crustacea bar, featuring not only oysters (three different varieties) but also fresh prawns, crabs, lobsters and yabbies (crayfish), to be enjoyed in a variety of preparations or in a fruits de mer platter, either at the marble-topped bar or at the white-clothed tables of the brasserie.</p>
        <p>Post is housed in the basement of the former post office, at the metaphorical heart of Sydney, recently transformed into a temple of gastronomy for perfect fruits, cosseted cheeses and silvery seafood. Its multipurpose menu caters to all appetites, from a cold selection for a starter or light lunch -- vitello tonnato with celery heart salad, for example -- to pasta, fish and substantial main courses. Reasonably priced wines are available by the glass or bottle; Hunter Valley, the wine region to the north of Sydney, is only sparsely represented but Tyrrell's  semillon is a perfect example.</p>
        <p>As appetizer, a shared charcuterie plate presented two different kinds of raw ham and two different sausages, accompanied by a small dish of salsa verde -- more a pale green mayonnaise than the traditional Italian sauce. Pea, spinach and mascarpone risotto with poached egg was delicate and creamy, the rice perfectly al dente; duck confit came with crisply grilled skin on a mound of borlotti beans cooked with bacon dice and thyme. Post's desserts feature familiar favorites such as bread and butter pudding as well as a superb passionfruit sorbet among a selection of ices.</p>
        <p>Smartly uniformed staff in charcoal shirts, well tuned to the requirements of businessmen from the offices above, provide swift and efficient service.</p>
        <p>Bistro Moncur</p>
        <p>A few miles to the east of the city, in Woollahra, is a sedate environment of leafy streets, decorous terrace houses and sophisticated shopping. Along Queen Street are fashion boutiques, art galleries and antiques dealers, including a specialist in antique corkscrews at The Art of Wine and Food. If these aren't enough enticement to venture out of town, there is also Bistro Moncur in the Woollahra Hotel.</p>
        <p>Damien Pignolet's restaurant has long been acknowledged as one of Sydney's best, for its style, service and the sheer quality of its cuisine. Under the supervision of Jason Robert, head chef, French bistro-style dishes are impeccable in execution, with no extraneous accessories to mar the purity of first-rate ingredients. The room, too, is elegantly simple, a band of mirror along one wall and a mural of stylized silhouettes, sitting casually at table, on the other. The philosophy of restraint extends to the staff, informed and responsive yet with a sense of humor.</p>
        <p>The basic menu of around 10 first and main courses is supplemented by  specials, which included, on a recent visit, a generous portion of soft, creamy-beige rillettes of rabbit. As an entree, the salad of cauliflower, golden beetroot, cucumber and radish with crisp toasted almonds and mustard dressing was an object lesson in harmony. On a warm summer evening, a chilled Spanish rose was an ideal accompaniment.</p>
        <p>One of the most popular of Bistro Moncur's dishes is its pure pork sausage, robust and rustic, served with potato puree and lyonnaise onions. Another bistro classic, minute steak marchand de vin, consisted of thin disks of excellent beef with a rich, well reduced sauce and a pile of crisp shoestring chips. The undisputed star of this meal, however, was the seafood boudin of flathead and prawns, a pale, skinless sausage of ethereal texture, delicate yet distinctive in flavor.</p>
        <p>Bistro Moncur does not take reservations, which can sometimes mean a wait in the bar. On weeknights, however, diners arriving before 7:30 can usually be assured of a table.</p>
        <p>BBQ King</p>
        <p>Seemingly a world away in Sydney's Chinatown is BBQ King, its narrow front concealing a maze of interconnected dining areas on two levels, differentiated by the presence of tablecloths (upstairs) or lack thereof (downstairs).</p>
        <p>Since the gold-rush days of the mid-19th century, Sydney has had its Chinatown, a loosely defined area close to the old fruit and vegetable markets. Dixon Street now marks the official Chinatown, though the whole Haymarket area abounds in Chinese restaurants, bakeries, jewelers and supermarkets full of unexpected treasures.</p>
        <p>Despite its expansive menu of over 200 dishes, BBQ King is a very basic, unsophisticated place; tables turn over several times on busy evenings. As the name suggests, it specializes in roast and barbecued meats, roast duck in particular, displayed in the window of the adjacent take-out section. Roast duck can be ordered with soy sauce, sweet and sour sauce, special sauce, or on a bed of dry noodles; it arrives chopped into small pieces to be eaten with chopsticks, its thin, crisp, slightly sweet skin contrasting with the dark, tender flesh.</p>
        <p>Roast duck needs no other accompaniment than a dish of leafy greens -- such as choy sum with oyster sauce or Chinese spinach well seasoned with chopped garlic -- but fried bean curd tossed with chili salt provides a gentle complement.</p>
        <p>The restaurant serves only bottled wines, a modest selection, but it offers a good range of beers.</p>
        <p>Service tends to be fast and furious, and you might need to make several requests for more water for the teapot, for example, but that is part of the fun of eating at BBQ King.</p>
        <p>Wockpool</p>
        <p>Less than 15 minutes' walk away is Wockpool, a very different style of Chinese -- or more precisely, pan-Asian -- restaurant. One of the clutch of restaurants at the southern (Cockle Bay) end of Darling Harbour, it takes full advantage of its waterfront position, with most of the tables in the glass house (to the right of the entrance) and on the terrace opposite offering prime views.</p>
        <p>Wockpool has separate lunch and dinner menus that vary from day to day, according to the availability and quality of seafood in the market. Both offer a serious selection of Chinese-  and Asian-influenced dishes; the lunch menu, however, also includes a range of modestly priced soups and noodle dishes, such as wonton soup and stir-fried hokkien noodles with barbecued pork, which are absent from the dinner menu.</p>
        <p>Though diners eat Chinese style with chopsticks and small porcelain bowls, wine is served in long-stemmed, ample glasses. Wockpool takes wine very seriously and boasts an excellent cellar of Australian and imported wines, together with a  knowledgeable staff for guidance; a small number of house wines are available by the glass. Friends and I tried a rich, dark, moderately priced  1996 Brown Brothers graciano, a new Australian varietal from a grape once widely grown in Spain.</p>
        <p>On a balmy summer evening recently, our dinner began with deep-fried prawn wontons and sung choi bao of quail, crisp lettuce leaf cups holding quickly cooked minced quail with finely slivered vegetables.</p>
        <p>We followed it with a crab omelet, one of the specialties of Wockpool's co-owner, Neil Perry; a light puffed pillow, generously filled with a mixture of crab meat, snow pea sprouts and bean sprouts. The stir-fried beef fillet with black bean and pickled ginger was much more forceful, the black bean saltiness dominating yet not subduing rich beef flavors. Dinner ended with coffee and exquisite little chocolate truffles.</p>
        <p>Sydney Fish Market</p>
        <p>With the harbor at its heart and bounded by beaches, Sydney has a passion for the sea -- surfing, yachting, fishing -- and for its harvests.</p>
        <p>For the best choice of fresh fish and seafood, discerning cooks head for the Sydney Fish Market, second biggest in the world and so popular just before Christmas that it remains open around the clock.</p>
        <p>On weekdays, if you get there early -- around 7 a.m. -- you can watch the spectacle of the fish auction, but for a closer look at the catch, wander around any of the displays within the market, marveling at huge swordfish and tuna, live crabs and yabbies, iridescent trout and translucent salmon, expertly sliced for sashimi.</p>
        <p>As well as raw fish and seafood, most of the seafood retailers also offer take-out -- clear plastic packs of sushi ($4) and sashimi ($3.25) from De Costi; barbecued baby octopus and prawn kebabs outside Musumeci; more sushi and sashimi from the Sushi Bar; barramundi and chips and salads from Nicholas Seafood; and a complete seafood menu from Peter's Fish Market, from a dozen oysters natural ($6.50) to tuna teriyaki ($6) to lobster mornay ($17.50).</p>
        <p>Cutlery is plastic, napkins are paper, and plates are plastic foam cartons, but this is fast food at its finest, quality and freshness assured. Make your selection, take your place in the line, pay the cashier, then wait for 10 minutes or less for your number to be called.</p>
        <p>In the meantime, you can duck into the liquor store on the other side of the central aisle and choose a bottle of wine or beer; it will be opened for you on the spot, and for an additional 20 cents you can buy small plastic glasses. If you want bread, cheese or any other delicacies for an impromptu picnic, they're available at the adjacent deli.</p>
        <p>Thus provisioned, choose a table on the wharf alongside the market, or find a place on the lawn beneath the palms. The view is free.</p>
        <p>Arena Bar and Bistro</p>
        <p>For a more sophisticated market experience, an open-air Growers' Market operates each Wednesday, from 1 to around 9 p.m., at the Fox Studios complex, Moore Park, a few miles from the city center. About 20 stalls offer beautifully fresh ingredients -- eggs laid the day before! --  direct from grower or producer. You can taste your way around the market -- fresh raspberries, sourdough bread, farmhouse cheeses, olives and olive oils, jams and mustards, kangaroo pies, traditional cordials, hand-made fudges, corn-fed chicken and pasture-fed beef.</p>
        <p>In the same general area of what was, until recently, the site of the annual agricultural show are now a number of new restaurants, including Arena Bar and Bistro. At ground level, it looks directly onto the produce stalls, which, under lights in the evening, give the impression of a traditional arcaded market in rural France.</p>
        <p>Arena offers both outside and inside dining. The spacious interior is decorated in neutral tones and offers a choice of seating -- banquettes along one wall, comfortable webbed-canvas dining chairs or cosy sofas for two. At one end of the room is the sleek, stainless-steel, open kitchen.</p>
        <p>After only two months, the restaurant still seemed to be feeling its way, but service was prompt and correct. The small wine list affords choice, with a good selection sold by the glass; Trentham Estate viognier (about $3.50) was an interesting example of this Rhone variety recently introduced to Australia.</p>
        <p>The simplest dishes probably succeed best -- in late summer (our winter), a big white bowl of simply dressed tomato wedges, or a warm tart of oil-roasted seasonal vegetables (zucchini, peppers, tomatoes) with curd cheese, surrounded by a salad of arugula, or pan-fried kingfish fillets with a Michel Guerard-style sauce vierge, tiny dice of peeled tomatoes with olive oil, garlic and fresh herbs. Salads and vegetable accompaniments are ordered separately. A simple panna cotta dessert worked well; the usual vanilla-sugar flavoring replaced by ginger-palm sugar, the usual berries by mango slivers and cubes of fresh coconut.</p>
        <p>Bill of fare: oysters, inevitably</p>
        <p>Some of these restaurants have outdoor tables where smoking is permitted; others, such as Bistro Moncur, allow smoking after a certain hour. None require reservations, and some don't take them. The country and city codes for Sydney are 61-2.</p>
        <p>Quay Bar, 31 Alfred Street (Oyster Bar entrance around the corner in Loftus Street), Circular Quay; 9251 3305. The Oyster Bar seats 63. Open daily for breakfast, lunch and dinner. Oysters are $11.75 a dozen; light meals for two $8.75; main courses for two $16 to $23. Most wines $15.</p>
        <p>Post Brasserie, 1 Martin Place;  922 9744. Seats 150. Open for dinner  Monday to Saturday, lunch Monday to Friday. Light lunch dishes for two  $16.50 to $21; two-course lunch for two $40; desserts $4.50. Wines $13 to $21. Reservations advised for lunch.</p>
        <p>Bistro Moncur, Woollahra Hotel, 116 Queen Street, Woollahra; 9363 2519. Seats 90. Open for lunch Tuesday to Sunday, dinner daily Entrees or light meals for two $16.50 to $23.50; three-course meal for two $47 to $62. Most wines $15 to $30.</p>
        <p>BBQ King, 18-20 Goulburn Street;  9267 2586. Seats 200. Open for lunch and dinner daily. Dinner for two, $32. Most wines $15.</p>
        <p>Wockpool, Panasonic Imax Theatre (entrance off Wheat Road), Darling Harbour; 9211 9888. Open daily for lunch and dinner. Lunchtime noodles for two $14 to $16.50; two-course meal $25 to $30 a person. Wines from $15.</p>
        <p>Sydney Fish Market, Blackwattle Bay, Pyrmont; 9660 1611. Lunch only, daily. Prices range from $4 for a tray of sushi to $5.25 to $6 for grilled fish plus chips and $6.50 for one dozen oysters; bottled wines from liquor store, from $6.</p>
        <p>Arena Bar and Bistro, Shop 212, Bent Street, Fox Studios Australia, Moore Park; 9361 3930. Seats 50 inside, 50 outside. Open daily for lunch and dinner. Entrees or light meals for two $13 to $16.50; three-course meal for two $47 to $56. Most wines $12 to $27.</p>
        <p>CHOICE TABLES BARBARA SANTICH is author of ''The Original Mediterranean Cuisine'' (Chicago Review Press).</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">BARBARA SANTICH is author of ''The Original Mediterranean Cuisine'' (Chicago Review Press).</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
