<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lights, Videos and Photos in a Biennial</title>
    <meta content="28ART.$20" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202922"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ART REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">College of New Rochelle</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zimmer, William</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07EFD6153DF93BA15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1007" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lights, Videos and Photos in a Biennial</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM ZIMMER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zimmer, William</byline>
      <dateline>NEW ROCHELLE</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William Zimmer reviews Westchester Biennial 2000 art show at College of New Rochelle's Castle Gallery; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''THE Westchester Biennial 2000,'' now at the Castle Gallery at the College of New Rochelle here, simply doesn't live up to its billing; in fact, it falls painfully short.</p>
        <p>There may not be a hard-and-fast definition of a biennial, but it implies a big show that is also an event -- something of a splash. With one stunningly large exception, the art in this show is on the small side and quite modest and tame.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''THE Westchester Biennial 2000,'' now at the Castle Gallery at the College of New Rochelle here, simply doesn't live up to its billing; in fact, it falls painfully short.</p>
        <p>There may not be a hard-and-fast definition of a biennial, but it implies a big show that is also an event -- something of a splash. With one stunningly large exception, the art in this show is on the small side and quite modest and tame.</p>
        <p>But what most lowers great expectations is that it contains only nine artists. A biennial should be a survey, a temperature-taking of the geographical area chosen as its boundaries.</p>
        <p>The image persists of curators knocking themselves out visiting studios to discover significant work. The process here was to have a panel of judges pick artists out of 75 applicants.</p>
        <p>Even with only a handful of artists, a trend seems to emerge. Three of them use montage, a process related to collage. In the montages here, however, the whole that is created from bringing disparate materials together is not the result of pasting bits of paper. It is more sophisticated, as it makes use of video and photography.</p>
        <p>The most arresting work, a piece that almost sucks in the viewer, is ''Wave Transformations'' by Rosalind Schneider of Irvington. Ms. Schneider uses a balloon 10 feet in diameter for her video screen. Sheer size alone raises her visibility far above the other artists, but the work is also very artful in a way that is both spontaneous and calculated. Water imagery courses across her globe, sometimes calmly but also cataclysmically.</p>
        <p>Sections of the production feature contrasting imagery similar to a screen within a screen. Although elaborate technology is behind the work, it involves the audience through its evident simplicity.</p>
        <p>''Digital Poems, Odd Year, 1999'' by Yechiam Gal of White Plains uses a more conventional monitor; there is a bench in front of it for the audience. But this setup provokes restlessness. It mimics watching television, and Mr. Gal's overlapping images are severely constricted by this format.</p>
        <p>The art world at large has found an obvious solution to the difficulty of holding an audience for a video work, and that solution is to employ huge screens that seem to embrace the viewer. Whatever the merits of Mr. Gal's work, it looks like a relic compared with Ms. Schneider's work with which it shares a room.</p>
        <p>The third montage artist, Renata Rainer, is the kind of well-known Westchester artist with an impressive track record who should be a major part of a meaningful biennial. Ms. Rainer of Irvington is a teacher of photography and a frequent curator of shows. Her medium of 30 years is black-and-white photography, and she has perfected exposing two or more negatives on a single sheet of paper. The results are a kind of nonjarring surrealism.</p>
        <p>Among the four painters represented, Jenna Pallio of Yonkers is the strongest. Her technique involves achieving a hazy look like a blurred photograph, which serves her mildly anxious content. ''Spring Cleaning'' depicts a woman standing in front of what is probably a bathroom mirror. The deliberate fuzziness often makes for ambiguity, but the implication is that her head, her psyche is in need of a good cleaning. Ms. Pallio's strongest contribution is ''Monday.'' The familiar content of a society driving back to work is visually clearer than that of the other paintings and a genuine sensation, but the artist has fun with a melange of colored flashing lights.</p>
        <p>The show is satisfying in those moments where the work is simple and thought out. This is one recipe for beauty, and the paintings of Patricia Spargell of Larchmont follow it. Her four rather gauzy abstractions nevertheless contain bold patterning, which seems to disappear beneath the surface and then reassert itself.</p>
        <p>The leitmotif of Katherine Hu-Fan's ''Extasis'' is a few words that begin with ''ex'' scattered across a diptych format. The painting is, appropriate to her language game, expressionistic; but it's finally chaotic, and the viewer remains clueless. Ms. Hu-Fan, who lives in Ossining, might have been helped if she were represented by more works than this one; they might have clarified her intentions.</p>
        <p>The paintings with commonplace domestic content by Joseph Cooke of Scarsdale are nicely done in their own right, but images of mundane egg cartons and cookware are perfect illustrations of this show's lack of the heft expected of a biennial.</p>
        <p>Art about other art is a commonplace, too, but Marcy B. Freedman of Croton-on Hudson evokes a couple of the hoary 20th-century cliches, Duchamp's mustachioed ''Mona Lisa'' and a self-portrait by Frida Kahlo, as backgrounds for written phrases, which she says touch on the female psyche. The one-liners in these pieces, from what she calls her ''Tough Cookie'' series, are livelier than her overused backgrounds. But another example, based on work by the controversial contemporary photographer Andreas Serrano, isn't any more galvanizing.</p>
        <p>The female psyche resides somewhere in two large ceramic sculptures by Grace Powers Fraioli of Rye. Two half-length figures, who are seemingly in meditation, comprise ''Sisters II.'' The artist said the work is about the special relationship between siblings. The specialness must be deep in the clay, for externally these naked sisters, who are draped with a few large leaves, are the kind of eccentrics one wants to avoid.</p>
        <p>''The Westchester Biennial 2000'' is at the Castle Gallery at the College of New Rochelle through June 11. The number to call for information is 654-5423.</p>
        <p>ART REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
