<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Revisiting an Impetuous Yet Probing Virtuoso on CD</title>
    <meta content="28HORO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202814"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Horowitz, Joseph</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arrau, Claudio (1903-91)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E7DC163DF93BA15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1396" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Revisiting an Impetuous Yet Probing Virtuoso on CD</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSEPH HOROWITZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Horowitz, Joseph</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>rivisiting an impetuous yet probing virtuoso on cd**Newly released CD's of performances by pianist Claudio Arrau evidence an exceptionally fruitful and eventful artistic life cycle; Arrau's career reviewed; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DURING the 20th century, a special glamour surrounded concert pianists. Franz Liszt, the progenitor of the piano recital a century before, was, of course, the king of this species. But Liszt, who stopped touring at 35, was also a major composer and an important teacher and conductor. The performance specialist, championing previous generations of canonized composers, was a 20th-century phenomenon, embodied by such keyboard luminaries as Vladimir Horowitz, Rudolf Serkin and Sviatoslav Richter: recreative interpreters divorced from the creative act.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the purest exemplars of the solo pianist were Arthur Rubinstein, and Claudio Arrau, who may be reheard in a recent flurry of recordings. Unlike Serkin, Rubinstein and Arrau were not major pedagogues. Unlike Richter, they rarely performed chamber music. Unlike Horowitz, they maintained an uninterrupted schedule of recitals and concertos, tirelessly visiting the musical capitals of the world, performing more than 100 times a season: a rarefied calling.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DURING the 20th century, a special glamour surrounded concert pianists. Franz Liszt, the progenitor of the piano recital a century before, was, of course, the king of this species. But Liszt, who stopped touring at 35, was also a major composer and an important teacher and conductor. The performance specialist, championing previous generations of canonized composers, was a 20th-century phenomenon, embodied by such keyboard luminaries as Vladimir Horowitz, Rudolf Serkin and Sviatoslav Richter: recreative interpreters divorced from the creative act.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the purest exemplars of the solo pianist were Arthur Rubinstein, and Claudio Arrau, who may be reheard in a recent flurry of recordings. Unlike Serkin, Rubinstein and Arrau were not major pedagogues. Unlike Richter, they rarely performed chamber music. Unlike Horowitz, they maintained an uninterrupted schedule of recitals and concertos, tirelessly visiting the musical capitals of the world, performing more than 100 times a season: a rarefied calling.</p>
        <p>Rubinstein's public career lasted 82 years; he gave his final recital and made his last recordings at 89. Arrau's career, strangely enough, also spanned 82 years; he last played in public at 86 and recorded at 87. It seems safe to predict that no concert pianist will again pursue a comparable regime.</p>
        <p>Liszt proclaimed, ''Le concert, c'est moi.'' The Rubinstein experience radiated joie de vivre. Arrau embodied scenarios of suffering and redemption. His life story, stranger than fiction (unless by Garcia Marquez), mapped an exotic and tortuous odyssey that was itself a source of fascination, not least for a young New York Times critic -- this writer -- whose first book, in 1982, was a study of Arrau the man and musician.</p>
        <p>Arrau was born in 1903 in Chillan, Chile, a dusty seven-hour train ride from Santiago. His earliest memory was of his home caving in during an earthquake. The ''Chilean Mozart,'' he read music (and scribbled clefs and notes) before he could read words. At 8, a national celebrity, he was sent abroad with a government stipend. He wound up in Berlin, the favorite pupil of Martin Krause, himself a pupil of Liszt. He played for kings and queens, and under Nikisch and Steinbach.</p>
        <p>Krause, a surrogate father, died in 1918. Arrau refused to submit to another teacher. In postwar Berlin, his career as a prodigy collapsed. He supported himself and his mother, sister and aunt by giving lessons; the family was reduced to pawning the necklaces and bracelets with which he had once been showered by royalty. With the help of psychoanalysis, he arduously consolidated a mature artistic identity.</p>
        <p>World War II drove Arrau to the United States and a keyboard culture, crowned by Horowitz, into which he did not fit. He lived in Douglaston, Queens. He died in Munich. He was buried in Chillan.</p>
        <p>By the late 1970's, when I undertook my ''Conversations With Arrau,'' he had begun to retreat into a world without words. More than ever, his world was music, and it ensnared him absolutely. To see and hear him perform the Liszt Sonata was a frightening experience. Then, in 1989, his wife of 52 years died. He told friends he would never perform again, and he never did.</p>
        <p>I had lost touch with Arrau by the time he died in 1991. My collection of Arrau LP's gathered dust for more than a decade. But the recent spate of Arrau CD's reanimated my interest. ''Claudio Arrau: The Early Years'' (Marston 52023-2; two CD's) includes everything Arrau recorded from 1921 to 1939. And Philips's Great Pianists of the 20th Century series includes three Arrau sets (456 706-2, 456 709-2, 456 712-2): six CD's with recordings extending from 1928 to 1990.</p>
        <p>Though the repertory on these discs -- embracing Albeniz, Bach, Balakirev, Busoni (an unforgettable 1928 version of the ''Carmen'' Fantasy), Debussy, Granados, Mozart and Stravinsky -- is remarkably catholic, Arrau's core affinities included Chopin, Liszt and Schumann at both ends of his long career. Comparing early and late Arrau in the same music, I again find myself gripped by evidence of an exceptionally fruitful and eventful artistic life cycle.</p>
        <p>Of the early recordings, the longest is of Schumann's ''Carnaval'' (1939). This is a ''modern'' performance, literal and straightforward. Unlike Edwin Fischer, also a Krause pupil, Arrau does not rewrite dynamics or poetically blur rests. Unlike Fischer, he is an impetuous virtuoso. In fact, this is a dazzling ''Carnaval.'' But it is not, like Rachmaninoff's famously diabolical version of 1929, specifically personal.</p>
        <p>To judge from recordings, Arrau did not acquire a highly distinctive interpretive signature until he was in his 60's. This is when he began probing every musical crevice, burrowing under and around the written note to extract expression. The outcome was complex: slower tempos, grander rubatos and, in profusion, the accents pianists call agogics: stresses produced by delayed attack. Arrau's style grew microscopically detailed. The straight lines of his earlier interpretations acquired curves and detours.</p>
        <p>All this would have proved anarchic but for three consolidating features of the Arrau style. First, rubatos aside, Arrau remained a dogged literalist. Second, he retained his youthful facility: he mastered the performer's art of combining poised physical relaxation with maximum emotional expenditure. (His recommended books included Eugen Herrigel's ''Zen in the Art of Archery.'') Third, he commanded a liquid piano sonority, unsurpassed for tonal depth and fullness of texture. No other pianist could flood a great space with sounds as luminous and majestic.</p>
        <p>For some, Arrau's marriage of refinement and angst was perverse or ponderous. For others, Arrau was revelatory. A performance like his 1973 version of the Chopin Preludes (in the Great Pianists collection) does not sound like any Chopin the composer might have imagined. Discussing this music, Arrau used words like ''desolation,''  ''exasperation,''  ''desperation'' and, for the opening C major salvo, ''orgasmic.'' The dark opulence of Arrau's tonal palette and the 10-fingered breadth of articulation forge a tragedy of epic proportions.</p>
        <p>Of the other performances in the Great Pianists sets, Chopin's F minor Fantasy (1977) and Brahms's ''Paganini Variations'' (1974) are distinctively regal. The Liszt Sonata (1970) and Beethoven's ''Waldstein'' Sonata (1963) and ''Emperor'' Concerto (1984), all Arrau specialties, were recorded too early or too late.</p>
        <p>Arrau, who could claim no national cultural identity, took pride in his eclecticism. But his later style -- like those of the conductors Toscanini and Klemperer, also fanatic literalists -- formidably (yet unwittingly) personalized everything he touched. That said, the composer he most inhabited was Liszt.</p>
        <p>He utterly lacked Lisztian irony or ease. His repugnance for pianistic display canceled the fun of the Hungarian Rhapsodies. Yet the Arrau sound -- its velvet blues and blacks -- ennobled Liszt. And Liszt's religious strivings found in Arrau a true believer, immune to sham. From Krause, Arrau inherited a reverence for Liszt the man. He even portrayed Liszt in a 1936 Mexican film biography, ''Sueno de Amor,'' and wept playing the final scene.</p>
        <p>Rubinstein said of Busoni that he made Liszt's compositions ''sound even more important than they actually were.'' So it was with Arrau (who heard and worshiped Busoni). The Great Pianists CD's include two indelible examples.</p>
        <p>The first is a 1971 recording of a late and obscure paraphrase of themes from ''Aida'': not a medley, but a concentrated exploration of several ''Egyptian'' numbers and the final duet. On the page, this music looks unprepossessing. In Arrau's hands, it is grandly erotic: ''Tristan'' revisited.</p>
        <p>The second example, a 1976 recording of the ''Transcendental Etude''  ''Chasse-Neige,'' defines Arrau's greatness in microcosm. The vortex of shuddering, writhing tremolos peaks tremendously, then recedes in exhaustion. The turbulence of Romantic introspection and the pathos of Romantic retrospection are made unbearably real. The combination of visceral intensity and pianistic integrity -- every tremolo is thick with incident -- is shattering. The performance is a fearless act of surrender.</p>
        <p>Remembering Arrau, listening to his seven decades of recordings, I mainly recall his humility.</p>
        <p>MUSIC Joseph Horowitz's 1982 book ''Conversations With Arrau'' is now available as ''Arrau on Music and Performance'' (Dover).</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Joseph Horowitz's 1982 book ''Conversations With Arrau'' is now available as ''Arrau on Music and Performance'' (Dover).</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
