<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Report Sees Dangerously High Smog Levels</title>
    <meta content="28OZON" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202886"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ozone</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Putnam County (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Orange County (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">American Lung Assn</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brenner, Elsa</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E2D9143DF93BA15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="567" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Report Sees Dangerously High Smog Levels</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELSA BRENNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brenner, Elsa</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>American Lung Assn releases report predicting dangerously high ozone levels this summer in Westchester, Putnam and Orange counties, NY (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THOUSANDS of residents of Westchester, Putnam and Orange Counties will face ''dangerously high smog levels'' this summer, the American Lung Association said in a report released last week.</p>
        <p>Children and the elderly will be most affected, according to the report, which gave failing air quality grades to the three Hudson Valley counties. The report did not rate Rockland County because there are no monitoring stations there.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THOUSANDS of residents of Westchester, Putnam and Orange Counties will face ''dangerously high smog levels'' this summer, the American Lung Association said in a report released last week.</p>
        <p>Children and the elderly will be most affected, according to the report, which gave failing air quality grades to the three Hudson Valley counties. The report did not rate Rockland County because there are no monitoring stations there.</p>
        <p>From 1996 to 1998, the report said, there were 24 days in Westchester and 19 each in Putnam and Orange when ozone levels reached unhealthy levels. The Bronx also received a failing grade. Only Herkimer County, which did not experience any unhealthy levels of ozone during that period, was graded ''A.''</p>
        <p>''The problem isn't going away,'' said Dr. George P. Maguire, a pulmonary physician and a former president of the board of the American Lung Association of Hudson Valley. Observing that the number of smog violations increased in New York State to 205 last summer from 80 in 1996, he predicted that this summer would be as bad or worse than last year for those sensitive to ozone. The problem is likely to continue, he said, until industrial and automotive emissions are reduced.</p>
        <p>Ozone exposure often leads to asthma episodes, shortness of breath, chest pain when inhaling deeply and wheezing and coughing. Long-term exposure can permanently damage lung tissue and result in the loss of lung function.</p>
        <p>It is estimated that between 20 and 30 percent of all children under 6 suffer from asthma, said Dr. Allen J. Dozor, chief of pediatric pulmonology at the Children's Hospital of Westchester Medical Center and New York Medical College in Valhalla. ''Many, many children have been having trouble breathing,'' said Dr. Dozor, whose department sees from 30 to 40 new pediatric asthma cases a week. ''Patients are pouring into the medical center,'' Dr. Dozor said, adding that many families moved out of the city to escape bad air, only to discover serious problems in the Hudson Valley as well.</p>
        <p>In Westchester, 172,666 residents under 14 are considered at risk this summer; of those, 12,690 suffer from asthma. As summer approaches, doctors and health officials warn that even those people who are not considered at risk can experience some pulmonary distress and constriction of airways on days when ozone levels peak.</p>
        <p>Ozone is a highly reactive form of oxygen , which results primarily from the action of sunlight on hydrocarbons and nitrogen oxides emitted in fuel combustion. Ozone levels typically rise between May and October, when higher temperatures and increased sunlight combine with the stagnant atmospheric conditions associated with ozone air pollution.</p>
        <p>Mary Landrigan, a spokeswoman for the county's Health Department, recommends that on ozone-alert days, ''when you just can't seem to get a breath of air,'' people exercising outdoors should confine activities to the morning or evening hours when ozone levels tend to be lower.</p>
        <p>The Health Department also suggests that travelers seek alternatives to driving whenever possible on such days and use public transportation, telecommuting or car pooling.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
