<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Yearlong Search for That First House</title>
    <meta content="28COV.$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202856"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Peekskill (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leder, Michelle</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/Upstate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E1D6173DF93BA15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2939" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Yearlong Search for That First House</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHELLE LEDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Leder, Michelle</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Michelle Leder article on the ups and downs of her and her husband's yearlong search for their first house; they finally bought a house in Peekskill, NY, for $215,000; drawing; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BY the numbers, the median price for a single-family starter home in the New York region should be about $188,275, according to the National Association of Realtors.</p>
        <p>And then there's reality.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BY the numbers, the median price for a single-family starter home in the New York region should be about $188,275, according to the National Association of Realtors.</p>
        <p>And then there's reality.</p>
        <p>As scores of first-time buyers know (and more are  finding out as the spring house-hunting season bumps along), finding a house that costs less than $250,000 --  more than 32 percent above the median -- is becoming increasingly difficult. And if the house needs to be within, say, an hour's commute to Midtown Manhattan, it borders on the impossible. Indeed, real estate agents say that they are steering a growing number of first-time house-hunters toward condominiums and co-ops or two-family homes, often against the buyer's wishes. Those that refuse to give up on the single-family dream are being directed to outlying areas where the commute to Midtown can run an hour and a half or more each way.</p>
        <p>I know this from first-hand experience. In the last year, my husband, Scott Cooper, and I have searched the New York area for our first home. This has not been a part-time job. Most weekends, we would spend both Saturday and Sunday actively hunting. And when a promising listing became available during the week, I would frequently drop whatever I was doing and run out -- even when it meant driving an hour or more.</p>
        <p>Together -- sometimes with our parents tagging along -- we have looked at more than 100 houses in eight  counties, from Bergen through Rockland and Dutchess to Fairfield, worked with more than a dozen real estate agents, bid on six houses (some several times) and paid for two home inspections. We looked at houses whose prices ranged from $99,000 to $379,000. Gradually, we began increasing the amount we were willing to spend, while at the same time crossing things off the wish list  every how-to book tells first-timers to make.</p>
        <p>Though those same books say that looking for a first home is supposed to be fun, they clearly didn't envision a market like this. For us, it became a joyless weekly chore, like doing the laundry or going grocery shopping, only much less productive.</p>
        <p>When we first began this process in March 1999, we were like any other idealistic couple in their early 30's.  Tired of renting, we couldn't wait to head off to Home Depot and start spackling away. But as spring turned into summer and then into fall, we grew more and more cynical. We thought we would never find a house. Several  times -- usually after one of our bids was rejected -- we contemplated giving up and waiting for the market to cool down.</p>
        <p>Despite the lack of buying power, first-timers like us remain a critical part of the market. ''Unless there's an active first-time market, the whole thing collapses like a bunch of dominoes,'' said Walt Molony, a spokesman for the National Association of Realtors, in Washington.</p>
        <p>The association defines a starter home as one that costs 85 percent of the median price. Nationally, according to an N.A.R. survey of first-time buyers released earlier this month, the median price of a starter home was $104,000, and such homes represented 42 percent of the market. In the New York area in the third quarter of last year, the median price of a starter home was $176,715 -- a figure that jumped to $188,275 for the first quarter of this year.</p>
        <p>Real estate brokers in the New York area say that it's much worse for first-time buyers now than during the last big real estate boom, in the mid-80's. Though interest rates are lower now, even after the runup of recent months, than they were in the 80's, prices are up sharply and inventory is sparse. That is prompting furious competition, even over properties that just a few years ago might have lingered on the market for a year or more.</p>
        <p>''People are fighting over a house that costs $240,000, and some of these houses aren't even in good condition,'' said Carole Zeilman, an associate broker at Rowan Realty in Carle Place, Long Island. Ms. Zeilman says she has seen the price of the typical starter home in her area climb to about $250,000, compared with $175,000 just a few years ago. ''It's throwing a lot of people out of the market,'' she said.</p>
        <p>So what does $250,000 -- or a quarter of a million dollars -- buy?</p>
        <p>''What you're probably talking about is a modest ranch or a Cape that typically needs some updating,'' said Gary Herbst of Buyer's Edge Realty in Tarrytown, N.Y. ''Maybe the kitchen is dated or it needs a new heating system or a new roof.''</p>
        <p>Many brokers, when asked to describe the types of homes available in the $175,000 price range, simply laughed. Scott Cohen, a broker at Better Homes and Gardens Real Estate in New Rochelle, N.Y., said he recently showed two two-bedroom homes that were listed at around $160,000 each. But the houses were not very desirable: one sat on top of busy Interstate 95 and the other was adjacent to the Metro-North railroad tracks. In that area, a typical starter home costs around $300,000.</p>
        <p>In Stamford, Conn. -- a 45-minute commute to Midtown -- basic Capes and ranches are also running around $300,000. By adding 15 minutes more in commuting time, the price drops to $250,000, said John Curry, an agent in Prudential Connecticut's Norwalk office. And in Maplewood, N.J. -- a 30-minute train ride to Penn Station -- a house that sold for $185,000 14 months ago was recently listed at $295,000 and quickly received three offers over $300,000, said Susan Palmaffy, an agent at Klein Company Realtors.</p>
        <p>As a result, many first-timers are being pushed to New York's exurbs -- towns in Dutchess and Orange Counties in New York, Monmouth and Ocean Counties in New Jersey, or Suffolk County on Long Island. Prices are cheaper, but the commute into Midtown typically runs well over an hour.</p>
        <p>During our yearlong search, we looked just about everywhere. But many of the houses we looked at we couldn't even envision renting, let alone plunking down a sizable chunk of our savings to buy. There was the small Dutch colonial house that was virtually on top of a noisy elementary school; the colonial with several large holes in its walls, floors and ceilings, and an Arts and Crafts-style house with a gorgeous Hudson River view and an industrial-sized oil tank as a next-door neighbor. In fact, when we came across a house that was in decent shape and didn't have some glaring problem, we almost always put in a bid.</p>
        <p>Sometimes, it seemed as if it was all a bad dream -- a kind of starter-home purgatory. Still, we tried to remain hopeful. Each time we bid, we tried to learn from our past mistakes. Here is what we learned along the way:</p>
        <p>LESSON 1: Prior sales don't mean much in a hot market.</p>
        <p>On a sunny March morning in 1999, we meet with a real estate agent in Cold Spring, N.Y., the Putnam County village we've called home for the last five years, who could easily pass for one of our grandmothers. We reel off our wish list: a three-bedroom older home in reasonably good condition and on a quiet street. Also on the list: a front porch, decent-sized backyard, fireplace and good school district for the children we don't yet have. Our target price is $200,000 -- a price we know is feasible after carefully tracking several years of sales in the area.</p>
        <p>But after about a month of looking, we begin to realize that the past is prologue. Most of what we are shown starts at $225,000 and runs higher. And even at the higher prices, we're still not seeing anything that grabs us. Indeed, most of what we see needs $50,000 or more in work to make it habitable. Only one house even comes close, though it's on a busy street. But before we can make up our minds, somebody else decides to make a full-price offer and the house is gone.</p>
        <p>Lesson 2: Normal negotiating tactics don't work in this market.</p>
        <p>In May, after two months of looking in Cold Spring, we decide to expand the search to Peekskill, in northern Westchester. After looking at a few houses, we finally see one  we really like. It's an old Victorian that has been fully restored. We're seduced by the parquet floors, the large modern kitchen and the big wraparound porch. And at $185,000, it's much more reasonable than anything else we've been shown. We spend over an hour looking around. When we go back home, we can't stop thinking about the house. We never thought that we would say this with a straight face, but it's like falling in love all over again.</p>
        <p>During the week, I spend hours researching the area. I talk to people in the assessor's office, the library, the police department, the Chamber of Commerce and the school system. And it's a good thing, because it's only after doing so that I learn that two critical pieces of information on the listing sheet -- the taxes and the school district -- are inaccurate.</p>
        <p>When I talk to our agent, I point out these inaccuracies as well as some of the home's less-than-desirable features. The house is across the street from a large high school and the rest of the block quickly deteriorates into older row houses.</p>
        <p>From our how-to book, we know that each of these negatives should be negotiation points. The book even provides ranges on what to deduct from the asking price: $15,000-$20,000 when the house is the nicest one on the block; $10,000 more for being across the street from the school. But when we present an offer based on those figures, we are promptly rejected and lectured about not being serious buyers.</p>
        <p>Lesson 3: Parents can provide fresh perspective.</p>
        <p>By midsummer, we have looked at more than 40 houses and we're tired. We start asking brokers to fax us listings first, so that we waste less time. Though we're feeling desperate, we haven't reached the point where we're willing to totally abandon our wish list and look at just anything.</p>
        <p>Then we find not one but two houses that we like, back in Cold Spring. Both are small -- though each has three bedrooms, they are both less than 1,200 square feet -- and they don't appear to need massive amounts of work. It's not quite love, but it's close enough, and we decide to make an offer on one.</p>
        <p>Still, because we have looked at so many houses and are worried about being burned out, we ask Scott's parents to take a look. Experienced homebuyers, they look the houses over carefully. Their assessment, while welcomed, is not favorable. Both houses, they say, need more work than we initially thought. And buying a small house at the height of the market will make it more difficult for us to recoup the price when we sell. We're dejected, but we trust their opinion and decide to rescind our offer.</p>
        <p>Lesson 4: A longer commute buys a lot more house.</p>
        <p>Frustrated, we decide to expand our search to outlying areas and start looking in Dutchess and Orange Counties. Though the commute is much longer, the homes are significantly cheaper. For $225,000, we could buy a large Tudor on nearly an acre of land in Orange County. My husband, who already commutes a little more than an hour each way by train to his job as a storyboard artist at Nickelodeon Animation Studios in Manhattan, tries to figure out how much an extra five hours of his time -- a half hour each way, each workday -- is worth. (I work at home, so commuting for me isn't relevant.)</p>
        <p>Several mornings, we wake up before 6 a.m. to head out to the house and time the commute to the train. When there's no traffic, it adds only an extra 20 minutes. But one day, the Newburgh-Beacon bridge is backed up, and it takes us 45 minutes just to get to a train that still takes more than an hour to get to the city.</p>
        <p>But soon we find an even better house in the small southern Dutchess County city of Beacon, 10 minutes more of a commute than from Cold Spring. It's a restored Victorian and is in pretty good shape. We start getting that warm-fuzzy feeling all over again. We look at it twice and decide to put in a bid on the spot. When the bid is initially rejected, we decide to up the offer. After about a week of wrangling, we have an accepted offer, for $139,250 -- our first. We're elated.</p>
        <p>LESSON 5: Never underestimate the importance of the inspection.</p>
        <p>I interview several home inspectors and choose one who seems to answer my questions the best. We purposefully avoid the inspector recommended by the real estate agent, even though he is $200 cheaper. On a brisk October morning, we meet in front of the house.</p>
        <p>But almost as soon as we go inside, the inspector runs back out to his truck. ''You didn't tell me the house stinks,'' he says, referring to a strong pet odor that seems particularly potent that day. He literally holds his nose when he goes down to the basement -- where the owner's three dogs apparently live and where the smell is even stronger.</p>
        <p>Though we were aware of the smell when we made the offer, we thought it was something that could easily be fixed with fresh paint and new curtains. It's not. The odor is so severe, the inspector says, that in 20-plus years of doing home inspections he has never been in a house that smells worse. Not willing to give up, we ask an industrial cleaner to assess the situation. He heads down to the basement with a device that can apparently detect pet urine and determines that the concrete foundation will need to be professionally treated and that floorboards may have to be replaced. We decide to withdraw our bid.</p>
        <p>Lesson 6: The seller is in the driver's seat.</p>
        <p>It's officially winter, and we figure we'll now have less competition. After all, who wants to move when it could snow? Plenty of people, it turns out. On a Sunday in early January, we head off to look at a house in Maplewood, N.J. The owner, selling the house himself, says he plans to sell it that day. We bring along my mom for company, and the all-important second opinion. No longer novices, we notice a roof that looks like it should have been replaced last year. But we still decide to bid, taking the roof into consideration. Later that night, we learn that we're not even close. Another buyer bids $2,000 over the asking price.</p>
        <p>We are shown another house, in Croton-on-Hudson, by the agent we first started working with last March -- and we like it so much, we make a quick offer. Though ours is the first bid in, the listing broker takes her time getting back to us. When the house is advertised the next two weekends, we realize she's trying to get more bids.</p>
        <p>Sure enough, two weeks later, she tells our agent that another couple offered more money. Our agent suggests that we raise our bid to the $255,000 asking price. But we're already at the top of our range.</p>
        <p>LESSON 7: It takes a lot of work, but there can be a happy ending.</p>
        <p>Finally, just about a year to the day that we started our quest, we find a house in Peekskill that fulfills most of the items on our now pared-down wish list.</p>
        <p>It's an older house, it appears to be in good condition and it has lots of interesting features. There's plenty of wood trim and some really nice 1920's-style stained glass. Yes, the third bedroom is really small, and there's no front porch, and the schools are not the most desirable. But for us, the pluses definitely outweigh the minuses.</p>
        <p>One added bonus, after dealing with real estate agents for a year, is that the owners, who turn out to be very nice people, are selling it themselves. As we walk through the dining room on a Saturday in early March, Scott and I look at each other and realize we have found our new house. All that's left is the negotiations, and even they go pretty smoothly.</p>
        <p>The asking price is $220,000. Our first bid is $205,000. By Sunday night, we have an accepted offer, of $215,000.</p>
        <p>When the inspector shows up a few days later, the house gets a relatively clean bill of health. Our nightmare of spending every weekend in our car bouncing from house to house -- peeping through closets and feigning interest over furnaces -- is finally over. We closed on May 12. We are planning to move in mid-June.</p>
        <p>We are homeowners. At last.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
