<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Dozen Acts to Keep The Bluegrass Flowing</title>
    <meta content="28MINO$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202909"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Strawberry Park Bluegrass Festival</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Preston (Conn)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Minor, E Kyle</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E0D8153DF93BA15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="807" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Dozen Acts to Keep The Bluegrass Flowing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By E. KYLE MINOR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Minor, E Kyle</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Live entertainment and instrumental workshops are planned for 23rd Annual Strawberry Park Bluegrass Festival, which opens on July 28 in Preston, Conn; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>REGARDLESS of what the traditional calendar indicates, summer officially begins next weekend with the 23rd Annual Strawberry Park Bluegrass Festival in Preston.</p>
        <p>Operating under the shadow of the larger Winterhawk Festival (which will be held July 28, 29, 30 at Long Hill Farm just outside Hillsdale, N.Y.), Strawberry Park Bluegrass Festival offers 20 hours of live entertainment, as well as instrumental workshops both Saturday and Sunday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>REGARDLESS of what the traditional calendar indicates, summer officially begins next weekend with the 23rd Annual Strawberry Park Bluegrass Festival in Preston.</p>
        <p>Operating under the shadow of the larger Winterhawk Festival (which will be held July 28, 29, 30 at Long Hill Farm just outside Hillsdale, N.Y.), Strawberry Park Bluegrass Festival offers 20 hours of live entertainment, as well as instrumental workshops both Saturday and Sunday.</p>
        <p>''We've been growing steadily through the years,'' said Buck Biber, owner of Strawberry Park and its festivals organizer. ''It's as big as anything we do.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Biber has assembled a dozen acts to keep bluegrass music flowing through the 77-acre campground from 6 p.m. Friday through 5 p.m. Sunday. This year's performers include Amy Gallatin, Blueridge, Breakaway, Dry Branch Fire Squad, Jonathan Edwards, Laurie Lewis and her Bluegrass Pals, the Lonesome River Band, Ralph Stanley, Ryan Holladay, the Seldom Scene, Shankman Twins and Traver Hollow.</p>
        <p>Since few families can live for three days on bluegrass alone, the rest of the park's recreational attractions will operate in full swing.  Situated about 10 minutes from the Foxwoods Resorts Casino, Strawberry Park accommodates campers, day visitors and offers a variety of athletic events for the family.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the biggest-name act on the roster is Ralph Stanley, widely recognized as a bluegrass living legend. Mr. Stanley, 73, and his brother Carter began working in 1946 and developed their band the Stanley Brothers and the Clinch Mountain Boys. When Carter died in 1966, Mr. Stanley kept the pace with a succession of bands. He always remained true bluegrass, however.</p>
        <p>If Mr. Stanley represents the best in old time bluegrass, Ryan Holladay and Shankman Twins represent its rising generation. Mr. Holladay, not even 10 years old, is an accomplished singer and instrumentalist on the outdoor festival circuit. The teenage Shankman Twins (Dana and Lauren) of Los Angeles, have been rapidly becoming well known to the bluegrass world since they began performing nationally at age 14.</p>
        <p>Veterans of Winterhawk Festival, they have appeared on many television shows including NBC Today in Los Angeles. Jonathan Edwards, Laurie Lewis, the Seldom Scene, Dry Branch Fire Squad have long been established national acts.</p>
        <p>Mr. Edwards, best known for his early folk records, frequently crosses over into bluegrass and has recorded with the Seldom Scene. Ms. Lewis is a singer-songwriter who plays fiddle, guitar and bass. Having grown up in San Francisco Bay area in the 60's, she was exposed to the era's best folk music at the Berkeley Folk Festivals, from Doc Watson, Jean Ritchie and Mississippi John Hurt to the bluegrass revival group called the Greenbriar Boys.</p>
        <p>After more than 20 years together, the Seldom Scene remains one of the premier bluegrass bands in America. Although some of the members of the group have changed, their music remains a centerpiece of contemporary bluegrass.</p>
        <p>Dry Branch Fire Squad has been around just as long but sticks closer to the traditional acoustic style. Its founder and mandolinist, Ron Thomason, who began his professional career with Ralph Stanley's Clinch Mountain Boys, proves year in and year out his loyalty to the most traditional aspects of bluegrass, old-time and Southern gospel music.</p>
        <p>Amy Gallatin is the festival's lone Connecticut resident. She started her singing career singing at Lone Mountain Ranch in Big Sky, Mont., where she worked in the 70's. A native of Muscle Shoals, Ala., Ms. Gallatin plays a combination of bluegrass, country western and folk. She also throws into her set little-known songs from writers like Karla Bonoff or Richard Dobson.</p>
        <p>''We try to strike a balance with traditional and crossover talent,'' said Mr. Biber, ''with well-known and new acts. After 23 years, you want to keep it recognizable and fresh at the same time.''</p>
        <p>The Strawberry Park Bluegrass Festival in Preston runs Friday through Sunday.</p>
        <p>The music schedule is Friday from 6 p.m. to 11 p.m.; Saturday from noon to 5 p.m. and 7 to 11 p.m.; Sunday from 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. The numbers to call for more information are (860) 886-1944 or (888) 794-7944.</p>
        <p>Directions: Take Interstate 395 to Exit 85. Right on Route 164 South, five miles to left on Route 165 East. Continue one mile to Strawberry Park.</p>
        <p>MUSIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
