<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Seeking an Early Edge Into Elite Colleges</title>
    <meta content="28SQUA$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202904"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Squash Racquets</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Westchester Squash (Mamaroneck, Ny)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cruice, Valerie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E2D8153DF93BA15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1587" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Seeking an Early Edge Into Elite Colleges</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VALERIE CRUICE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cruice, Valerie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on rising number of parents who are encouraging their children, some as young as four, to take up squash as way to increase chances of being admitted to top colleges; junior program enrollment at Westchester Squash in Mamaroneck, NY, has grown from handful two years ago to nearly 80; some colleges take sport very seriously although National Collegiate Athletic Assn has no plans to make squash sanctioned sport; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>PARENTS have long jockeyed to get their children into the top colleges, from sending them to the right prep schools to hiring tutors for the College Boards. In an environment where high grades don't guarantee admission, parents are always looking for an edge. Lately, they have found that edge in the game of squash.</p>
        <p>Squash, spawned in English boarding schools in the 19th century, is a prestigious sport in the Ivy League, and although it doesn't have an impact on revenues or the endowments of basketball or football, there is much school pride riding on this gentleman's game. So at many schools, admission officers are looking beyond SAT scores to see if applicants can handle a racket.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>PARENTS have long jockeyed to get their children into the top colleges, from sending them to the right prep schools to hiring tutors for the College Boards. In an environment where high grades don't guarantee admission, parents are always looking for an edge. Lately, they have found that edge in the game of squash.</p>
        <p>Squash, spawned in English boarding schools in the 19th century, is a prestigious sport in the Ivy League, and although it doesn't have an impact on revenues or the endowments of basketball or football, there is much school pride riding on this gentleman's game. So at many schools, admission officers are looking beyond SAT scores to see if applicants can handle a racket.</p>
        <p>''At Yale, the admissions and athletic departments are working more closely together,'' said Mark Talbott, the Yale women's squash coach. ''We're combing the globe for squash players. A lot of American kids, there's no way they would get in without the help of the squash.''</p>
        <p>This is not a secret to many parents, who are not only encouraging their children to take up the sport, but are getting them to start as young as 4 years old. Craig Brand of the United States Squash Racquets Association in Bala Cynwyd, Pa., said junior membership, which runs up to 18 years old, in the organization has doubled to about 1,000 in the last six to seven years, with about 150 junior members in Connecticut. Richard Millman, the owner of Westchester Squash in Mamaroneck, N.Y., said his junior program has grown from a handful of children just two years ago to nearly 80 now. Two of his students, both girls, recently got into Brown University and another into Harvard.</p>
        <p>''I would say that squash was certainly a consideration,'' Mr. Millman said of their acceptance. ''They were very good students, but not necessarily strong students.''</p>
        <p>The membership may be on its way up, helped by a change to a softer ball in the 1980's that made the game easier to play, but there are still few enough players in the state, which gives those athletes a distinction on their college application forms.</p>
        <p>''Squash definitely can influence admissions decisions,'' said Jan Traynor of New Canaan, an educational consultant who helps children get into prep schools and colleges.</p>
        <p>''I've had students whose athletics allowed them to be viewed by a college in a different light,'' Ms. Traynor said. ''Squash is becoming a hot sport, especially with the females. If a student is outstanding on the court, and if a school is building new squash courts or a team, even a selective college will be looking for other indicators of excellence, not just academics.''</p>
        <p>All three of Jan Endresen's children play squash. His oldest, Blair, 21, is graduating from Harvard next week and was captain of the Harvard women's squash team.</p>
        <p>''She got into most of the schools she applied to,'' said Mr. Endresen of Rye, N.Y. ''One of the reasons that she got into the schools she got into was certainly squash.''</p>
        <p>Mae Miller of Weston said squash probably gave her son, Alexander, an advantage in getting into Bates College in Lewiston, Me.</p>
        <p>''Squash is not played in the public schools, and so it's unusual for colleges to get applicants who are squash players,'' she said. ''When they see that on the application, the little green light comes on.''</p>
        <p>There is no doubt that some colleges take the sport very seriously, even if the National Collegiate Athletic Association said it had no plans of making squash a sanctioned sport any time soon. Yale just spent $6 million for its new squash complex called the Nicholas Brady Squash Center.</p>
        <p>Trinity College, which has won two straight national men's titles (the first non-Ivy League school to win the national title), scours the world for players. The team's 16-player roster consists of 14 foreign-born players.</p>
        <p>''For years and years the Ivy League dominated, Harvard in particular,'' said Trinity Coach Paul Assiante, referring to the Crimson's one-time, 91-game winning streak. ''You create that kind of legacy, it becomes a source of pride and recognition.''</p>
        <p>Peter Doucette, the boys' varsity squash coach at Greens Farms Academy, said nearly all of his seniors from last year's varsity are playing on their college squash teams, which include Brown, Amherst and Bates. All were strong students.</p>
        <p>''Squash is such a pervasive sport in Greenwich,'' Mr. Doucette said, ''people there know how much a role it can play in college admissions.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Brand of the squash association said he sees parents pushing their children in the sport just to increase their odds at getting admitted to an elite college.</p>
        <p>''It is worse than ever, what I see,'' he said. ''There's an enormous amount of pressure because parents believe squash will grease the skids into college.''</p>
        <p>Sometimes, said Maxim Weithers, the squash pro at the Southport Racquet Club, the parents are nudging children who have no interest.</p>
        <p>''There are some kids here because their parents have pushed them. They don't want to be on the court,'' he said. ''I don't see the fire in their eyes, the spark for the game.'' Mr. Weithers and his assistant pros conduct numerous clinics, some for children as young as 4 years old.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brand said the junior committee of the squash association hasn't been this active in a decade. It recently mailed a booklet, ''How to Survive Y2K Junior Squash,'' which is a primer for juniors, coaches, tournament directors and parents.</p>
        <p>''Our domestic calendar has as many as 40 events September through March,'' he said. ''A junior can play in a tournament almost every weekend.''</p>
        <p>That's important for a player looking at getting into college. Playing in tournaments is a way to gain a ranking and the attention of a college coach, although the national association makes an effort to advise members not to schedule tournaments that would conflict with SAT and P.S.A.T. testing weekends.</p>
        <p>''Juniors should be very savvy about planning their own personal tournament campaign,'' the Y2K survival booklet points out. ''Five or six well-chosen tournaments should be sufficient to establish your ranking accurately.''</p>
        <p>Holly Haertel, 17, an association member, is a junior at Greenwich Academy. She picked up the game in fifth grade on her school's courts. She started playing tournaments in seventh and eighth grades.</p>
        <p>''I think squash is really fun. It's challenging. I find the tournaments stressful, but its good for your ranking and for college,'' she explained in between drills at Westchester Squash.</p>
        <p>Mr. Doucette said rankings aren't the only way to get noticed. Some of the best junior players are in prep schools and are unable to travel to the minimum of four tournaments required to earn a ranking. It is up to the coach and the player and parent to make the child's ability known to a college coach through calls, letters and video tape.</p>
        <p>Ned Gallagher, the director of athletics and squash coach at Choate-Rosemary Hall in Wallingford, said on the high school level, squash is mostly played in prep schools.</p>
        <p>''Squash is one of a handful of sports where children can start at the high school level and become quite accomplished such that it will open doors to some very prestigious colleges and universities,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Of the 35 boys teams in the New England Interscholastic Squash Association, the top four were all Connecticut schools: Taft in Watertown, Brunswick in Greenwich, Hotchkiss in Lakeville and Choate.</p>
        <p>The junior squash season runs from mid-September to July and is a winter sport for the colleges.</p>
        <p>Coach Talbott (his brother Dave coaches the Yale men's team), runs the Talbott Squash Academy in Rhode Island, which began as the national training center for the United States men's and women's teams. It grew from a one-week summer program nine years ago to a seven-week program this year.</p>
        <p>''I've gone from 16 kids to about 230 last year,'' said Mr. Talbott, who with his brother were stars of the game in this country in the 80's.</p>
        <p>''Now it's about 45 percent girls, where originally it was 10 percent,'' he said. ''And on the national tour, there's a lot of depth in the under-16 girls: they are much more on a par with the European girls.''</p>
        <p>About half of the 50 children swarming over the squash courts at the Apawamis Club in Rye, N.Y., one afternoon were girls, many of them from Connecticut.</p>
        <p>Peter Briggs, a coach, oversaw the clinics for 6- to 11-year-olds. The clinics have about 200 children from Westchester and Connecticut. Often, parents stay and watch their children practice.</p>
        <p>''There are just as many psycho parents in squash as tennis,'' Mr. Briggs said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
