<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Witness for the Prosecution</title>
    <meta content="28WEST" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Washington; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202756"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Westlake, Donald E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schmidt, Susan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weisskopf, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Starr, Kenneth W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lewinsky, Monica S</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Truth at Any Cost (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE1DE143AF93BA15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1095" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Witness for the Prosecution</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Donald E. Westlake</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Westlake, Donald E</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Donald E Westlake reviews book Truth at Any Cost: Ken Starr and the Unmaking of Bill Clinton by Susan Schmidt and Michael Weisskopf; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TRUTH AT ANY COST</p>
        <p>Ken Starr and the</p>
        <p>Unmaking of Bill Clinton.</p>
        <p>By Susan Schmidt and</p>
        <p>Michael Weisskopf.</p>
        <p>326 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>HarperCollins Publishers. $26.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TRUTH AT ANY COST</p>
        <p>Ken Starr and the</p>
        <p>Unmaking of Bill Clinton.</p>
        <p>By Susan Schmidt and</p>
        <p>Michael Weisskopf.</p>
        <p>326 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>HarperCollins Publishers. $26.</p>
        <p>THERE are two things you absolutely need if you are going to tell a story: a good, surprising plot and a lively, interesting hero. ''Truth at Any Cost'' is the Monica Lewinsky story again, this time with Kenneth Starr as the hero. Houston, we have a problem.</p>
        <p>In the beginning, it was sort of touching to watch these two accomplished journalists, Michael Weisskopf, formerly of The Washington Post and currently at Time magazine, and Susan Schmidt, still at The Post, as they earnestly rooted for truffles in this desert. After a while I moved on to irritation, but finally to sympathy when I understood that what I was reading was a variant on the Stockholm syndrome. Schmidt and Weisskopf had spent so much time with the tribe of the prosecutors they'd begun to identify with them, and then to become them: humorless, inhumane, self-righteous, rigid. If it weren't for tunnel vision, they wouldn't have any vision at all. The interesting thing about reporters getting too close to the story is that they inadvertently tell us more than they intend, beginning with that title. True, all the really good titles, like ''God Is My Co-Pilot,'' had already been taken, but ''Truth at Any Cost''? Who would want to live their lives with truth at any cost? The tribe of the prosecutors would, and so would their journalist blood brothers, and they think you should, too.</p>
        <p>The prosecutorial attitude is mainly what this book is about. You remember when Monica Lewinsky's mother, mellifluously named Marcia Lewis, broke down during the second day of interrogation before the grand jury, but you probably don't remember why she was there in the first place. No matter. Until then, America had thought she was flighty and silly; after that, America thought she was flighty and silly and sympathetic, a distraught mother. ''Prosecutors thought the breakdown was staged,'' Schmidt and Weisskopf say. The tribe of the prosecutors apparently never saw anybody outside their offices in human terms. The world was divided into prosecutors and targets, and woe betide targets who saw themselves in any other way.</p>
        <p>There was one brief moment when I thought I detected a hint of humanity. Sol Wisenberg, the prosecutor in charge of running targets through the grand jury, would schedule them and then forget, make them wait, make them come back, start all over. (This is what you get when correct thinking is valued above competence.) Another prosecutor, Bob Bittman, ''demanded to know why witnesses had to go before the grand jury so many times.</p>
        <p>'' 'What difference does it make?' asked Wisenberg.</p>
        <p>'' 'It makes us look like Keystone Kops,' said Bittman. He worried that it fueled criticism that the prosecutors were imperious.''</p>
        <p>Oh. It isn't about jerking people around, it's about the prosecutors' image.</p>
        <p>One of the proofs of the targets' perfidy was that they kept showing up with lawyers, usually provided by the White House and described as ''part of an old-boy network of former prosecutors.'' Not lawyers in the usual sense, though; the prosecutors considered them mostly spies, who ''even created rough transcripts of their clients' grand jury testimony that could be useful to the White House.'' On the other hand, there came a time when ''Starr told his staff to call the best lawyers they knew and see if they'd be interested in signing up for a few months.'' Language choices can be fascinating.</p>
        <p>As you can imagine, the contrast between Starr and the Great Satan in the White House is made pretty clear: ''And while Bill Clinton got through Yale Law School borrowing notes and cramming for exams, Starr never missed a class at Duke Law School, taking exquisitely organized notes and freely lending them to less dedicated students.'' Wait, it gets worse. Bittman was on the golf course with another prosecutor, and saw Clinton shanking ''one ball after another, abandoning each as he went. When he finally hit the fourth one onto the green, he announced, 'I'll play that one.' They couldn't get over it: Clinton must be shaving his scores.'' Can you imagine? Bill Clinton doesn't take golf seriously. At that time, he was taking Israel seriously, and he was taking Ireland seriously, but he wasn't taking golf seriously. He was treating it as, well, a diversion. And this is the man we put next to the nuclear button; what can we have been thinking?</p>
        <p>Some of the story Schmidt and Weisskopf have to tell is almost nutty enough to be worth the price of admission. For instance, we are told that Linda Tripp's lawyer, Jim Moody, was ''legally blind'' and, in the same paragraph, that when he was carrying the infamous tapes, he ''feared that he was being followed by 'men in black.' Too many people knew about the tapes, he fretted.'' So ''he dove in and out of downtown buildings, entering through the front door and exiting through the rear.'' The image belongs in a W. C. Fields movie, but our authors don't notice, or they wouldn't have given us that ''fretted.''</p>
        <p>Their ears can be more seriously tin as well. They say Ken Starr's ''authority dervied not just from the law, but from the American public.'' Wrong. The American public is Nielsen ratings: it's the American people they owe. Our Constitution begins, ''We, the People,'' a brand new powerful idea in the world. These folk weren't rolling the polls of the public, they were flouting the Will of the People.</p>
        <p>Which they'll never get. At the end, the book turns unexpectedly into a horror story. Starr didn't merely leave, he was replaced, by a ''tough, experienced prosecutor'' named Robert Ray, who would ''face some of the same challenges his predecessor endured,'' like whether to start a criminal indictment to welcome Bill Clinton back to civilian life. ''During his first four months in office,'' the book ends, Ray ''hired four new lawyers. Three of them have backgrounds in investigation or prosecution.''</p>
        <p>Is it too late to flee to Canada?</p>
        <p>Donald E. Westlake's only work of nonfiction is ''Under an English Heaven.'' His most recent novel, ''The Hook,'' was published in March.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Donald E. Westlake's only work of nonfiction is ''Under an English Heaven.'' His most recent novel, ''The Hook,'' was published in March.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
