<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From Children to Medicine, a Particular Look at the World; Children's Books And Author's Duty</title>
    <meta content="28BOO3" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Books; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202867"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Adler, David A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tagliaferro, Linda</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Cam Jansen and the Barking Treasure Mystery (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E5DD143DF93BA15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="518" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From Children to Medicine, a Particular Look at the World; Children's Books And Author's Duty</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LINDA TAGLIAFERRO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tagliaferro, Linda</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of children's book writer David A Adler of Woodmere, Long Island, whose latest work is Cam Jansen and the Barking Treasure Mystery; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR David A. Adler, children's book writing is not all bunny rabbits and talking mice.</p>
        <p>''It's a much heavier responsibility writing for children than for adults,'' said Mr. Adler, a resident of Woodmere. ''When you write for adults, you're basically educating them, but with children, you're molding them.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR David A. Adler, children's book writing is not all bunny rabbits and talking mice.</p>
        <p>''It's a much heavier responsibility writing for children than for adults,'' said Mr. Adler, a resident of Woodmere. ''When you write for adults, you're basically educating them, but with children, you're molding them.''</p>
        <p>''Cam Jansen and the Barking Treasure Mystery,'' just released by Viking Publishing, is Mr. Adler's 150th published book. His books, both fiction and nonfiction, include the Cam Jansen mystery series, more than 35 picture book biographies, and even books for children about the Holocaust.</p>
        <p>His character, Cam Jansen, who has starred in 19 books and spawned the Young Cam Jansen series, is a girl, but Mr. Adler has given her traits that are frequently ascribed to boys. ''She's aggressive and curious, and that's often how boys are stereotyped in literature,'' Mr. Adler said. ''I think that if children read enough about people who aren't what you'd assume because of their gender or their color or their age, then stereotypes can be broken.''</p>
        <p>Tolerance is a common theme in many of his books. His biographies, for instance, tell the stories of people like Anne Frank, Rosa Parks and Sitting Bull. ''In these books,'' Mr. Adler said, ''I try to prove how some generalizations can be wrong.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Adler, a former math teacher, had his first book, ''A Little at a Time,'' published in 1976. Inspired by questions from his 2-year-old nephew, the book tells the story of a little boy whose incessant questions are patiently answered by his grandfather. ''He asks how a tree got to be so tall when it started out as a small seed,'' Mr. Adler said, ''and his grandfather answers that it grew and grew, but it only grew a little at a time. The end of each answer is always 'a little at a time.' It shows how things happen gradually.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Adler took a child-care leave from his teaching job after the birth of his first child, Michael, in 1977. ''Everybody without exception told me that writing for children full time wouldn't work out,'' he said. His agent encouraged him to get a steady day job. Mr. Adler's response was to drop the agent and continue his search for a publisher. ''Within six months,'' he said, ''Viking picked up the book and asked me to make it into a series.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Adler still gets excited by the prospect of each new title. He said he strives to get his readers emotionally involved in his books. ''I think children's books are a greater means to social change than books for adults,'' he said, ''because we wouldn't have today's problems if people thought differently.''</p>
        <p>He added: ''I can't force children to pick up my books. I can only hope that when they do read them, that it will in some way affect how they feel about things.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
