<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Feeling Like an Orphan in Ma Bell's Domain</title>
    <meta content="28COLM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202961"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="COPING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bell Atlantic Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kershaw, Sarah</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E6D8123DF93BA15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="985" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Feeling Like an Orphan in Ma Bell's Domain</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SARAH KERSHAW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kershaw, Sarah</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sarah Kershaw essay recounts 42-day saga to get Bell Atlantic to install working phone in her new Brooklyn apartment; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THERE isn't enough room in the Manhattan Yellow Pages to detail my attempts to get a working telephone in my new apartment in Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>In the end, after a 42-day odyssey during which the installation department at Bell Atlantic probably received more calls from me than my bosses, my best friends and my sister combined, I had a dial tone.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THERE isn't enough room in the Manhattan Yellow Pages to detail my attempts to get a working telephone in my new apartment in Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>In the end, after a 42-day odyssey during which the installation department at Bell Atlantic probably received more calls from me than my bosses, my best friends and my sister combined, I had a dial tone.</p>
        <p>Sure, it was after a flurry of calls to the company from pay phones and, eventually, a cell phone. There were pleas for mercy to customer care representatives and favors from friends and my downstairs neighbor. I made threats and an attempt to switch to another local service provider, and wrote an angry letter to a company I have not so affectionately come to call Hell Atlantic. Then came the whopping cell phone bill for $2,065.94. (That was not a typo.) But I was plugged in.</p>
        <p>Even better, I had an urban fairy tale, starring my hero, an eager-to-connect-me repairman named K. Smith, who told me he had had to wait five weeks for telephone installation from his own employer.</p>
        <p>K. Smith was determined to hook me up, and he single-handedly got me a dial tone. Just when I was ready to check into the Bellevue psych ward, he appeared -- K. Smith, herald of humanity inside a vast and coldhearted bureaucracy.</p>
        <p>After it was all over, I relayed my saga to a Bell Atlantic spokesman, John Bonomo. ''Your case, we think, was the exception,''  he told me. He said that it typically takes three to five business days to get a home phone, and that the company's latest customer satisfaction survey showed that 92 percent of its 7 million residential customers in New York State were satisfied with Bell Atlantic. I feel so much less alone. That means there are 560,000 others across the state who are not satisfied.</p>
        <p>I suppose there is some technical explanation for all the problems with my telephone having to do with wires and telephone poles and jacks. Mr. Bonomo reviewed my records, said, ''We do see you went through hell and back to get your line,'' and concluded that he still could not explain exactly what went wrong. But I'm not sure I care.</p>
        <p>My trouble started when I moved from Park Slope to Boerum Hill. I ordered a phone line from Bell Atlantic on a Wednesday, and was told it would be ready two days later, for $55. I arrived at the apartment on a Saturday night, unpacked the phone and plugged it into the jack. No dial tone.</p>
        <p>I called the following Monday for an installation appointment. The next available Saturday, the only day I was available, was three weeks away. I agreed to a weekday, taking a morning off a new job. While I waited for the appointment, I asked for voice mail. Over the next few weeks, they turned it on and turned it off three times, leaving grandmothers and other perplexed callers to believe my phone had been disconnected.</p>
        <p>During the first appointment I learned that a key was needed to my neighbor's apartment. This is the type of information customer care representatives declined to share with me. I took more time off work, and the company sent over two more technicians. I waited four hours for one of them and seven for the other. Neither was able to connect the line for mysterious reasons.</p>
        <p>Frustrated with Bell Atlantic, I switched to MCI for local service, only to be told I would have to wait another seven weeks because that was when Bell Atlantic, which is in charge of installations for everybody, could put in the line.</p>
        <p>I switched back to Bell Atlantic and made another appointment, after my neighbor kindly agreed to leave work early to wait for the technician because I could not. The day of the appointment, I arrived home about 10:30 p.m. to find a handwritten note on top of my television.</p>
        <p>''Dear Customer,'' the note said, before explaining that my telephone line had gone bad because of troubles with the outside wiring that were missed by previous repair workers. The writer said my telephone line should be working by 9:30 that evening.</p>
        <p>If not, the author said: ''I will come back personally. I take pride in my work and I will do everything in my power to get you phone service. Thank you. K. Smith.''</p>
        <p>What?</p>
        <p>By morning, there was no dial tone. So I beeped this K. Smith. He came over right away. He had been on the job only three months, he told me, and he seemed committed to this notion of customer satisfaction. So every time I woke up to a dead phone or went home to one I beeped him, and he always came over within an hour or two.</p>
        <p>The other day, while I was waiting for K. Smith, who was uncharacteristically late, I found a letter in the mail from Bell Atlantic, from the office of the general manager of operations in Brooklyn. ''I understand that you had some difficulty with your telephone service,'' the general manager wrote. For my troubles, he said, I had earned a prepaid Bell Atlantic calling card worth $5.</p>
        <p>Buddy, I've got a $2,000 cell phone bill and a headache the size of Montana, and K. Smith is nowhere in sight. I picked up the cell phone to beep him again, but first I checked the home phone one more time. Dial tone! Thank you, K. Smith.</p>
        <p>COPING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
