<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Tale Of Art In Two Romes</title>
    <meta content="28RUSS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202818"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ART/ARCHITECTURE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roman Civilization</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Rome (Italy)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Palazzo delle Espsizione (Rome)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Russell, John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bellori, Giovan Pietro (1613-96)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy/Rome</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roman Civilization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roman Civilization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Archaeology and Anthropology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E0DC163DF93BA15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1394" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Tale Of Art In Two Romes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">BY JOHN RUSSELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Russell, John</byline>
      <dateline>ROME</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Exhibition at Palazzo delle Espsizione in Rome documents both the achievements in 17th-century Roman art and Rome's artistic history as seen through eyes of connossieur Giovan Pietro Bellori (1613-1696)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR years, the problem of how to be both relevant and imaginative in the first summer of the new millennium has nagged at curators the world over. But nowhere, to my knowledge, has that problem been solved as nimbly or as persuasively as in an exhibition in Rome called ''L'Idea del Bello'' at the Palazzo delle Esposizione on the Via Nazionale, on view through June 26. (The title can be read in English as ''The Idea of Beauty'' or ''Beauty as an Idea.'')</p>
        <p>For many foreign visitors, Rome has a mammoth attraction that can breed problems. The restored paintings by Michelangelo in the Sistine Chapel constitute an overwhelming experience, one that can get in the way of the fact that there was art in Rome after Michelangelo. Whether consciously or not, that is the subject of ''L'Idea del Bello.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR years, the problem of how to be both relevant and imaginative in the first summer of the new millennium has nagged at curators the world over. But nowhere, to my knowledge, has that problem been solved as nimbly or as persuasively as in an exhibition in Rome called ''L'Idea del Bello'' at the Palazzo delle Esposizione on the Via Nazionale, on view through June 26. (The title can be read in English as ''The Idea of Beauty'' or ''Beauty as an Idea.'')</p>
        <p>For many foreign visitors, Rome has a mammoth attraction that can breed problems. The restored paintings by Michelangelo in the Sistine Chapel constitute an overwhelming experience, one that can get in the way of the fact that there was art in Rome after Michelangelo. Whether consciously or not, that is the subject of ''L'Idea del Bello.''</p>
        <p>Its credentials are summed up in its subtitle: ''A Journey Through 17th-Century Rome With Giovan Pietro Bellori.'' To many foreign tourists, that subtitle is anything but a grabber. In several visits to the show, I never heard an English-speaking voice among the crowds of visitors. (Nor, for that matter, does the English language figure anywhere in the show, whether on wall labels or in the catalog, which is packed with vital information.)</p>
        <p>Bellori (1613-1696) is well known to specialists as someone familiar with both the art and the artists of his own day at first hand. He wrote at length about them, and his judgments (many of them quoted in the show and in its catalog) have not gone stale.</p>
        <p>Among the cultural elite of Rome in the 17th century, Bellori was Mr. Versatility. Though not a grandee, a natural courtier, a politician or a man of business, he was widely regarded as the leading connoisseur of his time, not least in the Academy of St. Luke's, where the cognoscenti fought the aesthetic battles of the day. From 1660 to 1674 he was the papal commissioner for ancient art.</p>
        <p>Nothing was alien to him -- not philosophy, not numismatics, not the architecture of Rome from its earliest times, not what he had heard a few days before from Nicolas Poussin, the great French painter who had lived for many years in Rome and shared Bellori's interest in Roman antiquities.</p>
        <p>Three hundred years later, many major museums were fired up by the proposed duet between Roman antiquity and Rome in the age of Caravaggio, the Carraccis, Domenichino, Guido Reni and others. Paris, London, Berlin, Dresden, Moscow, St. Petersburg, Vienna and Washington all came forward with loans.</p>
        <p>The result is a pandemonium of paintings, antique and later sculptures, drawings, prints, engraved gems and cameos and rare books. It includes casts made in the 17th century from Trajan's Column, which has been one of the sights of Rome since A.D. 112. There are also some reminiscences of the gigantic marble map of the entire city of Rome, on a scale of 1 to 246, commissioned by the Emperor Septimius Severus at the end of the second century.</p>
        <p>At a high level, these exhibits document both the history of discernment and the history of artistic achievement in 17th-century Rome. It is clear from the start that neither the choice of exhibits nor their installation will always conform to expectation.</p>
        <p>Right-angled rooms are not the rule. Nor is the traditional march-past of framed paintings in chronological order. Quite often works of art play hide-and- seek. At one and the same time we see what was cherished from the past in 17th-century Rome and what was being done in the present.</p>
        <p>A prime example of this is the opening section. We walk in and out of the almost secretive areas in which congruities between antique sculptors and the brothers Annibale and Agostino Carracci are brought to our attention in pertinent quotations in handwritten form.</p>
        <p>A key painting at this point is ''Hercules at the Parting of the Ways'' by Annibale Carracci. Hercules (very much of two minds) is seated between Virtue and Vice. Hints of antique sculpture play a part in all three figures, but a new naturalism, allied to sumptuousness of color, gives the scene a vibrant actuality. Virtue's outstretched arm shows Hercules the path of wisdom, but the voluptuous and all but naked figure of Vice is big competition.</p>
        <p>At an altogether lower level of ambition is the small group of mildly libidinous prints by Agostino Carracci that hark back to pranksters of many centuries earlier. Among other once abhorred but distinctly mild improprieties are the copy of an early Roman sculpture of a sleeping hermaphrodite from the Uffizi in Florence. There is also a second-century sarcophagus from Naples that portrays, among other things, a nocturnal Dionysiac orgy. If this once spelled fireworks, they have long ago sputtered out.</p>
        <p>As the organizers themselves say, it may surprise Roman visitors that the artist most fully represented is Poussin.</p>
        <p>Bellori was a passionate student of what is now called ''contemporary art.'' He was quick off the mark with the young Caravaggio, but in Poussin he recognized a fellow spirit who was also one of the great painters of all time. When Poussin was alive, Bellori could study his paintings almost day by day. But after their deaths Poussin's work was drawn, as if magnetized, to great museums and inspired collectors worldwide. In Rome, not much of his output is normally on public view. Now, if ever, is his turn to reappear.</p>
        <p>Bellori well knew, for instance, that during his many years' residence in Rome Poussin was not only the foremost painter of the day but also an inspired student of Trajan's Column. (At one time, Poussin hoped to install casts made from episodes on the column in a gallery in Paris that was to run from the Louvre to the Tuileries.)</p>
        <p>As for the role of antiquity in Poussin's paintings, it is shown in detail to a public that has rarely, if ever, seen it at such close quarters. If anyone asks, ''Was there great art in Rome after Michelangelo?,'' they need look no further. There could have been no greater privilege in the Rome of Bellori's day than to see these paintings emerge, one by one.</p>
        <p>What Bellori prized in the art of his own time in Rome was twofold: an abundant physicality allied to depth of true feeling. When a painter or sculptor had been inspired by a work of ancient art and taken it a step farther, Bellori was in ecstasy.</p>
        <p>There is in the show a figure of Santa Susanna by the Belgian sculptor Francois du Quesnoy. Prompted by an antique statue of Urania in the Campidoglio, du Quesnoy produced a figure that was heavily draped from head to feet. The personification of sainted modesty, she had laid aside -- but could not quite conceal -- a sensuous potential that was almost beyond belief. Bellori thought that for once a sculptor of his own day had gone farther than the ancients.</p>
        <p>There is much else in this enormous show. But for the interaction of antiquity and the 17th century nothing surpasses the ''Allegorical Portrait of the Singer Pasqualini'' by Andrea Sacchi, which belongs to the Metropolitan Museum of Art in New York. This is, in fact, an adorable conjunction of the classical ideal, in the person of the stark naked Apollo (borrowed from the Belvedere in Rome) with the prim little, trim little figure whom he crowns with laurels.</p>
        <p>Nothing in that little figure is invented. Marcantonio Pasqualini (1614-91) was called in his day a ''soprano castrato,'' but it may be that he was simply the ancestor of the countertenors whom we now prize so highly. In any case, Sacchi gave equal billing to him, and to the musical instruments in the painting, as to Apollo.</p>
        <p>ART/ARCHITECTURE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
