<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The D.J. Moves Into a New Arena</title>
    <meta content="28KELL$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202808"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Disk Jockeys</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kelley, Robin D G</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Haynes, Graham</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">M Singe (Beth Coleman)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E4DE163DF93BA15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1543" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The D.J. Moves Into a New Arena</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBIN D.G. KELLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kelley, Robin D G</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>A new improvisatory music rooted in hip-hop that mixes instrumentalists and turntablists, programmers and poets is pushing technology to new limits and blurring distinctions between genres; photos of Beth Coleman, who performs as deejay M Singe, and cornetist Graham Haynes (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SEVERAL months ago, I followed a rabbit into a hole and had a musical encounter of a most magical kind. Entering 56 Walker Street in TriBeCa, better known as the Electric Church, I passed through a bright orange passageway to enter a dark, cavernous room with a low stage weighed down with all manner of mixers, turntables, CD players, wires, computers, samplers, drum machines, keyboards and gadgets I've only seen in science fiction flicks. Alone stood Graham Haynes, known to most jazz fans as the avant-bop master of the cornet and fluegelhorn, mixing beats like a mad scientist. A video artist projected random clips that moved in unison with the music on the 30-foot wall behind him. After a while, Mr. Haynes was joined by Val Jeanty on electronic percussion and turntables, Craig Taborn on keyboards, Steve Hall on soprano and tenor saxophone and Imani Uzuri on vocals. Mr. Haynes grabbed his fluegelhorn and retreated to what looked like the master control board.</p>
        <p>And then the serious head noddin' began.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SEVERAL months ago, I followed a rabbit into a hole and had a musical encounter of a most magical kind. Entering 56 Walker Street in TriBeCa, better known as the Electric Church, I passed through a bright orange passageway to enter a dark, cavernous room with a low stage weighed down with all manner of mixers, turntables, CD players, wires, computers, samplers, drum machines, keyboards and gadgets I've only seen in science fiction flicks. Alone stood Graham Haynes, known to most jazz fans as the avant-bop master of the cornet and fluegelhorn, mixing beats like a mad scientist. A video artist projected random clips that moved in unison with the music on the 30-foot wall behind him. After a while, Mr. Haynes was joined by Val Jeanty on electronic percussion and turntables, Craig Taborn on keyboards, Steve Hall on soprano and tenor saxophone and Imani Uzuri on vocals. Mr. Haynes grabbed his fluegelhorn and retreated to what looked like the master control board.</p>
        <p>And then the serious head noddin' began.</p>
        <p>The music was entirely improvised, with Ms. Jeanty laying down the beats and the band providing rhythmic dynamism and harmonic textures, cutting and pasting phrases as if they were in conversation. Mr. Taborn's improvisations were ingenious, displaying a sensitivity to sound textures, not just key or pitch -- a necessity in the expansive world of electronic music. The group worked like a D.J.; there were no breaks between songs because there were no ''songs'' -- only continuous music full of surprising elements, tempo and time changes. For all of its postmodernity, this was an old-fashioned ''jam session.'' The evening was not without missteps, but that comes with the territory whenever artists reach beyond their grasp.</p>
        <p>Graham Haynes is one of several leaders of an experimental-music underground in which instrumentalists and turntablists, programmers and poets have begun to revolutionize improvisational music by pushing technology to new limits and crushing all distinctions between genres. They have practically discarded the old rhythm-section concept (piano, bass and drums) for something more dynamic, more expansive: turntables, digital samplers, electronic percussion, effects pads, computer programs that enable sonic manipulation of acoustic instruments, while maintaining the avant-garde tradition of incorporating ancient instruments -- tablas, koras, ouds, water drums.</p>
        <p>Hip-hop is a primary source of this new music. The D.J., hip-hop's very heart and soul, simultaneously mirrors and deconstructs improvisational practices usually associated with jazz. These turntablists, like their counterparts in rap and electronica, literally make new music from old records by mixing, cutting and altering original recordings, manipulating records by hand to change pitch, to create rhythmic effects and to milk the groove itself for new sounds by ''scratching.'' The most innovative D.J.'s, the creators of what is now called ''illbient'' music (a kind of ambient-meets-funky abstraction), can make John Coltrane's tenor sound like a drum or turn an Art Blakey snare roll into a horn or a drone.</p>
        <p>''The best of the illbient D.J.'s have created a new jazz instrument,'' says the writer and musician Greg Tate. ''And they've done it by having an encyclopedic approach to improvisation.''</p>
        <p>The illbient D.J.'s have opened a new path in improvisational music precisely because they resist music labeling, embrace experimentalism and are willing to take risks. DJ Spooky (Paul Miller), one of the best known illbient D.J.'s on the scene today, performs with live jazz musicians, spins and remixes records from all subgenres of ''jazz'' and occasionally picks up the upright bass. Two of the most sought-after turntablists are DJ Mutamassik (Guilia Loli), known for her funky reconfigurations of North African music, and DJ M. Singe (Beth Coleman), who is regarded as a master stylist of illbient.</p>
        <p>Ms. Coleman has performed with countless jazz and experimental artists, including Ilhan Ersahin, Lawrence D. (Butch) Morris and Mr. Haynes. She proves that innovative turntablism requires an extensive musical knowledge, quick reflexes and an ear sensitive not just to pitch and rhythm but also to textures, colors and moods. As with any improviser in an ensemble setting, knowing when to lay out is often more important than virtuosity. At the same time, traditional instrumentalists should also respect the D.J.; such respect, Ms. Coleman says, is rare. She found that even some of the most experimental artists do not consider turntablists ''real'' musicians, and being female in a male world adds yet another obstacle.</p>
        <p>Ms. Coleman is also co-founder, with Howard Goldkrand (MC Verb), of Soundlab Cultural Alchemy, an arts group dedicated to creating location-specific performances of sound and visual art. In many ways, Soundlab is the most recent manifestation of an older tradition of experimentation with electronic music, dating back at least to Sun Ra in the 1950's.</p>
        <p>Less known are the avant-garde composers who not only embrace new technology but also stand among its most important innovators. George Lewis, the virtuoso trombonist and composer, developed technologies that enabled him to create improvised transformations of sound in real time. One hears in Mr. Lewis's 1979 recording ''Homage to Charlie Parker'' a precursor to what the illbient D.J.'s try to achieve through distortion, drones, environmental sounds and other kinds of ''noise.'' Lawrence (Butch) Morris is another pioneer whose influence is even more direct, since he has worked with many of the artists central to this movement. An innovative cornetist and composer, Mr. Morris is the inventor of ''conduction,'' a system of conducted improvisation. He is also one of the first of his peers to see the possibilities of employing D.J.'s as instrumentalists. In the early to mid-1980's, he worked with Christian Marclay, an experimental turntablist who not only explored distortion and ambient sounds but was also known for placing objects on records to generate new sonic textures or an added rhythmic pulse. Mr. Morris continued to explore electronics, turntablism and live sampling through collaborations with J. A. Deane, Yoshihide Otomo, Paul Miller and Ms. Coleman.</p>
        <p>While many of these collaborations have not been recorded, new releases by Carl Craig, DJ Logic (Jason Kibler) and Mr. Haynes provide a glimpse into the future. Mr. Craig's ''Programmed'' is a kind of electronic avant-garde jazz-meets-techno-and-trip-hop. Joined by Francisco Mora on drums and Mr. Taborn on keyboards (not to mention a host of guest artists), Mr. Craig knits together the best of 70's instrumental funk and the space-age futurism of Sun Ra and his Arkestra, with techno. DJ Logic, known to jazz fans for his recordings with the popular organ trio Medeski, Martin and Wood, has developed an improvisational style fiercely attentive to pitch, rhythm and space. He treats the bands he plays with ''like my third turntable,'' as he put it, and says his role as an ensemble member is to create ''some nice colors to match or blend with what's going on.'' His debut album, ''Project Logic,'' might be described as the ultimate turntablist jazz record. It is a collaboration with the bassist Melvin Gibbs and the drummer Skoota Warner in which DJ Logic is joined by an all-star cast of of musicians and poets, including Mr. Haynes and the guitarists Vernon Reid and Brandon Ross.</p>
        <p>Mr. Haynes stands out as the exemplar of the new music. He is the son of the jazz drummer Roy Haynes and a product of the jazz tradition, and his most recent release, ''BPM,'' evolves from his interest in drum 'n' bass, a fast-tempo dance music with lots of starts and stops and rhythmic breaks. He began sitting in with D.J.'s and learned how to play against the rapid fire, stop-go tempos. For Mr. Haynes, it offered a challenge: ''With drum 'n' bass, you actually have improvisation in the groove itself. It creates fresh possibilities for improvisation. But part of the problem with drum 'n' bass is that there isn't much going on harmonically. So as a soloist you have to figure out another way to play.''</p>
        <p>''In order to achieve the kinds of tone colors I heard over the groove,'' he added, ''I started adding a lot of effects to my horn.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Haynes's compositions ''Variations on a Theme by Wagner'' and ''Variations II'' are masterpieces. With Wagner's last opera, ''Parsifal,'' as the basis, Mr. Haynes places 19th-century opera and 21st-century dance music in an improvisational setting. The result is infectious and danceable, contemplative and spare, classic and modern.</p>
        <p>In an age when a growing number of critics are lamenting the loss of romanticism in modern music, it is fitting, if not ironic, that Mr. Haynes would resurrect ''Parsifal'' for contemporary dance audiences. These new explorations by him and others recall the combative antiromanticism of the Italian Futurist Filippo Marinetti, who almost a century ago predicted a future in which global energy would be ''transformed by man's genius into many millions of kilowatts . . . controlled from keyboards with a fertilizing abundance that throbs beneath the fingers of engineers.''</p>
        <p>''How shall we avoid 'Parsifal' and its cloudbursts, puddles and bogs of mystical tears?'' Marinetti asked. Mr. Haynes and his comrades give us the most compelling answer of all: don't avoid it, just plug in and make it funky.</p>
        <p>MUSIC Robin D.G. Kelley, a professor of history and Africana studies at New York University, writes about American culture.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Robin D.G. Kelley, a professor of history and Africana studies at New York University, writes about American culture.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
