<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>AT THE GALLERY WITH/Candace Perich; Unwaning Enthusiasm for Photography</title>
    <meta content="28GALL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202921"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Perich, Candace, Gallery (Katonah, Ny)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perich, Candace</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zimmer, William</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E0D6153DF93BA15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="769" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>AT THE GALLERY WITH/Candace Perich; Unwaning Enthusiasm for Photography</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM ZIMMER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zimmer, William</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with Candace Perich, owner of photo gallery in Katonah, NY, who comments on commemorative group exhibition celebrating gallery's fifth anniversary; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE Candace Perich Gallery in Katonah, which specializes in photography, is observing its fifth anniversary with a commemorative group exhibition that sums up its director's enthusiasms.</p>
        <p>Ms. Perich talked about art and photography -- inseparable topics in her mind -- during an interview in the gallery, which is on Katonah Avenue, the town's major commercial street, and in her home, where she lives with her husband, Anton Perich, a painter and photographer, and their two sons.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE Candace Perich Gallery in Katonah, which specializes in photography, is observing its fifth anniversary with a commemorative group exhibition that sums up its director's enthusiasms.</p>
        <p>Ms. Perich talked about art and photography -- inseparable topics in her mind -- during an interview in the gallery, which is on Katonah Avenue, the town's major commercial street, and in her home, where she lives with her husband, Anton Perich, a painter and photographer, and their two sons.</p>
        <p>Q. How did you come to open a photography gallery?</p>
        <p>A. The story starts a long time ago, when I was about 9 years old. My mother had an art gallery, the Dwan Gallery in Los Angeles, and I got to help some of the artists make their work. So art is what I've lived and breathed; it's second nature to me. I'm comfortable with it. The real challenges are something like writing an effective press release.</p>
        <p>The Dwan Gallery moved to New York in 1963, where it became the gallery for minimal art, which was emerging then. When I was a teenager, a lot of these artists became my friends. I was especially close to Robert Smithson. He gave me some of his strata-like glass pieces when I was 16 and 17.</p>
        <p>Q. Why didn't you open an art gallery?</p>
        <p>A. Well, my mother was so good at it, I wanted to do something else. And I did want to be a photographer at some point -- an animal photographer. In my 20's I went to Africa to photograph animals.</p>
        <p>Q. You first opened in Ridgefield,  not far from here. What was that gallery like?</p>
        <p>A. It was a kind of serendipity. I found an old barber shop, which looked something like a gingerbread house. It was off the beaten path. There was what I think was a beauty parlor in the back. I felt really fortunate to have two rooms to show in. Here, there's just this one space.</p>
        <p>But soon the building was torn down. This space became available, so after 14 months in Ridgefield, I relocated my business here to Katonah, which is where I live. We've lived here for 15 years.</p>
        <p>Q. After five years, would you say that you are a success?</p>
        <p>A. I'm not bankrupt. (She laughs).I'm now becoming established in the photography world. A lot of New York dealers consign work to me. People from the city actually come here -- to Katonah.</p>
        <p>Q. How would you describe the way you run your gallery, the choices and decisions you have to make about what to show?</p>
        <p>A. I've chosen to not represent anyone, although I did try to once and was turned down. When you represent artists, you have to give them shows on a periodic basis. I don't want to take on that much responsibility for an artist's career. On the other hand, during the past five years I've shown over 200 artists, and not many galleries can make that claim. In the future, however, I'll probably have more one-person shows.</p>
        <p>Q. In my mind at least, your gallery has a strong black and white aesthetic. Would you agree?</p>
        <p>A. I'd say that I show about 5 percent color. I did a show especially for children that was all color. I hung it low for them.</p>
        <p>Q. Nature seems to figure prominently in the photographs you show.</p>
        <p>A. Yes, I would say that my focus is on landscape. Several years ago I started the Cross River Reservoir Association, mainly to make people aware of the beautiful environment they live in, and that it is also always vulnerable. I've done a lot of work to preserve trees. Recently, a tree from around 1850 was cut down in Katonah. It's heartbreaking when you see just a stump.</p>
        <p>Nature will be the focus of an exhibit titled ''One Tree'' from June 1 through July 19. The show is a tribute to the Bedford Oak, a tree between 400 and 500 years old, and the symbol of the town.</p>
        <p>The Candace Perich Gallery is at 27 Katonah Avenue; for information about exhibits, call 232-3966. The gallery Web site is www.perichphotogallery.com.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
