<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Talking to Teenagers To Get Guns Off Streets</title>
    <meta content="28GUNS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202927"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="EDUCATION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Firearms</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gun Control</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Newman, Julianne</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lombardi, Kate Stone</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Firearms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gun Control</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E0DF123DF93BA15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="672" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Talking to Teenagers To Get Guns Off Streets</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATE STONE LOMBARDI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lombardi, Kate Stone</byline>
      <dateline>OSSINING</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Julianne Newman and other Westchester County assistant district attorneys are addressing local high school students in effort to determine what it will take to get guns off streets and away from childen (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''HAS anyone in this classroom ever seen a gun?''</p>
        <p>Julianne Newman, an assistant district attorney, was addressing a group of Ossining High School students. More than half raised their hands.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''HAS anyone in this classroom ever seen a gun?''</p>
        <p>Julianne Newman, an assistant district attorney, was addressing a group of Ossining High School students. More than half raised their hands.</p>
        <p>''What kinds of guns have you seen?'' she asked.</p>
        <p>The answers came back -- handguns, rifles, shotguns and more handguns. Most of the students shrugged when asked if it was wrong for a teenager to have a gun.</p>
        <p>In Westchester, nearly half the gun possession charges filed last year involved teenagers, and four of the eight people killed by handguns in the county in 1999 were under the age of 21.</p>
        <p>''Kids are increasingly possessing guns, and they're using them,'' District Attorney Jeanine Pirro said. ''The proportion of juvenile murders that involved guns has increased in this county to an alarming proportion. We are trying to figure out what it takes to get the guns off the street.''</p>
        <p>As part of that effort, prosecutors from Mrs. Pirro's office are speaking to roughly 500 students at high schools in Ossining, Peekskill, Somers and Montrose this month. In Ossining, Ms. Newman used several scenarios to stimulate a conversation about teenagers and guns.</p>
        <p>In one, she told of a group of four teenagers who broke into an abandoned house with a six-pack of beer. At one point one of the boys, Rob, pulled a handgun from his jacket and waved it around. Rob assured his friends it was not loaded, pulling out the ammunition clip to show them. As he spoke, the police enter the house, having received a call about the party from a neighbor.</p>
        <p>Ms. Newman asked the class to guess what crimes, if any, had been committed. The students came up with the following: under-age drinking, trespassing and breaking and entering. Not one volunteered anything about the gun.</p>
        <p>Ms. Newman persevered. ''Does anyone think it's wrong for Rob to have the gun in the house? Entering the house is a trespass, and a violation. Does anyone have any ideas about how the gun in the house presents another set of problems?''</p>
        <p>She explained that not only did the presence of the gun elevate the charge to a felony but also that under the law, everyone in the house -- not just Rob -- could be charged with gun possession. ''It started out with them going into the house to have a beer,'' Ms. Newman said. ''But now you've gone from 15 days possibly for simply entering the house to a maximum of two and a third to seven years for entering the house and one of these people having a gun. That's a whole lot of jail time.''</p>
        <p>The same day the prosecutor spoke the county was kicking off a new gun buy-back and amnesty program. The payment for those voluntarily surrendering weapons was $50 for a handgun and $25 for each rifle and shotgun. All firearms were accepted ''no questions asked.''</p>
        <p>After the class, one 17-year-old said he thought he could get more money selling a weapon on the street than from the county. Asked if he were frightened of guns, he said: ''No, not really. I see them all the time.''</p>
        <p>This is precisely the attitude that frustrates Mrs. Pirro. ''This is so much a part of their reality, it's everyday stuff,'' she said. ''But we have an 8-year-old in the county who walks around today with a bullet in his right thigh, a bullet that was shot by a teenager and passed through another teenager into that child. He'll have it for life. If we can prevent one person from being shot with this program, it's worth it.''</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
