<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Style &amp; Entertaining; Tea and Geometry</title>
    <meta content="28STYLET" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="46" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202775"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Christie's</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnson, Philip</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Viladas, Pilar</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rockefeller, Blanchette</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Plains</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Engineering and Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Architecture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E4DB1E3AF93BA15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="821" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Style &amp; Entertaining; Tea and Geometry</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Pilar Viladas</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Viladas, Pilar</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on architect Philip Johnson and house he created for Blanchette Rockefeller in 1950; house, located on East 52nd Street in Manhattan, will be offered at auction by Christie's International Realty with estimated sale price of $3.5 to $5 million; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>You've heard of celebrity homes; here is the home celebrity. On June 8, Christie's International Realty will offer to the highest bidder (estimate: $3.5 to $5 million) a house at 242 East 52nd Street that was designed by the architect Philip Johnson and completed in 1950 for the art collector and philanthropist Blanchette Rockefeller at a cost of $75,000. In fact, this is the house's second time on the auction block. Its current owner, Anthony d'Offay, a London art dealer, bought the house at Sotheby's in 1989 for $3.5 million.</p>
        <p>For Johnson, the idea of having one of his works auctioned off (again) as if it were a piece of art is pure validation. ''It intimates that I'm an artist,'' says Johnson disingenuously. ''Architects would give anything to be thought of as artists. We're usually thought of as technicians.'' Clearly, he does think of himself as an artist. And why not? The house looks an awful lot like the abstract art it was meant to display. An austere Modernist composition of brick, glass and steel, it was typical of Johnson's houses of that era, like the house for John and Dominique de Menil in Houston and the architect's own legendary Glass House in New Canaan, Conn.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>You've heard of celebrity homes; here is the home celebrity. On June 8, Christie's International Realty will offer to the highest bidder (estimate: $3.5 to $5 million) a house at 242 East 52nd Street that was designed by the architect Philip Johnson and completed in 1950 for the art collector and philanthropist Blanchette Rockefeller at a cost of $75,000. In fact, this is the house's second time on the auction block. Its current owner, Anthony d'Offay, a London art dealer, bought the house at Sotheby's in 1989 for $3.5 million.</p>
        <p>For Johnson, the idea of having one of his works auctioned off (again) as if it were a piece of art is pure validation. ''It intimates that I'm an artist,'' says Johnson disingenuously. ''Architects would give anything to be thought of as artists. We're usually thought of as technicians.'' Clearly, he does think of himself as an artist. And why not? The house looks an awful lot like the abstract art it was meant to display. An austere Modernist composition of brick, glass and steel, it was typical of Johnson's houses of that era, like the house for John and Dominique de Menil in Houston and the architect's own legendary Glass House in New Canaan, Conn.</p>
        <p>For Rockefeller, Johnson tore down an existing four-story building, keeping only its brick side walls and eventually painting them white to provide a suitable background for art: ''The brick gives you the scale of the wall.'' His new design had a two-story structure with a solid brick facade on the ground floor and a glass and steel facade for the second floor. (A one-story building would have looked like ''a bad tooth . . . on a face,'' Johnson once explained.) The house, with its large, open living-and-dining area downstairs and its guest bedroom and bath upstairs, is separated from the master bedroom by a courtyard and small reflecting pool. (A kitchenette, once part of the living area, is now located in the basement.)</p>
        <p>Johnson's design, which seems more like an open-air pavilion than a house, was conceived as a place for Blanchette Rockefeller to put up guests, to entertain and to show off a growing collection of modern art that her husband, John D. Rockefeller III, didn't care to see around the couple's Beekman Place apartment. Like her mother-in-law, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller, who was a founder of the Museum of Modern Art, Blanchette thrilled to the shock of the new, eventually becoming that museum's first female president.</p>
        <p>The house has had several owners over the years, and Johnson himself rented it in the 1970's. The current owner used the house much as Rockefeller did, although instead of Brancusis and Rothkos, d'Offay filled it with Warhols, which were still hanging on the walls when these photographs were taken for the magazine. (The furnishings, meant to approximate what was originally in the house, were borrowed for the shoot.)</p>
        <p>It is almost uncanny that the first house to be accorded celebrity-auction status (twice!) would be designed by Johnson, who has stayed eerily ahead of the curve for most of his 93 years. In 1932, Johnson (and Henry-Russell Hitchcock) organized a groundbreaking exhibition on the International Style at the Museum of Modern Art, where he was also the first curator of architecture and design.</p>
        <p>In the 50's, he worked with his idol, Mies van der Rohe, on the design of the Seagram Building, one of America's Modernist landmarks. In the 80's, Johnson relegated Modernism to the Out List with his Chippendale-influenced AT&amp;T Building, but by 1988, he had tacked yet again, anointing deconstructivist architecture the Next Big Thing by organizing a show on the subject at the Modern. Decon's fame barely lasted the requisite 15 minutes, but Johnson had already caught the next wave. Seven years later, in the most recent addition to his New Canaan compound, he designed a gatehouse, called the Monsta, that pays homage to Frank Gehry, whom Johnson was presciently touting as the next Next Big Thing.</p>
        <p>Johnson explains his postmodern phase as a rebellion against his Modernist master, Mies. But in light of modern architecture's spectacular comeback, Johnson can safely allow -- with characteristic slyness -- that the Rockefeller guest house ''all of a sudden, doesn't seem so old-fashioned.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
