<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Many Sides of Siding</title>
    <meta content="28HOME$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202902"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="YOUR HOME"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roofing and Siding</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Romano, Jay</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Your Home</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Building (Construction)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E5D8153DF93BA15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1210" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Many Sides of Siding</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAY ROMANO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Romano, Jay</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jay Romano column on the array of options available with vinyl siding; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHILE there are many ways to enhance the appearance of a house --  installing a new front door, adding shutters, painting the window frames, sprucing up the landscaping -- few improvements provide the metamorphosis that results from installing new siding.</p>
        <p>''In the last few years, the siding market has exploded,'' said Bruce Herlitschek,  president of American Home Exterior Design, a siding company based in Yonkers.  Mr. Herlitschek said that the growth relates both to the number of homeowners calling to have their existing siding replaced and to the range of choices of replacement materials now available.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHILE there are many ways to enhance the appearance of a house --  installing a new front door, adding shutters, painting the window frames, sprucing up the landscaping -- few improvements provide the metamorphosis that results from installing new siding.</p>
        <p>''In the last few years, the siding market has exploded,'' said Bruce Herlitschek,  president of American Home Exterior Design, a siding company based in Yonkers.  Mr. Herlitschek said that the growth relates both to the number of homeowners calling to have their existing siding replaced and to the range of choices of replacement materials now available.</p>
        <p>''Homeowners have more options now than ever before,'' he said, explaining that in addition to traditional siding materials like cedar-shake shingles and wood clapboard, homeowners can choose from various styles, shapes, colors and even thicknesses.</p>
        <p>And while many homeowners still install aluminum siding, he said, the most common siding material for new installations in the Northeast is vinyl. ''Vinyl siding is molded into different shapes and sizes in the factory,'' he said, adding that since the color of vinyl is imbedded in the material itself -- as opposed to being a surface finish, as it is on aluminum -- scratches are virtually invisible.</p>
        <p>The traditional vinyl panel, Mr. Herlitschek said, is called a ''single-eight,'' which means that the panel is eight inches high. Most vinyl panels come in standard 12-foot lengths.</p>
        <p>The panels most commonly used today, however, are known as ''double-fours'' --  eight-inch-high lengths of vinyl that are molded to appear as two four-inch clapboards, one above the other. Panels are also available in a style called shiplap or Dutchlap, a nine-inch-high panel that looks like two four-and-a-half-inch-high boards that are beveled on the edges.</p>
        <p>''If everybody else on your block has double-fours, using shiplap will give your house a unique exterior detail,'' Mr. Herlitschek said.</p>
        <p>Joseph J. Horan, an owner of Vinylseal, an East Meadow, Long Island, contractor, said that it is also possible to purchase vinyl panels that look like three-inch-high clapboards. ''If you have a one-story ranch, oftentimes we'll recommend going with three-inch panels because it makes the house look taller,'' Mr. Horan said, adding that such panels on a two-  or three-story colonial, on the other hand, could make the house look too busy.</p>
        <p>Another popular style of vinyl siding mimics the look of cedar shingles. ''There are rustic shakes, scallops and even gingerbread,'' he said. ''And there are also a lot of accessory items that can enhance the look of a house.'' Among the accessories, he said, are shutters and decorative moldings that can be installed around windows and doors.</p>
        <p>Mr. Horan said that in most cases, before new vinyl siding can be installed, the existing siding should be removed. Failure to remove it will result in an uneven base for the new siding and make it impossible to assess the condition of the surface underneath the old siding, he said.</p>
        <p>''You have to make sure you have a sound subsurface,'' he said, explaining that it is not uncommon to find rotted wood near where the foundation meets the sheathing and around windows and doors.</p>
        <p>The sole exception, he said, is shingle-type siding that contains asbestos; such siding is generally left in place so that no asbestos fibers are released into the air. ''Then you install a plastic vapor barrier and a layer of foam insulation underneath the new siding that's being installed,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The cost of installing standard vinyl siding, including removing the existing siding and installing a vapor barrier and insulation, should run anywhere from $500 to $700 for every 100 square feet of surface to be covered, he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Horan said that an average house would cost between $12,000 and $15,000. Vinyl shakes, he said, typically cost somewhat more.</p>
        <p>For those who want the very best in vinyl, however, Gerald Damora, president of Seamless Siding Management in Randolph, N.J., said he has just the thing. ''Installing siding is like putting a suit on the house,'' Mr. Damora said. ''And if you want a custom-made suit, what you want is seamless siding.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Damora said that since the longest standard vinyl panels come in 16 1/2-foot lengths, and since house walls are often wider than that, it is generally necessary to install one or more panels to cover the span from one end of a wall to the other. That results in a number of unsightly seams where the ends of adjacent panels overlap.</p>
        <p>Seamless vinyl, however, comes in panels up to 40 feet long, permitting most spans to be covered without overlapping the ends and allowing Mr. Damora's franchisees to install the thickest vinyl available. ''We can make it thick because there are no seams,'' he said. ''If you were to make conventional siding as thick as we make ours, the seams would stand out like pickles in a mayonnaise jar.''</p>
        <p>Yet another advantage of using thicker vinyl, Mr. Damora said, is that it can be produced with a smooth surface. ''The reason ordinary vinyl usually comes with a wood-grained surface is for structural stability,'' he said, explaining that the embossing of relatively thin vinyl is necessary to keep it shaped properly and to keep it from sagging and bowing.</p>
        <p>Thicker vinyl, on the other hand, needs no such internal support and can be manufactured with a smooth surface that looks more like wood than does thinner vinyl with an artificial grain pattern.</p>
        <p>''Seamless is smooth, perfectly straight, and makes a house look like it's supposed to look,'' Mr. Damora said, adding that there is a price to be paid for such quality: seamless siding generally costs 15 to 25 percent more than traditional siding.</p>
        <p>Another option for those who want a custom look is to have a specially designed masonry finish. ''Anywhere you can put siding, you can put our finish,'' said Larry Landes, president of Garden State Brickface, Windows and Siding in Roselle, N.J. Among the various finishes the company can apply are stucco, limestone, brownstone and brickface.</p>
        <p>''In the city, you're certainly not going to put vinyl siding on an old brownstone,'' he said, adding that masonry buildings that have deteriorating facades -- as well as wood-frame buildings that have had the old siding removed -- can be resurfaced with masonry using the company's hand-sculptured process.</p>
        <p>The process generally involves attaching a galvanized steel lath to the building and then applying two coats of cement to the lath. Once the cement has dried, one or more layers of colored stucco are applied to the surface. Then, depending on the type of finish desired, the stucco is hand-carved to simulate brownstone, limestone, brick or stone.</p>
        <p>Mr. Landes said that while a simple stucco finish could cost about the same as a premium vinyl siding job, most other masonry finishes are from 20 to 25 percent more expensive than siding.</p>
        <p>YOUR HOME</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
