<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Singular Appetite, And a Special Place, For Precious Books</title>
    <meta content="28REIF$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="32" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202813"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ART/ARCHITECTURE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wills and Estates</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Rare Books</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Christie's</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reif, Rita</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Foyle, Christina</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rare Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wills and Estates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E3DD163DF93BA15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="967" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Singular Appetite, And a Special Place, For Precious Books</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RITA REIF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Reif, Rita</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Rare book collection of legendary British bookseller William Foyle, which he housed in sumptuous private library that was kept intact by his daughter Christina until her death last June, will be sold by heirs at Christie's auction; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BOOKS were William Foyle's life. But he began collecting them only in 1945 when, at the age of 60, he stepped down as the head of Foyle's, the bookstore he had founded here with his brother, Gilbert, in 1903. In its heyday a half century ago, Foyle's, on Charing Cross Road, was known the world over as the people's bookstore, stocking five million books, mostly secondhand, on every imaginable subject on its 30 miles of shelves.</p>
        <p>As a collector, William Foyle bought with the same passion and savvy that he had shown as a bookseller, acquiring ''like crazy'' rare books and illuminated manuscripts from the Middle Ages through the early 20th century, said a grandson, Christopher Foyle, 57, who is Foyle's chairman. Mr. Foyle said his grandfather seemed intent on finding books that were appropriate for the great library at Beeleigh Abbey, the 12th-century monastery at Maldon in Essex that he acquired to retire to and live in as a country gentleman. He let his silver hair grow to his shoulders and wore waistcoats and winged collars and cravats with diamond stickpins. For the spectacular pageants he staged at Beeleigh, he donned medieval robes and regalia to lead townspeople on parades through the 11 acres of gardens.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BOOKS were William Foyle's life. But he began collecting them only in 1945 when, at the age of 60, he stepped down as the head of Foyle's, the bookstore he had founded here with his brother, Gilbert, in 1903. In its heyday a half century ago, Foyle's, on Charing Cross Road, was known the world over as the people's bookstore, stocking five million books, mostly secondhand, on every imaginable subject on its 30 miles of shelves.</p>
        <p>As a collector, William Foyle bought with the same passion and savvy that he had shown as a bookseller, acquiring ''like crazy'' rare books and illuminated manuscripts from the Middle Ages through the early 20th century, said a grandson, Christopher Foyle, 57, who is Foyle's chairman. Mr. Foyle said his grandfather seemed intent on finding books that were appropriate for the great library at Beeleigh Abbey, the 12th-century monastery at Maldon in Essex that he acquired to retire to and live in as a country gentleman. He let his silver hair grow to his shoulders and wore waistcoats and winged collars and cravats with diamond stickpins. For the spectacular pageants he staged at Beeleigh, he donned medieval robes and regalia to lead townspeople on parades through the 11 acres of gardens.</p>
        <p>At William Foyle's death in 1963, Beeleigh's library held 4,000 books and manuscripts. It remained intact throughout the residency of a daughter, Christina Foyle Batty, who succeeded him as the head of the business. She died at 88 last June.</p>
        <p>Now, the Foyle family and other heirs are selling William Foyle's books at Christie's here in a sale described by Tom Lamb, director of the rare books and manuscripts department, as ''the largest British book collection to be auctioned in 20 years.'' Some of the most important books will be on view in New York from June 28 to 30 at Christie's annex, 308 East 59th Street, before the three-day sale, July 11 to 13. The collection is expected to fetch more than $9.5 million.</p>
        <p>''It's most unusual to have so many 12th-century manuscripts -- seven -- some even in their original bindings,'' said Kay Sutton, Christie's specialist in London on such medieval material. ''The greatest of these is St. Augustine's 'Commentary on the Psalms' illuminated by Solomon of Gottschalk at Lambach Abbey in Austria.''</p>
        <p>Amazingly, this gloriously illuminated volume is still in its original leather binding, darkened now from white to tawniness and bearing markings on the back cover of the chains that had been used to secure it to shelves. Because most of Lambach's books were re-bound in the 15th century and none had ever been found with chain marks on the original bindings, Mrs. Sutton said scholars were surprised to find the book in this state. The simple line drawings illustrating the texts in the ''Commentary'' include a bright red drawing of King Solomon, a scepter in one hand, a globe in the other, next to Solomon's ''Psalm.'' The manuscript is expected to bring $230,000 to $350,000.</p>
        <p>''Foyle obviously wanted monastic books for Beeleigh,'' she said. ''But it seemed remarkable to find one: St. Bernard of Clairvaux's 'Apologia' that was originally in another Essex library, at St. Osytz, an abbey across an estuary from Beeleigh.'' The book has its original binding and a most unusual stitched strap that experts at the Beinecke Library at Yale told Mrs. Sutton ''they had never seen anything quite like before.'' Christie's expects it will bring as much as $120,000.</p>
        <p>Foyle could not resist acquiring all the 15th- and 16th-century copies he could find of the ''Book of Hours,'' a medieval best-seller. So he bought 58, 32 as manuscripts, 8 of which are in Dutch. He also acquired a leaf from a 15th-century Gutenburg Bible, a copy of Jacques Lefevre's 16th-century translation of the letters of St. Paul and all four Shakespeare Folios from the 17th century. Foyle loved old maps and amassed an impressive group of 18th-century topographical works on Essex. His interest in English literature is revealed in the Kelmscott Press's ''Works of Geoffrey Chaucer'' as well as 19th- and 20th-century works by Wordsworth, Keats, Dickens, Austen, the Bronte sisters, Hardy and Eliot.</p>
        <p>Christopher Foyle remembers his grandfather perusing leather-bound books in Beeleigh's 40-foot-long, two-story barrel-vaulted library, a space that had served as the dormitory for the Augustinian monks between the 13th century, when it was added, and 1536, when Henry VIII broke with Rome and closed the monasteries. But Mr. Foyle and his brother, Anthony, preferred playing in the attic with their steam engines and electric trains.</p>
        <p>THE toys are gone -- as are most of the books -- from Beeleigh, which Mr. Foyle is buying for himself and his family. ''It should take me no time at all to fill the shelves and replace the trains,'' he said. But because of his interests in archaeology, anthropology and travel as well as in aviation, as the founder and head of Air Foyle, a private cargo airline, the kinds of books in the library will be different from those collected by his grandfather. Mr. Foyle, who is also modernizing the bookstore, adding computers and a Web site, envisions building another great library. ''Yes, more books will be coming to Beeleigh,'' he said.</p>
        <p>ART/ARCHITECTURE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
