<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>It's Hard to Predict What Admissions Office Wants Each Year</title>
    <meta content="28ADMI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202882"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Admissions Standards</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Green, Howard, And Associates</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greene, Matthew</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bowles, Adam</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Admissions Standards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E7D9143DF93BA15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="595" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>It's Hard to Predict What Admissions Office Wants Each Year</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM BOWLES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bowles, Adam</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Matthew Greene, senior associate for Howard Greene and Associates educational consulting firm, comments on difficulties parents face in trying to predict what top colleges will deem as important admissions criteria from year to year (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ARE you a high school senior who can debate the pros and cons of such controversial issues as cloning? Then Georgetown University wants you. Can you deftly handle the basketball at point guard? Try Princeton University. Or maybe soccer is your game. In that case, head to Dartmouth College.</p>
        <p>Those are the perceptions many families have as they try to find a way that will make their children stand out in this bumper year of high schools seniors nationwide, said Matthew Greene, a senior associate for Howard Greene and Associates, an education consulting company in Westport and New York City.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ARE you a high school senior who can debate the pros and cons of such controversial issues as cloning? Then Georgetown University wants you. Can you deftly handle the basketball at point guard? Try Princeton University. Or maybe soccer is your game. In that case, head to Dartmouth College.</p>
        <p>Those are the perceptions many families have as they try to find a way that will make their children stand out in this bumper year of high schools seniors nationwide, said Matthew Greene, a senior associate for Howard Greene and Associates, an education consulting company in Westport and New York City.</p>
        <p>Problem is it doesn't quite work that way. For all college admissions officers at higher universities care, it could be stamp collecting that gets you ''in.''</p>
        <p>''The myth is that if you put your kid into fencing school at age 5 that is your magic key to a higher university,'' said Mr. Greene, whose company supports and guides families through the admissions process at private schools, graduate schools, and universities.</p>
        <p>''But that is not a guarantee of anything. What we counsel families to do is for students to pursue their passions. Colleges are looking for talented academic students who have one or two clearly defined passions.''</p>
        <p>The key is to be ''angular,'' the buzzword among consultants like Mr. Greene who point out that colleges want to build well-rounded classes of strongly defined individuals rather than simply classes full of well-rounded students.</p>
        <p>Mr. Greene said Ivy League schools do have a history of focusing admissions efforts on certain areas.</p>
        <p>For Harvard University in Massachusetts, squash and crew have been traditional targets, he said Yale University in New Haven also prizes rowing athletes. At Princeton University in New Jersey, it has been basketball and lacrosse. And at Dartmouth College in New Hampshire, he said, soccer and football players seem to gain an advantage over other equally academic students.</p>
        <p>Parents and their children take notice because they understand the competition is intense. Most selective universities receive more than 10,000 applications a year. And the reality is a student may be the class valedictorian with straight A's and still get rejected, while an outstanding high school athlete with a more modest academic record may be accepted, Mr. Greene said. But, he added, academics are still the priority.</p>
        <p>Mr. Greene encourages families to view the process differently. Say out of 10 applicants with equal grades to Georgetown University in Washington, D.C., nine are experienced debaters and one is a French literature enthusiast. Mr. Greene said the odds are the French literature student will be accepted and several of the debaters won't be.</p>
        <p>''If a particular college doesn't have a lot of people like you it means you actually have a better chance of getting into that college,'' Mr. Greene said. He said a family's strategy should include the child's participation in music competitions, athletic camps or anything that shows the student is dedicated to developing a particular talent.</p>
        <p>''You don't have to be a junior Olympian or performing at Carnegie Hall to get into one of these colleges,'' Mr. Greene said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
