<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From Start As a Tot To No. 1 Girl Golfer</title>
    <meta content="28GOLF$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202875"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FOR THE RECORD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Francella, Meaghan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Slater, Chuck</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E4DC143DF93BA15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="768" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From Start As a Tot To No. 1 Girl Golfer</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHUCK SLATER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Slater, Chuck</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Meaghan Francella of Port Chester, best female high school golfer in New York State, who has finished tenth out of 50 in Scott Robertson Memorial in Roanoke, Va; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE best female high school golfer in New York State weighs 110 pounds -- spikes included -- and drives the ball 240 yards.</p>
        <p>Last weekend, in her first competition of the year against the nation's best junior golfers, she finished 10th out of 50 in the Scott Robertson Memorial in Roanoke, Va.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE best female high school golfer in New York State weighs 110 pounds -- spikes included -- and drives the ball 240 yards.</p>
        <p>Last weekend, in her first competition of the year against the nation's best junior golfers, she finished 10th out of 50 in the Scott Robertson Memorial in Roanoke, Va.</p>
        <p>She has shot a 73 at the PGA Junior Nationals and, at 18, plays to a 2 handicap.</p>
        <p>But then, she got an early start on the game.</p>
        <p>''As soon as I was walking, I had a club in my hands,'' Meaghan Francella of Port Chester and the tiny Holy Child School in Rye said. ''I guess I just took to it.''</p>
        <p>That she did.</p>
        <p>''She loved to hit the ball,'' said Denise Francella, her mother and a physical education teacher at Holy Child. ''My husband, Joe, cut down a 3-iron and Meaghan would hit in the backyard of her grandparents' house. We were both athletes and wanted her involved in sports -- her first toy chest was shaped like a basketball.''</p>
        <p>Meaghan would go on to be a standout point guard at Holy Child and was a good enough baseball player to be the only girl in the Port Chester Little League. But it was golf that interested her the most.</p>
        <p>''While we never belonged to a club, we would get her out anywhere hitting golf balls,'' Mrs. Francella said. ''A driving range. The local high school -- there we'd put tees down and shag for her.''</p>
        <p>By 9, Meaghan was entering local and regional golf competitions. By 10, she was winning them. She is the two-time New York State Junior Girls champion and last summer also won the Westchester and Metropolitan junior girls titles, a triple that had never been accomplished before. She is ranked 36th nationally among high school girls and is headed to the University of Memphis on a full athletic scholarship.</p>
        <p>Meaghan is not only the main reason Holy Child is a golf power but she is also the main reason Holy Child has a golf team.</p>
        <p>Cathy Giandurco, the Holy Child golf coach, is the first to say so.</p>
        <p>''Two years ago I asked our athletic director, Cathy Wasilik, to start a team, pointing out that we already had Meaghan in the school,'' Mrs. Giandurco said. ''She agreed, and everyone has been very happy with it. Meaghan is not only an exceptional player but also an exceptional young woman.''</p>
        <p>Her dual-meet record is exceptional, too: 26 to 0.</p>
        <p>And she can only get better, said Tom Patri, the director of instruction at the Westchester Country Club in Rye. He has been giving Meaghan lessons for three years.</p>
        <p>''I think she's got it all in front of her,'' Patri said. ''She's as good an athlete as any female junior I've ever come across. It's her exceptional hand-eye coordination which gives her such distance off the tee. She has a great sense of timing.''</p>
        <p>And she is still very much a teenager.</p>
        <p>''I have some issues with her on her short game, the shots of 50 yards or less,'' Patri added. ''I think with juniors, short shots are just not as glamorous -- they don't get that that's how this game is played, how you bring down your score.''</p>
        <p>It can make for friction, the coach said.</p>
        <p>''She's such a great kid -- my wife and I love her like a daughter,'' Patri said, ''so it can be tough.''</p>
        <p>But Patri looks at Meaghan and sees an athlete 50 yards from greatness. So he battles.</p>
        <p>''If she works on her short game, her playing tournament golf for a living is not a long shot,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Meaghan said of Patri: ''Yes, he's right. My short game needs a little work.''</p>
        <p>It's not obvious at her league competition, where Meaghan routinely closes out her nine-hole matches well before the ninth hole. Still, she admits she is haunted by a missed two-foot putt on the final hole, which would have tied her for first place in a tournament in Rochester last summer. But like most teenagers, she is more into fun than introspection.</p>
        <p>''I like the exercise,'' she said of her sport. ''I like the walking. I like the competition, and it's fun going around the country with my parents and meeting other people at tournaments.''</p>
        <p>Referring to the junior golfer Courtney Wood, she added, ''My best friend lives in Tennessee.'' Brentwood, Tenn., to be exact.</p>
        <p>FOR THE RECORD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
