<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From Children to Medicine, a Particular Look at the World; First Novel Delves Into Dark Passions</title>
    <meta content="28BOO1$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Books; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202872"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Merrill, Susan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Verongos, Helen</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Member of the Family, A (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902EEDD143DF93BA15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="530" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From Children to Medicine, a Particular Look at the World; First Novel Delves Into Dark Passions</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HELEN VERONGOS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Verongos, Helen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of Long Island writer Susan Merrill, whose first novel, A Member of the Family, deals with adopting troubled Romanian child; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SUSAN MERRELL does much of her writing wearing a coat -- out of necessity rather than eccentricity. Her office, in the basement of her house in Sag Harbor, is chilly. But the temperature guarantees that when she wants to concentrate on her work, interruptions from her family will be minimal.</p>
        <p>''It didn't have to be nice or anything, it just had to be mine,'' she said, leading the way to a desk nesting among book-filled shelves, a space heater, her old nursing rocker, and a file cabinet newly acquired to contain her research material.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SUSAN MERRELL does much of her writing wearing a coat -- out of necessity rather than eccentricity. Her office, in the basement of her house in Sag Harbor, is chilly. But the temperature guarantees that when she wants to concentrate on her work, interruptions from her family will be minimal.</p>
        <p>''It didn't have to be nice or anything, it just had to be mine,'' she said, leading the way to a desk nesting among book-filled shelves, a space heater, her old nursing rocker, and a file cabinet newly acquired to contain her research material.</p>
        <p>In this corner of the airy shingled house designed by her husband, an architect, Ms. Merrell worked out the complex relationships and interlaced lives that are the foundation of ''A Member of the Family,'' her first novel, published in March by HarperCollins. The book is an account of a secure, happy Sag Harbor family, Chris and Deborah Latham, their daughter, Caroline, and adopted son, Michael.</p>
        <p>When they save Michael from a Romanian orphanage, he is a toddler in age but not in fact. Like many of the neglected children of Romania's notorious institutions, he received little stimulation or love in his infancy. At the age of 18 months he cannot yet walk and his intellectual and emotional development are stunted.</p>
        <p>The Lathams have plenty of love to salve Michael's wounds and the assurance that, although adoptions like this one often are troubled, they can provide everything Michael needs to thrive. Chris himself was an orphan who relied on the generosity of the community for love and care when his parents died, and he grew up with a deep awareness of the value of a secure home as well as the values embraced by the townspeople.</p>
        <p>Chris, a dentist known to everyone, protects some of his neighbors' -- and the town's -- deepest secrets, while Deborah, who is ''from away,'' devotes herself to her home and her children on one hand and tries to build connections to the community with another.</p>
        <p>But love, affluence and the best intentions are not enough to save Michael from growing increasingly destructive and violent, tearing at the family until it has nearly unraveled. After doctors, brain scans, therapy, holistic healers and support groups fail, the Lathams face a decision that is hard to imagine and even harder to talk about -- what does a family do when an adoption simply collapses, threatening to bring down the entire family?</p>
        <p>Running as crosscurrents to the plot are the lives and troubles of other people who flesh out the small town existence in Sag Harbor, in both its picturesque and malignant aspects. Strangers become friends, friends become enemies and most everyone becomes a judge of the Latham family as their problems become public. The result is a drama that can be disturbing, an outcome Ms. Merrell said she did not expect.</p>
        <p>''I was genuinely surprised when people said it was so dark,'' the author said. She said some readers have asked, ''How dare you do this?'' Others reacted with relief, saying, ''Finally, someone is telling our story.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
