<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From Children to Medicine, a Particular Look at the World; L.I. Family Saga Of the Revolution</title>
    <meta content="28BOO2$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Books; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202873"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cleary, Rita</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Delatiner, Barbara</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Spies and Tories (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DEEDD143DF93BA15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="654" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From Children to Medicine, a Particular Look at the World; L.I. Family Saga Of the Revolution</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA DELATINER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Delatiner, Barbara</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of author Rita Cleary of Oyster Bay Cove, Long Island, whose latest hisorical novel, Spies and Tories, deals with early years of American Revolution; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WITH Raynham Hall, the pre-Revolutionary home of the Townsend family, just minutes away from her house in Oyster Bay Cove, Rita Cleary says she has ''always been fascinated'' by the legendary Long Island family -- ''especially by Sally Townsend.''</p>
        <p>So when Ms. Cleary, a writer whose two previous historical novels -- ''Sorrel,'' a tale about homesteading in 1886 and ''Goldtown,'' about the placer gold rush in 1867 -- took place in Montana, decided to change geography, if not genre, she hit upon the Townsend saga, specifically during the Revolutionary War.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WITH Raynham Hall, the pre-Revolutionary home of the Townsend family, just minutes away from her house in Oyster Bay Cove, Rita Cleary says she has ''always been fascinated'' by the legendary Long Island family -- ''especially by Sally Townsend.''</p>
        <p>So when Ms. Cleary, a writer whose two previous historical novels -- ''Sorrel,'' a tale about homesteading in 1886 and ''Goldtown,'' about the placer gold rush in 1867 -- took place in Montana, decided to change geography, if not genre, she hit upon the Townsend saga, specifically during the Revolutionary War.</p>
        <p>After two years of researching the  story and another two years of writing, her interest produced ''Spies and Tories,'' published recently by Sunstone Press. Set in New York from 1776 to 1781, the novel provides a panoramic view of life in the early years of the war. It ranges from the teeming streets of lower Manhattan, where the wealthy Townsend merchant family maintained a warehouse and store, to the grassy plains, virgin forests and busy harbors of bucolic Long Island.</p>
        <p>The cast of characters are equally inclusive, with a cross-section of players: fiery colonials bent upon righting the wrongs suffered under English rule, complacent Loyalists anxious to preserve their status and material well-being, English soldiers either merely doing their professional duty or cruelly enjoying the subjugation of the Colonials, neutral Quakers unwilling to formally take sides.</p>
        <p>Although the Townsends have been prominent since their arrival on Long Island in the 1620's -- a Townsend Society of America still operates -- when Ms. Cleary began her research she soon discovered that information was hard to come by.</p>
        <p>''They didn't write much down,'' said Andrew Batten, a historian who is the director of Raynham Hall. ''There aren't even portraits; only one sketch of Robert done by a nephew.'' Mr. Batten applauds ''Spies and Tories'' for ''capturing the way it would have been here, especially in the depiction of places.''</p>
        <p>So in creating her tale about how one of the four Townsend sons, Robert, became a spy for the revolutionaries and how one of the three daughters, Sally, fell in love with an English officer quartered in their home, Ms. Cleary had to rely on other sources. She found her facts in histories, historical society collections and contemporary journals, like Rivington's Loyalist Gazette, the newspaper for which Robert Townsend wrote.</p>
        <p>Except for some minor characters, the people in the novel are all real, fleshed out by the author's imagination or by contemporary accounts. Equally authentic are such aspects of the war as the deadly prison ship hulks anchored off Manhattan -- Ms. Cleary called them ''concentration camps'' -- that held suspected rebels. A detailed description of building British battlements in Oyster Bay comes directly from an English officer's journal.</p>
        <p>Even when the author took fictional leaps, she said they were based on conclusions drawn from facts. For example, she created a female spy, Mary, to be Robert's colleague and mistress.</p>
        <p>''Records show one woman spy in that ring, only known as No. 355, and accounts mention a housekeeper, Mary, at the Peck's Slip house, who reportedly slept with the brothers,'' Ms. Cleary said. ''I just combined both.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Cleary admits to one major literary license: calling the Townsend Oyster Bay house ''Raynham Hall.'' Built in 1740, the house did not receive its impressive name, after the ancestral home in England, until the 1850's.</p>
        <p>And if the novel ends abruptly in 1781 it isn't because Ms. Cleary plans a sequel. ''I had to stop at that point because nothing more happened to my main characters,'' she said. ''Sally never married. Robert just sort of disappears. The war and what happened to them during it was their defining moment.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
