<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Seasoned and Seasonless</title>
    <meta content="28DINE$13" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202929"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="RESTAURANTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Rebecca's (Edgewater, Nj, Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jones, Catherine</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02EEDF123DF93BA15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1085" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Seasoned and Seasonless</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CATHERINE JONES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jones, Catherine</byline>
      <dateline>EDGEWATER</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Catherine Jones reviews Rebecca's restaurant in Edgewater, NJ; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN asked about what I like in a restaurant, I generally talk about those that are continually fiddling with ingredients available only at a specific time of year. But that said, I hope Rebecca's never changes its menu. Or at the very least that the jerk chicken skewers, camarones con mojo, cumin-cilantro red snapper, and caramel flan are here to stay, whatever the season. I want to enjoy them every time I go there.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN asked about what I like in a restaurant, I generally talk about those that are continually fiddling with ingredients available only at a specific time of year. But that said, I hope Rebecca's never changes its menu. Or at the very least that the jerk chicken skewers, camarones con mojo, cumin-cilantro red snapper, and caramel flan are here to stay, whatever the season. I want to enjoy them every time I go there.</p>
        <p>Rebecca's is the type of place in which you will want to become a regular if you aren't one already: you can nestle into a window seat or around a small table (pairs or even solo diners are comfortable here) and recall the menu after one visit. What's more, you will have delicious fare presented by a familiar person -- Rebecca herself, a graceful Cuban-born beauty, graduate of Fairleigh Dickinson's hotel school in Rutherford, who greets 90 percent of her clients by name. (I hope that she too can remain a fixture after her baby arrives in August.)</p>
        <p>Rebecca's is on the first floor of a cheery white town house backed against a cliff face that adds a dramatic edge to the rear patio. Although the space is named after Rebecca, it is actually her husband, Glenn Chernalis, who is the true backbone of the cozy 40-seat place.  Mr. Chernalis not only built the restaurant but is also the chef who, along with Rebecca's mother, Rosa, created the superbly fresh Cuban-Caribbean menu. He learned the business at any early age at his father's Cedar Hill Inn in Wycoff and is also the photographer and antique collector who decorated the interior.</p>
        <p>After transferring our bagged Corona beers into chilled, curvy glasses, Rebecca delivered an assortment of tantalizing appetizers to our table.  The Cuban croquetas of chicken, pork or beef were steaming bundles of herby ground meat enclosed in very thin yet crispy crust, perfectly suited to the accompanying horseradish sauce. The yuca fingers, an elegant, sweeter version of steak frites, just couldn't compare, though they were perfectly suited to the setting. Few quesadillas out there  can match Rebecca's grilled chorizo versions, served with tomato-cilantro salsa and fresh guacamole, intensely flavored and artfully presented. Cilantro shrimp were plump and salty, happily paired with a generous portion of the same salsa. Skewered strips of tender jerk chicken perched over a mixture of sweet potato and red pepper, but not for long.</p>
        <p>Salads are a separate course at Rebecca's. While the dressings were overly sweet and the components lacked the necessary acidity, who can pass up a steaming, juicy portobello mushroom over field greens with goat cheese and roasted red peppers? Or grilled shrimp atop glistening slivers of mango? I enjoyed the fresh cranberries paired with walnuts, but wished that the balsamic dressing and goat cheese had not been incorporated into practically every salad. Fortunately, the warm chick pea and chorizo salad was tossed in garlic and olive oil, although the combination of garbanzos and sausage made for a curious pairing of textures.</p>
        <p>As entrees approached, I recognized there would be several redundancies within my meal. Shrimp, jerk chicken, black beans and avocadoes permeate the menu. But when each manifestation is this good who cares about variety? In fact, the dishes that feature these items were my favorites. Camarones con mojo -- shrimp marinated in a sauce of garlic, olive oil and sour orange juice, then grilled and served over white rice with a splash of the mojo and garnished with fried plantains -- is something I could have night after night. Smooth rather than biting garlic scents wafted up from my plate, and the accompanying flavors were  sweet and inviting. Coconut shrimp Savanna (named after the couple's firstborn) were equally fragrant and simple, sauteed in coconut milk, fresh basil and red chilies and playfully planted in a bowl of dirty rice, studded with black beans.</p>
        <p>Before I get to the authentic Cuban dishes, I must mention the most memorable entree of all: cumin-cilantro red snapper, so moist I could barely distinguish the flesh from the silken lemon butter sauce. Alongside, large chunks of vibrant avocado were tossed with hearts of palm and lime, creating an addictive and memorable salad.</p>
        <p>Jerk chicken was just as good if not juicier than its appetizer version.  Rebecca's spice rub was chunky but not bitter, and the accompanying pineapple mango salsa competed admirably with the tomato-cilantro  condiment. Lechon asado (Cuban roast pork) came marinated in mojo sauce, and was roasted, sliced and served with a choice of rice, black beans, yuca con mojo, coconut mashed yams and either maduros (sweet plaintains) or tostones (salty); a vegetarian would be in paradise with a plate of these side dishes. Amazingly, the pork was outdone by the salty ropa vieja, shredded beef cooked in a sauce of red wine and tomatoes with a delicious blend of peppers, olives and onions.</p>
        <p>Rebecca suggested I have dessert outside; the courtyard is truly an oasis within an oasis. Seated between a bubbling fountain and a wall of rock, I sampled the most seductive treat of all: Cuban flan. It was dense, rich, syrupy and cold -- a sinful ending to an already exquisite feast.</p>
        <p>As I drove through Weehawken, topping off my nearly perfect night with a breathtaking view of Manhattan, I wondered if I should bother seeking out a farmer's-market-driven restaurant again.</p>
        <p>Rebecca's  236 Old River Road, Edgewater  (201) 943-8808;  Reservations, (201) 313-3537</p>
        <p>EXCELLENT  ATMOSPHERE -- Romantic and relaxed.  SERVICE -- So efficient it was barely perceptible.  SMOKING -- Only on the patio.  WINE LIST -- B.Y.O.  RECOMMENDED DISHES -- Croquetas; cilantro shrimp; quesadillas; jerk chicken skewers; grilled portobello mushroom salad; avocado and hearts of palm salad; fresh cranberry and goat cheese salad; coconut shrimp Savanaa; cumin cilantro red snapper;  jerk chicken; lechon asado; ropa vieja; pescado del dia; flan.</p>
        <p>PRICE RANGE -- Appetizers and salads: $6 to $15; entrees: $15 to $24; desserts: $6 to $8.  RESERVATIONS -- Recommended; responses to requests on answering machine can take a while.  CREDIT CARDS -- All major.  HOURS -- Tuesdays through Saturdays, 5:30 to 10 p.m.  WHEELCHAIR ACCESS -- Up a few steps but management will assist.  RATINGS -- Poor, Fair, Satisfactory, Good, Very Good, Excellent, Extraordinary.  Ratings reflect the reviewer's reaction to food, ambiance and service, with price taken into consideration. Menu listings and prices are subject to change.</p>
        <p>RESTAURANTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
