<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lament for Karla</title>
    <meta content="RUS.$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202780"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Moscow (Russia)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stasio, Marilyn</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia/Moscow</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E6D81E3AF93BA15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1274" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lament for Karla</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARILYN STASIO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stasio, Marilyn</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Marilyn Stasio travel essay on Moscow, part of series about links between places and fictional detectives; laments loss of sinister Soviet-era Russia with its atmosphere of bleak despair; quotes from several books set in Moscow (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I WENT to Russia not too long ago and it wasn't there -- at least, not the sinister, Soviet-era Russia that writers of cold war spy thrillers had prepared me to find behind the Iron Curtain. For that matter, the Iron Curtain wasn't there.</p>
        <p>Where was the cold air of menace that hung over Moscow in Martin Cruz Smith's ''Gorky Park,'' smothering a politically sensitive murder investigation in an oppressive landscape of ''white breath, white trees, white snow, white sky''? What ever happened to Karla, the implacable chief of Soviet espionage (''so self-possessed that he could allow, if need be, 10 years for an operation to bear fruit'') who relentlessly pursued the British agent George Smiley in ''Quest for Karla,'' the trilogy of cerebral thrillers that John Le Carre wrote in the 1970's? Where, oh where, among the spring buds of a new political climate, were the bitter snows of yesteryear?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I WENT to Russia not too long ago and it wasn't there -- at least, not the sinister, Soviet-era Russia that writers of cold war spy thrillers had prepared me to find behind the Iron Curtain. For that matter, the Iron Curtain wasn't there.</p>
        <p>Where was the cold air of menace that hung over Moscow in Martin Cruz Smith's ''Gorky Park,'' smothering a politically sensitive murder investigation in an oppressive landscape of ''white breath, white trees, white snow, white sky''? What ever happened to Karla, the implacable chief of Soviet espionage (''so self-possessed that he could allow, if need be, 10 years for an operation to bear fruit'') who relentlessly pursued the British agent George Smiley in ''Quest for Karla,'' the trilogy of cerebral thrillers that John Le Carre wrote in the 1970's? Where, oh where, among the spring buds of a new political climate, were the bitter snows of yesteryear?</p>
        <p>Gone, gone, gone.</p>
        <p>Nobody reads that stuff anymore, my Russian hosts gently informed me, as they hustled me into the smart shops, fancy restaurants and gleamingly refurbished landmarks of modern Moscow. Actually, they don't even write that stuff anymore. The great spy masters are either abandoning the old Russia and striking out for new frontiers or repudiating the genre entirely. Martin Cruz Smith's latest novel takes place in Cuba, and Frederick Forsyth's last book was set in a Coney Island fish factory.</p>
        <p>Having had a glimpse of the new Russia, I can understand the disenchantment of the genre masters. Compared with the subtle chess players in cold war thrillers, those black-booted Mafia gangsters who gun their BMW motorbikes on the cobbled side streets of the Tverskaya while making their shakedown rounds are drugstore cowboys. The millionaire bankers, oil tycoons, media moguls and industry barons who make up Russia's new oligarchy might prove to be more cunning villains. But don't ask these greedy biznizmeni (stout men who ostentatiously park their big Bentleys on public sidewalks) to adapt their crass style to the classic spy thriller, with its reflective foreign agents, its byzantine games of intrigue and agonizing moral dilemmas.</p>
        <p>The buy-or-die spirit of Russia's new market economy doesn't adapt any better to the atmosphere of bleak despair in these novels. Pleasant as it may be, shopping in the fashionable boutiques of the Arbat and Ma nezh Square will never replace the old thrill of being herded through the GUM department store by a glum Intourist guide. Luckily, my reading matter on this trip took the edge off the unnerving civility that dollar-bearing foreigners now encounter.</p>
        <p>Lenin was still rotting decorously in his tomb on the morning that I went to Red Square, and the Tsarskaya -- the wooden tower where Ivan the Terrible stood gloating over the protracted executions of state criminals -- was still good for a heartfelt shudder. But the sun was shining, tourists were gamboling, and the little army of fuzz-faced soldiers who marched up to me only wanted to have their pictures taken to send home to their mothers in Gdansk.</p>
        <p>So, it was with some relief that I buried my nose in ''The Forbidden Zone,'' a political thriller by Michael Hetzer. Hetzer was the founding editor of The Moscow Times, the English-language newspaper in Moscow, and a survivor of the fusillade of gunfire that ripped up the newspaper's offices (and killed four people) in the chaotic street fighting of 1993. In the eyes of his heroine, an American astronomer named Katherine Sears, Moscow in 1984 was still a ''gloomy, oppressive and sinister'' place for a woman traveling alone.</p>
        <p>Although I encountered no hostility on my own trip (beyond the supercilious sneer of a waiter at the ever-so-trendy Boyarsky restaurant), poor Katherine fares otherwise when she tries to find out the fate of a dissident astrophysicist. Pegged as a spy, she is dragged from her room at the huge and hideous Ukraine Hotel (''the city's largest foreigner ghetto'') by K.G.B. agents and hounded into hiding by a senior member of the Politburo. Happily, the chase takes her to the very landmarks I was headed for that day: the magnificent Cathedral of the Assumption (where she's torn away from the splendid icons and pursued to the bell tower by a hooded monk); the medieval enclosure of Novodevushi Convent (where a woman in a red scarf slips her a cryptic message); the swank Moskva Restaurant (where she catches the same awful floor show I did).</p>
        <p>While Katherine's jaunty Perils-of-Pauline adventures are fine for sightseeing, Robert Harris's ''Archangel'' is a book best taken out after dark. The hero is a British scholar named Fluke Kelso who has come to Moscow to attend an international symposium marking the reopening of the Soviet archives only to discover that the cult of Stalinism is still very much alive in Russia. Caught up in the ''charge of history,'' he wanders the city like a traveler in a time warp. ''That was what always drew him back,'' he says, ''the way history hung in the air between the blackened buildings like sulfur after a lightning strike.''</p>
        <p>When night falls on the city in ''Gorky Park'' -- ''the evening a maternal black, windows small and bright, the faces on the street bright as windows'' -- Martin Cruz Smith's police inspector, Arkady Renko, experiences the same sensation of being adrift in time. Standing alone in the winter twilight, ''he felt he could have been in any Moscow of the past five centuries, and he wouldn't have been surprised by the sound of hooves in mud.''</p>
        <p>In the paranoid world of the espionage novel, the hovering past is always alive with menace. In ''Archangel'' Robert Harris makes the present seem as malevolent as the past. I never made it to Robotnik, a fictional Mafia-run nightclub where Fluke Kelso observes rich Russians at sexual play and learns the going rate for a ''respectable'' prostitute ($300). But the stark night scenes of a place where the ''serious money'' goes to sin, where ''teeth and eyes and nails and banknotes flashed in the gloom like knives,'' elicits the kind of shiver that you just don't get from going to the Bolshoi.</p>
        <p>ANY Westerner in Moscow on business should find John Le Carre's ''Single &amp; Single'' sobering reading, especially after staggering back to the hotel from a jovial trade dinner. The idealistic hero, Oliver Single, is the junior partner in a London investment house that used to launder dirty money for members of the old Politburo. Now the merchant bankers are back in town to cut some deals with a new breed of crook. After meeting his clients -- a thuggish family of Georgian drug dealers who want to use their illicit profits to corner the international market in human blood -- Oliver is whisked off to one of those glitzy hotel casinos that have sprung up around Red Square (the sort of place where ''plainclothesmen guard the swing doors, pink-stained fountains play,'' and the wheels are spun by ''women croupiers in low-cut dresses.'') Then it's off to the family digs, where Oliver and his new associates sit in chairs once owned byCatherine the Great, puff on Cuban cigars, and toast their business venture from silver-chased ram's horns.</p>
        <p>Sipping tea in the lobby of the Metropol and eavesdropping on a thin-lipped Danish businessman ''in phones'' struggling to negotiate a contract with two beefy Muscovites in black leather jackets, I could appreciate Oliver's culture shock.</p>
        <p>MARILYN STASIO writes the Crime column for The Times Book Review.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">MARILYN STASIO writes the Crime column for The Times Book Review.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
