<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cash in Hand, Suffolk Still Can't Get Land</title>
    <meta content="28SUFF$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000604T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202870"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conservation of Resources</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Riverhead (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Suffolk County (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rather, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conservation of Resources</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E1DD143DF93BA15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1388" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cash in Hand, Suffolk Still Can't Get Land</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN RATHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rather, John</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Owners, frustrated after 14 months of haggling and repeated delays, announce contract to sell former Broad Cove Duck Farm, leading to Flanders Bay in Riverhead, Long Island, to private buyer; Suffolk County dropped initial purchase offer from $8.5 million to $6 million for nearly 100-acre parcel it hoped to protect from shoreline development; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SINCE the 1960's, Suffolk County had periodically pursued the purchase of the former Broad Cove Duck Farm, nearly 100 acres of waterfront woods and fields on a creek leading into Flanders Bay in Riverhead.</p>
        <p>A former owner of Broad Cove, which is next to the Indian Island county park, another former duck farm, once proposed 500 condominiums and a marina. But the site is widely considered a natural for expanding Indian Island while protecting the bay and the Peconic estuary from shoreline development.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SINCE the 1960's, Suffolk County had periodically pursued the purchase of the former Broad Cove Duck Farm, nearly 100 acres of waterfront woods and fields on a creek leading into Flanders Bay in Riverhead.</p>
        <p>A former owner of Broad Cove, which is next to the Indian Island county park, another former duck farm, once proposed 500 condominiums and a marina. But the site is widely considered a natural for expanding Indian Island while protecting the bay and the Peconic estuary from shoreline development.</p>
        <p>''It would pay you back twice for preserving it,'' said Howard R. Meinke of Nassau Point, the president of the North Fork Environmental Council. ''You get park land and you strike a big blow for protecting the estuary.''</p>
        <p>Suffolk officials heartily agreed, and last year brought funds approved by voters for open space and water protection to its talks with the current owners, three real estate investors eager to sell to the county.</p>
        <p>But after 14 months of talks between willing buyers and willing sellers, the deal collapsed this month when the owners, saying they were frustrated by haggling and the repeated delays, announced a contract to sell the land to a private buyer.</p>
        <p>The failed purchase reflects the difficulties and, some critics said, the sometimes mishandled efforts by the county to convert more than $100 million approved by voters into actual land protection.</p>
        <p>''We bent over backwards to try to make a deal with the county,'' said Anthony Labozzetta of Manhattan, one of the owners. ''We did everything we could.''</p>
        <p>A consultant to the owners, Douglas J. Riemer of Riverhead, said the county, represented by the director of real estate, Allan D. Grecco, had offered $8.5 million for the property, but then reduced that to about $6 million after saying, according to Mr. Riemer, that there had been a mistake in an initial appraisal.</p>
        <p>At a news conference this month on the Broad Cove property, environmentalists attacked the county for failing to complete the purchase.</p>
        <p>''The county botched this acquisition,'' said Richard L. Amper Jr., executive director of the Long Island Pine Barrens Society. ''If there were problems, they should have known about them before they went out and said they were acquiring it.''</p>
        <p>County Executive Robert J. Gaffney and other officials said questions about the title and an environmental cleanup were not resolved. ''They wanted top dollar but were not willing to do what was necessary to make it an effective purchase,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Grecco, who provided a very different version of the talks, said there were ''so many issues that we hadn't resolved.'' He said the environmental groups and the owners ''have gone crying to the media because they didn't get their way.''</p>
        <p>''Those in the environmental community who have criticized us in our handling of the Broad Cove matter should at least look at the facts and praise us for standing within the bounds of the drinking water protection program,'' Mr. Grecco said, referring to the county program under which the land would be bought. ''I do not believe they would want us to inherit the sellers' problems.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gaffney said, ''We don't want to spend eight-something million dollars for something they can't deliver clear title to.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Labozzetta insisted that all title questions had been resolved, and Mr. Riemer said the owners had agreed to remove buildings and perform the additional $54,000 in cleanup that an environmental consultant said was necessary.</p>
        <p>Mr. Grecco said the county had asked the Long Island chapter of the Nature Conservancy, a frequent county representative in land acquisitions, to help revive negotiations.</p>
        <p>There are three funds approved by voters that the county can draw on for the land program: $60 million for the Greenways program, of which only a small fraction has been spent, and $20 million for farm rights and $20 million for parks, neither of which have been drawn on yet. The last two programs require cost-sharing by towns.</p>
        <p>Last week, in an advance for land preservation efforts, Mr. Gaffney announced the county would purchase more than 300 acres on the South Fork, where development pressure has been intense.</p>
        <p>The purchases included 63 acres of wetlands and coastal forest near North Sea, bought for $2.4 million under a drinking water protection program financed by sales taxes, and two parcels totaling 213 acres in Montauk, bought with $4.6 million from the Greenways program.</p>
        <p>''We haven't spent a lot'' recently, Mr. Gaffney acknowledged, ''but we are preparing to spend a lot. There's a lot of things in the pipeline at this point, but it always takes a while. It goes in spurts.''</p>
        <p>He said that over the past 30 years, the county had purchased 24,000 acres and spent $283 million on farm development rights, open space and watershed protection. ''None of the 48 continental states has protected more acreage than Suffolk County,'' he added.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gaffney, who made the Greenways program the cornerstone of his environmental program, said the program was ''doing fine.''</p>
        <p>But in a booming real estate market, having money to buy land is not enough. Finding willing sellers is often the difficulty. County legislator George O. Guldi, whose district includes the South Fork, said acquisition programs were hobbled ''without owners willing to forgo windfall profits.''</p>
        <p>One parcel highlighted by Mr. Gaffney for possible acquisition under the Greenways program, the 180-acre Wading Brook in Wading River, now seems unlikely to be preserved.</p>
        <p>''We are dealing with a property owner who has preliminary approval by the Town of Brookhaven for a subdivision and he is not interested in selling at this point,'' said Michael J. Caracciolo, the county legislator representing Wading River.</p>
        <p>The Talmage family and its development partners, who own the top-rated parcel for county acquisition under the Greenways program, 370 acres of farmland and woods in Baiting Hollow, have rebuffed the county.</p>
        <p>Instead, despite pleas from environmental and conservation groups for preservation of a fragile sector called the Grandifolia Sandhills, the owners are proceeding with plans to build a golf course and have bulldozed portions of the sand hills.</p>
        <p>The park expansion program has also moved slowly for lack of sellers, and in some cases because of neighbors' opposition. Suffolk towns, which must provide financial support to back sports teams or other groups that would have a role in the expansions and use the new facilities, have been slow to respond.</p>
        <p>''It's frustrating because we have a need and we have the means, but we can't find the partners,'' said County Legislator David Bishop of West Babylon. But Mr. Bishop said two projects in Babylon Town and one in Huntington were advancing.</p>
        <p>The Broad Cove negotiations remained stalled last week despite the intervention of the Nature Conservancy. A broker for the owners, Aziz Haghani, was also trying to bring the county and the owners together.</p>
        <p>''Where did they get stopped? What went wrong?'' asked Mr. Haghani, who attended Mr. Gaffney's news conference and buttonholed Mr. Grecco for a private discussion.</p>
        <p>Some officials familiar with the negotiations said they questioned whether the owners really intended to sell to a third party or were just putting pressure on the county.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Labozzetta said the owners were in contract with another buyer, and had told the county for weeks they would sign the competing contract if the county did not ''move it along.''</p>
        <p>''If they thought that was a negotiating tactic, they misjudged,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He said the only way the talks with the county could be revived now would be ''if this new contract blows up for some reason of if the county came back and made a proposal and we went to the buyer and they would be willing to step back.''</p>
        <p>''The odds are much longer now than they were two weeks ago,'' he added, but ''life is full of surprises.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 4, 2000, Sunday  Because of an editing error, an article last Sunday about Suffolk County's difficulties in buying land for conservation referred to two funds incorrectly. A $20 million fund for farm preservation and a $20 million fund for parks are part of the $60 million Greenways program, not separate funds.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 4, 2000, Sunday</p>
        <p>Because of an editing error, an article last Sunday about Suffolk County's difficulties in buying land for conservation referred to two funds incorrectly. A $20 million fund for farm preservation and a $20 million fund for parks are part of the $60 million Greenways program, not separate funds.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
