<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Silicon Valley, Loyalty Means Paying a High Price; Cultural Strengths Help Offset Loss of Paper Wealth</title>
    <meta content="28CALI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203058"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stock Options and Purchase Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Calico Commerce (Co)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berenson, Alex</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Human Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stock Options and Purchase Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E1DC103DF93BA15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2445" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Silicon Valley, Loyalty Means Paying a High Price; Cultural Strengths Help Offset Loss of Paper Wealth</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEX BERENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Berenson, Alex</byline>
      <dateline>SAN JOSE, Calif.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>More than 100 employees of Calico Commerce were millionaires when company stock peaked in November 1999, but shares have fallen 80 percent since then, wiping out paper wealth of many employees; nevertheless, only 15 of company's 330 employees have left company so far this year, for annual turnover rate of 12 percent, less than half the typical rate at Silicon Valley companies; Calico's stability derives from strong company culture that makes employees feel like partners and fosters commitment to long-term success of company; still, Calico expects to begin to lose people eventually if stock price remains depressed; photo (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN November, more than 100 employees of Calico Commerce were millionaires, at least on paper.</p>
        <p>Today only 20 are. As Calico's stock has fallen 80 percent from its November peak, the rest have watched their fleeting wealth burn away like fog in the California sun. In April alone, Calico shares lost nearly half their value.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN November, more than 100 employees of Calico Commerce were millionaires, at least on paper.</p>
        <p>Today only 20 are. As Calico's stock has fallen 80 percent from its November peak, the rest have watched their fleeting wealth burn away like fog in the California sun. In April alone, Calico shares lost nearly half their value.</p>
        <p>In Silicon Valley, where job hopping is a way of life and even robust companies regularly lose workers to start-ups dangling chances at instant wealth, a stock meltdown like Calico's might seem a recipe for disaster, prompting top employees to flee and crippling morale among those who remain.</p>
        <p>But Calico, which makes software that helps companies sell products over the Internet, has weathered the storm so far, thanks to an intangible commodity that is supposedly even scarcer around here than out-of-work software engineers: the striking loyalty of its workers.</p>
        <p>So far this year, only 15 of Calico's 330 workers have left the company. That translates into an annual rate of 12 percent, barely half the typical turnover at Silicon Valley companies, according to Steve Radford, who has surveyed salaries and turnover at high-technology companies for more than two decades.</p>
        <p>Calico's stability is no accident, employees say. While many Silicon Valley companies depend largely on the promise of riches to attract and retain workers, Calico has gone a different route, using more than money to keep employees happy. The company tries to combine the openness and workplace perks common in Silicon Valley companies with the very uncommon understanding that employees sometimes have lives outside the office.</p>
        <p>So far, the mix seems to be working. From Alan Naumann, Calico's chief executive, to Aleida Kolodzieski, an administrative assistant, employees interviewed at Calico's headquarters in San Jose last month said they believed in their company, whatever the stock market might think.</p>
        <p>Of course they say that, a cynic might interject. But many Calico employees have put their money where their mouths are.</p>
        <p>In March, five months after the company went public, restrictions on insider stock sales expired and Calico workers were free to sell shares and turn their paper wealth into cash. Few did. In fact, Mr. Naumann actually spent more than $2 million in late April to buy 150,000 shares on the open market, building his total stake in the company to 1.65 million shares.</p>
        <p>Joe Schwartz, a 29-year-old manager who was Calico's 13th employee and has been with the company since 1995, said he shared that confidence. With more than 5,000 options, Mr. Schwartz lost more than $300,000 in paper wealth as Calico's stock price shriveled. Yet he remains a believer. ''I would encourage my parents to buy, my best friends to buy,'' he said.</p>
        <p>A strong company culture only goes so far, and even Mr. Naumann admits that his company will eventually start losing people if the stock price remains depressed. And it is hard to forecast what the immediate future holds for the company. Its products compete in a hotly contested market niche against offerings from specialists like FirePond and giants like Oracle. Though Calico's sales have grown steadily at 70 percent annually or better, reaching $35.6 million in the year ended March 31, its losses have widened as well, to $27.8 million -- a new-economy story that investors used to shrug off but now have little patience for.</p>
        <p>Still, Calico's efforts to make its employees feel like partners seem for the moment to have cushioned the blow of the stock slump.</p>
        <p>''The difference between good and bad management teams in the valley is their ability to manage through the natural ebb and flow of the business,'' said Roger McNamee, a venture capitalist whose investment funds own more than 5 percent of Calico. ''This is a management team that understands the business that they're in. They made a conscious choice to run the business for the long term.''</p>
        <p>That choice makes Calico unusual -- and could help the company prosper over time, management consultants said.</p>
        <p>The notion that employees and companies have a social contract with each other that goes beyond a paycheck has largely vanished in United States business. In its place is a free-agent culture where workers are expected to look out for themselves and switching jobs regularly is seen as normal.</p>
        <p>BUT a few big companies, like Cisco Systems, Southwest Airlines and Men's Wearhouse, have found success by going out of their way to make employees feel valued, according to Charles O'Reilly, a Harvard professor who is writing a book about the cultures of successful companies.</p>
        <p>''The average point of view is that loyalty is for chumps, that the longer you stay on the job, the stupider you are,'' said Fred Reichheld, a fellow at Bain Consulting who is writing a book about loyalty. ''Most business leaders cannot tell you why their people should be loyal. They get it confused with obedience, or just staying there, or fear.''</p>
        <p>Instead, companies often try to combat turnover with big salaries and option grants. But Mr. Reichheld said that approach is self-defeating, because it works only as long as times are good and an organization can afford to pay a fairly small roster of stars above-market salaries.</p>
        <p>Being honest with employees and giving them a chance to grow at their jobs builds loyalty in a way that money cannot, he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Naumann appears to have taken that lesson to heart. He shares lots of information with employees, holding monthly company-wide meetings to discuss where Calico stands relative to its competitors and internal goals. In addition, he hosts a monthly group breakfast for employees whose birthdays have fallen that month and solicits feedback from the group. That level of disclosure and communication is vital to building loyalty, Mr. O'Reilly said.</p>
        <p>''The all-too-typical M.B.A. response is that people can't be trusted, and they're not very smart, so why would you give them this information?'' he said. But companies that keep workers well informed find that employees come to feel they have a stake in the company, even if they own only a little stock. ''Then people feel like owners, and they stick around even if the stock price dips,'' Mr. O'Reilly said.</p>
        <p>OF course, Calico is not alone in fostering an atmosphere of openness. Young companies often share more information with their employees than bigger, older businesses; the gulf between management and the rank and file tends to widen over time. And some of Calico's other perks, like allowing employees to telecommute twice a week, are typical at young Silicon Valley companies where employees put in long hours.</p>
        <p>But Calico does differ from its young cousins in some crucial ways. With weak or nonexistent human resources departments and a culture that puts work first, many young companies stumble when dealing with employees having personal crises. Not at Calico, said Rob Devine, a 32-year-old consultant who joined the company in June, six months before his wife died of ovarian cancer.</p>
        <p>''Leadership two and three levels above was completely fair'' in its treatment of him, Mr. Devine said. As his wife's health worsened, he said, the company arranged his work to minimize travel and offered him extra time off, an offer he declined because, he said, ''it's important when you're in a situation like that to have something where you feel you're contributing.''</p>
        <p>Shelly Begun, Calico's vice president for human resources, said the company allowed an employee whose wife gave birth prematurely more than two months' leave to help care for the baby. ''It is a huge deal for people that, when they have these types of situations, Calico will help to deal with them,'' Ms. Begun said.</p>
        <p>Nancy McDermand, a manager whose grant of more than 10,000 options has just begun to vest, said she had recently turned down a job at a start-up that offered her ''lots of shares'' and more money, preferring to remain at Calico for its collegial atmosphere. ''If it weren't like that, I could leave tomorrow,'' she said.</p>
        <p>To maintain that spirit, Calico has made a concerted effort to seek out employees considered likely to fit into its culture, placing a premium on recruiting graduates directly from college or business school.</p>
        <p>Hewlett-Packard and other successful technology companies ''do superaggressive college hiring, because it's the only way to get people who fit in,'' said Mr. Naumann, an Iowa native who worked for Hewlett-Packard for five years after graduating from college. ''We're trying to do the same thing.''</p>
        <p>Make no mistake, though, this is still Silicon Valley, the overnight-millionaire factory. Most Calico employees acknowledge forthrightly that tantalizing stock windfalls like those that were briefly within their grasp are a large part of what brought to Calico to begin with.</p>
        <p>''The potential money that could be made getting into a company pre-I.P.O. really was a big consideration,'' said John Driver, Calico's director of field marketing.</p>
        <p>So too, for many people in Silicon Valley, are bragging rights, and Calico's stock no longer yields employees much of those. ''There is a gold rush mentality'' in the new economy, said Barry Obrand, managing director of Russell Reynolds Associates, the executive recruiting firm. ''For people who haven't made it in some way, shape or form, there's a sense that you haven't done as well for yourself or your family.''</p>
        <p>YURI SMIROV, an engineer who joined Calico last year after two years at a privately held start-up, looks at Calico's prospects through that lens. Working for a company that does not succeed is extremely costly in Silicon Valley, he said, because ''time is becoming the most expensive resource.''</p>
        <p>''Time is something you lose and it doesn't come back,'' Mr. Smirov said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Smirov, who emigrated to the United States from Russia in 1992 and earned a doctorate in computer science at Carnegie Mellon University in Pittsburgh, said moving from Russia to Pennsylvania was a smaller adjustment for him than moving from Pennsylvania to Silicon Valley. The people he met in Pittsburgh were white and middle-class, with ''the same income, with the same interests,'' he said. ''Here, people are stratified much more.''</p>
        <p>As for the stock, he said, ''the hardest part is mismatching your expectations.'' Mr. Smirov, who will receive more than 25,000 options between now and 2003, used to think he would be able to buy a house large enough for his two children to have separate bedrooms. That prospect is now remote, but Mr. Smirov remains hopeful.</p>
        <p>Housing is on the mind of Ms. Kolodzieski, the administrator with only ''a couple of thousand shares,'' as well. She and her husband hope one day to move out of the condominium apartment they rent. ''We want to have a family, and part of that equals buying a home,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Naumann knows his staff's patience will not last forever. ''Our total compensation packages have to be competitive, or we won't retain people,'' he said. But for now, the stock woes have, if anything, pulled the company closer together, he said. ''The market's got it wrong, and we're just going to have to prove them wrong.''</p>
        <p>For a New Insider, It Was a Risk Worth Taking</p>
        <p>OF Calico Commerce's 330 employees, John Driver might have the best reason to be upset with the company's plunging stock price.</p>
        <p>Mr. Driver joined the San Jose-based software company as director of field marketing two weeks before it became a public company last October, scrapping a thriving business as an independent consultant. His take-home pay at Calico came to only half what he had been making in fees; to compensate, Calico promised him more than 25,000 stock options, a potentially huge payoff. (Typically for Silicon Valley, Mr. Driver will receive his options over four years -- one-quarter of the grant on his first anniversary with the company and the rest in equal monthly installments thereafter.)</p>
        <p>When Calico shares soared to $75 in November, Mr. Driver's decision to join the company looked brilliantly lucrative. Even if the stock failed to rise any farther before 2003, he stood to reap more than $1.5 million from his options.</p>
        <p>Not so now that Calico's stock has plunged by 80 percent, right back to the initial offering price of $14 a share. At that price Mr. Driver's options are worthless.</p>
        <p>So does Mr. Driver, who has an 18-month-old daughter and another child on the way, regret his career decision now?</p>
        <p>No, he said, for lots of reasons. First off, his stock wealth does not yet really exist, even on paper; it will only accumulate over time as his options vest. ''I have a very practical view of the stock,'' he said. ''Even if the stock was trading at 100 today, I don't vest until September.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Driver, who said he is a fan of Warren E. Buffett, invests for the long haul and has ''actually never sold a stock,'' is optimistic that by the time the options are actually his to exercise, Calico shares will have rebounded.</p>
        <p>''I think Calico at the moment is actually undervalued,'' he said. ''We have a good strategy, a good management team. There's a market there, and Calico is going to get some of it.''</p>
        <p>Even if the stock does not recover, Mr. Driver said, he is glad he joined the company. He enjoys working there, and even on half his former pay he and his wife will be able to support their family, he said. And the chance to be a part of the action, instead of on the outside looking in, was too exciting to pass up.</p>
        <p>''It was a gamble,'' he said. ''It was a risk, and if things don't work out, you've really got to be okay with the outcome. I have a great life the way it is -- I have a great house, I have a little kid, another on the way. If I wind up making millions of dollars, it's a bonus. If it doesn't happen, I have a really good life.''</p>
        <p>ALEX BERENSON</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
