<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Indonesia's Presidential Flash in the Pan</title>
    <meta content="28JAKA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203177"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Indonesia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mydans, Seth</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Habibie, B J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Suharto</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Indonesia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Indonesia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E1D71E3DF93BA15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1253" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Indonesia's Presidential Flash in the Pan</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SETH MYDANS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mydans, Seth</byline>
      <dateline>JAKARTA, Indonesia, May 27</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>B J Habibie, who took over power in Indonesia after Pres Suharto resigned in 1998, has quickly become an irrelevance in country's political scene; during his 17 months as head of state, he pursued steady course toward democracy, dismantling dictatorship that Suharto put in place during 32 years in power; Habibie freed press, labor unions and political parties, and began slow process of pulling military out of politics; then, he became first Indonesian president ever to be voted out of office--event he calls one of his proudest achievements; Habibie was widely seen as eccentric and lightweight when Suharto appointed him vice president; Suharto thought this clearly unqualified man would quiet critics calling for him to step down; photo; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>People were burning cars in the streets again, but there was a presidential hush in the jasmine-scented living room of B. J. Habibie, the sprightly enigma who, for a bewildering moment not long ago, found himself the most powerful person in the land.</p>
        <p>''You should understand my background,'' said Mr. Habibie, a tiny, animated man. ''I am not a politician; I am not even interested in politics. And suddenly I had to take over.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>People were burning cars in the streets again, but there was a presidential hush in the jasmine-scented living room of B. J. Habibie, the sprightly enigma who, for a bewildering moment not long ago, found himself the most powerful person in the land.</p>
        <p>''You should understand my background,'' said Mr. Habibie, a tiny, animated man. ''I am not a politician; I am not even interested in politics. And suddenly I had to take over.''</p>
        <p>That was in May 1998, when former President Suharto suddenly resigned and, without a single word to him, left Indonesia in the hands of his vice president, Mr. Habibie, an aircraft engineer who was one of the most spectacularly unprepared people ever to lead a nation.</p>
        <p>Over the next 17 months, Mr. Habibie rode the bucking bronco of power, challenged from all sides as Indonesia began to redefine itself. But he pursued a remarkably steady course toward democracy, dismantling the dictatorship that his predecessor and close friend had painstakingly put in place during 32 years in power.</p>
        <p>Mr. Habibie freed the press, the labor unions and the political parties, and began the slow process of pulling the military out of politics.</p>
        <p>Then, in what he calls one of his proudest achievements, he became the first Indonesian president ever to be voted out of office -- replaced last October by an equally eccentric leader, the voluble, half-blind Muslim cleric Abdurrahman Wahid.</p>
        <p>Now Mr. Habibie, 64, has less power than he has had since becoming Mr. Suharto's minister for science and technology more than 20 years ago -- time, he said, to stare at his face in the mirror and decide, yes, let's try a mustache. (''Do you like it? Do you?'')</p>
        <p>This week he opened the Habibie Center, a political research institute that he is mostly financing himself. But he has quickly become an irrelevance in Indonesia's political scene.</p>
        <p>Unlike Mr. Suharto, who has been the target of protests this week by rioters demanding that he be put on trial for wide-scale corruption, Mr. Habibie arouses few emotions. He serves mostly as a political science teaser: did he lead the nation into its emerging democracy or was he, like the rest of the men in power, simply buffeted by the prevailing typhoon of change?</p>
        <p>While many analysts say he had little choice but to allow the new freedoms that were being demanded on the streets, Mr. Habibie has insisted from the start that he was a heartfelt liberal who learned his democratic lessons during decades of residence in Germany.</p>
        <p>''I am a man who is never reactive,'' Mr. Habibie insisted. ''I'm proactive. I always work based on my beliefs and my convictions.''</p>
        <p>This may be true, despite his closeness for decades to his autocratic mentor. Whether he led or followed, he was part of a nationwide passion for change that exploded to the surface the moment Mr. Suharto's grip was loosened.</p>
        <p>''It's going to take some time to assess Habibie,'' said Daniel S. Lev, a professor at the University of Washington at Seattle. ''But the best one can say and the worst one can say is that he did not make things as bad as they could have been.''</p>
        <p>He did not block reforms, and he did not use the military to try to stay in power, Mr. Lev said. ''The point is, he didn't stand as a major obstruction, and those are all sort of backhanded compliments, but he deserves them, I think.''</p>
        <p>Defense Minister Juwono Sudarsono, who was education minister under Mr. Habibie, was similarly equivocal. ''People say he was forced into those things, but you must give him credit for taking them on at an early stage,'' he said. ''I think he was basically being used by so many people who focused on their own personal gain. He was an O.K. guy, very charming, very witty, very bubbly.''</p>
        <p>In the interview, Mr. Habibie described himself as a man who threw a stone into a pond and set off waves of turbulence. The process he set in motion, he said, was a shift from ''unipolar'' to ''multipolar'' power -- a difficult transition for a vastly diverse nation of many islands and more than 200 million people that had learned to submit to a single central leader.</p>
        <p>''I am convinced that the lows which exist today in our economy and our political life are because of this transition,'' he said. ''We should help the president today to shorten the time of this transition that is decreasing our efficiency and productivity. Because the president is O.K., I think; he is O.K.''</p>
        <p>In his first week as president, Mr. Habibie said, he confounded his aides by paying a visit to Parliament in a gesture of respect to the legislative branch. ''Suddenly the situation happened where I have de-powered myself as president,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He then helped set the ground rules for Indonesia's first democratic election, and submitted gracefully to the result last fall, calling himself proudly, ''the first victim of democracy.''</p>
        <p>But there has been one sad element in Mr. Habibie's presidency, the loss of a lifelong friendship with Mr. Suharto, a surrogate father who is 15 years his senior.</p>
        <p>Paradoxically, Mr. Habibie's moment of destiny began as a calculated insult. Mr. Suharto, the man he called his best friend, had appointed him vice president just two months earlier as a sort of slap at a growing chorus of critics.</p>
        <p>Mr. Habibie was widely seen as an eccentric and a lightweight, and when Mr. Suharto came under pressure to step down, one of the last cards he tried to play was to point to the clearly unqualified man who would take his place.</p>
        <p>Then, when he capitulated, he refused even to speak to Mr. Habibie, who said he was still stunned and bewildered as he took the oath of office two years ago, on May 21, 1998.</p>
        <p>Remarkably, he said, Mr. Suharto still refuses to see him.</p>
        <p>The only time they have spoken, he said, was on Mr. Suharto's birthday later that year, when he was allowed to place a telephone call to his former friend.</p>
        <p>''I called him and I told him, 'Happy birthday, I want to see you,' '' Mr. Habibie said. ''And he told me, 'No, you are not going to see me. It is not good for the country or for you or for me. You have to stop all of this. You cannot see me.'</p>
        <p>'' 'But you are just like my own father and my friend. Why should I not see you? I have the right to see you and to talk.'</p>
        <p>'' 'No. But you should try and contact me through spiritual -- through telepathy.' He told me like this, and then I forgave him,'' Mr. Habibie said.</p>
        <p>Since then, Mr. Suharto has suffered a third stroke, this one apparently so debilitating that he has trouble understanding and communicating.</p>
        <p>And so, as Mr. Habibie looks back at his unexpected moment in history, it appears that he will never learn why Mr. Suharto, his old friend, turned over to him the leadership of the nation without saying a word.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
