<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>SportsWorld Sometimes Needs a Shrink</title>
    <meta content="Y28LIP$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203130"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PERSPECTIVE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Depression (Mental)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Indiana University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lipsyte, Robert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Knight, Bobby</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Depression</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Depression (Mental)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E4D6113DF93BA15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="895" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>SportsWorld Sometimes Needs a Shrink</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT LIPSYTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lipsyte, Robert</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Robert Lipsyte discusses Indiana University Coach Bob Knight framing his abusiveness toward players as a psychological problem that needs to be addressed; other athletes suffering from depression who have been helped by therapy and medication are discussed but Lipsyte concludes Coach Knight would resist this kind of help; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Because our Bob Knight problem was framed as either a moral question -- Is it wrong to throw chairs, talk dirty and choke your players? -- or as a pragmatic question -- Is it imprudent for a university president to jeopardize major donations by dumping an iconic coach? -- we will probably have to deal with the blustery bully for a while. Until he slugs someone who really matters, such as a rich Indiana booster, or has three losing seasons in a row, Knight will continue to have an impact on young lives in formation and offer an affirming role model to abusive coaches and corporate managers everywhere.</p>
        <p>Had our Bob Knight problem been properly framed as a psychological question -- does this man have a personality disorder and is it having an adverse emotional impact on others? -- we might be a lot closer to getting rid of him, or at least getting him into therapy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Because our Bob Knight problem was framed as either a moral question -- Is it wrong to throw chairs, talk dirty and choke your players? -- or as a pragmatic question -- Is it imprudent for a university president to jeopardize major donations by dumping an iconic coach? -- we will probably have to deal with the blustery bully for a while. Until he slugs someone who really matters, such as a rich Indiana booster, or has three losing seasons in a row, Knight will continue to have an impact on young lives in formation and offer an affirming role model to abusive coaches and corporate managers everywhere.</p>
        <p>Had our Bob Knight problem been properly framed as a psychological question -- does this man have a personality disorder and is it having an adverse emotional impact on others? -- we might be a lot closer to getting rid of him, or at least getting him into therapy.</p>
        <p>But that would entail having in place an objective, competent mental health presence in SportsWorld. At the moment, what we have is a gaggle of performance enhancers, personnel evaluators and the head-shrinking equivalent of the stereotypical orthopedic surgeon who thinks he is a coach with an M.D. (''Snap out of that depression, Jimbo; this is the seventh game.'') No brain, no gain.</p>
        <p>This current grist for thelipsite@aol.com comes from a week at the American Psychiatric Association's annual meeting, in Chicago, earlier this month. The key symposium for me, numbingly entitled, ''Psychopharmacological Approaches to the Athletic and Exercise Population,'' was provocative and groundbreaking, and poorly attended. Just as psychiatry has yet to crack SportsWorld's taboos against athletes appearing emotionally needy, so jock culture has yet to become an area of serious study in ShrinkWorld.</p>
        <p>But Dr. Ronald L. Kamm of New Jersey, who led the symposium, thinks that a bridge between the two worlds can be built by the likes of Julie Krone, the recently retired Hall of Fame jockey; Cincinnati Reds pitcher Pete Harnisch; and Jack Farrell, a champion skeet shooter, talking unselfconsciously about their therapy and psychiatric drugs. Krone and Harnisch are paid by the drug companies to talk about their experiences.</p>
        <p>Harnisch was in spring training with the Mets in 1997 when he became depressed. Interviewed by Kamm in a 16-minute video, Harnisch said that Mets management responded poorly to his illness, but that after seven months of talk therapy and antidepressants (he was helped by Paxil) he got his game back. Since then, he said, a number of players have approached him for advice and to share stories.</p>
        <p>Farrell, 67, a retired engineer, went into depression after he quit smoking cigarettes. Anger management was one of his main problems, he said; Paxil made him a better shooter because ''I'm calmer and I don't flinch.''</p>
        <p>Krone's story of her reluctance to ask for help even after she felt suicidal and her eventual return to self after talk therapy and Zoloft evoked dozens of phone calls and e-mail messages to thelipsite@aol.com. Most were from other athletes, elite and recreational, sharing their stories. They were thrilled that she called her condition a ''mental illness,'' a step toward destigmatizing it. There were quibbles. A noted psychopharmacologist, Dr. Arthur Rifkin of Hillside Hospital in Queens, thought that two years of talk therapy before taking drugs was too long (Krone's psychiatrists had vainly urged her to start sooner). Bob Carolla of the National Alliance for the Mentally Ill pointed out that the football players Alonzo Spellman and Earl Campbell have also spoken out publicly about their illnesses.</p>
        <p>The Chicago symposium was sponsored by the International Society for Sport Psychiatry, a nine-year-old group of about 80 members searching for its place in an arena dominated by the aggressive marketing of psychologists who promise to raise your batting average and lower your golf score. In papers that were presented, Dr. Antonia L. Baum of George Washington University, Dr. Ira D. Glick of Stanford and Dr. Robert W. Burton of Northwestern called for research into the effect of psychiatric drugs on ''finely tuned'' elite athletes, and a re-examination of the banning of substances that might treat mood or anxiety disorders. Burton is also co-editor, with Dr. Daniel Begel, of the newly published book ''Sport Psychiatry'' (Norton).</p>
        <p>A sexier symposium, on Coach Knight or even Latrell Sprewell, might have drawn better against such competing offerings at the same time that night as the movies ''Life is Beautiful'' and ''Good Will Hunting,'' followed by psychiatric evaluations. And a Knight-Spree entry might have been more on the mark; the emotional impact of jock culture is incalculable.</p>
        <p>Even if there was an independent body of SportsWorld therapists available to help the needy, one can assume that neither Knight nor Indiana would sit for a session. Psychiatrists tend to be too lofty to give distant diagnoses, probably a good thing, but some general speculation about Knight's lack of control (or calculated use of abuse?) might be instructive. There is good video available.</p>
        <p>No video exists of Sprewell choking P. J. Carlesimo, but that would have been a perfect episode for analysis, assuming the National Basketball Association could stand the psychiatric spotlight on what might have been the case of an emotionally troubled player pushed too far by a coach with unresolved issues of his own.</p>
        <p>PERSPECTIVE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
