<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bard Graduates Are Urged to Make Impact</title>
    <meta content="28COMM$10" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000530T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203183"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="COMMENCEMENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bard College</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E3D61E3DF93BA15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="423" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bard Graduates Are Urged to Make Impact</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bard College holds commencement (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ANNANDALE-ON-HUDSON, N.Y. May 27 -- This afternoon, 274 students, including a Bosnian refugee on her way to becoming an expert in international law, became the largest graduating class in Bard College's 140-year history.</p>
        <p>The president of the college, Leon Botstein, celebrating his 25th year as head of the small liberal arts school, also conferred master's degrees on  57 other students.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ANNANDALE-ON-HUDSON, N.Y. May 27 -- This afternoon, 274 students, including a Bosnian refugee on her way to becoming an expert in international law, became the largest graduating class in Bard College's 140-year history.</p>
        <p>The president of the college, Leon Botstein, celebrating his 25th year as head of the small liberal arts school, also conferred master's degrees on  57 other students.</p>
        <p>The graduates, sitting on the college's main lawn, were addressed by Arnold J. Levine, a biochemist who in 1979 discovered a single gene associated with about 60 percent of human cancers. Dr. Levine's discovery of gene p53 is aiding in the development of cancer therapies.</p>
        <p>Dr. Levine, a geneticist who is also the president of Rockefeller University in New York, discussed a new collaboration between Rockefeller and Bard. Next fall, Bard students will be able to take classes at Rockefeller while while Bard faculty members will teach high school students in Rockefeller's summer program.</p>
        <p>Dr. Levine spoke of scientific advances in the last 100 years and  wished the graduates ''the chance to do something that will make an impact upon the lives of your children and your grandchildren.''</p>
        <p>At least one young woman was already well on her way. Irma Dedich, 25, has already seen civil war in her native Bosnia, been held hostage by rebel Muslims and -- upon her release -- worked as an interpreter for United Nations peacekeepers. In 1996 she fled to Croatia and applied for a scholarship to come to America, where a synagogue in Croton-on-Hudson, N.Y., chose to sponsor her. Rabbi Helen Ferris took her in and, acting as her mentor, helped Ms. Dedich apply for a scholarship to Bard.</p>
        <p>At Bard, Ms. Dedich excelled, earning a 3.97 grade point average. In her second year, she was invited to return to Europe to give a paper at the European Third International Relations Conference in Austria. Her paper, ''Can the Perpetrators of Genocide Really Suffer From Denial Syndrome?'' will be published in  June.</p>
        <p>Before receiving her degree, Ms. Dedich said, ''It was just incredible to discuss things in a class, not just study what they give you to study, like I did before under communism.''</p>
        <p>COMMENCEMENT  Correction:  May 30, 2000, Tuesday  An article on Sunday about commencement at Bard misstated the college's age in some copies. It is 140 years old, not 104. The article also misstated the age of a graduate, Irma Dedich, a former Bosnian refugee who worked as an interpreter for United Nations peacekeepers before attending Bard on a scholarship. She is 25, not 22.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 30, 2000, Tuesday</p>
        <p>An article on Sunday about commencement at Bard misstated the college's age in some copies. It is 140 years old, not 104. The article also misstated the age of a graduate, Irma Dedich, a former Bosnian refugee who worked as an interpreter for United Nations peacekeepers before attending Bard on a scholarship. She is 25, not 22.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
