<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Jeter's Back. Just a Nice Day at the Park.</title>
    <meta content="28YANK$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203191"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Boston Red Sox</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olney, Buster</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Boston Red Sox</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04EFD61E3DF93BA15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="970" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Jeter's Back. Just a Nice Day at the Park.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olney, Buster</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Yankees defeat Boston Red Sox 8-3; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Yankees desperately missed Derek Jeter, his run production, his confidence that seems to stick like lint on his teammates. But Jeter rejects the notion that the team is built around him, that he is the difference between victories and losses. The Yankees are the type of team, he said, that must have donations from all parts of its roster to succeed.</p>
        <p>And in Jeter's first game since being activated off the disabled list, the Yankees served a pot-luck victory for 55,671 at Yankee Stadium yesterday, defeating the Boston Red Sox, 8-3. Jason Grimsley, who started on short notice when back soreness kept Orlando Hernandez from pitching, chipped in five solid innings, and Mike Stanton followed and shut out the Red Sox for three innings. The Yankees' offense came to life, capitalizing on an act of vengeance by the Boston starter Brian Rose, as four players slugged home runs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Yankees desperately missed Derek Jeter, his run production, his confidence that seems to stick like lint on his teammates. But Jeter rejects the notion that the team is built around him, that he is the difference between victories and losses. The Yankees are the type of team, he said, that must have donations from all parts of its roster to succeed.</p>
        <p>And in Jeter's first game since being activated off the disabled list, the Yankees served a pot-luck victory for 55,671 at Yankee Stadium yesterday, defeating the Boston Red Sox, 8-3. Jason Grimsley, who started on short notice when back soreness kept Orlando Hernandez from pitching, chipped in five solid innings, and Mike Stanton followed and shut out the Red Sox for three innings. The Yankees' offense came to life, capitalizing on an act of vengeance by the Boston starter Brian Rose, as four players slugged home runs.</p>
        <p>The Yankees and Red Sox are tied for first in the American League East, with identical records of 27 victories and 18 losses. Each team has won once in this three-game series, and tonight the Yankees' Roger Clemens will pitch against Pedro Martinez. Toronto beat Martinez last Tuesday; the Red Sox right-hander has not lost back-to-back starts since September 1998, when he lost three straight games, including two losses to the Yankees.</p>
        <p>There was a moment early in the second inning when Ricky Ledee stood in left field and wondered if anything more could possibly go wrong for the Yankees. They gave away runs in Friday's loss. They learned only minutes before yesterday's game that Hernandez could not pitch. They had to play without the lead-off hitter Chuck Knoblauch for the second day in a row. They have had their regular lineup of players intact for only six of 44 games.</p>
        <p>Then Paul O'Neill rolled his ankle chasing a fly ball and fell to the ground. Ledee saw O'Neill limping badly and couldn't believe it: Jeter finally comes back and then O'Neill goes down. But O'Neill walked off the injury; he had done the same thing dozens of times playing basketball, he said. He would contribute to the potluck before the day was over.</p>
        <p>The Yankees got a heaping portion of Grimsley. The middle of Hernandez's back ached after he took batting practice Friday, and about half an hour before yesterday's game, Grimsley -- a middle reliever -- was alerted that he might have to start. Grimsley went to the bullpen with Hernandez, watched the right-hander struggle with his warm-ups and knew there was no way El Duque could pitch. ''I'm sorry,'' Hernandez said in English to Grimsley. ''Good luck.''</p>
        <p>Grimsley retired the first six batters, surrendered three runs and hit Brian Daubach with a pitch in the third, then shut out Boston in the fourth and fifth innings. ''He was the guy who really gave us a lift today,'' Manager Joe Torre said of Grimsley.</p>
        <p>But more than Grimsley was needed. The Yankees trailed, 3-0, in the bottom of the third and Rose retired the first two batters. Ledee, who was next, changed his bat before he went to the plate -- and never thought he would get to use it. He figured Rose would throw a pitch at him intentionally, in retaliation for when Grimsley plunked Daubach; the Red Sox, after all, have a reputation for strictly adhering to the beanball code.</p>
        <p>Sure enough, Rose drilled Ledee in the thigh, perhaps ignoring a subparagraph in the unwritten beanball code: Do not inflame a slumping team. Jeter singled, Ledee stopping at second, and O'Neill ripped a run-scoring single through the middle. The Yankees were alive again.</p>
        <p>Shane Spencer contributed in the fourth inning, his eighth home run of the season cutting the Boston lead to 3-2. Ledee, who made a spectacular running and lunging catch in the fourth, tied the score in the fifth with a home run, his third of the year.</p>
        <p>John Wasdin came on to pitch the bottom of the sixth for Boston, and Jorge Posada ripped his second pitch deep into the right-field stands, his 10th homer of the season; Posada hit a total of 12 last year.</p>
        <p>Two batters later, Clay Bellinger singled and stole second. Ledee walked. Jeter singled and Bellinger scored, giving the Yankees a 5-3 lead. The left-hander Tim Young was summoned to pitch to O'Neill, who was handled well last year by Boston's left-handed relievers.</p>
        <p>Not this time. O'Neill swung, the sound of the contact was loud and O'Neill lowered his head and jogged toward first, giving a passing glance to his three-run homer. The Yankees had an 8-3 lead and were in control of this game, and when O'Neill jogged to play his position in the top of the seventh, fans in the bleachers stood and cheered him.</p>
        <p>Stanton and Mariano Rivera followed Grimsley, six Yankees scored runs, seven had hits, share and share alike.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>The Yankees will know more today about the extent of ORLANDO HERNANDEZ's back injury, after seeing how he responds to treatment for the sore muscles. Hernandez said he thought he would be able to make his next scheduled start, in Atlanta on June 3. . . . Second baseman CHUCK KNOBLAUCH was scratched from the lineup for the second consecutive game because of a bruise on his left wrist, an injury that occurred as he tagged out a runner on May 21. But Knoblauch said his wrist had improved since Friday and he expected to play tonight. . . . To make room for DEREK JETER on their roster, the Yankees optioned shortstop ALFONSO SORIANO to Class AAA Columbus.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
