<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Time for Dialogue at CUNY</title>
    <meta content="28SUN3$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203104"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">City University of New York</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E0D8113DF93BA15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="475" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Time for Dialogue at CUNY</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial calls on administration and faculty in 20-campus City University of New York to work through their disagreements over proposed core curriculum and other changes; says last thing CUNY needs is more of intramural warfare that ravaged system for much of last decade</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The 20-campus City University of New York was in chaos when the board of trustees hired Matthew Goldstein as the new chancellor last summer. Political infighting among the trustees had paralyzed the administration, driven out some of the institution's most talented minds and further demoralized a faculty that was already embittered by hiring freezes and disrespect from a few trustees who put politics ahead of academics.</p>
        <p>The tensions between the faculty and the administration seemed to subside when Mr. Goldstein was installed as chancellor. But the faculty and the administration were at loggerheads again last week over proposed curriculum changes that the trustees voted for, including a plan to consider a systemwide core curriculum, in the style of elite institutions like Columbia and the University of Chicago.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The 20-campus City University of New York was in chaos when the board of trustees hired Matthew Goldstein as the new chancellor last summer. Political infighting among the trustees had paralyzed the administration, driven out some of the institution's most talented minds and further demoralized a faculty that was already embittered by hiring freezes and disrespect from a few trustees who put politics ahead of academics.</p>
        <p>The tensions between the faculty and the administration seemed to subside when Mr. Goldstein was installed as chancellor. But the faculty and the administration were at loggerheads again last week over proposed curriculum changes that the trustees voted for, including a plan to consider a systemwide core curriculum, in the style of elite institutions like Columbia and the University of Chicago.</p>
        <p>The board chairman, Herman Badillo, says the faculty will be consulted on the details of the new curriculum, which he says is aimed at raising standards across the system. But the faculty union president, Barbara Bowen, charged the trustees with conspiring to usurp faculty powers, forcing through a curriculum dictated by conservative groups like Change New York and the National Association of Scholars, two organizations that have long sought, in the faculty's judgment, to commandeer the university. Both sides will need to proceed rationally -- and in good faith -- to avoid yet another destructive round of intramural warfare.</p>
        <p>The master plan put forward by the trustees  has many commendable aspects. For starters, the plan is aimed at eliminating program duplications, and augmenting each campus's strength in order to produce flagship campuses with higher admissions standards, in the style of the California system. The plan also calls for strengthening teacher education and for more systematic relations between CUNY and the public schools that provide most of the system's students.</p>
        <p>The trustees realized that none of this can  be accomplished unless CUNY rebuilds its faculty, which is far too dependent on poorly paid part-timers, who dash from one part-time job to another, leaving little time for student counseling or for other activities that sustain a vibrant university. The trustees want at least 70 percent of the four-year college faculty to be full-time teachers.</p>
        <p>The faculty applauds the rebuilding effort but fears that conservatives outside the university will have undue influence over the shape of the proposed core curriculum, making for a narrower selection of course offerings at CUNY. Mr. Goldstein and the trustees dispute this emphatically, saying that the entire program is up for discussion. It is incumbent upon both sides to work this through. The last thing CUNY needs is more of the intramural warfare that ravaged the system for much of the last decade.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
