<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="28FSUM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203181"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E6D61E3DF93BA15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="742" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>3-12</p>
        <p>Building Missile Defense May Start Arms Race  American intelligence officials are warning that building a limited national missile defense could set off a cold-war-style arms race between China, India and Pakistan, administration officials say, as President Clinton nears a decision on whether to build such a system.</p>
        <p>1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>3-12</p>
        <p>Building Missile Defense May Start Arms Race  American intelligence officials are warning that building a limited national missile defense could set off a cold-war-style arms race between China, India and Pakistan, administration officials say, as President Clinton nears a decision on whether to build such a system.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Ulster Set for Local Rule  Northern Ireland's largest Protestant party voted by a narrow margin to return to a power-sharing administration with their Catholic rivals in Sinn Fein, the political representatives of the Irish Republican Army, meaning that governing of the province will shift to Belfast in days.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Iran's New Parliament Opens  Iran's new reformer-dominated parliament opened in Tehran, the first since the Islamic revolution to include a majority of members who appear eager and ready to challenge the conservative clergy's control.</p>
        <p>8</p>
        <p>Presidential Debate in Mexico  In a televised debate with two rivals, Vicente Fox Quesada, the leading opposition presidential candidate in Mexico, gave a vigorous performance that helped him recover from embarrassing mistakes last week.</p>
        <p>12</p>
        <p>Low Turnout at Belgrade Rally  About 10,000 people attended an anti-government rally, a relatively low turnout reflecting popular disappointment with the leaders of the political opposition.</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>14-26</p>
        <p>Gore Faults Bush Plan On Arms Cuts and Defense  Vice President Al Gore, speaking at the United States Military Academy, criticized Gov. George W. Bush's support for a national missile defense system along with a possible one-sided reduction in American nuclear warheads.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Where Beauty Reigns Supreme  South Beach, the southernmost tip of the city of Miami Beach, is utterly absorbed by beauty, peopled with fashion models and dreamers and others who just like moving about a place where bartenders pose like Grecian statues and cafe hostesses are achingly lovely.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Bennington College in Turmoil  Bennington College is once again in turmoil with dissident and dismissed faculty members casting Dr. Elizabeth Coleman, the president, as a dictatorial figure who crushes any criticism. Two trustees have resigned.</p>
        <p>14</p>
        <p>Labor Split by China Trade Vote  The labor movement is badly divided on political strategy after last week's vote in favor of the China trade bill, which labor opposed. Some union leaders and Democratic consultants say this split could set back the party's electoral chances.</p>
        <p>22</p>
        <p>Drivers Pay Record Gas Prices  Gasoline prices have soared to the highest levels of the year in many parts of the nation, after falling a good bit in the wake of a decision by the petroleum-exporting countries in March to increase oil production.</p>
        <p>24</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>27-32</p>
        <p>Giuliani Departure Changes Assumptions in Senate Race  The New York Senate race has been transformed from a battle over a few undecided voters into a broad and complex contest. Voting blocs and geographical preferences that had seemed fixed are suddenly up for grabs after Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani's departure, strategists say.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>New Rent Rules Contested  There is a new battlefront between tenants and landlords: 200 pages of legalese drafted by New York State officials to rewrite the rent regulations that cover 2.4 million residents, most of them in New York City.</p>
        <p>30</p>
        <p>Fear of Crime Remains Low  Despite a number of recent ghoulish crimes making the news in New York, it is difficult to catch many people -- especially affluent people -- in the act of worrying about the return of crime to where they live.</p>
        <p>27</p>
        <p>Fresh Air Fund</p>
        <p>28</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>33-34</p>
        <p>Rocket Richard  The charismatic star of the Montreal Canadiens through the 1940's and 1950's, one of the most electrifying goal-scorers in National Hockey League history and a revered figure in French-speaking Canada, he was 78.</p>
        <p>34</p>
        <p>Frank G. Wangeman  A mentor to a generation of hotel managers, he was 88.</p>
        <p>33</p>
        <p>Chess</p>
        <p>33</p>
        <p>Weather</p>
        <p>35</p>
        <p>Cong. Vote</p>
        <p>23</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
