<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>INVESTING WITH: Mayer Offman; Carlin Equities Group</title>
    <meta content="28INVO$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203079"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Carlin Equities Group</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rosenberg, Hilary</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Offman, Mayer</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Investing With</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02EED9103DF93BA15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="889" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>INVESTING WITH: Mayer Offman; Carlin Equities Group</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HILARY ROSENBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rosenberg, Hilary</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mayer Offman, chief investment strategist at Carlin Equities Group, which caters to day traders, invests about 75 percent of his own portfolio in positions that are held for no longer than a day, 15 percent in investments of two or three months and the rest in what he calls 'quirks,' such as merger candidates; may make as many as 500 trade a day in particularly active rising market; a devout Jew and ordained rabbi, Offman says his trading returns decline when he slacked off on his devotions and improved again once he resumed his synagogue worship; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LAST March, after attending synagogue morning and evening for nearly a year, Mayer Offman decided to take a break from his devotions.</p>
        <p>It was not a wise investment move, according to Mr. Offman, chief investment strategist at Carlin Equities Group, a New York firm that caters to day traders. Soon, Mr. Offman, who is an ordained rabbi, began losing money on his trades. While others might have put the blame on Nasdaq's sell-off, Mr. Offman believes other factors were also at work. ''In Judaism, everything you do, there's reward or punishment,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LAST March, after attending synagogue morning and evening for nearly a year, Mayer Offman decided to take a break from his devotions.</p>
        <p>It was not a wise investment move, according to Mr. Offman, chief investment strategist at Carlin Equities Group, a New York firm that caters to day traders. Soon, Mr. Offman, who is an ordained rabbi, began losing money on his trades. While others might have put the blame on Nasdaq's sell-off, Mr. Offman believes other factors were also at work. ''In Judaism, everything you do, there's reward or punishment,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Once he resumed his synagogue worship, after a few weeks, his returns improved. Year to date through May 19, his portfolio is up more than 125 percent versus a loss of 3.8 percent for the S.&amp; P. 500.</p>
        <p>Mr. Offman, 49, pursued rabbinical studies at Yeshiva University in the mid-1970's. But he could not resist business school at night. Eventually, the lure of finance won out: After a stint as a Hebrew school teacher, he became, first, an auditor at Ernst &amp; Young and then a broker and trader. In 1993, he co-founded Carlin with Ronald H. Shear, now its chief executive.</p>
        <p>A large man with flyaway graying hair  and a yarmulke, Mr. Offman has a rapid-fire style of speaking that reflects his trading style. As it turns out, he seems to be good at what he does. Over the last three years through May 19, he said, his portfolio has risen some 2,300 percent to $43.5 million.</p>
        <p>Although he does not practice as a rabbi, Mr. Offman serves as Carlin's in-house mentor, training less-experienced traders and conducting morning conference calls in which he recommends long and short positions to the firm's 1,000 or so day-trading customers nationwide.</p>
        <p>As for whether day trading is a noble profession, Mr. Offman has strong views; it brings much-needed liquidity to the markets, he said. Unlike day-trading houses that cater to ordinary investors, Carlin generally welcomes only experienced brokers or traders, most of whom are seasoned Wall Street professionals.</p>
        <p>About three-quarters of Mr. Offman's own portfolio is used to take positions that are held for no longer than a day. Another 15 percent is reserved for investments of two to three months. And the rest is invested in what Mr. Offman calls ''quirks,'' such as merger candidates in which he takes an arbitrage position.</p>
        <p>For his short-term investments, Mr. Offman said he usually just follows the trend, buying stocks that are hot and betting against the stocks that are weakening by selling them short. He holds stocks as long as they outperform: when they stop doing so, he sells. The reverse is true when he shorts a stock.</p>
        <p>But such trading is not as off-the-cuff as it first appears. Mr. Offman incorporates fundamental research in his decisions about whether to buy or short. During the day, Mr. Offman devours analysts' reports and scans news services. His aim is to understand as much as he can about active stocks so that he can take a stand on whether a stock or group of stocks is starting on an upward or downward trend.</p>
        <p>Mr. Offman begins his day at around 8:30 a.m., watching premarket trading in S.&amp; P. 500 futures and stock trading on Instinet, the electronic market. He pays special attention to the previous day's five or so strongest and weakest stocks. When the market opens, Mr. Offman often trades those stocks, expecting the trends to continue.</p>
        <p>But he also watches stocks that open at prices significantly higher than the previous day's close. ''If in the first half-hour, the stock is down only a small amount from the opening, it will probably make another run on the upside,'' he said. So he buys in. For shorting opportunities, Mr. Offman does the reverse, looking for stocks that open significantly lower than the previous close.</p>
        <p>Mr. Offman may make 500 trades a day in a particularly active rising market. In the month of May, through Friday, he has held about 350 different stocks.</p>
        <p>EACH day, in the last half-hour of trading, Mr. Offman sells out some positions and makes sure that the remainder are completely hedged, balanced out by shorts on stocks in industries that he views negatively.</p>
        <p>One of Mr. Offman's favorite longer-term stocks is NeoRx, a Seattle biotechnology company that, among other things, is testing a radioactive compound for the treatment of multiple myeloma. Mr. Offman started buying at $5 a share in early February. He sold those shares in the first week in March at prices ranging from $25 to $40. The stock dipped in early April, and he began purchasing shares again for an average price of about $15. Shares closed Friday at $13.125.</p>
        <p>His favorite short position recently has been Amazon.com. ''I began shorting it the day Time magazine made Jeff Bezos the Man of the Year,'' Mr. Offman said, referring to Amazon's chief executive. At the time, the stock was trading at more than $95 a share. It closed Friday at $46.50. ''I think they're a long way from making money,'' said Mr. Offman, adding that he believes the stock will sink to $25 or $30.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
