<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ideas &amp; Trends: Antitrust Annals; The Uncertain Art Of Legal Remedies</title>
    <meta content="28LOHR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203089"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Microsoft Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lohr, Steve</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE7DE113DF93BA15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="908" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ideas &amp; Trends: Antitrust Annals; The Uncertain Art Of Legal Remedies</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVE LOHR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lohr, Steve</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Justice Dept's antitrust case against Microsoft Corp notes that issue of appropriate punishment in antitrust cases has been conundrum since 388 BC, when group of Athenian grain dealers who formed corn monopoly and manipulated prices were put to death (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN a court filing last week Microsoft called the government's proposal to break the company in two ''the antitrust equivalent of the death penalty.''</p>
        <p>Lawyerly hyperbole, it seems, but in the old days -- the very old days -- antitrust offenders couldn't afford to take any chances. In 388-386 B.C., a group of Athenian grain dealers formed a corn monopoly and manipulated prices, according to research by Spencer Weber Waller, a professor at the Brooklyn Law School. The dealers were caught, prosecuted and put to death.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN a court filing last week Microsoft called the government's proposal to break the company in two ''the antitrust equivalent of the death penalty.''</p>
        <p>Lawyerly hyperbole, it seems, but in the old days -- the very old days -- antitrust offenders couldn't afford to take any chances. In 388-386 B.C., a group of Athenian grain dealers formed a corn monopoly and manipulated prices, according to research by Spencer Weber Waller, a professor at the Brooklyn Law School. The dealers were caught, prosecuted and put to death.</p>
        <p>Ever since, the issue of the appropriate punishment in antitrust cases has been a conundrum, if not a lethal one.</p>
        <p>''We kill companies occasionally, but we've never killed any people with antitrust enforcement in America,'' said Herbert Hovenkamp, a professor at the University of Iowa law school.</p>
        <p>Antitrust is a flexible doctrine intended to prohibit ''anticompetitive behavior'' -- a concept whose definition shifts according to the economic and political thinking of the day. So the remedial steps, too, have varied widely over the years.</p>
        <p>There are two broad approaches: ''structural'' remedies, which involve breaking up the offending company; and ''conduct'' remedies, which involve prohibiting certain kinds of corporate behavior, like threatening rivals or writing contracts that restrict competition.</p>
        <p>Both approaches have drawbacks. Breaking up a company is drastic, irrevocable and runs the risk of doing more harm than good. Restraints on a company's behavior can be easily sidestepped, may do little to curb its market power and may require constant policing by a court or government.</p>
        <p>In the Microsoft case, Judge Thomas Penfield Jackson appears to be seriously weighing a breakup of the company. In his court in Washington last Wednesday, Judge Jackson pointedly asked the government why it did not go even further and recommend breaking up Microsoft into three companies instead of just two. The judge may issue his remedies order as soon as this week, but no matter what he decides, Microsoft will appeal both his sanctions and his legal ruling, which found the company to be a monopolist that used its market power to stifle competition.</p>
        <p>THE track record of antitrust remedies is decidedly mixed, even humbling. For decades, from Standard Oil in 1911 through United Shoe Machinery in 1968, the courts tended to look approvingly on structural remedies, says Mr. Hovenkamp, editor of the 18-volume treatise ''Antitrust Law,'' begun in 1978 by Philip Areeda of the Harvard Law School, who died in 1995.</p>
        <p>United Shoe Machinery is the classic cautionary tale for skeptics of the structural approach. The government sued the company and in 1953 a district court in Boston found that it had violated the law but declined to break it up. In his opinion, Judge Charles Wyzanski explained that federal judges are not experts in economics or politics and ''their prophecies as to the economic future are not guided by unusually subtle judgment.''</p>
        <p>YEARS later, the government asked the Supreme Court to modify Judge Wyzanski's remedies order so that United Shoe could be broken up. In 1968, the Supreme Court agreed with the government and United Shoe was split up, even though United Shoe's share of the shoe-making machinery market declined from 85 percent to 48 percent between 1953 and 1968.</p>
        <p>United Shoe eventually collapsed, though the role of the government's misguided ministrations is unclear. Among antitrust scholars, however, ''A lot of people who have studied it since believe that the courts got it wrong,'' Mr. Hovenkamp observed.</p>
        <p>Maybe, but 1968 was the height of the ''big is bad'' bias against business and for the notion that government should step in to restrain corporate power. That changed by the late 1970's, as international rivals began to challenge America companies and as free-market academics, led by University of Chicago theorists, influenced antitrust thinking.</p>
        <p>The courts, in general, have been skittish about splitting up companies in antitrust cases since the 1980's. A qualified exception was the AT&amp;T breakup in 1984, but that was unusual, a consent decree applied to a government-sanctioned monopoly.</p>
        <p>Antitrust experts say the structural approach to antitrust remedies is gaining renewed respect. One reason, they say, is that the consent decree the Justice Department signed with Microsoft in 1994 is widely seen as a failure.</p>
        <p>The decree, antitrust experts say, was a backward-looking remedy that did little to restrain Microsoft's market power in an industry moving ahead at a rapid clip. ''The government was shooting at a moving target, and it aimed, shot and missed,'' noted William Kovacic, a professor at the George Washington University law school.</p>
        <p>The cases in which breakup remedies will now receive serious consideration by the courts, according to antitrust experts, involve ''durable'' monopolies (at least five years old) for which there is ''no reasonable prospect'' that the market will become competitive unless the monopolist is split up.</p>
        <p>So much for theory. In the Microsoft case, what are the chances that the company will be broken up after all the appeals are over? A straw poll of six antitrust scholars who are not affiliated with either side in the case rated that probability at 20 percent to 50 percent.</p>
        <p>Significantly, all six wanted to do their handicapping anonymously. There have been too many surprises already, they say, in the antitrust soap opera formally known as the United States of America v. the Microsoft Corporation.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
