<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The World: U.S.-Europe Relations; Tiffs Over Bananas And Child Custody</title>
    <meta content="28COHE$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203099"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E6D9113DF93BA15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1124" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The World: U.S.-Europe Relations; Tiffs Over Bananas And Child Custody</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROGER COHEN</byline>
      <dateline>BERLIN</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ACLOSE aide to Chancellor Gerhard Schroder was recently astounded to find a cabinet meeting devoted to the divisive issue of child custody in German-American relations. Foreign Minister Joschka Fischer weighed in; so did Mr. Schroder himself. There was much agonizing as they reviewed the family difficulties of Lady Catherine Meyer, who is the wife of the British ambassador to Washington.</p>
        <p>Welcome to the new trans-Atlantic relationship, one that is bereft of an overarching mission yet so intimate that issues long considered domestic or secondary become major irritants. Lady Meyer has two sons from a previous marriage to a German doctor. The boys live in Germany with their father. Because of the vagaries of German custody laws, the children have had limited access to their mother, who is indignant. President Clinton, moved by this and other similar cases, is expected to raise the issue during a visit to Germany this week.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ACLOSE aide to Chancellor Gerhard Schroder was recently astounded to find a cabinet meeting devoted to the divisive issue of child custody in German-American relations. Foreign Minister Joschka Fischer weighed in; so did Mr. Schroder himself. There was much agonizing as they reviewed the family difficulties of Lady Catherine Meyer, who is the wife of the British ambassador to Washington.</p>
        <p>Welcome to the new trans-Atlantic relationship, one that is bereft of an overarching mission yet so intimate that issues long considered domestic or secondary become major irritants. Lady Meyer has two sons from a previous marriage to a German doctor. The boys live in Germany with their father. Because of the vagaries of German custody laws, the children have had limited access to their mother, who is indignant. President Clinton, moved by this and other similar cases, is expected to raise the issue during a visit to Germany this week.</p>
        <p>The cold war, whose heart was in Germany, has been over for a decade, and the big questions -- Euromissiles, Soviet divisions, global peace itself -- have disappeared from Washington's relations with Berlin and other European capitals. Beyond the intermittent flaring of Balkan crises, their place has largely been taken by genetically altered food, banana trade, the death penalty and even child custody. America's apparent determination to build a national missile defense system could still spur a major confrontation with Russia that would be deeply troubling to Washington's European allies. But, in general, how to live, what to eat and whether to accept the death sentence seem to have become the stuff of trans-Atlantic tiffs.</p>
        <p>The recurrent rows over such questions are sometimes viewed as a sign of the fraying ties between Western Europe and the United States. A voguish band of French intellectuals predict a coming clash with the all-devouring, all-knowing ''hyperpower.'' But there is another way of looking at these issues, many of which are essentially moral. Their prominence demonstrates the unprecedented closeness of European and American societies linked through business and cultural bonds intensified over the Internet.</p>
        <p>''What we now have with the United States is a relationship so close that it is quasi-domestic,'' said Karsten Voigt, a senior German foreign ministry official. ''The distinction between foreign and domestic policy has blurred as our societies have interwoven. That is why emotional issues like genetically altered food or the way we treat the children of international divorces rise to the surface. In a way, foreign policy was easier when it dealt with interests rather than emotions and morals.''</p>
        <p>Emotions being what they are, discussion of the new issues can get heated. An overwhelming majority of Germans consider the death penalty as unconscionable as the slave trade. Lady Meyer and others see Germany's child custody laws as barbaric.</p>
        <p>But Europeans and Americans are now divided by how they run their domestic societies even as they are bound by a shared international goal: enlarging the areas of the world with a functioning market economy governed by the rule of law. Such enlargement, in turn, opens new avenues to prosperity.</p>
        <p>''The pressures on all advanced nations are similar in the global economy,'' said Sidney Blumenthal, an adviser to President Clinton. ''So what we find ourselves discussing are values -- how open we should be to immigration, how to educate people for an information society.''</p>
        <p>Of course, divisions of substance do persist. President Clinton will hear much criticism in Europe of the proposed national missile defense system, which European governments view as a risky recourse to an unproven system against an unproven enemy -- so-called rogue states like North Korea whose inclination or ability to attack the United States is doubted here. Many European officials are not happy about the new isolationism they see in the House of Representatives, which tried to end the deployment of American peacekeepers in Kosovo. Europeans are uncertain about the American view of the old continent's determination to forge a more united Europe with its own credible military force; they also wonder what America thinks of a European federation -- a kind of United States of Europe -- suggested as a long-term aim by Foreign Minister Fischer this month.</p>
        <p>But even these issues seem to be about preserving a bond, and not about confrontation. True, the French argue for the euro or a proposed European rapid-reaction force as means to counterbalance the United States, but such talk is de rigueur. As Karl Kaiser, a German political scientist, noted, ''The first to scream if American troops upped and left Germany would be the French, because of their lingering fears of German hegemony.''</p>
        <p>AT a profound level, America has become an essential European power. Hence the concern here over possible isolationism and a missile system that poses the question: what happens when Americans have protected themselves and their European allies are sitting ducks? ''Our militaries have gotten in the habit of working together and that gives us something people don't want to give up,'' said John Roper, a British security expert. ''So problems will be finessed.''</p>
        <p>No doubt they will. For in some senses, the deepest concern of European governments today is that the United States is not paying Europe enough attention. ''Americans think Europe's problems are largely solved,'' said John Kornblum, the American ambassador to Germany. ''They are not thinking about the structures of Europe any more, they are thinking about why they can't sell their beef. Europeans, however, see themselves at a critical and rather treacherous juncture and would like America to pay more attention.''</p>
        <p>At that juncture stands the question of what ''Europe'' should be. The continent is at a crossroads. It feels a historic obligation to expand the 15-member European Union to include the former Communist states of Eastern Europe, but fears hordes of poor immigrants pouring in. It knows that this larger union would become ungovernable unless moves begin toward Mr. Fischer's federative United States of Europe, but the end of the nation state in places like France or Britain is a deeply divisive idea.</p>
        <p>Here, in these intra-European differences, the most painful and substantive clashes of the coming months and years may well emerge. Meanwhile, Europe and the United States, ever closer, will bicker over Texan executions and the fate of children whose mothers and fathers separated.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
