<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Our Towns; Charming Schemer May Be Near the End of the Road</title>
    <meta content="28TOWN$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203184"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">First Jersey Securities Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Purdy, Matthew</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brennan, Robert E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Our Towns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Futures and Options Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE3D61E3DF93BA15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="831" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Our Towns; Charming Schemer May Be Near the End of the Road</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW PURDY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Purdy, Matthew</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Matthew Purdy Our Tow</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BACK when life was good, Robert E. Brennan had racehorses, waterfront homes, helicopters, a plane and the tanned good looks and hint of mystery that make for star quality. Financing it all was his nationwide penny stock firm, First Jersey Securities, which he promoted with televised commercials from his helicopter, imploring investors to ''Come grow with us.''</p>
        <p>In the 1980's, he always seemed headed somewhere exciting -- a possible run for political office, the dedication of another building his generosity made possible, a visit with an important politician.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BACK when life was good, Robert E. Brennan had racehorses, waterfront homes, helicopters, a plane and the tanned good looks and hint of mystery that make for star quality. Financing it all was his nationwide penny stock firm, First Jersey Securities, which he promoted with televised commercials from his helicopter, imploring investors to ''Come grow with us.''</p>
        <p>In the 1980's, he always seemed headed somewhere exciting -- a possible run for political office, the dedication of another building his generosity made possible, a visit with an important politician.</p>
        <p>Thursday he seemed headed for jail.</p>
        <p>An artist of the shady deal and a champion charmer, Mr. Brennan, 56, was momentarily out of moves. In civil actions, a federal judge ruled in 1995 that Mr. Brennan's operation was a ''massive and continuing fraud,'' and last year a New Jersey judge called him ''a big crook.'' He owes $120 million in restitution to state and federal authorities. On Thursday, he surrendered his prized golf course in Monmouth County to avoid jail on contempt charges. Creditors are also seeking the palatial house in Juno Beach, Fla., where he lives and the multimillion-dollar off-shore trusts they say he controls in Gibraltar and Nevis.</p>
        <p>His eyes a bit bloodshot, the once-voluble Mr. Brennan was subdued outside the courtroom in Manhattan, saying only: ''This is a difficult time. I hope you'll respect that.''</p>
        <p>Bob Brennan may be downcast now, but for years he led the crowded field of New Jersey's Rogues' Biathlon -- winning respect while outrunning investigators.</p>
        <p>''If you summed it up in a word, it might be audacity,'' said James M. Smith, once chief of the New Jersey Bureau of Securities. ''The in-your-face way of operating, the open challenge to government.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Brennan created First Jersey in 1974 out of an investment firm that had been suspended by New Jersey officials for securities violations. It went nationwide even as authorities investigated Mr. Brennan for fraudulently inflating the price of cheap stocks, often in lackluster companies in which he had an interest. The stocks were sold by more than 1,000 salesmen making cold calls and reading from sales scripts.</p>
        <p>GOVERNMENT investigations rarely went smoothly. In 1980, an entire filing cabinet of documents in a case against First Jersey vanished from a Securities and Exchange Commission office in New York. A federal judge, John E. Sprizzo, removed himself from the case after learning that Mr. Brennan had named a racehorse Sprizzo. The two-legged Sprizzo barred Mr. Brennan from ever again naming a horse after a federal judge.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brennan saw opportunity everywhere. When Forbes magazine ran an article critical of him, he ripped off the cover, which featured his picture, and sent it to clients, never mentioning the words inside.</p>
        <p>If his money was ill-gotten, at least he was charitable. Buildings at Seton Hall University, Jersey Shore Medical Center and St. Benedict's Prep School in Newark bear the Brennan name. ''He is a hero to our students, to their parents and to the people of the city of Newark,'' the Rev. Edwin D. Leahy, St. Benedict's headmaster, testified at Mr. Brennan's 1994 federal civil trial.</p>
        <p>Powerful people were drawn to him and his money. Richard J. Hughes, the late governor of New Jersey, and John Degnan, a former state attorney general, were on one of his corporate boards. W. Hunt Dumont, the former United States attorney in Newark and now a state judge, was First Jersey's general counsel.</p>
        <p>''Some people have charm up the gazoo,'' said Edward I. Koch, the former mayor of New York, who attended parties at Mr. Brennan's home and had him to Gracie Mansion. ''He had it. He would make you feel comfortable. If he could send a car or his helicopter to bring you to his home in South Jersey, he would do it.</p>
        <p>''As for his business, all you knew was he never went to jail,'' Mr. Koch said. ''You had the feeling, here was this brave guy standing up to government. I guess they finally got him and rightfully so, I guess.''</p>
        <p>Whatever ''getting'' Mr. Brennan means. Although bankrupt and adamant that he cannot pay the government, he ran up $2,000 in golf fees and nearly $3,000 in liquor store bills in two months last year, and $248,000 in private jet fees for an overseas trip last summer, government lawyers say. Just after filing for bankruptcy in 1995, they say, he went to a Las Vegas casino looking to cash in $500,000 in chips he neglected to report in the bankruptcy case.</p>
        <p>Thursday's court agreement takes away the aptly named Due Process golf course, formerly his horse farm, but allows him to  use his office and apartment there until the course is sold in bankruptcy proceedings.</p>
        <p>He left court crushed. But there were reports Friday that back at the golf course, he was flying high again -- in a helicopter.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
