<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>I.P.O.'s Say Stocks' Downturn Not Over</title>
    <meta content="28WATC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203064"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MARKET WATCH"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Salomon Smith Barney Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Morgenson, Gretchen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mullins, L Keith</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Gretchen Morgenson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E2DB103DF93BA15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="743" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>I.P.O.'s Say Stocks' Downturn Not Over</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GRETCHEN MORGENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Morgenson, Gretchen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>L Keith Mullins, head of emerging growth research at Salomon Smith Barney, believes stocks' recent downturn will not hit bottom until investor demand for initial public offerings dries up completely; the number of IPOS has dropped sharply in recent weeks, with only 23 companies going public in May, down from 65 in March, and 61 percent of this year's new issues are trading below their offering prices; Mullins insists stocks as a whole will remain vulnerable to correction as long as there is any life left in IPO market; graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INVESTORS in stocks have endured a lot of pain since the markets peaked a few months back. With the Dow Jones industrial average down 10.42 percent for the year, and the Nasdaq composite down more than twice that, investors are probably wondering when all this agony will be over.</p>
        <p>Not just yet, according to L. Keith Mullins, head of emerging growth research at Salomon Smith Barney.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INVESTORS in stocks have endured a lot of pain since the markets peaked a few months back. With the Dow Jones industrial average down 10.42 percent for the year, and the Nasdaq composite down more than twice that, investors are probably wondering when all this agony will be over.</p>
        <p>Not just yet, according to L. Keith Mullins, head of emerging growth research at Salomon Smith Barney.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mullins believes the bloodletting in stocks will not be stanched until investor fervor for initial public offerings goes completely cold.</p>
        <p>The number of new stock offerings has dropped considerably in recent weeks -- only 23 companies have offered shares to the public in May, down from 65 in March, according to Richard J. Peterson, chief market strategist at Thomson Financial Securities Data.</p>
        <p>Even worse for investors, 61 percent of this year's new issues are trading below their offering prices. ''It's ugly out there,'' Mr. Peterson said.</p>
        <p>Not ugly enough, according to Mr. Mullins. As long as there is any life in the market for new company shares, he thinks stocks as a whole remain vulnerable. Last Thursday's offering of Sonus Networks shares indicates the I.P.O. market still has a pulse. Sonus offered 5 million shares to the public at $23 each, and the stock closed its first day of trading at $50.50.</p>
        <p>''An enormous amount of damage has been done to investor psyches,'' Mr. Mullins said. ''But the new-issue market continues to be fairly resilient. My expectation is we will see the market continue to be much more selective about what issues will be brought out. The window will shut completely before the correction is done.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Mullins bases this view on 20 years of initial public offering data. New stock issues, he has found, are a perfect measurement of investor sentiment. ''It's when investors know the least about the companies and the information has been structured to have maximum appeal,'' he explained. ''When investors are wildly bullish, you can put anything through the channel. When they are bearish, if you had a company turning dirt to gold, people would say gold is going down.''</p>
        <p>One reason Mr. Mullins thinks we still have a way to go in the correction is that prices of new issues on their first day out are still popping like champagne corks.</p>
        <p>During April and most of May, Mr. Mullins said, first-day gains in I.P.O.'s averaged 13 percent. While that is well below the 109 percent average pop seen last December, it is still above the average for 1994 through 1998, when the figure was 12.7 percent.</p>
        <p>And while the number of deals has declined in recent weeks, it has not fallen enough for Mr. Mullins. Around the 1987 crash, for example, the average number of deals each month fell from 63 to 9. And during the Long Term Capital Management crisis in the fall of 1998, the number of deals fell from 53 monthly to 15. So the 23 stocks issued so far in May looks a bit high.</p>
        <p>Still, one piece of Mr. Mullins' data may indicate we are close to the correction's end. That is the difference between a new stock's offering price and the middle of the price range company management expected when they presented their deal to investors.</p>
        <p>When investors are euphoric for new issues, the stocks typically fetch prices well above the expected range. Last January, for instance, the average I.P.O.'s price was an astonishing 45 percent above the middle of the expected range. By comparison, between 1994 and 1998, the average I.P.O. came out at a  price 0.1 percent below the middle of the expected range.</p>
        <p>This month, however, I.P.O.'s have been pricing at 30 percent below the midpoint. Mr. Mullins said this was the lowest monthly average he has seen in six years.</p>
        <p>Still, the I.P.O. market has further to cool before Mr. Mullins will be convinced that the correction in stock prices is over. When investor appetite for new issues disappears altogether, he said, be on the alert for a ripping rally in small and mid-cap stocks.</p>
        <p>MARKET WATCH</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
