<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Out For a Night In Search Of the In</title>
    <meta content="28CLUB$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203056"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nightclubs and Cabarets</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mckinley, Jesse</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nightclubs and Cabarets</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E6DC103DF93BA15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2423" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Out For a Night In Search Of the In</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JESSE McKINLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mckinley, Jesse</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jesse McKinley article on new dance clubs, lounges, restaurants and hybrids contending for attention in New York's crowded club scene; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IF you're the kind of person who likes to meditate to the pounding beat of Run DMC, do I ever have a club for you.</p>
        <p>It's Spa, a cavernous new dance scene on East 13th Street, which has boldly attempted to graft a New Age ethos -- waterfalls! plants! -- with a sound system so loud it makes your teeth chatter.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IF you're the kind of person who likes to meditate to the pounding beat of Run DMC, do I ever have a club for you.</p>
        <p>It's Spa, a cavernous new dance scene on East 13th Street, which has boldly attempted to graft a New Age ethos -- waterfalls! plants! -- with a sound system so loud it makes your teeth chatter.</p>
        <p>So overwhelming is the decibel level, in fact, that the club has hired a jockey-size man whose job, apparently, is to take orders from patrons, jump up on the bar (boing!) and tell the deafened barkeeps what to mix. This lephrechaun-like go-between then hands the drinks back to the customer. I thought I was watching some obscure alcoholic Olympic event.</p>
        <p>Such are the surreal sights encountered during a recent  expedition around the night-life circuit, those mythical grounds behind the velvet ropes, where club owners are constantly juggling concepts and looks to try to satisfy the city's fickle night crawlers.</p>
        <p>It is a brutally competitive terrain, which has recently seen the arrival of several major contenders for the crown of ''it'' club. Before everyone who's anyone leaves for the summer, of course. The roster includes three handsome new downtown establishments -- Lotus, Eugene and Luahn -- each of which has built good advance buzz with private parties for gossip column-worthy outfits like Inside.com, GQ magazine and the talent agency International Management Group. These three newcomers joined two late 1999 entries, Centro-Fly and Chaos.</p>
        <p>Then there's the Brazilian-theme danceteria called Saci, which opened in March off Times Square and promptly became known as a favorite spot of Sean Combs. Which, of course, can be a mixed blessing.</p>
        <p>With the no-dancing lounge scene feeling more and more tired, night-life entrepreneurs are diversifying, creating increasingly ambitious hybrids. Lotus, for example, fuses a restaurant, lounge and nightclub into a single, three-level space -- divided, of course, by a velvet rope or three.</p>
        <p>''We've taken a $3.5 million bet that people want to dine, lounge and dance all in one space,'' said Jeffrey Jah, a former promoter at the defunct Life nightclub, who is a co-owner of Lotus. ''We want to be everything to everybody.''</p>
        <p>His partner Mark Baker put it more succinctly: ''You have so many slightly older guys, 28 to 40, who are most comfortable sitting in a lounge sipping cocktails and seeing their friends. But their 22-year-old model girlfriends want to dance.''</p>
        <p>Enter Lotus; that is, when it does enter. Originally scheduled to open in mid-May at 409 West 14th Street, the club is now aiming for a June 8 opening. ''The policy at the door is to be friendly,'' Mr. Jah promised.</p>
        <p>This could be a trend. Many seemingly haughty door folk often defy expectations. Last weekend, I found easy, unannounced access to such roped-off establishments as Serena, Joe's Pub, Moomba, Veruka and Lot 61.</p>
        <p>Not that some places aren't still practicing the ancient art of sidewalk humiliation. For a demonstration of this ego-brutalizing contact sport, I recommend Halo, a subterranean Greenwich Village club whose crack two-person door team (he is big, she is blonde) rejects all who aren't very good looking or flashing $5,000 shoulder bags. Once inside the former after-hours club (49 Grove Street), the beautiful, multi-racial crowd bask in fine amber lighting and in the glow of celebrities like Harrison Ford and Taye Diggs.</p>
        <p>If you get in, of course. But it was here, on a recent Saturday, that a bespectacled young man heard four of the most dreaded words in masculinity: ''No more men tonight.''</p>
        <p>Not that I was too upset. With their ever-present promise of supermodels, $11 cocktails and long bathroom lines, many of these ''scene'' clubs feel interchangeable. (Note to designers: There ought to be a permanent ban on red banquettes and little white table candles.)</p>
        <p>And after all, there were plenty of other places to go.</p>
        <p>I had begun my Cook's tour the night before at Luahn, a lounge-cum-restaurant on Fifth Avenue near 13th Street. Luahn is the brainchild of Jason Strauss and Noah Tepperberg, two promoters in their mid-20's, who also run the club Conscience Point in Southampton. (Stephen Baldwin, the Baldwin brother in those M&amp;M ads, is also a co-owner.)</p>
        <p>Already popular with the fashion set, Luahn (59 Fifth Avenue) easily has the most velvet ropes per square foot of any establishment in town. Visitors who get past the ropes outside are immediately greeted by another set leading to the lounge downstairs, manned by members of some new pro-stubble cult. Once inside the lounge, there's even a third rope, on the back stairs leading to and from the bathroom, guarded by an unhappy looking fellow who apparently didn't know that the Census Bureau is still hiring.</p>
        <p>For all that -- probably because of all that -- the lounge at Luahn has the feeling of a hot-and-getting-hotter scene. The crowd was standing room only last Friday at 11:30 p.m., as was the line at the door. Some of that may be the size of the place; the lounge fits about 50 average-size people comfortably. Or 75 models.</p>
        <p>The decor is minimal: red banquettes, little white table candles, amber overhead lighting. The single decorative flair is a series of small, blue-tinted X-rays framed on one wall. And of course, the kitchen-cam. Part of Luahn's see-and-be-seen vibe is a series of small video monitors located around the restaurant and lounge showing a live feed of the kitchen. The idea, Mr. Strauss said, is to allow ''patrons to watch their food prepared.'' Of course. The crudites will be televised.</p>
        <p>Not that anybody was looking at the monitors the night I was there. Imitating the natives, I slouched behind a small table to take in the scene, whereupon my cool was immediately under assault from an overenthusiastic middle-aged man. A Joe Pesci look-alike with heavy-rimmed glasses, this gentleman began dancing while still seated, launching into a sort of head-rolling, shoulder-gyrating break dance. He looked as if he were being Rolfed.</p>
        <p>His suffering, and the overpacked crowd, left me longing for a quieter, more peaceful domain.</p>
        <p>I chose Spa. As they often say in jail, it seemed like a good idea at the time.</p>
        <p>Opened in April, Spa (76 East 13th Street) is the direct descendant of Life, the popular Bleecker Street dance hall that closed last year. Several staffers from Life helped establish Spa, and their influence is felt. The music is loud, the covers steep and the crowd turnover heavy.</p>
        <p>That said, at 1 a.m. on a Saturday morning, there was a swarm of people seeking admission. A security staff strolled the sidewalk, warning people to remain in line. There were barricades and beefy bouncers and vacant-eyed, clipboard-wielding doorwomen.</p>
        <p>Inside, on the other hand, the theme is the healing power of water. Overhead video screens flash underwater scenes, the bar stocks 16 varieties of bottled water and if you lean against the slated walls you can hear water running.</p>
        <p>Holistic pretensions aside, Spa is all about commotion. Visitors pack its bars three deep, and the lines to the bathrooms (decorated like saunas, get it?) snake out their doors. The club also traffics in such notions as a two-bottle minimum (liquor, that is, not water, at $250 a bottle) for all who wish to occupy its white leather booths.</p>
        <p>In a booth elevated over the dance floor, Grandmaster Flash, the D.J., led the crowd through all manner of hip-hop, disco and rap. The Virgil-like character guiding me and a date through the scene was a polite fellow named Gianpaolo (''But everyone calls me J.P.''). He lead us to a booth, one of about a dozen that circle the main dance floor. ''This area is usually completely filled with celebrities,'' Gianpaolo said.</p>
        <p>I had to take his word for it. I did spy, on the other hand, a pair of ''American Psycho,'' Wall Street types in the next booth. What did they think of Spa?</p>
        <p>''This place is bullish,'' one said. Or something like that.</p>
        <p>Spa also has a back room, a quieter, classier space where the minimum-bottle business is less strict and the music is devoted to rhythm and blues, trance and pop.</p>
        <p>We returned to the dance floor, where the crowd continued to grow and where I encountered, no kidding, another polyester rope, this time in front of the bar. And there, sitting on top with his legs dangling, was the gymnastic man whose job it was to take my order. He heard me out, jumped back atop the bar and efficiently delivered a small plastic cup of cocktail. Diana Ross was singing, ''I'm Coming Out.'' I drank my drink and did the same.</p>
        <p>While Spa is the newest, a couple of other recently opened dance spots offer variations on a similar theme. The red-curtained environs of Chaos (225 East Houston Street) are impressive, as are its exotic sounding hideaways -- the Neptune Room, the Red Salon. But the club also subscribes to the same obnoxious policy requiring the minimum order of a bottle of pricey Champagne or liquor to secure a table, and it is often beset by around-the-corner lines.</p>
        <p>The motif at work at Centro-Fly, meanwhile, at 45 West 21st Street, is futurism, which from a decorative standpoint apparently means Op Art spirals, plentiful plexiglass and a door staff dressed in orange jumpsuits.</p>
        <p>Centro-Fly, which boasts a state-of-the-art D.J. booth, has been a hot spot since opening in December, drawing big crowds of electronic music aficionados and just plain dancing fools. The night I dropped in, the music was high-volume house, accompanied by eye-dazzling lights. Toward the back is a dark hallway that leads to the club's restaurant and lounge, a sleek, sedate space where the walls are painted with a series of perspective-twisting paintings. (The future, apparently, will not smile on realism.)</p>
        <p>It would be an ideal space for nondancers to drink and gossip -- it has a slight Los Angeles feel -- except for the fact that one has to enter through the dance club, with its $20 cover, to get there. (If you make a reservation for dinner, the cover is waived.) The owners say they will soon open a separate entrance. I endorse that plan.</p>
        <p>Still, after a complete weekend out, I felt slightly under-fabulous. There was only one solution: I would Moomba.</p>
        <p>Despite all the newcomers, for sheer celebrity quotient, the prize still goes to that mother of all swank lounges, Moomba (133 Seventh Avenue South, near 10th Street). On the Monday night I visited, the door to the third-floor V.I.P. room was crowded as usual, with about 15 would-be hipsters bantering for entrance.</p>
        <p>''Hey, dude,'' one suited young man said to the skinny fellow at the door.</p>
        <p>''Yes?'' he replied.</p>
        <p>''Dude?'' the suit said with a lilt in his voice.</p>
        <p>He might as well have been saying goodbye.</p>
        <p>The draw on this particular Monday, as it has been for the last month, was karaoke, that cheesiest of art forms, which has somehow snuck back intact from suburbia.</p>
        <p>The karaoke evening is overseen by Samantha Ronson, the tomboyish younger sister of the celebrity D.J. Mark Ronson. Her idea for the evening is simple.</p>
        <p>''Get them drunk enough,'' she said, ''and anybody will sing.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, the crowd upstairs was wobbling room only, a sight reminiscent of Moomba's very first days back in 1997, when Leo once juggled four models at a single table and began work on his second chin. A small stage is set up near the windows, lighted by a single rose-colored spotlight.</p>
        <p>As I entered, the words of Tommy James's ''Mony Mony'' were scrolling across the wall, and two buxom blondes were leading the crowd in a cheer of ''Get laid.''</p>
        <p>My attention was drawn away by Jeff Gossett, Moomba's soft-spoken majority owner, who still spends an inordinate amount of his time shuffling celebrities from door to table and table to door. He gave me a quick lay of the land: the crowd included the television talk-show personality Lisa Ling, the actors Liev Schreiber and James Van Der Beek, the model Yasmine Bleeth, members of the rock bands the Foo Fighters and the Black Crowes and ''some of those guys from that show 'Popular.' ''</p>
        <p>There was also ample evidence of disposable income; a gentleman to my left put his cigarette out in my drink and offered to buy me another.</p>
        <p>As I stood watching a soulful version of ''New York, New York,'' a well-dressed, bald, snaggle-toothed man approached me, eyed my notebook and said: ''You should talk to me. I'm a big celebrity.''</p>
        <p>Yeah right, buddy, and I'm the Duchess of Windsor.</p>
        <p>He asked my name and I asked his.</p>
        <p>''I'm Moby,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Sure enough, it was Mr. Moby himself, the multi-platinum D.J., who told me he is between European and American tours.</p>
        <p>He is not a singer by trade, of course, but this was his night; he was clutching a bulky black notebook with the titles of hundreds of potential karaoke songs. He had already made his choice: ''What a Wonderful World'' by Louis Armstrong.</p>
        <p>''The lure is watching celebrities humiliate themselves,'' he said, a minute before taking the stage. ''And watching women pretend to enjoy it.''</p>
        <p>Moments later, Moby began to sing in a quivering voice, and for a few minutes the din subsided. When he finished, the crowd went wild.</p>
        <p>Moby slipped quietly out of the club -- I later spotted him eating falafel in the East Village -- but the crowd kept cheering for him.</p>
        <p>They seemed happy, having gotten what any decent prowler of the night demands: an experience they couldn't have had anywhere else, any other time.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
