<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Bluefish Blitz With Trappings of a Minuet</title>
    <meta content="28OUTD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203136"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="OUTDOORS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fishing, Sport</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bluefish</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Martha's Vineyard (Mass)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bryant, Nelson</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Fishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts/Cape Cod and the Islands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts/Cape Cod and the Islands/Martha's Vineyard</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fishing, Sport</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E0DD1E3DF93BA15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1017" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Bluefish Blitz With Trappings of a Minuet</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Nelson Bryant</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bryant, Nelson</byline>
      <dateline>EDGARTOWN, Mass.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article describes classic 'bluefish blitz' on Martha's Vineyard with rods bent, fish flopping on sand, anglers enjoying camaraderie that exists among surf casters (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The day was dark and dank, a stiff near gale from the south hurling good-sized combers against the outer beach of Martha's Vineyard Island, when, with Nelson Sigelman and me on board, Cooper Gilkes nosed his four-wheel-drive vehicle out onto the strand and headed west toward Wasque Rip on Chappaquiddick.</p>
        <p>Coop had already been there several times this spring, but it was the first visit of the season for Nelson and me. We were after the northward-migrating bluefish that year after year in recent times have arrived at Wasque Rip off Chappaquiddick shortly before mid-May. This year, the first bluefish was caught from shore at that location on May 1, and by May 11 bluefishing at Wasque Rip was well under way.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The day was dark and dank, a stiff near gale from the south hurling good-sized combers against the outer beach of Martha's Vineyard Island, when, with Nelson Sigelman and me on board, Cooper Gilkes nosed his four-wheel-drive vehicle out onto the strand and headed west toward Wasque Rip on Chappaquiddick.</p>
        <p>Coop had already been there several times this spring, but it was the first visit of the season for Nelson and me. We were after the northward-migrating bluefish that year after year in recent times have arrived at Wasque Rip off Chappaquiddick shortly before mid-May. This year, the first bluefish was caught from shore at that location on May 1, and by May 11 bluefishing at Wasque Rip was well under way.</p>
        <p>Scanning the water as we drove, we were about halfway to Wasque when we thought we saw a different wave pattern on the water, perhaps indicating feeding bluefish even though no gulls or terns were about.</p>
        <p>We stopped and began casting metal jigs: Hopkins, Kastmasters, Krokodiles and others of that genre. Within 10 minutes, Coop had a couple of hits and Nelson and I were each fast to a fish that subsequently pulled free. Nothing more occurred after that flurry, so we kept on to the west to where we could see more than a dozen vehicles parked on the beach. When we got closer, Coop said, ''I don't see any bent rods.''</p>
        <p>It was true. About half the anglers were casting and the others were sipping coffee or working on gear or sitting on tailgates and gamming.</p>
        <p>We stopped about 100 yards short of them and resumed fishing. Ten minutes later, bent rods were the rule rather than the exception, and all hands were catching fish ranging from five to eight pounds.</p>
        <p>At first, most of the fish were taken on the aforementioned metal, but some casters switched to popping plugs, which also worked. Many anglers prefer to go after bluefish with poppers, the surf fisher's equivalent of the flyrodder's floating fly, because it's exciting to see the wind-blown spray from a smashing strike.</p>
        <p>At one point some of the blues were right against the beach, and that reminded me to shorten my casts. There's little point in hooking a fish 90 yards offshore when you can accomplish the same thing with a 30-yard toss. This has particular merit when a strong tide -- for which Wasque Rip is famous -- is running, greatly reducing the time needed to bring your quarry to the beach.</p>
        <p>A classic bluefish blitz was soon under way, rods bent, fish flopping on the sand, an occasional angler frantically striving to remove a deeply embedded hook from a fish without getting part of a finger bitten off, all the while glancing over his shoulder at the action. A bluefish minuet developed: anglers fast to fish moving downtide with them, a maneuver that requires the casters in their path to reel in and get out of the way. With a big rod and heavy line, you can usually stand your ground and bring the fish to you, but it's a different ball game with light tackle, particularly if the blue was hooked at the end of a long cast.</p>
        <p>At one point, Janet Messineo, a Vineyard taxidermist and a talented angler who was catching bluefish at a furious rate, asked if I would help her put an elastic bandage on her wrist to alleviate her tendinitis.</p>
        <p>On another occasion, such is the camaraderie among surf casters, Don Mohr, a longtime regular at Wasque, took pity on me as I was trying to extract a popping plug's treble hook from the upper jaw of a bluefish and offered me his pliers. I asked him how he was doing.</p>
        <p>''My replacement parts seem to be wearing out,'' he said cheerfully and limped away to resume casting. Don, a former semipro football and baseball player, has had a series of operations that include two hip and two knee replacements, but that doesn't keep him from his beloved Wasque.</p>
        <p>Nelson Sigelman, who is a reporter for the weekly Vineyard Times, couldn't focus solely on fishing. He needed photographs of the event, which were hard to get because spray kept dashing over his camera, but he did beach a couple of blues.</p>
        <p>In addition to catching that evening's supper, I wanted half a dozen or more fish to put in my smoker, a once-sacrosanct ritual for me with the first bluefish of the season. Coop took the pressure off me by saying I could have his fish.</p>
        <p>Coop, who runs a tackle shop in Edgartown, is also a well-known fishing guide. He was taking a busman's holiday with Nelson and me and hinting that he might return to Wasque that evening. Keeper striped bass -- in Massachusetts the minimum length this year is 30 inches -- are already being caught at Wasque and the area east of it, East Beach.</p>
        <p>We were fishing the latter part of the falling tide at midday on our bluefish caper, but Coop said that he had been doing well with stripers on the rising tide, particularly at night.</p>
        <p>Back home by midafternoon, I began fileting my fish and discovered that the stomachs of most were empty. Those that had been feeding recently had been dining on squid, sea robins and something that appeared to be from the herring family. I was delighted to find that the bluefish were still stiff and firm. Bluefish deteriorate rapidly after capture.</p>
        <p>I was still busy at my task when Ruth, my companion, returned from a trip to the supermarket, squealed with delight and confessed that she had purchased a pound of hamburger just in case I had failed in my quest, a purchase that, if nothing else, reveals something about my angling prowess.</p>
        <p>OUTDOORS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
