<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Overcoming Obstacles, 4 Determined Students Earn Degrees -- A Late Start; Long, Hard Climb To Academic Peak</title>
    <meta content="28GRA2$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203201"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Age, Chronological</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Graduate Schools and Students</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of Tennessee</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yellin, Emily</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eichelbaum, Elizabeth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Age, Chronological</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Graduate Schools and Students</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E4DF1F3DF93BA15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="700" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Overcoming Obstacles, 4 Determined Students Earn Degrees -- A Late Start; Long, Hard Climb To Academic Peak</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EMILY YELLIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Yellin, Emily</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article in series on four determined students who earned degrees this month focuses on Elizabeth Eichelbaum, who at age of 90 recived PhD in education from University of Tennessee, 25 years after earning high school equivalency diploma; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>At 90, Elizabeth Eichelbaum has had enough experiences to fill several lives, and has earned nothing if not a rest. But she had other ideas, and this month was awarded a Ph.D. in education from the University of Tennessee in Knoxville.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Eichelbaum arrived in the United States in 1921, an 11-year-old who had narrowly survived the ravages of the Russian Revolution and who had been separated from her mother for more than a decade, until the two were reunited in New York. She has little memory of her father.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>At 90, Elizabeth Eichelbaum has had enough experiences to fill several lives, and has earned nothing if not a rest. But she had other ideas, and this month was awarded a Ph.D. in education from the University of Tennessee in Knoxville.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Eichelbaum arrived in the United States in 1921, an 11-year-old who had narrowly survived the ravages of the Russian Revolution and who had been separated from her mother for more than a decade, until the two were reunited in New York. She has little memory of her father.</p>
        <p>Unable to attend school in Russia during World War I, she finally entered the fifth grade at P.S. 184 in Harlem. But in eighth grade she felt she had to drop out to work in a dress shop.</p>
        <p>After that, her life strayed further from the classroom. She married and raised four sons, including twins; ran a delicatessen in Detroit; and nursed her husband through battles with diabetes and heart disease, to which he succumbed in 1973.</p>
        <p>She herself has lived with a brain tumor that doctors diagnosed in 1977 as not life-threatening.</p>
        <p>She had earned a high school equivalency diploma in 1975 and, eager to pursue a lifelong love of painting, enrolled at age 65 as an art student at Wayne State University in Detroit. She would later receive a bachelor's degree and a master's degree.</p>
        <p>On May 12, despite having macular degeneration, which has left her nearly blind, Mrs. Eichelbaum donned a graduation robe once again and stepped onto a Knoxville stage to accept her doctorate. Her thesis focused on the value of art therapy to older adults.</p>
        <p>''I felt bad when I had no education,'' said Mrs. Eichelbaum, her voice unwavering. ''I had people I met who'd ask me what university I went to, when I didn't even have more than four years of grade school.''</p>
        <p>But ultimately, she said, it was her own opinion that weighed more heavily than the judgments of others. ''I thought, this is what I needed and didn't get and I'm going to get it,'' she said. ''It never left my mind.''</p>
        <p>All her sons went to college before their mother did. The twins, now 67, live in New York City, where one, Stuart, is an artist, and the other, Edward, is a sex therapist who has appeared on ''Geraldo.'' Her third son, Marvin, 61, owns several clothing stores in Savannah, Ga. And her youngest, Stanley, 54, is an international real estate developer.</p>
        <p>All four were in the audience when she received her doctorate, joined by most of her four grandchildren and eight great-grandchildren. One grandson wrote a letter to ''Dear Abby'' in April, extolling his grandmother's accomplishment. Abby responded: ''Readers, Elizabeth has proved it can be done, so what's stopping you? Go back to school if that is your dream.''</p>
        <p>On a recent, unusually hot afternoon, Mrs. Eichelbaum provided a ready example of her endurance and perseverance. With the energy of someone decades younger, she prepared a lunch of homemade vegetable soup, turkey sandwiches and fresh fruit salad for herself and two visitors in her Knoxville apartment. She insisted on serving and clearing, as she says she does at the dinner parties she often throws for 20 or more guests.</p>
        <p>In describing her marathon quest to reach the pinnacle of higher education, Mrs. Eichelbaum said: ''It wasn't a case of maybe. I just waited for the opportunity and I'm finally finished.''</p>
        <p>Her son Marvin remembers an aphorism of his mother's that seems to have guided her life: ''If we ever complained that we could not get on a sports team, or get into a certain college, my mother would say, 'The only thing you can't do is live when it's time to die.' ''</p>
        <p>EMILY YELLIN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
