<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rutgers' Late Gamble Fails, Helping Penn State Move On</title>
    <meta content="28RUTG" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203219"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="COLLEGE BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Collegiate Athletic Assn</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pennsylvania State University</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Rutgers, the State University of New Jersey</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of North Carolina</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lilly, Brandon</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E7DE1F3DF93BA15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="501" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rutgers' Late Gamble Fails, Helping Penn State Move On</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRANDON LILLY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lilly, Brandon</byline>
      <dateline>LITTLE FALLS, N.J., May 27</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Penn State defeats Rutgers in National Collegiate Athletic Association baseball tournament and moves into subregional championship against North Carolina (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rutgers' Brian Ciemniecki was thrown out at home plate while trying to score the tying run from second base on a fly out to center field in the ninth inning, preserving Penn State's 6-5 victory tonight in the National Collegiate Athletic Association tournament subregional at Yogi Berra Stadium.</p>
        <p>The Nittany Lions got timely hitting and defense by center fielder Zack Smithlin and solid pitching from Dan Goebler to move into the subregional's championship round on Sunday against North Carolina.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Rutgers' Brian Ciemniecki was thrown out at home plate while trying to score the tying run from second base on a fly out to center field in the ninth inning, preserving Penn State's 6-5 victory tonight in the National Collegiate Athletic Association tournament subregional at Yogi Berra Stadium.</p>
        <p>The Nittany Lions got timely hitting and defense by center fielder Zack Smithlin and solid pitching from Dan Goebler to move into the subregional's championship round on Sunday against North Carolina.</p>
        <p>North Carolina won its first two games in the double-elimination subregional, including by 14-5 over Penn State on Friday. So if Penn State wins Sunday, the teams will play a second game to determine who advances.</p>
        <p>Rutgers (40-18) gambled in an attempt to tie the score in the ninth. With one out and Ciemniecki, a pinch-runner, on second, Joe B. Cirone hit a towering fly ball to deep center field. When Smithlin caught the ball running away from home plate, Ciemniecki tagged up and tried to score. Smithlin threw to second baseman Eric Spadt, whose relay to the plate was in time to nail Ciemniecki and secure the victory for Penn State (43-18) and oust Rutgers.</p>
        <p>''When he hit the ball, I thought it had a chance to leave the yard,'' Rutgers Coach Fred Hill said. Ciemniecki, he said, ''runs pretty well, so I thought we had a chance to make it; I'm not going to second-guess the call.''</p>
        <p>Goebler went six and two-thirds strong innings for the victory, while Smithlin's two-run single in the bottom of the seventh inning provided the margin of victory.</p>
        <p>The Tar Heels (46-15) reached the championship round by pounding Rutgers, 9-3, earlier in the day. Ryan Earey's two-out three-run home run off Buddy Gallagher in the seventh inning turned a 3-1 deficit into a 4-3 North Carolina lead.</p>
        <p>The shot to right helped the Tar Heels regain their confidence at the plate. After being held to one run and six hits over the first six innings, North Carolina exploded for 8 runs and 11 hits over the final three.</p>
        <p>''In these N.C.A.A. games, I've always thought that it's not how you start but how you finish,'' Tar Heels Coach Mike Fox said. ''We got a big swing of the bat from Ryan, and everything sort of fell into place from there.''</p>
        <p>With the score tied at 1-1 entering the bottom of the sixth, Rutgers scored twice on infield singles by Mike O'Brien and Leon Shade. Rutgers then loaded the bases with one out, but O'Brien was thrown out at the plate while trying to score on a shallow fly ball to center.</p>
        <p>In the first game of the day, Penn State's Pete Yodis pitched a complete game, giving up one run on six hits to eliminate Army, 3-1.</p>
        <p>COLLEGE BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
