<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BEHIND THE WHEEL/Chevrolet Tahoe and GMC Yukon; Big Enough for a Trek to Texas</title>
    <meta content="28AUTO$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203053"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">General Motors Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Chevrolet Division of General Motors Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Apcar, Leonard M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E5DD103DF93BA15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1167" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BEHIND THE WHEEL/Chevrolet Tahoe and GMC Yukon; Big Enough for a Trek to Texas</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LEONARD M. APCAR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Apcar, Leonard M</byline>
      <dateline>WICHITA FALLS, Tex.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Leonard M Apcar article on the newly redesigned Chevrolet Tahoe and GMC Yukon sport utility vehicles; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FIVE years ago, when General Motors ran its huge Suburban through a buzzsaw, cutting a 20-inch slice from its length, it created the Chevrolet Tahoe and the GMC Yukon: shorter, more manageable sport utilities with major V-8 power that could seat up to six people and practically tow a mountain.</p>
        <p>What the new utilities lacked was a third row of seats, like the one in the Suburban, and the bright lights at Ford and Dodge didn't let G.M. forget it. In a year, Ford brought out the Expedition, with three rows, and a year later Dodge crammed a third bench into its slightly smaller Durango.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FIVE years ago, when General Motors ran its huge Suburban through a buzzsaw, cutting a 20-inch slice from its length, it created the Chevrolet Tahoe and the GMC Yukon: shorter, more manageable sport utilities with major V-8 power that could seat up to six people and practically tow a mountain.</p>
        <p>What the new utilities lacked was a third row of seats, like the one in the Suburban, and the bright lights at Ford and Dodge didn't let G.M. forget it. In a year, Ford brought out the Expedition, with three rows, and a year later Dodge crammed a third bench into its slightly smaller Durango.</p>
        <p>Now the big news in this part of the market is that G.M. has not only put a third seat in its Tahoes and Yukons, but it split the third bench in half so that each part can fold neatly out of the way for carrying cargo.</p>
        <p>Big deal, you say? Well, the geniuses at Ford and Dodge didn't think of it, most minivans don't have it, and if you don't see the advantages of it, then you didn't just drive 1,300 miles around Texas on a family vacation with four, sometimes five, people, and six, sometimes eight, bags.</p>
        <p>I did so in a Tahoe and I would do it again. We folded up one of the far back seats and loaded three big pieces of luggage in its place. Then we stashed three smaller pieces behind the remaining seat, which my 11-year-old son used as his base camp. My 10-year-old daughter settled into her own perch in a window seat in the middle row, and my wife and I commandeered the front buckets.</p>
        <p>We picked up grandma and her two bags here for one segment (5 hours, 300 miles), and when the bags were unloaded we put the rear seat in its full, upright, locked position and comfortably carried seven people, including four adults, on a day trip.</p>
        <p>In these parts -- we made a loop from Dallas to Wichita Falls to Austin and San Antonio, then back to Dallas -- full-sized sport utilities are about as common as taxicabs in Manhattan. The neatly packed dark-gray Tahoe caught the attention of several bystanders in parking lots and at filling stations. (It did tend to guzzle gas.) The onlookers marveled at the convenience of the back seat and at how much we had stuffed around it. They also gulped at the sticker, which exceeded $41,000, including $760 for the optional third seat, on the well-equipped test truck.</p>
        <p>The full-sized sport utility market just keeps growing. Never mind these vehicles' voracious appetite -- I averaged about 14.8 miles per gallon over all, in both city and highway driving -- and their less than pristine record on emissions. People like them because they increasingly seem like minivans on the inside while looking downright unstoppable on the outside.</p>
        <p>The interiors of the Tahoe and the Yukon have both grown more comfortable. The top-of-the-line LT and SLT, respectively, have all the usual power this and leather that. An Autoride feature, standard on the Yukon and optional on the Tahoe, automatically adjusts the ride with the load. Cup holders abound and air-conditioning, available with separate controls for the rear passengers, includes vents in the ceiling. Outside a Dairy Queen in Salado, with the thermometer display on the rear-view mirror registering 102 degrees outside, nobody in the back complained that they lacked cool air.</p>
        <p>The trick to making the third seat convenient is making it easy to get to. The Durango's middle seats are split in a 40-20-40 proportion; the outer portions fold out of the way to allow access from either side.</p>
        <p>Ford and G.M. use an 80-20 configuration that allows entry only from the right. The G.M. seat easily lifts and folds better than that of the Expedition, which requires tilting a heavy seat out of the way. I also thought the Expedition's passageway was tight.</p>
        <p>Look for the seating competition to heat up, too, when Ford adds a third row to its next-generation Explorer and Toyota brings out its full-sized Sequoia in November. That truck's second and third seats are ingenuously designed for easy tilting and removal, and caused a stir among executives from competing companies when the Sequoia was shown at the Detroit auto show in January.</p>
        <p>Once you're in the back 40 of the Tahoe, though, the seat is not exactly a box at the Met. Ford and Chevy both angle the seatback to allow greater headroom. This can be disconcerting at first. (Dodge raised the Durango's rear roofline.) And all three manufacturers have seating for three people including two positions with shoulder straps. They have also raised the seat up a bit to give greater visibility. G.M. has two adjustable headrests back there; the Durango has two fixed ones and the Expedition has none. Only the Expedition can be ordered with rear windows that pop out to serve as vents.</p>
        <p>Adults would not want to sit in the rear for long. My son, who is just over 5 feet tall, thought it was great. But he also kept the seat in front of him folded down to stretch out on long drives.</p>
        <p>The redesigned Tahoe and Yukon, which are virtually identical under the skin, use essentially the same new frame that underpins the redesigned Suburban, the GMC Yukon XL (formerly known as the GMC Suburban) and the full-size G.M. pickups. By virtue of its fewer welds and stress points, the ride is quieter, smoother and more carlike.</p>
        <p>Over all, the Tahoe is also easier to drive, partly because the entire feel of the truck is softer and more welcoming. The turning radius is considerably smaller, making it easier to maneuver in parking lots.</p>
        <p>Gripes were few. I don't like the power seat adjustments on the sides of the seat. Also, the ceiling light in the rear hardly illuminated the cargo area. Dodge smartly puts its lamp in the hatchback and lights the entire loading area. The G.M. hatch, though, is made mostly of aluminum, so it is light and easy to shut.</p>
        <p>The quality of G.M.'s trim and finish still gives me pause. During our trip, one air vent fell out of the ceiling when one of our children fiddled with it; the louvers on another came apart, and a piece of seat trim repeatedly fell off. Both the Tahoe and a Yukon test truck had occasional squeaks from the padding around the steering column.</p>
        <p>All in all, though, these were modest flaws in a couple of much-improved family trucks.</p>
        <p>INSIDE TRACK: G.M. plays catch-up in the seat-stuffing contests.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
