<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Kramden's Fire Escape and Washington's Tea Set</title>
    <meta content="28SHEL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Books; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203027"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEW YORK BOOKSHELF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Freeman, Joshua B</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tchen, John Kuo Wei</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cudahy, Brian</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Working-Class New York (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">New York Before Chinatown (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Malbone Street Wreck (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03E7D7133DF93BA15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="824" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Kramden's Fire Escape and Washington's Tea Set</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Excerpts from Joshua B Freeman book Working-Class New York, John Kuo Wei Tchen's New York Before Chinatown and Brian Cudahy's The Malbone Street Wreck (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THREE recent works of history, in these excerpts, provide vivid glimpses of a bygone New York: the 1950's Brooklyn of ''The Honeymooners,'' the Revolutionary War household of George Washington and a disastrous subway wreck of 1918.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THREE recent works of history, in these excerpts, provide vivid glimpses of a bygone New York: the 1950's Brooklyn of ''The Honeymooners,'' the Revolutionary War household of George Washington and a disastrous subway wreck of 1918.</p>
        <p>WORKING-CLASS NEW YORK  By Joshua B. Freeman  The New Press  (Hardcover, $35)</p>
        <p>From the 1920's through the 1970's, in literature, scholarship and reportage about work and industrial relations, automobile workers often were held forth as the archetypical proletarians. . . . But in the realm of workers' culture and home life -- workers away from work -- the national media were more likely to portray a New Yorker, and typically not a factory worker, than an auto worker from Detroit or Cleveland.</p>
        <p>Probably the best-known working-class families of the 1950's were the fictional Kramdens and Nortons of Bensonhurst, Brooklyn, whose domestic doings and comic misadventures kept ''The Honeymooners'' near the top of the television ratings for eight years. Jackie Gleason's Ralph Kramden drove a bus on Madison Avenue, while Art Carney's Ed Norton was a sewer worker, occupations that had little to do with the heroic image of the proletarian so popular among leftists and liberals.</p>
        <p>The Kramdens and Nortons were everymen, whose struggle for dignity and to keep their heads above water (in Ed's case literally) had universal meaning. Because New York was an entertainment and literary center, it was natural that New York workers were used as representatives of the common man. Yet in some respects the Kramdens and Nortons were distinctly New Yorkers. Where else did neighbors visit one another via the fire escape?</p>
        <p>In the metaphorical device used to project the pluralist vision of the nation which came to the fore during the 1940's, the small group of diverse characters forced to work together for their mutual survival (the platoon or the survivors of a shipwreck), the working-class New Yorker (usually a Brooklynite) was one of the stock characters, along with the Appalachian, the upper-class WASP, and the Midwestern farm boy. Who could forget William Bendix dying in ''Lifeboat' (1944), with his last, delirious thoughts of the Brooklyn Dodgers and dancing at Roseland? In images of mid-century America, working-class New Yorkers were portrayed as their own ethnic group, full of idiosyncrasies that set them off from the rest of America.</p>
        <p>NEW YORK BEFORE CHINATOWN  By John Kuo Wei Tchen  Johns Hopkins University Press  (Hardcover, $42.50)</p>
        <p>General George Washington made plans for New York City's defense. At the same time, under Washington's customarily close personal supervision, his New York City housekeeper, Mrs. Mary Smith, proceeded to furnish his New York home. Carefully kept accounts and receipts reveal the purchase of mahogany knife cases, a carpet, a damask tablecloth, a feather bed, pillows, a tureen, eight porcelain mugs, two dozen plates and other miscellany.</p>
        <p>Pro-British Burling Slip merchants Frederick and Philip Rhinelander supplied numerous imported creamware dishes, sauceboats, plates, and fluted bowls, including three, more costly, ''china'' bowls. And the Bayard Street retailer George Ball sold ''burnt china cups &amp; saucers'' and other tea service items to the household. During this time the general and Mrs. Washington kept up ''a high level of comfort in dining and furnishings, maintaining a ''tolerably genteel'' table.</p>
        <p>By September, major miscalculations had forced Washington's inexperienced troops to retreat. At great expense and trouble, the general's household was packed up and re-established at the Morris-Jumel Mansion in Harlem Heights.</p>
        <p>What explains this desire for luxury in the midst of war? It would be easy to ridicule General Washington's extraordinary attention to material wants at this moment of hardship. This enigmatic anecdote, however, offers fresh insights into this founding generation's efforts to formulate a cultural identity. While these details may appear trivial . . .  they pose a question fundamental to this study:</p>
        <p>Why were tea, porcelains, and other representations of China so desired by the founding fathers?</p>
        <p>THE MALBONE STREET WRECK  By Brian Cudahy  Fordham University Press  (Paperback, $19.95)</p>
        <p>Although the first fire alarm calling rescue forces to the site of the Malbone Street Wreck was rung into the fire department's headquarters on Jay Street . . . at 6:44 P.M., two minutes after the accident, it was almost half-past seven before reasonable numbers of properly equipped personnel were on the scene.</p>
        <p>The disaster took place in the very middle of one of the busiest intersections in all of Brooklyn -- the spot near the Willink Entrance to Prospect Park where Malbone Street, Ocean Avenue and Flatbush Avenue all intersect -- but the wrecked train and its passengers were wedged in a narrow tunnel under the intersection and were not in a readily accessible location. Responding companies from the New York Fire Department who performed the bulk of the rescue work that evening were faced with a disaster that was as much a cave-in as a train wreck.</p>
        <p>NEW YORK BOOKSHELF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
