<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Again, Camby's Knee Can't Keep Up</title>
    <meta content="Y28BAS$09" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203172"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Indiana Pacers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Popper, Steve</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Camby, Marcus</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Indiana Pacers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E0D91E3DF93BA15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="869" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Again, Camby's Knee Can't Keep Up</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVE POPPER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Popper, Steve</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Knickerbockers Marcus Camby injures knee in game 3 of Eastern Conference Finals against Indiana Pacers; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Marcus Camby was only trying to do what he thought was necessary. Early in the second quarter of yesterday's Game 3, he needed to make something happen, even if he knew that his body was not quite up to the task. His right knee was already hurting and his right elbow was sore, too, when he took the ball on the right side of the lane.</p>
        <p>The 6-foot-11-inch Knick started to drive toward the basket with Indiana's Austin Croshere on his hip, and as he reached the baseline, he tried to stop short. But his right foot slid out from under him and his right knee buckled awkwardly as he almost did a split on the Madison Square Garden court. He then laid on the floor, writhing in pain and reaching for his knee. Croshere tried to grab the ball away while a referee called Camby for traveling, and Camby did not even notice.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Marcus Camby was only trying to do what he thought was necessary. Early in the second quarter of yesterday's Game 3, he needed to make something happen, even if he knew that his body was not quite up to the task. His right knee was already hurting and his right elbow was sore, too, when he took the ball on the right side of the lane.</p>
        <p>The 6-foot-11-inch Knick started to drive toward the basket with Indiana's Austin Croshere on his hip, and as he reached the baseline, he tried to stop short. But his right foot slid out from under him and his right knee buckled awkwardly as he almost did a split on the Madison Square Garden court. He then laid on the floor, writhing in pain and reaching for his knee. Croshere tried to grab the ball away while a referee called Camby for traveling, and Camby did not even notice.</p>
        <p>He already knew that his knee was injured as his face pushed toward the floor. He remained there, with 8 minutes 49 seconds remaining in the first half, until his teammate John Wallace and the Knicks trainer, Mike Saunders, helped him to the locker room moments later, bracing him on their shoulders. The next time Camby would leave the Knicks locker room was in a wheelchair, with a towel draped over his head, as he was driven to Beth Israel Hospital, missing the rest of the Knicks' 98-95 victory over the Pacers that cut their deficit in the Eastern Conference final series to two games to one.</p>
        <p>Camby has a sprained medial capsule in his right knee. A magnetic resonance imaging test revealed there was no ligament damage, and Camby is day to day. Camby had strained his anterior cruciate ligament on Feb. 6 and was sidelined for 17 games. He then missed the final week of the season with a sprained capsule of the right knee.</p>
        <p>Even before Camby had started his drive down the lane yesterday, he had struggled through the postseason, fighting to perform the aerial acrobatics that he had soared through in last season's playoffs. He would talk about his minutes this season and how he had just not gotten enough. He spoke of how the opponents key on him now, as if they were leaving Latrell Sprewell and Allan Houston alone to form a wall between Camby and his path toward an offensive rebound.</p>
        <p>And if you stayed long enough and listened as he calmly explained, he would tell you the truth, the words that he did not really want to say.  ''I'm not as well as last year,'' Camby said after Friday's practice. ''My explosiveness, my jumping ability is not there evidently, or I'd have been dunking a lot of those shots I've been missing.''</p>
        <p>While he spoke, his right knee, bothering him even before yesterday's fall, had ice strapped to it. He showed off the bruises on his right elbow. Camby, who was gliding over and around the opposition in the postseason a year ago, has been grounded by an accumulation of injuries. The athleticism that changed the Knicks' fortunes last season, as well as the Indiana Pacers' roster in response, was just not there.</p>
        <p>After practice on Friday, the Knicks assistant coach Brendan Malone prodded him to finish strong, a message that Coach Jeff Van Gundy also tried to instill in Camby. ''It's easier said than done,'' Camby said. ''Brendan, that's my guy, like my favorite uncle. He's always in my ear, wants me to do my best and he talks to me every day about that stuff.''</p>
        <p>Even before this injury and regardless of the final diagnosis,  Camby was not performing as well as he had in last season's playoffs. Last season, Camby averaged 5.5 points and 8.5 rebounds in the first two games of the Eastern Conference finals against Indiana. Then, with Patrick Ewing out of the lineup, Camby scored 21 points and grabbed 11 rebounds in 33 minutes in Game 3 and went on to average 18.8 points and 11.8 rebounds over the final four games of the series.</p>
        <p>This season, he averaged 5.0 points and 9.5 rebounds in the first two games, a performance similar to the troubles he has endured throughout this postseason. After sitting out the final week of the regular season with his knee ailing, Camby has averaged 5.5 points on just 34.3 percent shooting in the playoffs.</p>
        <p>It is not just the physical condition, though, that causes these doubts. After scoring 20 or more points three times in the nine games the Knicks played without Ewing in the playoffs last year, Camby repeated that feat just 5 times in 59 regular-season games this year and had not scored more than 11 in these playoffs.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
