<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cup in Sight, Devils Savor Tough Victory</title>
    <meta content="28DEVI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203156"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Jersey Devils</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Philadelphia Flyers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Dallas Stars</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yannis, Alex</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Dallas Stars</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New Jersey Devils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Philadelphia Flyers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E1DB1E3DF93BA15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="805" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cup in Sight, Devils Savor Tough Victory</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEX YANNIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Yannis, Alex</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New Jersey Devils, having won semifinal series against Philadelphia Flyers, look ahead to Stanley Cup finals against Dallas Stars, defending Stanley Cup champion (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Now that they have overcome a seemingly insurmountable obstacle by rallying from two games down in the semifinals, an achievement unmatched by any team in the Stanley Cup playoffs since expansion in 1967, the Devils are taking aim at hockey's ultimate prize.</p>
        <p>The Devils seem to have everything in place going into the Stanley Cup finals. They have a coach who has his finger on the pulse of his team, a goaltender who has raised his play to the highest level at the right time, a captain who has been the dominant player in the first three rounds of the playoffs and a first-line threesome that has been no match for anyone.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Now that they have overcome a seemingly insurmountable obstacle by rallying from two games down in the semifinals, an achievement unmatched by any team in the Stanley Cup playoffs since expansion in 1967, the Devils are taking aim at hockey's ultimate prize.</p>
        <p>The Devils seem to have everything in place going into the Stanley Cup finals. They have a coach who has his finger on the pulse of his team, a goaltender who has raised his play to the highest level at the right time, a captain who has been the dominant player in the first three rounds of the playoffs and a first-line threesome that has been no match for anyone.</p>
        <p>All these ingredients converged to help the Devils rally from a three-games-to-one deficit and eliminate the Flyers in the Eastern Conference finals Friday night in Philadelphia with a 2-1 triumph in Game 7. This game of a physical series also may have marked the end of Eric Lindros's career.</p>
        <p>By eliminating the Flyers, the Devils have reached the Stanley Cup finals for the second time. In 1995, with Jacques Lemaire at the helm and Larry Robinson as his assistant, the Devils swept the favored Detroit Red Wings in a memorable series.</p>
        <p>Unlike 1995, when they opened the finals on the road, this time the Devils will play host to the first two cup games, starting Tuesday night. And this time, Robinson, who replaced Robbie Ftorek with eight games left in the regular season, is the head coach.</p>
        <p>The Devils will face Dallas, the defending Stanley Cup champion. The Stars, who defeated Colorado by 3-2 last night in Game 7 of the Western Conference finals, defeated the Devils in their two regular-season games.</p>
        <p>Savoring their remarkable comeback against the Flyers, the Devils had no interest in talking about next week's opponent.</p>
        <p>They politely said before the other series concluded that it didn't matter whether they faced the Stars or the Avalanche because, in the words of Bobby Holik, ''either team is a great team.'' The Devils were given the day off yesterday and will practice this afternoon.</p>
        <p>Western Conference teams have captured the Stanley Cup every year since the Devils won it in 1995. As they were against the Red Wings then, the Devils must again be considered the underdogs.</p>
        <p>But now the Devils have Robinson. His tirade after the Devils fell behind by 3-1 in the series with the Flyers was so perfectly timed that it drew the admiration of his players as well as outsiders. The Devils gave Robinson the bulk of the credit for their comeback.</p>
        <p>''He did it from the heart,'' was the phrase almost a dozen players used about Robinson's fusillade after the third consecutive loss put the team on the verge of elimination. Robinson's reaction to his inspirational ploy was almost a shrug. ''Sometimes it works and sometimes it doesn't,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Needless to say, this time it worked to perfection because it obviously touched a chord in the hearts of the Devils.</p>
        <p>They responded to a man. Scott Stevens's dominance of the opposition's top players in each of the three rounds, starting with Florida's Pavel Bure and Toronto's Mats Sundin, culminated with his crunching check on Lindros that took the heart out of the Flyers on Friday night. Lindros, whose head crashed violently against the ice, sustained his third concussion this season and his fifth in the past two years. He spent Saturday night in a hospital before going home.</p>
        <p>Martin Brodeur's brilliant saves in a second period dominated by the Flyers on Friday night gave the Devils the chance they needed going into the third.</p>
        <p>''Marty gave us a chance to win in the third period,'' said Patrik Elias, who scored the winning goal with 2 minutes 32 seconds left in the game.</p>
        <p>Elias also scored the first goal, and both scores came on passes from Jason Arnott, who has combined with Elias and Petr Sykora to form the team's top line. The threesome combined for eight goals in the series, four by Elias and two each by Arnott and Sykora, and was a constant threat to the Flyers. Philadelphia simply failed to come up with a solution for the combination.</p>
        <p>''Someone had to come through for us and Patty was the one,'' Sykora said of Elias's winning goal. ''It's unbelievable how satisfying it is to come back like that and go to the finals.''</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
