<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Opposition Rally in Belgrade Draws Relatively Low Turnout</title>
    <meta content="28SERB" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203158"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Serbia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Belgrade (Serbia)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Erlanger, Steven</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Milosevic, Slobodan (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Draskovic, Vuk</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Serbia/Belgrade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE0DB1E3DF93BA15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="932" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Opposition Rally in Belgrade Draws Relatively Low Turnout</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN ERLANGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Erlanger, Steven</byline>
      <dateline>BELGRADE, Serbia, May 27</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Only 10,000 people show up for anti-government rally in Belgrade; relatively low turnout reflects popular disappointment with leaders of political opposition; Vuk Draskovic, head of main opposition party, delivers wandering speech; he calls for early democratic elections but he is seemingly unable to articulate clear strategy to alleviate Serbs' feeling of despair and helplessness in face of power of Pres Slobodan Milosevic; opposition officials say they will concentrate more on meetings and retail politics in countryside, where feelings run higher than in Belgrade; opposition politicians are criticized for their disunity and squabbling (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Some 10,000 people showed up today for an anti-government rally, a relatively low turnout reflecting popular disappointment with the leaders of the political opposition here.</p>
        <p>They heard Vuk Draskovic, the head of the main opposition party, the Serbian Renewal Movement, describe a city and a country ''paralyzed by fear, despair and a feeling of helplessness'' in the face of the power of President Slobodan Milosevic of Yugoslavia.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Some 10,000 people showed up today for an anti-government rally, a relatively low turnout reflecting popular disappointment with the leaders of the political opposition here.</p>
        <p>They heard Vuk Draskovic, the head of the main opposition party, the Serbian Renewal Movement, describe a city and a country ''paralyzed by fear, despair and a feeling of helplessness'' in the face of the power of President Slobodan Milosevic of Yugoslavia.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Draskovic, in a wandering speech, seemed unable to articulate a clear strategy to alleviate that paralysis, other than a united push for early democratic elections.</p>
        <p>Zoran Djindjic, head of the Democracy Party, the main element of the Alliance for Change coalition, preached unity, patience and collective self-defense. ''We can't checkmate Milosevic in one move,'' he said. ''We have to pressure him, surround him and drain out his political life drop by drop.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Milosevic ''is most afraid of three million people who will come to the polling station and say, 'We don't want you,'' Mr. Djindjic said.</p>
        <p>Unlike previous rallies, this one heard only three opposition leaders speak -- not all 16 -- and there were more speakers from other parts of Serbian society, including academics, women's activists and the spreading student movement, Otpor, or Resistance.</p>
        <p>The idea, said Zarko Korac, a political leader in the alliance, is to present a wider social front of solidarity against the government.</p>
        <p>''The opposition right now is not capable of making a very consistent, clear program,'' Mr. Korac said.  ''It's not just that the big parties are not up to the situation, but what you need is a wider front to confront the dictatorship.''</p>
        <p>Ognjen Pribicevic, a Draskovic adviser, said: ''We are doing what we can at the moment. And we are more united than you think, especially the big parties.''</p>
        <p>Officials said the opposition would concentrate more on meetings and retail politics in the countryside, where feelings run higher than in Belgrade.</p>
        <p>But an Otpor speaker named Nemanja, from Krusevac, criticized the politicians for disunity and squabbling. ''For seven days, dear leaders,'' he said, ''you were wasting time on useless meetings.'' He said Otpor had drawn up a plan for hunger strikes, then tried to give it to Mr. Draskovic, who kept his hands to his side. Mr. Djindjic finally took it.</p>
        <p>With declining numbers -- a rally in mid-April drew more than 100,000 people, but one on May 15 drew only about 25,000 -- this rally is likely to be the last of its kind for now.</p>
        <p>It followed a dispiriting 10 days for the political opposition here.</p>
        <p>On May 17, the Serbian government seized control of the Belgrade television station Studio B, controlled by Mr. Draskovic's party. But fearing a wider crackdown on all opposition-run cities and independent media, Mr. Draskovic urged other opposition leaders not to attempt outright confrontation with the government, bringing accusations that he was capitulating without a struggle.</p>
        <p>Otpor in particular has been urging a program of civil disobedience, but at the same time, nightly rallies here for Studio B have shrunk to fewer than 500 people. To blunt Otpor, the government closed universities a week early, allowing students to enter only for final exams.</p>
        <p>At a rally of 3,000 people in the southern city of Nis Friday night, Goran Svilanovic, head of the Civic Alliance, said his opposition colleagues were not rising to the new challenge by the government. ''If we do not resist now, they will come into our houses, burn them and chase us away,'' Mr. Svilanovic said, referring to Serbian tactics against Albanians in Kosovo.</p>
        <p>The opposition has wide support in Serbia as the only alternative to Mr. Milosevic, but polls indicate that the support can be shaky and is not growing. A poll just done for the National Democratic Institute shows the Alliance for Change in early May -- before the seizure of Studio B -- recovering some of the support it had lost earlier in the year.</p>
        <p>Still, the alliance plus Mr. Draskovic's party get about 46 percent of the vote, with the ruling coalition getting about 30, with 18 percent still undecided and 7 percent saying they will not vote, with a margin of error of 2.9 percent. The problem with all polls here is that they underestimate support for the Radical Party of Vojislav Seselj, part of the ruling coalition, whose voters are more suspicious of pollsters.</p>
        <p>But the number of undecided indicates deep uncertainty about the credibility of the opposition, since 63 percent of those polled say they are unfavorable toward Mr. Milosevic and some 70 percent say ''it's time for someone new.''</p>
        <p>Still, 38 percent say Mr. Milosevic ''may not be perfect, but he's better than the opposition,'' and he remains the only single leader whose ratings are larger than the ''don't knows.''</p>
        <p>More than 80 percent of those polled say opposition leaders spend so much time ''fighting among themselves that they don't accomplish as much as they should.''</p>
        <p>Separately, in yet another court case by an official against the independent media, the newspaper Danas and its editor were fined 570,000 dinars (about $14,300 at the unofficial rate of exchange) for printing a letter from a law school professor to his dean accusing Mr. Seselj of plagarizing Lenin. It was the seventh such case Danas has lost.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
