<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The World; Yes, Trade Brings Freedom. Except When It Doesn't.</title>
    <meta content="28SANG$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203095"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Taiwan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">South Korea</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Malaysia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Singapore</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sanger, David E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Malaysia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Taiwan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/South Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Singapore</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E0DA113DF93BA15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1182" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The World; Yes, Trade Brings Freedom. Except When It Doesn't.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID E. SANGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sanger, David E</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Most members of Congress who voted 'yes' on China trade bill say they believe Pres Clinton's oft-repeated assertion that enmeshing Chinese people in Western markets, legal systems and technology will tempt them to cast off one-party rule of Communists; there has been clear--if sometimes tenuous--connection between growth of market capitalism and growth of some kind of democratic institutions in Taiwan and South Korea; in Singapore and Malaysia, free enterprise has been embraced while strict one-party control has been maintained; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE arguments that finally persuaded wavering members of Congress to grant China permanent trade status last week had very little to do with tariffs or even whether China's state-run industries would finally allow American farmers to deliver beef and wheat directly to the world's largest market.</p>
        <p>Instead, it came down to one of the biggest bets in geopolitics: Most of the members of Congress who voted  ''yes'' said they believed President Clinton's oft-repeated assertion that the faster the Chinese people are enmeshed in Western markets, legal systems and technology, the faster they will be tempted to cast off the one-party rule of the Communists.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE arguments that finally persuaded wavering members of Congress to grant China permanent trade status last week had very little to do with tariffs or even whether China's state-run industries would finally allow American farmers to deliver beef and wheat directly to the world's largest market.</p>
        <p>Instead, it came down to one of the biggest bets in geopolitics: Most of the members of Congress who voted  ''yes'' said they believed President Clinton's oft-repeated assertion that the faster the Chinese people are enmeshed in Western markets, legal systems and technology, the faster they will be tempted to cast off the one-party rule of the Communists.</p>
        <p>''When over 100 million people in China can get on the Net,'' Mr. Clinton argued in a commencement speech days before the vote, which he won by a surprisingly wide margin of 237 to 197, ''it will be impossible to maintain a closed political and economic society.''</p>
        <p>Really? Who knows. Mr. Clinton may be well into a second career as an investment banker or a third one as a movie producer before anyone has the foggiest sense of whether last week's decision to end the annual Congressional review of China's trading rights, and usher the country into the World Trade Organization, has any real effect on political freedom in China.</p>
        <p>Yet recent history suggests it is not an entirely wild gamble. Look around the rest of Asia, where there is a clear -- if sometimes tenuous -- connection between the growth of market capitalism and the growth of some kind of democratic institutions.</p>
        <p>Taiwan and South Korea are the success stories that everyone points to, places where the arrival of high technology, commercial legal systems and a gradual opening of the market was followed by an end to autocratic rule. But economists and political theorists have spent years arguing over the precise connections between freer markets and freer political systems and -- no surprise -- they can't agree on much.</p>
        <p>And for every success story there are exceptions like Singapore and Malaysia, which have managed to embrace free enterprise while maintaining strict one-party control. Or Russia, where political liberty has preceded the introduction of a real market economy. But there are a few common themes:</p>
        <p>Free markets don't equal freedom. But they make it a lot harder for the government -- or corrupt bureaucrats -- to rule over everyday choices.</p>
        <p>Before China began to embrace market principles, a Communist Party official would get up at 5 a.m. in cities like Shanghai, go to the market and decide who got what. As in the old Soviet Union, the system worked for a while -- goods and services got produced, and people didn't starve. Usually. In short, the apparatchik played the role that pricing plays today, allocating scarce resources. And since handing out goodies was the local official's main source of power -- to say nothing of an opportunity to have his pockets stuffed with bribes -- the arrival of a market economy means the diminution of the party's arbitrary power. Entry into the W.T.O. promises to reinforce this process. ''The arrival of foreign competition means the local party officials will lose their control over what the big factory in town produces, or even how many people it employs,'' says Nicholas Lardy, a China expert at the Brookings Institution. Chang Lin Tien, the former chancellor of the University of California at Berkeley, just returned to Taiwan a week ago to witness the swearing in of the new president, and he says it got him thinking about what prompted the change from the martial law of his youth to the election of the opposition leader, Chen Shui-bian, earlier this year. ''We had some ruthless leaders,'' he said, ''but as the economy came up, and Taiwan became part of the global market, it ended up giving more and more influence to the local Taiwanese and less to the party. State-owned enterprises just couldn't compete.''</p>
        <p>A rising middle class first demands a decent apartment, then a car, and sooner or later a vote.</p>
        <p>Well, sometimes. In South Korea, American efforts to push a series of authoritarian leaders toward greater freedom failed before the country's workers began making decent wages. ''When I think about our first efforts to convince South Korean leaders to liberalize, well, we saved the life of Kim Dae Jung,'' said William H. Gleysteen Jr., the former American ambassador to Seoul, referring to the onetime dissident who is now president. ''But a lot of the other efforts didn't amount to much. Then people started to buy cars, to travel, and to demand a bit more political space. They became less compliant with the government.'' By 1987 the movement had become unstoppable.</p>
        <p>The I.M.F. may be much reviled, but sometimes it aids and abets a democratic coup.</p>
        <p>Suharto did not found the Indonesian state, but he ruled over it for 35 years. For years the Central Intelligence Agency speculated how his regime would end -- heart attack, coup, assassination. ''We forgot about economic chaos,'' says one of the agency's old Asia hands. Once the Asian economic crisis began, the International Monetary Fund began demanding changes -- including the dismemberment of Suharto's family enterprises, which were skewing the government's budgets. And that unleashed political forces that Suharto couldn't withstand. The I.M.F. made a lot of mistakes, and the Indonesian bailout was not intended to oust Suharto. In retrospect, though, the world got a more open Indonesia and one less authoritarian ruler. ''Of course there was no plan,'' says Jeffrey E. Garten, a former senior official in the Commerce Department. ''But from the beginning of the Clinton administration there was a sense that economic liberalization and political liberalization would somehow go together. Of course, no one envisioned how this dangerous cocktail would come together.''</p>
        <p>The Internet will change this. But no one knows how.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton is probably right that the Chinese will never be able to control discourse on the Internet (which doesn't stop them from trying). And while it may be a force for democracy, it may also prove a spur for anti-market, anti-American feelings. No sooner had the House passed the trade bill last week than Chinese scholars like Han Deqiang were on the Web preaching the dangers. Mr. Han told China Online, an electronic newsletter for executives, that through the W.T.O. ''American economic hegemony could easily control China.'' Oh, and he added: ''There are 133 W.T.O. members. Look at some of the African countries, the corruption there is much worse than in China.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
