<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Leader Back in Lineup, All Is Right With Yanks</title>
    <meta content="28BATS$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203190"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Curry, Jack</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jeter, Derek</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E0D61E3DF93BA15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="984" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Leader Back in Lineup, All Is Right With Yanks</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jack Curry</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Curry, Jack</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses return of Derek Jeter from disabled list to rejoin New York Yankees; focuses on Jeter's role with team as leader; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Yankees always assemble in foul territory in front of the first base dugout to do stretching exercises before games. It is a monotonous routine that usually goes unnoticed because it is so mundane. But, there was reason to watch the Yankees bend and stretch yesterday because it was the first time in over a week that Derek Jeter was part of it. The Yankees were complete again.</p>
        <p>Jeter's impact on the Yankees was realized before they even played the Red Sox yesterday as his teammates behaved like a gang of 12-year-olds while treating him like the kid who had been away for summer vacation. There were so many voices talking at Jeter simultaneously that it sounded like recess at an elementary school.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Yankees always assemble in foul territory in front of the first base dugout to do stretching exercises before games. It is a monotonous routine that usually goes unnoticed because it is so mundane. But, there was reason to watch the Yankees bend and stretch yesterday because it was the first time in over a week that Derek Jeter was part of it. The Yankees were complete again.</p>
        <p>Jeter's impact on the Yankees was realized before they even played the Red Sox yesterday as his teammates behaved like a gang of 12-year-olds while treating him like the kid who had been away for summer vacation. There were so many voices talking at Jeter simultaneously that it sounded like recess at an elementary school.</p>
        <p>Jorge Posada had to tell him about the 24-year-old man who had tumbled out of the upper deck and onto the protective screen behind home plate on Friday night. Tino Martinez added his version of the odd incident and Chuck Knoblauch pointed to a sagging portion of the screen to show Jeter where the fan had landed. Jeter responded with animated expressions, knowing he was one of them again.</p>
        <p>''I'm ready to go,'' Jeter said. ''That's all you'll hear from me.''</p>
        <p>That is all the Yankees wanted to hear and all they needed to see. The Yankees were an inferior team without Jeter because they missed the jolt he provides from the second spot in the batting order, the steadiness he provides from shortstop and the leadership he provides by being himself. When Joe Torre first saw Jeter yesterday, he said ''Hi, son'' and exhaled. Yankee fans should do the same now that Jeter's strained abdominal muscle has healed.</p>
        <p>Soon, very soon, Jeter's imprint was all over a game the Yankees rallied from a 3-0 deficit to win, 8-3. Jeter emerged from a 0-for-14 slump with three singles, he scored a run, he knocked in a run and he also stole a base. It was a 4-3 game when Jeter stroked a two-out, run-scoring single off John Wasdin in the sixth. Paul O'Neill followed Jeter with a three-run homer. Game over.</p>
        <p>Jeter was only at the Stadium because of his own dedication. He rented a private jet to insure that he could be flown from Tampa, Fla., to New York after a rehabilitation game and be prepared to start in the second game of the series. The Yankees were content to have Jeter fly commercially yesterday and then play tonight. But Jeter offered to rent the seven-seat plane that he uses throughout the off-season and the Yankees agreed that it was a logical decision.</p>
        <p>''They didn't pay for it,'' Jeter said, joking. ''Write that. I'm going to talk to them.''</p>
        <p>Coincidentally, Boston's Nomar Garciaparra -- who had been on the disabled list with a strained hamstring -- and Jeter, the fabulous shortstops who will be compared and contrasted for the next decade, were both activated yesterday.</p>
        <p>''Is he coming back? Really?'' Jeter said. ''Good for him.''</p>
        <p>Good for Garciaparra and Jeter means good for the Red Sox and the Yankees. Torre quickly inserted Jeter into the second spot in the batting order and hoped that Jeter's presence would help the Yankees return to some normalcy. It did. He was on base in three of the first four innings and looked refreshed.</p>
        <p>The Yankees were 4-9 from the time Jeter left a game on May 11 and they had one run batted in from the shortstop position in the month. Although Torre cautioned against expecting the Yankees to win 10 straight games because Jeter is back, the manager added, ''Jeter, in the every day scheme of things, is a tough guy to lose.''</p>
        <p>Jeter might be the toughest Yankee to lose. Mariano Rivera might be the best closer in baseball and Bernie Williams is a switch-hitting dynamo in the middle of the lineup. But Jeter produces more on offense and defense every day and gives the Yankees a spark whether he is ripping a single to right field or tweaking Posada about an awful haircut. Without Jeter, the Yankees lose a huge part of their swagger, their identity.</p>
        <p>''It feels good because everybody is used to seeing him out there,'' Torre said. ''He's got a confident personality and he loves competition.''</p>
        <p>Jeter admitted that he was nervous when he tested his abdominal muscle while playing for Class A Tampa on Friday night, but the fears vanished after he roped two hits in three at bats and felt no more pain. He only watched two games while he was disabled because his cable system could not get some of the games. Still, Jeter needs to compete and watching is torturous, even though he claimed to watch while wearing his uniform and swinging a bat.</p>
        <p>While Jeter was joking about the uniform, he was not joking about the bat. He usually has a bat beside the white stuffed chair in his living room while he watches television. Jeter grabs the bat often, gripping it and reminding himself how fortunate he is to be playing baseball. That reminder was vivid while Jeter was injured, to him and especially to the Yankees.</p>
        <p>''It's a situation where you do realize how much you miss playing,'' Jeter said. ''There's no substitute for playing. It put things in perspective. It tells you that you can't take the games for granted.''</p>
        <p>ON BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
