<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>POP AND JAZZ GUIDE</title>
    <meta content="07POP" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212972"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000707T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E7DB1F39F934A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="4676" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>POP AND JAZZ GUIDE</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Here is a selective listing by critics of The Times of new or noteworthy pop and jazz concerts in the New York metropolitan region this weekend. * denotes a highly recommended concert.</p>
        <p>STEVEN BERNSTEIN'S MILLENNIAL TERRITORY ORCHESTRA, Tonic, 107 Norfolk Street, Lower East Side, (212) 358-7501. The fearless slide-trumpeter has copious, nonpartisan enthusiasms (he digs everything from cha-cha-cha to Prince to Fathead Newman to rock 'n' roll to Wynton Marsalis) that make his performances energetic and cheerful. He has been doing what all smart bandleaders have been doing lately: expanding. Every six months, it seems, there's a new Steven Bernstein band; this latest one includes the violinist Charles Burnham, a three-man reed section, the bassist Ben Allison and the banjoist Doug Wamble. It will skip between eras and styles, probably making a case at one point or another for music that you haven't thought about much. Tonight at midnight; admission is $6 (Ben Ratliff).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Here is a selective listing by critics of The Times of new or noteworthy pop and jazz concerts in the New York metropolitan region this weekend. * denotes a highly recommended concert.</p>
        <p>STEVEN BERNSTEIN'S MILLENNIAL TERRITORY ORCHESTRA, Tonic, 107 Norfolk Street, Lower East Side, (212) 358-7501. The fearless slide-trumpeter has copious, nonpartisan enthusiasms (he digs everything from cha-cha-cha to Prince to Fathead Newman to rock 'n' roll to Wynton Marsalis) that make his performances energetic and cheerful. He has been doing what all smart bandleaders have been doing lately: expanding. Every six months, it seems, there's a new Steven Bernstein band; this latest one includes the violinist Charles Burnham, a three-man reed section, the bassist Ben Allison and the banjoist Doug Wamble. It will skip between eras and styles, probably making a case at one point or another for music that you haven't thought about much. Tonight at midnight; admission is $6 (Ben Ratliff).</p>
        <p>VINICIUS CANTUARIA, Tonic, 107 Norfolk Street, near Delancey Street, Lower East Side, (212) 358-7504. Vinicius Cantuaria is steeped in the bossa nova: its gently brushed guitar chords, its quietly elaborate melodies, its shades of sensuality and melancholy. He knows it well enough to stretch the form without losing its essence. He'll have the drummer Joey Baron backing him up. Tomorrow night at 8 and 10, with Steamboat Switzerland at midnight; admission is $15 (Jon Pareles).</p>
        <p>* BILL CHARLAP TRIO, Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232. Not yet out of his 30's, Mr. Charlap knows more obscure songs of Broadway, Tin Pan Alley, the movies and the great jazz composers than a lot of great musicians twice his age, and he can be a pretty extraordinary pianist. Be warned that you're in for some of the old school; his rhythm section of Peter Washington on bass and Kenny Washington on drums is happy to be as classical as the bandleader. Sets tonight and tomorrow night are at 8, 10:30 and midnight, with a $25 cover; Sunday night sets are at 7 and 9, with a $18 cover (Ratliff); $10 minimum all nights.</p>
        <p>* ALEX CHILTON, Maxwell's, 1039 Washington Street, at 11th Street, Hoboken, N.J., (201) 798-0406. This year's MacArthur Fellowships were recently announced, so now is the time to get a jump on nominations for next year. May I suggest Alex Chilton? The intrepid interpreter of American dive music -- the songs played on dingy bar jukeboxes from Florida to New Mexico -- recently released ''Set'' (Bar None), a shambling disk recorded with his trio in one sleep-depriving swoop last year at Spear Studios in New York. Mr. Chilton displays his ineffable wit and coolly fierce guitar skills on songs by Yip Harburg, Naomi Neville, Frank Foster and other obscure songwriters. Without such efforts, America would forget songs like ''Oogum Boogum!'' But only a select few fully appreciate Mr. Chilton's genius, so he must tour constantly, which is great for his fans but must tire him out. Give Mr. Chilton the grant! Let him rest! In the meantime, don't miss him in concert. Tomorrow at 10 p.m.; admission is $10 (Ann Powers).</p>
        <p>COATI MUNDI AND HIS RHUMBA-PHONIC BAND, Midsummer Night Swing, Fountain Plaza, Lincoln Center, (212) 875-5766. Long before Ricky Martin, Andy (Coati Mundi) Hernandez brought Latin rhythms to Kid Creole and the Coconuts; his Rhumba-Phonic Band promises both the syncopations and the sense of humor. His guests include Cory Daye, the tart-voiced singer from Dr. Buzzard's Savannah Band; N'Dea Davenport, who sang with the Brand New Heavies, and the pianist Joe Bataan, whose bands in the 1960's and 70's fused funk and Latin rhythms, then picked up rapping early. Tomorrow; dance lessons from 6:30 to 7:30 p.m., followed by music from 8:15 to 11 p.m.; admission is $11 (Pareles).</p>
        <p>DOGSTAR, Irving Plaza, 17 Irving Place, at 15th Street, Manhattan, (212) 777-6817. Give Keanu Reeves credit. He only gets bigger as a movie star; ''The Matrix'' basically put him at the top of his generation's action-hero heap. Yet he keeps slogging away with his beloved band, making chimey rock that aspires to the genius of the Goo Goo Dolls. Mr. Reeves is the bass player, so don't expect any revelations on his love life from the lyrics. Instead, Dogstar offers standard alternative rock of a sort so passe that it's a miracle Mr. Reeves's agent hasn't insisted that the band enlist a turntable artist and start imitating Korn instead. Middling success never seemed so glamorous. Tonight at 8; admission is $20 (Powers).</p>
        <p>* DIAMANDA GALAS, Joe's Pub, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 539-8770. Hey, kids, do you think Eminem is scary? Then you don't know about Diamanda Galas, the true matriarch of popular music's sinister caverns, the woman with the bloodcurdling four-octave voice and the courage to use it to expose society's darkest secrets. In this program, Ms. Galas surveys her repertory, which means you may get to hear her amazing versions of Willie Dixon's ''Insane Asylum'' and Johnny Cash's ''25 Minutes to Go,'' alongside her own stirring compositions. This is the first of three successive Saturday night performances. Tomorrow at 9 p.m.; admission is $30 (Powers).</p>
        <p>* FISHBONE, THE PERSUASIONS, Central Park Summerstage, Rumsey Playfield, midpark at 72d Street, (212) 360-2777. Fishbone's manic, ambitious combination of ska, funk, hard rock, punk and reggae -- not to mention lyrics that jump from raunch to relevance -- never fails to transmit its energy to a crowd. The Persuasions, who have honed their a cappella harmonies for 37 years, have just made an album of Frank Zappa songs; their set may well include Zappa's ''Cheap Thrills,'' ''Any Way the Wind Blows'' and ''My Guitar Wants to Kill Your Mama.'' D.J. Swamp, a champion turntablist who's now with Beck's band, will scratch and mix between sets. Fantastic Plastic Machine, a disk jockey from Tokyo, plays an opening set at 1:30 p.m., followed by live music at 3. Admission is free. (Pareles).</p>
        <p>* STEVE FORBERT, VICTORIA WILLIAMS, Bottom Line, 15 West Fourth Street, at Mercer Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 228-7880. Steve Forbert, from Mississippi, never had to outgrow his early fondness for Bob Dylan; his own folk-rock, backed by his band the Rough Squirrels, mixes tall tales and winsome takes on romance. Victoria Williams, from Louisiana, moves from sun-dappled childhood memories to musings on age and mortality; she also dips into pop standards. With her sweet, cracked, quizzical voice and timing so leisurely it's almost otherworldly, she finds new, private longings in the most familiar songs. Tonight at 7:30 and 10:30; admission is $30 (Pareles).</p>
        <p>* LARRY HARLOW, Birdland, 315 West 44th Street, Clinton, (212) 581-3080. One of the in-house wizards behind the sound and style that was New York's Fania record label in the 1960's and 70's, Mr. Harlow can be a tremendously exciting pianist -- far more than his reputation, which cloisters him into the salsa scene, would indicate. The concept behind these evenings at Birdland is Latin jazz, and Mr. Harlow will play with the baritone saxophonist Ronnie Cuber, the percussionist Bobby Sanabria, the fierce trumpeter Mac Gollehon and others. Sets are tonight and tomorrow at 9 and 11; cover charge is $25 with a $10 minimum (Ratliff).</p>
        <p>WINARD HARPER QUINTET, Sweet Basil, 88 Seventh Avenue South, above Bleecker Street, West Village, (212) 242-1785. A former member of the Harper Brothers, who for a minute in the late 80's looked as if they might make a splash in mainstream jazz, Winard Harper has settled into his role as being one of the busiest and best freelance drummers around town. He has flash and energy to burn. Sets through Sunday night are at 9 and 11, with a 12:30 set tonight and tomorrow night; cover charge is $20 with a $10 minimum (Ratliff).</p>
        <p>FRED HERSCH TRIO, Village Vanguard, 178 Seventh Avenue South, at 11th Street, West Village, (212) 255-4037. Mr. Hersch, the pianist, is a musician's musician, but that didn't stop him from gaining a lot of new fans over the course of the 90's under contract to Nonesuch records. The label helped him with a series of recordings that paid tribute to favorite composers (Monk, Rodgers and Hammerstein, and Billy Strayhorn, back when he was still neglected); it also spread the knowledge out that he is one of the best solo piano performers around. His trio has been a regular at the Vanguard over the last few years, and he has developed a great rapport with the bassist Drew Gress and the drummer Tom Rainey. Sets through Sunday night are at 9:30 and 11:30, with a 1 a.m. show tonight and tomorrow night; cover charge is $20 (Ratliff).</p>
        <p>* HOLY MODAL ROUNDERS, Tonic, 107 Norfolk Street, near Delancey Street, Lower East Side, (212) 358-7503. The inimitable duo of Peter Stampfel and Steve Weber, surviving members of the Lower East Side's greatest countercultural folk band, return to present their fabulously skewed take on American music, viewed through a cracked psychedelic lens. When the Rounders are on (that is, when Mr. Weber is feeling grounded enough to stay in his chair), they produce one of the most joyous sounds in pop history. Add some more sunshine to your summer with this show. Sunday at 8 p.m.; admission is $10 (Powers).</p>
        <p>* KROSFYAH, GRUPO SAVEIRO, Midsummer Night Swing, Fountain Plaza, Lincoln Center, (212) 875-5766. Krosfyah, from Barbados, galvanizes the dance floor without leaving behind calypso's tradition of social commentary. With a drummer who could hold his own against a drum machine at any speed, Krosfyah whips up frenetic, unstoppable grooves, pushing soca toward its fastest tempos while its party chants equate positive thoughts with hip-swiveling locomotion. Grupo Saveiro is an American band driven by Brazilian carnival rhythms. Tonight; dance lessons from 6:30 to 7:30, followed by music from 8:15 to 11 p.m.; admission is $11 (Pareles).</p>
        <p>* LIL' BAND O' GOLD, Mercury Lounge, 217 Houston Street, at Ludlow Street, Lower East Side, (212) 260-4700. Almost as soon as there was rock 'n' roll, Louisiana musicians started sliding the backbeat around to create swamp pop. Warren Storm, the drummer who helped concoct the swamp-pop beat as the 1950's ended, was recruited by younger fans including the accordionist Steve Riley (who leads his own modern Cajun band, the Mamou Playboys) to form Lil' Band o' Gold; with both a horn section and a pedal steel guitar, it can tilt toward soul, country or bluesy Louisiana rock. Tomorrow night at 10; tickets are $10. Tuesday night at 8:15 at Midsummer Night Swing, Fountain Plaza, Lincoln Center, (212) 875-5766; tickets are $11 (Pareles).</p>
        <p>NATALIE MERCHANT, WILCO, New Jersey Performing Arts Center, 1 Center Street, Newark, (888) 466-5722. American folk music gets some refreshment from two rock-based acts on this bill. Ms. Merchant applies her always intense focus to a selection of traditional songs in her set, including ''Poor Wayfaring Stranger'' and ''Which Side Are You On,'' though her faithful can be assured they'll hear her own compositions at show's end. Wilco, fresh from recording its second collection of unearthed Woody Guthrie songs with Billy Bragg, shares some of those favorites, along with Jeff Tweedy's own fine compositions. Sunday at 7:30 p.m. Tickets are $32 to $56 (Powers).</p>
        <p>THE MIGHTY SPARROW, S.O.B.'s, 204 Varick Street, at Houston Street, South Village, (212) 243-4940. The songwriter and singer who revolutionized calypso after World War II still has sly rhymes and ebullient dance moves, and he's still coming up with up-to-the-minute topical songs. Tonight doors open at 11 and the concert is at midnight; tickets are $20 in advance, $22 at the door (Pareles).</p>
        <p>MOMUS, Knitting Factory, 74 Leonard Street, TriBeCa, (212) 219-3006. Momus is part of an international cabal of songwriters who love the 1960's pop that hovered outside rock: lounge combos, soundtracks, bossa nova, Burt Bacharach and Martin Denny and Brian Wilson. In his songs, he's a word-loving, mildly misanthropic character who is particularly fascinated with the way lust derails reason, and he sets his proudly clever ruminations to synthesizer tracks that never quite run amok. Tomorrow at 9 p.m., with Centimeter opening; tickets are $10 (Pareles).</p>
        <p>N'DAMBI, S.O.B.'s, 204 Varick Street, at Houston Street, South Village, (212) 243-4940. N'dambi, who used to sing backup for Erykah Badu, has followed her former employer into the realm where hip-hop meets soul. Tonight at 8; admission is $18 (Pareles).</p>
        <p>JOHNNY PACHECO, Celebrate Brooklyn, Prospect Park Band Shell, Prospect Park West and Ninth Street, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 855-7882, extension 45. The flutist and bandleader Johnny Pacheco was born in the Dominican Republic but fell in love with Afro-Cuban music early on. He has been a prime mover in New York Latin music since the 1960's, when he helped start Fania Records; he went on to lead the Fania All-Stars, the band that defined New York salsa. Tonight at 7:30, with Bryan Vargas opening; admission is free (Pareles).</p>
        <p>* MILLY QUEZADA, LOS HERMANOS ROSARIO, LOS TOROS, Central Park Summerstage, Rumsey Playfield, midpark at 72d Street, (212) 360-2777. Milly Quezada is one of the few women to have her say in merengue, the galloping Dominican dance music that is usually full of masculine come-ons and double entendres. Sharing the bill are Los Hermanos Rosario, who bring all-out showmanship to their songs, and Los Toros. A merengue dance class begins at 1:30 p.m., followed by the concert Sunday at 3; admission is free. There is also a lecture by Euclides Gutierrez on the history of merengue at noon at the Arsenal, at 850 Fifth Avenue, at 64th Street; admission is free, but reservations are required by calling (212) 360-2777 (Pareles).</p>
        <p>DIANA ROSS AND THE SUPREMES, Jones Beach, Meadowbrook Parkway South, Wantagh, Long Island, (516) 221-1000. Motown's reigning diva, Miss Ross has hired two women who toured as the Supremes after she left the group. They recreate a catalog of songs -- and some synchronized arm movements -- that keep hanging on in every baby-boomer's memory. Tonight at 7:30; tickets are $49 to $254 (Pareles).</p>
        <p>WHEAT, Knitting Factory, 74 Leonard Street, TriBeCa, (212) 219-3006. Remember collegiate rock, full of earnest sentiments set to brawny, slightly off-center folk-rock guitar riffs? So does Wheat, which thrills current undergraduates with its update of R.E.M. and Sebadoh. Jack Drag, Mendoza Line and Starlight Mints share the bill. Tonight at 9; admission is $10 (Pareles).</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
