<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>SPARE TIMES: FOR CHILDREN</title>
    <meta content="07KIDS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="36" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212954"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000707T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07EFDE1F39F934A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2719" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>SPARE TIMES: FOR CHILDREN</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Theater</p>
        <p>''VENUS AND ADONIS,'' Shakespeare's 1593 bawdy epic poem about the love goddess and her unsuccessful seduction of young Adonis, has been adapted into a comedy by the Shakespeare Project, performed by live actors and puppets. Today through Sunday at 6 p.m. at Rector Park in Battery Park City, Lower Manhattan, as part of the Hudson River Festival. Free. Information: (212) 528-2733.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Theater</p>
        <p>''VENUS AND ADONIS,'' Shakespeare's 1593 bawdy epic poem about the love goddess and her unsuccessful seduction of young Adonis, has been adapted into a comedy by the Shakespeare Project, performed by live actors and puppets. Today through Sunday at 6 p.m. at Rector Park in Battery Park City, Lower Manhattan, as part of the Hudson River Festival. Free. Information: (212) 528-2733.</p>
        <p>Events</p>
        <p>''THE ADVENTURES OF ROCKY AND BULLWINKLE AND FRIENDS,'' a screening series of selections from works by the television animator Jay Ward, through Sept. 17 at the Museum of Televison and Radio, 25 West 52nd Street, Manhattan. Screenings are Tuesdays through Sundays at 12:15 p.m., with additional screenings Thursdays at 6 p.m. and Fridays at 7 p.m. Through Sunday, the screenings include original episodes of ''Crusader Rabbit,'' the premiere of ''Rocky and His Friends'' and a rare appearance by the Bullwinkle puppet on ''The Bullwinkle Show'' and ''Fractured Flickers.'' Admission: $6; students and the elderly, $4; 13 and under, $3. Information: (212) 621-6800.</p>
        <p>BRASS RUBBING WORKSHOP, tomorrow from 10 a.m. to noon at the Cathedral of St. John the Divine, 1047 Amsterdam Avenue, at 112th Street, Morningside Heights. Children 4 to 12, accompanied by an adult, can explore the bronze memorials with educators and then create life-size rubbings. Fee: $5 a child. For reservations: (212) 932-7347.</p>
        <p>''BEADS, BODY AND SOUL: ART AND LIGHT IN THE YORUBA UNIVERSE,'' an exhibition presented jointly by the Studio Museum in Harlem (through Sept. 17) and the Museum for African Art (through Aug. 27), explores 1,000 years of beaded arts in the Yoruba culture, including thrones, necklaces and divination beads. The Studio Museum in Harlem will present a bead-making workshop tomorrow from 10:30 a.m. to 12:30 p.m. for children 8 and older and their families, at 144 West 125th Street, (212) 864-4500, extension 230. Free with museum admission; suggested donation is $5 for adults; $3 for students and the elderly; $1 for children under 12. The Museum for African Art will present a narrative pictures workshop for children 5 and older, tomorrow at 1 p.m., at 593 Broadway, SoHo. Free with museum admission: $5; $2.50 for children, students and the elderly. Call to reserve space. Information: (212) 966-1313), extension 125.</p>
        <p>CHILDREN'S MUSEUM OF THE ARTS, 182 Lafayette Street, SoHo, will feature two workshops this weekend for children 10 and younger: tomorrow from 1 to 4 p.m, creating works of art from fabrics, papers and yarn; Sunday from 1 to 3 p.m., a batik workshop in which children can create pictures with different fabric dyes. Free with admission: $5. Information: (212) 274-0986.</p>
        <p>FREE FRIDAY FAMILY FUN, music, dance and comedy Fridays at 6:30 p.m. through August at the Brooklyn Children's Museum, 145 Brooklyn Avenue, at St. Marks Place, Crown Heights, under the stars in the rooftop theater. Tonight's program is ''Uptown Comes Downtown: Harlem Swing Festival,'' the music of Ellington, Armstrong and Basie with the Uptown Swingers and the Arch Thompson Quartet. Suggested admission to exhibitions: $3; shows are free. Information: (718) 735-4400.</p>
        <p>''JUDY! JUDY! JUDY!'' Busby Berkeley's ''Babes in Arms'' (1939) is the first of six films in a Judy Garland film series presented by the Film Society of Lincoln Center, tomorrow and Sunday at 11 a.m. Walter Reade Theater, Lincoln Center. Tickets: $3. Information: (212) 875-5601.</p>
        <p>''NOAH SUMMONS THE ANIMALS.'' Youngsters 5 to 10 can learn how Noah saved the animals and enjoy whimsical metal sculptures by Manuel Bennett, then create a wire animal to take home. Sunday from 2:30 to 3:45 p.m. at the Yeshiva University Museum's Children's Discovery Center, 15 West 16th Street, Chelsea. Free. Information: (212) 294-8330.</p>
        <p>NEW YORK FAMILY ARTS FESTIVAL, the second annual arts festival of multicultural performances and events, presented by the Theater of the Riverside Church, 91 Claremont Avenue, at 120th Street, Morningside Heights. The four-week festival begins tomorrow with a street fair and runs through Aug. 8. On Sunday the theater will be home to a Native American village, with a drum song workshop at 1 p.m., storytelling at 3 p.m. and dance performances at 5 p.m. For ticket prices and information: (212) 870-6784.</p>
        <p>NEW YORK TRANSIT MUSEUM'S NOSTALGIA TRAIN. The subway has been called a lot of things; a time machine isn't one of them, although that may change on Sunday when a 1928 D-type leaves about 10:15 a.m. (boarding is at 10 a.m.), from the 59th Street-Columbus Circle Station in Manhattan. The cars, made of bolted steel, have wicker seats, hand grips covered in enamel, exposed light bulbs and operational ceiling fans. The train drives into the New York Transit Museum, Boerum Place and Schermerhorn Street, downtown Brooklyn, with a chance for ticket holders to explore the space. Then it's off to the ultimate nostalgia stop: Coney Island and a chance to trade the subway for the Ferris wheel or the waves and after two hours reboard for Jay Street-Borough Hall and 59th Street-Columbus Circle. Tickets: $25 ($20 for new museum members); under 17, $10; under 3, free (limit one free child per adult). Reservations required: (718) 243-8601.</p>
        <p>PAINTING AT THE MEER. The beauty of the Harlem Meer is the setting for a watercolor painting workshop tomorrow from 1 to 2:30 p.m. at the Charles A. Dana Discovery Center, 110th Street near Fifth Avenue. For ages 8 and up. Free. Reservations: (212) 860-1370.</p>
        <p>''STORY CORNER: IN THE CITY.'' What do people do in the city? Youngsters will discover the answer through stories and photographs inspired by the exhibition ''Vivian Cherry: A Working Street Photographer,'' tomorrow at 4 p.m. in the Prints, Drawing and Photographs Gallery, second floor, Brooklyn Museum of Art, 200 Eastern Parkway, at Prospect Park. Free with museum admission: $4; students and the elderly, $2; under 12, free. Information: (718) 638-5000.</p>
        <p>''PLANT POWER,'' the latest addition to the Children's Museum of Manhattan's outdoor Sussman Environmental Center, greets children with a wide-eyed topiary squirrel. Youngsters can then enjoy the five-foot garden veggies springing up all around or go on a texture terrain tour, traveling through New York City's biggest watering can. They can also learn interesting facts about garden goodies like which plants are used in making dyes or how to identify edible plant parts -- or simply get their hands dirty. 212 West 83rd Street. Museum hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. until Labor Day. Free with museum admission: $6; infants under 1, free. Information: (212) 721-1234.</p>
        <p>SOAP SCULPTURE WORKSHOP. A program for ages 5 to 12 to complement ''The Art of William Edmondson,'' an exhibition of limestone carvings, Sunday from 2 to 4 p.m. (also July 23) at the Museum of American Folk Art, 2 Lincoln Square, Columbus Avenue at 66th Street. Materials fee of $1; admission free. Reservations: (212) 595-9533.</p>
        <p>Exhibitions</p>
        <p>''REPTILES: REAL AND ROBOTIC,'' including an alligator snapping turtle 10 times life size and a Western diamondback rattlesnake 36 feet long, is part of the exhibition (through Sept. 17) at the New York Hall of Science, 47-01 111th Street, Flushing Meadows-Corona Park, Queens. Although those are robots, the real ones are no less impressive, including gila monsters, bearded dragons and blue-tongued skinks. Children will enjoy ''Reptiles Revealed'' shows each day in the hall at 1 and 3 p.m., and at noon and 2 p.m. they can see demonstrations of NASA's use of robotics. And through Aug. 26 the museum will offer shows of live reptiles every Saturday at 2 p.m. for $2. Hours in July and August: Mondays from 9:30 a.m. to 2 p.m.; Tuesdays through Sundays, 9:30 a.m. to 5 p.m. Admission: $7.50; $5 for ages 4 to 17 and the elderly; free for ages 3 and under. Information: (718) 699-0005.</p>
        <p>Zoos</p>
        <p>BIRD KEEPER WEEKEND at Prospect Park Zoo, 450 Flatbush Avenue, near Empire Boulevard, Prospect Heights, Brooklyn, tomorrow and Sunday from 1 to 4:30 p.m. Youngsters can join the zoo keeper for a chat to learn about the zoo's bird population at 3 p.m. at the emu exhibition. Other activities include creating paper birds with colorful feathers and joining an expert from 2:30 to 4:30 p.m. at the macaw exhibition. Zoo hours: Mondays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; weekends, 10 a.m. to 5:30 p.m. Admission: $2.50; the elderly, $1.25; children 3 to 12, 50 cents; 2 and under, free. Information: (718) 399-7339.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
