<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nature's a Stage, and Often a Player</title>
    <meta content="07HUDS$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Travel; Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212983"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Boscobel (Historic Home) (Garrison, NY)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Garrison (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hudson Valley Shakespeare Festival</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'Brien, Terrence</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shakespeare, William (1564-1616)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Taming of the Shrew, the (Play)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Measure for Measure (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People/William Shakespeare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000707T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E5D91F39F934A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2257" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nature's a Stage, and Often a Player</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER MARKS</byline>
      <dateline>GARRISON, N.Y.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of Hudson Valley Shakespeare Festival, which perform on grounds of Boscobel estate in Garrison, NY; company is presenting Measure for Measure and The Taming of the Shrew this summer; Terrence O'Brien is co-founder and artistic director; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN the theater it isn't always an encouraging sign when the audience leaves humming the scenery. But at the Hudson Valley Shakespeare Festival, it's all but inevitable.</p>
        <p>The festival, one of the best-kept theatrical secrets of summer in the gentrified outer reaches of the New York metropolitan area, is ensconced in the most lyrical of settings for open-air theater: the grounds of the Boscobel Restoration, a historic house and gardens on a promontory overlooking the Hudson River across from West Point. The plays change each July and August, but the magnificent backdrop is immutable. At sunset on performance nights, the spectators take their seats in a yellow open-sided tent and watch as the actors materialize in the distance, rising from behind a bluff over the riverbank and making their way to the stage by way of a manicured lawn bathed in a shimmering, late-day amber.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN the theater it isn't always an encouraging sign when the audience leaves humming the scenery. But at the Hudson Valley Shakespeare Festival, it's all but inevitable.</p>
        <p>The festival, one of the best-kept theatrical secrets of summer in the gentrified outer reaches of the New York metropolitan area, is ensconced in the most lyrical of settings for open-air theater: the grounds of the Boscobel Restoration, a historic house and gardens on a promontory overlooking the Hudson River across from West Point. The plays change each July and August, but the magnificent backdrop is immutable. At sunset on performance nights, the spectators take their seats in a yellow open-sided tent and watch as the actors materialize in the distance, rising from behind a bluff over the riverbank and making their way to the stage by way of a manicured lawn bathed in a shimmering, late-day amber.</p>
        <p>Now, there's an entrance.</p>
        <p>The festival's co-founder and longtime artistic director, Terrence O'Brien, knows from long experience not to try to compete too grandly with the landscape: the company's program notes the contributions of designers of lighting, sound, costumes and choreography. Notably missing: any mention of a set designer. Nature got the job long ago.</p>
        <p>''I come here on some days and I think, 'This is my office,' '' Stephen Paul Johnson says as he sits under an ancient shade tree on the vast Boscobel lawn, taking a break from rehearsing ''Measure for Measure,'' the festival's current offering, in which Mr. Johnson plays Angelo, the lecherous villain. ''Our curtain goes up as the sunlight starts to fade.''</p>
        <p>Theatrical fads inevitably fade, too, but Shakespeare alfresco, it appears, is forever. From Lenox, Mass., where Shakespeare and Company is in residence, to Central Park, where free Shakespeare is such an entrenched institution that theatergoing New Yorkers seem to claim tickets as a birthright, the summer months ring with the sounds of 400-year-old soliloquies and sway to the rhythms of iambic pentameter.</p>
        <p>That is not to say classical theater in the great outdoors doesn't have some obvious drawbacks; when nature doesn't cooperate, the tortures can descend in an unair-conditioned environment as potently as the 12 plagues. ''Heat and bugs,'' Mr. O'Brien says, enumerating two of the festival's most intrepid enemies. On especially sultry nights, a lightheaded ticketbuyer or two have been known to lose consciousness momentarily, and the squadrons of mosquitoes will brazenly divebomb their targets through the most heartbreaking moments in all of Shakespeare. The festival, in response, has developed its own arsenal, a table laid with insect sprays and lotions, and a new ventilation system that it says can suck the hot air out of the tent every five minutes.</p>
        <p>It does take a certain kind of resourcefulness to create art under these circumstances, and the festival, now in its 14th season, is used to squeezing every bit of advantage out of its glorious surroundings. No one, of course, is getting rich doing Elizabethan drama in a tent in Putnam County; the festival operates on a relative shoestring. The budget for putting on two full-scale productions, paying actors Equity scale, housing them at a local college, renting the tent, leasing the grounds, printing the programs and making the costumes is just under $600,000. The troupe has almost no money for promotion, so it does not take out many advertisements in the local papers, let alone film any of those television commercials with the sappy post-show testimonials.</p>
        <p>What it does have is powerful word of mouth, helped along by Mr. O'Brien's accessible and intelligent productions, many of which have received favorable notices, including one this week for the current production by Ben Brantley in The New York Times.</p>
        <p>Last summer's ''Titus Andronicus,'' for example, was a daring and controversial choice. The festival had built up an audience over the years with safer fare like ''A Midsummer Night's Dream'' and ''As You Like It,'' but the director found in ''Titus'' an intriguing parallel between its blood-soaked plot and the mechanics of action-adventure movies. The violent denouement was played in slow motion, a splatter scene in which the actors clutched spurting bladders filled with a mixture of red food dye, chocolate syrup and laundry detergent. Shakespeare, in other words, as a kind of hokier version of ''Gladiator.''</p>
        <p>The festival is greatly aided, too, by those breathtaking vistas of the Hudson, which put a visitor in mind of a hazy day on the Rhine. There are, in fact, few pre-theater dinners more beguiling than a picnic on the Boscobel grass, with a view clear down to the Bear Mountain Bridge. (You can take your own meal or buy one of the festival's, prepared in the kitchens of a nearby golf club.) The combination has made it an ever more popular destination: last year, a record 14,700 playgoers attended the festival's 45 performances of ''Twelfth Night'' and ''Titus.'' This season, Mr. O'Brien and the festival's executive director, Susan Landstreet, are hoping to do even better with 50 performances of ''Measure for Measure'' and ''The Taming of the Shrew.''</p>
        <p>Still, there are no ''Lion King''-size paydays here. Even with the record turnout, the festival finished last summer with exactly zero dollars in the till. ''We took a bit of a bath,'' Ms. Landstreet says, explaining that reviews for ''Titus'' were not published until late in its run, so attendance at the early performances of one of Shakespeare's obscurer plays was disappointing. The festival's board came to the rescue with enough money to keep the troupe afloat. But the experience pointed up how precarious staging the classics becomes when a company of some ambition opts for something other than the tried and true. Those bucolic country roads can quickly become filled with potholes.</p>
        <p>An Unorthodox Choice</p>
        <p>It is a humid Saturday afternoon in late June at Boscobel, a crucial day in the life of the Hudson Valley Shakespeare Festival. In a few hours, ''Measure for Measure'' is to open, and like ''Titus'' the summer before, it is an unorthodox choice. (In contrast, ''Shrew,'' the season's second offering, is ''selling like hot cakes,'' Ms. Landstreet says.) The play tells the improbable story of a man sentenced to death for fornication; his sister, a novice in an abbey, pursued by a venomous lawman; and a noble duke roaming his corrupted city in disguise. It veers wildly between comedy and tragedy and has a thoroughly unconvincing happy ending tacked on.</p>
        <p>Under the tent, Mr. O'Brien has Mr. Johnson, a festival veteran, and Aidan Sullivan, a recent Juilliard graduate, in the key role of Isabella, the novice, going over one of the play's most difficult scenes, in which Angelo makes his sexual desire known to Isabella. ''That felt mechanical,'' Mr. Johnson says after hesitantly caressing Ms. Sullivan. Mr. O'Brien, a lug of a guy in Bermuda shorts and sandals, whispers something to the actors, and they try the scene again. This time, Ms. Sullivan registers more revulsion, and the director seems satisfied.</p>
        <p>Mr. O'Brien, who lives in Manhattan with his wife and two young children, has been having at Shakespeare every summer since 1987, when an actress friend, Melissa Stern Lourie, invited him to Putnam to stage a benefit outdoor performance of ''A Midsummer Night's Dream.'' It proved so popular that Mr. O'Brien and Ms. Lourie -- who has since left the troupe -- decided to found the festival, with the help of a group of local supporters who formed a board. In its second season the festival moved to Boscobel, an 18th-century estate restored by a private foundation in 1961.</p>
        <p>Moonlighting</p>
        <p>''I sort of feel like my job is as a divining rod, just to sit there and see if what's going on is true or not,'' said Mr. O'Brien, who is, in a sense, moonlighting in the countryside. His day job is creating customized software, which seems about as far removed from the forests of Arden, the courts of Vienna and the midsummer fairies as one can get. ''Most of my clients think it's exciting,'' he said. ''But my cell phone does go off during rehearsals, and it's 'Hi, we ran out of disk space in the notes server.' ''</p>
        <p>When you are a serious theater person, and you get to direct one show a year (the ''Shrew,'' now in rehearsals, is being directed by his colleague Nick Mangano), the emotional stakes can be pretty high. Mr. O'Brien says he begins thinking about his production months before the first actor is cast, and usually the initial ideas for his interpretation come from music.</p>
        <p>''I end up being very intuitive about these choices,'' he says. ''Suddenly a song will come to my mind, and I'll make a connection between the lyric of the song and the play.'' For ''Measure,'' the inspiration was, of all things, ''Santa Baby,'' a kitschy Eartha Kitt song from the 50's. Mr. O'Brien's quirky linkage is incorporated into the production in a highly visible way. The number, lip-synched by Ms. Sullivan to Ms. Kitt's recording and accompanied by a vamping chorus of actors, provides a stylish opening to the second act.</p>
        <p>''The song is like a comic extreme of what's happening in the play,'' Mr. O'Brien says, adding, ''I end up justifying the choice intellectually, even though the choice was intuitive to begin with.''</p>
        <p>If the tent is a fairly spartan affair -- 400 folding chairs on risers arranged in a wide semicircle -- so are the actors' living conditions. This year, the company consists of 11 Equity players, who make $415 a week, and are put up in the dorms of Mount St. Mary College in Newburgh, which charges the festival $9 an actor a night, Ms. Landstreet said.</p>
        <p>''They gave Kurt and me a double bed,'' Nance Williamson said with a laugh, referring to her husband, Kurt Rhoads. They are what you might call the festival's answer to the Lunts, having appeared together as Beatrice and Benedick in ''Much Ado About Nothing''' and, this summer, as Kate and Petruchio in ''Shrew.'' They have attracted a following among Hudson Valley's audiences, which come chiefly from Westchester, Putnam and Dutchess counties, though the festival is looking for ways to increase its draw from Manhattan.</p>
        <p>'Weird Little Setup'</p>
        <p>The Lunts live in the dorm like everyone else. ''When you first hear about it, it's like, 'Oh, no, there's a tent and bare grass and a mud floor?'' said Mr. Rhoads, who is playing the duke in ''Measure'' and is in his sixth festival season here. ''The ingredients are not for a very professional experience. But you know, this environment, this weird little setup, is a great way to tell a story.''</p>
        <p>Mr. O'Brien uses the vast Boscobel space in inspired ways to tell the stories. There was the time, in ''Tartuffe,'' when he had the actors arrive at the tent on a wagon, as if they were members of a road company of the Comedie Francaise. And there are times when the space uses them, as on the Fourth of July weekend last year, when teenagers setting off firecrackers nearby provided inadvertent sound and lighting effects for ''Twelfth Night.'' A company member had to explain to the audience that the celebration was not of the festival's devising. Another evening, during ''Titus,'' the power blew, and the cast performed with flashlights.</p>
        <p>On the opening night of ''Measure,'' the tent is packed with people, not mosquitoes. Mr. O'Brien sits in a seat near the back, a legal pad in his lap. There will be notes for the actors, a couple of more rehearsals, and Mr. O'Brien is in essence done for the year. It's back to custom database applications, and thoughts of next summer.</p>
        <p>''I'm thinking very strongly about doing 'Richard III,' '' he said. ''I'll latch onto something and just sort of daydream. I picture what something might look like in that space.''</p>
        <p>And already, he's hearing music.</p>
        <p>Shakespeare w/Vu</p>
        <p>The Hudson Valley Shakespeare Festival is offering two comedies, ''Measure for Measure'' and ''The Taming of the Shrew,'' in repertory this season at the Boscobel Restoration, 1601 Route 9D, Garrison, N.Y.</p>
        <p>''Measure for Measure'' will be presented today and tomorrow at 8 p.m. and Sunday at 6 p.m. Tickets are $19 to $30 ($17 for previews), with a 20 percent discount for students and the elderly and a 50 percent discount for children 12 and younger for all but Saturday night performances.</p>
        <p>Prepared picnics, $16 and $18, are available by reservation.</p>
        <p>Other performances of ''Measure for Measure'' this season will be July 12 to 16, 20, 22 to 23, 26 and 30.</p>
        <p>''The Taming of the Shrew'' will be presented on July 19, 21 and 27 to 29; Aug. 2 to 6, 9 to 13, 16 to 20 and 23 to 27.</p>
        <p>Information and reservations: (914) 265-9575.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
