<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>World Briefing</title>
    <meta content="Y07BRI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212994"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000707T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E0D71F39F934A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1607" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>World Briefing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by Jeanne Moore</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>FRANCE: VOTE ON PRESIDENTIAL TERM  President Jacques Chirac said a referendum will be held Sept. 24 on whether to cut the presidential term from seven years to five. Polls show that about three-quarters of French people support a cut in the seven-year term, which was written into the Constitution of the Fifth Republic by de Gaulle in 1958.</p>
        <p>(Agence France-Presse)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>FRANCE: VOTE ON PRESIDENTIAL TERM  President Jacques Chirac said a referendum will be held Sept. 24 on whether to cut the presidential term from seven years to five. Polls show that about three-quarters of French people support a cut in the seven-year term, which was written into the Constitution of the Fifth Republic by de Gaulle in 1958.</p>
        <p>(Agence France-Presse)</p>
        <p>VATICAN: ON REMARRIAGE  The Vatican affirmed its prohibition on Communion for Catholics who have divorced and remarried, saying that many priests are too lenient toward divorced parishioners. Remarried couples may receive Communion, however, if they abstain from sex.</p>
        <p>Alessandra Stanley (NYT)</p>
        <p>SWITZERLAND: MOSSAD TRIAL  Prosecutors demanded a 15-month jail sentence for an agent of Mossad, the Israeli secret service, who was caught during a bungled wiretap in Switzerland in 1998. The agent, being tried under a false name, said earlier in the trial that the man he was trying to place under surveillance was suspected of links to Hezbollah. The court is expected to rule today.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>ASIA</p>
        <p>CAMBODIA: KHMER ROUGE TRIAL CLOSER  The United Nations and Cambodia reached a provisional accord on arrangements for a genocide trial of former Khmer Rouge leaders, a United Nations spokesman said. The agreement and new laws paving the way for the trial will now be debated by Cambodia's Parliament, where some opposition is expected.</p>
        <p>(Agence France-Presse)</p>
        <p>INDIA: PUZZLING TIGER DEATHS  The government set up a team of experts to help investigate the deaths of 10 tigers, including 7 rare white tigers, in a zoo in the eastern state of Orissa. Early post-mortem reports suggest that they died of a parasitic infection, although suspicion has also fallen on medication used to fight the infection.</p>
        <p>P. J. Anthony (NYT)</p>
        <p>SRI LANKA: EMERGENCY RULE EXTENDED  Parliament approved the extension of a nationwide state of emergency, giving security forces sweeping powers to arrest suspects. The laws also give the government powers to impose the censorship reordered by President Chandrika Kumaratunga last week after the Supreme Court ruled that a previous censorship order was illegal.</p>
        <p>P. J. Anthony (NYT)</p>
        <p>JAPAN: FOOD POISONING  The president of Japan's biggest dairy company said he would resign after more than 11,300 people were afflicted with diarrhea and vomiting after consuming bacteria-tainted milk. Government investigators said workers at the Snow Brand Milk Products Company's Osaka plant failed to clean equipment properly.</p>
        <p>Calvin Sims (NYT)</p>
        <p>AFGHANISTAN: TERROR CHARGE REJECTED  The Taliban militia dismissed accusations at a regional summit meeting in Tajikistan that terrorism and drugs originating in Afghanistan posed threats to its neighbors. A Taliban official said the fears expressed by Russia, China, Kazakhstan, Kyrgyzstan and Tajikistan were related to those countries' own domestic problems and had no connection to Afghanistan.</p>
        <p>(Agence France-Presse)</p>
        <p>AFRICA</p>
        <p>ZIMBABWE: ELECTION CHALLENGE  Charging that intimidation and vote-rigging may have skewed last month's parliamentary balloting, the opposition Movement for Democratic Change has decided to formally challenge the results in 28 of the 120 voting districts. Movement officials said the party would file formal complaints with the High Court, requesting that the results be thrown out. The Movement won 57 seats in the June 24-25 elections, the largest opposition win in 20 years, while the governing party of President Robert Mugabe won 62.</p>
        <p>Rachel Swarns (NYT)</p>
        <p>ZIMBABWE: FARMS FOR SALE  White farmers are offering to sell 400 more farms to President Robert Mugabe's government for its black resettlement program, bringing to 600 the number of farms made available to the government this week. A farmers' representative said the government did not need to pursue its land seizure plans because white farmers were prepared to sell some of their land for a properly managed resettlement program. Last month, the government published a list of 804 white-owned farms it wants to seize.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>THE AMERICAS</p>
        <p>VENEZUELA: RESTIVE OFFICERS  A junior military officer who accused President Hugo Chavez, left, of ''destroying Venezuela'' and called for his resignation has been dismissed, and another who criticized the president in a letter to his superiors is under investigation. The videotaped statement by Capt. Luis Garcia, who says he represents a ''patriotic junta'' within the military, came as Mr. Chavez is seeking re-election this month and opposition groups warn that discontent in the military is growing and could lead to a coup.</p>
        <p>Larry Rohter (NYT)</p>
        <p>PERU: ADVICE REBUFFED  President Alberto K. Fujimori said he had no intention of following the advice of an Organization of American States mission that he fire his intelligence chief, Vladimiro Montesinos. Mr. Montesinos is blamed for directing a dirty tricks campaign against opposition candidates in recent elections. Clifford Krauss (NYT)</p>
        <p>MIDDLE EAST</p>
        <p>IRAN: NEW ARRESTS OVER VIDEOTAPE  Five people were arrested and charged with helping make a videotape featuring an Islamic vigilante group member discussing his links to hard-line politicians, state-run Tehran radio reported. In the tape, Amir Farshad Ebrahimi, a member of a violent Islamic vigilante group, names several top politicians and says they used his group to attack their reformist opponents.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
