<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bidding Is Hot At London Sale</title>
    <meta content="07INSI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212977"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="INSIDE ART"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Archaeology and Anthropology</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Christie's</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Tate Modern (London)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Israel Museum (Jerusalem)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vogel, Carol</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wernher, Julius</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bronfman, Charles</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Columns/Inside Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Archeology and Anthropology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Archaeology and Anthropology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000707T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E6DA1F39F934A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1052" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bidding Is Hot At London Sale</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Carol Vogel</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Vogel, Carol</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, July 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Rare group of old master paintings, French furniture, silver and sculptures that once belonged to Julius Wernher is sold at Christie's London for $30.4 million, twice pre-sale estimate; photo; art was housed for nearly century at family's Bath House in Piccadilly and Luton Hoo in Bedfordshire; Tate Modern welcomes millionth visitor just six weeks after opening; Israel Museum uses $10 million Bronfman family donation to renovate archaeology wing (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A rare group of old master paintings, French furniture, silver and sculptures that once belonged to Julius Wernher, a diamond merchant who was a governor of the South African conglomerate De Beers, sold at Christie's here on Wednesday night for $30.4 million, twice its $15 million estimate.</p>
        <p>In a packed salesroom, dealers and collectors bid relentlessly for the best of the art and objects housed for nearly a century at the Wernher family's two homes: Bath House in Piccadilly, and Luton Hoo, a stately home in Bedfordshire.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A rare group of old master paintings, French furniture, silver and sculptures that once belonged to Julius Wernher, a diamond merchant who was a governor of the South African conglomerate De Beers, sold at Christie's here on Wednesday night for $30.4 million, twice its $15 million estimate.</p>
        <p>In a packed salesroom, dealers and collectors bid relentlessly for the best of the art and objects housed for nearly a century at the Wernher family's two homes: Bath House in Piccadilly, and Luton Hoo, a stately home in Bedfordshire.</p>
        <p>A small group of old master paintings and several extraordinary pieces of silver were the stars of the evening. While the buyers were mainly dealers, Christie's executives said after the sale that many were bidding on behalf of museums.</p>
        <p>Anthony Blumka, a New York dealer, bought a rare piece of silver, a late Gothic figure of St. Sebastian dated 1497 and estimated at $1 million, for $2.9 million. Officials at the Metropolitan Museum of Art confirmed today that Mr. Blumka was bidding on behalf of the Cloisters, which is part of the museum.</p>
        <p>''Diana and Her Nymphs Hunting'' (circa 1636), an oil sketch by Rubens from one of the famous series made for Philip IV of Spain to display at the Torre de la Parada, his lodge near Madrid, sold for $4.6 million, nearly three times its high estimate of $1.6 million. Experts said that the sketch was considered one of the best examples of Rubens's Baroque period. It was bought by the Savings Bank of Madrid for the Prado, Christie's confirmed today.</p>
        <p>Hazlitt, Gooden &amp; Fox, the London dealers, bought Titian's ''Portrait of Giacomo Doria'' (circa 1531) for $3.6 million, nearly twice its $1.9 million estimate. Christie's confirmed that the dealers bought it for the Ashmolean Museum at Oxford.</p>
        <p>Another top price was paid for ''Saturn Devouring His Children,'' a bronze cast from a 17th-century model by Pietro Francavilla. Estimated at $940,000 to $1.4 million, it was sold for $1.6 million to Cyril Humphries. Mr. Humphries was sitting next to Robert H. Smith, the celebrated bronze collector who is chairman of the National Gallery of Art in Washington, and people at the sale speculated that Mr. Humphries was buying the bronze for Mr. Smith.</p>
        <p>Proceeds from Wednesday's sale will go to the Wernher heirs and to maintaining Luton Hoo.</p>
        <p>The Tate's Crowds</p>
        <p>Last week, only six weeks after opening, the new $214 million Tate Modern welcomed its millionth visitor. By now, more than 1,063,161 people have gone to see the giant renovated power station in the regenerated Southwark section of London, the first new national museum in Britain in 100 years and its first devoted solely to modern art.</p>
        <p>Before the opening, officials at the Tate projected attendance in its first year at about two million. Now, they say, they are hoping for twice that figure.</p>
        <p>The crowds are bigger than the first Tate Gallery, now called Tate Britain, across the Thames in Milbank, has ever drawn. That museum broke a record in 1996 during its Cezanne retrospective, when it averaged about 14,000 visitors a day. The Tate Modern is getting about 15,000 people a day, down from 24,000 in May.</p>
        <p>Attendance is also far greater at the new museum than at the Guggenheim Bilbao, the three-year-old museum in the Basque region of Spain designed by the Los Angeles architect Frank O. Gehry. In its first year, the Guggenheim Bilbao had about 1.4 million visitors.</p>
        <p>But you don't have to go to London to see art from the Tate. The institution has just begun its first online art program. ''It's a way of extending the frame of the gallery,'' said Nicholas Serota, director of all the Tate museums. ''It makes art accessible to millions.'' The first commissioned work in the program, ''Uncomfortable Proximity,'' a Web art project by Harwood De Mongrel, a team of British computer artists, can be seen at the Tate's Web site, www.tate .org.uk. It looks similar to the rest of the Tate's Web site in layout and design but has new images and texts. It is parallel to the main portion of the site, emphasizing the difference between them.</p>
        <p>A second commissioned artwork, ''Le Match des Couleurs'' by the British sculptor and installation artist Simon Patterson, will go online on Wednesday. It features a recording of Radio France 1's soccer commentator, Eugene Sacomano, reading the  results for all the teams that have ever played in the French soccer league. He gives each team a color based on the hexadecimal equivalent color system, a system of specifying colors on the Internet. Both works will be online until June 30, 2001.</p>
        <p>''Not unlike the video artists of the 1960's, there are some practitioners working only in this field,'' Sir Nicholas said. ''And there are others like Simon Patterson, who migrate and explore art online.''</p>
        <p>Gift to Israel Museum</p>
        <p>The Israel Museum in Jerusalem has been refurbishing and renovating its galleries one by one with donations. The latest gift -- $10 million from Andrea and Charles Bronfman, of the family that is selling the Seagram Company to Vivendi S.A., a French conglomerate -- will be used to renovate and reinstall the wing housing the archaeology collection, including some of the world's best biblical Jewish, early Christian and Islamic antiquities.</p>
        <p>The wing was built in 1965, when the museum opened, with money from Edgar and Charles Bronfman and their sisters, Baroness Minda de Gunzburg and Phyllis Lambert, to honor the 70th birthday of their father, Samuel Bronfman.</p>
        <p>Since the space has not been touched in 35 years, it can no longer accommodate a growing collection of material from newly excavated sites throughout Israel.</p>
        <p>''Over the years, Charles Bronfman has been a visible player in Israel, both in the business and cultural community,'' said James Snyder, the museum's director. ''He recognized that archaeology is the true and most important cultural patrimony of Israel.''</p>
        <p>INSIDE ART</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
