<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Weegee</title>
    <meta content="RV010543" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213109"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ART IN REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weegee (Arthur Fellig) (1899-1968)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, Roberta</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000707T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E6D81638F934A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="532" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Weegee</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERTA SMITH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smith, Roberta</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Roberta Smith reviews creative photographic work of Weegee, at Matthew Marks Gallery; photos (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>'Distortions'</p>
        <p>Matthew Marks Gallery</p>
        <p>523 West 24th Street, Chelsea</p>
        <p>Through July 28</p>
        <p>Working for the New York dailies  between 1935 and 1945, Arthur Fellig, known as Weegee, simultaneously invented and surpassed tabloid photojournalism, creating images of urban life in all its shadings that endure as art. Weegee's photographs from the last two decades of his life are less well known, but this exhibition of nearly 90, the largest yet, suggests that they, too, will endure.</p>
        <p>By 1947, Weegee had stopped working as a photojournalist and had become in effect an artist of the darkroom, a wizard of zany development techniques and an avid recycler of images, both his own and those clipped from magazines. He subjected these to a range of abuses, placing curved or textured glass between the enlarger and the photographic paper or orchestrating multiple exposures. He also burned or melted negatives.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>'Distortions'</p>
        <p>Matthew Marks Gallery</p>
        <p>523 West 24th Street, Chelsea</p>
        <p>Through July 28</p>
        <p>Working for the New York dailies  between 1935 and 1945, Arthur Fellig, known as Weegee, simultaneously invented and surpassed tabloid photojournalism, creating images of urban life in all its shadings that endure as art. Weegee's photographs from the last two decades of his life are less well known, but this exhibition of nearly 90, the largest yet, suggests that they, too, will endure.</p>
        <p>By 1947, Weegee had stopped working as a photojournalist and had become in effect an artist of the darkroom, a wizard of zany development techniques and an avid recycler of images, both his own and those clipped from magazines. He subjected these to a range of abuses, placing curved or textured glass between the enlarger and the photographic paper or orchestrating multiple exposures. He also burned or melted negatives.</p>
        <p>Several photographs were newly taken and, as he lived in Hollywood from 1947 to 1952, movie stars and other celebrities, including Marilyn Monroe, Marlon Brando and Judy Garland, were frequent victims of his distortions. But new images could also start out distorted, thanks to a technique that he invented of covering the camera lens with a kaleidoscope. (He aimed it both at people and the television set.)</p>
        <p>The results go far beyond fun-house mirror distortions. They demonstrate both the surface elasticity and inner lives of images, showing them to be wildly polymorphous and bubbling with conflicting emotions. Four images of the ''Mona Lisa,'' developed using square-patterned glass, go from shifty-eyed to Donald Duck to Dali-soft to Spiro Agnew.</p>
        <p>Elizabeth Taylor, young, beautiful, bare-shouldered and photographed through the kaleidoscope-covered lens while eating from a fork, is multiplied and reversed into a creature of exquisite Pre-Raphaelite viperishness, a ravishing, ravaging Medusa. The famous features of Monroe, whose face the camera was often said to love, go through so many changes here that you begin to feel just the opposite: that her face was mad for the camera and began performing whenever one appeared.</p>
        <p>The features of Jerry Lewis, seen through the tiny facets of ''fly-eye'' plastic, multiply into a suitably manic mass of overlapping eyes, noses and mouths. Garland becomes a demonic mouse, although when Weegee isolates and multiplies her eyes with the help of wavy glass, he gets at the essence of her vulnerability and temperament. A large image of the Duke and Duchess of Windsor looking exceptionally pinched and prissy is worthy of Daumier, as are rephotographed photographs of Mao, Charles de Gaulle and Richard Nixon.</p>
        <p>Weegee's corniness threshold is sometimes too high: J. Edgar Hoover with a third eye, for example. But for the most part his late work parlayed the visceral, somewhat nasty edge of his street work into a suitably physical, rough-and-tumble darkroom technique. The images resonate with Surrealism, animation, political cartooning and, most recently, photo appropriation. They give further expression to the instinct for brutality and beauty, often in tandem, that made him famous in the first place.</p>
        <p>ROBERTA SMITH</p>
        <p>ART IN REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
