<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Windup, Where Are the Pitchers?</title>
    <meta content="07BASE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213031"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chass, Murray</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Houston Astros</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000707T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E3DD1638F934A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="942" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Windup, Where Are the Pitchers?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Murray Chass</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chass, Murray</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Murray Chass column on problems of New York Yankees pitchers as team faces doubleheader against New York Mets; tables; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When the Yankees proposed making up their rained out game with the Mets tomorrow night as part of a movable feast of New York baseball -- Queens in the afternoon, the Bronx in the evening -- they didn't realize the dire straits their starting pitching would be in.</p>
        <p>Their pitching, after all, had been the engine that drove them to three World Series championships in four years, and who would have thought it would crumble into something Edgar Allan Poe referred to in one of his short stories, ''The Facts in the Case of M. Valdemar,'' ''a nearly liquid mass of loathsome -- of detestable putridity.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When the Yankees proposed making up their rained out game with the Mets tomorrow night as part of a movable feast of New York baseball -- Queens in the afternoon, the Bronx in the evening -- they didn't realize the dire straits their starting pitching would be in.</p>
        <p>Their pitching, after all, had been the engine that drove them to three World Series championships in four years, and who would have thought it would crumble into something Edgar Allan Poe referred to in one of his short stories, ''The Facts in the Case of M. Valdemar,'' ''a nearly liquid mass of loathsome -- of detestable putridity.''</p>
        <p>What, the Yankees' pitching isn't that bad? Of course it is, when they are forced to remove David Cone from the rotation for the first time in his life and when they drag Dwight Gooden off the scrap heap of discarded major league pitchers and throw him into what could be their most important series of the season. Did someone say panic?</p>
        <p>What a turn of events. In five previous series since the advent of interleague play in 1997, the Yankees have played the Mets as the superior team, at least the one with the better won-lost record and the better position in the standings. But when they meet at Shea Stadium tonight for the first game of the four-game series, the Yankees will have a 42-37 record, the Mets 47-35.</p>
        <p>The Mets will also have the more stable starting rotation. Not that such stability guarantees victory, but the Mets should be buoyed by the contrast in the development of their starting corps and the deterioration of the Yankees' crew.</p>
        <p>Even Bobby J. Jones has pitched impressively since his return from the disabled list: three starts, two victories, no losses, a 2.25 earned run average and a six-inning shutout performance in the one start he didn't win.</p>
        <p>It will be Jones who pitches against the reinvented Gooden in the Queens share of tomorrow's festivities. The scenario could be an audition for a Hollywood script: a pitcher considered by other major league teams to be finished trying desperately to salvage his career against the team with which he attained stardom, then undermined by his use of substances that weren't resin and pine tar.</p>
        <p>Gooden has never pitched against the Mets. The closest he came was in 1997, when he pitched for the Yankees the first time around. He started against Florida in the game before the Yankees played the Mets for the first time in interleague play, and he pitched against Cleveland in the game immediately after the series with the Mets.</p>
        <p>By the 1998 intracity series, Gooden was no longer a member of the Yankees, and he didn't last with the Astros long enough this season to pitch for them against the Mets (the teams have yet to play each other and won't until next month).</p>
        <p>Gooden didn't last with the Astros because, in the view of Larry Dierker, the Astros' manager and former pitcher, he had only ''average stuff'' with less than precision control. He lasted a little longer with the Tampa Bay Devil Rays, but even that team, despite a serious need for pitching help, released him.</p>
        <p>In his last 15 2/3 innings with the Devil Rays, Gooden gave up 9 home runs, giving him a total of 15 allowed in 40 2/3 innings with both teams. He permitted 17.5 baserunners per nine innings in nine starts, had a career-high 6.86 E.R.A. and allowed opposing teams to hit .319 against him and compile a .645 slugging percentage.</p>
        <p>But he developed a new pitch, a cut fastball, working for the Yankees in the lowest-level minor league, and now he is ready to reclaim a spot in the majors. On the other hand, anyone who blinks might miss him.</p>
        <p>The Yankees are scrambling to find five able-armed starters. The Mets like the ones they have, beginning with Al Leiter, whose start against the Yankees tonight will be the latest in a terrific season.</p>
        <p>Leiter has a history in these games. Last season he pitched and won the game against the Yankees that ended an eight-game Mets losing streak and ignited a run to the playoffs. Last month he pitched the first game of the first series between the teams and won that one, too. The Yankees beat Jones in the second game, and then the third was rained out, setting the stage for the two-borough doubleheader tomorrow.</p>
        <p>Some members of the Mets aren't thrilled with the idea of the split doubleheader. But the way the Yankees have been playing they should be more concerned with the prospect of losing two games 10 miles apart than the Mets.</p>
        <p>Leading up to the first series between the teams, the Yankees won 11 of 26 games (.423); since the series, they have won 9 and lost 13 (.409). The Mets had a 15-9 (.625) record in the same period before the series and have compiled a 13-8 (.619) record since.</p>
        <p>Despite the disparity in their records, both teams are elbow-deep in contention for their division championships. The Yankees are there because the American League East is having trouble identifying a team that is good enough to take control. The Mets are there because they have capitalized on stumbling steps suffered by the Atlanta Braves.</p>
        <p>The weekend series won't determine the continued presence of the Yankees and the Mets in their championship quest, but it figures to tell the Yankees more about themselves than it does the Mets. And that, for a change, is different.</p>
        <p>ON BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
