<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Subway Signal Inspections Under Review</title>
    <meta content="07SIGN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213060"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Subways</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York City Transit</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Metropolitan Transportation Authority</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kennedy, Randy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Malan, Roland M (Inspector General)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Subways</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000707T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02EFDB1638F934A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="729" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Subway Signal Inspections Under Review</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RANDY KENNEDY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kennedy, Randy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York City Transit officials say Roland M Malan, Metropolitan Transportation Authority inspector general, is investigating charges that supervisors who oversee subway's signal system failed to make hundreds of inspections; notes all signals in question were routinely inspected by signal maintenance crews (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The inspector general for the Metropolitan Transportation Authority is investigating allegations that supervisors who oversee the subway's signal system failed to make hundreds of inspections of the lights that direct trains throughout the city.</p>
        <p>Officials with New York City Transit said yesterday that they had learned of the allegations late last year from the inspector general, Roland M. Malan, and that transit investigators had determined that even if the allegations were true, safety would not have been compromised, because all the signals in question had been routinely inspected by signal maintenance crews.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The inspector general for the Metropolitan Transportation Authority is investigating allegations that supervisors who oversee the subway's signal system failed to make hundreds of inspections of the lights that direct trains throughout the city.</p>
        <p>Officials with New York City Transit said yesterday that they had learned of the allegations late last year from the inspector general, Roland M. Malan, and that transit investigators had determined that even if the allegations were true, safety would not have been compromised, because all the signals in question had been routinely inspected by signal maintenance crews.</p>
        <p>But a person with knowledge of the inspector general's investigation and who spoke on the condition of anonymity said that that office was looking into whether a team of supervisors had ever actually completed back-up inspections of as many as 2,500 signals from April through July of last year in Manhattan, Brooklyn, Queens and the Bronx.</p>
        <p>The investigation, triggered last fall by an anonymous letter to the inspector general, whose office conducts independent investigations within the M.T.A., is focusing on whether the signal maintenance supervisors falsified inspection reports to say that the back-up inspections had been carried out, when in fact they had not been, the person said.</p>
        <p>Under New York City transit procedures, all signal and switch inspections are supposed to be routinely double-checked by supervisors.</p>
        <p>''The allegation was that because the supervisors' inspections were behind, all of a sudden management decided they had to catch up, so hundreds of extra inspections were entered into the database as having been done that had not been done,'' the person said.</p>
        <p>In addition, the person said, when the supervisors were questioned by investigators from the inspector general's office, they could not say with certainty whether they had completed the inspections in question. And time cards showed that some inspectors had not worked on the days when records indicate that they performed the inspections.</p>
        <p>Al O'Leary, the chief spokesman for New York City Transit, said yesterday that Mr. Malan's office had discussed the allegations with the transit agency because the inspector general's office considered the allegations a potential threat to the safety of passengers.</p>
        <p>But Mr. O'Leary added that it was transit officials' understanding from those discussions that no inspection reports had been falsified. Instead, Mr. O'Leary said, the agency understood that the supervisors had entered a computerized code indicating that they had done only a visual inspection of the signals and also of some related switches, the mechanisms that shift trains from one track to another.</p>
        <p>But the supervisors are also required to make physical inspections of the equipment, using tools, and the allegations were that that part of the job was not done, leaving many backup inspections incomplete, Mr. O'Leary said. It alerted transit officials to a possible shortage of supervisors, he said, adding that the agency was investigating the problem.</p>
        <p>Mr. O'Leary said that after a B train derailed while passing over a switch at the DeKalb Avenue station in downtown Brooklyn last month, transit inspectors checked the switches and were confident that all periodic inspections -- both initial and back-up -- had been performed.</p>
        <p>The subway system has around 11,000 signals, most along simple stretches of track and some connected to switches that change trains' routes. The Transit Authority's 123 signal supervisors oversee 971 signal maintainers, Mr. O'Leary said. It is unclear how many supervisors are alleged to have been negligent.</p>
        <p>Nicholas P. Kapur, a supervising associate general counsel for the inspector general's office, would say only that the office was ''in the process of conducting an investigation that is related to signal inspections.''</p>
        <p>Roger Toussaint, a leader of the New Directions Caucus, a faction of the Transport Workers Union, contended yesterday that a longstanding shortage of signal and switch supervisors had contributed to a backlog of secondary inspections and that supervisors were under constant pressure to catch up.</p>
        <p>''To anyone who works in the system, this is not news at all,'' said Mr. Toussaint, a former track worker and the chairman of the union's track division. ''It is not at all uncommon for inspection reports to be signed off on without being performed.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
