<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>We Can't Tell the Missiles From the Mylar</title>
    <meta content="07POST$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213032"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Missiles and Missile Defense Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Defense Department</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Postol, Theodore A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lewis, George N</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Missiles and Missile Defense Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000707T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E2DD1638F934A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="617" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>We Can't Tell the Missiles From the Mylar</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Theodore A. Postol and George N. Lewis</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lewis, George N; Postol, Theodore A</byline>
      <dateline>CAMBRIDGE, Mass.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Op-Ed article by Thoeodore A Postol and George N Lewis of Massachusetts Institute of Technology on inherent flaw in Defense Department's missile defense technology: that it can easily be fooled by decoys; says Pres Clinton should appoint an independent commission of accomplished scientists who are not connected to Pentagon to look into claims being made about this ill-conceived system; says Americans, before forking over $60 billion, deserve an answer to obvious question of whether missile defense will work (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A success in today's well-publicized test of a missile defense weapon system, the Clinton administration claims, will establish that national missile defense technology is ready for deployment. But unfortunately, bagging the sort of precooked and strapped-down chicken of a target that is being used today will do nothing of the sort. If Americans want a real test of the Pentagon's missile defense system, they should insist that it be designed by someone other than the Pentagon.</p>
        <p>The Defense Department discovered a program-stopping flaw in its system in tests three years ago: The system can easily be fooled by decoys nearly as simple as the traffic cones we encounter on the street or the Mylar balloons that are so popular at the zoo.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A success in today's well-publicized test of a missile defense weapon system, the Clinton administration claims, will establish that national missile defense technology is ready for deployment. But unfortunately, bagging the sort of precooked and strapped-down chicken of a target that is being used today will do nothing of the sort. If Americans want a real test of the Pentagon's missile defense system, they should insist that it be designed by someone other than the Pentagon.</p>
        <p>The Defense Department discovered a program-stopping flaw in its system in tests three years ago: The system can easily be fooled by decoys nearly as simple as the traffic cones we encounter on the street or the Mylar balloons that are so popular at the zoo.</p>
        <p>The first response to this discovery was to try to conceal it. Then the Defense Department dumbed down all the development tests planned for the missile defense program so the somewhat different version of the so-called ''kill vehicle'' that is now being used would never have to be tested against competently designed, simple decoys.</p>
        <p>In the near-vacuum of space where the missile defense would operate, there is no air drag to cause light decoys to move differently from heavy warheads, so it is relatively easy to create cheap impostors. The Pentagon has stated that for the 100-interceptor defense system that President Clinton is likely to recommend, the kill vehicle -- the interceptor that ''shoots down'' the incoming missile -- will have the primary responsibility for picking out the warhead. Since all the objects the kill vehicle will see are far away, they will appear as points of light -- like stars in the night sky -- all moving in about the same way.</p>
        <p>Instead of the 10 objects that confounded the kill vehicle in the first test, in 1997, today's test, like the two before it, will use only a single mock warhead and a large balloon. The balloon has been carefully designed to be nearly 10 times brighter than the warhead, and the kill vehicle will be programmed to home in on the dimmer of the two targets.</p>
        <p>The Pentagon claims that the warhead and the ineffective large balloon decoy it is testing against are representative of the missile threat from an idealized imagined adversary -- an adversary presumed to be capable of building intercontinental range ballistic missiles and nuclear warheads that are sufficiently light and compact to be mounted on such missiles, but at the same time so bungling as to be unable to hide the warhead inside a Mylar balloon decoy released along with empty balloons or to build warhead-shaped cone decoys.</p>
        <p>A recent technical study by the Union of Concerned Scientists and the M.I.T. security studies program showed that the same simple countermeasures that can defeat the kill vehicle could also defeat all of the other sensors envisioned in the Clinton administration plan.</p>
        <p>If every one of the currently planned national missile defense tests proved to be an unqualified success, we would be still stuck with a defense system that had not been realistically tested and would have no hope of performing successfully in a real-world attack.</p>
        <p>What the country needs, and what the president should give us, is an independent commission of accomplished scientists who are not connected to the Pentagon to look into the claims being made about this ill-conceived national missile defense system. Before forking over $60 billion to pay for such a system, Americans deserve an answer to the obvious question of whether it will work.</p>
        <p>Theodore A. Postol is professor of science, technology, and national security policy at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology. George N. Lewis is associate director of M.I.T.'s security studies program.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Theodore A. Postol is professor of science, technology, and national security policy at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology. George N. Lewis is associate director of M.I.T.'s security studies program.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
