<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Teams Wooing as Fast as They Can to Land Hill</title>
    <meta content="07HOOP$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213107"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Orlando Magic</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Broussard, Chris</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hill, Grant</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Orlando Magic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000707T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E6D81638F934A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="616" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Teams Wooing as Fast as They Can to Land Hill</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRIS BROUSSARD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Broussard, Chris</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Basketball teams continue to woo Grant Hill, despite signs that he plans to join Orlando Magic (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Picture the Knicks' Scott Layden, the Nets' Rod Thorn, Miami's Pat Riley, San Antonio's Gregg Popovich and Chicago's Jerry Krause standing in a hotel lobby making small talk while each nervously awaits his turn to speak with the coveted Grant Hill. The goings-on in Detroit this week have not been that dramatic, but that is essentially what is taking place.</p>
        <p>Representatives from those five teams visited Hill this week to try to sell the Detroit Pistons star on their franchise.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Picture the Knicks' Scott Layden, the Nets' Rod Thorn, Miami's Pat Riley, San Antonio's Gregg Popovich and Chicago's Jerry Krause standing in a hotel lobby making small talk while each nervously awaits his turn to speak with the coveted Grant Hill. The goings-on in Detroit this week have not been that dramatic, but that is essentially what is taking place.</p>
        <p>Representatives from those five teams visited Hill this week to try to sell the Detroit Pistons star on their franchise.</p>
        <p>With Hill having all but slipped into an Orlando Magic uniform after last weekend's visit to Disney World, the extra efforts may be wasted time, but even in the National Basketball Association, teams must give it that old college try.</p>
        <p>''We're hopeful,'' said an official from a team that recently met with Hill. ''We're obviously hoping that the reports of him going to Orlando are not true. We want him to take his time to make a decision. He owes it to himself and his family to take a long, hard look at his options.''</p>
        <p>Options abound for the five-time All-Star, who will likely turn his team of choice into an immediate conference contender. The Knicks met with Hill in a suburb of Detroit on Wednesday, and the San Antonio Spurs met with him later that day.</p>
        <p>The Nets, a surprise entry in the Hill sweepstakes, made their pitch yesterday morning, and Miami and Chicago are believed to have met with Hill yesterday afternoon.</p>
        <p>Every one of those teams is a long shot to land Hill, who has stated publicly that he is ''leaning strongly'' toward signing with Orlando. Proof of his preference for the Magic is the fact that he flew to Orlando on Saturday and went house hunting with his wife, Tamia, on Monday. Unlike everyone else, the Magic did not have to run to Hill.</p>
        <p>''It feels great, but it will feel greater when we -- if we -- can sign him on Aug. 1,'' Orlando General Manager John Gabriel said yesterday of the privilege his team was afforded. ''We expected there would be interviews by all of the candidates.''</p>
        <p>For the Knicks to acquire Hill, a sign-and-trade deal most likely involving Latrell Sprewell and Marcus Camby would have to be worked. What is unfounded is the talk of the Knicks' signing Hill for the $2.25 million midlevel exception and then giving him a maximum money contract the next season. The Knicks will not have the salary cap room to make such an offer.</p>
        <p>Layden and Coach Jeff Van Gundy confirmed that they had met with Hill but would not comment. The Knicks are hoping to get him to visit New York soon, but no date has been set.</p>
        <p>The Nets, who are in the process of revamping their franchise, would also have to work a sign-and-trade deal for Hill. Keith Van Horn would likely be involved, and the Nets would also have to throw in a couple of other players, perhaps Jamie Feick and Elliot Perry, to satisfy base-year compensation rules.</p>
        <p>San Antonio and Miami are in similar situations. Both offered Hill the $2.25 million exception for this season and then will be in position to give him a six-year contract worth at least $90 million next season.</p>
        <p>Several players around the league have said that Hill's top priority is playing with a top-flight big man; both San Antonio and Miami would qualify.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
