<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bradley Will Offer Support To Gore Soon, Officials Say</title>
    <meta content="Y07BRA$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213058"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE FORMER OPPONENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions, National (US)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dao, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mitchell, Alison</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bradley, Bill</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000707T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04EFDB1638F934A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="792" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bradley Will Offer Support To Gore Soon, Officials Say</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES DAO and ALISON MITCHELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dao, James; Mitchell, Alison</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Democratic officials say former Sen Bill Bradley will end months of silence and appear alongside Vice Pres Al Gore in a week to voice his 'enthusiastic support' for the man who trounced him in bitterly contested primary; appearance would come at time when Gore is working hard to unify party in time for national convention in August (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ending months of silence, former Senator Bill Bradley plans to appear alongside Vice President Al Gore next week to voice what Democratic officials described as his ''enthusiastic support'' for the man who trounced him in the bitterly contested Democratic presidential primaries last spring, Democratic officials said last night.</p>
        <p>Though details of the joint event were still being thrashed out, the officials said the two men were expected to meet in an important swing state at a rally next Thursday in Green Bay, Wis. The officials said the appearance might be just the first of several joint events before the November election.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ending months of silence, former Senator Bill Bradley plans to appear alongside Vice President Al Gore next week to voice what Democratic officials described as his ''enthusiastic support'' for the man who trounced him in the bitterly contested Democratic presidential primaries last spring, Democratic officials said last night.</p>
        <p>Though details of the joint event were still being thrashed out, the officials said the two men were expected to meet in an important swing state at a rally next Thursday in Green Bay, Wis. The officials said the appearance might be just the first of several joint events before the November election.</p>
        <p>The appearance comes just as Mr. Gore is working hard to unify the party in time for the Democratic National Convention in Los Angeles next month, the event many Democrats are counting on to give his campaign a lift going into the home stretch this fall.</p>
        <p>In recent days, Mr. Gore has been trying to energize the Democratic base in his public appearances by using such tactics as attacking the oil and pharmaceutical industries.</p>
        <p>Smoothing things over with Mr. Bradley would be an important step in energizing the party, many Democrats say. A cloud of bitterness has hung over the relationship between Mr. Gore and Mr. Bradley since Mr. Bradley quit the race in March without having carried a single state. Some Democrats contend that friction has hurt Mr. Gore's ability to present a united front for the party.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bradley was furious with what he considered Mr. Gore's dishonest attacks on his campaign agenda, particularly his proposal for universal health care. At the news conference where he announced his withdrawal from the race, Mr. Bradley said he would support the vice president, but he refused to use the word ''endorse.''</p>
        <p>He also said he would not release the roughly 400 delegates he had won until the party's convention, raising the possibility that he might start policy fights with the vice president's camp. And he chided Mr. Gore for a hard-edged campaign style, a criticism the Republicans have repeatedly echoed in recent months.</p>
        <p>''I hope that he'll run a better campaign in the general election,'' Mr. Bradley said of Mr. Gore at the time.</p>
        <p>A Democratic official familiar with the current negotiations said Mr. Bradley would ''make it very clear that the vice president has his enthusiastic support.'' The official said it was even possible that Mr. Bradley would use the word ''endorse,'' though Mr. Bradley is well-known for changing his mind on such tactical matters at the last minute.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bradley's unequivocal support could help take the edge off Republican assertions that Mr. Gore is a dirty fighter and dishonest politician who will do or say whatever it takes to win. And because Mr. Bradley received much support from Republicans and independents, he could help Mr. Gore woo swing voters who are likely to determine the outcome in closely contested states.</p>
        <p>Discussions about when Mr. Bradley would campaign with Mr. Gore had been going on for several months, primarily between Tony Coelho, the former head of the Gore campaign, and John Roos, a fund-raiser and confidant to Mr. Bradley. William M. Daley, who replaced Mr. Coelho and has a good relationship with Mr. Bradley, picked up the negotiations when Mr. Coelho quit last month.</p>
        <p>The two sides have also agreed on Mr. Bradley's role at the convention, one official said. The official said Mr. Bradley would address the convention in a prominent slot, possibly in prime time. The official would not say on which day Mr. Bradley would speak.</p>
        <p>With Mr. Gore starting to draw starker contrasts between himself and his expected Republican rival, Gov. George W. Bush of Texas, this seemed like the right time for the two former rivals to appear together, an aide to Mr. Gore said.</p>
        <p>''We're beginning to ramp into the convention,'' he said. ''It's a good time for all Democrats to come together and focus on the task at hand. The differences between Gore and Bradley are minuscule compared to the miles of differences between them and George W. Bush.''</p>
        <p>The aide continued, ''Both Gore and Bradley were in favor of improving our health care system, and George W. Bush has not offered anything of substance.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE FORMER OPPONENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
