<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Teeming Courts, Finding Strength in Family Ties</title>
    <meta content="07FAMI$09" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213091"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rohde, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000707T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE0D91638F934A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1806" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Teeming Courts, Finding Strength in Family Ties</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID ROHDE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rohde, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Courtrooms and hallways of New York City's courthouses are filled each day with families of defendants and victims, a stream of human traffic driven by surging arrest rates and crowded court calendars; majority of families are those who have long been seen in criminal court--the poor; but lately, working-class families who have never before had brushes with the law are arriving in shock after a loved one is arrested and jailed overnight for minor 'quality of life' offense; experts say that, whatever family's background, their presence in court can be a critical factor in balance of justice by humanizing defendant standing before judge and jury; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The families fill the courtrooms and hallways of New York City's courthouses each day, a stream of human traffic driven by surging arrest rates and crowded court calendars.</p>
        <p>In some cases they arrive in force: parents, siblings and children determined to show support for a loved one with their sheer numbers. But in most cases they are women who arrive alone or with young children they cannot leave at home: a solitary mother, wife or girlfriend intent on supporting a scorned defendant, or serving as a poignant reminder of a murder victim.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The families fill the courtrooms and hallways of New York City's courthouses each day, a stream of human traffic driven by surging arrest rates and crowded court calendars.</p>
        <p>In some cases they arrive in force: parents, siblings and children determined to show support for a loved one with their sheer numbers. But in most cases they are women who arrive alone or with young children they cannot leave at home: a solitary mother, wife or girlfriend intent on supporting a scorned defendant, or serving as a poignant reminder of a murder victim.</p>
        <p>They are the families of the accused and the victims, and they are all in some form of mourning. They say their experiences in the courthouses are grim, but can also be cathartic. They also often display striking grace and loyalty.</p>
        <p>A majority of families are those that have long been seen in the criminal courts -- the poor. But defense lawyers say that they have seen a different type of family arrive in recent years as the city's quality-of-life crackdown continues. More working-class families who have never before had brushes with the law arrive in shock after a loved one is arrested and jailed overnight for a minor offense, like driving with a suspended license.</p>
        <p>''The quality-of-life arrests suck up a lot of people who have never been in trouble before,'' said David Kapner, a defense lawyer who supervises arraignments for the Legal Aid Society in Manhattan. ''And those are the people who are more likely to have their families show up in court. There are more teenagers for drinking beer, or immigrants for peddling.''</p>
        <p>But whatever the family's background, one longstanding legal truism endures: the concept of family remains a potent weapon in court. Despite high divorce rates and the far-flung nature of modern families, relatives are still expected to support one another. Interviews with judges, jurors, prosecutors and defense lawyers suggest that the presence of family members can have an impact, great or small, on the outcome of a trial or arraignment. The presence of these families, some tattered, some durably faithful, can be a critical factor in the balance of justice.</p>
        <p>A frantic wife or a grieving mother staring intently at a judge or jury can humanize a defendant or a murder victim, they said. And the lack of any family members in the audience -- a situation that roughly half of defendants face -- can further sully the accused.</p>
        <p>''It's very important for juries. It shows that a defendant's family hasn't abandoned them,'' said Acting Justice John P. Walsh of State Supreme Court, a former police inspector who supervises the city's arraignment courts. ''Psychologically for jurors, if it's a close case, it will have an impact.''</p>
        <p>Judges said that jurors sometimes did not realize the subtle emotional impact families had on them by sitting in a courtroom. Jurors also may disregard instructions to pay no attention to the audience, the judges said.</p>
        <p>Jurors in the first trial of Andrew Goldstein, a schizophrenic man convicted in March of murdering Kendra Webdale by pushing her in front of a subway, were instructed to draw no inference from the failure of Mr. Goldstein's family to testify in his defense or to attend his trial.</p>
        <p>But several jurors said they found the absence of Mr. Goldstein's family suspicious. And after Mr. Goldstein's first trial ended in a hung jury last November, several jurors apologized to members of Ms. Webdale's family and hugged them in front of the courthouse. Jurors said they owed it to the Webdale family to have reached a verdict. They said they had noticed the victim's relatives sitting resolutely in the courtroom each day.</p>
        <p>But the human tales that play out in the courtrooms and the crowded, often loud, sometimes menacing hallways of the courthouses typically do not receive much notice. The families come intent on doing the right thing and on perhaps gaining an edge in the legal fight.</p>
        <p>One morning last month in the Manhattan Criminal Courts Building was typical of a justice system in which a thousand people a day are arrested and thousands of cases are handled every week.</p>
        <p>Rosa Cabrera, 49, wept as she, her husband, her two daughters, her daughter-in-law and her nephew walked into the lobby desperately searching for her son, who she said had been arrested by immigration officials.</p>
        <p>''I would get run over by a bus or a train if that would make them let him go,'' said Ms. Cabrera, who sobbed and said she was afraid her son would be deported.</p>
        <p>Down the hall, Blanca Santiago, 18, sat on the floor waiting with her father-in-law for her husband to be released. The husband had been arrested and accused of selling flowers without a permit. A few feet away, a Chinese immigrant tried to comfort his two children as he and his sister-in-law tried to find out when his wife would be released after being arrested on a charge of buying untaxed cigarettes.</p>
        <p>Ms. Cabrera and Ms. Santiago were typical of the people who wait in the building's lobby for the release of husbands, boyfriends and sons who had been arrested. Anguished conversations on the bank of pay phones that line the lobby wall are common. Family members break the news that someone has been arrested, try to hire a lawyer or struggle to raise bail money.</p>
        <p>Most of the women are financially dependent on the men, defense lawyers said. Mothers who say they have no place to leave their children take them to the courthouse. At night, strollers and crying infants are common sights and sounds.</p>
        <p>''They say, 'I'm looking for my baby's father,' '' said Sgt. Stephen Crisafulli, a court officer who supervises the lobby.</p>
        <p>Mothers who struggle to keep the children quiet in courtrooms often retreat to the hallways. There, the children play impromptu games, sitting on the floor or running in circles and shrieking as their mothers wait.</p>
        <p>On a recent Wednesday night, Angela Medina, 18, gave her 1-month-old son a bottle as she sat in the lobby waiting for her sister's boyfriend to be released. ''I want to support him and my sister,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Other cases sometimes draw immigrant families who arrive in force. During one night-court shift, 12 relatives of a woman from Senegal who was arrested in a domestic dispute arrived at 1 a.m. to find her. The group included her 2-month-old niece.</p>
        <p>Some parents and spouses accept defendants' claims that they were victims of false arrests by officers overzealously enforcing the city's quality-of-life crackdown. But others fly into a rage at their loved ones.</p>
        <p>The most heated confrontation in the Manhattan Criminal Courts Building in the last several years was between a father and son, Sergeant Crisafulli said. The father, who had spent time in prison, flew into a rage after his own son was arrested. ''How could you do this! I work every day for you!'' the father thundered as court officers restrained him.</p>
        <p>''He was really ripping the boy to keep him from going down the same path,'' the sergeant said. ''It was fear and frustration, not anger.''</p>
        <p>Judges said that in less serious cases, defendants' ties to their families were factors in how much bail they set or whether they offered plea bargains involving probation or drug rehabilitation programs.</p>
        <p>''If he's got a mother, brother, sister and wife sitting in the audience, it shows he has a support system,'' Justice Walsh said. ''That support system is important for him to take his medicine.''</p>
        <p>But defense lawyers said that the presence of families could also complicate matters. Some young defendants will refuse to plead guilty in front of their mothers, for example, if they have sworn to their parents that they did not do the crimes. Other family members give terrible legal advice, the lawyers said.</p>
        <p>While the building's ground floor is filled with families usually suffering smaller heartaches, its upper floors are lined with families enduring far larger ones. There, defendants face more serious felony charges, most involving drugs, that can result in years in prison.</p>
        <p>Racial and class tensions can also hover over the courtrooms. Poor families frequently complain that their loved ones receive longer sentences because they cannot afford ''a real lawyer,'' and that fury finds expression in the court buildings. After a drug addict who killed a man with his car while on PCP was sentenced to 15 years in prison last month, one of his relatives shouted, ''Let it be a Mercedes-Benz, and you'll walk away no problem.''</p>
        <p>Many family members seem to fall into stereotypical roles in the courthouse, judges and lawyers said. Mothers generally attend trials religiously and are better able to express their emotions, they said. Fathers, by contrast, appear intermittently and seem to struggle with their anger.</p>
        <p>Many relatives on the building's upper floors are hoping to influence judges or to simply catch a glimpse of a jailed defendant during a brief court appearance. In January, the mother, two aunts, girlfriend and three cousins of Victor Rhymer, 19, waited hours for him to be sentenced for robbing a man of his beeper.</p>
        <p>''It's not a strain to come here because we love him,'' his aunt Claudette Rhymer said.</p>
        <p>Courthouse veterans said that explaining the continuing power of families in the court system was simple. Jurors and judges, like all people, may groan about their own nagging mothers, distant fathers and crazy siblings. But blood is still expected to bind.</p>
        <p>''The fact of the matter is that if you're alone in this world, it's much harder to rehabilitate yourself,'' said Mr. Kapner, the Legal Aid lawyer. ''But if you have some people in your life, you have a better chance of pulling yourself together. Intuitively, judges and juries understand that too.''</p>
        <p>Defense lawyers and judges say one of the most depressing sights in court is the roughly 50 percent of defendants who arrive alone, with no family members. Many are long-term drug abusers whose addictions have shattered their ties to their families.</p>
        <p>''Some of them are acquitted, and they walk out of the courtroom and there is no one there,'' said David Stern, a Manhattan defense lawyer. ''Some are convicted and no one sheds a tear.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
