<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Curling Up With an E-Book</title>
    <meta content="07BOLI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213018"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bolick, Robert</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000707T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E3DE1638F934A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="600" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Curling Up With an E-Book</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Robert Bolick</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bolick, Robert</byline>
      <dateline>DARIEN, Conn.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Op-Ed article by Robert Bolick, a vice president of McGraw-Hill, in praise of electronic books; noting possibilities for links to other information, as well as to sound and animation, says e-book is a challenge to authors and publishers, as well to readers, to master words, sense and form in a new way (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I was reading a good book the other day on the train home: ''Extraordinary Popular Delusions and the Madness of Crowds.'' Before I knew it, the train was stopping, and I was scrambling to gather my things to get off. So? So, the book was an electronic book: I was reading it on a hand-held computer.</p>
        <p>Like Elmore Leonard's ''Be Cool'' or ''The Education of Henry Adams'' or Stephen King's ''Riding the Bullet'' -- all of which I also read as e-books --  that book had pulled me into its world.  It didn't matter that I was looking at a screen, that I was tapping and pushing buttons to advance the text in readable chunks; just as if I were sitting with a good print book and turning pages, nothing mattered but the magic of the book itself.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I was reading a good book the other day on the train home: ''Extraordinary Popular Delusions and the Madness of Crowds.'' Before I knew it, the train was stopping, and I was scrambling to gather my things to get off. So? So, the book was an electronic book: I was reading it on a hand-held computer.</p>
        <p>Like Elmore Leonard's ''Be Cool'' or ''The Education of Henry Adams'' or Stephen King's ''Riding the Bullet'' -- all of which I also read as e-books --  that book had pulled me into its world.  It didn't matter that I was looking at a screen, that I was tapping and pushing buttons to advance the text in readable chunks; just as if I were sitting with a good print book and turning pages, nothing mattered but the magic of the book itself.</p>
        <p>Less than a year ago, there were only a few thousand e-books, stored at universities, readable only over the Internet on computer screens and only as scrolling text. Today, there are tens of thousands, available across different formats and several devices. But still, that is not nearly enough.</p>
        <p>The Association of American Publishers has created a task force for e-book standards, some major publishers are launching e-book initiatives and almost all of our university presses have experimented with the technology. One of our key national booksellers is leading in the selling of  e-books. But the sense of urgency should be greater -- not only for the sake of the book business, which must adapt to the digital world, but also for readers.</p>
        <p>Some of those readers are ready now. When a friend of mine who works for an e-bookseller told her son's school class about her job, children waved Gameboys in the air and asked, ''When can we read our books on these?'' College students and professionals now spend more time doing research on the Web than in libraries: e-books are the natural next step.</p>
        <p>With e-books, I can carry around 50 pounds of books in a device weighing a couple of pounds, or have access to vast libraries wherever I can log on to the Web, or share a good book with a blind friend because an e-book can be read aloud by software.</p>
        <p>And with its possibilities for links to other information, like reference books and maps, as well as to sound and animated diagrams, the e-book is a challenge to authors and publishers, as well as readers, to master words, sense and form in a new way.</p>
        <p>To be engrossed in a writer's argument, stumble over a word I thought I knew and be able to look it up on the page, on the screen, right there and then, with a movement of thumb and forefinger -- that speeds my growth as a reader. Or to be able to seek out the passages that interest me with a search engine rather than an inadequate or nonexistent index -- that gives me a map of my own discovery.</p>
        <p>Like the personal computer before it, the e-book opens a world of possibilities. It is not necessarily better than printed books, nor need it supplant them. But its time is here.</p>
        <p>Robert Bolick is a vice president at McGraw-Hill.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Robert Bolick is a vice president at McGraw-Hill.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
