<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gillette goes to the extreme with ads featuring Tom Green.</title>
    <meta content="Y07ADC$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213004"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Deodorants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Gillette Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bbdo New York</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lauro, Patricia Winters</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Green, Tom</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Advertising (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Deodorants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cosmetics and Toiletries</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000707T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06EED61F39F934A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1100" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gillette goes to the extreme with ads featuring Tom Green.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Patricia Winters Lauro</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lauro, Patricia Winters</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Tom Green, outrageous MTV comedian, is introducing Gillette Co's Right Guard Xtreme Sport deodorant in $61 million TV and print campaign; move is change for Gillette, which had relied on burly athletes as deodorant pitchmen in the past; BBDO New York developed campaign; photo (Advertising column) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TOM GREEN, the outrageous MTV comedian, is best known for stunts like dropping a live mouse into his mouth, as he does in the hit gross-out comedy film ''Road Trip,'' or snorkeling for change in a shopping mall fountain.</p>
        <p>Not exactly the kind of guy typically embraced by corporate America, right?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TOM GREEN, the outrageous MTV comedian, is best known for stunts like dropping a live mouse into his mouth, as he does in the hit gross-out comedy film ''Road Trip,'' or snorkeling for change in a shopping mall fountain.</p>
        <p>Not exactly the kind of guy typically embraced by corporate America, right?</p>
        <p>Wrong.</p>
        <p>Gillette has introduced a television and print campaign using Mr. Green to endorse Right Guard, a brand built over the last dozen years on the imagery of big, burly athletes like Emmitt Smith, Charles Barkley and Brett Favre. The Right Guard campaign, carrying the theme ''Anything less would be uncivilized,'' has helped the brand maintain its status as the leading deodorant-antiperspirant in America.</p>
        <p>Has Gillette gone mad in choosing Mr. Green?</p>
        <p>The appearance of anti-establishment entertainment figures in a variety of advertisements may be evidence of a shift in attitude from earlier generations. The use of songs by popular bands like the Red Hot Chili Peppers to advertise automobiles and Mr. Green's serving simultaneously as celebrity pitchman and anarchistic cable television comedian suggest that today's fans do not view such commercial activity as ''selling out.''</p>
        <p>The skinny Mr. Green -- seemingly the antithesis of an athlete -- was actually carefully selected by Gillette to pitch a new product called Right Guard Xtreme Sport, developed with the much-sought-after young male consumer in mind. Even the brand's name capitalizes on a youthful trend -- the popularity of extreme sports like bungee jumping, mountain biking and snowboarding. The sports are definitely not in the mainstream, which brings Gillette to Mr. Green.</p>
        <p>''Tom stood out as a unique personality and often his character is extreme,'' said Bernadette King, director of global business management for antiperspirants and deodorants at Gillette in Boston. ''He is free-spirited, high energy and always can make people laugh.''</p>
        <p>In focus groups, Mr. Green came up as a person boys and young men liked, Ms. King said, adding that additional research suggested to the company that the best way to reach young men was through humor and information they deemed useful.</p>
        <p>''They really don't want to hear a product story, but they want some product information,'' Ms. King said. ''They are saying, 'Tell me, give me a reason,' but they don't want to be bored to death and they don't want anything too intense or too scientific.''</p>
        <p>As a result, the introductory campaign, like the comic, does not take itself too seriously. The spots show Mr. Green, who is 28, reporting as if live from Muscle Beach, where he appears to be unleashing a trailer full of tigers on unsuspecting weight lifters to create extreme conditions.</p>
        <p>As the tigers wreak havoc, Mr. Green mugs for the camera, claiming, for example, to prove the product's effectiveness by rubbing Xtreme Sport on the forehead of a weight lifter trying to climb over a chain-link fence while a tiger is pursuing him.</p>
        <p>''He's great at shocking humor,'' Al Merrin, executive creative director at BBDO New York, the Right Guard agency, said of Mr. Green, who is in the midst of a well-publicized bout with cancer. ''There's a kind of sweetness about him; he gets away with the most outrageous stuff. And the kids like it.''</p>
        <p>BBDO New York, part of the BBDO Worldwide unit of the Omnicom Group, was looking for a new approach for the new product and sought to avoid demonstrations of the drama and energy of extreme sports, which have been commonplace in campaigns for brands aimed at younger consumers, like those for Mountain Dew, also produced by BBDO New York.</p>
        <p>Ironically, while extreme sports are popular as a backdrop for advertising, celebrities of the sports have yet to be tapped by corporate America, said Nova Lanktree, president of Lanktree Sports Celebrity Network in Chicago.</p>
        <p>''I see a lot of commercials, like car commercials, of wild involvement between man and nature, but you don't see the face of an extreme athlete -- they haven't emerged as stars and I don't know why,'' Ms. Lanktree said. ''The sports are kind of wild, hip and fun -- very MTV, so I think you would get a lot of bang for your buck with Tom Green if that's the audience you're targeting.''</p>
        <p>Right Guard has long been a top brand for Gillette, but its sales, like those of the entire $1.7 billion deodorant-antiperspirant category, are sluggish. Right Guard has a 9 percent share of the market, followed by Degree, made by Unilever, with 8.7 percent, and Mennen Speed Stick, made by Colgate-Palmolive, with 7.3 percent, according to Information Resources Inc., a market research company.</p>
        <p>Gillette decided to go after the youth market mainly because of its growth potential, Ms. King said, but it also recognized that boys as young as 10 are interested in appearance and are a factor behind the popularity of fragrances like Tommy. With that in mind, Ms. King said, Xtreme Sport is offered in light citrusy scents like Cool Peak and Fresh Blast.</p>
        <p>''In looking at the demographic trends, we saw a huge influx coming of echo boomers,'' she added, referring to the so-called Generation Y children of baby boomers. ''We want to make sure Right Guard is their brand of choice.''</p>
        <p>But Right Guard is not alone. Speed Stick sponsors televised coverage of the X Games and Gravity Sports. And last month, Mennen reformulated and repositioned Speed Stick Ultimate to reach men under 25, introducing fragrances like Glacier and Power Zone.</p>
        <p>Right Guard is not Mr. Green's first foray into advertising. Madison Avenue was unusually swift in spotting Mr. Green, who auditioned for his MTV series in 1998. PepsiCo Inc. used Mr. Green in 1999, shortly after his MTV show began, for a promotional campaign for Pepsi One linked to the N.C.A.A. championship tournament. Those commercials, also created by BBDO New York, featured his antics in visits to college campuses; they were well received, according to executives at Pepsi-Cola, but Mr. Green no longer appears in ads for the brand.</p>
        <p>The Right Guard Xtreme Sport campaign is the first from BBDO New York since the agency won the Right Guard brand account last year from Saatchi &amp; Saatchi in New York. Gillette plans to spend $61 million in total marketing and advertising to introduce the new deodorant in the United States.</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
