<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mexico Victor Faces Choices On Economy</title>
    <meta content="Y07PES$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213034"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hiring and Promotion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Foreign Investments</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cabinets and Sub-Cabinets</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mexico</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Depalma, Anthony</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fox Quesada, Vicente</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Investments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hiring and Promotion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000707T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04EEDD1638F934A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1510" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mexico Victor Faces Choices On Economy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY DePALMA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Depalma, Anthony</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Investors, analysts and business leaders are beginning to ask how Pres-elect Vicente Fox Quesada intends to handle complex economic issus facing Mexico and whether he has much leeway in the interconnected global economy that he says he wants Mexico to remain part of; Fox has made it clear he intends to stay economic course--opening Mexico to global economy and embracing free-market discipline--set by previous administrations, but he has made it equally clear he is not happy with the way that many Mexicans have been left behind; one of Fox's first economic tasks will be to name economic cabinet that inspires investor confidence in a party that has never run Mexico; graph; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Instead of the turmoil that many feared a close election in Mexico could set off, Vicente Fox Quesada's seven-percentage-point victory margin, wider by far than most polls had predicted, has buoyed the spirits not just of Mexican voters but of investors and business executives across North America.</p>
        <p>The Mexican peso strengthened immediately after the election, the Mexican stock market hit a three-month high before dropping back a bit, and American investors generally were delighted -- not necessarily because Mr. Fox won, but because the decisive way he won kept Mexico calm and open for business.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Instead of the turmoil that many feared a close election in Mexico could set off, Vicente Fox Quesada's seven-percentage-point victory margin, wider by far than most polls had predicted, has buoyed the spirits not just of Mexican voters but of investors and business executives across North America.</p>
        <p>The Mexican peso strengthened immediately after the election, the Mexican stock market hit a three-month high before dropping back a bit, and American investors generally were delighted -- not necessarily because Mr. Fox won, but because the decisive way he won kept Mexico calm and open for business.</p>
        <p>But as people get used to the idea that Mexico's 71 years of one-party rule are coming to an end, investors, analysts and business leaders are beginning to ask just how Mr. Fox, a former Coca-Cola executive, intends to handle the complex economic issues facing his country. And there are questions whether, in the interconnected global economy that he says he wants Mexico to remain part of, he has much leeway at all.</p>
        <p>''First there was this euphoria, then everybody was standing around scratching their head,'' said John M. Bruton, executive vice president of the American Chamber of Commerce in Mexico City. ''People of all classes voted for him because they think he can change their situations. Now, managing expectations is going to be Mr. Fox's greatest challenge.''</p>
        <p>So much of the campaign was focused on change for the sake of change that other issues did not get much attention. There was never much distance between the economic platforms of the principal candidates, and throughout the campaign Mr. Fox avoided laying out a detailed program of economic change. Instead, he offered standard campaign promises of increasing jobs, promoting investment and producing economic growth that would help the millions of Mexicans living in poverty.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fox has made it clear that he intends to stay the economic course -- opening Mexico to the global economy and embracing free-market discipline -- set by previous administrations, but he has made it equally clear that he is not happy with the way that many Mexicans have been left behind. He supports an independent central bank, a free-floating exchange rate and increased exports. He even said earlier this week that the North American Free Trade Agreement should be amplified to further integrate North America, perhaps with a common currency for Mexico, the United States and Canada, ''20, 30 or 40 years from now.''</p>
        <p>But he is facing many far more immediate issues, including the millions of Mexicans who have never recovered the purchasing power they had before the first of several end-of-administration crises in the early 1980's.</p>
        <p>''A lot of Mexicans feel their economic circumstances have gotten worse and they expect results very quickly,'' said Joyce Chang, global head of fixed-income research at Chase Securities in New York. ''Fox has to be careful about how he handles expectations.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Fox has a reputation as a pragmatist when it comes to business and the economy. As governor of the small state of Guanajuato, he started a program of providing loans for very small businesses as a way of promoting entrepreneurship, and he intends to repeat the program on the national level. He has also talked about copying Chile's program of providing tax relief for companies that reinvest in Chile.</p>
        <p>One of Mr. Fox's first economic tasks will be to name an economic cabinet that inspires investor confidence in a party that has never run Mexico. He is said to be considering a treasury secretary from the ruling Institutional Revolutionary Party, known as the PRI. One name being mentioned is Luis Tellez, the current energy secretary.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fox must also prepare a federal budget that by law has to be approved -- by a congress his party does not control -- within 15 days of his inauguration on Dec. 1.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fox's chief economic adviser, Luis Ernesto Derbez, a former World Bank official who is often mentioned as a possible treasury secretary under Mr. Fox, told investors in New York yesterday that work on the budget had already begun.</p>
        <p>Mr. Derbez said Mexican political leaders had been asked to outline budget priorities, and preliminary talks were under way with the PRI, as well as with the left-leaning Party of the Democratic Revolution, to gauge the limits of cooperation. Mr. Fox wants to name his cabinet by the end of August and present a budget proposal by Sept. 1.</p>
        <p>Analysts will be watching to see how Mr. Fox squares his campaign promise to increase spending for education and social programs with his pledge to decrease the current budget deficit by half. Mr. Derbez said legislation would be introduced to close tax loopholes. He also said the government would consider extending the value-added tax to medicine and food -- but only if there was a way to soften the effect on the poor.</p>
        <p>John B. Chambers, deputy head of the sovereign ratings group at Standard &amp; Poor's, said his company's analysts would be following the budget process and the fall legislative session in Mexico City for clues to whether the major parties will cooperate or stumble into gridlock.</p>
        <p>Another rating company, Moody's Investors Services, upgraded Mexico's debt to investment grade in early March, but Standard &amp; Poor's did not. This week, S.&amp; P. affirmed its rating of one notch below investment grade, with a positive outlook for an upgrade if the new administration takes care of some pending issues.</p>
        <p>''It really is a question of how effective we think the Fox administration is going to be in implementing the structural reform agenda,'' Mr. Chambers said. ''Clues on that could come as early as the fourth quarter of this year.'' S.&amp; P. says it will be watching for further strengthening of Mexico's banking system and deregulation of the electricity and petroleum sectors.</p>
        <p>The last three Mexican administrations ended with currency devaluations and economic turmoil. Fears of another crisis diminished with the strength of Mr. Fox's victory, and the continuing strength of Mexico's economy. Jonathan E. Heath, a Mexican economist who wrote a book on the causes of the end-of-administration crises, says most of the factors that caused them -- a fixed exchange rate and an oversized current accounts deficit, for example -- have been eliminated.</p>
        <p>''There's still the slim possibility of a shock that would be caused by an assassination attempt on Fox,'' Mr. Heath said, ''but barring something weird like that, the chances of another crisis are very slim.''</p>
        <p>Rather than a meltdown, some investors are worried that the post-election ecstasy could actually make Mexico's economy overheat just as the United States economy begins to show signs of slowing down. The first two days after the election, the Mexican stock market jumped 8.2 percent, but profit taking wiped away some of that gain, leaving the market up 5.1 percent since the vote.</p>
        <p>''Consumption, capital inflows, domestic investment, foreign direct investment, all are increasing because of this injection of confidence,'' said Jorge O. Mariscal, chief Latin American investment strategist for Goldman, Sachs. ''The thing to do now is slow down the Mexican economy using fiscal and monetary means. Fox needs to address that in the transition.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Mariscal said that for him one incident best described the current mood of excitement and uncertainty in Mexico. Just before the election, a  manufacturer in Mexico City who supported Mr. Fox loaded barrels of fragrances on a pickup truck and drove around the city's main highway. He wanted voters to know that the possibility of change was so real they could smell it.</p>
        <p>But something went wrong: a barrel spilled onto the roadway, and there was a multicar pileup.</p>
        <p>''Mexico,'' Mr. Mariscal said, ''still presents tremendous challenges.''</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
