<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Programmed For Breeding And Bonding</title>
    <meta content="07BIG" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213028"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE BIG CITY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Love (Emotion)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Magnetic Resonance Imagers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Brain</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tierney, John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fisher, Helen (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/John Tierney</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Magnetic Resonance Imagers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Brain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Emotions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000707T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E5DD1638F934A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="817" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Programmed For Breeding And Bonding</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN TIERNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tierney, John</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>John Tierney column on anthropologist Helen Fisher's efforts to use magnetic resonance imaging to analyze which parts of brains of romantically infatuated New Yorkers are activated by thoughts of the beloved to test her theory that human brain evolved with circuitry to promote pair-bonding for at least four years; notes Dr Fischer believes brain promotes what she identifies as three aspects of love: lust, attraction and attachment (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN trying to explain why his affections had shifted from his wife to another woman, Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani told a news conference, ''The fact that we've grown independent, we've grown more separate over the years -- who knows why those things happen?'' If he really wants an answer, he might enroll in Helen Fisher's experiment. She's ready to scan his brain.</p>
        <p>Dr. Fisher, an anthropologist at Rutgers University, has been trying to find out why people fall in and out of love by putting romantically infatuated New Yorkers into a magnetic resonance imaging machine. Working with scientists at Albert Einstein Medical College and the State University of New York at Stony Brook, she is analyzing which parts of the brain are activated by thoughts of the beloved.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN trying to explain why his affections had shifted from his wife to another woman, Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani told a news conference, ''The fact that we've grown independent, we've grown more separate over the years -- who knows why those things happen?'' If he really wants an answer, he might enroll in Helen Fisher's experiment. She's ready to scan his brain.</p>
        <p>Dr. Fisher, an anthropologist at Rutgers University, has been trying to find out why people fall in and out of love by putting romantically infatuated New Yorkers into a magnetic resonance imaging machine. Working with scientists at Albert Einstein Medical College and the State University of New York at Stony Brook, she is analyzing which parts of the brain are activated by thoughts of the beloved.</p>
        <p>Dr. Fisher is testing a grand unified theory of love that she began developing after noticing a pattern in divorce statistics from around the world: in all types of societies, the peak time for a couple to divorce tends to be in the fourth year of the relationship. Dr. Fisher believes the cycle is the remnant of our ancestors' breeding season.</p>
        <p>''Among hunter-gatherers,'' she said, ''it's my guess that a male and female had to stay together at least until the child was walking and weaned and could be cared for by others. So the human brain evolved with the circuitry to promote pair-bonding for at least four years. It's like robins in Central Park who are programmed to stay together for one breeding season.''</p>
        <p>The human brain promotes what Dr. Fisher identifies as three distinct aspects of love: lust, attraction and attachment. Lust is triggered by testosterone and gives an initial impetus to find a partner. Then comes attraction, the romantic infatuation that Dr. Fisher attributes partly to low levels of serotonin, the chemical associated with Prozac and feelings of well being.</p>
        <p>In selecting infatuated New Yorkers for her experiment, Dr. Fisher was looking for those in the throes of what psychologists call ''intrusive thinking,'' and what songwriters call ''can't stop thinkin' 'bout my baby.'' Intrusive thinking about your mate, like obsessive-compulsive disorders, has been linked to low levels of serotonin.</p>
        <p>Other commonly reported symptoms of romantic love are euphoria, hyperactivity, loss of appetite and sleeplessness. Dr. Fisher believes they're triggered by high levels of dopamine and norepinephrine -- natural stimulants activated by drugs like cocaine and amphetamines.</p>
        <p>PEOPLE love being in love because it's a chemical high,'' Dr. Fisher said. ''But the high often ends after about a year, probably because the brain produces less of the chemicals or the receptor sites become dulled. Romantic love wears off -- as it should, or we'd all die of sexual exhaustion. It evolved so you could distinguish between potential mating partners and conserve your mating energy by focusing on just one.''</p>
        <p>By the time your energy has produced a child, your brain has moved on to the next phase, attachment, which produces feelings of security, comfort and spiritual union with a long-term partner. Dr. Fisher believes it is triggered by higher levels of vasopressin and oxytocin, which have been demonstrated to trigger attachment in animals. Attachment is a more durable emotion than lust or infatuation, but it too can wane -- or eventually be overridden by other emotions.</p>
        <p>''The rub is that these different systems in the brain aren't always very well connected,'' Dr. Fisher said. ''You can feel deep attachment for one individual while you feel romantic love for someone else while you feel lust for a stranger in a magazine. You might get all three together when you're walking up the aisle to be married, but the brain isn't built to keep it that way forever. We're built to be restless in long-term relationships.''</p>
        <p>When divorce does come, it involves more than just the emotion-inducing chemicals in the brain. Humans also evolved with a prefrontal cortex capable of rationally overriding those extramarital temptations. The prospect, say, of winning a United States Senate seat might be enough to keep a certain man -- or a certain woman -- in a marriage when the chemicals are no longer flowing.</p>
        <p>''We have only so much mating energy, and we have to decide how to spend it,'' Dr. Fisher said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani fits the stereotype for the high-profile divorce in New York: the alpha male dumping his wife after he gains power or money. But most divorces are actually instigated by women, for reasons that are only just becoming apparent to researchers. More on that next week.</p>
        <p>THE BIG CITY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
