<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Costs and Delays Stir Clash Over a Breast Cancer Center</title>
    <meta content="07HEWL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213072"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hewlett House (Hewlett, NY)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Breast</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Nassau County (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blakeman, Bruce A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cooper, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Breast Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Breast</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000707T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E3DA1638F934A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="890" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Costs and Delays Stir Clash Over a Breast Cancer Center</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL COOPER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cooper, Michael</byline>
      <dateline>GARDEN CITY, N.Y., July 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Nassau County Legislature holds hearing into delays and cost overruns plaguing Hewlett House, breast cancer resource center, which has still not opened after three years of work; Bruce A Blakeman, former legislator, defends project, which he spearheaded; says county did not realize how costly it would be to renovate historic farmhouse; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Members of the Nassau County Legislature used to describe it as one of their proudest achievements: a plan to open a resource center for women with breast cancer and their families in a restored 18th-century farmhouse.</p>
        <p>But three years have passed since they began work on the project, called Hewlett House, and although the cash-strapped county and the state have spent nearly $1.5 million -- three times what they originally projected -- the center has still not opened.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Members of the Nassau County Legislature used to describe it as one of their proudest achievements: a plan to open a resource center for women with breast cancer and their families in a restored 18th-century farmhouse.</p>
        <p>But three years have passed since they began work on the project, called Hewlett House, and although the cash-strapped county and the state have spent nearly $1.5 million -- three times what they originally projected -- the center has still not opened.</p>
        <p>The county's leaders have found plenty of room for blame and recriminations.</p>
        <p>The county comptroller released an audit critical of the county executive. The executive began an investigation of the comptroller's investigation. And today the Democratic-controlled County Legislature held a hearing on the project. The first witness? Bruce A. Blakeman, who was the Republican presiding officer of the Legislature until he lost his seat and the Republicans lost their majority in last November's elections.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Blakeman defended the project, which he spearheaded, noting that the county bought the old, historic farmhouse for just one dollar and explaining that the county did not realize how costly renovations would prove to be, he was questioned by Jeffrey W. Toback, the Democrat who won his legislative seat from him in November.</p>
        <p>''Was it typical of the Legislature to get into projects in which the total cost was unknown?'' Mr. Toback asked the man who ran the Legislature for four years.</p>
        <p>Mr. Blakeman, who now is the chairman of the Hewlett House advisory council, did not answer, except to say: ''That's a loaded question.''</p>
        <p>In fact, the story of Hewlett House is one of spiraling costs and long delays. After the county bought the ramshackle farmhouse on East Rockaway Road in Hewlett in 1997, the Legislature approved $250,000 to fix it up. Republicans said they knew all along that it was just ''seed money'' to start the project; Democrats said they were led to believe that the renovation could be completed for that amount.</p>
        <p>At the time, officials estimated the total cost of the renovations would be $500,000. A 1998 document titled ''Capital Project Lifetime Budget''  gave the cost as $488,000. The project was entrusted to Friends for Long Island's Heritage, a citizens' group that raises money and helps restore historic properties for the county.</p>
        <p>But now, driven up by unforeseen troubles and the constraints of renovating a historic house, the total cost is believed to be more than $1.5 million. And despite a series of deadlines that have come and gone -- there was even a ceremonial ribbon-cutting and photo opportunity outside Hewlett House shortly before Election Day in 1998 -- the restoration is not expected to be completed until late October at the earliest, and it will take several months more to get the center up and running.</p>
        <p>Today, Mr. Blakeman criticized the heritage group, saying that it did not do enough to inform the county of the rising cost projections. Gerald S. Kessler, the president of the group, disputed that, and said his group had been hampered because the Legislature was so slow to give it the money it needed to pay contractors.</p>
        <p>Breast cancer has long been a potent political issue on Long Island. Concerned by the high incidence of the disease here, many women's groups mobilized and became a political force to be reckoned with. They successfully pushed for cancer studies and free mammograms.</p>
        <p>But at times, the intersection of health and politics has been less than smooth: when Geri Barish, the executive director of Hewlett House, made a radio commercial for George W. Bush this year, it did not sit well with some people. Soon afterward, Democrats moved to cut her county salary, which was part of their payroll, saying she should be paid by the Health Department. Last week, County Executive Thomas S. Gulotta, a Republican, said he would find money for her somewhere in the county budget.</p>
        <p>But the Hewlett House experience has troubled many people here. The county comptroller, Frederick E. Parola, who described the project as a ''money pit,'' said in an audit last month that the county could have bought a 7,600-square-foot luxury home or rented three easier-to-get-to centers for the same amount of money that was sunk into restoring the out-of-the-way 2,385-square-foot farmhouse.</p>
        <p>Stung, Mr. Gulotta directed his commissioner of accounts to conduct an investigation of the investigation. The report called Mr. Parola's report ''flawed and incomplete.''</p>
        <p>Stuck in the middle, Ms. Barish said she would just like to see Hewlett House open so that she could provide women with counseling, cooking classes, legal help and advice on where to get help or buy wigs. ''If we had to do it all over again, would we have asked for $250,000 to buy a new house?'' she asked. ''You bet.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
