<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>So Which One is Mommy Dearest?</title>
    <meta content="26COME$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/26/arts/26COME.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233776"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEW YORK FILM FESTIVAL REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">New York Film Festival</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Scott, A O</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ruiz, Raul</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Comedy of Innocence, The (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews/By A. O. Scott</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New York Film Festival</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New York Film Festival</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000926T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407EFDD153AF935A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="729" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>So Which One is Mommy Dearest?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By A. O. SCOTT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Scott, A O</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>A O Scott reviews Raul Ruiz movie The Comedy of Innocence, presented at New York Film Festival; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>At the center of ''The Comedy of Innocence'' is a round-faced, apple-cheeked moppet named Camille (Nils Hugon) who lives in serene haut-bourgeois elegance in an old house in Paris. Shortly after his ninth birthday, Camille, whose closest companions are a possibly imaginary friend named Alexandre and a video camera, starts behaving strangely. He insists that his name is Paul and starts addressing his mother (Isabelle Huppert), with cold formality, by her first name, which is Ariane. Soon he has dragged her halfway across the city to the chic bohemian apartment of the woman he claims is his real mother, a flighty violin teacher named Isabella (Jeanne Balibar), whose son drowned two years earlier.</p>
        <p>What is going on here? Some kind of strange supernatural event? Is this the latest movie to explore the possibility of parallel realities, to imagine a kind of lived hypertext? For its first hour, Raul Ruiz's film, adapted from a novel by the Italian writer Massimo Bontempelli called ''The Boy With Two Mothers,'' weaves an elegant spell of epistemological confusion. The quiet, elegant Parisian interiors take on a spooky, claustrophobic feel, which is intensified by the odd behavior of the people who inhabit them. Camille's uncle Serge (Charles Berling), a psychiatrist, is prone to odd mood swings; the au pair, Helene, sulks passive-aggressively around the house; and Isabella has a creepy neighbor whose most banal utterances sound mysterious, even threatening.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>At the center of ''The Comedy of Innocence'' is a round-faced, apple-cheeked moppet named Camille (Nils Hugon) who lives in serene haut-bourgeois elegance in an old house in Paris. Shortly after his ninth birthday, Camille, whose closest companions are a possibly imaginary friend named Alexandre and a video camera, starts behaving strangely. He insists that his name is Paul and starts addressing his mother (Isabelle Huppert), with cold formality, by her first name, which is Ariane. Soon he has dragged her halfway across the city to the chic bohemian apartment of the woman he claims is his real mother, a flighty violin teacher named Isabella (Jeanne Balibar), whose son drowned two years earlier.</p>
        <p>What is going on here? Some kind of strange supernatural event? Is this the latest movie to explore the possibility of parallel realities, to imagine a kind of lived hypertext? For its first hour, Raul Ruiz's film, adapted from a novel by the Italian writer Massimo Bontempelli called ''The Boy With Two Mothers,'' weaves an elegant spell of epistemological confusion. The quiet, elegant Parisian interiors take on a spooky, claustrophobic feel, which is intensified by the odd behavior of the people who inhabit them. Camille's uncle Serge (Charles Berling), a psychiatrist, is prone to odd mood swings; the au pair, Helene, sulks passive-aggressively around the house; and Isabella has a creepy neighbor whose most banal utterances sound mysterious, even threatening.</p>
        <p>But after a while the atmosphere starts to feel less haunting than irritating. Mr. Ruiz might have approached this material with Hitchcockian precision or Bunuelesque insouciance. Either of these directors would have pushed the confusion to some kind of dramatic or comic peak, but ''The Comedy of Innocence'' is content, like Ariane, to wander and brood.</p>
        <p>Events that should at least provoke a tremor of surprise -- why does Isabella move in with Ariane? Why does Ariane permit it? -- unfold so casually that they seem less mysterious than matter of fact. Ms. Huppert, a peerless purveyor of stifled melancholy, played a similar role -- a sorrowful, wealthy wife wandering the sepulchral halls of her ritzy home -- in Benoit Jacquot's ''Pas de Scandale.'' But she suffers with such passive stoicism that she robs the film of a psychological perspective it desperately needs.</p>
        <p>On Ariane's living room wall hangs an etching of King Solomon settling a quarrel between two women arguing over a baby. In the Bible story, the real mother is the one who offers the child to her rival, rather than stand by while the king cuts the baby in half. (The picture, Serge comments, is ''a bit too pertinent.'' I agree.) Perhaps Ariane's stunned acquiescence to Isabella's intrusion is proof that she loves Camille more.</p>
        <p>But psychological motive is not the film's primary concern. Rather, Mr. Ruiz seems enchanted with his own coyness and the curlicues and indirections the story allows him. He makes enthusiastic use of the video-within-the-film, which allows him to vary the movie's visual texture. But this technique is fast becoming tired and tiresome, and here it feels teasing and pretentious. The film's labored climax turns on the revelation that someone has been playing an elaborate mind game. This doesn't come as news: the mind game is ''Comedy of Innocence'' itself, and the perpetrator has been Mr. Ruiz all along.</p>
        <p>THE COMEDY OF INNOCENCE</p>
        <p>Directed by Raul Ruiz; written (in French, with English subtitles) by Francoise Dumas and Mr. Ruiz, based on a novel by Massimo Bontempelli; director of photography, Jacques Bouquin; edited by Mireille Hannon; music by Jorge Arriagada; set designer, Bruno Beauge; produced by Martine de Clermont-Tonnerre; released by Winstar Cinema. Running time: 98 minutes. This film is not rated. Shown with a 15-minute short, Felicity Morgan-Rhind's ''Donuts for Breakfast'' tonight at 6 and Thursday night at 9 at Alice Tully Hall as part of the 38th New York Film Festival.</p>
        <p>WITH: Jeanne Balibar (Isabella), Charles Berling (Serge), Laure de Clermont-Tonnerre (Helene), Nils Hugon (Camille), Isabelle Huppert (Ariane), Denis Podalydes (Pierre) and Edith Scob (Laurence).</p>
        <p>NEW YORK FILM FESTIVAL REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
