<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Shares Fall as Investors Worry About Earnings Reports</title>
    <meta content="Y26STO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/26/business/26STOX.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233841"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE MARKETS: STOCKS &amp; BONDS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dow Jones Stock Average</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Standard &amp; Poor's 500-Stock Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nasdaq Composite Index</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gilpin, Kenneth N</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dow Jones Stock Average</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nasdaq Composite Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000926T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E2D7153AF935A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="713" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Shares Fall as Investors Worry About Earnings Reports</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KENNETH N. GILPIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gilpin, Kenneth N</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Nasdaq composite index falls 62.54 points, or 1.6 percent, to 3,741.22; Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index falls 9.69 points, or 0.7 percent, to 1,439.03; Dow Jones industrial average slips 39.22 points, or 0.4 percent, to 10,808.15; graph; charts (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Stock prices slipped again yesterday, pulled down by continued worries about coming earnings reports from big technology companies.</p>
        <p>It appeared during morning trading that the impact of Intel's warning late Thursday about a shortfall in its third-quarter revenue figures had entirely dissipated. The Nasdaq composite index opened higher and remained in positive territory for a good part of the session.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Stock prices slipped again yesterday, pulled down by continued worries about coming earnings reports from big technology companies.</p>
        <p>It appeared during morning trading that the impact of Intel's warning late Thursday about a shortfall in its third-quarter revenue figures had entirely dissipated. The Nasdaq composite index opened higher and remained in positive territory for a good part of the session.</p>
        <p>But sellers began to lighten or eliminate positions in big-cap technology names later on, reasoning that if Intel was having problems, other companies must be having trouble, too.</p>
        <p>''The fact that Intel spoke to a secular issue, meaning demand, and not a cyclical one, meaning currency, suggests that if they are having a demand slowdown so are a bunch of the rest of the gang,'' said Arthur Hogan, chief market analyst at Jefferies &amp; Company in Boston.</p>
        <p>Pulled down by a further decline in Intel plus drops in bellwether issues like Microsoft and Cisco Systems, the Nasdaq composite index fell for a third consecutive session, dropping 62.54 points, or 1.6 percent, to 3,741.22.</p>
        <p>The Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index fell 9.69 points, or 0.7 percent, to 1,439.03. And the Dow Jones industrial average slipped 39.22 points, or 0.4 percent, to 10,808.15.</p>
        <p>Five stocks fell for every four that rose in price on the New York Stock Exchange. Volume on the Big Board was 990 million shares. Just under 2 billion shares changed hands on the Nasdaq stock market.</p>
        <p>Weakness in big technology stocks masked a good performance in other sectors of the market.</p>
        <p>Financial service stocks did better, helped by a decline in market interest rates and a further drop in spot oil prices. Shares of biotechnology companies had a good day. And most big pharmaceutical stocks were good performers.</p>
        <p>But large-cap technology names got most of the attention.</p>
        <p>Intel, which plunged 22 percent on Friday after it issued its revenue warning, fell again yesterday. The stock closed at $45.38, down $2.56.</p>
        <p>Cisco was another big loser, dropping $3.13, to $57.19. Hewlett-Packard dropped $6.25, to $98. And I.B.M. closed at $121.75, down $2.25.</p>
        <p>Among Nasdaq stocks, Network Appliance was a big loser. It closed at $130.44, down $16.94, after an analyst from Wit Soundview said the company was likely to see revenue growth slow.</p>
        <p>Ciena, by contrast, was a big winner on the Nasdaq. The fiber optic equipment maker jumped $6.81, to $127.56, after it said Korea Telecom had agreed to use Ciena systems for Internet and data-network traffic in Seoul and other cities in the country.</p>
        <p>--------------------</p>
        <p>Treasuries Rebound  By Bloomberg News</p>
        <p>Treasury bonds and notes rebounded yesterday after stocks erased gains and fell, bolstering demand for fixed-income securities as safe-haven investments.</p>
        <p>The 10-year Treasury note rose 3/32, to a price of 99 11/32. The note's yield, which moves in the opposite direction from the price, fell to 5.84 percent from 5.85 percent on Friday.</p>
        <p>The price of the 30-year Treasury bond rose 9/32, to 104 31/32. The bond's yield fell to 5.89 percent from 5.91 percent on Friday.</p>
        <p>''Stocks are probably the most important'' focus for bonds, along with falling oil prices and then the euro, said Michael Cloherty, a strategist at Credit Suisse First Boston. Declines in stocks can ''help bonds slightly, but you'd have to see them really breaking lower to get much of a reaction,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Results of yesterday's Treasury auctions of 3-month and 6-month bills:</p>
        <p>(000 omitted in dollar figures)</p>
        <p>3-Mo. Bills</p>
        <p>6-Mo. Bills</p>
        <p>Price</p>
        <p>98.482</p>
        <p>96.974</p>
        <p>High Rate</p>
        <p>6.00%</p>
        <p>5.98%</p>
        <p>Investment Rate</p>
        <p>6.18%</p>
        <p>6.25%</p>
        <p>Low Rate</p>
        <p>5.95%</p>
        <p>5.90%</p>
        <p>Median Rate</p>
        <p>5.99%</p>
        <p>5.96%</p>
        <p>Total applied for</p>
        <p>$28,080,867</p>
        <p>$28,610,714</p>
        <p>Accepted</p>
        <p>$14,625,917</p>
        <p>$13,129,964</p>
        <p>Noncompetitive</p>
        <p>$1,160,309</p>
        <p>$1,634,551</p>
        <p>Both issues are dated Sept. 28, 2000. The three-month bills mature on Dec. 28, 2000, and the six-month bills mature on March 29, 2001.</p>
        <p>THE MARKETS: STOCKS &amp; BONDS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
