<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Athletes' Injuries Go Beyond the Physical</title>
    <meta content="26SPOR$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Health &amp; Fitness" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/26/science/26SPOR.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233767"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tarkan, Laurie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Other Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000926T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE7DD153AF935A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1476" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Athletes' Injuries Go Beyond the Physical</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAURIE TARKAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tarkan, Laurie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Athletes who suffer injuries, even weekend athletes, are susceptible to depression, anxiety and other psychological symptoms, including nightmares, flashbacks to the accident, moodiness, irritability, fatigue, insomnia, weight gain and low self-esteem; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A month after badly breaking her left leg and blowing out her right knee in a skiing crash in Switzerland, Picabo Street, the fearless, spunky media darling of the 1998 Nagano Olympics, shut herself in the bedroom of her parents' house and closed the blinds. She would not let family or friends in, she took no phone calls, did not watch television, did nothing for weeks but lie there in the darkened room thinking miserable thoughts.</p>
        <p>''I went through a huge depression,'' Ms. Street said. ''I went all the way to rock bottom. I never thought that I ever would experience anything like that in my life.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A month after badly breaking her left leg and blowing out her right knee in a skiing crash in Switzerland, Picabo Street, the fearless, spunky media darling of the 1998 Nagano Olympics, shut herself in the bedroom of her parents' house and closed the blinds. She would not let family or friends in, she took no phone calls, did not watch television, did nothing for weeks but lie there in the darkened room thinking miserable thoughts.</p>
        <p>''I went through a huge depression,'' Ms. Street said. ''I went all the way to rock bottom. I never thought that I ever would experience anything like that in my life.''</p>
        <p>What sent her hurtling into a depression was the realization of how long and difficult her recovery would be. In the end, it took 20 months.</p>
        <p>''I think it was a combination of the atrophying of my legs, the new scars, and feeling like a caged animal,'' Ms. Street said. ''I went from being a very physical person, a very powerful athlete, to barely having any strength to get from my room to the kitchen. You're stuck and you can't do what you normally do and it makes you crazy.''</p>
        <p>Last year, Liesl Reichelt, 31, an investment banker and runner, famous only in her circle of friends and family, stepped off a high curb on her way to Central Park, landed hard and herniated a disk in her spine.</p>
        <p>When her doctor told her to quit running for a few months, Ms. Reichelt became depressed, moody and irritable, and she gained weight. Then things started to snowball. She could no longer take criticism at work, and she began to hate her boss, her job and New York.</p>
        <p>''I was constantly snapping at my boyfriend,'' said Ms. Reichelt, who now is running again. ''All I did was complain about not running. It just left such a void, and there wasn't anything I could think of doing to fill it.''</p>
        <p>For those athletes who made it to Sydney but were injured before or in their events, their agony was palpable.</p>
        <p>But a suddenly sidelined athlete doesn't have to be competing on the world stage to feel depressed. Even injured weekend athletes are susceptible to depression, anxiety and other psychological symptoms, including nightmares, flashbacks to the accident, moodiness, irritability, fatigue, insomnia, weight gain and low self-esteem.</p>
        <p>''In the running world, it's expected that you get depressed if you get injured,'' said Shelly-Lynn Florence, a running coach with the New York Road Runners Club.</p>
        <p>It is hard to pin down how common depression is among injured athletes; research in this field of sport psychology is limited. But one study of 343 male college athletes from a variety of sports found that 51 percent had some symptoms of depression after being injured, and 12 percent became moderately to severely depressed.</p>
        <p>''I'd say one out of every four or five of the injured athletes who come to our center suffer from depression,'' said Dr. Gerald Kaforey of the Vanderbilt Sport Medicine Center at the Vanderbilt Medical School.</p>
        <p>Those who do get depressed may stay that way for several weeks after being injured, their mood lifting only as their injuries begin to heal. Some athletes, especially those with longer recovery periods, may stay depressed for months. And in rare instances, injured athletes have attempted or committed suicide.</p>
        <p>Emotional reactions to injury may also affect how well people comply with the rehabilitation regimens and how quickly and completely they recover, according to research.</p>
        <p>Despite this, only about 2 percent of sports medicine centers have psychologists  available to help patients, Dr. Kaforey said. Although professional and Olympic athletes increasingly turn to sports psychologists, these experts are usually called on to improve the performance of great athletes, not to lift the moods of those on crutches.</p>
        <p>''We virtually ignore the psychological dynamics surrounding sport injury,'' said Dr. Jane Crossman, who is editing a book on how to help athletes cope with injury.</p>
        <p>One reason the sports world may be slow to acknowledge the emotional fallout of an injury is the stigma some see in needing help.</p>
        <p>Dr. Deborah Saint-Phard, who treats patients at the Women's Sports Medicine Center of the Hospital for Special Surgery in Manhattan said, ''There's a pervasive sense that athletes are superhuman, not only in their abilities to perform athletically, but also in their morals, their ability to handle pain, disappointment and injury.'' Dr. Saint-Phard, a former Olympic shot-putter, is a physiatrist, a doctor who specializes in rehabilitation.</p>
        <p>Athletes themselves take on these expectations and may not reveal to others how much they are suffering. Nicole Detling, who tore her a ligament in her knee while playing basketball in college a few years ago, could not take people feeling sorry for her, so she withdrew into her dorm room.</p>
        <p>''I was an athlete,'' Ms. Detling said. ''I not only had all this physical strength, but I had mental strength. And being injured was a huge kind of weakness.''</p>
        <p>Early theories held that injured athletes went through the stages of grief that Elizabeth Kubler-Ross defined in her groundbreaking book ''On Death and Dying'' -- denial, anger, bargaining, depression and acceptance.</p>
        <p>While some psychologists still believe this model applies, most reserve it for those athletes who are injured so severely that they cannot return to their sport. ''For a pro or college athlete, a serious injury could be very similar to losing a loved one, because that's their vitality, that's their life,'' Dr. Kaforey said.</p>
        <p>Initially, athletes can feel a deep sense of loss or a void in their lives. They lose not only the actual physical activity, but the gratification they get from competing and the social aspects of the sport. They may also lose that feeling of invulnerability and absolute trust in their bodies. Elite athletes may lose the fame, the travel, and sometimes the endorsements or salaries.</p>
        <p>With time away from their sport, athletes also lose a piece of identity, especially if they earned recognition for their athleticism early in life.</p>
        <p>''If all the sudden you can't be an athlete, it sends you into a bit of an existential crisis in terms of, 'Who am I, and what am I doing here?' '' Dr. Saint-Phard said.</p>
        <p>This identity crisis can be particularly hard for younger athletes, especially today.</p>
        <p>Children now tend to specialize in one or two sports at a young age, instead of being involved in three or four, said Dr. Aynsley Smith, research director of the Sports Medicine Center at the Mayo Clinic in Rochester, Minn.</p>
        <p>''All the eggs are in one basket,'' Dr. Smith said. ''They have significant goals, so many letters they want to earn. So when injury comes, it's devastating for them. They often feel it has totally wiped out almost their reason for being.''</p>
        <p>With people coming to sports as a way of moderating depression or stress, warding off illnesses like heart disease or cancer, or to lose weight, the stakes are higher. When injured, they not only have to deal with the pain and stress of being injured, but they have lost a primary coping strategy.</p>
        <p>Moody and depressed, some injured athletes are often left to brood by themselves.</p>
        <p>Athletes complain that their friends and family members are not always sympathetic.</p>
        <p>''If you're a nonathlete, it's hard to understand the importance sports plays in someone's life,'' Dr. Crossman said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Detling, the former basketball player, said: ''I explained myself over and over for a short time, and then I got frustrated with it. Because no matter how much detail I'd give, they would look at me with a blank face that said, 'I don't really get it.' ''</p>
        <p>Picabo Street came out of her depression and her bedroom on Mother's Day, and has now resumed training for competition.</p>
        <p>''I had gone over the pessimism so many times that it got old and boring and I needed something else to go over,'' she said. ''So I started thinking about what I had to be thankful for. What I came to was how much my family loves and supports me. After four hours of hashing it out, I got up and opened the door.''</p>
        <p>That was the first step toward becoming her old, cheerful self.</p>
        <p>''I just had to force myself every day to focus on the things that were good, even though it was so easy to think of all the things that were bad,'' she said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
