<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Says Asylum in Panama Helped Avert a Coup in Peru</title>
    <meta content="Y26PER$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/26/world/26PERU.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233852"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Asylum (Political)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coups D'Etat and Attempted Coups D'Etat</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Peru-International Relations-US</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Panama-International Relations-Peru</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Peru</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Panama</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Montesinos, Vladimiro</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marquis, Christopher</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Panama</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Peru</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Peru</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Panama</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Asylum (Political)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coups D'Etat and Attempted Coups D'Etat</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000926T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E5DF123AF935A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="770" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Says Asylum in Panama Helped Avert a Coup in Peru</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER MARQUIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Marquis, Christopher</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Sept. 25</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>US officials defend role in pressing Panama to give refuge to Vladimiro Montesinos, Peru's ousted intelligence chief, asserting that his departure was necessary to avoid coup by officers loyal to him; administration officials confirm Montesinos has had longstanding relationship with American intelligence agencies but say contacts were informal and had no bearing on efforts to help him obtain asylum (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>American officials today defended their role in pressing Panama to give refuge to the ousted intelligence chief of Peru, asserting that his departure was necessary to avoid a coup by officers loyal to him.</p>
        <p>Administration officials confirmed that the intelligence chief, Valdimiro Montesinos, has had a longstanding relationship with United States intelligence agencies. But they said the contacts were informal and had no bearing on the efforts to help him settle in Panama.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>American officials today defended their role in pressing Panama to give refuge to the ousted intelligence chief of Peru, asserting that his departure was necessary to avoid a coup by officers loyal to him.</p>
        <p>Administration officials confirmed that the intelligence chief, Valdimiro Montesinos, has had a longstanding relationship with United States intelligence agencies. But they said the contacts were informal and had no bearing on the efforts to help him settle in Panama.</p>
        <p>Even as administration officials insisted that Mr. Montesinos's departure was important to helping Peru remain on a path toward democracy, human rights groups voiced skepticism. They criticized the United States for seeking to arrange a soft landing for Mr. Montesinos outside Peru, where it may be more difficult to prosecute him for widespread abuses that were reportedly carried out under his command.</p>
        <p>Mr. Montesinos, who was a top adviser to President Alberto K. Fujimori, sought political asylum in Panama on Sunday, 10 days after the release in Peru of a videotape in which he apparently sought to bribe an opposition lawmaker. Mr. Fujimori has announced that he will step down next year after holding new elections and that he will abolish the National Intelligence Service. Mr. Montesinos had headed agency, which was implicated in numerous cases of human rights abuses.</p>
        <p>Panamanian authorities have granted Mr. Montesinos a 30-day tourist visa and have retained his passport, officials said. The decision to let him remain was made after appeals from the Organization of American States and six Latin American presidents, as well as telephone calls from Under Secretary of State Thomas R. Pickering.</p>
        <p>A senior American official said Peruvian officers loyal to Mr. Montesinos had given numerous signs, beginning last week, that they would attempt a coup against Mr. Fujimori unless they received an ''ironclad guarantee'' that Mr. Montesinos would be given safe haven outside Peru. American officials were specifically concerned about a military celebration, Armed Forces Day, that was held as planned on Sunday.</p>
        <p>Last week, as United States and Latin American diplomats struggled to defuse a confrontation between supporters of Mr. Fujimori and Mr. Montesinos, army leaders loyal to Mr. Montesinos sounded out the nation's two vice presidents to gauge their support for a coup, but were rebuffed, the officials said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Montesinos's loyalists in the army and the national police agreed to sign a document in support of Mr. Fujimori's government only after they had seen United States and Latin American leaders' efforts for Mr. Montesinos.</p>
        <p>Some experts on Peru and human rights advocates voiced skepticism about the rationale for granting him Montesinos safe haven. Cynthia McClintock, a political scientist at George Washington University, said Mr. Montesinos's military support in Peru was shallow, limited to several senior army officials. She raised the prospect that the Central Intelligence Agency might have been eager to remove Mr. Montesinos from Peru as he increasingly faced the prospect of prosecution there.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for the C.I.A., Mark Mansfield, declined to discuss Mr. Montesinos's ties. An American official insisted, however, that the intelligence agency did not play a role in arranging Mr. Montesinos's exit.</p>
        <p>A regional specialist for Human Rights Watch/Americas, Jose Miguel Vivanco, called the coup threat groundless and said the United States and other nations of the region were promoting impunity for a major violator of human rights. ''This shows how powerful Montesinos is, how he managed to get full support of the Peruvian government and the sympathy of key governments in the region, including the U.S., to find a nice sweet deal for him,'' Mr. Vivanco said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Vivanco's organization said Mr. Montesinos had ordered numerous crimes, including the ''disappearances,'' torture and executions of nine students and a professor from La Cantuta University in 1992.</p>
        <p>Despite such allegations, Mr. Montesinos drew praise from some American officials for helping eradicate a threat posed by guerrilla organizations in Peru and cooperating with American anti-drug efforts.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for the State Department, Richard A. Boucher, acknowledged Washington's role in persuading Panama to accept Mr. Montesinos. But he challenged the idea that the administration was standing up for antidemocratic forces in Peru. He also left open the possibility that Mr. Montesinos could eventually be prosecuted.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
