<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Night Full of Magic, Under the Cast of a Shadow</title>
    <meta content="26TRAC$09" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="S" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/26/olympics/26TRACK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233792"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SYDNEY 2000: TRACK AND FIELD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Track and Field</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Summer Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sydney (Australia)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Cuba</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Jamaica (West Indies)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Lithuania</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Germany</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Germany</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Australia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mozambique</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Austria</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Romania</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Ireland</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Ethiopia</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">O'Sullivan, Sonia</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Longman, Jere</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Garcia, Anier</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Trammell, Terrence</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Crear, Mark</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnson, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Harrison, Alvin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Haughton, Gregory</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Alekna, Virgillijus</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Riedel, Lars</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kruger, Frantz</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Edwards, Jonathan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Garcia, Yoel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kapistin, Denis</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Freeman, Cathy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Graham, Lorraine</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Merry, Katharine</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mutola, Maria</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Graf, Stephanie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holmes, Kelly</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Szabo, Gabriela</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wami, Gete</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Austria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Ireland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Lithuania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Romania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004/Track and Field</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Ethiopia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Mozambique</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Cuba</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Jamaica</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia/Sydney</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Mozambique</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Jamaica</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Ethiopia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Ireland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Cuba</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Austria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Lithuania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Romania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Track and Field</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000926T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E6DB153AF935A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="2018" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Night Full of Magic, Under the Cast of a Shadow</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JERE LONGMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Longman, Jere</byline>
      <dateline>SYDNEY, Australia, Sept. 25</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anier Garcia (Cuba) wins gold medal in men's 110 meter hurdles at Sydney Olympics; Terrence Trammell (US) wins silver and Mark Crear (US) wins bronze; Michael Johnson (US) wins gold medal in men's 400 meters; Alvin Harrison (US) wins silver and Gregory Haughton (Jamaica) wins bronze; Virgillijus Alekna (Lithuania) wins gold medal in men's discus; Lars Riedel (Germany) wins silver and Frantz Kruger (South Africa) wins bronze; Jonathan Edwards (Britain) wins gold medal in men's triple jump; Yoel Garcia wins silver and Denis Kaspustin (Russia) wins bronze; Cathy Freeman (Australia) wins gold medal in 400 meters; Lorraine Graham (Jamaica) wins silver and Katharine Merry (Britain) wins bronze; Maria Mutola (Mozambique) wins gold medal in women's 800 meters; Stephanie Graf (Austria) wins silver medal and Kelly Holmes (Britain) wins bronze; Gabriela Szabo (Romania) wins women's 5,000 meters; Sonia O'Sullivan (Ireland) wins silver medal and Gete Wami (Ethiopia) wins bronze; photo (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On the most anticipated night of track and field at the Sydney Games, Michael Johnson won his second gold medal in the men's 400 meters and Cathy Freeman stopped a nation in the women's 400. Stacy Dragila won the inaugural women's pole vault and tossed a bouquet of flowers over her shoulder like a bride at her reception. Haile Gebrselassie of Ethiopia ran 6.2 miles and had to lean like a sprinter at the tape to defeat his nemesis, Paul Tergat of Kenya.</p>
        <p>But amid these accomplishments, the Summer Games again found themselves engulfed in a drug scandal, one that has snared the husband of the sprinter Marion Jones and has inevitably added stress and suspicion to her attempt to become the first female track and field athlete to win five gold medals in one Olympics.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On the most anticipated night of track and field at the Sydney Games, Michael Johnson won his second gold medal in the men's 400 meters and Cathy Freeman stopped a nation in the women's 400. Stacy Dragila won the inaugural women's pole vault and tossed a bouquet of flowers over her shoulder like a bride at her reception. Haile Gebrselassie of Ethiopia ran 6.2 miles and had to lean like a sprinter at the tape to defeat his nemesis, Paul Tergat of Kenya.</p>
        <p>But amid these accomplishments, the Summer Games again found themselves engulfed in a drug scandal, one that has snared the husband of the sprinter Marion Jones and has inevitably added stress and suspicion to her attempt to become the first female track and field athlete to win five gold medals in one Olympics.</p>
        <p>C. J. Hunter, the 1999 world champion in the shot-put, tested positive for the banned steroid nandrolone at a track meet in Oslo, Norway, on July 28, track and field's world governing body said today. Hunter, who had withdrawn before the Games started after undergoing arthoscopic knee surgery, denied the allegations in a statement.</p>
        <p>But the news competed with the stirring performances of those athletes who ran and hurdled and vaulted tonight to the riveting enjoyment of 112,524 people at Olympic Stadium.</p>
        <p>At least one compelling moment -- the women's 400 meters -- transcended the blemish of drugs. Freeman has managed the difficult balance of being an exceedingly talented and popular athlete, as well as a political symbol who has forced Australia to publicly face the marginalizing of its Aboriginal people. Her own grandmother was part of the so-called stolen generation, taken from her family and uncertain of her own age or birthday.</p>
        <p>During the opening ceremony, Freeman lit the Olympic caldron in a moment that was widely viewed as an important gesture toward national reconciliation. As her name was announced before tonight's race, cameras flashed like strobe lights through the stadium and the roar for her was thunderous.</p>
        <p>The pressure on her to win was enormous. Australia's track and field stars cannot match the achievements of its swimmers. Freeman was the only real hope for a gold medal. She wore a hooded bodysuit that made her seem more like a speedskater than a sprinter, and the crowd seemed to carry her on a smooth glide around the track.</p>
        <p>In the final turn, Freeman lost her form and her head began to wobble and her arms began to flail. All that was left, really, was sheer determination. This indelible will carried her down the homestretch and allowed her to draw away from Lorraine Graham of Jamaica in the final 50 meters to win in 49.11 seconds. Exhausted from the race and the expectation, Freeman sat on the ground for a full two minutes before she removed her shoes and took a victory walk around the stadium, handing flowers to her mother.</p>
        <p>''I could feel the crowd around me, all over me,'' Freeman said. ''I felt everybody's emotion. Happiness and joy absorbed into every pore of my body. I had to sit down to make myself feel normal and get comfortable. It was beyond words.''</p>
        <p>She wore spikes in the Aboriginal colors of red for the earth, yellow for the sky and black for the people. And after she won, Freeman grabbed both the Australian and Aboriginal flags and wore them over her shoulder like a shawl. As a symbol, she said she hoped her achievement ''will make a difference in people's attitudes.'' But this victory's value was mostly in its personal currency.</p>
        <p>''I'm pleased that I withstood the pressure and won the gold medal,'' she said.</p>
        <p>In the men's 400, Johnson became the first man ever to win the quarter mile in consecutive Olympics, establishing a dominance not evident in any other event with his victory in 43.84 seconds. Over the past 11 years, Johnson has run this race 82 times and has won 79 times. He ran a controlled sprint tonight, starting patiently with his upright style and low knee lift. But, as usual, he took a wide lead coming out of the final turn and was never threatened by his teammate Alvin Harrison, who won the silver medal in 44.40.</p>
        <p>A cool night in an outside lane was no time to challenge his world record of 43.18 seconds, Johnson said. His victory was conservative but definitive and historic.</p>
        <p>''He's kind of like a gunslinger who snookered the others to look into the sun,'' said Clyde Hart, Johnson's longtime coach. ''You don't need to be quite as fast.''</p>
        <p>On Saturday, Johnson will anchor the American 4x400-meter relay team and should win his fifth career gold medal. With a double victory in the 200 and 400 meters at the 1996 Atlanta Games, world records in both events and a second gold in the quarter mile tonight, he cemented his position as second only to Carl Lewis among the great sprinters of all time.</p>
        <p>''There was nothing we set out to accomplish that we didn't do,'' Johnson said of himself and Hart. This was a night for deserved self-indulgence, not drug scandals, Johnson said. ''I think I should be allowed to be selfish and concentrate on the history I've been able to make, instead of what might be overshadowing it back home.''</p>
        <p>A shot-putter failing a drug test would not generally be a huge story. Many shot-putters have failed drug tests. At the 1992 Summer Games in Barcelona, Spain, all three medalists had previously been caught cheating.</p>
        <p>On most nights, the stories would focus on athletes like Gebrselassie and his desperate sprint to win the 10,000 meters by nine-hundredths of a second in 27 minutes 18.20 seconds. Or on Maria Mutola of Mozambique, discovered by a poet while she played soccer and granted an Olympic scholarship to attend high school in Springfield, Ore. After a career of frustration, she finally won a gold medal tonight in the 800 meters in 1:56.15.</p>
        <p>On most nights, the victory by Anier Garcia of Cuba in the 110-meter hurdles would make headlines because he upset the defending champion, Allen Johnson of the United States, in 13 seconds, a national record. Or Gabriela Szabo of Romania, the frail runner with the muscular kick, would grab attention with her victory in the 5,000 meters in 14:40.79, an Olympic record.</p>
        <p>But tonight was not most nights. Hunter was big news because his wife is Marion Jones.</p>
        <p>''Without Marion Jones, who cares about this fat man?'' said Giorgio Reineri, a spokesman for track and field's world governing body.</p>
        <p>Drug scandals involving the withdrawal of 27 Chinese athletes and the expulsion of the Bulgarian and most of the Romanian weight-lifting teams have already rocked these Games. Swimming's flurry of world records was tempered by drug suspicions in many races. Athletes talk openly of drugs now the way they once talked of sprained ankles. Drug testing is so deficient that no tests exist for many of the drugs athletes are believed to be using. In swimming and track and field, every remarkable performance brings not wonder but immediate distrust.</p>
        <p>''It takes a lot away from what we're doing, the clean athletes that are working hard at what they do every day,'' said Dragila, of Pocatello, Idaho, who won the first women's Olympic pole vault at 15 feet 1 inch. ''I hope that it doesn't tarnish what we've accomplished. I know that I'm clean and that I earned it.''</p>
        <p>Craig Masback, the chief executive officer of USA Track and Field, said, ''No one really knew how clean other Olympics were and no one really knows how clean this is.''</p>
        <p>Fair or not, Jones will face some skepticism as she attempts to win four more gold medals in the 200 meters, long jump, 4x100-meter relay and 4x400-meter relay after her victory on Saturday at 100 meters. She has not been accused, and she has not failed a drug test. Still, this does not keep other athletes from a despairing parlor game of cynicism.</p>
        <p>''If you are married to someone taking drugs, it would be surprising not to know about it,'' said Erica Johansson of Sweden, who will compete against Jones in the long jump, beginning Wednesday. ''I don't think she's doping, but she will live with this the rest of her career. Whatever result she has from now on, everyone will wonder.''</p>
        <p>Rightly or wrongly, Jones is certain to hear some of the same questions that the swimmer Michelle Smith of Ireland heard at the Atlanta Games, in part because her husband, Erik de Bruin, a discus thrower, had been suspended for steroid use. Smith won three gold medals in swimming, but was banned last year after spiking a drug test with alcohol.</p>
        <p>''I hope she can do this without interference,'' Gerhard Heiberg, a member of the International Olympic Committee from Norway, said of Jones. ''I know some people will speculate. I hope she's clean and she can do her best.''</p>
        <p>Today's announcement of Hunter's positive test was curious on a couple of levels. One, nandrolone has been readily detectable for years, and officials have been surprised that a flurry of positive tests for the drug have occurred in the past year. One possible explanation is improperly labeled nutritional substances, scientists said. Also, the timing of the announcement was viewed as an irritated reaction by the I.O.C. to relentless criticism that has come from the United States Congress, White House, corporate sponsors and news media in regard to corruption in the Salt Lake City bidding scandal and inadequacies in drug testing.</p>
        <p>Members of the I.O.C. have raised the possibility of covered-up drug tests by the American track and field officials. Masback issued a vehement denial, saying the American federation was the world leader in drug testing. Still, the I.O.C. sent an unmistakable message that the Americans need to clean up their own house before calling others dirty on the issue of drugs.</p>
        <p>''It's like alcoholism -- you first have to admit that there is a problem before you can get around to solving it,'' said Dick Pound, an I.O.C. delegate from Montreal and the chairman of its World Anti-Doping Agency. ''If one is in constant denial, there is no chance of recovery.''</p>
        <p>The attention will turn now to Jones, who will also run two rounds of the 200 on Wednesday besides attempting to qualify for the long jump final. Can she still win five golds? Will the anxiety from her husband's troubles sabotage her own ambitions?</p>
        <p>''Maybe she is stronger than the problem,'' Reineri said. ''I hope so for her. She's a winner. She doesn't deserve the stories swirling around her. She's a nice woman, a great athlete. It's a pity. This guy is her husband. Obviously for her it's a big problem. It can be a tragedy. We hope she is strong enough to beat this tragedy like she beats the other athletes on the track.''</p>
        <p>SYDNEY 2000: TRACK AND FIELD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
