<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Asian Satellite Network, Simplicity Is Simply Better</title>
    <meta content="Y26BIRD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/26/technology/26BIRD.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233823"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TECHNOLOGY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Satellites</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Indonesia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Far East, South and Southeast Asia and Pacific Areas</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Asia Cellular Satellite System</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">PT Pasifik Satelit Nusantara</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Feder, Barnaby J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Indonesia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Indonesia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Satellites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000926T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E7D8153AF935A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="782" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Asian Satellite Network, Simplicity Is Simply Better</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARNABY J. FEDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Feder, Barnaby J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Asia Cellular Satellite System, new Indonesian satellite phone venture that wills serve only Asia, is based on single satellite in fixed location more than 22 miles above earth instead of expensive constellation buzzing around in lower orbits; PT Pasifik Satelit Nusantara heads partnership that will operate system (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After months of gloomy news in the satellite communications sector, analysts are looking forward to the commercial debut tomorrow of an Indonesian satellite phone venture focused strictly on Asia.</p>
        <p>Unlike Iridium, the $5 billion global satellite system that went bankrupt last year, and Globalstar, a $3 billion system struggling with patchy service and too few customers, the Asia Cellular Satellite System, known in the industry as ACeS, is based on a single satellite in a fixed location more than 22 miles above earth instead of an expensive constellation buzzing around in lower orbits.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After months of gloomy news in the satellite communications sector, analysts are looking forward to the commercial debut tomorrow of an Indonesian satellite phone venture focused strictly on Asia.</p>
        <p>Unlike Iridium, the $5 billion global satellite system that went bankrupt last year, and Globalstar, a $3 billion system struggling with patchy service and too few customers, the Asia Cellular Satellite System, known in the industry as ACeS, is based on a single satellite in a fixed location more than 22 miles above earth instead of an expensive constellation buzzing around in lower orbits.</p>
        <p>That simplicity will result in slightly poorer voice quality, but with base prices ranging from 35 cents to 75 cents a minute, calls could be as much as 50 percent cheaper in some cases, analysts say. The satellite has a unique antenna design capable of directing traffic to the ground stations that can handle traffic most efficiently. And ACeS will be the first venture to offer satellite service on cell phones small enough to fit in a shirt pocket.</p>
        <p>''Everything from one end to the other has been done right,'' said Roger Rusch, president of Telastra, a satellite consulting company based in Palos Verdes Estates, Calif.</p>
        <p>However, in what might serve as a timely reminder for investors of how tough the satellite telecommunications business is, Globalstar, a former highflier on Wall Street that is now struggling financially, provided scant comfort to investors when it announced yesterday that it had rounded up $68 million in new money from its major backers. Globalstar shares, which have fallen 77 percent this year, edged up 28 cents, to $9.97.</p>
        <p>Globalstar's new funds will push the projected date when it will run out of money back about three months, or into next summer.</p>
        <p>Globalstar's new financing came on the heels of a deal last week in which Bear, Stearns agreed to buy $105 million in new Globalstar stock. But Merrill Lynch analysts in a note to investors warned them not to interpret it as a vote of confidence from Bear, Stearns. Instead, they said, Bear, Stearns is getting the shares at prices that should allow it to make a quick profit selling them.</p>
        <p>Another satellite venture, Orbcomm Global, filed a bankruptcy petition last Friday so that it could continue to negotiate a plan to convert some of its debt to equity to reduce its interest expenses. Tele globe Inc., a Montreal-based telecommunications company, owns 68 percent of Orbcomm. The remaining 32 percent is owned by the Orbital Sciences Corporation of Dulles, Va.</p>
        <p>Orbcomm's low-earth satellites do not carry voice communications but instead are used to track rail cars, trucks and other vehicles and to monitor the status of pipelines. The company ran into trouble, analysts said, because each user needs what amounts to a customized system. New customers are not being brought on line fast enough to provide the cash needed to service the debt.</p>
        <p>ACeS seems more straightforward, but it will not be generating profits anytime soon, said Adi R. Adiwoso, chief executive and president of P. T. Pasifik Satelit Nusantara, the Indonesia company that heads the ACeS partnership.</p>
        <p>Service will be expanded to the Philippines next month and Taiwan by January, Mr. Adiwoso said. The satellite is capable of reaching from Korea to India, covering three billion people, but ACeS has yet to reach an agreement for operations in China, the single biggest potential customer. Still, analysts like the venture's focus and the fact that Mr. Adiwoso's partners include companies like Lockheed Martin Global Telecommunications, the Philippine Long Distance Telephone Company and Jasmine International of Thailand.</p>
        <p>''If any mobile satellite phone system is going to survive, it will be a regional player like ACeS,'' said William Pitkin, who has been following Pasifik Satelit's stock for Merrill Lynch. A similar system called Thuraya that has been developed by the Hughes Space and Communications Company, a unit of General Motors, is scheduled for deployment in the Mideast next month.</p>
        <p>The biggest hurdle for ACeS, said Michael French, an analyst at ING Barings, is the cost of the GSM-format phones, which are made by L. M. Ericsson of Sweden. The list price of about $1,000 is cheaper than the Globalstar phones, which are listed at $1,500, but still a hefty investment for many potential users.</p>
        <p>TECHNOLOGY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
