<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ups and Downs for Diet Guinea Pigs</title>
    <meta content="26DIET" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/26/science/26DIET.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233764"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Longevity</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Diet and Nutrition</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nagourney, Eric</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Behrendt, Jeffrey A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sherman, Michael A</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Diet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Age, Chronological</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diet and Nutrition</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000926T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E7DE153AF935A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="997" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ups and Downs for Diet Guinea Pigs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC NAGOURNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nagourney, Eric</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jeffrey A Behrendt and Michael A Sherman are among small group of people who have put themselves on what they call calorie-restricted diet, consuming 20 percent to 40 percent fewer calories than what would be considered normal in order to prolong their lives to age 100, 120 even 140; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Like many people discussing the rigors of being on a diet, Jeffrey A. Behrendt, a lawyer in Ottawa, sounds both plaintive and hopeful.</p>
        <p>''I still eat chocolate!'' Mr. Behrendt wrote in a note, starting with the good news. ''Just a lot less than before.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Like many people discussing the rigors of being on a diet, Jeffrey A. Behrendt, a lawyer in Ottawa, sounds both plaintive and hopeful.</p>
        <p>''I still eat chocolate!'' Mr. Behrendt wrote in a note, starting with the good news. ''Just a lot less than before.''</p>
        <p>Then came the downside.</p>
        <p>There is the problem of buying a suit when one's jacket size is 36 tall and one's waist is 28. (''This is not easy to find in stores!'') There is the problem of sitting down. (''If the chair is not well padded, I find it uncomfortable.'') And then there is the problem of how people react to Mr. Behrendt's new look. (''Very negative! People started thinking I was very ill and I got comments that I looked like a concentration camp survivor.'')</p>
        <p>This is not your ordinary diet.</p>
        <p>Mr. Behrendt is among a small group of people who have put themselves on what they call a calorie-restricted diet. They consume 20 percent to 40 percent fewer calories than what would be considered normal, with a single goal: prolonging their lives to age 100, 120, even 140.</p>
        <p>The technique has appeared promising in tests on mice, and current experiments on monkeys also suggest that their aging has been slowed. Last week, Dr. Leonard Guarente of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology published a paper in Science that explains just how calorie restriction prolongs lifespan in yeast. But no one knows whether calorie reduction works in humans.</p>
        <p>Undeterred, Mr. Behrendt follows the regimen, along with hundreds of others he communicates with through a computer newsgroup.  They, and possibly many others, are a bold band of experimenters, one part guinea pig, one part scientist.</p>
        <p>Still, some freely own up to being a tad grumpy. Maybe it is the cold hands and feet that many of them experience. Maybe it is the decline in sexual interest many report. Maybe it is the social isolation some say such a radical diet imposes on them. Or maybe it is just that much of the time, they are just a little bit hungry.</p>
        <p>Many followers of the C.R. (for calorie restricted) diet, as the practice is known, were inspired by the writings of Dr. Roy Walford, a pathologist at the University of California at Los Angeles. For many of them, there are no forbidden foods: the only thing that matters is controlling the total calories taken in and ensuring that nutritional needs are met. As a practical matter, most eat vast quantities of vegetables.</p>
        <p>Michael A. Sherman, a software company owner in Mountain View, Calif., said a friend gave him one of Dr. Walford's books about three years ago, when he turned 40.</p>
        <p>''It sort of hit me pretty suddenly; everything's fine, but you're just moving in the wrong direction,'' he recalled. ''It just suddenly struck me that I was going to die.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Sherman went from consuming about 3,200 calories a day to taking in 1,725. At 5 five feet 5, he weighs 122 pounds, down from about 145. And he says he has seen tangible improvements in health indicators like his cholesterol levels and heart rate.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sherman says that he is rarely hungry, that his mental energy is good and that he is able to work out and run several times a week.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Sherman, who is married and has two children, says he has seen a decline in sexual interest, which he is combating by trying different preparations of testosterone. He has no qualms about whether he is following a ''natural'' approach.</p>
        <p>''I know what nature's plan is for me,'' Mr. Sherman said. ''It wants me to decay and die pretty soon. So I don't really put a lot of stock in sort of trying to be natural. So far, there's been about 50 billion humans -- and they all died, except for the last 6 billion. So that's what you get if you do things the natural way.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Sherman has other plans. He wants to see the 22nd century, and to do so, he needs to live to age 143.</p>
        <p>Still, he said that, unlike some C.R. followers, he is not fixated on his diet. He goes out to restaurants often, ordering carefully.</p>
        <p>T. Francesca Skelton, a 60-year-old Washington woman who has been on the diet for about four months, said that it seemed to attract some fanatics. ''They really wouldn't eat a bread crumb if it wasn't on the diet,'' she said.</p>
        <p>And that, said Dr. Gail C. Frank, a nutrition professor at California State University at Long Beach, is the big drawback. While she admires the intent behind the diet, Dr. Frank said the approach was too extreme.</p>
        <p>''What good is the aging if there can't be the pleasure to go with it?'' she asked.</p>
        <p>For Mr. Behrendt, 30, it has not been easy. He has lost 20 pounds and now weighs 120. He is 6 feet tall.</p>
        <p>In a telephone interview, he said that he felt better on the whole. But on just 1,800 calories day, he can no longer do the long-distance running  he once enjoyed because it burns too many calories. He feels more prone to irritability and depression. And he has had trouble getting others to accept his choice, especially his family.</p>
        <p>''A lot of families, mine included, show their love by a cooking a big meal for you,'' Mr. Behrendt said. ''They're really insulted. You go there and you hardly eat anything.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
