<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NTT DoCoMo Confirms Talks With AOL</title>
    <meta content="Y26DOC$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/26/technology/26DOCO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233828"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cellular Telephones</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Japan</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">America Online</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ntt Docomo Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tanikawa, Miki</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cellular Telephones</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000926T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE2D8153AF935A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="543" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NTT DoCoMo Confirms Talks With AOL</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIKI TANIKAWA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tanikawa, Miki</byline>
      <dateline>TOKYO, Sept. 25</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Japan's NTT DoCoMo Inc confirms it is in advanced talks about alliance with America Online; deal could greatly expand AOL presence in Japan; NTT DoCoMo has attracted 12 million subscribers in Japan to its service, known as i-mode, which allows users to gain access to Internet from their mobile phones (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NTT DoCoMo Inc., the largest mobile communications company in Japan, confirmed today that it was in advanced talks about an alliance with America Online. A deal could greatly expand the AOL presence in Japan, where it has made little headway since introducing its services here three years ago.</p>
        <p>NTT DoCoMo has attracted 12 million subscribers in Japan to its service, known as i-mode, which allows users to gain access to the Internet from their mobile phones. AOL, by contrast, has attracted 400,000 to 500,000 users.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NTT DoCoMo Inc., the largest mobile communications company in Japan, confirmed today that it was in advanced talks about an alliance with America Online. A deal could greatly expand the AOL presence in Japan, where it has made little headway since introducing its services here three years ago.</p>
        <p>NTT DoCoMo has attracted 12 million subscribers in Japan to its service, known as i-mode, which allows users to gain access to the Internet from their mobile phones. AOL, by contrast, has attracted 400,000 to 500,000 users.</p>
        <p>A tie-in would give AOL greater access to the Japanese market, where computer-based use of the Internet is minimal compared with that in the United States.</p>
        <p>''Hooking up with DoCoMo allows them to quickly gain a lot of users in this market,'' said Kevin Williams, a senior analyst with IDC Japan, ''since DoCoMo is the dominant player and the effects are immediate.''</p>
        <p>AOL officials declined to comment, but NTT DoCoMo confirmed that both companies were in the advanced stages of negotiations. ''Anything could change in the final stages,'' DoCoMo said through a spokesman. ''So we cannot discuss this at this point.''</p>
        <p>An imminent deal was first reported on Friday in a Japanese daily, Sankei Shimbun, which said that DoCoMo would acquire a stake of at least 40 percent in AOL Japan, a joint venture between America Online and a partnership of two Japanese companies -- the huge trading house Mitsui and the financial news publisher Nihon Keizai Shimbun.</p>
        <p>AOL Japan has fared badly since it was formed here in 1997. The current subscriber base trails far behind the nearly four million customers of a Fujitsu subsidiary, the Nifty Corporation, the leader among Internet service providers in Japan.</p>
        <p>Whether there are any immediate benefits to DoCoMo from an alliance with AOL is not clear. While DoCoMo would gain access to AOL's content, the Japanese company already has other ways to obtain content for its i-mode service. ''Everyone wants to play with DoCoMo, not the other way around,'' Mr. Williams said.</p>
        <p>But longer term, a DoCoMo linkup with AOL could prove enormously useful to the Japanese company in its effort to expand internationally. The alliance would ''bring DoCoMo a lot of exposure to AOL customers in the U.S.,'' Mr. Williams said.</p>
        <p>''A lot of consumers in the U.S. don't know much about DoCoMo,'' he went on. ''With this deal, it brings i-mode services and other DoCoMo services out in the open and could potentially accelerate the introduction of i-mode-type services in the U.S.''</p>
        <p>Sankei Shimbun said the two companies also agreed to establish a joint venture in the United States as part of an accord for cooperation on wireless access to the Internet.</p>
        <p>The wireless Internet has taken off in Japan, and DoCoMo's expertise is considered a valuable resource for other companies seeking to expand their wireless presence.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
