<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>POVERTY TOUR REVISITED/American Voices; Forget Washington. The Poor Cope Alone.</title>
    <meta content="26POVE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/26/national/26POVE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233874"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tax Credits</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Southern States (US)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Illinois</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mississippi</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Kentucky</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Appalachian Region</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Clarksdale (Miss)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Annville (Ky)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">East St Louis (Ill)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Appalachian Region</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nieves, Evelyn</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Illinois</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Mississippi</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Kentucky</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Illinois</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Kentucky</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Mississippi</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Mississippi</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Illinois</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Kentucky</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tax Credits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000926T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E5DD123AF935A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="3470" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>POVERTY TOUR REVISITED/American Voices; Forget Washington. The Poor Cope Alone.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EVELYN NIEVES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nieves, Evelyn</byline>
      <dateline>CLARKSDALE, Miss.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Life for poor remains same, year after Pres Clinton's much-heralded six-state, four-day poverty tour of depressed Southern communities to highlight places untouched by longest economic boom in nation's history, special report, Poverty Tour Revisited; his modest proposal for tax incentives to bring businesses to impoverished communities still awaits Senate approval; hope has faded that anything big might happen as has notion that federal government is answer to economic misery; in presidential election season, when major-party candidates are suggesting that everyone should benefit from nation's prosperity, those who might be buoyed by words have little use for national politics; many are more concerned over how to fix own communities than about state of country; conditions in Clarksdale (Miss), Annville (Ky), East St Louis (Ill) and parts of Appalachia since Clinton's visit discussed; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In Eastern Kentucky, a 15-year-old boy dreams of quitting school to make real money working at a pizza parlor. Here in Clarksdale, a 68-year-old widow thanks God that she can manage the $200-a-month rent on a house one good rain could wash away. In East St. Louis, Ill., a 20-year-old mother of six wishes she could find a public housing project where the broken glass on the stoop is swept away.</p>
        <p>Poor people learn to keep hopes small. So when President Clinton came calling on some of the poorest places in the country last year with ideas to make things better, it was like rain in the desert.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In Eastern Kentucky, a 15-year-old boy dreams of quitting school to make real money working at a pizza parlor. Here in Clarksdale, a 68-year-old widow thanks God that she can manage the $200-a-month rent on a house one good rain could wash away. In East St. Louis, Ill., a 20-year-old mother of six wishes she could find a public housing project where the broken glass on the stoop is swept away.</p>
        <p>Poor people learn to keep hopes small. So when President Clinton came calling on some of the poorest places in the country last year with ideas to make things better, it was like rain in the desert.</p>
        <p>The president's six-state, four-day poverty tour, highlighting for the first time in his two terms the places that remain untouched by the longest economic boom in this nation's history, caused an excitement that bordered on the spiritual. He was like a charismatic preacher, stirring the congregation to believe.</p>
        <p>A year later, the president's modest proposals for tax incentives to bring businesses to impoverished communities are still awaiting Senate approval. The idea that anything big might happen to places that have been down longer than they were ever up has long faded. And so has the notion, if it ever existed, that the federal government is the answer to the empty downtowns, idle laborers and the dilapidated buildings all too common in these communities.</p>
        <p>In a presidential election season, when the two major-party candidates are suggesting that everyone should benefit from the nation's prosperity, the people who might be buoyed by the words have little use for national politics. In dozens of interviews in communities the president visited -- Clarksdale,  East St. Louis and the Eastern Kentucky towns of Hazard and Annville -- what was clear was that Democrats are Democrats, Republicans are Republicans and people are more concerned with how to fix their own communities than in the state of the country.</p>
        <p>Unlike the extensively reported tour of poor communities by Robert F. Kennedy in 1968, when he was a presidential candidate, Mr. Clinton's tour was a day's headlines. And perhaps because this is the age of welfare changes, the places Mr. Clinton  visited expected little beyond the visit. East St. Louis, which looks leftover from a bombing, is bent on proving that it is not the urban war zone it became known as a decade ago. Appalachia, which is humming along, in parts, is concerned with telling the world that it is not a haven for barefoot hillbillies in shotgun shacks.</p>
        <p>Clarksdale  Facing Adversity, Showing Resilience</p>
        <p>Clarksdale, in the heart of the Mississippi Delta, is determined to prove that with grit, it will not only endure, but prevail.</p>
        <p>It is, as the mayor says, ''resilient in the face of adversity.''</p>
        <p>The morning of the day the president came to town, Shirley Fair opened Ooo So Pretty flowers and gifts at the regular time, 9 a.m. Ms. Fair nodded to the Secret Service agents on the roof, said hey to the ones who had been hanging around the store for 10 days and managed to take a few orders for bouquets.</p>
        <p>Her store, on the corner of a nearly abandoned strip of downtown Issaquena Avenue, had been chosen for a meeting between the president and local small-business owners. Word was that he was bringing ways to lure businesses that had fled to Highway 61 back to town, besides enticing new ones.</p>
        <p>But Ms. Fair, barely getting by after 21 years in business, would bet on just two things that day. It would be hotter than heck, and Mr. Clinton's visit would make great pictures.</p>
        <p>She was right. When President Clinton strolled through the tired, broken streets of downtown, sweating enough for two men in the 105-degree heat, it was the most exciting thing to happen to Clarksdale (population 22,000) in a long time. Maybe ever. He passed the boarded Roxy Theater, the closed-down Pac-Man lounge and the falling-down wooden houses as if he were right at home. Then he came into Ooo So Pretty and listened to people sing the business blues for about an hour, a lot longer than his schedulers had planned.</p>
        <p>And then, he left.</p>
        <p>''It was a great Kodak moment,'' Ms. Fair said.</p>
        <p>As she expected, nothing has really changed on Issaquena Avenue. Like so many downtowns abandoned for highway strips, the Roxy (the mayor pointed it out to the president as a place that might make a great cultural center with some kind of grant or loan), is still boarded. The Pac-Man lounge is still closed. The falling down houses look ready to give up completely.</p>
        <p>Johnny Newson is still putting in the long hours at Newson's Auto Parts, in a blocklong building, inherited from his dad, across the street from Ooo So Pretty. Mr. Newson opens at 7 and stays until 7 or 8 to compete with the Wal-Mart and Auto Zone on Highway 61. ''Right now,'' he said, ''it's just like the president never came.''</p>
        <p>A lot of people say the same thing. Hardly anyone blames the president, though. In Clarksdale, people pay as little attention to Washington politics as Washington politics pays to them. No one faults any of the presidential candidates for not coming around; they are used to being ignored.</p>
        <p>They tend to blame Wal-Mart for their problems, for stealing business from downtown. Or Memphis, 75 miles away, for stealing brain power. Or the local politicians, for letting downtown slip into a coma without a fight.</p>
        <p>They blame themselves, too.</p>
        <p>''People got to want to improve,'' said Ethel Mae Clark, sitting on her mother's porch on downtown Yazoo Street. Next door was a boarded shack of a house. Across the street, where houses used to be, was a lot overrun with weeds.</p>
        <p>Ms. Clark, who lives nearby, has diabetes and a failing kidney, and her world is framed by the $400 Social Security check she receives each month. Her mother, Martha Riley, who was sitting on the porch sewing a quilt under a sign for ''Pigee's Beauty Salon'' -- a remnant of her landlord's defunct business -- is in similar straits. Ms. Riley pays $200 a month rent for the house and wishes she could afford better. She blames not being able to read or write for her lot. ''Here,'' she said, ''Things just get worser.''</p>
        <p>Still, Clarksdale is a proud old place. Some of the biggest names in the blues walked these streets. Muddy Waters and John Lee Hooker grew up in town. Bessie Smith died here.</p>
        <p>The Delta Blues Museum, which is fighting for financing from the Clarksdale Board of Commissioners, attracts visitors from all over the world. Tony Czech, the director, showed off the guest book to prove it.</p>
        <p>''Look at these,'' Mr. Czech said, leafing through a few pages that revealed addresses from Paris, the Netherlands, Sweden, Germany and Alaska. ''And these are just over a couple of days.''</p>
        <p>But after these visitors tour the museum, they have nowhere else in Clarksdale to go.</p>
        <p>For the really poor people -- and that means nearly 40 percent of Clarksdale residents, who live below the poverty level -- shopping means taking a long walk along a busy road. Local bus service is nonexistent.</p>
        <p>Richard M. Webster Jr., the mayor, had hoped the president's visit would lead to a real change. But Mr. Webster is not surprised that it did not. ''We Deltans have learned to be resilient,'' he said. ''Resilient in the face of adversity. Just the fact that we are able to live and work here is a sign of that.''</p>
        <p>Yet there are occasional cries of desperation. Dave Williams, a part-time carpenter, started shouting, ''Factories! We need some factories here!'' when he saw a reporter and photographer walking around town.</p>
        <p>He has lived here all his life, 42 years, but cannot see sticking it out much longer. ''I would like to have a full-time job,'' Mr. Williams said. ''So would a lot of people. I know a friend of mine, he's living in one of those cattle boxes that sit on the tracks. So are a lot of people. See for yourself.''</p>
        <p>On a scorching day, there was no one in the metal cars. Hardly anyone walked the streets, either, except for a twig-skinny woman who asked for $5 for a fix, and a man gathering cans in a plastic grocery bag.</p>
        <p>East St. Louis  Self-Help Is Seen As the Solution</p>
        <p>It was Sunday, the sun shining like a halo, and the streets of East St. Louis were virtually empty, as though the city had been warned of an air raid.</p>
        <p>This made the abandoned buildings all over town stand out in bold relief. From boarded churches to closed-down gas stations and burned-out houses and storefronts, the rotting buildings, more than 1,500 in all, mocked the city's pride, marring every neighborhood.</p>
        <p>Businesses, even on State Street, the main drag, are few and far between. The city's only places to eat are the kind that measure customers by the millions. So many businesses have left that when the president stopped by on his poverty tour, the best example of a positive economic growth that the city could come up with was a new Walgreen's.</p>
        <p>East St. Louis, with about 32,000 residents, 99 percent of them African-American, is clearly one very poor city. About 40 percent of the residents live below the federal poverty line of $16,600 for a family of four. A three-bedroom house can be bought for $10,000. The unemployment rate is more than 10 percent, twice the national average.</p>
        <p>President Clinton, with an entourage that included the Rev. Jesse Jackson and several cabinet members, promised that East St. Louis would not be forgotten. But while his brief visit has yielded little concrete change, residents overwhelmingly vote Democratic, all the time. Few people have anything but praise for the president's gestures toward their city.</p>
        <p>''The visit shed a lot of light on the things that we have to offer,'' said Greg Lewis, one of a dozen members of the local Democratic club who was spending his Sunday afternoon renovating a building the club recently bought for its headquarters. ''A lot of it,'' Mr. Lewis added, to a chorus of yeahs, ''depends on us.''</p>
        <p>Like other members of the committee, Mr. Lewis, who is 38, the father of two boys, 12 and 15, and a relocation supervisor in nearby St. Louis, could not say enough good things about his hometown.</p>
        <p>''My wife and I have a six-figure income between us,'' he said. ''We live in this city because we believe in it. The stigma is something we're trying to get away from.''</p>
        <p>Told that the city looks grim, Mr. Lewis and other residents talk about how much it has improved from 10 years ago. The police cars did not have working radios and the fire engines would not run. Trash was piled high in the streets because the city had no money to hire haulers. In 1990, a man who was physically abused while in jail sued East St. Louis and won, forcing the city to turn over the deed to City Hall to him to satisfy the court judgment. And when things seemed as if they could not get any worse, they did. In 1991, the city posted 68 homicides, a record.</p>
        <p>Now, with tax revenue from the Casino Queen riverboat, which opened here in 1993, just across the Mississippi River from St. Louis's Gateway Arch, and the new $15 million waterfront hotel adjacent to it, the city can afford at least basic services. Still, many of the casino's 1,200 employees, even those who come from East St. Louis, live elsewhere, where the schools are better and there are neighborhoods where houses appreciate in value.</p>
        <p>For the very poor in East St. Louis, prone to not voting or participating in civic life, the city still looks very bleak. Andrea Mitchell, a 20-year-old mother of six, moved to East St. Louis from Washington Park, Ill., less than two years ago. With local schools too overcrowded to accept her 5-year-old and 4-year-old, Ms. Mitchell said she was about ready to move again. She lives in the Normandy Houses, a barrackslike public housing complex, and despite help from neighbors, she cannot manage her young family in her two-bedroom apartment and police her neighborhood as well.</p>
        <p>''All these empty lots and empty houses are terrible,'' Ms. Mitchell said. ''The streets need to be fixed. There really ain't no businesses here. People should all pitch in and clean this place up.''</p>
        <p>Since the president's visit, a Blockbuster video store and Save-A-Lot grocery store that had already been in the works have opened by the Walgreen's, creating a small but bona fide shopping center in the heart of town. They represent the first major retail development in the city since the 1950's.</p>
        <p>But with so much abandonment, and such seemingly intractable poverty, longtime residents and business owners say it will take more than a few new chain stores to lift the city off its knees.</p>
        <p>Fredericka Nash and her two sisters run the Nash Funeral Home, which their parents opened more than 70 years ago. Ms. Nash, 80, remembers when East St. Louis was ''a bustling city.''</p>
        <p>''To look around, you certainly wouldn't see it,'' Ms. Nash said. ''Sometimes, it looks like a battle zone. The people want better. But how are you going to achieve that?''</p>
        <p>Like others, she brushed off the possibility of a federal solution. ''With the proper city administration,'' she said sternly, ''possibly it may be able to stem the tide.''</p>
        <p>The mayor, Debra Powell, did not keep a scheduled appointment to talk about her city, and was busy the next day as well. Her assistant said Ms. Powell was too busy planning to meet the actors Harry Belafonte and Danny Glover, who were considering investing in the city.</p>
        <p>Appalachia  Anger at Being Part Of Poverty Tour</p>
        <p>Of all the jobs in Jackson County, Ky., those on the assembly line at the Mid-South Electronics Company in Annville are among the most coveted.</p>
        <p>Mid-South, a contract manufacturer for several multinational companies, has nearly 900 employees, up from 40 workers 10 years ago. And the nonunion shop keeps hiring more workers, while few leave. Employees say the pay, which starts at $5.75 an hour, is pretty good, especially considering medical benefits.</p>
        <p>Kevin Dunn, who has worked at Mid-South for 7 years, after 11 years at a textile plant in London, a town 22 miles away, considers himself lucky. ''I'd say it's one of the better jobs around,'' said Mr. Dunn, 50, the single father of two boys.</p>
        <p>It was at Mid-South that President Clinton stopped on his poverty tour last year of the Appalachian region of Eastern Kentucky to prove his point that companies can park themselves anywhere and do well.</p>
        <p>Folks at Mid-South say it was a big thrill to have the president walk through the plant, even though many workers are Republicans through and through.</p>
        <p>''I voted for him, but I'd better not say that too loud,'' said Mr. Dunn, giggling, as he sat on a picnic table outside the plant on his lunch break.</p>
        <p>Della Dell, a quality control supervisor who has been at Mid-South for 16 years, said she was excited to meet the president, even though she is a Republican.</p>
        <p>''He stopped in here because he cared about jobs,'' Ms. Dell said, ''even if we were doing fine already.''</p>
        <p>There is a lot of that kind of talk in Eastern Kentucky. People are weary of the image of Appalachian hillbillies in miners' hats and rope belts. Time and again they said it would be wrong to take pictures or interview the rural poor without including the rest of the people. Some were insulted that the president's visit was part of a ''poverty tour.''</p>
        <p>As poor as the region is -- nearly 35 percent of the people in Jackson County, which includes Annville, live below the poverty line, as do 30 percent of those in Perry County, where the president addressed a rally in Hazard -- the emphasis is on telling the world that encouraging private investment is the way to go.</p>
        <p>This is God's country. From Annville to Hazard, people grow patches of tobacco in the backyard and post the Ten Commandments on their lawns. Signs on lampposts read: ''God is coming soon. Are you ready?''</p>
        <p>People time and again said they were blessed to live in a place as beautiful as Kentucky, where the mountains are green and lush and the trees look as old as time.</p>
        <p>William Gorman, the mayor of Hazard,  invited the president to visit his town months earlier, largely to show how well Appalachia is doing.</p>
        <p>''I'm a Republican, and I really think he did us a great honor,'' said Mr. Gorman, who traces his family's roots in the region to the Revolutionary War. ''The greatest problem I've seen with people is the lack of hope. You give them hope and they'll conquer the world.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton talked about his ''new markets initiative,'' to entice businesses to invest here, but for Mr. Gorman, who has been mayor for 23 years, Hazard (population 5,416) is already benefiting from the new economy.</p>
        <p>''Appalachia has a lot of problems,'' he said, taking the time on a Saturday with his assistant and friend of 50 years, Charlie Hammonds, to give reporters a tour of the town. All traffic pointed to the Wal-Mart, and the grand opening of a new off-track betting center, the U-Bet.</p>
        <p>''But the quality of life here is no different than it is anywhere in the country,'' Mr. Hammonds piped in. ''We're just the same as most places.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hammonds was worried that the president spent a little too much time in places where the old stereotype of Appalachia persists -- on rural roads, out where families have little education or work.</p>
        <p>But the fact remains that very poor people still live along the back roads of Appalachia, in houses that look like abandoned barns. Some of them even live right on the roads for all the world to see.</p>
        <p>Take Jesse McWhorter and his family, who live off a county road in Burning Springs (population about 500), up the road from Annville.</p>
        <p>Jesse, 15, lives with his mother and two sisters, 11 and 8, in a house with so many dogs and puppies and cats and kittens that no one can say exactly how many they own.</p>
        <p>He owns cocks, too, beautiful bantam roosters that he has spared from death despite his belief, once he was born again last year, that raising cocks is the Devil's business.</p>
        <p>''I kept two cocks because they're so beautiful,'' Jesse said. ''The other ones I just took and went like this,'' he said, twisting his hands to show how he snapped their necks.</p>
        <p>When the school van dropped him off recently, his mother, Linda, was on the porch with his sister Chrissie, home from school because she did not feel like going. An old friend, Martha Couch, was on the porch, too.</p>
        <p>Ms. McWhorter and Ms. Couch vaguely remembered the president's visit, though they said they did not vote or pay much attention to politics.</p>
        <p>Ms. Couch, who recently learned from a social worker that she was 75 years old (''I thought I was 72'') said there were not many people like herself and the McWhorters left, families who have lived in the area for generations, mining or growing tobacco,  minding no one's business but their own.</p>
        <p>But Jesse, chewing tobacco and spitting it, awkwardly, said he was going to live a different life.</p>
        <p>''I can't wait to start making some money,'' he said. ''I can drive a truck. Or I can make pizzas.''</p>
        <p>He said he was not even thinking of college. ''I can't afford it,'' he said, dismissing the notion of scholarships or loans. ''I can afford to find my own way, though. I can definitely afford that.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
