<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Happier Second Act; After a Slow Season and a Community Protest, Manhattan Theater Club Savors Its Comeback</title>
    <meta content="26CLUB" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/26/arts/26CLUB.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000927T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233789"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Manhattan Theater Club</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pogrebin, Robin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Meadow, Lynne</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lindsay-Abaire, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Busch, Charles</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Auburn, David</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Fuddy Meers (Play)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Tale of the Allergist's Wife, the (Play)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Proof (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/Companies and Organizations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/Companies and Organizations/Manhattan Theater Club</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000926T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E7DB153AF935A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1834" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Happier Second Act; After a Slow Season and a Community Protest, Manhattan Theater Club Savors Its Comeback</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBIN POGREBIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pogrebin, Robin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Manhattan Theater Club, nonprofit institution, has a great comeback season, with three of its shows becoming hits--Fuddy Meers by David Lindsay-Abaire, Tale of the Allergist's Wife by Charles Busch and Proof by David Auburn; Lynne Meadow, artistic director of Manhattan Theater Club, comments; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Nineteen ninety-eight was not a good year for the Manhattan Theater Club. In the spring the playwrights Jon Robin Baitz and Richard Greenberg said they would no longer bring their work to the theater club because they felt that its aging audiences were unresponsive. Then the theater club, a 30-year-old nonprofit institution that produces plays off Broadway at City Center, became front-page news for caving in to bomb threats and canceling its production of Terrence McNally's ''Corpus Christi,'' a decision it later reversed after protests from writers, actors and civil liberties groups.</p>
        <p>Then one show after another fell flat: the musical ''Captains Courageous,'' and the plays ''Red'' and ''The Memory of Water.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Nineteen ninety-eight was not a good year for the Manhattan Theater Club. In the spring the playwrights Jon Robin Baitz and Richard Greenberg said they would no longer bring their work to the theater club because they felt that its aging audiences were unresponsive. Then the theater club, a 30-year-old nonprofit institution that produces plays off Broadway at City Center, became front-page news for caving in to bomb threats and canceling its production of Terrence McNally's ''Corpus Christi,'' a decision it later reversed after protests from writers, actors and civil liberties groups.</p>
        <p>Then one show after another fell flat: the musical ''Captains Courageous,'' and the plays ''Red'' and ''The Memory of Water.''</p>
        <p>But last season the tide turned. Although Andrew Lippa's new musical, ''The Wild Party,'' was not a success, three other shows became hits: ''Fuddy Meers,'' David Lindsay-Abaire's quirky play about an amnesiac with characters that include an ex-convict, a stroke victim and a sock puppet; Charles Busch's ''Tale of the Allergist's Wife,'' a comedy with Linda Lavin about a West Sider's angst and a mysterious stranger; and David Auburn's ''Proof,'' a drama starring Mary Louise Parker that tracks a young woman's relationships with her ailing father and mathematics.</p>
        <p>''Fuddy Meers'' moved to the Minetta Lane theater for a commercial run last spring, and the other two are moving to Broadway this fall, with ''Allergist's Wife'' reopening at the Barrymore and ''Proof'' at the Walter Kerr.</p>
        <p>Because the Manhattan Theater Club was so recently consumed with damage control, the triumphs are especially welcome. ''I have come to see that variability is in fact an essential byproduct of creating new work,'' said Lynne Meadow, artistic director of the club and director of ''The Allergist's Wife.'' ''I won't underestimate, however, how thrilled I feel that one season later, we are moving two brand new plays by young playwrights to Broadway.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Meadow and Barry Grove, the theater's executive producer, who have worked together for 25 years, say they have been through such ups and downs many times. They attribute their current success to a strong roster of plays, a long-planned retinkering of their subscription audience mix and a recommitment to basic principles after the ''Corpus Christi'' debacle.</p>
        <p>''These things come in cycles; some years you are more responded to by the critics than others,'' Mr. Grove said. ''But I don't think you see any significant change in audience support over the long haul.''</p>
        <p>Since it was founded in 1970 at the Bohemian Benevolent Society Hall on East 73rd Street, the club has established itself as one of New York City's leading nonprofit theaters, with a lineup of hits that includes ''Ain't Misbehavin','' ''Crimes of the Heart'' and ''Love! Valour! Compassion!'' Operating from a two-theater venue at City Center on West 55th Street, it has 17,500 subscribers and an operating budget of $11 million, and has amassed six Tony Awards and 40 Obies.</p>
        <p>Yet the theater may have drawn the most public notice at its lowest ebb, when bomb threats led it to cancel Mr. McNally's ''Corpus Christi,'' which depicts a gay Jesus-like character who has sex with his apostles.</p>
        <p>The theater community mobilized in protest. The South African playwright Athol Fugard threatened to remove his play ''The Captain's Tiger'' from the club's schedule, and postcards registering opposition to the play and its cancellation poured into the theater by the thousands.</p>
        <p>The theater club reversed its decision, prompting protests from Roman Catholic groups and letters of support from the theater community, the public and subscribers. To provide security for its audiences the club enlisted the police and private detectives, and required people attending performances to pass through a metal detector. On opening night on Oct. 13, 1998, the street outside the theater was crowded with some 2,000 demonstrators: at one end those in opposition, at the other those in support.</p>
        <p>''It was a time during which I became perhaps the most acutely aware during all my time at M.T.C. just how weighty a responsibility it is to be at the helm of an institution,'' Ms. Meadow commented. ''I was concerned for people's safety and concerned about protecting freedoms that I had taken as a given my whole career and my whole life: the value and preciousness of the right to freedom of expression.''</p>
        <p>The playwright Tony Kushner, who helped mobilize the arts community during the controversy, said that Ms. Meadow had recovered well. ''She did the right thing,'' he said, ''which isn't easy to do.''</p>
        <p>''Corpus Christi'' was an anomaly for the theater club, which has otherwise been consistent in producing a particular type of play, Mr. Kushner said. '' 'Proof' and 'Allergist's' are of a piece with the general aesthetic that M.T.C. has developed for years and years,'' he said. ''It supports and does a spectacular job with a certain kind of narrative realism on stage that has some political overtones but isn't bitingly political.''</p>
        <p>This season the theater club has chosen new musicals like ''A Class Act,'' with songs by Ed Kleban, who wrote the lyrics for ''A Chorus Line''; ''Time and Again,'' adapted from the novel by Jack Finney; and ''Newyorkers,'' a satirical look at surviving the challenges of city living, by Stephen Winer and Glenn Slater. Among the new plays it will offer are ''Boy Gets Girl,'' by Rebecca Gilman, who wrote ''Spinning Into Butter,'' this season's exploration of race on a college campus; ''Wonder of the World'' by Mr. Lindsay-Abaire, author of ''Fuddy Meers''; and ''Comic Potential'' by Alan Ayckbourn, who has already had three plays produced at the club.</p>
        <p>''A lot of people have their guns out for Manhattan Theater Club as too commercially based,'' said Douglas Cramer, one of the commercial producers who is joining with the club to bring ''Allergist'' to Broadway. ''But you look at their season, and they're taking big chances again.''</p>
        <p>The club is also a co-producer of August Wilson's play ''King Hedley II,'' on Broadway. The club did not invest money in the production but contributed its list of subscribers, which gives the show a valuable built-in audience. The theater club did this with ''The Weir'' in 1999.</p>
        <p>Having clearly grown accustomed to defending the club against charges of conventionality, Ms. Meadow made the point that many of the writers who are now considered establishment were unknown when they started working at the club, including Mr. McNally, Beth Henley and Mr. Greenberg. The same, she pointed out, could be said about the actors Holly Hunter, Dianne Wiest and Kevin Spacey.</p>
        <p>This season's schedule involves a delicate calibration that partly supports the argument made by Mr. Baitz and Mr. Greenberg. The club is featuring work by emerging playwrights like Ms. Gilman and Mr. Lindsay-Abaire that puts it in the buzz. But it is also maintaining its commitment to more established writers who are favorites of its subscriber audience, which tends to be older and probably more conservative than single-ticket buyers.</p>
        <p>''It's been an evolution to create an audience that was responsive to the artists,'' Mr. Grove said. ''For a few years the audience was entirely subscription. I think we came to realize that wasn't an entirely ideal situation. So we made room for additional single-ticket buyers. On the other hand we are very grateful to the loyal subscribers who are sophisticated theatergoers and have supported the careers of all of these artists.''</p>
        <p>''These are people who really have sustained us,'' Ms. Meadow added.  Among them are the theater's 1,000 ''patrons'' who contribute $1,000 or more each year to a budget sustained by grants, gifts and box office receipts. A subscription can cost as much as $275 for a series of six plays and is typically bought by prosperous couples over 40, who tend to plan in advance.</p>
        <p>Lately the theater club has aimed its direct mail at a greater variety of groups, and over the last two years, has allowed some attrition in the total number of subscriptions as well as extending each subscriber run by one week. In addition they have tried to be more creative in attracting nontraditional theatergoers with post-performance discussions on Sundays, gay and lesbian nights and couples' events. Now, Mr. Grove said, one-third of the club's audiences are single-ticket buyers.</p>
        <p>''They're doing great things with younger playwrights,'' Mr. Baitz said. ''One hopes that younger audiences will follow.''</p>
        <p>Moving the two shows to Broadway promises to help the theater broaden its reach further. It has assembled two groups of commercial producers, some of whom are involved in both ventures, to finance the productions. The teams include Broadway veterans like Roger Berlind as well as the newcomer Mr. Cramer, a television producer, and Daryl Roth, who has mostly produced Off Broadway.</p>
        <p>The commercial producers are putting up the entire capitalization of each show: $1.3 million for ''Proof'' and $1.6 million for ''Allergist's Wife.'' The productions originally cost the theater club $750,000 each.</p>
        <p>Someday soon the club hopes to have a larger venue of its own. It  considered two historic Broadway theaters, the Biltmore and the Selwyn, the latter of which was recently transformed into the American Airlines Theater at a cost of $25 million.</p>
        <p>In the meantime the club's main stage and smaller second space at city-owned City Center are undergoing a $1.6 million renovation that will be paid for through the city's capital budget.</p>
        <p>The theater occasionally avails itself of what is called enhancement money, funds contributed by entrepreneurial producers to nonprofit productions in exchange for the option to move a show to a commercial house.</p>
        <p>Nonprofit theaters say they have little choice but to pursue these collaborations, given how government grants have diminished. ''It is virtually impossible to do a series of musicals without additional money of one kind or another,'' Mr. Grove said.</p>
        <p>But such arrangements also raise the question of whether some nonprofit shows are little more than tryouts for commercial productions and weaken the appetite for more experimental, challenging fare.</p>
        <p>For plays like ''The Allergist's Wife,'' Ms. Meadow and Mr. Grove say, the main creative decisions had already been made when the commercial producers came into the picture. ''Barry and I produced and directed the shows for Manhattan Theater Club without any involvement with any commercial producers,'' Ms. Meadow said. ''These are shows that were created by us.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  September 27, 2000, Wednesday  A picture caption yesterday with an article about a successful turnaround for the Manhattan Theater Club misspelled the given name of its artistic director. As noted in the article, she is Lynne Meadow, not Lynn.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: September 27, 2000, Wednesday</p>
        <p>A picture caption yesterday with an article about a successful turnaround for the Manhattan Theater Club misspelled the given name of its artistic director. As noted in the article, she is Lynne Meadow, not Lynn.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
