<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; Facing Backlash Head-On</title>
    <meta content="26GEOR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/26/sports/26GEOR.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233864"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Jets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Tampa Bay Buccaneers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">George, Thomas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnson, Keyshawn</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Tampa Bay Buccaneers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000926T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E1DE123AF935A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="927" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; Facing Backlash Head-On</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS GEORGE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">George, Thomas</byline>
      <dateline>TAMPA, Fla.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Thomas George Sports of The Times column discusses reaction of Tampa Bay Buccaneers receiver Keyshawn Johnson, former New York Jets, to his new team's loss to his old team; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>KEYSHAWN JOHNSON flipped through the clippings of New York newspaper articles about his new team's 21-17 loss to his old team on Sunday. He expected what he saw: ''This Flashlight Leaves Key in the Dark.'' ''Keyshawn Looks Like Invisible Star.'' ''Keyshawn's a Mascot for All Loudmouths.''</p>
        <p>''I understand that I'm the big, bad bully and they are the heroes,'' Johnson said. ''That's fine. I play my game the way I believe in and they play it their way. There is no lesson to be learned here about me shutting up before any battle. A game is in the books. We have Washington next and that is the place for us to get better and correct things. Sure, I would have loved to beat the Jets, but I've lost to friends before. This wasn't the first time and it won't be the last. But I am going to battle to the end, because Super Bowls are not won in September.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>KEYSHAWN JOHNSON flipped through the clippings of New York newspaper articles about his new team's 21-17 loss to his old team on Sunday. He expected what he saw: ''This Flashlight Leaves Key in the Dark.'' ''Keyshawn Looks Like Invisible Star.'' ''Keyshawn's a Mascot for All Loudmouths.''</p>
        <p>''I understand that I'm the big, bad bully and they are the heroes,'' Johnson said. ''That's fine. I play my game the way I believe in and they play it their way. There is no lesson to be learned here about me shutting up before any battle. A game is in the books. We have Washington next and that is the place for us to get better and correct things. Sure, I would have loved to beat the Jets, but I've lost to friends before. This wasn't the first time and it won't be the last. But I am going to battle to the end, because Super Bowls are not won in September.''</p>
        <p>But some grudge matches are, and the Jets are the victors in this one.</p>
        <p>Johnson showed yesterday that he was willing to mix it up before, during and after games, regardless of the outcome. Surprised? Of course not. He will always have something to say -- win, lose or tie.</p>
        <p>''I'm not going to hide or run,'' he said. ''After the game, on the field, I talked to a few of the Jets I'm friends with and that I care about. Some of them were Cox, Ward, Hayes, Glenn, Coleman, Mickens, Phifer, Farrior, Al Groh. No, just kidding.''</p>
        <p>He laughed. It was an easy laugh, but there was frustration behind it. There was concern.</p>
        <p>The first one was over a mistake he admits he made before the game. During a Tampa Bay practice last week, Johnson was filmed tossing his finger at a camera, the wrong finger.</p>
        <p>''I was playing with him,'' Johnson said. ''It never even crossed my mind that they would air that. It was meant in fun, between me and him, but I know it was not the proper thing to do. It was my mistake and I learned from it. That is the only thing leading up to the game that I would take back and do over if I could.''</p>
        <p>But he takes back none of what he said about Groh, about Jets receiver Wayne Chrebet being a flashlight and Johnson a star, about the greatness of the Tampa Bay defense.</p>
        <p>His second concern is over the way he was used in the game. He was nearly invisible in a Tampa Bay offense that scored a field goal in each of the first two quarters and with no points in the second half. For the game, he had one catch for 1 yard.</p>
        <p>''And that was a shovel pass, so that's not even like a catch,'' Johnson said.</p>
        <p>Still, Tampa Bay led, 17-6, with two minutes left. That was when the Jets took the game.</p>
        <p>''I believe we learned from this game how we have to go for the throat, go for the kill,'' Johnson said. ''We can't play around with teams and just try to hold on at the end or win in the end. We've got to go for it, grab it.''</p>
        <p>Maybe Tampa Bay realizes that there is a crack in its armor. This is a team, a franchise, that insists on winning with defense. But the Jets game showed that style leaves little margin for error, that a team built to win with defense cannot have that defense on the field for much of the last quarter trying, repeatedly, to protect a lead against a good team.</p>
        <p>Here the Buccaneers were with Johnson versus his old team, and he catches one pass. There is no way he should only touch the football once in such a game. More creativity and more insistence on his involvement -- flanker screens, moving him repeatedly in various formations, hitch passes, short tosses, any design and play that puts his hands on the ball -- might have meant more points and more margin for defensive error.</p>
        <p>The way some of the Buccaneers viewed it, on Sunday Johnson was a $53 million decoy. It appeared that Tampa Bay did not want to challenge the Jets with Johnson and use him as a dagger.</p>
        <p>But the Jets sure did that with Chrebet.</p>
        <p>''You think that halfback option play to him wasn't put in and used with me in mind?'' Johnson said with a wink. ''And used right there in that situation?''</p>
        <p>Johnson, however, is not ready to write ''Just Give Me the Damn Ball, Part II.''</p>
        <p>''I put my trust in this team, our coaches and our quarterback,'' Johnson said. ''I believe that everyone here will do the right thing by me and the team. I've been through this before. With the Jets, I had to work to get the ball more and it paid off. I've only been here for four games. They are just learning how to use me and to really know what I can do. I understand that.''</p>
        <p>But for how long?</p>
        <p>''As long as it takes,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
