<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>OBSERVATORY</title>
    <meta content="26OBSE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/26/science/26OBSE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233759"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Aspen Trees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wolves</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lead</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pluto (Planet)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Yellowstone National Park</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">California</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">San Francisco Bay</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fountain, Henry</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Columns/Observatory</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Wyoming/Yellowstone National Park</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lead</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pluto (Planet)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leisure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000926T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE5DF143AF935A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="677" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>OBSERVATORY</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HENRY FOUNTAIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fountain, Henry</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Researchers at Yellowstone National Park suggest that a sharp decline in aspen trees over past century can be linked to elimination of wolves; researchers report that leaded gasoline spewed from cars three or four decades ago is still washing out of central valleys of California into rivers, and then into southern parts of San Francisco Bay; NASA stops work on planned mission to Pluto, and scientists worry that this will delay any chance to visit planet for years (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Fates of Wolf and Aspen</p>
        <p>The hip bone's connected to the thigh bone, as the old children's song goes, and in ecology, things are tied together as well. The latest case in point comes from Yellowstone National Park, where researchers suggest that a sharp decline in aspen trees over the past century can be linked to the elimination of wolves.</p>
        <p>The researchers, from Oregon State University, have been studying the decline in aspen groves in the park, using historical documents, aerial photographs and ring-dating. As they report in the journal Biological Conservation, they determined that for more than a century and a half, until the late 1920's, young trees were able to survive and mature within existing groves. Things changed around the time that the wolves in and around the park were eliminated (the last wolves were seen in 1926).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Fates of Wolf and Aspen</p>
        <p>The hip bone's connected to the thigh bone, as the old children's song goes, and in ecology, things are tied together as well. The latest case in point comes from Yellowstone National Park, where researchers suggest that a sharp decline in aspen trees over the past century can be linked to the elimination of wolves.</p>
        <p>The researchers, from Oregon State University, have been studying the decline in aspen groves in the park, using historical documents, aerial photographs and ring-dating. As they report in the journal Biological Conservation, they determined that for more than a century and a half, until the late 1920's, young trees were able to survive and mature within existing groves. Things changed around the time that the wolves in and around the park were eliminated (the last wolves were seen in 1926).</p>
        <p>Here is the connection, as theorized by the researchers. Wolves are natural predators of elk, and elk like to munch on aspen suckers in the winter, stunting the trees. When the wolves disappeared, the numbers of elk increased, and their behavior changed -- they no longer avoided areas, like aspen groves, where they were vulnerable to wolf attack. So this might be one reason the trees suffered.</p>
        <p>The researchers are testing this theory. And of course, wolves were reintroduced to the park in 1995. But it is too early to say whether their reintroduction will help the aspens.</p>
        <p>Long-Lingering Pollution</p>
        <p>When it comes to pollution, the hip bone's connected to the thigh bone as well, and it can stay connected for a long time. Pollution from one source can wind up elsewhere, and linger.</p>
        <p>Take leaded gasoline, which is long departed from American gas stations but still doing its dirty work, according to researchers from the University of California at Santa Cruz who have studied lead pollution in San Francisco Bay and its tributaries, the San Joaquin and Sacramento Rivers.</p>
        <p>The researchers determined that lead spewed from cars three or four decades ago is still washing out of the Central Valley of California into the rivers, and then into southern parts of the bay. They reported on their work in The Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences.</p>
        <p>The researchers calculate that it will be another 50 to 100 years before all the lead is washed out. And because as estuaries go, San Francisco Bay does not flush very well, the lead is likely to remain in sediments in the bay indefinitely.</p>
        <p>While there is no indication that this lead is hurting humans or animals, the study offers fresh evidence that pollution is like an unwanted house guest -- it just won't go away.</p>
        <p>Setback for Pluto Mission</p>
        <p>NASA has stopped work on a planned mission to Pluto, and planetary scientists are worried that this will delay any chance to visit the planet for years.</p>
        <p>NASA issued a stop-work order to the Jet Propulsion Laboratory this month, citing rising development costs for the mission, called the Pluto-Kuiper Express, and two others to far reaches of the solar system (although work continues on these).</p>
        <p>But a committee of the division of planetary sciences of the American Astronomical Society noted that if work was not resumed before the end of the year, any chance to launch the mission in 2004 would be lost. The next launching window would not be until about 2011, with an arrival date of 2019 or later.</p>
        <p>Don Savage, a spokesman, said NASA acted because of ''significant cost growth'' of most missions over the past few months. ''The best thing was to go with the highest priority science missions first,'' he said, and to redesign the Pluto project to reduce costs.</p>
        <p>Pluto is the only planet in the solar system yet to be visited. After encountering the planet, the spacecraft would probably go on to one or more icy asteroidlike bodies in the Kuiper Disk, a cloud of small objects believed to be left over from the formation of the solar system.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
