<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>How to Dance Balanchine? 6 Troupes Count the Ways</title>
    <meta content="26BALA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/26/arts/26BALA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233779"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BALLET REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">San Francisco Ballet</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pennsylvania Ballet</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Kennedy, John F, Center for the Performing Arts (Washington, DC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Anderson, Jack</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Balanchine, George (1904-83)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000926T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E6DC153AF935A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="781" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>How to Dance Balanchine? 6 Troupes Count the Ways</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK ANDERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Anderson, Jack</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Sept. 23</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jack Anderson reviews dance program by San Francisco Ballet and Pennsylvania Ballet at Kennedy Center, Washington, part of two-week Balanchine celebration involving six dance companies; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>George Balanchine the abstractionist. Balanchine the storyteller. Balanchine the prankster. Those facets of Balanchine's choreographic personality were beautifully displayed when the San Francisco Ballet and the Pennsylvania Ballet shared a program this afternoon as part of the Balanchine Celebration at the Kennedy Center here.</p>
        <p>The San Francisco Ballet, directed by Helgi Tomasson, danced Balanchine's abstract ''Symphony in Three Movements'' and his dramatic ''Prodigal Son.'' The Philadelphia-based Pennsylvania Ballet, under Roy Kaiser's direction, offered Balanchine's tongue-in-cheek ''Western Symphony.'' Each performance was admirable in itself. And to see the two groups on the center's Opera House stage made one realize the value of the Balanchine Celebration.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>George Balanchine the abstractionist. Balanchine the storyteller. Balanchine the prankster. Those facets of Balanchine's choreographic personality were beautifully displayed when the San Francisco Ballet and the Pennsylvania Ballet shared a program this afternoon as part of the Balanchine Celebration at the Kennedy Center here.</p>
        <p>The San Francisco Ballet, directed by Helgi Tomasson, danced Balanchine's abstract ''Symphony in Three Movements'' and his dramatic ''Prodigal Son.'' The Philadelphia-based Pennsylvania Ballet, under Roy Kaiser's direction, offered Balanchine's tongue-in-cheek ''Western Symphony.'' Each performance was admirable in itself. And to see the two groups on the center's Opera House stage made one realize the value of the Balanchine Celebration.</p>
        <p>The two-week celebration has featured six companies in significant Balanchine works. At today's matinee all the dancers looked scrupulously coached and rehearsed. Moreover, their presentations of three familiar ballets suggested that there is no single correct way to dance Balanchine, just as there is no single correct way to interpret a Beethoven symphony. Just as different orchestras and conductors may invest compositions with their own special aesthetic insights, so dance companies may have their own individual approaches to ballets.</p>
        <p>Take ''Symphony in Three Movements.'' However it is danced, this plotless work of 1972 to a Stravinsky score is an outburst of energy. Some companies emphasize the choreography's sheer forcefulness, making dance phrases seem like potentially lethal bolts of lightning, but the San Franciscans bounded with such exhilaration in this staging supervised by Richard Tanner that watching the ballet was like beholding a brilliant fireworks display.</p>
        <p>The ensemble brought distinctive flair to the rushings and leaps in the first movement, which featured Lucia Lacarra, Vanessa Zahorian, Lorena Feijoo, Yuri Possokhov, Parrish Maynard and Michael Eaton as soloists. And Ms. Lacarra and Mr. Possokhov looked elegant in the pas de deux, much of which is in slow motion.</p>
        <p>''Prodigal Son,'' Balanchine's biblical parable of 1929 to music by Prokofiev, invites many nuances of characterization. In the San Francisco production, staged by Elyse Borne and Mr. Tomasson with additional coaching by Gloria Govrin, Gonzalo Garcia was an extremely boyish Prodigal, eager to see the world outside the family walls, but so naive that he easily fell prey to the predators he encountered there. Near the end of the ballet, when they had robbed him of his possessions and he crept wearily homeward, the sense of exhaustion Mr. Garcia created in his strugglings suggested that the Prodigal's illusions as well as his body had been battered.</p>
        <p>As the Siren who seduced him, Yuan Yuan Tan made her face an impassive mask while smoothly bending her body into one strange eye-catching contortion after another. This was a professional temptress whose job was simply to tempt, and she performed that job well.</p>
        <p>She was alluring yet oddly detached at the same time. No wonder the Prodigal was both puzzled and fascinated by her.</p>
        <p>Kester Cotton and Ikolo Griffin were appropriately boisterous as the Servants. Ashley Wheater gave an especially fine portrayal of the Prodigal's Father. In some productions this character merely stands firmly like a big boulder with a long beard. But the attentiveness with which Mr. Wheater gazed at the dancers portraying his children and the careful way in which he reached his hands toward them implied that this patriarch was loving as well as strong.</p>
        <p>''Western Symphony,'' choreographed in 1954 to a score by Hershey Kay based on American folk tunes, is Balanchine's joking tribute to western music and cowboy movies. The men look like cowhands; the women like dance-hall entertainers. And although all the steps derive from classical technique, group sequences are often reminiscent of square-dance patterns.</p>
        <p>The Pennsylvania Ballet brought a suitable zest to a staging by Sandra Jennings. Originally Balanchine choreographed ''Western Symphony'' in four movements. Later he cut one of them. Companies remain free to choose which version they prefer. The Pennsylvanians did ''Western Symphony'' in three movements, and made all three fun.</p>
        <p>Heidi Cruz was a smiling flirt and Edward Cieslak was an extroverted cowpoke in the first movement's pas de deux. Jonas Lundqvist was a dreamy cowboy and Martha Chamberlain was his dainty vision in the second movement and everyone whirled exuberantly in the finale.</p>
        <p>The Kennedy Center Opera House Orchestra gave a fine account of the scores, as conducted by Emil de Cou and Scott Speck of the San Francisco Ballet and Beatrice Affron of the Pennsylvania Ballet.</p>
        <p>BALLET REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
