<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Parade Of Youth And Stars For Stern</title>
    <meta content="26STER" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/26/arts/26STER.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233778"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holland, Bernard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stern, Isaac</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000926T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E7DC153AF935A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="660" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Parade Of Youth And Stars For Stern</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BERNARD HOLLAND</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Holland, Bernard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Concert tributes to celebrate violinist Isaac Stern's 80th birthday are held at Carnegie Hall; photo; Bernard Holland review (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Deciding evidently that one evening would not do, Carnegie Hall took a weekend to celebrate Isaac Stern's 80th birthday. On Saturday there were films. Sunday was packed with family concerts. The Miro and Aviv String Quartets played at Weill Recital Hall. Distinguished soloists, singers and members of the New York Philharmonic were everywhere. And a long tribute -- a parade of youth and celebrity -- serenaded Mr. Stern on Sunday evening. Two of his sons conducted; a daughter spoke.</p>
        <p>A performer is by nature a public person, but Isaac Stern has been more public than most. In his prime he was a violinist known for powerful musicianship and an unadulterated sense of style. As a civic activist, he prominently figured in saving of Carnegie Hall from demolition 40 years ago and became its president. As a teacher of individuals and chamber groups he has had the gift of avoiding vague generalizations and empty rhetoric and addressing the problems of learning acutely and specifically. Mr. Stern had serious heart surgery barely a month ago, but he was present in a first-tier box with his family on Sunday, frail yet happily attentive.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Deciding evidently that one evening would not do, Carnegie Hall took a weekend to celebrate Isaac Stern's 80th birthday. On Saturday there were films. Sunday was packed with family concerts. The Miro and Aviv String Quartets played at Weill Recital Hall. Distinguished soloists, singers and members of the New York Philharmonic were everywhere. And a long tribute -- a parade of youth and celebrity -- serenaded Mr. Stern on Sunday evening. Two of his sons conducted; a daughter spoke.</p>
        <p>A performer is by nature a public person, but Isaac Stern has been more public than most. In his prime he was a violinist known for powerful musicianship and an unadulterated sense of style. As a civic activist, he prominently figured in saving of Carnegie Hall from demolition 40 years ago and became its president. As a teacher of individuals and chamber groups he has had the gift of avoiding vague generalizations and empty rhetoric and addressing the problems of learning acutely and specifically. Mr. Stern had serious heart surgery barely a month ago, but he was present in a first-tier box with his family on Sunday, frail yet happily attentive.</p>
        <p>His colleague Leonard Bernstein came up more than once. Glenn Dicterow was the splendid violinist in two movements from the Serenade; Betty Comden and Adolph Green made boisterous appearances in show tunes. Sarah Chang, Sharon Robinson and Joseph Kalichstein did the first movement of the Beethoven Triple Concerto with great sureness. A group heavy with members of the Guarneri and Juilliard Quartets played two movements of Mendelssohn's E flat Octet. Supporting the bigger pieces was the Symphony Orchestra of the Curtis Institute of Music, a tight and elegant young ensemble that David and Michael Stern conducted to great effect.</p>
        <p>Such events hover by nature between the carefully prepared and the ad hoc, and some moments seem better rehearsed than others. It would not be generous to dwell on the mismatch of Midori and Pinchas Zukerman in two movements from Mozart's Sinfonia Concertante for violin and viola: Midori with her slim, penetrating music next to Mr. Zukerman's big bear-hug approach to Classical style. If Yefim Bronfman and Leon Fleisher had a few balance problems of their own in Schubert's D major Rondo for piano four hands, we have to remember that this wonderful music (especially as played by musicians this good) is best celebrated in a private not a public place.</p>
        <p>Easily the evening's most satisfying music came with its most familiar item: ''The Swan'' from Saint-Saens's ''Carnival of the Animals,'' played here with magisterial simplicity by Yo-Yo Ma, cellist, and Emanuel Ax, pianist. Sir Peter Ustinov, himself nearly 80, delivered his own text to the Saint-Saens, prefacing it with a comic riff on German musicology.</p>
        <p>With Carnegie Hall's executive director, Franz Xaver Ohnesorg, cheerleading and directing traffic, a grand finale adapted Ernst Toch's spoken ''Geographical Fugue'' to a new text that followed Mr. Stern's long career. Kurt Masur, music director of the New York Philharmonic, conducted the chorus of Carnegie staff members who may have been the best prepared of Sunday's small army of performers. Everyone crowded the stage at the end. Mr. Stern spoke briefly. ''Happy Birthday'' was sung.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
