<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>St. Vincents Mourns Loss Of 4 Nurses</title>
    <meta content="26CRAS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/26/nyregion/26CRAS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233937"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parking Garages and Lots</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Virginia Beach (Va)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Christian, Nichole M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dono, Mary Ann</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mollick-Kelly, Kathleen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Walsh, Joan Ellen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Going, Mary Ann</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Virginia/Virginia Beach</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000926T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E0DB123AF935A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="778" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>St. Vincents Mourns Loss Of 4 Nurses</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NICHOLE M. CHRISTIAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Christian, Nichole M</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Friends and felow workers St Vincents Hospital in Manhattan discuss Mary Ann Dono, Kathleen Mollick-Kelly, Joan Ellen Walsh and Mary Ann Going, four women who were killed when their car plowed through wall in parking lot in Virginia Beach; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Friends since nursing school, the four women had worked a combined 158 years at St. Vincents Hospital in Manhattan, caring for ill children. They loved traveling almost as much as they loved their work, and that  common passion sent them on trips around the world together.</p>
        <p>That bond offered some comfort to their colleagues yesterday, as they mourned the deaths of the women,  pediatric nurses who died together Sunday afternoon in Virginia Beach  when their car smashed through a parking garage wall and fell 41 feet onto a busy beachfront entrance.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Friends since nursing school, the four women had worked a combined 158 years at St. Vincents Hospital in Manhattan, caring for ill children. They loved traveling almost as much as they loved their work, and that  common passion sent them on trips around the world together.</p>
        <p>That bond offered some comfort to their colleagues yesterday, as they mourned the deaths of the women,  pediatric nurses who died together Sunday afternoon in Virginia Beach  when their car smashed through a parking garage wall and fell 41 feet onto a busy beachfront entrance.</p>
        <p>The crash killed Mary Ann Dono, 60, of Bay Ridge, Brooklyn; Mary Ann Going, 60, of East Elmhurst, Queens; Kathleen Mollick-Kelly, 63, of the Upper West Side of Manhattan; and Joan Ellen Walsh, 56, of Flatlands, Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>''If you wanted to get one of them, all you had to do was call one of the others,'' said Dr. Anthony Gagliardi, the medical director of St. Vincents Hospital and Medical Center, who knew the women for more than 20 years. ''They were almost inseparable, a true family. They made care at this institution not just clinically proper but humanistically proper.''</p>
        <p>Police in Virginia Beach, where the women were vacationing, remained puzzled yesterday as to what caused the women's 1999 Honda Accord to plow through a three-foot-high concrete wall and crash to the ground from the top floor of the five-story parking garage. A police spokesman said a preliminary investigation showed no signs of mechanical problems with the car or alcohol use by the driver, Ms. Walsh.</p>
        <p>Barbara Rogus, a neighbor of Ms. Walsh's, said: ''They worked together, they traveled together. So God took them together.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Dono, known around the hospital as the ''walking pediatrics encyclopedia,'' managed the pediatric and neonatal intensive care unit and  had worked at St. Vincents since 1960, officials said. Ms. Going, who joined the staff a year later, was the unit's nursing care coordinator and staff education instructor. Ms. Walsh began work at the hospital in 1964 and was the pediatric case manager. Mrs. Mollick-Kelly, the only one of the women to ever marry, was the head nurse of the pediatric and obstetrics/gynecology outpatient clinic. She was divorced and had worked at the hospital since 1957.</p>
        <p>Ms. Dono, who was a eucharistic minister at St. Patrick's Church in  Bay Ridge, Brooklyn, had been an instructor at St. Vincents' nursing school, which closed in 1999.</p>
        <p>In between consoling one another, colleagues spent the day reminiscing  and marveling at how the women had dedicated their lives to caring for children but never had any of their own.</p>
        <p>''They were totally, totally dedicated to children and nursing,'' said Sister Miriam Kevin Phillips, the former nursing school director, who knew the women for 30 years. ''Hundreds of nursing students were exposed to their wisdom and compassion. Our pediatric department is just incapable of even talking about what it will be like not to see them.''</p>
        <p>As St. Vincents began to grapple with the loss, the police in Virginia Beach continued to try to piece together the details of the accident. Witnesses told the police they saw it drive into the garage then plunge from the rooftop level shortly after 12:30 p.m. Sunday. The garage is next to the Sandcastle Oceanfront Motel, where the women were staying.</p>
        <p>''In almost 30 years of policing, this is one of the most bizarre accidents I've ever seen,'' said Don Rimer, a spokesman for the Virginia Beach Police. ''The car drove up the ramp, made a turn, then went through the wall. There is no evidence that the brakes were applied and no evidence that excessive speed or alcohol were involved. We don't know what caused this one.''</p>
        <p>The police hope to answer some of the questions by dismantling and rebuilding the car, he said. They are also examining the garage to see whether it was structurally sound.</p>
        <p>Ms. Rogus, Ms. Walsh's neighbor, said, ''These were mature women who wouldn't go out and do something reckless.''</p>
        <p>The motel's general manager, Varshid Vachhani, said: ''The management and the staff are deeply shocked. It's something that we can't imagine happening in our wildest nightmares.''</p>
        <p>Thousands of people had been milling about for an end-of-summer festival at the time of the crash. ''The true miracle is that no one on the ground was hit,'' Mr. Rimer said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
