<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nightclub Incident Leaves Celtic Recovering From Stab Wounds</title>
    <meta content="26CELT$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/26/sports/26CELT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233889"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Assaults</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Boston (Mass)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Boston Celtics</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pierce, Paul</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Williams, Lena</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Boston Celtics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts/Boston</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Assaults</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000926T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E7DC123AF935A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="536" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nightclub Incident Leaves Celtic Recovering From Stab Wounds</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LENA WILLIAMS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Williams, Lena</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Boston Celtics basketball player Paul Pierce is stabbed more than five times during an altercation inside Boston nightclub; he is listed in fair condition; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Paul Pierce, considered one of the Boston Celtics' rising stars, was stabbed more than five times during an altercation early yesterday inside a Boston nightclub, according to the police.</p>
        <p>Pierce, a versatile 6-foot-7-inch, 220-pound swingman who played guard and forward last season, underwent surgery at the New England Medical Center for wounds to his face, neck and back. A hospital spokesman said Pierce was listed in fair condition.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Paul Pierce, considered one of the Boston Celtics' rising stars, was stabbed more than five times during an altercation early yesterday inside a Boston nightclub, according to the police.</p>
        <p>Pierce, a versatile 6-foot-7-inch, 220-pound swingman who played guard and forward last season, underwent surgery at the New England Medical Center for wounds to his face, neck and back. A hospital spokesman said Pierce was listed in fair condition.</p>
        <p>''He's doing fine. We're all hoping for a speedy recovery,'' Celtics Coach Rick Pitino told The Associated Press as he left the hospital.</p>
        <p>According to a report on the Boston radio station WEEI-AM, the injuries to Pierce, a 22-year-old former Kansas All-American, did not appear to be so grave as to threaten his career. Pierce averaged 19.5 points for the Celtics last season and was second in the National Basketball Association in steals with 2.08 per game.</p>
        <p>WBZ-TV in Boston reported that Pierce had been hit over the head with a bottle and that most of the stab wounds were superficial except for a 7-inch-deep cut to his sternum.</p>
        <p>Boston police said the stabbing took place around 1 a.m. yesterday in a poolroom at the Buzz Club in the city's theater district. Pierce, who was scheduled to report for training camp next Monday, was attending a private party with friends, including another Celtics player. Several stations and The Associated Press reported that the player was Tony Battie.</p>
        <p>Pierce was driven by friends to a nearby hospital for treatment.</p>
        <p>Mariellen Burns, director of information for the Boston Police Department, said yesterday that no arrests had been made. She said the police were looking into statements made by witnesses that the incident might have involved associates of the Boston rap group Made Men.</p>
        <p>In 1998, Pierce decided to forgo his senior year at Kansas to enter the N.B.A. He was drafted by the Celtics in the first round. In his rookie season, he started 47 of the 48 games he appeared in and averaged 16.5 points, 6.4 rebounds and 1.71 steals. He was named to the all-rookie first team.</p>
        <p>In a statement released yesterday, Kansas Coach Roy Williams described Pierce as ''one of the greatest young men I have ever been around.''</p>
        <p>''I am shocked and saddened by last night's events,'' he said. ''I have been in contact with the Celtics people and the hospital and I expect to be in touch with the family later today. Right now, it's just too early to tell what the final word on this will be.''</p>
        <p>Eric Chenowith, a junior center at Kansas who played with Pierce, said he was surprised when he heard about the incident.</p>
        <p>''He's a happy-go-lucky guy,'' Chenowith said in a statement released by the college. ''He always jokes around with guys, always has a smile on his face. From what I heard he was breaking something up, and that's totally in the character of Paul to break something up.''</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
