<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Composer May Age, but the Compositions Are Ever Young</title>
    <meta content="26REIC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/26/arts/26REIC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233771"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Schuman, William, Award</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Columbia University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Griffiths, Paul</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reich, Steve</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000926T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E2DD153AF935A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="600" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Composer May Age, but the Compositions Are Ever Young</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAUL GRIFFITHS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Griffiths, Paul</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Music of Steve Reich is presented at Miller Theater of Columbia University; Reich receives Columbia's prestigious William Schuman Award; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Things both change and do not change. That is perhaps the central lesson of Steve Reich's music, and through matching concerts he gave with his regular musicians at Miller Theater on Thursday and Saturday evenings, the lesson zigzagged through many dimensions.</p>
        <p>The four players intent on a pair of xylophones in the first part of ''Drumming'' -- Bob Becker, Russell Hartenberger, James Preiss and Mr. Reich himself -- were there when the music was new nearly three decades ago, wearing similar plain outfits of white shirts and dark pants. Time might have silvered and thinned the hair on their heads, but the music they were making now was as young as ever, exuberantly rattling through processes of growing complexity and changing pattern against a stable pulse and a stable repeating frame.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Things both change and do not change. That is perhaps the central lesson of Steve Reich's music, and through matching concerts he gave with his regular musicians at Miller Theater on Thursday and Saturday evenings, the lesson zigzagged through many dimensions.</p>
        <p>The four players intent on a pair of xylophones in the first part of ''Drumming'' -- Bob Becker, Russell Hartenberger, James Preiss and Mr. Reich himself -- were there when the music was new nearly three decades ago, wearing similar plain outfits of white shirts and dark pants. Time might have silvered and thinned the hair on their heads, but the music they were making now was as young as ever, exuberantly rattling through processes of growing complexity and changing pattern against a stable pulse and a stable repeating frame.</p>
        <p>Yet that identical music has altered in its implications over the years. Where once it started a piece lasting not much more than an hour, now it opens toward half a lifetime of music. In other ways, meanwhile, its focus has concentrated. Connections with Ghana, where Mr. Reich had recently studied when he wrote these notes, have relaxed; the music is now more personal.</p>
        <p>Particularly -- since ''Different Trains,'' the 1988 piece for string quartet and recordings that was also played at these concerts -- the regular click-clack rhythmic appoggiaturas of Mr. Reich's music, weak-strong, have gained another history in his childhood experience of rail travel across the United States.</p>
        <p>The two concerts -- given to a packed and enthusiastic audience for the most part younger than ''Drumming'' -- were devised around the presentation of Columbia University's infrequently given and prestigious William Schuman Award to Mr. Reich. The events thoroughly achieved their celebratory objective. Both opened with a classic -- the ''Drumming'' introduction on Thursday, the intellectually sparkling and physically exciting ''Music for Pieces of Wood'' on Saturday -- and then moved through the dark 1980's (Sextet and ''Different Trains'') to arrive at the joyful 1976 of ''Music for 18 Musicians.''</p>
        <p>Joyful, too, were the performances of this final piece on each occasion. The work went around the world in the late 1970's in the form of a recording, but it gains a lot from being experienced in live performance. One can see and hear how the vibraphone player chimes signals, like courses of bells from a tower, to which the others respond with a gearing up or down of harmony, or how musicians move from one instrument to another to bring about changes in the texture. Watched as well as heard, ''Music for 18 Musicians'' is a kind of ceremony, voiced in repeating bits of tune, in harmonic progressions, in sumptuous sonorities, in time.</p>
        <p>A ceremony enjoins submission to order, and ''Music for 18 Musicians''  looks and sounds like human clockwork. But this is not frightening. When engaged in with full heart, vigor and alertness by everyone, as here, the detailed plan is not a confinement but a recipe for exuberance. The wheels of the clock go around smoothly at their different rates: a few seconds for a measure, an hour for the giant cycle that is the entire work. And the passing of time is not baneful but exhilarating.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
