<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Searching for Genes to Slow The Hands of Biological Time</title>
    <meta content="26PROF$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/26/science/26PROF.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233803"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SCIENTIST AT WORK: LEONARD GUARENTE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Longevity</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Diet and Nutrition</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wade, Nicholas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Guarene, Leonard (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Columns/Scientist at Work</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Diet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Age, Chronological</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diet and Nutrition</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000926T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE1DB153AF935A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="2032" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Searching for Genes to Slow The Hands of Biological Time</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NICHOLAS WADE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wade, Nicholas</byline>
      <dateline>CAMBRIDGE, Mass.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of Dr Leonard Guarente, professor of biology at Massachusetts Institute of Technology who studies genes that control aging and who has reported a finding that may explain exactly how very low calorie diets--the one known intervention known to prolong life in experimental organisms--may achieve that end; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''Research is a very circuitous road. It requires tremendous patience and tolerance for failure. That's something you don't find out about yourself till you actually do it. It's depressing to put so much time and effort into something and have nothing to show for it.''</p>
        <p>So says Dr. Leonard Guarente, a professor of biology at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology who studies the genes that control aging. But this connoisseur of failure has recently been enjoying a string of successes in a long intractable field of research.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''Research is a very circuitous road. It requires tremendous patience and tolerance for failure. That's something you don't find out about yourself till you actually do it. It's depressing to put so much time and effort into something and have nothing to show for it.''</p>
        <p>So says Dr. Leonard Guarente, a professor of biology at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology who studies the genes that control aging. But this connoisseur of failure has recently been enjoying a string of successes in a long intractable field of research.</p>
        <p>On Sept. 22, after a nine-year pursuit, he reported a finding that may explain exactly how very low calorie diets -- the one intervention known to prolong life in experimental organisms -- may achieve that end.</p>
        <p>The discovery, though made in yeast cells, could have broad consequences should it prove true of people too, because it identifies a cellular pathway -- and possible drug target -- by which caloric restriction works. Actuaries, put down your gloomy mortality tables and sharpen your pencils! Heirs and legatees, contain yourselves in patience! If any such drug were to work in humans the same way that this diet of 30 percent less than normal calories works in laboratory rodents, people would start enjoying a maximum life span of 170 years, most of it in perfect health.</p>
        <p>Dr. Guarente's startling insight into caloric restriction was gained by taking a large though well-calculated career risk. Growing up in Revere, Mass., he preferred physics and chemistry to biology, which seemed purely descriptive, and to this day the biology questions in Jeopardy are his weakest subject. But the buzz about molecular biology in his freshman dormitory at M.I.T. piqued his interest.</p>
        <p>He trained under two well-known Harvard biologists, Dr. Jon Beckwith and Dr. Mark Ptashne, and after setting up his own lab at M.I.T. in 1981 he became over the next nine years an expert in gene transcription, the mechanism cells use to make working copies of the genes on their chromosomes.</p>
        <p>But instead of staying in this safe and mainstream field, he started looking around for some riskier subject, one where if he could make any headway at all he would have an impact.</p>
        <p>''After I got tenure, for four or five years I batted around some ideas, one of which was learning and memory,'' Dr. Guarente said. But the memory process looked difficult and it seemed to him there was a better chance of making progress in aging. ''It's a less crowded field, partly because it's less clear what to do,'' he says.</p>
        <p>At the time, a decade ago, almost no molecular biologists -- people who study life at the level of genes and molecules -- were working on aging. The field belonged to evolutionary biologists whose work in the field consisted largely of thought experiments.</p>
        <p>When molecular biologists wish to understand a process, they look for the genes that may control it. Experiments on aging tend to take a long time even in mice, which live for two years, so Dr. Guarente chose to look first in yeast for genes that might affect aging. Yeast is a long way from people in evolutionary terms, but both are eukaryotes, the order of higher celled organisms, and many fundamental pathways in human cells were worked out first in yeast.</p>
        <p>In 1991 two postdoctoral students, Brian Kennedy and Nick Austriaco, arrived in Dr. Guarente's laboratory and embraced his idea of looking for aging genes. It took them four whole years to find a strain of yeast that lived longer than others.</p>
        <p>The strain's longevity seemed connected with a group of genes whose role was to shut down other genes. Called the sir2, sir3 and sir4 genes (sir standing for silent information regulator), their protein products formed a complex that usually sat on the tips of the yeast cell's chromosomes and repressed the activity of certain genes there. But in the longer lived yeast, the sir complex left its usual position and migrated to the cell's nucleus, to a subcompartment called the nucleolus where the ribosomes, the cell's protein-making factories, are assembled.</p>
        <p>By 1997 Dr. Guarente's group had established a principal mechanism of aging in yeast: the nucleolus sooner or later gets clogged up with waste circles of ribosomal material until it can no longer produce ribosomes and the yeast cell dies. The arrival of the sir complex in the longer-lived yeast strain repressed the genes from which the circles were generated and delayed aging.</p>
        <p>That might explain longevity in yeast, but what about people? At this point an intriguing but diversionary hint turned up in the form of the discovery of the human gene for a striking hereditary disease known as Werner's syndrome.</p>
        <p>Werner's patients generally die in their teens with symptoms of old age such as gray hair, wrinkled skin and cataracts. All these defects are caused by the malfunction of a single gene, a house-keeping gene known as a helicase because it helps the cell unwind the double helix of DNA.</p>
        <p>Yeast cells possess a helicase-making gene with a similar structure to the human gene. Dr. Guarente and his colleagues showed that when the yeast helicase gene is disrupted, the yeast cells become more sensitive to the waste circles and age prematurely.</p>
        <p>But just as everything seemed to be hanging together for establishing a universal mechanism of aging, two of the elements fell apart. No waste circles could be seen building up in the nucleolus of animal cells. And the yeast counterpart to the Werner's syndrome gene does not seem to be central to aging because adding extra copies of it does not enhance life span.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, Dr. Guarente felt sure that the silencing of genes was a profound enough process that it was likely to tie in somehow with the equally profound process of aging, and that in higher organisms the failure of silencing might lead to some less visible damage than the waste circle build-up seen in yeast.  Probing the role of the sir genes he found that one of them, sir2, seemed more directly involved than the others in determining the yeast cell's life span. If he disrupted the sir2 gene, the yeast cells led short lives; if he inserted an extra copy of sir2, they lived longer.</p>
        <p>''Once we had developed the idea that sir2 was of primary importance, we wanted to know exactly what it does,'' Dr. Guarente said.</p>
        <p>Other scientists have shown that the chromatin, the material that clads and controls the DNA, carries many small chemical groups known as acetyl groups when the genes are active, but that when the acetyl groups are shaved away, the chromatin binds the DNA more tightly.  The underlying genes are then silenced because the cell's gene-copying machinery cannot access them.</p>
        <p>Many researchers had assumed that sir2 was likely to perform its gene-silencing role by stripping acetyl groups off the chromatin. But in test-tube experiments sir2 showed no sign of doing that.</p>
        <p>Another scientist had noticed that sir2 can sometimes add a certain chemical group to proteins. To see if it might be doing the same to chromatin, Dr. Guarente and a postdoctoral student, Shinichiro Imai, wondered if sir2 might be adding this chemical to chromatin, rather than removing acetyl groups. They mixed the yeast sir2 protein with the chromatin material and with a chemical called NAD, which would generate the chemical group to be added.  NAD, nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide, is a substance well known to biochemists because of its central role in the cell's energy production through the breakdown of glucose.</p>
        <p>The experiment did not go according to plan. The chromatin material, far from having chemical groups added to it, emerged lighter than before, and the difference in weight corresponded exactly to acetyl groups being removed.</p>
        <p>Dr. Guarente and Dr. Imai had discovered, by lucky accident, that sir2 does indeed remove acetyl groups from chromatin, but only in the presence of NAD. This role had escaped detection previously because there was no reason to assume that sir2 required NAD as a cofactor.</p>
        <p>This finding, made last year, suggested to Dr. Guarente there might be a deep link between energy metabolism and gene silencing, the link being made through sir2. When food is plentiful, most of the cell's NAD is locked up in metabolizing glucose; the sir2 protein is in passive mode, because it has little NAD to work with, and the cell or organism, with its genes fully active, burns the candle of life at both ends. But when glucose supplies are low, NAD is plentiful, and the sir2 protein can silence genes up and down the chromosome, seeing that all genes the cell does not need remain switched off. Such a mechanism would have a distinct evolutionary advantage: it would enable the organism to postpone reproduction when food was scarce, living longer to reproduce when conditions later improved. Animals on a calorically restricted diet are usually healthy in every respect save that their fertility is reduced.</p>
        <p>The sir2-NAD interaction at the cellular level would explain in large part how a calorically restricted diet prolongs life span. In yeast, an active sir2 would silence the genes that generate the waste circles; in animals, it would maintain the integrity of the cell. As gene silencing becomes looser with age, Dr. Guarente supposes, many genes that should stay turned off in a cell become active, degrading cellular function throughout the body.</p>
        <p>To test these ideas, Dr. Guarente turned again to yeast. Last week he and two postdoctoral students, Su-Ju Lin and Pierre-Antoine Defossez, reported that yeast cells kept on a low glucose, low calorie diet indeed live longer than normal, just as do rats and mice. This effect did not occur either in yeast strains whose sir2 gene had been disrupted, or in those whose principal gene for making NAD had been destroyed, establishing that both genes are necessary to mediate the effect between diet and longevity.</p>
        <p>Dr. Guarente is now looking to see if the same is true in the laboratory roundworm and in mice. ''If this is general I think it is profoundly significant,'' he says. The reason is that by developing drugs that mimic the effect of NAD on sir2, people in principle might at one stroke gain the health and longevity benefits of a calorically restricted diet, which in practice very few people could adhere to.</p>
        <p>Evolutionary biologists believe, on largely theoretical grounds, that many genes govern aging and that there can be no single mechanism of aging, whether the one Dr. Guarente suggests or any other. ''Even though I think Guarente's whole set of prejudices is wrong, I think it is relatively harmless for him to bash away at it,'' is the faint praise he gets from one evolutionary biologist, Dr. Michael Rose of the University of California at Irvine.</p>
        <p>Dr. Guarente respects evolutionary theory but believes that questions about aging can now be settled by experiment. His particular ideas about aging are too new to have become gospel, but many of his molecular biology colleagues have confidence in what he is doing. ''He thinks very clearly and sees to the heart of a problem,'' said Dr. Cynthia Kenyon, who studies aging in roundworms at the University of California, San Francisco. Dr. Ptashne, his post-doctoral adviser who now works at the Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center, praises his ability to join formal analysis with imaginative approaches.</p>
        <p>There are doubtless many more failures to savor before piercing all the veils of the aging process. But Dr. Guarente has seized one end of a highly interesting thread and is tugging with gusto to see where it may lead. ''Although it seems unlikely that any drastic extension in life span is imminent,'' he wrote in a recent article, ''a therapeutic that compresses the period of morbidity may be more than a flight of fancy.''</p>
        <p>SCIENTIST AT WORK: LEONARD GUARENTE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
