<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Giants See Error of Their Ways, but Take It Lightly</title>
    <meta content="26GIAN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/26/sports/26GIAN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233839"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Washington Redskins</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Giants</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hermoso, Rafael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Washington Redskins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000926T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE3D7153AF935A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="971" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Giants See Error of Their Ways, but Take It Lightly</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RAFAEL HERMOSO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hermoso, Rafael</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., Sept. 25</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Giants discuss loss to Washington Redskins; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The mistakes had seemed minor in the past, hidden behind winning scores and masked by inferior opponents. The Giants realized they had eluded perfection each week and yet they entered their game Sunday night against the Washington Redskins undefeated.</p>
        <p>But after being thoroughly outplayed by the Redskins in nearly every aspect of the game, the Giants today attempted to explain their 16-6 defeat as nothing more than a missed opportunity.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The mistakes had seemed minor in the past, hidden behind winning scores and masked by inferior opponents. The Giants realized they had eluded perfection each week and yet they entered their game Sunday night against the Washington Redskins undefeated.</p>
        <p>But after being thoroughly outplayed by the Redskins in nearly every aspect of the game, the Giants today attempted to explain their 16-6 defeat as nothing more than a missed opportunity.</p>
        <p>Linebacker Jessie Armstead said that only two or three misplays had led to the defeat. Coach Jim Fassel lamented that a missed fumble recovery on the opening kickoff of the second half. If the Giants had recovered and scored, who knows what would have happened, Fassel said.</p>
        <p>Yet, beyond the rationalizations lie some disturbing problems for the Giants to address this week as they prepared for an arguably even tougher opponent. The game against the Titans at Tennessee on Sunday will match the Giants against the reigning American Football Conference champions.</p>
        <p>By then, perhaps the Giants will discover what happened to their once efficient offense, which was held to one late touchdown.</p>
        <p>The Giants' defense fell victim to an aerial show by Redskins quarterback Brad Johnson, who passed for 289 yards and two touchdowns. He repeatedly threw over the Giants' secondary.</p>
        <p>''It's not a situation where there's no hope,'' Armstead said.</p>
        <p>Most Giants today thought Sunday's mistakes were correctable, but several of them acknowledged that these same mistakes had been overlooked in a 14-7 victory over the Chicago Bears the previous week.</p>
        <p>''If we want to be a championship football team, these are the kind of games you've got to come out and you have to be flowing from play one,'' quarterback Kerry Collins said. ''I don't think we did that last night. I don't think it was a letdown or anything like that. I don't think we realized the level we had to play at.''</p>
        <p>The Giants' offense, so much more diverse and potent this season, still struggles to score deep in an opponent's territory even after sustained drives.</p>
        <p>The offense failed repeatedly to move the ball on first down Sunday, putting the Giants into long-yardage situations. After the first quarter, the Giants did not cross midfield until late in the third quarter, and that drive stalled at the 50-yard line.</p>
        <p>So how was the National Football Conference's second-ranked offense held to fewer than 300 yards (261) for the first time this season?</p>
        <p>The Giants had built a 3-0 record by taking early leads and letting the running backs Tiki Barber and Ron Dayne run down the clock, keeping the defense fresh. For the first time Sunday, an opponent held the ball longer than the Giants.</p>
        <p>The offense went three and out on the game's opening possession to set an ominous tone.</p>
        <p>''We've got to be able to make some big plays,'' Coach Jim Fassel said today. ''We made them with the run game. The better teams you play, the harder those plays are to make. They have to come in the form of the passing game.''</p>
        <p>The Giants' effort to bolster the running game worked for the first three weeks, but they had not trailed in a game before Sunday, and Collins had predicted that that would be a major test.</p>
        <p>Collins was hard on himself after the game, taking the blame for all of the offense's woes. He overthrew and underthrew receivers and missed open teammates. He did not complete a pass longer than 20 yards and Fassel called that a result of the Redskins' top cornerbacks, Deion Sanders and Champ Bailey, and the quickly deteriorating pocket around Collins.</p>
        <p>He was sacked four times, after the offensive line had allowed only three sacks in the previous three games, and was constantly under pressure.</p>
        <p>The team's offensive coordinator, Sean Payton, tried some of the Giants' new plays, calling for a flea flicker in the second quarter. But that resulted in a Collins sack for a 13-yard loss.</p>
        <p>''I thought we were beyond that as a team, making mental mistakes, the penalties and things like that that held us back,'' guard Glenn Parker said. ''We're a young team in a lot of ways, but we've never been in a situation where we've been behind and had to play catch-up or were under pressure. I'm sure that adds up to it. Guys want to make the big play and end up doing something they shouldn't.''</p>
        <p>Free safety Shaun Williams took the heat for the battered secondary and said he had played his worst game at any level of football. Williams's major misplay led to a 53-yard pass play for the Redskins and set up the touchdown that gave the Redskins a 16-0 lead two minutes into the second half.</p>
        <p>When Johnson found receiver Albert Connell on the left sideline, Williams thought Connell was behind him and jumped. But Williams fell out of bounds as Connell made a leaping catch. Connell then fell and got up to dash another 15 yards.</p>
        <p>''We should be waiting there for the interception,'' Fassel said. ''That's a slam dunk, no question in my mind.''</p>
        <p>Fassel did not think there was a lack of talent in the Giants' secondary, but cornerback Dave Thomas had a rough preseason, and Sunday was the first time an opponent had continually threw his way with success.</p>
        <p>Johnson had not completed a pass longer than 22 yards to a wide receiver in the Redskins' first three games. Sunday against the Giants, he had five.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
