<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Crumbling of the Milosevic Fortress</title>
    <meta content="26JUDA$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/26/opinion/26JUDA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233820"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Serbia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Milosevic, Slobodan (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kostunica, Vojislav</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Judah, Tim</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000926T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506EED9153AF935A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="804" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Crumbling of the Milosevic Fortress</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Tim Judah</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Judah, Tim</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Tim Judah Op-Ed article on victory by opposition in Serbia's presidential election; says Pres Slobodan Milosevic has suffered severe blow and that it may be difficult for him to recapture 'genie of democracy' that he has released (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As Yugoslavia voted on Sunday, one friend's e-mail message from Belgrade summed it all up: ''We're all in election fever, hope and horror at the same time. Wish us luck!'' No amount of analysis and informed guesswork could have caught the mood better.</p>
        <p>At dawn yesterday, less than 12 hours after the polls had closed, Zarko Korac, my friend and the leader of one of Serbia's opposition parties, sent this: ''It is a cold and cloudy morning in Belgrade, but I see some strange light. Whatever happened, Serbia changed.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As Yugoslavia voted on Sunday, one friend's e-mail message from Belgrade summed it all up: ''We're all in election fever, hope and horror at the same time. Wish us luck!'' No amount of analysis and informed guesswork could have caught the mood better.</p>
        <p>At dawn yesterday, less than 12 hours after the polls had closed, Zarko Korac, my friend and the leader of one of Serbia's opposition parties, sent this: ''It is a cold and cloudy morning in Belgrade, but I see some strange light. Whatever happened, Serbia changed.''</p>
        <p>Of course, it's not over yet. As I write, both the opposition and the forces of Slobodan Milosevic, the Yugoslav president, are claiming victory, though no official results have been announced. But whatever happens next, Serbia is highly unlikely ever to be the same. Mr. Milosevic has suffered a tremendous blow. He may not be out, but he is certainly down.</p>
        <p>This was clear already on Sunday night, when the riot police deployed in the center of Belgrade to head off potential clashes between supporters and opponents of Mr. Milosevic ended up chatting with the people who were chanting: ''Slobo, kill yourself! Save Serbia!'' Only a couple of hundred Milosevic supporters showed up, and, dejected, they went home.</p>
        <p>With the opposition saying it has won a landslide in both presidential and local elections, it would seem very hard now for Mr. Milosevic to recapture the genie of democracy that he unwittingly released. Of course his own camp is also declaring victory, but in a muted sort of way. And that is important. With credibility oozing away, the bonds of loyalty loosen.</p>
        <p>It is not too late, of course, for Mr. Milosevic to clamp down and send Serbia squarely back on the road to becoming Europe's own pocket Cuba. But with every hour that passes, it becomes more difficult.</p>
        <p>How did Slobodan Milosevic, the arch-tactician who, until now, had gambled and lost everything except his own hold on power, make such a fatal mistake? He set the terms of the election. He said: ''It's me or NATO!'' But the opposition finally managed to unite, and it shrewdly chose a candidate, Vojislav Kostunica, who could not be tarred as a tool of NATO. (There is no film of him kissing Madeleine Albright's hand.) This turned the tables. The question became: Mr. Milosevic or someone else? And more people than ever before have chosen someone else.</p>
        <p>In part this is thanks to the students from the Otpor (Resistance) movement who trudged the highways and byways of Serbia, quietly mobilizing people against their president. Many political commentators in the West  dismissed this sort of challenge to Mr. Milosevic, saying dictators are not removed through the ballot box. But that is to misunderstand the nature of Mr. Milosevic and to fall prey to our own Western rhetoric of Serbian tyranny and dictatorship. For Serbs, Mr. Milosevic is an authoritarian ruler, but not a tyrant</p>
        <p>Shooting Albanians or Muslims may be one thing, but Mr. Milosevic has not been shooting young Serbs, at least as of yesterday. Thousands have been detained, beaten and intimidated. Newspapers have been shut down, and one brave journalist, Miroslav Filipovic, is in prison. But there is no Serbian gulag, and there are no mass graves of young Serbs who have raised their voices against Mr. Milosevic. Whatever he does now, and unless he does start shooting people, it is equally unlikely that Otpor and the opposition will give up the struggle until he is gone.</p>
        <p>So, what if Mr. Milosevic is indeed on the way out?</p>
        <p>First, the issue of independence for Montenegro would fade away, since most Montenegrins are not anti-Yugoslav as much as anti-Milosevic. The question of Kosovo would not, but with Mr. Kostunica at its head, a new Serbia would argue with words, not bullets, that Kosovo belonged to Serbia. That would be bad news for Kosovo's Albanians, who want independence and for whom Mr. Milosevic, an indicted war criminal with whom no one could be expected to talk, has therefore been an asset.</p>
        <p>And for Serbia itself, for the heartland? It is now a disaster zone economically and socially, not helped by 78 days of NATO bombing, of course, but a catastrophe primarily of Mr. Milosevic's making. The last 10 years of war, sanctions and isolation have knocked Serbia back to an extraordinary degree. Huge problems remain to be solved, both among the Serbs and between Serbs and their neighbors. But it seems clear that there is reason for hope and that Zarko Korac is right: Something has changed.</p>
        <p>Tim Judah is the author of ''The Serbs: History, Myth and the Destruction of Yugoslavia.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Tim Judah is the author of ''The Serbs: History, Myth and the Destruction of Yugoslavia.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
