<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Public Interests; A Hot-Button Issue</title>
    <meta content="26COLL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/26/opinion/26COLL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233811"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Collins, Gail</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/Gail Collins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000926T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E1DA153AF935A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="777" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Public Interests; A Hot-Button Issue</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GAIL COLLINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Collins, Gail</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gail Collins Op-Ed column on disappearance of defense policy as issue in presidential campaign (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The presidential campaign has stopped talking about nuclear defense because married women, the critical swing voters, aren't supposed to be interested. (Our motto: If it hasn't come up on Regis it can't be all that important.)</p>
        <p>Look, we're not going to be satisfied with six weeks of prescription drug coverage and dragging Dick Cheney to kindergarten show-and-tell sessions. We are thinking people. We ponder the big stuff. We do not quail at the mention of the word ''pixels.'' (As in ''How many pixels does it take to make an exoatmospheric kill vehicle?'')</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The presidential campaign has stopped talking about nuclear defense because married women, the critical swing voters, aren't supposed to be interested. (Our motto: If it hasn't come up on Regis it can't be all that important.)</p>
        <p>Look, we're not going to be satisfied with six weeks of prescription drug coverage and dragging Dick Cheney to kindergarten show-and-tell sessions. We are thinking people. We ponder the big stuff. We do not quail at the mention of the word ''pixels.'' (As in ''How many pixels does it take to make an exoatmospheric kill vehicle?'')</p>
        <p>You're ready to talk weaponry, and you probably already know more than you think. Check your nuclear I.Q.:</p>
        <p>1. In its last three tests, the hardware for the Clinton administration's proposed $60 billion antimissile defense program has hit:</p>
        <p>A) Three targets.</p>
        <p>B) Two targets.</p>
        <p>C) One target that was flying in front of a large bright balloon.</p>
        <p>2. Explaining the latest $100 million failure, the head of the Pentagon Ballistic Missile Defense Organization said:</p>
        <p>A) ''We're closing the pixel gap.''</p>
        <p>B) ''It all depends on what you mean by the word 'hit.'</p>
        <p>C) ''This is rocket science.''</p>
        <p>3. The missile shield is supposed to protect the United States against weapons launched by ''rogue nations'' like North Korea. The Clinton administration has abolished the term ''rogue nation'' in favor of:</p>
        <p>A) ''Diplomatically challenged nation.''</p>
        <p>B) ''The nation formerly known as rogue.''</p>
        <p>C) ''State of concern.''</p>
        <p>If you guessed C on every question, you are very well versed in nuclear weapons issues, and qualified to head the Senate Armed Services Committee. (The current chairman, John Warner of Virginia, recently demanded of an expert witness: ''Look straight into the cameras and say, 'We are, as a nation, defenseless.' '')</p>
        <p>You are also way ahead of your fellow citizens, who believe we already have a system that will shoot down any incoming missiles. When told that no such item exists, a quarter of the respondents in one poll said we should build one even if it isn't actually going to work.</p>
        <p>Those of us in the Bush-Gore generation were not raised to put much faith in the defensive side of military technology. As youngsters, we were told that we could ward off a nuclear attack by hiding under our desks with our heads down. We spent the gulf war watching those Patriot missiles on CNN, weapons apparently so precise they could trail an Iraqi Scud down the street and into a saloon, and blast it right off the bar stool. It was only much later that we learned the Patriots may not have ever hit anything, and that the secret to our defense against the Scuds was that the Scuds were lousy weapons.</p>
        <p>George W. Bush and Al Gore both support an antimissile program, although Mr. Gore's heart doesn't seem to be entirely in it. The vice president is cautious -- what about the downside? If we put up a shield, the Chinese could respond by simply adding more missiles. We could raise the odds of an attack, and then the shield might not work when it happens. (Unless we get lucky and the North Koreans decide to assail us with large balloons.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush, characteristically, goes for something more daring. (When the last interceptor flunked its test due to a computer glitch, Mr. Bush suggested that the problem was a lack of ''the right leadership.'') His shield proposal is frequently referred to as ''robust'' -- the French roast of ballistic missile defense. Further details, such as what it would look like and how much it will cost, will become available after the inauguration. ''He is an excellent decision maker, but you don't have time on the campaign trail, nor really the resources on the campaign trail, to make a decision of this magnitude,'' his foreign policy adviser, Condoleezza Rice, told The Washington Post last week.</p>
        <p>If the recollections of their old friends are right, Mr. Bush and Mr. Gore were two early baby boomers who didn't spend their youth practicing what to do if the Soviet Union decided to bomb their classrooms. ''Down here we had tornado drills,'' said John Bizilo, who was principal of Mr. Bush's elementary school in Midland, Tex. No wonder Mr. Bush is a diplomatic risk-taker. He was raised to fear Mother Nature more than Mother Russia.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
