<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>2 Korea Defense Chiefs Agree On Small Steps at Initial Talks</title>
    <meta content="Y26KOR$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/26/world/26KORE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233915"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Railroads</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Boundaries and Territorial Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">North Korea-International Relations-South Korea</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">North Korea</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">French, Howard W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/North Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/North Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Railroads</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000926T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E6DB123AF935A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="768" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>2 Korea Defense Chiefs Agree On Small Steps at Initial Talks</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOWARD W. FRENCH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">French, Howard W</byline>
      <dateline>CHEJU, South Korea, Tuesday, Sept. 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Defense ministers from North and South Korea meet in Cheju, South Korea, to discuss lowering of tensions across most heavily armed border in world; agree to open demilitarized zone so workers can begin reconstructing several railroad links; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the most important meeting between North and South Korea since their leaders met in June, the defense ministers from both countries traveled here on Monday to discuss lowering tensions across their border, the most heavily armed in the world.</p>
        <p>At the conclusion of the talks today, South Korean military officials said the two sides had agreed to opening the demilitarizied zone along the border so that workers could begin the reconstruction of severed railroad links. The details of which areas of the heavily armed zone would be opened are to be negotiated at a lower level next month.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the most important meeting between North and South Korea since their leaders met in June, the defense ministers from both countries traveled here on Monday to discuss lowering tensions across their border, the most heavily armed in the world.</p>
        <p>At the conclusion of the talks today, South Korean military officials said the two sides had agreed to opening the demilitarizied zone along the border so that workers could begin the reconstruction of severed railroad links. The details of which areas of the heavily armed zone would be opened are to be negotiated at a lower level next month.</p>
        <p>The meeting was in what for the visiting 13-member North Korean delegation must have been almost surreal opulence, a luxurious seaside resort on the southernmost island of South Korea.</p>
        <p>Perhaps appropriately for nations that only recently began to discuss political and military issues after more than a half-century of animosity, the meeting site, with its beaches and volcanic peaks, is best known as a honeymooners' destination.</p>
        <p>But just how difficult progress on the security issues that separate the two sides could be was underscored even before the talks began on Monday morning by the lack of a working agenda for the two-day meeting.</p>
        <p>The sessions began with smiles after a lengthy handshake for the cameras between the South Korean defense minister, Cho Seong Tae, a retired general, and Kim Il Chol, minister of the People's Army of North Korea.</p>
        <p>Despite a huge range of potential items for discussion, the delegations remained behind closed doors for less than an hour and a half before going on a sightseeing tour of mountain fortifications on Cheju built centuries ago against Mongol attacks.</p>
        <p>An official of the South Korean Unification Ministry said the Monday talks had been positive and relaxed. Although he declined to elaborate, he said the discussions had allowed each side to ''better understand the other side's position.''</p>
        <p>General Kim and Mr. Cho were each in charge of their countries' forces the last time the countries exchanged fire, in June 1999, in a naval skirmish in a disputed border area in seas west of the Korean Peninsula. The fighting sank at least one North Korean patrol vessel.</p>
        <p>Before the talks began, it was widely reported here that North Korea had sought to keep the discussion between the two military forces narrowly focused on demining and other security problems related to reopening rail service between the countries, which the heads of state agreed on in June. Train travel between the Koreas ended just before the start of the Korean War in 1950.</p>
        <p>South Korea has reportedly been pushing for a much broader discussion of security problems. Among the confidence-building measures that it sought to propose for early adoption were a hot line between the two armies, prior notification of major troop movements and observation of military exercises by each side.</p>
        <p>Seoul has also proposed a second round of talks by the defense ministers, in the North in November, and seeks to make the meetings a regular feature of the improving relations between the countries. After the Monday meeting ended, the semiofficial Yonhap News Agency agency said the two sides had agreed to hold the round in Pyongyang, the North Korean capital, in November.</p>
        <p>In the background here, not on any public agenda but unmistakably in the air, are increasingly bitter charges by the South Korean opposition that the government is rushing through financial assistance, food aid and diplomatic support for the Communist North with little to show for the effort beyond the symbolic.</p>
        <p>As the military delegations met on Monday, two other delegations met in Seoul to discuss investment in the North, whose economy has been devastated by the disappearance of its former Soviet-bloc allies and by a cycle of drought and flooding.</p>
        <p>Today, North Korea said it would require 1.4 million tons of grain from international donors to feed its population of 22 million and to avoid a return of the famines that are believed to have killed as many as two million people in recent years.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
