<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>METRO BRIEFING</title>
    <meta content="26MBRF" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217768"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000726T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E4DB113AF935A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1034" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>METRO BRIEFING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by Anthony Ramirez</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NEW YORK</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: HOSPITAL LOSES SUIT -- Mount Sinai Medical Center was ordered by a jury to pay $32.2 million to a Westchester couple, Elena and Jonathan Greenhill, who claimed that members of the hospital's staff mishandled the delivery of their son, causing brain damage and cerebral palsy. The child, Alexander, now 6, is in special education classes. Joan Lebow, a spokeswoman for the hospital, said yesterday that Mount Sinai lawyers expected the verdict to be sharply reduced at an Aug. 1 hearing.</p>
        <p>(NYT)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: CITY BUSINESS CHIEF NAMED -- Deborah R. Weeks, who has been acting commissioner of the New York City Department of Business Services since 1998, was appointed commissioner yesterday by Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani. Ms. Weeks, a lawyer, replaces Rudy Washington, who was appointed deputy mayor for business services and community development. Ms. Weeks is in charge of city assistance to small companies, business improvement districts and economic development zones.</p>
        <p>Thomas J. Lueck (NYT)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NEW YORK</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: HOSPITAL LOSES SUIT -- Mount Sinai Medical Center was ordered by a jury to pay $32.2 million to a Westchester couple, Elena and Jonathan Greenhill, who claimed that members of the hospital's staff mishandled the delivery of their son, causing brain damage and cerebral palsy. The child, Alexander, now 6, is in special education classes. Joan Lebow, a spokeswoman for the hospital, said yesterday that Mount Sinai lawyers expected the verdict to be sharply reduced at an Aug. 1 hearing.</p>
        <p>(NYT)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: CITY BUSINESS CHIEF NAMED -- Deborah R. Weeks, who has been acting commissioner of the New York City Department of Business Services since 1998, was appointed commissioner yesterday by Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani. Ms. Weeks, a lawyer, replaces Rudy Washington, who was appointed deputy mayor for business services and community development. Ms. Weeks is in charge of city assistance to small companies, business improvement districts and economic development zones.</p>
        <p>Thomas J. Lueck (NYT)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: RAT COMPLAINTS ONLINE -- The New York City Department of Health has established a Web page for complaints about rats. Complaints can also be made by telephone, letter or in person. Web complaints will be investigated ''as soon as possible,'' said John Gadd, a spokesman for the Department of Health. The address is www.ci.nyc.ny.us/html/doh/html/pest/pestrat.html.</p>
        <p>Stacy Albin (NYT)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: WORKER INJURED -- A man working as a contractor for Consolidated Edison was in critical condition at Bellevue Hospital yesterday after his leg was severed when a woman leaving a Manhattan parking garage lost control of her car and pinned him against his truck, police officials said. The man, James Lynch, 40, works for Felix Industries. Officer Jeffrey Stella ran to the scene and used his belt as a tourniquet to try to stop the bleeding.</p>
        <p>Elissa Gootman (NYT)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: PROSECUTION CLOSES MURDER TRIAL -- In a packed courtroom yesterday, an assistant district attorney, Ann Prunty, presented the prosecution's closing arguments in the trial of Edmund Ko, who is accused of murdering a former girlfriend, Hyseung Linda Hong, a Columbia University law student, in 1998. Ms. Prunty reviewed evidence step by step that she said pointed to a single killer who knew his victim and her apartment well. The jury is expected to begin its deliberations today after receiving instructions from Judge Harold Beeler.</p>
        <p>Katherine E. Finkelstein (NYT)</p>
        <p>BROOKLYN: A POLITICAL REMATCH -- Barry Ford, a lawyer who ran against United States Representative Edolphus Towns in 1998, will run against him for the seat from the 10th Congressional District. Mr. Ford, who ran against Mr. Towns in a three-way race in the 1998 primary and got 36 percent of the vote, announced his candidacy yesterday.</p>
        <p>Jonathan P. Hicks (NYT)</p>
        <p>WATERLOO: WOMEN'S RIGHTS HOUSE -- Hunt House, where the first women's rights convention was planned in 1848, can become part of the Women's Rights National Historical Park, under legislation that passed in the House of Representatives yesterday. The bill, which has been passed by the Senate, allows the National Park Service to acquire the house. It was at a tea given by Richard and Jane Hunt in July 1848 that Elizabeth Cady Stanton and other early women's rights advocates hatched the idea of holding a women's rights convention.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>CONNECTICUT</p>
        <p>TRUMBULL: SCHOOL COACH ARRESTED -- A 37-year-old baseball and wrestling coach at Trumbull High School, Glen A. Liscinsky, surrendered to the police last Thursday and was charged with assault for choking a man during a board meeting of the town's Pop Warner football program, the police said. Witnesses said the incident stemmed from a disagreement over the selection of a new football coach. Meanwhile, three former Trumbull High wrestlers received two years' probation on Monday and were ordered to perform 300 hours of community service for aiding in a teammate's violent hazing, which included hogtying and sodomizing him.</p>
        <p>David M. Herszenhorn (NYT)</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY</p>
        <p>NEW BRUNSWICK: TURNPIKE BONUSES -- The New Jersey Turnpike Authority is paying a $50 bonus to all 260 temporary toll collectors if they show up to work for two consecutive weeks. The authority has found that it is cheaper to pay a bonus to a part-timer making $9 an hour than to pay $21 overtime to a full-timer. The part-timers will be phased out with the introduction of E-ZPass electronic payment at 160 booths, scheduled for Sept. 30.</p>
        <p>John G. Holl (NYT)</p>
        <p>RIVER VALE: LIBEL SUIT DROPPED -- The Board of Education said it would withdraw its libel suit against Stanley Morrow, a parent of two elementary school students. He had criticized the board's handling of several personnel matters in a letter to a local newspaper. Mr. Morrow's supporters, including the American Civil Liberties Union, said the suit should never have been filed because the First Amendment protected criticism of government agencies.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>TRENTON: NEW MONEY FOR THE ARTS -- Gov. Christine Todd Whitman signed a Cultural Trust bill yesterday that created a $100 million fund for the arts. The bill enables groups to create endowments, pay off debt and repair or build facilities. The state will provide the money over 10 years, to be matched by private contributions for a fund that could total $200 million. The Dodge Foundation immediately donated $1 million.</p>
        <p>Natania Blumenkehl (NYT)</p>
        <p>NEWARK: HAIR COMPANY FINED -- A Camden County company has agreed to pay nearly $300,000 to settle state charges that it used false information to market a ''permanent'' hair replacement system (which cost from $2,000 to $8,000) that involved gluing a toupee to a person's scalp. United Micro Systems of Voorhees admitted no wrongdoing but agreed to change its sales and advertising practices, the state Division of Consumer Affairs announced yesterday.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
