<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>FOOD CHAIN</title>
    <meta content="26CHAI$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217737"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000726T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03EFD6103AF935A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="886" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>FOOD CHAIN</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MELISSA CLARK</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hard-Cooking Made Easy</p>
        <p>Q.  What is the best way to hard-boil and peel eggs?</p>
        <p>A.  Some restaurants and caterers use this method: Place as many eggs as needed in a single layer in a saucepan, and cover them with an inch of water. Bring the water just to a boil, turn off the heat and cover the pan. Let the eggs sit for 10 minutes in the hot water, then use a slotted spoon to transfer them to a bowl of ice water to cool.</p>
        <p>The cooked eggs can be stored in the shell up to three weeks, or peeled immediately. To peel them cleanly, tap the eggs gently all around on a hard surface, then roll lightly under your hand until the shells crush into a network of tiny pieces. The egg's broader end contains an air cell that provides an easy entry point, allowing you to get in between the thin membrane, which adheres to the shell, and the surface of the egg. Once the shell has been cracked all over it will pull away flexibly in big pieces, leaving an unscarred egg.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Hard-Cooking Made Easy</p>
        <p>Q.  What is the best way to hard-boil and peel eggs?</p>
        <p>A.  Some restaurants and caterers use this method: Place as many eggs as needed in a single layer in a saucepan, and cover them with an inch of water. Bring the water just to a boil, turn off the heat and cover the pan. Let the eggs sit for 10 minutes in the hot water, then use a slotted spoon to transfer them to a bowl of ice water to cool.</p>
        <p>The cooked eggs can be stored in the shell up to three weeks, or peeled immediately. To peel them cleanly, tap the eggs gently all around on a hard surface, then roll lightly under your hand until the shells crush into a network of tiny pieces. The egg's broader end contains an air cell that provides an easy entry point, allowing you to get in between the thin membrane, which adheres to the shell, and the surface of the egg. Once the shell has been cracked all over it will pull away flexibly in big pieces, leaving an unscarred egg.</p>
        <p>Early to Salt</p>
        <p>Q.  Why is it necessary to add salt to the water when cooking pasta? And when in the cooking process should you add it?</p>
        <p>A.  Salt adds to and brings out the flavor of pasta, and does it more evenly when added to the cooking water. As the pasta boils in the salted water, the salt penetrates the noodles, giving them a fuller taste. If you cook the pasta in plain water and then sprinkle on the salt, the grains remain on the surface, yielding a pasta that's potentially bland in the center yet salty on the exterior.</p>
        <p>While even a pinch of salt added to the cooking water makes a difference, most cooks use two tablespoons for a large pot (six quarts) of water. You can add the salt either when you fill the pot with water or after the water has come to a boil; it won't matter in terms of taste. Since bringing salted water to a boil takes slightly longer than plain water, however, you might as well add the salt along with the pasta, giving the pot a stir after putting them in.</p>
        <p>Dry the Greens</p>
        <p>Q.  What's the best way to store greens? Should they be wet or dry, washed or unwashed?</p>
        <p>A.  Store greens when they are clean and moist, but not wet. A good method is to soak the greens in a sink of cold water (or several changes of water if necessary), spin them dry and wrap in a plastic bag before refrigerating. The soaking hydrates and plumps the leaves, making them crisp; spinning removes surface moisture that can lead to mildew.</p>
        <p>Perforated vegetable bags are ideal for storage. They protect the leaves from most of the oxygen that causes evaporation and results in wilting, yet allow some air flow, which discourages mildew. Sealable bags, squeezed of air, are also fine, as long as the leaves have been well dried. I wrap them in paper towels before placing them in the bags.</p>
        <p>The greens may keep for as long as two weeks, if they are fresh to begin with. For short-term storage (up to a day), wash and dry your greens, then wrap them in moist paper towels or a moist clean dish towel and refrigerate until you are ready to serve them.</p>
        <p>There's Nothing Like a Truffle</p>
        <p>Q.  Are there any tasty substitutes for truffles or truffle oil?</p>
        <p>A.  No. There is nothing like the taste of a truffle, and nothing as delicate as its essence. But there are less expensive mushrooms and flavored oils that you might consider using, though the dish will be different.</p>
        <p>In recipes in which the truffles are cooked, try using meaty mushrooms like portobellos, morels or shiitakes. If the truffles are simply shaved raw on top of a dish like pasta or risotto, you'll have no choice but to leave them out, or substitute another delicacy like shavings of good Parmigiano-Reggiano.</p>
        <p>To substitute other oils for truffle oil, consider the dish you are making, and try to match the flavors with the oils. Nut oils, like hazelnut, walnut and pistachio, are excellent on salads and on uncooked vegetables. Herb-infused oils can be drizzled on cheese dishes, like a pizza, and are terrific with starchy foods like risotto and polenta. Experimentation is key for this inexact substitution.</p>
        <p>While truffles are expensive and hard to find, truffle oils are not. Most specialty shops carry them, as do large supermarkets; the price can vary from $17 for a three-ounce bottle to $5.95 for an eight ounces.</p>
        <p>MELISSA CLARK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
