<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New U.S. Guards Promised Against Steel Import Surges</title>
    <meta content="Y26STEE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217780"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Steel and Iron</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dumping (Trade Term)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Organized Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Commerce Department</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Steelworkers of America</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kahn, Joseph</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Steel and Iron</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Organized Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000726T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE0DA113AF935A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="718" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New U.S. Guards Promised Against Steel Import Surges</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSEPH KAHN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kahn, Joseph</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 25</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Commerce Department report indicates that Clinton administration plans to take aggressive new steps to protect domestic steel production from import surges, speeding up its use of anti-dumping measures and providing faster relief for companies and workers; release of report seems timed to help Vice Pres Al Gore shore up political support from steel workers and unions (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Clinton administration plans to take aggressive new steps to protect domestic steel producers from import surges, speeding up its use of antidumping measures and providing faster relief for companies and workers, according to a report the administration will release today.</p>
        <p>The 240-page report, a copy of which was made available by an administration official, seems timed to help Vice President Al Gore shore up political support from steel workers and unions. Some union leaders sharply criticized Mr. Gore's support for the China trade bill this year, and many have expressed disappointment that the administration has not done more to guard against sudden increases in low-price steel imports.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Clinton administration plans to take aggressive new steps to protect domestic steel producers from import surges, speeding up its use of antidumping measures and providing faster relief for companies and workers, according to a report the administration will release today.</p>
        <p>The 240-page report, a copy of which was made available by an administration official, seems timed to help Vice President Al Gore shore up political support from steel workers and unions. Some union leaders sharply criticized Mr. Gore's support for the China trade bill this year, and many have expressed disappointment that the administration has not done more to guard against sudden increases in low-price steel imports.</p>
        <p>The report, prepared by the Commerce Department, says the administration will start imposing duties on imported steel faster than it has in the past -- and in some cases even before reaching a final judgment on whether a foreign country is selling steel in this market below cost -- so as to minimize the damage to domestic companies and workers when dumping does occur.</p>
        <p>Administration officials said they had also requested funds to set up an interagency ''rapid response team'' that would distribute aid to hard-hit communities as soon as it became clear that a sudden rise in import volumes threatened profits and jobs.</p>
        <p>Many of the nation's leading trading partners, including Japan, South Korea, Russia and Brazil, have complained bitterly about United States antidumping laws, especially as used to shield the politically sensitive steel industry. The administration's pledge to use those laws more actively seems sure to inflame already tense trade ties with those nations, especially with Japan.</p>
        <p>Just last month, foreign steel producers released their own study that contended that the American restrictions on imported steel had cost consumers here as much as $150 billion over the last three decades. Trade barriers and government subsidies effectively raise the cost of everything with steel components, from aircraft to kitchen utensils, said that study, which was prepared by lawyers for foreign steel makers.</p>
        <p>The Commerce Department's study makes essentially the opposite claim. It suggests that if anything, the United States has erred on the side of free trade and needs to speed up and stiffen its response when the industry faces unfair competition from abroad.</p>
        <p>The United States imposed antidumping duties on hot rolled steel from Russia, Japan and Brazil in 1998. The administration decided at the time that the United States was flooded with below-cost steel after the Asian financial crisis that began in 1997 led to devalued currencies and bankrupt companies abroad. Some steel industry and union officials have complained that it took the administration too long to respond to that crisis.</p>
        <p>''This is designed to make sure that what happened to the industry two years ago doesn't happen again,'' a senior Commerce official said. ''We want to move as fast and as aggressively as we can, because we know that it takes time for the remedies to work.''</p>
        <p>In the future, the report says, the administration will act faster to break out and distribute trade data on steel. That will help people spot evidence of potential import surges. When surges occur, the administration will act faster to head them off, the report says. Among other actions, the report recommends starting negotiations with trading partners as soon as it becomes clear that an import surge is in the works.</p>
        <p>The report also says that the administration will work to address long-term ''structural factors'' that cause foreign countries to sell steel at prices the United States has determined are below the cost of production.</p>
        <p>Russia, the report says, has allowed steel exporters to escape paying bills at home, allowing them to sell goods abroad below cost. Japan allows steel makers to coordinate with one another and keep prices artificially high at home to help promote low-price exports. South Korea has unsound banking practices that have effectively subsidized a glut of steel production capacity.</p>
        <p>The administration will use its influence at the World Bank and other international lending agencies to end loans that expand steel production capacity, the study says. It will also propose that international economic bodies study how best to knock down informal barriers that protect and subsidize steel companies.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
