<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Long Long Trail Is Awinding, Right Across Canada</title>
    <meta content="Y26CAN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217754"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trans Canada Trail</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Walking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Volunteers</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Canada</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brooke, James</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Hiking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leisure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Walking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Volunteers</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000726T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE4DD113AF935A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="920" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Long Long Trail Is Awinding, Right Across Canada</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BROOKE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brooke, James</byline>
      <dateline>TUKTOYAKTUK, Northwest Territories</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Canada prepares to open Trans Canada Trail, new 10,000-mile network that will link Atlantic, Pacific and Arctic Oceans; building of trail, billed as world's longest recreational trail, has become exercise in nation building as thousands have volunteered for relay teams snaking way across nation with water from three oceans for Sept inauguration, near Ottawa; 250,000 Canadians have donated money for trail; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Here on North America's northern edge, a treeless peninsula offers a timeless scene: slabs of whale meat drying in the 24-hour summer sun, a chained husky barking at visitors, and a chill wind blowing off polar ice, only 10 miles offshore.</p>
        <p>But wedged between a Royal Canadian Mounted Police barracks and the wind-whipped waves of the Beaufort Sea, tourists now inspect a new sight: a tricolor sculpture marking this native village as the Arctic trail head for a new 10,000-mile trail network stretching from sea to sea to sea.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Here on North America's northern edge, a treeless peninsula offers a timeless scene: slabs of whale meat drying in the 24-hour summer sun, a chained husky barking at visitors, and a chill wind blowing off polar ice, only 10 miles offshore.</p>
        <p>But wedged between a Royal Canadian Mounted Police barracks and the wind-whipped waves of the Beaufort Sea, tourists now inspect a new sight: a tricolor sculpture marking this native village as the Arctic trail head for a new 10,000-mile trail network stretching from sea to sea to sea.</p>
        <p>Joining the Atlantic, Pacific and Arctic, the Trans Canada Trail is to be inaugurated in September when relay runners converge near Ottawa with flasks of water from Canada's three oceans. Billed as the world's longest recreational trail, it will be open to hiking, bicycling, horseback riding, cross-country skiing and, in some areas, in-line skating and snowmobiling.</p>
        <p>''Ecotourism is becoming a huge industry,'' said Rob McPhee, a Yellowknife resident who was part of a five-man team that undertook an 86-day trans-Arctic snowmobile trip from here to Iqaluit, capital of the new Nunavut Territory, which was carved out of the eastern half of the Northwest Territories in 1999. The team left here last February after ceremonies that included drilling through six feet of ice to draw sealskin bags filled with water from the Arctic Ocean.</p>
        <p>Crossing Canada's 10 provinces and three territories, the trail is doing more this summer than promoting tourism.</p>
        <p>In the late 19th century, Canadians rallied around the epic effort to push a railroad across their new nation. As the automobile age flourished after World War II, Canadians rallied around the construction of the Trans-Canada highway. Today, the construction of a cross-country recreational trail has become a 21st-century exercise in nation building. In a country where each province trades more with the United States than with the rest of Canada, the trail redirects the Canadians' gaze from south to east, to west, and even to north.</p>
        <p>''It encourages people from the south to go up and see what our country really is,'' said Carol Jones, an occupational health specialist  who divides her time between Ontario and Inuvik, a town 85 miles southwest of here that is Canada's northernmost spot reachable by car. ''During the summers, you used to see more people here from Europe than from Canada. All of a sudden you are seeing Ontario vehicles. I give a lot of credit to the publicity the media has done of the trail.''</p>
        <p>One visitor, Betty Veitch, a retired schoolteacher who drove from Ontario to Inuvik with two friends, said after flying here: ''We had our picture taken with the monument. It was quite exciting.''</p>
        <p>As the three relay teams snake their way this summer across Canada, the world's second largest country after Russia, excitement is building. So far, 5,000 volunteer water carriers have signed up for the relay, 250,000 Canadians have donated money for trail construction, and, in June, trail brochures were mailed to every household in the nation. Reflecting Canada's diversity, the water canisters have moved by dog sleds here in the Arctic, by Indian war canoes in the Pacific, and, to the sound of bagpipes, by a team of joggers from a lighthouse in the Atlantic.</p>
        <p>''We were in one town of 60 people, and they had 300 people there,'' said Sherman Olson, chairman of the Trans Canada Trail Foundation, the nonprofit group that is creating the trail. The inauguration ceremonies in Hull, Quebec, across the river from Ottawa, are set for Sept. 9 so schoolchildren across Canada can watch live television coverage.</p>
        <p>Intended to celebrate the millennium, the project, integrating existing trail networks and adding new ones, is expected to be only 75 percent complete this fall. The trail's biggest benefactor so far has been Canadian Pacific Railroad, which donated 1,000 miles of discontinued rail lines. Canadian National Railroad is expected to make a similar donation in coming days.</p>
        <p>''The whole thing will probably take another five years to complete,'' Mr. Olson said from his home near Vancouver. ''Then you will be able to walk from Victoria, British Columbia, to St. John's, Newfoundland, on a trail, not on a road.''</p>
        <p>Canadian magazines regularly publish free supplements about the progress of the trail and DaimlerChrysler Canada has donated fleets of Jeeps to the Trail Foundation.</p>
        <p>The Bronfman Foundation has given $1 million for signs and pavilions. The pavilions will hold trail information as well as the name of each person who donated $25 for the construction of a yard of trail.</p>
        <p>The trail logo is a stylized maple leaf composed of three arrows, which represent the three coastal trail heads and ''directions west, north and east emanating from Canada's heartland.''</p>
        <p>''You have politicians saying 'coast to coast,' not 'coast to coast to coast,' '' said Katherine McPhee, northern coordinator of the relay race and wife of Rob. ''When you hear people talk of Canada's three waters, it is a tremendous boost for the north.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
