<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Symbol of France Crashes in Flames</title>
    <meta content="Y26SCE$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217831"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE CONCORD CRASH: THE SCENE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">gonesse (france)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Air France</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Erlanger, Steven</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000726T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE2DF1E3AF935A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="887" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Symbol of France Crashes in Flames</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN ERLANGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Erlanger, Steven</byline>
      <dateline>ROISSY, France, July 25</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Witnesses say Air France Concorde jet was on fire as it took off from airport near Paris; residents of nearby Gonesse, where plane crashed, are shocked and distressed; maps; drawings table of data on Concorde (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Witnesses described the brief, fiery flight of AF 4590 as a vision of hell or a kind of bomb, in flames from the time it rolled down the runway at Charles de Gaulle airport until it smashed three minutes later into a tiny, wooden hotel.</p>
        <p>''It was like some bomb taking off,'' said John Palmerston, an Australian who saw the plane leave the runway from the airport here. ''The whole back end of the plane was on fire. I thought it was going to crash right here at the airport.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Witnesses described the brief, fiery flight of AF 4590 as a vision of hell or a kind of bomb, in flames from the time it rolled down the runway at Charles de Gaulle airport until it smashed three minutes later into a tiny, wooden hotel.</p>
        <p>''It was like some bomb taking off,'' said John Palmerston, an Australian who saw the plane leave the runway from the airport here. ''The whole back end of the plane was on fire. I thought it was going to crash right here at the airport.''</p>
        <p>In the little town of Gonesse, barely four miles southwest of the airport, there were reactions of shock and distress. ''It was truly a hell; there were flames everywhere,'' a witness told the French television channel LCI. ''There were pieces of the fuselage over more than 200 meters, pieces of plastic, of cloth, bits of metal, pieces of the wing, rivets. As for the hotel, there is nothing left; it was blown to pieces.''</p>
        <p>According to authorities, 109 people died on the airplane, and 4 more on the ground, apparently in the hotel Hotelissimo . A huge cloud of gray and black smoke surged into the sky, visible for at least 10 miles.</p>
        <p>For Fabien Tillon, an official trying to manage the crisis from the local government offices in Cergy-Pontoise, the first crash of a Concorde was also a terrible blow to French pride.</p>
        <p>''It's a big national shock,'' he said, as he tried to handle two telephones and a cigarette. ''Many people died, but the symbol of the Concorde, too. The Concorde is a huge national idea for France, a symbol of engineering pride, and the fact that the Concorde crashed, and so many people died, and on the soil of France, it's a terrible shock.''</p>
        <p>The elegant, needle-nosed Concorde, the world's first supersonic passenger plane, was developed by the French and the British in the 1960's as a kind of response to the American and Soviet technological competition, another version of the cold war.</p>
        <p>It also served to heal some wounds left over a veto by France in December 1967 of British membership in the Common Market, now the European Union -- hence the name of the plane. In more than 20 years of commercial flying, however uneconomical and however noisy, the Concorde had never crashed.</p>
        <p>Firemen placed traffic cones across a blackened field, apparently marking the places where charred bodies were found. ''Once you got used to looking through the smoke, the horror hits you,'' an emergency worker who had been at the scene told Agence France-Presse. ''By the dozens, bodies or pieces of bodies, horribly mutilated. Here and there, shoes, books, parts of suitcases that are wasted away.''</p>
        <p>At the hotel, another witness told French television that onlookers had smashed a window and tried to get into the building, but the victims inside were already dead. ''There was nothing we could do,'' that witness said.</p>
        <p>At least one guest jumped out the window to safety, witnesses said.</p>
        <p>Extraordinarily, it seemed, another hotel nearby, Les Relais Bleus, was untouched. ''I thought the plane was going to land on my desk,'' the owner told Europe 1 radio. ''I saw it heading for me in flames. I just let go of the telephone and ran.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Tillon said his staff was unbelieving at first. ''Frankly, when we heard the news, we thought it was some kind of joke or an emergency exercise,'' Mr. Tillon said. ''And then we had confirmation, that the Concorde had crashed and presumably everyone was dead. It really came like a blow.''</p>
        <p>Valerie Tourbon, a Frenchwoman flying today from Charles de Gaulle, echoed the normal sense of pride felt when a Concorde is spotted in the air. ''It always excites me to see one,'' she said. ''It makes me proud. It's awful what's happened.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Tillon described the ''red plan'' for national emergencies that went smoothly into operation in his department, Val d'Oise, which governs Gonesse. More than 200 firefighters were soon on the scene, along with 110 policemen and 80 gendarmes, 13 ambulances, three helicopters, the prefect and the prime minister, Lionel Jospin.</p>
        <p>But even as more emergency workers arrived, their vehicles blocking the roads, there wasn't much to save, Mr. Tillon said. The passengers all appeared to have died, and after the fire was put under control, there came the grisly task of bagging the dead and taking them to the waiting line of hearses.</p>
        <p>''First, there was a large explosion, then barely a second later, another large explosion,'' an office worker said. ''We went to the window, and the flames were higher than the trees. When we went outside, pieces were falling down on us.'' One piece of metal fell on the roof of a colleague's car.</p>
        <p>Another witness told French television: ''I heard the noise, because each time the Concorde flies over, I always have a look. I saw it coming with an engine on fire, it tried to turn on its left, then it fell and fell onto the hotel.''</p>
        <p>THE CONCORD CRASH: THE SCENE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
