<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Though Liked by House Democrats, Cheney Was a Consistent Conservative</title>
    <meta content="Y26VOT$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217841"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE RECORD IN CONGRESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vice Presidents and Vice Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cheney, Richard B</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rosenbaum, David E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Rockies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vice Presidents and Vice Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000726T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE6DE1E3AF935A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="937" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Though Liked by House Democrats, Cheney Was a Consistent Conservative</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID E. ROSENBAUM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rosenbaum, David E</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 25</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dick Cheney, in his 10 years as Republican congressman from Wyoming, had one of most consistently conservative voting records in Congress; was personally well liked by Democrats, who then controlled House (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In his 10 years as a Republican congressman from Wyoming, Dick Cheney had one of the most consistently conservative voting records in Congress.</p>
        <p>He regularly voted for the tightest restrictions on abortions, including proposals to ban Medicaid coverage of abortions for poor women whose lives could be endangered by continued pregnancy. And he voted against all gun-control legislation, including measures like one to regulate what are known as cop-killer bullets that were supported by all but a handful of lawmakers from both parties.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In his 10 years as a Republican congressman from Wyoming, Dick Cheney had one of the most consistently conservative voting records in Congress.</p>
        <p>He regularly voted for the tightest restrictions on abortions, including proposals to ban Medicaid coverage of abortions for poor women whose lives could be endangered by continued pregnancy. And he voted against all gun-control legislation, including measures like one to regulate what are known as cop-killer bullets that were supported by all but a handful of lawmakers from both parties.</p>
        <p>On issues in which business and labor were on opposite sides, he invariably supported the business position. When developers and environmentalists were at odds, he was on the side of the developers.</p>
        <p>He opposed a constitutional amendment to guarantee equal rights to women and voted against economic sanctions on South Africa.</p>
        <p>During Mr. Cheney's time in Congress, from 1979 to 1989, Democrats controlled the House. As is normally the case with lawmakers in the minority party, he was not directly responsible for any major legislation.</p>
        <p>While rigidly conservative on issues, he was not known for strident rhetoric and was well liked by Democrats. Mr. Cheney was not a visible leader in the fight to outlaw abortion, but the National Right to Life Committee said today that he voted against abortion rights on all the roll calls for which he was present.</p>
        <p>For instance, he voted in 1984 to define ''person'' under discrimination laws to include fetuses. The sponsor of the measure -- which Al Gore, then a congressman, also supported -- said its purpose was to deny federal funds to all institutions performing abortions. Mr. Cheney also supported a constitutional amendment banning abortion, but the issue never came to a vote.</p>
        <p>He was an unwavering advocate of the Reagan administration's economic policy of deep tax cuts, more spending for the military and less money for social programs. Annual vote analyses by Congressional Quarterly showed that in most of the years he was in the House, Mr. Cheney supported President Ronald Reagan more consistently than almost any other member of Congress.</p>
        <p>In only his second term, he moved into the Republican leadership, and he was the Republican whip, the No. 2 position, by the time he left. Had he stayed in the House, he might well have become speaker when Republicans gained control.</p>
        <p>Beyond his leadership responsibilities, Mr. Cheney was most deeply involved in foreign policy and intelligence matters. He strongly supported covert spending for guerrilla forces trying to oust communist governments in Nicaragua and Angola.</p>
        <p>In 1987, Mr. Cheney served as the top Republican on the House committee investigating the Iran-contra affair. The committee determined that the administration had raised money selling arms secretly to Iran, then used the proceeds to finance the rebels, known as contras, in Nicaragua. Mr. Cheney voted against the final report, which accused Mr. Reagan of failing to meet his constitutional mandate to ''take care that the laws be faithfully executed.''</p>
        <p>Some issues important when Mr. Cheney was in Congress are no longer in the news. For example, he repeatedly voted to produce the MX missile, a hugely expensive weapon designed to carry 10 nuclear warheads that was the symbol of what opponents considered the excesses of the Reagan nuclear weapons policy.</p>
        <p>He also often voted against proposals to apply sanctions on South Africa to protest its apartheid policy, andvoted in 1986 against a nonbinding resolution calling for the release of Nelson Mandela from prison.</p>
        <p>In his first year in Congress, Mr. Cheney voted for a constitutional amendment to ban busing for school desegregation. In 1980, he voted against strengthening the laws banning discrimination in housing.</p>
        <p>The only time he turned against the Reagan administration on an important issue was in 1985, when he helped lead a revolt against a bill negotiated by the president and Democrats to overhaul the income tax system. He accused the administration of selling out. Even after the bill was modified by the Republican-controlled Senate and came back to the House in 1986, he voted against it.</p>
        <p>President Reagan signed the tax bill and considered it one of his foremost legislative accomplishments.</p>
        <p>Other issues from that era will be featured in this year's campaign.</p>
        <p>On gun control, he was one of just 21 House members to vote against a bill regulating the manufacture, import and sale of armor-piercing ammunition known as cop-killer bullets. He was one of four who voted in 1988 against a proposal to ban firearms that did not contain enough metal to be picked up by a metal detector.</p>
        <p>On education, Mr. Cheney often voted against Head Start, the federal preschool program. He voted in 1985 against federal aid to college students, and opposed the creation of the Department of Education.</p>
        <p>On the environment, he voted in 1987 against extending the Clean Water Act and in favor of postponing sanctions against cities that did not comply with the Clean Air Act.</p>
        <p>Appearing tonight on CNN's ''Larry King Live'' program, Mr. Cheney discussed his conservative record and said ''I'm proud of it.''</p>
        <p>But he said some votes had been motivated by a concern for fiscal responsibility in an era when the nation did not have the projected surpluses it now had. ''I would not vote against Head Start today,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He also spoke in a tempered voice about abortion. ''I don't think it should be a defining issue for our party,'' he said, adding that the party needed to be sensitive to different views about abortion rights.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE RECORD IN CONGRESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
