<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On the North Fork, Dreams of Napa</title>
    <meta content="26WINE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217734"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="WINE TALK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Prial, Frank J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Columns/Wine Talk</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000726T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E4D6103AF935A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1754" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On the North Fork, Dreams of Napa</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>PECONIC, N.Y., July 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Frank Prial Wine Talk column on booming wine business on Ling Islandl increasing number of wineries and vineyards are being operated by self-assured professionals backed by deep-pocketed investors who are also seeking different lifestyle--as owners of Napa Valley-like showcase wineries making prize-winning and sought-after wines; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It's high summer out here on the North Fork of Long Island. The corn is sweet, the first peaches are in, and in the vineyards, the still-green merlot and cabernet franc are looking good. It will be long weeks, maybe two months, before the pickers arrive and the air grows heady with the seductive aroma of crushed grapes.</p>
        <p>But don't be deceived by the bucolic calm. The Long Island wine business is booming; it's almost giddy from its own success. Handsome new wineries are opening, old ones are changing hands for astonishing prices, new vineyards are springing up from Aquebogue to Greenport, and suddenly, there isn't enough wine to go around.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It's high summer out here on the North Fork of Long Island. The corn is sweet, the first peaches are in, and in the vineyards, the still-green merlot and cabernet franc are looking good. It will be long weeks, maybe two months, before the pickers arrive and the air grows heady with the seductive aroma of crushed grapes.</p>
        <p>But don't be deceived by the bucolic calm. The Long Island wine business is booming; it's almost giddy from its own success. Handsome new wineries are opening, old ones are changing hands for astonishing prices, new vineyards are springing up from Aquebogue to Greenport, and suddenly, there isn't enough wine to go around.</p>
        <p>What's more, these developments are not due to the hesitant little band of artisans and amateurs who started it all in converted barns and potato fields some 30 years ago, seeking a simpler agrarian lifestyle, so they thought. The current scene is made up of self-assured professionals backed by deep-pocketed investors, who are also seeking a different lifestyle -- as owners of Napa Valley-like showcase wineries making prize-winning and sought-after wines.</p>
        <p>World-class wines may be a few years away, but the money, the talent and the will to make them are all in place. It is, everyone out here will tell you, just a matter of time.</p>
        <p>I'm inclined to agree, with a few reservations. Seven of every 10 bottles of wine Americans consume is California wine. California wines, for the most part, are jammy, full-bodied, velvety and relatively easy to drink. Fat, buttery chardonnay is the paradigm. Long Island wines, at their best, are just as intense, but are leaner, less voluptuous. Perhaps more elegant. They are a different taste experience, and for many wine fans they take some getting used to.</p>
        <p>The North Fork is a narrow strip of farmland on eastern Long Island between Long Island Sound and Peconic Bay, about 70 miles from Manhattan. In 1970 it was on the brink of the same drab suburbanization that had already overwhelmed Nassau County and much of western Suffolk. Then the affluent and photogenic Alex and Louisa Hargrave, children of the 1960's, arrived, wanting to go ''back to the land.'' They founded Hargrave Vineyard in Cutchogue, and almost miraculously, other vineyards soon followed, bringing new life to the faltering agricultural economy.</p>
        <p>Today, vineyard land totals about 2,800 acres, of which about 2,200 are in production. Annual wine production, still negligible, is estimated to be 300,000 cases, about the same as for one medium-size California winery. It's hardly enough to supply a growing market and the hordes of tourists who descend on the tasting rooms each weekend, particularly in the fall, when some of the wineries receive 400 to 500 visitors a day. Not long ago, the Long Island wineries sold most of their production in their tasting rooms. Now, with their business growing in many markets, tasting room depletions are forcing some wineries to charge for what they once gave away free.</p>
        <p>(Several of the region's 21 wineries are actually on Long Island's South Fork, which was once agricultural but is now given over principally to the Hamptons.)</p>
        <p>If any North Fork endeavor symbolizes how the Long Island wine industry has progressed in less than three decades, it is the striking Italianate Raphael winery going up on the Main Road in this hamlet 10 miles east of Riverhead. It is a $6 million testimony to the faith that the owner, John Petrocelli, has in the Long Island wine industry. A year before its opening, it has already raised the bar on what is expected from Long Island's vineyards and fledgling wine producers in the years ahead. No expense has been spared by Mr. Petrocelli, a commercial builder in New York City.</p>
        <p>At the same time, Raphael is based on what came before: the winemaker is Richard Olsen-Harbich, a veteran of 20 years in Long Island cellars.</p>
        <p>Raphael, named for the owner's father, an immigrant and home winemaker, will be a one-wine winery, and that wine will be merlot. Of the 60 acres of vines planted, 45 are merlot. Small amounts of cabernet sauvignon and other Bordeaux varietals are cultivated, but only to enhance the merlot. There is -- hold on to your seat -- no chardonnay. In fact, there is no white wine at all, except a smidgen of sauvignon blanc for friends.</p>
        <p>It was in deciding on merlot, and only merlot, that Mr. Petrocelli and Mr. Olsen-Harbich drew a figurative line in the sand to mark the spot where the old Long Island wine industry ends and a new one begins.</p>
        <p>Mr. Olsen-Harbich has a foot in both camps. A 20-year veteran of the Long Island wine industry who was born in Queens and studied viticulture at Cornell University, he started as founding winemaker at Bridgehampton Vineyards, worked with the Hargraves for a time and spent several years as a consultant to newcomers eager to start up wineries. But the arrival of Mr. Petrocelli ratcheted up the stakes.</p>
        <p>''Hit or miss experimentation, putting vineyards in and pulling them out -- those days are all behind us,'' Mr. Olsen-Harbich said. ''We know this is merlot country now.''</p>
        <p>Does this sound rather like Bordeaux? It does, and with good reason.</p>
        <p>Mr. Olsen-Harbich, 39, shares his Raphael responsibilities with Paul Pontallier, the 44-year-old managing director of Chateau Margaux, one of Bordeaux's legendary premier-cru wine properties. He has been a  consultant to Raphael since 1996, when the project began.</p>
        <p>''Our soil, our climate, both are Bordeaux-like,'' Mr. Olsen-Harbich said, ''and our wines taste more like Bordeaux wines than California wines. We needed the Bordeaux influence. Before we planted a grape, Paul determined the vineyard layout and the spacing of the vines. He is here four, occasionally six times a year, and we talk, sometimes daily, on the phone.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Pontallier is circumspect: ''The main problem on the North Fork is to get the grapes ripe,'' he said by telephone from Bordeaux. ''The region has an interesting combination of warm and cold temperatures, and the grapes must struggle to get ripe. Often they are not picked until November. Our merlot here in Bordeaux is three to four weeks ahead of the merlot on the North Fork.''</p>
        <p>''We are not going to make great wine overnight,'' he added, ''but we will make very good wine. Of that I am sure.''</p>
        <p>Raphael, using Pellegrini's cellar, produced 200 cases in 1997 and plans to make about 700 of the 1999 vintage. Eventually, the goal is around 10,000 cases. Compare that with Pindar Vineyards, the region's largest, which reports it produces more than 80,000 cases and plans to reach 150,000.</p>
        <p>Even if its production is small, Raphael is a winery on the grand scale. It will be the goal for new investors to top.</p>
        <p>Robert Entenmann, of the baked-goods family, who owns Martha Clara Vineyards in Mattituck, might be one of the first to do that. He has plans for a $4-million tasting room and a $2-million-to-$3-million winery. Leslie Alexander, the owner of the Houston Rockets basketball team, paid about $1.5 million last year for acreage in Cutchogue and Mattituck and is said to plan a winery. Marco Borghese, an Italian with a number of silent partners, last year bought the Hargrave Vineyard, also in Cutchogue, for around $4 million.</p>
        <p>Other prominent Long Island wineries sold last year included Corey Creek, Laurel Lake, Peconic Bay and Bedell Cellars. Bedell went to Michael Lynne, a Time Warner executive, for about $5 million. Still on the block are two other Cutchogue wineries, Gristina Vineyards at $5.5 million, and Bidawell Vineyards for $3.5 million.</p>
        <p>With most of these sales, the founders plan to stay on making the wine, while the new owners, mostly businessmen, take over management, marketing and promotion and enjoy the prestige that comes with being in the wine business.</p>
        <p>At the same time, many existing wineries are expanding. Bob Pellegrini, who in 1982 started Pellegrini Vineyards in Cutchogue, recently bought 60 acres in two parcels ''not to increase production, but to become totally estate,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''Totally estate'' means that he will own all his own vineyards and can call his wine estate-bottled. Pellegrini Vineyards currently buys about 40 percent of its grapes, Mr. Pellegrini said.</p>
        <p>Buying new vineyards is not done casually. Twenty years ago, prime farmland sold for $4,000 an acre on the North Fork. Today, driven by competition among wealthy investors, the price can reach $20,000 to $30,000 an acre, Mr. Olsen-Harbich said.</p>
        <p>Compared with, say, Pindar, Raphael is very small. But there are grape growers on the North Fork, many of them weekend farmers, whose vineyards are even smaller -- far too small to support wineries. For them, Russell Hearn, Pellegrini's Australian winemaker, is putting up the region's first custom-crush winery in Mattituck. Called the Premium Wine Group, it will produce, age, bottle and label wine for these owners of small vineyards. In California, similar operations, like the Napa Wine Company, produce wines for dozens of vineyard owners.</p>
        <p>At least one longtime resident, Russell McCall of Cutchogue, has rejected all the conventional wisdom and has planted a dozen acres of pinot noir across the road from Pellegrini. Pinot noir is a temperamental grape with a high rate of failure. But then the experts said it would never succeed in California, and it has -- impressively. On the North Fork, they welcome a challenge like that.</p>
        <p>WINE TALK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
