<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.N. Weighs Rebuilding Its Complex</title>
    <meta content="26NATI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217797"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000726T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E0D8113AF935A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="900" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.N. Weighs Rebuilding Its Complex</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>UNITED NATIONS, July 25</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>United Nations is considering spending nearly $1 billion on six-year rebuilding program to address structural and environmental woes of its aging headquarters buildings in Manhattan; $964 million rebuilding plan outlined; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The United Nations is considering spending nearly $1 billion on a six-year rebuilding program to address the structural and environmental woes of its aging headquarters buildings -- potent, though tarnished, symbols of postwar cooperation and enlightened urbanism.</p>
        <p>''From the business standpoint, there is no alternative,'' said Joseph E. Connor, the under secretary general for management, who presented an analysis of the proposal to reporters today.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The United Nations is considering spending nearly $1 billion on a six-year rebuilding program to address the structural and environmental woes of its aging headquarters buildings -- potent, though tarnished, symbols of postwar cooperation and enlightened urbanism.</p>
        <p>''From the business standpoint, there is no alternative,'' said Joseph E. Connor, the under secretary general for management, who presented an analysis of the proposal to reporters today.</p>
        <p>The rebuilding plan would require about a third of the organization's staff members to move out of the complex temporarily or into new quarters on the site, and it would be likely that the General Assembly would have to meet in a conference room for a year.</p>
        <p>The proposal is the result of a two-year study completed last year that is to be submitted to the General Assembly when it convenes in September. If it is approved by the 188-member General Assembly, detailed plans will be drawn up, and the work could begin early in 2003, Mr. Connor said.</p>
        <p>Under the $964 million plan, about a third members of the staff of the United Nations Secretariat would be relocated in ''swing space'' during the renovation and refurbishment, which would be conducted in phases.</p>
        <p>By far the boldest -- and, at $245 million, the most costly -- of the  options for space features a 10-story addition to be built atop the Secretariat Building, New York City's first curtain-walled glass skyscraper and, along with the sprawling, saddle-shaped General Assembly Building, a widely recognized emblem of the organization. Another addition would be built atop the Dag Hammarskjold Library, and the South Annex would be rebuilt.</p>
        <p>Because the 17-acre site is considered international territory, none of the buildings or interiors at the United Nations headquarters have been designated New York City landmarks.</p>
        <p>Another, less costly option is the construction of two entirely new buildings, a six-story structure on an empty expanse of the North Lawn, below East 48th Street, and a four-story building off site. A third option is to lease commercial office space in the neighborhood, which is less costly but fails to address future space needs significantly, Mr. Connor said.</p>
        <p>Although the capital master plan focuses on basic infrastructure and  compliance with New York City building codes, it includes plans for expansion of the organization's meeting rooms and Conference Building, and refurbishing of the General Assembly auditorium, public lobbies and visitors' area, at a cost of $74 million. The chambers of the Security Council, Trusteeship Council, and Economic and Social Council, which are among the more architecturally distinguished interiors in the complex, will remain more or less untouched, Mr. Connor said.</p>
        <p>The United Nations buildings, still elegant and imposing when viewed from First Avenue or across the East River, have suffered years of budget-based neglect, and ad hoc maintenance cannot keep pace with the breakdowns. Corroded pipes leak, railing supports are rusted out, roofs are soaked and spongy. Motors and water pumps are so antiquated that replacement parts are unavailable, and the air-conditioning system has long been a source of consternation.</p>
        <p>The Secretariat Building -- a shimmering, 572-foot transparent glass slab, built on a north-south axis, with 5,400 windows that actually open and close -- stands as a modern monument to wasteful energy consumption, and the buildings do not comply with city fire codes, handicapped accessibility standards or environmental safety codes.</p>
        <p>Mr. Connor displayed charts showing that if a rebuilding plan was not approved, the current ad hoc approach to maintenance would cost the United Nations almost $1.2 billion over the next 25 years, mostly in emergency repairs and maintenance, while $490 million would be required to buy energy.</p>
        <p>Unless off-site space is leased, the refurbishment would be the first substantial new construction on the site since the completion of the Hammarskjold Library in 1961. Most of the 2.7-million-square-foot complex, which was designed by an international team of architects that included Le Corbusier, Oscar Niemeyer and Wallace K. Harrison, was built between 1949 and 1952.</p>
        <p>The United Nations will have to rely largely on member states to pay for putting the plan into effect. The preferred form of payment would be a special assessment, levied over six to eight years and paid directly in cash, Mr. Connor said. Consideration will also be given to spreading the cost over 25 years, either through interest-free loans from member states or commercial borrowing through a bond issue based on individual sovereign states' credit ratings.</p>
        <p>The involvement of major contributors like the United States, which according to the United Nations already owes more than $1 billion in back dues, will be essential to the plan's success.</p>
        <p>''The Congress would have to look at it before any proposals can be made in response to this initiative,'' said Don Hayes, the representative in charge of management and reform at the United Nations. ''But we are the host country, and we will want to play our proper role when our time comes.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
