<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BULLETIN BOARD</title>
    <meta content="26BULL$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Education Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217788"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holloway, Lynette</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wyatt, Edward</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arenson, Karen W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Anderson, Lionel</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education/Columns/Bulletin Board</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000726T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02EFD9113AF935A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="458" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BULLETIN BOARD</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Lynette Holloway, Edward Wyatt, Karen W. Arenson and Lionel Anderson</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wyatt, Edward; Holloway, Lynette; Arenson, Karen W; Anderson, Lionel</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bulletin Board column offers college and school news (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Pataki Stiffens Penalties for School Violence</p>
        <p>GOV. GEORGE E. PATAKI has signed a law stiffening penalties for violence in schools and making it easier to remove disruptive students from classrooms. The measure requires school districts to draw up codes of conduct for students, set up statewide reporting systems and increase public education campaigns aimed at reducing student violence. Mr. Pataki also signed a measure that requires prospective teachers and other school employees to be fingerprinted and to have their backgrounds checked for criminal records.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Pataki Stiffens Penalties for School Violence</p>
        <p>GOV. GEORGE E. PATAKI has signed a law stiffening penalties for violence in schools and making it easier to remove disruptive students from classrooms. The measure requires school districts to draw up codes of conduct for students, set up statewide reporting systems and increase public education campaigns aimed at reducing student violence. Mr. Pataki also signed a measure that requires prospective teachers and other school employees to be fingerprinted and to have their backgrounds checked for criminal records.</p>
        <p>New Dean of Engineering at C.C.N.Y.</p>
        <p>The City College of New York has a new engineering dean. He is MOHAMMAD A. KARIM, right, chairman of electrical and computer engineering at the University of Tennessee in Knoxville. SHELDON WEINBAUM, a City College professor who headed the search, said the committee was impressed by Dr. Karim's energy, his publications (six books and nearly 200 articles) and his record in building engineering enrollments at the University of Dayton before moving to Tennessee.</p>
        <p>Compensation for 'Sacrifices'</p>
        <p>When the REV. FLOYD FLAKE announced in May that he was joining Edison Schools, the education company started by H. CHRISTOPHER WHITTLE, he gave up a potential run for mayor, seats on boards advising other charter school companies, and ambitions to start a charter school himself. According to documents filed this month, Mr. Flake received something for those sacrifices. Edison agreed to pay $200,000 to Global Lyceum Inc., a company controlled by Mr. Flake, as compensation for its expenses, as an inducement for the company not to compete with Edison, and for the release of Mr. Flake and two associates from obligations to Global Lyceum.</p>
        <p>Princeton Capital Campaign More Successful Than Hoped</p>
        <p>Princeton University has raised $1.1 billion in its five-year capital campaign, nearly 50 percent more than the $750 million it set out to collect in the summer of 1995. Gifts of $1 million or more made up about half of the total, and around 41,500 alumni made donations, according to BILL HARDT, director of annual giving.</p>
        <p>Middle Schoolers in a Literacy Experiment</p>
        <p>Sixty Queens middle school students are taking part in an unusual four-week summer program at SUNY Stony Brook aimed at improving literacy skills through scientific research. The sixth and seventh graders from Intermediate Schools 172 and 216 are living in dormitories and conducting DNA research in a program initiated through a partnership with New York City's Board of Education.</p>
        <p>Lynette Holloway, Edward Wyatt, Karen W. Arenson and Lionel Anderson</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
