<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>G.M. Unites Media Planning At New Shop</title>
    <meta content="Y26ADC$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217790"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">General Motors Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">B Com3 Group</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Starcom MediaVest Group</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Elliott, Stuart</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Advertising (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000726T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E7D8113AF935A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="923" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>G.M. Unites Media Planning At New Shop</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STUART ELLIOTT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Elliott, Stuart</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Largest assignment in history of New York advertising is made when General Motors Corp consolidates responsibilities for media planning at a new agency to be formed by unit of B Com3 Group; consolidation of media planning under unit, Starcom MediaVest Group, will affect all GM brands sold in US execpt Saab and Saturn (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The largest assignment in the history of Madison Avenue was made yesterday when General Motors consolidated responsibilities for media planning -- deciding where to run ads with an annual budget of $2.9 billion -- at a new shop to be formed by a unit of the giant agency company known as the B Com3  Group.</p>
        <p>The consolidation of media planning under the unit, the Starcom MediaVest Group, came after a monthlong review of three contenders and will affect all G.M. brands sold in the United States except Saab and Saturn.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The largest assignment in the history of Madison Avenue was made yesterday when General Motors consolidated responsibilities for media planning -- deciding where to run ads with an annual budget of $2.9 billion -- at a new shop to be formed by a unit of the giant agency company known as the B Com3  Group.</p>
        <p>The consolidation of media planning under the unit, the Starcom MediaVest Group, came after a monthlong review of three contenders and will affect all G.M. brands sold in the United States except Saab and Saturn.</p>
        <p>''As you can imagine, this is a huge undertaking for us,'' Michael A. Browner, executive director for media and marketing operations at the General Motors Corporation in Detroit, said in a conference call to reporters to announce the decision.</p>
        <p>Media planning is taking on additional strategic importance as marketers seek to increase the long odds that a potential customer -- busy with life and bored by most ads -- will pay attention to a sales pitch, particularly when many products are aimed at narrow demographic groups rather than mass audiences.</p>
        <p>One way media planning works is to use tools like consumer research to try tailoring media schedules to the tastes of would-be buyers so they are more likely to encounter the ads, whether watching television, listening to the radio, surfing the Internet, passing by billboards or reading a newspaper or magazine. Another way media planning tries to improve the chances that consumers will see ads is to have them appear in unexpected places, from store floors and plastic bags wrapped around dry cleaning to elevators and airport baggage carousels.</p>
        <p>''If we do our job well, the effectiveness of our advertising will be improved by putting ads in better places at better times,'' Mr. Browner said, ''making sure we can reach more of the target audience more effectively.''</p>
        <p>The decision to select Starcom MediaVest was made by a committee of seven high-ranking G.M. marketing and advertising executives. There were two other agencies under consideration in the review: the Interpublic Group of Companies and Carat North America, part of the Aegis Group.</p>
        <p>The decision by G.M. to consolidate media planning at a stand-alone shop came seven years after the company, the nation's largest advertiser and largest automaker, consolidated media buying -- the negotiations to determine how much ads will cost -- at G.M. Mediaworks in Warren, Mich., formed by Interpublic at G.M.'s request.</p>
        <p>The creative duties for G.M. brands remain at the various agencies now handling those tasks, including Starcom MediaVest siblings like Leo Burnett in Chicago and D'Arcy Masius Benton &amp; Bowles in Troy, Mich., as well as Interpublic agencies like Campbell-Ewald in Warren and McCann-Erickson in Troy. The creative agencies had also been handling media planning for their particular brands; so, for instance, Burnett took care of creative and planning tasks for Oldsmobile and D'Arcy did the same for Cadillac and Pontiac.</p>
        <p>The goal of consolidation is to wring additional economies from the elaborate planning and buying processes that lead to the delivery of ads to consumers.</p>
        <p>''Efficiencies come from improved effectiveness in the marketplace,'' John G. Middlebrook, vice president and general manager for vehicle brand marketing at G.M., said during the conference call.</p>
        <p>That will best be accomplished, he added, by ''the formation of a dedicated media-planning operation, tentatively titled G.M. Planworks,'' to consolidate the national and regional brand-planning duties that had been divided among 17 agencies. The responsibilities had been about evenly divided between agencies owned by B Com3  and Interpublic.</p>
        <p>Starcom MediaVest will form G.M. Planworks -- in Detroit or a nearby suburb -- to handle the media planning for brands that include Chevrolet, Pontiac, Oldsmobile, Buick, Cadillac and G.M.C. Currently, more than 200 people handle those planning tasks, developing and producing media schedules for each brand based on the intended audience for each car, minivan or truck. G.M. Planworks, which is to be fully operating by the first quarter of 2001, is to have 150 to 200 employees.</p>
        <p>''This is all about trying to raise the bar higher,'' said Jack Klues, chief executive at Starcom MediaVest, which was formed by B Com3  in May by merging Starcom Worldwide, affiliated with Burnett, with MediaVest Worldwide, affiliated with D'Arcy. Other Starcom MediaVest clients include Coca-Cola, Philip Morris and Procter &amp; Gamble.</p>
        <p>''We've always admired and respected'' the performance of G.M. Mediaworks, he added. ''Now our goal and purpose is to deliver that same quality of work from a strategic planning perspective.''</p>
        <p>Carat North America, unlike Starcom MediaVest and Interpublic, has not handled media planning for G.M. But the chief executive there, David Verklin, is well known to the automaker for his work at the San Francisco agency now known as Publicis &amp; Hal Riney, which handles creative and media planning assignments for Saturn.</p>
        <p>''The two 'inside' competitors and the one 'outside' competitor all came in with an equal opportunity to win the assignment,'' Mr. Browner said, adding that the criteria by which Starcom MediaVest was chosen included ''the successes the agency has had for G.M. as well as with other companies'' and ''its strategic media research.''</p>
        <p>''We have had no dissatisfaction with the quality of the media plans done for our brands by the individual agencies,'' Mr. Browner said. ''But we should benefit from the integration across the brands, the shared learning when you've got best-in-class research.''</p>
        <p>Riney continues to handle media planning for Saturn and the Martin Agency in Richmond, Va., owned by Interpublic, continues to handle media planning for Saab.</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
