<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Michel Richard</title>
    <meta content="26CHEF" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217703"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE CHEF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Richard, Michel</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Columns/The Chef</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000726T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E1DA133AF935A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="751" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Michel Richard</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sixth of eight article in The Chef series by Michel Richard gives recipe for sage chicken in fried potato crust; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I HAVE thought a lot about fried chicken because Americans love it. The idea for a potato crust on it came to me from  frozen Tater Tots. I loved their crunch and thought if I coated the chicken with potatoes instead of bread crumbs the crunch would be better. It's more work, but it's more than worth it.</p>
        <p>I had to play with the recipe a few times before I got it right. The hardest part was getting the potatoes to stick to the skinless chicken.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I HAVE thought a lot about fried chicken because Americans love it. The idea for a potato crust on it came to me from  frozen Tater Tots. I loved their crunch and thought if I coated the chicken with potatoes instead of bread crumbs the crunch would be better. It's more work, but it's more than worth it.</p>
        <p>I had to play with the recipe a few times before I got it right. The hardest part was getting the potatoes to stick to the skinless chicken.</p>
        <p>The potatoes are diced very small because that adds so much more texture. You  don't want them to be uniform because you get a better crunch if the pieces are different sizes. I use a mandoline to cut fine strips and then a very sharp knife to cut tiny cubes, but you can do it all with a knife.</p>
        <p>At first I tried potato starch, but it didn't adhere, so I switched to flour. I also wanted to marinate the chicken to give it more flavor and sophistication. An oil-based marinade also kept the coating from sticking, so  I had to change to a dry rub with sage, cumin and garlic. They all add interesting notes that are not found in traditional fried chicken. I mix the chicken and the dry rub with my hands in order to massage the seasonings into the flesh.</p>
        <p>Wrapping the chicken in plastic film also helps the coating adhere. When I first tried it, it was very tricky to remove the plastic without having some of the coating come with it. So I tried putting the wrapped pieces in the freezer for an hour and that was all it needed. The plastic was easy to remove.</p>
        <p>I prefer to make this dish with boneless chicken because it cooks more quickly and is easier to eat. I fry only a few pieces at a time so that the temperature of the fat does not cool down too much.</p>
        <p>In the restaurant I fry the chicken in clarified butter, but at home I do it in grapeseed oil because it is healthier. I have to admit, though, that the clarified butter gives it more flavor.</p>
        <p>SAGE CHICKEN IN A FRIED POTATO CRUST  Time: 1 hour 15 minutes, plus 2 hours' refrigeration and 1 hour's freezing</p>
        <p>3 skinless, boneless chicken breast halves  3 skinless, boneless chicken thighs</p>
        <p>1/2 cup loosely packed chopped sage  1 teaspoon minced garlic  1 teaspoon ground cumin  2 pounds (2 to 3 large) baking potatoes  7 tablespoons all-purpose flour  2 tablespoons lightly beaten large egg white  Freshly ground black pepper  2 large eggs, lightly beaten  Grapeseed oil for deep frying.</p>
        <p>1. Cut each chicken breast half into three pieces, and each thigh into two pieces. In a bowl, combine chicken, sage, garlic and cumin. Cover and refrigerate for 2 hours.</p>
        <p>2. Using a mandoline or sharp knife, slice  potatoes into  1/8-inch-thick julienne, then crosswise into  1/8-inch dice. Rinse, then pat dry between cloth towels. Roll in towels to squeeze out moisture. In a medium bowl, combine potatoes with 4 tablespoons flour and beaten egg white. Set aside.</p>
        <p>3. Scrape garlic and sage from chicken pieces, and pat dry with paper towels. Season with pepper to taste and dust with  remaining flour.</p>
        <p>4. Place a 10-inch square of plastic wrap on a work surface. Evenly spread about 2 tablespoons of potato in center of plastic. Dip a piece of chicken in beaten egg, and place in  center of potato. Top with about 1 tablespoon potato, and wrap plastic securely so that potato covers chicken completely. Repeat with remaining chicken, egg and potatoes, to make a total of 15 packets. Place in  freezer for one hour.</p>
        <p>5. Preheat oven to 200 degrees. Preheat at least 4 inches oil in a deep fryer to 325 degrees. Unwrap three chicken packets, and deep fry until potatoes are crisp and golden brown, 5 to 8 minutes. Transfer to baking sheet lined with paper towels, and keep warm in oven. Repeat with remaining packets. Serve hot.</p>
        <p>Yield: 4 servings.</p>
        <p>THE CHEF This is the sixth of eight columns by Michel Richard, the chef and owner of Citronelle in Washington. They are being written with Marian Burros.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">This is the sixth of eight columns by Michel Richard, the chef and owner of Citronelle in Washington. They are being written with Marian Burros.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
