<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Senator Moynihan Objects to Being Spliced in Step With Lazio</title>
    <meta content="26LAZI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217835"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE AD CAMPAIGN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Republican Leadership Council</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blair, Jayson</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Moynihan, Daniel Patrick (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lazio, Rick A (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000726T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E0DF1E3AF935A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="786" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Senator Moynihan Objects to Being Spliced in Step With Lazio</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAYSON BLAIR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Blair, Jayson</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of new 30-second commercial that Republican Leadership Council plans to begin broadcasting this week; it features President Clinton praising leadership of his wife's Republican Senate opponent, Representative Rick A Lazio; also uses split screen focus to link Lazio with outgoing Sen Daniel Patrick Moynihan; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>This is a new 30-second commercial that the Republican Leadership Council plans to begin broadcasting this week. It features President Clinton praising the leadership of his wife's Republican Senate opponent, Representative Rick A. Lazio. The advertisement includes videotape of Mr. Clinton praising Mr. Lazio and the man he hopes to replace, retiring Senator Daniel Patrick Moynihan. The council says it is independent of Mr. Lazio's campaign, and thus can use largely unregulated ''soft money,'' which is supposed to be used mainly for party building and not for urging votes for particular candidates, to pay for the ad.</p>
        <p>The council plans to spend $1 million to run the commercial on broadcast stations through Labor Day in Albany, Buffalo, Rochester, Syracuse, Binghamton and the Hudson Valley. It will run on cable stations in Westchester County and on Long Island.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>This is a new 30-second commercial that the Republican Leadership Council plans to begin broadcasting this week. It features President Clinton praising the leadership of his wife's Republican Senate opponent, Representative Rick A. Lazio. The advertisement includes videotape of Mr. Clinton praising Mr. Lazio and the man he hopes to replace, retiring Senator Daniel Patrick Moynihan. The council says it is independent of Mr. Lazio's campaign, and thus can use largely unregulated ''soft money,'' which is supposed to be used mainly for party building and not for urging votes for particular candidates, to pay for the ad.</p>
        <p>The council plans to spend $1 million to run the commercial on broadcast stations through Labor Day in Albany, Buffalo, Rochester, Syracuse, Binghamton and the Hudson Valley. It will run on cable stations in Westchester County and on Long Island.</p>
        <p>In a letter dated yesterday, Senator Moynihan called the spot misleading and asked Mr. Lazio to urge the leadership council to pull the ad. ''I do not believe you would wish to be associated with this species of soft money fakery,'' the senator said in the letter. In an interview, Mr. Moynihan said that ''there was no question that Mr. Lazio was the principle sponsor'' of the legislation, but added that his role was more limited.</p>
        <p>PRODUCER -- Heintz Media</p>
        <p>ON THE SCREEN -- The commercial opens with Mr.  Lazio walking into a Capitol Hill office and extending his hand to someone off-screen. The narrator declares: ''Democrats and Republicans agree'' that ''Rick Lazio is a leader.'' President Clinton is then shown on a makeshift blue stage in front of the Franklin Delano Roosevelt Memorial in Washington. Mr. Clinton, flanked on both sides by invited guests, thanks Senator Moynihan and Representative Lazio.</p>
        <p>The advertisement shows a split screen, using separate footage, with Mr. Lazio and Senator Moynihan both walking toward viewers as the narrator describes how the two men helped disabled New Yorkers find jobs without losing access to health care services.</p>
        <p>The advertisement then shows back-to-back pictures of two women in wheelchairs: one pushing herself down a hallway, and the other working with vials in what appears to be a laboratory.</p>
        <p>The advertisement closes with a shot of a logo and telephone number for the Lazio campaign.</p>
        <p>THE SCRIPT -- ''Democrats and Republicans agree -- Rick Lazio is a leader,'' the announcer says. President Clinton says ''. . . Senator Moynihan, Representative Lazio, thank you, sir.'' The announcer adds: ''Together, Lazio and Moynihan helped disabled New Yorkers work, without losing access to vital health care benefits. Lazio and Moynihan made a difference. They're from New York. They're fighting for New York. Tell Lazio and Moynihan to keep fighting for us.''</p>
        <p>ACCURACY -- Mr. Lazio was the primary sponsor of legislation in the House of Representatives to make it possible for disabled Americans to take jobs without having to give up many Medicare and Medicaid benefits. The bill was supported by most Democrats and Republicans and was far from controversial. It passed the House with 412-9.</p>
        <p>The Republican Leadership Council supports its attempt to link Senator Moynihan and Mr. Lazio through President Clinton's quotation from the bill-signing ceremony.</p>
        <p>Senator Moynihan said his primary objection to the ad was that he had never been photographed together with Mr. Lazio. ''There is one thing I felt that had to be objected to,'' Mr. Moynihan said. ''We have never been photographed together and that is not the way a respectable campaign behaves.''</p>
        <p>Dan McLagan, a campaign spokesman for Mr. Lazio, tried to disassociate the campaign from the ad, saying complaints should be forwarded to the leadership council.</p>
        <p>SCORECARD -- The advertisement effectively makes a link between Mr. Lazio and the man he is seeking to replace in the Senate, Mr. Moynihan. It uses Mr. Clinton, the husband of his Democratic opponent, Hillary Rodham Clinton, to further promote a moderating image of Mr. Lazio as a friend of the disabled.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, without naming Mrs. Clinton, the advertisement attempts to weave in subtle criticism of Mrs. Clinton's recent move to New York State, a theme throughout the campaigns of both Mr. Lazio and his predecessor, Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani. The ad is a clear bid for independent voters and Democrats who might not be pleased with Mrs. Clinton -- from its inclusion of Mr. Clinton to its emphasis on issues that tend to be of interest to Democratic voters.</p>
        <p>JAYSON BLAIR</p>
        <p>THE AD CAMPAIGN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
