<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE MARKETS: Market Place; S.E.C. Is Seeking to Open the Curtains on Stock-Trading Executions</title>
    <meta content="Y26PLA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217793"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Securities and Exchange Commission</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Norris, Floyd</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Market Place (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Market Place</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000726T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E2D8113AF935A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1148" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE MARKETS: Market Place; S.E.C. Is Seeking to Open the Curtains on Stock-Trading Executions</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FLOYD NORRIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Norris, Floyd</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 25</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Securities and Exchange Commission proposes rule that would force people who actually execute the trades, ranging from Nasdaq market makers to specialists on New York Stock Exchange floor, to compile and disclose statistics on how they handle each stock in which they make a market (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Many investors know to the penny how much they pay in commissions when they trade a stock, but have no idea how good an execution they get for their money.</p>
        <p>The Securities and Exchange Commission proposed a rule today that would force the people who actually execute the trades, ranging from Nasdaq market makers to specialists on the New York Stock Exchange floor, to compile and disclose statistics on how they handle each stock in which they make a market. The commission is asking for comment for 45 days, after which it will decide whether to act on the measure.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Many investors know to the penny how much they pay in commissions when they trade a stock, but have no idea how good an execution they get for their money.</p>
        <p>The Securities and Exchange Commission proposed a rule today that would force the people who actually execute the trades, ranging from Nasdaq market makers to specialists on the New York Stock Exchange floor, to compile and disclose statistics on how they handle each stock in which they make a market. The commission is asking for comment for 45 days, after which it will decide whether to act on the measure.</p>
        <p>If the rule is adopted and works as commissioners hope, it will provide answers to many questions that have bedeviled the market as competition among brokers and order-handling firms has grown. For the first time, investors who trade through either traditional or online brokers will be able to see what they are getting for their commissions in terms of the quality of trade execution.</p>
        <p>''How can it be that most investors today simply do not know what happens to their orders after they click 'submit'?'' asked Arthur Levitt, the S.E.C. chairman. ''It doesn't make sense when you recognize that missing the best price by the minimum increment available -- 1/16  -- on a 1,000-share order is worth $62.50, an amount that dwarfs the commission of most online firms.''</p>
        <p>Many of those online firms, as well as others that take orders by phone, have been able to offer low commission rates because they effectively get a part of the profit that is generated by each trade. Some do that by sending orders to markets or to market makers that pay for order flow -- or that give a penny or two a share back to the firms. Some other brokerage firms send their orders to sister companies, in a practice that is known as internalization.</p>
        <p>The statistics the S.E.C. would start requesting would make it possible to assess how quickly and at what price each market maker in each stock executed trades. They would also measure the maker's performance on different kinds of orders. The figures would probably provide information on whether market makers that pay for order flow can now do so because they generally force investors to pay higher prices than their competitors.</p>
        <p>The new information would show how often market makers are able to better prices -- that is, allow the investor to buy or sell a stock at a price better than the posted bid or asked price -- and how often investors end up doing worse.</p>
        <p>''This will provide information on the cost of trading, which I don't think most investors understand,'' said Laura S. Unger, a commission member.</p>
        <p>Robert Colby, deputy director of the S.E.C.'s division of market regulation, said he hoped the disclosures would force some market makers to improve the quality of their markets or risk losing business.</p>
        <p>Some market makers voiced support of the commission's actions,  while noting that they had not yet seen details. ''This will hold everyone's feet to the fire,'' said Bernard L. Madoff, the chairman of Bernard L. Madoff Investment Securities.</p>
        <p>Michael T. Dorsey, general counsel of Knight Trading, said that ''disclosure is the right way to go'' and that he was pleased the commission  had not moved to impose rules mandating market structure.</p>
        <p>The commission said it would study trading on Nasdaq and the New York Stock Exchange to see if further steps were needed on internalization and payment for orders.</p>
        <p>For investors, analyzing the numbers to be produced by the firms would be a daunting task, but the S.E.C. hopes that the financial press and others could make sense of them. Each market maker would be releasing about 300 numbers monthly on each stock that it traded. The figures would be posted on the market makers' Web sites.</p>
        <p>The large volume of figures stems from the many different kinds of orders. It is clearly easier to execute small orders than large ones, and market orders, to buy or sell a stock at the best price available, differ from limit orders, which call for buying or selling a stock only at a certain price. Moreover, limit orders that are close to the current market price are different from orders that are farther away. So numbers would be needed for many different permutations.</p>
        <p>Also, brokerage firms would have to tell their customers once a quarter how they decided where to send orders, and what relationships the firms had with those places. They would also have to state the rationale for choosing that market maker. The statistics would then make it possible to determine if that market maker really was making a good market.</p>
        <p>The proposed rules are one way the S.E.C. is trying to deal with issues raised by the recent proliferation of competitors, like electronic trading networks, that have fragmented the markets.</p>
        <p>Such competition can bring efficiencies, but it also risks stranding orders. One investor enters a limit order to buy a stock at $20, and another may be trying to sell it for the same amount. But if the orders are sent to different market makers, neither might be executed.</p>
        <p>The obvious way to deal with fragmentation would be to create a central limit-order book, or a ''clob,'' in Wall Street jargon. But that would effectively make all markets into one, and the S.E.C. has backed away from that proposal under heavy pressure from market officials and some members of Congress.</p>
        <p>A similar restraint by the securities commission was shown today when it dealt with the options markets, where intermarket competition has grown sharply since last fall. Those options markets now have no way to send orders from one market to another that might have better prices, and the commission has been asking them to develop linkages.</p>
        <p>The S.E.C. approved a proposal from three of the five options exchanges -- the Chicago Board Options Exchange, the American Stock Exchange and the International Securities Exchange -- for linkage that will allow unlimited transfer of customer orders but only limited ability by a market maker at one exchange to trade on another. It stopped short of requiring other exchanges to join that linkage or creating a central limit order book.</p>
        <p>Instead, the other exchanges -- the Philadelphia Stock Exchange and the Pacific Stock Exchange -- will be free to devise their own linkage plan if they want, or to join the other one. If they do neither, however, they will have to disclose to customers when an order was executed at a price that was not as good as was available in another market. Fears of having to make such disclosures are expected to propel all markets into a linkage.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
