<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Failure at Camp David</title>
    <meta content="26WED1" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217776"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Israel-International Relations-US</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Jerusalem</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arafat, Yasir</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barak, Ehud (Prime Min)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel/Jerusalem</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000726T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E4DA113AF935A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="636" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Failure at Camp David</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial calls collapse of Camp David talks wrenching setback for Israel, Palestinians and Mideast peace; lauds Israeli Prime Min Ehud Barak and Palestinian leader Yasir Arafat for seriously discussing Jerusalem and other key issues for first time and Pres Clinton for his extraordinary peace efforts; cites need for both sides to look more creatively and courageously at Jerusalem issue</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The collapse of the Camp David talks is a wrenching setback for Israel, the Palestinians and the cause of Mideast peace. Israel's prime minister, Ehud Barak, and the Palestinian leader, Yasir Arafat, came remarkably close to agreement on some of the most difficult issues of the 52-year-old conflict. But they stumbled at the most sensitive point, sovereignty over East Jerusalem. On that subject Mr. Barak found Mr. Arafat unprepared to make the kind of hard compromises needed to seal an agreement.</p>
        <p>There is now only a remote chance that a comprehensive peace settlement can be reached before the Sept. 13 deadline the two leaders have set. It will be difficult enough just to keep the Middle East conflict from flaring into renewed tensions and violence.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The collapse of the Camp David talks is a wrenching setback for Israel, the Palestinians and the cause of Mideast peace. Israel's prime minister, Ehud Barak, and the Palestinian leader, Yasir Arafat, came remarkably close to agreement on some of the most difficult issues of the 52-year-old conflict. But they stumbled at the most sensitive point, sovereignty over East Jerusalem. On that subject Mr. Barak found Mr. Arafat unprepared to make the kind of hard compromises needed to seal an agreement.</p>
        <p>There is now only a remote chance that a comprehensive peace settlement can be reached before the Sept. 13 deadline the two leaders have set. It will be difficult enough just to keep the Middle East conflict from flaring into renewed tensions and violence.</p>
        <p>Mr. Barak and Mr. Arafat deserve credit for coming to Camp David and, for the first time, seriously discussing issues like borders, refugees and Jerusalem. So does President Clinton, who committed much time and energy to the talks and made extraordinary efforts to keep the two sides engaged. Arranging the marathon meeting was a risk, but it was a chance that had to be taken.</p>
        <p>On virtually every issue, previously unthinkable compromises were discussed. But under the ground rules, none of these advances will be binding absent an overall accord. Realistically, neither leader has much chance of winning public support for painful compromises unless they are part of a deal that delivers a final peace. Nevertheless, the new understandings reached need not evaporate. They may be revived if discussions on a comprehensive agreement resume.</p>
        <p>For that to happen, both sides will have to look more creatively, and courageously, at Jerusalem. The larger burden lies with Mr. Arafat. When the talks began two weeks ago, Israel was insisting on retaining full sovereignty over East and West Jerusalem while the Palestinians demanded a full return of the East, including the Old City and its religious sites. Mr. Barak moved far from his initial position, agreeing to consider expanded Palestinian sovereignty over parts of East Jerusalem. Mr. Arafat, encouraged by Egypt and Saudi Arabia to be unyielding, showed little interest in American compromise proposals. Washington should make clear its disappointment with Cairo and Riyadh.</p>
        <p>It is not clear what happens next. Mr. Barak spoke yesterday of considering all options, even a termination of the peace effort that began with the Oslo agreement in 1993. His political situation at home is tenuous, with his cabinet reduced to a parliamentary minority. Conservative politicians argue that he has already shown too much willingness to compromise. But public opinion supports him, and he must persevere in his efforts to enhance Israeli security through a fair and defensible peace.</p>
        <p>Mr. Arafat must also consider his next moves. He should begin by resisting pressure to declare Palestinian independence, without an agreement with Israel, on Sept. 13. Such a declaration would invite new violence. Israel would probably respond by annexing areas of the West Bank that it has until now envisioned as part of an eventual Palestinian homeland.</p>
        <p>In the statement ending the Camp David talks, Mr. Barak and Mr. Arafat recognized the importance of ''avoiding unilateral actions that prejudge the outcome of negotiations.'' Proclaiming Palestinian independence would be just such a step. If there is ever to be a durable peace, Mr. Arafat must reconsider his unyielding approach to Jerusalem.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
