<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Taking Fusion Cuisine Into New Territory</title>
    <meta content="26REST$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217712"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="RESTAURANTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Az (NYC Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Grimes, William</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Columns/Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000726T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E0D9103AF935A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1056" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Taking Fusion Cuisine Into New Territory</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By William Grimes</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Grimes, William</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William Grimes reviews AZ, Manhattan restaurant; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EARLY in its young life, AZ was supposed to be pronounced Ah-ZEE, yielding Asie, which is French for Asia. Plans changed. AZ is now pronounced like the first and last letters of the English alphabet, a shrewd move, for two reasons. Diners who try to pronounce the letters as a word could easily come up with Oz or As. And how many who don't would figure out the French wordplay?</p>
        <p>A second, even better reason for sticking with the English letters is truth in advertising. There is a lot of Asie in AZ, but A to Z more accurately reflects the range of influences that Patricia Yeo, the executive chef, brings to her highly inventive, extroverted and wildly successful brand of fusion cooking. You get the general idea early on in the meal, when a waiter approaches bearing a Japanese-style white ceramic plate with three condiments to accompany three international breads. The rotation changes, but the three might include an Indian raita, Italian-style white beans with pesto or a sweetly fiery Mexican chili sauce.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EARLY in its young life, AZ was supposed to be pronounced Ah-ZEE, yielding Asie, which is French for Asia. Plans changed. AZ is now pronounced like the first and last letters of the English alphabet, a shrewd move, for two reasons. Diners who try to pronounce the letters as a word could easily come up with Oz or As. And how many who don't would figure out the French wordplay?</p>
        <p>A second, even better reason for sticking with the English letters is truth in advertising. There is a lot of Asie in AZ, but A to Z more accurately reflects the range of influences that Patricia Yeo, the executive chef, brings to her highly inventive, extroverted and wildly successful brand of fusion cooking. You get the general idea early on in the meal, when a waiter approaches bearing a Japanese-style white ceramic plate with three condiments to accompany three international breads. The rotation changes, but the three might include an Indian raita, Italian-style white beans with pesto or a sweetly fiery Mexican chili sauce.</p>
        <p>Ms. Yeo (pronounced Yo) spent her formative years cooking with Bobby Flay at Miracle Grill, Mesa Grill and Bolo, with two midcareer detours to San Francisco, where she worked at the celebrated China Moon with Barbara Tropp and opened Hawthorne Lane, a California-Asian restaurant. AZ is her big break, and she is obviously grabbing for it with both hands. In dish after dish, she shows a rare combination of audacity and refinement, sustained with admirable consistency over the entire menu.</p>
        <p>It takes nerve to come up with duck schnitzel. The dish sounds like a joke. The laughter stops after one bite, when the rich duck meat, wrapped in a paper-thin crunchy layer of breading, makes contact with brown butter, specks of hazelnut and a well-judged intervention of sweet and bitter flavors provided by sliced golden beets. If Austria can meet Asia halfway, then why not America? Congee, the East's traditional meal in a bowl, takes on a chowderish character with the addition of shredded peekytoe crab and fresh corn. Oxtail may not seem like the logical partner for tuna, but Ms. Yeo makes it work, brilliantly, marinating the meat in a liquid flavored with black beans, ginger, garlic and orange zest and then braising it in sake and veal stock. The interplay between the braising spices and a lightly applied coriander crust on the tuna is one of the great flavor adventures on the menu.</p>
        <p>Ms. Yeo works wonders with Asian teas. Chicken smoked in Lapsang souchong leaves absorbs the dusky perfume of the tea, which is nicely offset by a scallion pancake and a thick fig chutney. Prunes macerated in Armagnac make a classic French pairing for a double-cut pork chop, but the prunes pick up herbal complexity from steeping in oolong tea as well as the brandy. As often happens on the menu at AZ, one ingenious twist pays big dividends. It happens again with hefty gulf prawns, simply seared on the grill but paired with won-ton wrappers filled with sweet, creamy soybean paste and surrounded by a sharp tomato broth.</p>
        <p>There are times when execution does not quite keep pace with invention. Striped bass on a hash of lobster, fennel and potato needed more voltage from its sweet red chili sauce, and the lobster was fairly flavorless. Salmon baked in parchment with sweet and tart gooseberries never quite synthesized with the authority of, say, halibut bathed in a light soy-ginger sauce and accented with slivers of shiitake mushroom and bits of Chinese sausage. In other words, some dishes are merely good.</p>
        <p>The dessert menu, created by Heather Miller, feels a little quiet after the snap, crackle and pop of the appetizers and main courses, and it fails to interweave Asian flavors with much conviction or subtlety. Two non-Asian desserts make the strongest impression, a fig tarte Tatin with fromage blanc ice cream, and a small coconut financier, almost a cross between cake and macaroon, topped with a ball of very rich vanilla ice cream and sweetened just a bit with chips of buttery macadamia brittle.</p>
        <p>AZ is gorgeous, an improbable but enchanting blend of strict Asian geometry, Western Art Nouveau and turn-of-the century Viennese craft influences. The decor, in other words, matches the menu. The sultry bar and lounge on the ground floor has already begun to attract the young and the beautiful. But the lucky ones step into the silver steel elevator and head for the third-floor dining room, a double eyeful designed by Grant Koerner of Untitled Inc.</p>
        <p>Tilted glass panels open up to the sky in clear weather, and a thin sheet of water flows down a stone slab near the entrance. A flagstone floor and exposed brick walls cool the room, but the color scheme is warm and opulent, with earth-tone tables and place mats offset by deep-blue velvet upholstery and Chinese lanterns that glitter with a ruby light.</p>
        <p>It's a room to dream in, and a threat to steal the show. When the food arrives, however, the stargazing stops. After that, Ms. Yeo holds center stage.</p>
        <p>AZ  *** [Rating: Three Stars]  21 West 17th Street; (212) 691-8888.</p>
        <p>ATMOSPHERE: Boldly international fusion cooking in a richly Asian decor.  SOUND LEVEL: Quiet enough to converse easily.  RECOMMENDED DISHES: Crab and corn congee, tea-smoked chicken with scallion pancake, duck schnitzel, halibut in soy-ginger sauce, pork chop with prunes, coconut financier, fig tarte Tatin.  SERVICE: Earnest, obliging and reasonably efficient.  WINE LIST: A far-ranging, very original list of about 350 wines, with nearly 60 half bottles and 24 wines by the glass.  PRICE RANGE: Dinner, three-course prix fixe, $52; six-course tasting menu, $75.  HOURS: Dinner, Sunday through Wednesday, 5:30 to 11 p.m.; Thursday through Saturday, to 11:30. Lunch service begins Aug. 7.  CREDIT CARDS: All major cards.  WHEELCHAIR ACCESS: Elevator to dining room, where restrooms are accessible.</p>
        <p>WHAT THE STARS MEAN:</p>
        <p>(None) Poor to satisfactory  * Good  ** Very good  *** Excellent  **** Extraordinary</p>
        <p>Ratings reflect the reviewer's reaction to food, ambience and service, with price taken into consideration. Menu listings and prices are subject to change.</p>
        <p>Past restaurant reviews from The New York Times, with additional capsule reviews by Times critics, are available on New York Today: www.nytoday.com</p>
        <p>RESTAURANTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
