<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>State Faults Coney Island Hospital, Citing Case of Woman Who Said She Was Raped</title>
    <meta content="26CONE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217796"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fines (Penalties)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hospitals</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Coney Island Hospital (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chivers, C J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Hospitals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hospitals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fines (Penalties)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000726T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E1D8113AF935A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1050" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>State Faults Coney Island Hospital, Citing Case of Woman Who Said She Was Raped</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By C. J. CHIVERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chivers, C J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York State Department of Health cites Coney Island Hospital for 23 health violations and orders it to hire consultant to improve its emergency room care; hospital is also fined $46,000 and placed on probation for year; action comes after woman allegedly was mistreated for rape (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The New York State Department of Health cited Coney Island Hospital yesterday for 23 health violations and ordered it to hire a consultant to improve its emergency room care, saying the staff provided insufficient treatment last summer to a woman who said she had been beaten and raped under the Boardwalk.</p>
        <p>The department also fined the hospital $46,000 and placed it on probation for one year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The New York State Department of Health cited Coney Island Hospital yesterday for 23 health violations and ordered it to hire a consultant to improve its emergency room care, saying the staff provided insufficient treatment last summer to a woman who said she had been beaten and raped under the Boardwalk.</p>
        <p>The department also fined the hospital $46,000 and placed it on probation for one year.</p>
        <p>It was the fourth time this year that the state's health commissioner, Dr. Antonia C. Novello, sharply criticized a New York City hospital and issued a large fine.</p>
        <p>The investigation examined the hospital's treatment of a 31-year-old woman who was attacked last July by Anthony Jones, a serial sex offender who had been released the night before from the Great Meadow Correctional Facility. He placed the woman in a chokehold and dragged her under the Boardwalk; she told the police that she had been raped and that her life had been threatened  until she broke free and ran onto Surf Avenue. The authorities took her to Coney Island Hospital for treatment and a rape exam.</p>
        <p>The New York Times reported in May that the hospital had failed to send critical pieces of forensic evidence from the victim's rape examination -- including the woman's underwear and swabs from her genital area -- to the city medical examiner's office, where officials try to isolate attackers' DNA in rape cases.  Without the evidence, prosecutors had to withdraw their rape charge against Mr. Jones, who pleaded guilty to attempted assault and was sentenced to two to four years in prison.</p>
        <p>Mr. Jones, 42, who has spent much of his adult life in prison for sex attacks in New York and Arizona, had faced a possible life sentence if convicted of rape.</p>
        <p>The state's investigation found a series of problems in the victim's treatment, from an exam by a resident that was deemed cursory to a failure to ensure that the victim received adequate screening for sexually transmitted diseases and complete medication to prevent pregnancy. Although the woman's case was classified as urgent, she was not fully examined for more than three hours, the state said in its conclusions, which were submitted to the hospital yesterday. The mistakes continued until the victim's last moment at the hospital, the state found, and included an incomplete evaluation by a social worker, who apparently did not offer the victim, a homeless prostitute and heroin addict, referrals for substance abuse treatment or shelter, the state found.</p>
        <p>''There were multiple problems that occurred in the care of this individual,'' said Wayne M. Osten, director of the state's Office of Health System Management, which investigated the case. Dr. Jane D. Zimmerman, spokeswoman for the city's Health and Hospitals Corporation, which supervises Coney Island Hospital and 10 other public hospitals, said the investigation had gone too far. The hospital's emergency room, she said, handled 46,000 visits last year, including more than 100 rape and sexual assault cases. ''This is the first and only time the contents of a rape kit have been questioned,'' she said. ''This is an extreme overreaction by the State Department of Health. It is overkill of enormous proportion.''</p>
        <p>What exactly happened to the missing evidence is still not clear.  Dr. Zimmerman said the resident who performed the exam told investigators that she had done it completely.</p>
        <p>Dr. Zimmerman also said that the fallout of the case had reverberated through the hospital, to the extent that the State Hospital Review and Planning Council was holding up the corporation's effort to get approval on a $105 million renovation.</p>
        <p>Dr. Novello, the health commissioner, said she was particularly angered about the case because it involved a homeless victim; she suggested that medical care and compassion was denied the woman because of her station in life. Rape victims, she said, should be treated the same, ''irrespective of whether the victim was homeless or the richest woman in New York State.''</p>
        <p>The investigation's list of deficiencies was unsparing, criticizing the hospital from its nursing staff and social workers to its highest level of management.</p>
        <p>The state ordered the hospital to submit a plan within 10 days describing how it would correct each of the 23 violations. The state also ordered the hospital to hire an independent consultant to analyze the operation and management of the emergency department, and to submit recommendations for improvement within 90 days. The hospital has 10 days to decide if it wants to contest the findings. Dr. Zimmerman said the corporation had not yet decided how to proceed.</p>
        <p>Katherine N. Lapp, the state's director of criminal justice, applauded the state's findings yesterday.</p>
        <p>''We need to send them a message, and that's what the commissioner of health is doing,'' Ms. Lapp said.  ''This is sending a message to this hospital, and to every hospital in the state, that when a woman presents herself as a victim of a sex crime, she receives an immediate and thorough check-up, and a proper rape kit examination,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The sanction was the fourth  against a hospital in the city this year. In February, the health department fined Beth Israel Medical Center after an obstetrician carved his initials into a woman's abdomen. In March, it fined Maimonides Medical Center for covering up an operation in which a surgeon removed a patient's healthy kidney. Also that month, it fined Staten Island Hospital for failing to monitor and discipline its chief of neurosurgery, who, the department said, operated on the wrong side of two patients' brains.</p>
        <p>Dr. Zimmerman said the mistakes at Coney Island Hospital were not of the same magnitude. ''This particular incident does not even rise to the threshold of a reportable event,'' she said. ''The state is treating this as if it were an egregious medical error, which it is not.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
