<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Squirt! Splat! Gone!</title>
    <meta content="26NOTE$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217730"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Grimes, William</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000726T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE7D6103AF935A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="925" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Squirt! Splat! Gone!</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By William Grimes</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Grimes, William</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William Grimes Critic's Notebook column reports that chefs have given up on using squeeze bottles with brightly colored sauces to paint and embellish dinner plates; drawing; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SOME things you don't notice until they're gone. The painted plate is one of them. It was not too many years ago that no plate left a New York kitchen until, like a subway car parked overnight in a rail yard, it had been decorated in drips, dots, dabs and hash marks.</p>
        <p>Plastic squeeze bottles in hand, Manhattan's chefs rebelled at the sight of white. Every square inch of blank, shiny china beckoned like a freshly stretched canvas, begging for a Jackson Pollock makeover.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SOME things you don't notice until they're gone. The painted plate is one of them. It was not too many years ago that no plate left a New York kitchen until, like a subway car parked overnight in a rail yard, it had been decorated in drips, dots, dabs and hash marks.</p>
        <p>Plastic squeeze bottles in hand, Manhattan's chefs rebelled at the sight of white. Every square inch of blank, shiny china beckoned like a freshly stretched canvas, begging for a Jackson Pollock makeover.</p>
        <p>Now, white is making a comeback.</p>
        <p>The squeeze bottles are still around, but now, more often than not, they serve a purely utilitarian function. They're great for storing sauces, vinaigrettes, oils and vinegars. They come in handy when a chef needs to direct a precise squirt of flavoring. And pastry chefs are never going to release their grip. The squeeze bottle is simply too efficient a writing instrument when it's time to put a sweet signature on dessert. But the great fiesta of finger painting, like the era of tall food, seems to be over.</p>
        <p>Its history is obscure, but it's always safe to blame anything on nouvelle cuisine. When chefs began developing brightly colored sauces based on previously unimaginable ingredients, it became tempting to lay down a perfect puddle of vermilion, or Kelly green, on the discus-size plates that nouvelle favored. With a new, broader palette, the door was open for a technological breakthrough in applying the new colors.</p>
        <p>No one knows for certain who first hit on the idea of the squeeze bottle, but Jean-Jacques Rachou, the owner of La Cote Basque, is happy to put himself forward as a candidate. ''I invented it in 1975 or 1976, when we were starting to use the lighter sauces,'' he said. Inspiration came after he made a beurre blanc with saffron. The writing was on the wall. And then, almost instantly, on the plate.</p>
        <p>Rick Moonen, now the executive chef at Oceana, said: ''I was commissioned to buy the bottles. I'd go to the hair-dye section of the drugstore and buy dozens of the tint and tone bottles.''</p>
        <p>In time, the painted plate appeared everywhere.</p>
        <p>''From the early- to mid-90's, people were just going crazy with it,'' said Bobby Flay, a chef who painted with the best of them not so many years ago, smitten after seeing his first squeeze bottle in use at Cafe Annie in Houston about 13 years ago.</p>
        <p>As a piece of technology, it could not be beat. Previously, Mr. Flay and his assistants stored their liquids in wine bottles and, positioning a thumb over the mouth of the bottle, directed a more or less steady stream of liquid over the plate. The squeeze bottle brought instant precision to an imprecise art.</p>
        <p>''When I first discovered it, I was definitely taken by it,'' Mr. Flay said. ''It was like a new toy.'' Gradually, he worked through his obsession. He uses the bottles, but not to decorate. ''When I see sauces on a plate, it drives me nuts,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The squeeze bottle lent itself to the vibrant colors of Nuevo Latino and Southwestern cuisine, and to the precious ''small food, big plate'' format favored by the newer restaurants. Colors and designs that had been limited to the dessert menu suddenly invaded the world of appetizers and main courses.</p>
        <p>Then, inevitably, the backlash came. Douglas Rodriguez, of Chicama, well remembers his personal epiphany. ''I overheard a chef referring to 'squirt-bottle cuisine,' '' he said. ''I've kept away from it ever since.''</p>
        <p>Other chefs have stuck with the squeeze bottle but adopted a more chaste approach. Andrew DiCataldo, the executive chef at Patria, likes to circle the plate with dots of diminishing size. ''We use them for herb oils when we really want to control the amount of oil or sauce on the plate,'' he said. ''It gives you the essence of the flavor and not a big, greasy slick.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Moonen still likes to brighten the plate with a dot or a blob, but not with the sauces that he used back in the days of La Cote Basque. He sticks to oils, or thickened pepper juices.</p>
        <p>Of course, color thrown out the door can come in through the window. Mr. Rodriguez likes to add a touch of brightness with microgreens, and a lot of chefs seem to be discovering the eye-pleasing pleasures of brightly colored vegetables, which can be sliced as fine as thread, deep fried and then piled in a glorious, tousled toupee atop a main course.</p>
        <p>One alternative to liquid color is dry pigment, like a dusting of cayenne pepper sprinkled with bits of chive or bell pepper. Another is liquid whipped into a decorative froth.</p>
        <p>The squeeze bottle, meanwhile, seems to be wandering the devolutionary road followed by all trends, which make their way to the other boroughs and farther afield, eventually arriving at destinations like Toledo and Indianapolis. By that time, New York may be ripe for a revisionist school.</p>
        <p>In the meantime, there's always foam. We just need someone to figure out how to get it into a spray gun.</p>
        <p>CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
