<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Doctors Assert Cheney Leads Vigorous Life, Despite Ills</title>
    <meta content="Y26HEA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217805"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE MEDICAL FACTOR"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vice Presidents and Vice Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Altman, Lawrence K</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cheney, Richard B</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vice Presidents and Vice Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000726T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E2D7113AF935A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="809" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Doctors Assert Cheney Leads Vigorous Life, Despite Ills</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAWRENCE K. ALTMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Altman, Lawrence K</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dick Cheney's doctors say Gov George W Bush's designated running mate is in excellent health and takes many drugs for heart disease and other medical conditions (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dick Cheney, Gov. George W. Bush's newly announced running mate, is in excellent health and takes many drugs for heart disease and other medical conditions, his doctors said yesterday.</p>
        <p>''He is up to the task of the most sensitive public office,'' Mr. Cheney's personal physician, Dr. Gary Malakoff, said in a letter dated July 22 and released by the Bush campaign yesterday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Dick Cheney, Gov. George W. Bush's newly announced running mate, is in excellent health and takes many drugs for heart disease and other medical conditions, his doctors said yesterday.</p>
        <p>''He is up to the task of the most sensitive public office,'' Mr. Cheney's personal physician, Dr. Gary Malakoff, said in a letter dated July 22 and released by the Bush campaign yesterday.</p>
        <p>Dr. Malakoff and Dr. Jonathan S. Reiner, Mr. Cheney's cardiologist, said they monitored Mr. Cheney, a former secretary of defense, closely for ''a long list of medications'' that he takes for heart disease, gout and metabolic disorders.</p>
        <p>''He has shown no side effects of any of these medications which would alter intellectual performance or impair his judgment,'' Dr. Malakoff said.</p>
        <p>The doctors, who practice at George Washington University Medical Center in Washington where Mr. Cheney has received care since 1985, did not say what drugs he takes. And they provided few specifics about test results, test dates or the types of conditions affecting Mr. Cheney.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cheney has had several minor episodes of gout in his feet and receives drug treatment to prevent additional attacks and to lower the amount of uric acid in his blood. He has suffered a potentially fatal allergic reaction, known as anaphylaxis, from pomegranates and has been treated for skin cancer. The doctors did not say whether the skin cancer was a common, generally harmless type known as basal cell or a potentially fatal type known as melanoma.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cheney has suffered three heart attacks, but none since he underwent quadruple coronary bypass surgery in 1988. Since the operation, Mr. Cheney has had no symptoms of heart disease. He leads a ''vigorous lifestyle,'' traveling extensively for work, exercising on a treadmill for 30 minutes several days a week, hunting and engaging in other strenuous recreational activities, Dr. Reiner said in a separate letter dated July 24.</p>
        <p>Heart attacks destroy muscle cells that cannot be replaced. The amount of heart function lost after an attack, or a series of attacks, depends in part on how much heart muscle has been destroyed.</p>
        <p>In providing new medical details concerning Mr. Cheney's heart condition, the doctors said the three heart attacks had left Mr. Cheney with an unspecified amount of dysfunction of the heart's main pumping chamber, the left ventricle. The dysfunction was detected by an ultrasound test known as an echocardiogram and the affected regions of heart muscle correlated with the areas on the bottom of the heart that were damaged by the heart attacks, Dr. Reiner said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cheney's ''heart disease is optimally treated with medication,'' Dr. Malakoff said. He said Mr. Cheney had long had an elevated level of blood cholesterol that ''has been vigorously and successfully treated with medication.'' The doctors did not provide Mr. Cheney's cholesterol count or tests of other fatty substances.</p>
        <p>Monitoring examinations like nuclear stress tests that are standard for individuals with heart disease ''have been stable and unchanged for the past several years'' in Mr. Cheney's case, Dr. Reiner said.</p>
        <p>However, the doctors did not provide a crucial number known as the ejection fraction. It indicates the proportion of blood in the main chamber that is pumped to the body with each heartbeat and is a principal way doctors monitor patients with heart disease.</p>
        <p>The type of heart disease affecting Mr. Cheney is known as coronary artery disease and it takes its name from the buildup of fatty substances, or plaques, in the coronary arteries that block blood flow through them.</p>
        <p>Surgeons perform bypass operations to help prevent future heart attacks. In the operation, arteries and veins are taken from elsewhere in the body and grafted to coronary arteries to provide channels around the blockages. But over time new blockages can develop in the grafted blood vessels, particularly veins. No specific information was provided about the state of Mr. Cheney's four grafts.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cheney suffered his first heart attack at age 37 in 1978 when he was running for Congress from Wyoming. At that time, he had moderate coronary artery disease for which he received drug therapy for several years, Dr. Reiner said. He also stopped smoking. But in 1984, Mr. Cheney suffered a second heart attack. The third came in 1988.</p>
        <p>Coronary artery disease often progresses despite bypass surgery and drug treatment. A cardiac catheterization in 1988 showed that the coronary artery disease had progressed over the preceding decade, a factor that led to the bypass surgery.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE MEDICAL FACTOR</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
