<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mama Is a Bounty Hunter, Just Making an Honest Living</title>
    <meta content="26WERT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217733"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Usa Cable Network</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wertheimer, Ron</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Huntress, The (TV Program)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Cover Me (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000726T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE5D6103AF935A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="915" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mama Is a Bounty Hunter, Just Making an Honest Living</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RON WERTHEIMER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wertheimer, Ron</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ron Wertheimer reviews two USA cable network dramas, The Huntress and Cover Me; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Look, it's another vulnerable single woman with a heart of gold, just trying to find her way along life's rocky road, which is strewn with all the wrong men. But Dottie Thorson stands out from the pack. She drinks, smokes, cusses and uses her 19-year-old daughter and large firearms as accessories in her work. Dottie is a bounty hunter, making ends meet by hauling in miscreants who have jumped bail.</p>
        <p>That's the premise of ''The Huntress,'' a  series USA is unveiling tonight. Played straight, it would surely be tiresome. But presented as an off-kilter spoof, and draped around a winningly drawn central character, the premise has promise.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Look, it's another vulnerable single woman with a heart of gold, just trying to find her way along life's rocky road, which is strewn with all the wrong men. But Dottie Thorson stands out from the pack. She drinks, smokes, cusses and uses her 19-year-old daughter and large firearms as accessories in her work. Dottie is a bounty hunter, making ends meet by hauling in miscreants who have jumped bail.</p>
        <p>That's the premise of ''The Huntress,'' a  series USA is unveiling tonight. Played straight, it would surely be tiresome. But presented as an off-kilter spoof, and draped around a winningly drawn central character, the premise has promise.</p>
        <p>As portrayed with slightly nutsy, dewy-eyed enthusiasm by Annette O'Toole, Dottie is someone you know you'll never meet. But that doesn't stop you from wishing that you could.</p>
        <p>Just to make things complicated, there really is a bounty hunter named Dottie Thorson, who was the inspiration for a television movie, shown on USA in March, that also starred Ms. O'Toole. Ms. Thorson, you're told, took up bounty hunting, the occupation of her husband, Ralph, after he was killed by a car bomb. And despite such occupational hazards, she brought her daughter, Brandi, into the family business. Thus the voice-over line that opens the series: ''Only the unbelievable parts are true.'' True? Well, who cares?</p>
        <p>When first glimpsed, Brandi (Jordana Spiro) is standing on a street corner in the flimsiest of tiny frocks, winking at passing cars. An S.U.V. stops, she climbs in and throws a pair of handcuffs on the driver, announcing that she knows he's a fugitive. Mom shows up in an instant, holding a rifle to the guy's head, and Brandi socks him.</p>
        <p>''If you get blood on that dress, I'm gonna kill you,'' wails Dottie. Brandi whines back, ''Chill out, Mom, O.K.?''</p>
        <p>Luis Antonio Ramos plays Ricky Guzman, the bail bondsman who reluctantly hires the Thorsons. Ricky's business is a mess. His office is overflowing with the appliances and other large objects his long-gone clients left as collateral. ''I make half my money these days on eBay,'' he says.</p>
        <p>Then there's Tiny Bellows (James Remar). Dottie brought him in, but he captured her heart. When her daughter describes Tiny as ''the baddest killer psycho biker in the state,'' Dottie coos: ''He's not a psycho, Brandi. Yes, he's made some bad lifestyle choices.''</p>
        <p>Now, thanks to Dottie, Tiny's in prison, where she visits him for heart-to-heart chats. When he assures her that she is a natural bounty hunter, she's so thrilled she giggles. ''It's like finding out you're naturally talented in karaoke or something,'' she says, beaming.</p>
        <p>On another visit she confesses her lack of confidence about finding her prey. ''I feel like I'm chasing a ghost,'' she says.</p>
        <p>He replies dreamily, ''You are.''</p>
        <p>That ghost is Ralph, whose wife and daughter are still pretty angry over his neglect. As they try to deal with their feelings, the show threatens to turn maudlin. Big mistake. Even a little more of that would turn this loopy soap bubble into mere soap opera.</p>
        <p>Fortunately there's little time for feelings in tonight's episode, written by the series's executive producer, Pamela Norris, and directed by Jeffrey Reiner. Mother and daughter race another bounty hunter to capture yet another bounty hunter who has gotten himself into more than the usual trouble.</p>
        <p>Dottie and Brandi catch up with their quarry (Gary Busey, who fits right into the antic spirit of the enterprise) at a car wash, where Brandi chases him through suds and spray.</p>
        <p>''What's that smell?'' asks Dottie, once they get back in the car.</p>
        <p>Brandi replies: ''That would be me. Got the optional air freshener applied.''</p>
        <p>That kid's smart mouth does get annoying after a while. Good thing her mom is such a charmer.</p>
        <p>THE HUNTRESS  USA, tonight at 10</p>
        <p>A USA Cable Entertainment production. Pamela Norris, writer and executive producer; Jeffrey Reiner, director; Scott White, producer; Bruno Heller, consulting producer.</p>
        <p>WITH: Annette O'Toole (Dottie Thorson), Jordana Spiro (Brandi Thorson), James Remar (Tiny Bellows), Luis Antonio Ramos (Ricky Guzman) and Gary Busey (Tommy Van Slyke).</p>
        <p>COVER ME  USA, tonight at 9</p>
        <p>Just before ''The Huntress'' on Wednesdays, USA is offering new episodes of another familial adventure, ''Cover Me.'' This is the story of Danny Arno (Peter Dobson), an undercover F.B.I. agent who shares his work and peril with his wife and three teenage children. Despite that obvious similarity, these two shows are far apart in approach. ''Cover Me'' is far more slick, for good and ill. Its production has the sheen of the best television productions, but you may feel that you've been down this road a few times too many.</p>
        <p>Tonight's episode puts the family in danger as a onetime pornographer gets out of prison vowing vengeance upon Danny and the mysterious femme fatale who helped Danny get the goods on the guy years before. There is a nifty plot twist, but you may well guess the secret long before the bad guy does.</p>
        <p>Melora Hardin, as Danny's wife, Barbara, and Cameron Richardson, Antoinette Picatto and Michael Angarano, as the children, make a sensitive, picture-perfect family. The suspense tonight is supposed to come from your fears that at least two family members may be killed by that bad guy. On the first night of a new season? You think so?</p>
        <p>TELEVISION REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
