<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Success of City School Pupils Isn't Simply a Money Matter</title>
    <meta content="14SCHO$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207334"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Textbooks</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wyatt, Edward</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7DE133EF937A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2572" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Success of City School Pupils Isn't Simply a Money Matter</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWARD WYATT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wyatt, Edward</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Analysis of how New York City's 32 community school districts allocate funds finds sharp disparities in spending choices; suggests money spent on aides and administrators does less to improve student achievement than money spent on books, teacher training and other instructional categories; finds districts with highest-performing students got least money per pupil and had most crowded classes; tables and graphs of spending by top, average and bottom districts; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For years, New York City educators have assailed the state's school financing system as unfair, saying it provides the city with nearly $2,000 less per student than areas upstate and in the suburbs. More money, they say, will help improve the education of the city's 1.1 million students.</p>
        <p>To get better teachers and solve other problems, Schools Chancellor Harold O. Levy said at a recent education forum at City Hall: ''You do it the old-fashioned way. It's money. Money.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For years, New York City educators have assailed the state's school financing system as unfair, saying it provides the city with nearly $2,000 less per student than areas upstate and in the suburbs. More money, they say, will help improve the education of the city's 1.1 million students.</p>
        <p>To get better teachers and solve other problems, Schools Chancellor Harold O. Levy said at a recent education forum at City Hall: ''You do it the old-fashioned way. It's money. Money.''</p>
        <p>But even as the school system seeks more money and supports a lawsuit to overturn the state's method of allocating education dollars, it has already been spending more -- 30 percent more over the last three years, or $10.7 billion in the current school year, while enrollment has risen only 2 percent. Nearly half of this new money has been spent on school aides, administration and student support services -- areas that seem to have less to do with improved academic performance than, say, teacher training.</p>
        <p>A New York Times analysis of how the city's 32 community school districts have allocated money in the last four years shows sharp disparities in the districts' spending choices. And it suggests that money spent on aides and administrators does less to improve student achievement than money spent on books, teacher training and other instructional categories.</p>
        <p>The analysis contradicts two common assumptions about educational disparities. It found that the districts with the highest-performing students received the least amount of money per pupil. They also have the most crowded classrooms.</p>
        <p>''It is the proper use of resources that plays the key role in outcomes,'' said Neil F. Kreinik, the superintendent of District 28, which spans Forest Hills and Jamaica in Queens. Mr. Kreinik said that meant taking money that one year goes to buy books and computer software and using it the next year for teacher development. His district ranks 29th in total spending, at about $8,000 per student, and in the top 10 in reading and mathematics test scores.</p>
        <p>In District 32 in Bushwick, Brooklyn, which ranks 10th in total spending, at $8,900 per student, 10 cents of every dollar goes to pay for school aides and other jobs that historically have been used as sources of patronage for school board members and local politicians. By contrast, District 2, which embraces Lower Manhattan and the Upper East Side, ranks 23rd in total spending. It lays out about 45 percent less than District 32 on aides and similar jobs, and 40 percent more on teacher training.</p>
        <p>District 2, it turns out, is one of the city's best-performing, while the Bushwick district's test scores are generally in the bottom half of city rankings.</p>
        <p>Poor districts contend that they have to hire more school aides because they cannot attract or keep the most experienced teachers and so have to supplement the classrooms of inexperienced teachers with paraprofessionals, who serve as classroom assistants, and other aides. Many of the highest-performing districts, meanwhile, operate above their official student capacity, in part because families move into districts whose schools have good reputations. Seven of the city's 10 most crowded districts rank in the top half of all districts on standardized test scores.</p>
        <p>Across the city, the school districts that rank highest academically have, in most cases, the smallest per-student budgets. That apparent paradox results in part from federal and state programs that funnel money to districts that are in very poor neighborhoods and that have students in need of extra academic help. The result, however, is that the system appears to reward a district's continued poor performance with more dollars.</p>
        <p>In District 1 on the Lower East Side of Manhattan, for example, public schools are seemingly awash in money, spending more than $11,000 a student, 25 percent more than the citywide average. Yet their results on reading and math tests are no better than those in District 29 in southeastern Queens, which spends only $7,600 a student, the lowest in the city.</p>
        <p>While most of a district's budget goes to fixed costs like school lunches, maintenance and teacher salaries, district superintendents say they exercise broad leeway over as much as one-quarter of their budgets.</p>
        <p>Even a reform-minded chancellor like Mr. Levy acknowledges that the board has not done everything it can to keep tabs on its free-flowing dollars.</p>
        <p>''One criticism I'd make as a general observation is the place is run a little bit like a mom-and-pop store,'' Mr. Levy said recently in an address at New York University's School of Education. ''There is no internal audit worth speaking about.''</p>
        <p>The Times examined spending on all students in elementary and middle schools, who account for nearly two-thirds of the city's pupils and education dollars. It also looked specifically at general education students in those schools, eliminating money going to special education students, who enjoy the benefit of two to three times as much money per capita. In each analysis, the same spending patterns held among districts.</p>
        <p>Clearly, not all of the discretionary spending in low-performing districts is wasted money. But education experts say it is easy to spot areas of questionable spending -- among them, job categories that traditionally have been associated with political patronage.</p>
        <p>District 32 in Bushwick ranks first in the city in spending on categories traditionally associated with patronage -- paraprofessionals, school aides and assistant principals. Last year, 10 percent of the district's total spending, or roughly $884 a student, went to pay for those categories of employees.</p>
        <p>By contrast, District 2, the high-performing Manhattan district, spends 6 percent of its total budget, or $491 a student, on those jobs.</p>
        <p>Felix R. Vazquez, the superintendent of District 32, said the district's relatively high spending on aides stemmed from its difficulty in recruiting experienced teachers and from its higher-than-average population of students whose primary language was not English.</p>
        <p>Those are common problems among overwhelmingly poor and minority districts like 32, where two-thirds of the students are Hispanic and nearly one-third are black, and 95 percent qualify for free or reduced-price lunch programs.</p>
        <p>Unable to find enough experienced teachers, the district supplements its staff with classroom paraprofessionals and aides, Mr. Vazquez said. He added that he thought it was unfair to compare his district with those in wealthier neighborhoods. To its credit, District 32 also ranks fourth in the city in total spending on teacher training.</p>
        <p>To be sure, it is unlikely that most of the classroom paraprofessionals, assistant principals, secretaries and school aides in the district got their jobs through patronage. The ability of school boards to use jobs for political purposes has lessened somewhat since 1996, when the Legislature, in response to previous patronage scandals, granted greater power to district superintendents over personnel appointments in their districts.</p>
        <p>But there is a close correspondence between a district's spending on school aides and its relative ranking in standardized test scores in the three years since the Legislature changed the school governance laws.</p>
        <p>Seven of the 10 districts with the most money going for jobs traditionally associated with patronage rank in the bottom half of all districts on test scores. In addition to District 32, those include Districts 17 in Crown Heights in Brooklyn, 10 in the northern Bronx and 4 in East Harlem.</p>
        <p>Correspondingly, districts that spend relatively little on patronage positions rank high on standardized tests, among them Districts 2 and 26 in Queens, and 31 on Staten Island.</p>
        <p>It is difficult to tell what spending decisions have a positive impact on educational achievement because correlations are often skewed by programs that route more dollars to lower-performing districts. But several district superintendents said they had garnered positive academic results from spending on books and professional development.</p>
        <p>District 19 in East New York, Brooklyn, is one impoverished district with a history of low reading scores where book expenditures may have started to make a difference. Over the last three years, the district has spent an average of $111 a student per year on textbooks and library books, the city's highest rate and 50 percent more than the citywide average of $74 per student.</p>
        <p>Joan E. Mahon-Powell, the acting superintendent of District 19, said much of the spending had gone to stocking classroom libraries, collections of 200 to 300 books in each classroom that are available to students to supplement their lessons. Getting books into children's hands -- a continuing problem in many districts -- has made a big difference in how the students react to reading exercises, she said.</p>
        <p>''When children can talk to you about reading and writing, you know you're moving in the right direction,'' Ms. Mahon-Powell said. She acknowledged, however, that the district, which still ranks near the bottom in reading scores, had far to go. ''Are our scores zooming through the roof?'' she said. ''No, they are not. But we do know that they will.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kreinik of District 28 in Queens says he, too, has emphasized spending on books and classroom libraries as well as software and other classroom supplies that do not show up on the book budget line. That money, he said, has definitely helped to improve the district's test scores.</p>
        <p>District 2 in Manhattan takes a different approach, spending every dollar it can scrape together on teacher training.</p>
        <p>''In order to get good performance from your kids, you have to get good performance from your teachers,'' said Elaine Fink, the district superintendent. ''The education field does not stand still. The only way to get to the point where you reach the highest achievement levels for all students is for teachers to study together and learn together.''</p>
        <p>District 2's student population has some characteristics that historically have proved to be highly correlated with educational achievement: only about half of its students qualify for free or reduced-price federal lunch programs, based on income, compared with three-quarters  across the city. Of District 2's students, 32 percent are white, twice the citywide average, and 33 percent are black or Hispanic, in contrast to nearly three-quarters citywide.</p>
        <p>But officials in District 2 say that as important as those factors is teacher training, on which it spends about 9 percent, or $416 a student, of its classroom expenditures. The four districts with the next highest level of spending on curriculum and professional development each spent about 6 percent of their classroom budgets.</p>
        <p>Over the last decade, District 2's emphasis on teacher development has had demonstrable results. ''Ten years ago, more than 20 percent of our kids were in the bottom quartile'' on citywide standardized tests, Ms. Fink said. ''This year, only 9 percent of our kids were left in that quartile.</p>
        <p>''If I could have what I wanted,'' she said, ''professional development would be up to 25 percent of the budget.''</p>
        <p>Spending dollars on teacher development does not guarantee good test results, nor does lack of such spending relegate a district to the bottom ranks. The same holds for spending on books; districts with wealthier student populations and fewer minorities generally spend less on books, both because they get fewer dollars specifically designated for books and because their annual replacement costs are lower.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Levy said if he had more money to spread around the school system, he would make sure that superintendents used it first on teacher training.</p>
        <p>''As long as you have the most inexperienced teachers in the lowest performing districts, the system is not fair,'' he said. ''The things we need to do that would most improve the system are to recruit more good teachers, mentor and train them when they are here, and put in place a support system to keep them.''</p>
        <p>He also is clearly hoping for a favorable verdict in the lawsuit against the state to infuse the school system with more dollars.</p>
        <p>In the meantime, the school system's budget is expected to rise above $11 billion next year -- by itself more money than is spent on public schools in all but a handful of other states.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
