<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Limits on Patients' Rights</title>
    <meta content="14WED2$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207318"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Health Maintenance Organizations and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Health Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Supreme Court (US)</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E6DF133EF937A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="471" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Limits on Patients' Rights</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial holds Supreme Court ruling that patients cannot sue health maintenance organizations for giving doctors financial incentives to hold down costs underscores need for Congress to set standards for managed-care industry and expand rights of patients harmed by managed-care decisions</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Supreme Court's unanimous decision that patients cannot sue health maintenance organizations for giving their doctors financial incentives to hold down costs is a reasoned analysis of the state of federal law. But the decision also underscores the need for Congress to set standards for how the managed-care industry operates and to expand the rights of patients who have been harmed by managed-care decisions, including the denial of care.</p>
        <p>The case, Pegram v. Herdrich, has been watched with considerable interest because it deals with whether a for-profit managed-care plan violates its fiduciary duties to patients by rationing care. The plaintiff sued her H.M.O., a doctor-owned health plan, and her doctor under state law for medical malpractice and fraud when her appendix ruptured while she was made to wait for several days for an ultrasound test. She eventually won $35,000 in damages on the malpractice claim.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Supreme Court's unanimous decision that patients cannot sue health maintenance organizations for giving their doctors financial incentives to hold down costs is a reasoned analysis of the state of federal law. But the decision also underscores the need for Congress to set standards for how the managed-care industry operates and to expand the rights of patients who have been harmed by managed-care decisions, including the denial of care.</p>
        <p>The case, Pegram v. Herdrich, has been watched with considerable interest because it deals with whether a for-profit managed-care plan violates its fiduciary duties to patients by rationing care. The plaintiff sued her H.M.O., a doctor-owned health plan, and her doctor under state law for medical malpractice and fraud when her appendix ruptured while she was made to wait for several days for an ultrasound test. She eventually won $35,000 in damages on the malpractice claim.</p>
        <p>The issue before the Supreme Court was whether she could also sue the H.M.O. for violating a fiduciary duty to act ''solely in the interest of the participants and beneficiaries'' of the plan under the Employee Retirement Income Security Act of 1974, which applies to employer-sponsored health plans. Her theory was that the H.M.O. violated its legal duty because it gave the doctor-owners financial bonuses achieved by limiting medical care.</p>
        <p>Justice David Souter, writing for the court, rejected that argument, finding it doubtful that Congress intended fiduciary standards to cover decisions involving treatment made by doctors on behalf of a health plan. He wrote that Congress was free to restrict H.M.O. practices, but that ''the federal judiciary would be acting contrary to the Congressional policy'' that has existed for decades if it allowed this broad fiduciary breach claim to stand.</p>
        <p>Congress needs to change inadequate federal laws that fail to address emerging issues related to managed care. Several states have enacted laws barring financial incentives for H.M.O. doctors to deny patients necessary medical care. The bipartisan patients' rights bill that passed the House, and is now stalled in a House-Senate conference committee, has a similar provision.</p>
        <p>This case dealt with a patient who did in fact get medical care, though it was too late. She at least was able to recover damages for medical malpractice. But patients who are harmed by denial of care are precluded by Erisa from suing for damages. The House bill would close this liability loophole under federal law. The unanimous court decision is a sign that these complicated policy decisions can be addressed only by Congress itself.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
