<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Brush With Death Bonds a Family</title>
    <meta content="14HOST$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207328"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berkow, Ira</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hostetler, Jeff</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hostetler, Tyler</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06EFDF133EF937A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2795" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Brush With Death Bonds a Family</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By IRA BERKOW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Berkow, Ira</byline>
      <dateline>MORGANTOWN, W. Va.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on former football player Jeff Hostetler and his thoughts about 8-year-old son Tyler's recovery from paralyzing neck injury; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>One year ago, Tyler David Hostetler, age 8, died. Last week, he played in a Little League game. This is the story:</p>
        <p>The soft, spring rain had stopped and the evening sun angled through the clouds as Jeff Hostetler walked the family's 6-month-old buff-and-white cocker spaniel, Rookie, down a path from his spacious house. It was about 7 p.m. last June 14 when they headed to Cheat Lake, which sparkled alongside his property. Hostetler moved with Rookie down a hill -- this is West Virginia, after all, ''almost heaven'' as the locals often refer to it -- and the hills and mountains are indelible to the majesty of the terrain.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>One year ago, Tyler David Hostetler, age 8, died. Last week, he played in a Little League game. This is the story:</p>
        <p>The soft, spring rain had stopped and the evening sun angled through the clouds as Jeff Hostetler walked the family's 6-month-old buff-and-white cocker spaniel, Rookie, down a path from his spacious house. It was about 7 p.m. last June 14 when they headed to Cheat Lake, which sparkled alongside his property. Hostetler moved with Rookie down a hill -- this is West Virginia, after all, ''almost heaven'' as the locals often refer to it -- and the hills and mountains are indelible to the majesty of the terrain.</p>
        <p>At age 38, Hostetler, the former Giants quarterback who helped his team win two Super Bowls, had fashioned, surely, an idyllic life. He had married his college sweetheart, Vicki, and the Hostetlers had three boys: Jason, age 14 at the time, Justin, 11, and Tyler.</p>
        <p>Tyler, the youngest and perhaps the most willful, was spending the night at a friend's house. He was tall and strong for his age, and had recently been chosen for his Little League's all-star team. Like his brothers, he was an honor-roll student, as well as a good athlete.</p>
        <p>Hostetler, still sporting the mustache familiar to Giants fans, saw Rookie trot onto the tennis court. As Jeff was about to chase him off, he suddenly heard anguished screams from Vicki, up at the house.</p>
        <p>''Jeff! Jeff! Hurry! Something terrible has happened! Tyler's hurt! Hurry!''</p>
        <p>He ran toward the house.</p>
        <p>''Beth Ann called,'' cried Vicki, in the doorway. ''She could hardly talk. She said: 'Come immediately. Tyler had an accident.' ''</p>
        <p>Jeff and Vicki jumped into his white Suburban and flew down Eastlake Drive, up Sunset Beach and around to Snake Hill Road to the France farm, about six miles away, where Tyler had gone to stay with 9-year-old Charles France.</p>
        <p>Charles and Tyler had hopped onto the Gator, a six-wheel all-terrain vehicle used for hauling lumber and other farm objects. Charles drove it a short distance, then jumped off and told Tyler to get on and follow him as he chased locusts. Tyler had never driven one before, but that would hardly have bothered him.</p>
        <p>Tyler lost control and hit a fence post, and the vehicle flipped over on its side, pinning Tyler. A bar from the 1,000-pound vehicle wedged into Tyler's neck. Charles screamed for help and began running the 700 or so yards over a hill to the farmhouse.</p>
        <p>Dr. John France, a local trauma injury and spinal cord surgeon who is Charles's father, does not usually leave the hospital until much later in the night. But by a quirk of fate this night he had come home early. He was speaking with a contractor building his barn when he heard his son's shouts.</p>
        <p>''I didn't know what he was screaming about,'' John France recalled, ''but it sounded terrible. I took off running in the direction of Charles.'' The contractor was at his heels.</p>
        <p>''I found Tyler lying under the Gator. He wasn't breathing. It looked like his neck had been broken. His face had turned a purplish white, indicating cardiac arrest.</p>
        <p>''I thought he might have either a spinal cord injury or brain injury. I don't remember how this other fella and I got the vehicle off Tyler, but we did. I gave Tyler CPR. He began to breathe again, and he had a thready, barely palpable pulse. I've seen a lot of cases of accidents where someone's neck is broken, and I wondered if I was saving a little boy who would be a quadriplegic the rest of his life, who might be ventilator-dependent the rest of his life, and was I doing the right thing?</p>
        <p>''But I kept giving him breaths, and breaths, and breaths. And he opened his eyes. I stopped the CPR. Then his eyes shut and he stopped breathing again, began to discolor again. I applied CPR again. By this time my wife had called an ambulance, and within about 10 minutes it came. I had kept Tyler perfectly still to keep him stabilized, to keep from having further damage to his neck.''</p>
        <p>A Turn for the Worse</p>
        <p>It had begun to drizzle again, and someone brought out a poncho to place over Tyler to keep the sandy-haired boy dry and warm. Tyler was now alert, and John France assumed correctly that he had got to Tyler within three to five minutes of the accident, otherwise the lack of oxygen to his brain would have been disastrous.</p>
        <p>Tyler was carefully placed in the ambulance and the vehicle began to pull up the winding, mountainside roads from the farm when the Hostetlers drove up.</p>
        <p>''We just knew that Tyler was in the ambulance, and we followed it,'' Jeff Hostetler said. ''All the while we saw from the back window the medics working on Tyler. We still didn't know what had happened.''</p>
        <p>''I can't begin to describe what our feelings were, to see our little boy like this,'' Vicki Hostetler recalled.</p>
        <p>When the ambulance arrived at Ruby Hospital, and Tyler was carried out in a stretcher, Jeff would remember the absolute fear in his son's eyes when they looked at each other.</p>
        <p>''Daddy, Daddy,'' Tyler said.</p>
        <p>''It's all right, Tyler,'' he said. ''Everything's going to be all right.''</p>
        <p>John France emerged from the ambulance, and told Jeff and Vicki what had happened.</p>
        <p>''How bad is he, John?'' Jeff asked.</p>
        <p>''He was dead, Jeff,'' France said. ''He's alive now, but he's badly injured. There's some paralysis. We just don't know yet how bad it's going to be.''</p>
        <p>''Does he have a chance to recover, to have a normal life?''</p>
        <p>''Yes, he's young, he's moved each extremity; the field's wide open for recovery.''</p>
        <p>Jeff and Vicki understood, of course, that there was also the distinct possibility of little or no recovery.</p>
        <p>In bed now, with tubes in his arms and wearing a halo, Tyler asked his parents if he would get better. ''Will I be able to play with the all-star team next week?'' he asked.</p>
        <p>''We'll have to see what happens, Tyler,'' Vicki said. ''We're all praying for the best.''</p>
        <p>That night, Tyler took a turn for the worse. He stopped being able to move his arms, his legs, his fingers, his toes. He was completely paralyzed from the neck down.</p>
        <p>Doctors told the Hostetlers that they could help by continuing to massage Tyler's feet, to keep the muscles limber, to give healing a chance.</p>
        <p>For six weeks, either Vicki or Jeff or both were with Tyler every minute, day and night. They took turns sleeping overnight in his room, talking to him, trying to encourage him and kneading his feet to try to maintain muscle tone. Everything was devoted to Tyler.</p>
        <p>Jeff, a free agent, had offers from the Tennessee Titans and the St. Louis Rams. ''It would have been impossible for me to leave my son,'' he said. ''There was simply no question about it.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Russell Biundo, medical director of the Healthsouth Mountain View Regional Rehabilitation Hospital in Morgantown, where Tyler was eventually sent, called the Hostetlers ''two of the most devoted parents I have ever seen.''</p>
        <p>Progress in Small Steps</p>
        <p>For six days after the accident, Tyler lay in the intensive care unit, his left side paralyzed totally and only the slightest bit of motion in his right hand and right leg. His nerve endings were so sensitive that a breeze could cause him pain. He yelped in agony when his mother's hair brushed against his bare arm.</p>
        <p>''I hate my life,'' he said. ''I want to die.''</p>
        <p>''You can't say that, Tyler,'' Jeff said. ''You're tougher than that.''</p>
        <p>Jeff reminded Tyler about his own struggles in football, how he didn't give up. He talked about his injuries and the rehabilitation had to go through, and his time as a second-string quarterback, just waiting for his opportunity.</p>
        <p>''Quit has never been in my vocabulary, and it's not going to be in yours,'' he told Tyler.</p>
        <p>Jeff recalled, ''All of the lessons I learned in football -- discipline, motivation, drive -- all came into play in how I tried to deal with Tyler.''</p>
        <p>After eight days in Ruby Hospital, Tyler was transferred to Healthsouth for rehab. A little more movement appeared in his right side. In the third week, there was some motion in his left leg.</p>
        <p>One day, Tyler's aunt Janie came to visit and asked if she could kiss him. ''O.K.,'' he said, not altogether thrilled. When she did, it appeared that he had moved the forefinger on his left hand, the hand that had remained paralyzed.</p>
        <p>''Did you see that?'' Jeff asked. They had.</p>
        <p>''Tyler,'' Vicki said, ''can you do that again?''</p>
        <p>And he did. It was the first movement of an extremity in a week. ''There was such joy, just for this little moment,'' Vicki recalled. ''I turned away. I didn't want Tyler to see me crying.''</p>
        <p>After that, Hostetler said, ''Tyler really took off.'' In the fifth week he started to try to walk again. ''He had to relearn everything, every step,'' Hostetler said.</p>
        <p>Tyler had the advantage of youth, but rehab was arduous, exhausting and painful. He wanted to quit.</p>
        <p>''You can do it, Tyler,'' Jeff said, with a decisive tone. ''You will do it!'' He helped him to take one more step than Tyler thought he could take. And then another. This went on day after day.</p>
        <p>Several things helped Tyler's improvement, besides the various medications and, as Hostetler said, ''incredibly wonderful care by the doctors.'' Visitors were important for Tyler, from his Little League teammates to his family -- his brothers, uncles, aunts, grandparents -- to family friends and even his beloved Rookie.</p>
        <p>Calls came from a host of friends, and beyond. There were phone calls, from people like a longtime family friend Jon Miller, senior vice president of NBC Sports; as well as Barry Larkin, the Cincinnati Reds' shortstop and a hero of Tyler's; and Michael Jordan. (All the tongue-tied Tyler could say to Jordan was: ''Uh-huh. . . . Uh-huh. . . . Uh-huh. . . . O.K.'')</p>
        <p>Inspiring Family Stories</p>
        <p>There were the stories Tyler enjoyed hearing, such as how his parents met, when Jeff was quarterbacking the West Virginia Mountaineers in the Gator Bowl in December 1982. He saw the pretty daughter of his coach, Don Nehlen, in a convertible. ''Can you give me a ride?'' Jeff asked her, and she said yes.</p>
        <p>''And what about when you kissed her, Daddy?'' he asked. Indeed, on that first day, there was a kiss. It seemed comforting to Tyler to hear of the romance of his parents, since he was feeling so apart from everyday things.</p>
        <p>And he asked his father to tell him the football stories that he had heard on many other occasions. The story, perhaps, that he liked best was framed on the wall of Jeff's business here, Hostetler's Cafe, which specializes in bagels, a taste that he acquired not on the Pennsylvania farm where he grew up, but in Hillside, N.J., where he lived during football seasons with the Giants. On the wall is an article from The Tampa Tribune, written the day after Super Bowl XXV, on Jan. 27, 1991, after the Giants' 20-19 victory over Buffalo. The headline read, ''HOSTETLER'S 7-YEAR WAIT WORTH IT NOW.''</p>
        <p>Jeff, who had been a career backup, passed for 222 yards, 1 touchdown and no interceptions in the Super Bowl, filling in for the injured Phil Simms.</p>
        <p>''The greatest thing about Jeff,'' George Young, the Giants' general manager, said in the article, ''is that no matter how frustrated, he hung in there and waited several years for his great opportunity, and he had it now.''</p>
        <p>Jeff indeed knew frustrations. He had a scholarship to Penn State, but after starting a few games and doing well, he was still second string to Todd Blackledge. The 6-foot-3-inch, 220-pound quarterback transferred to West Virginia; he starred on the football field as well as in the classroom, where he was a dean's list student.</p>
        <p>In the pros, where Jeff also played for the Redskins and the Raiders in a fine 15-year career, he suffered a wide range of injuries, including a torn rotator cuff, a broken back and several concussions. He also had three knee operations and ankle surgery.</p>
        <p>Tyler was strong and tough like his dad, even to the point of being the lone third grader at Cheat Lake elementary school to pass the Presidential Physical Fitness test with, among other tests, push-ups, pull-ups and a mile run.</p>
        <p>''And something else helped, I want to believe,'' Jeff said. ''And that is prayer. We're a religious Christian family. Every night, Vicki and I and the two boys knelt and said prayers for Tyler. Every night.''</p>
        <p>A Miraculously Normal Life</p>
        <p>Six weeks after the accident, Tyler went home. The environment proved to be therapeutic. In a week, he was able to brush his teeth by himself. Two weeks later, Tyler was able to move about without help from anyone else. Shortly after, he started school with the rest of his classmates.</p>
        <p>Dr. Gary Marano, a radiologist who is a neighbor of the Hostetlers, read the X-rays after the accident and observed the boy recently. ''Tyler,'' he said, ''is a little miracle.''</p>
        <p>But Tyler's head still did not sit properly on his neck. It listed ever so much. Last December, Jeff took Tyler to Miami so Dr. Barth Green of the Miami Project could operate on Tyler's neck, to straighten it out.</p>
        <p>The operation was a success, and Tyler, Green said, ''was walking around the next day like a champ.''</p>
        <p>Things have resumed a relatively regular pace in the Hostetler home. When Tyler was in the hospital, his two older brothers were eager to please, were even a bit deferential to him. No more.</p>
        <p>''He's buggin' me again,'' Jason said, stating an older brother's time-honored position.</p>
        <p>Bugging you about what? he was asked.</p>
        <p>''Everything,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Just a few weeks ago, Jeff turned down an offer to quarterback the Minnesota Vikings.</p>
        <p>''My football days are over,'' he said. ''Tyler's injury and recovery have been the most significant period of my life. And I realized that my time is much more valuable here, with my family, watching my kids grow up, being a part of it. I understand the frailties of life better than I ever have. How precious each day is.''</p>
        <p>What does Tyler think of his dad giving up football?</p>
        <p>''I think he's crazy,'' said Tyler, not one to mince words. ''We watched the Super Bowl between the Titans and Rams, and I thought it would be great if Dad was in the game. I'd play.''</p>
        <p>Not football, not for Tyler, or hockey. The regular pounding in those sports could cause a recurrence of problems for him. Basketball, baseball, golf and tennis are permitted.</p>
        <p>Tyler is back in the Cheat Lake Little League, playing first base and wearing No. 5 for the black-jerseyed BlaineTurner Advertising team. He is still not 100 percent back, the doctors say. He still has some problems with mobility in his left hand, for example, but he is almost there.</p>
        <p>On a close play at first base in the first inning on a sun-splashed early afternoon recently, the runner stopped before he might have run into Tyler.</p>
        <p>''I hold my breath on plays like that,'' said Jeff, sitting in the bleachers along the first-base line.</p>
        <p>''You're always on pins and needles,'' Vicki said, ''but the doctors said that Tyler could take a hit like that and still be O.K.''</p>
        <p>Now Tyler came to bat, a left-handed hitter. In his age group, a pitching machine serves up balls to the batters. In his first three games of the season, Tyler had 9 hits in 10 at-bats. He gets respect.</p>
        <p>''Get back, Joey,'' the coach of the opposing team called to his center fielder. The words had hardly escaped from him when Tyler cracked a line drive over Joey's head. In the stands, Vicki and Jeff jumped up and clapped. The ball hit the wooden fence and bounced back, and Tyler David Hostetler, age 9, pulled up at second base with a double, standing there, under his black batting helmet, as if nothing much had happened.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
