<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Microsoft's Arguments Seeking a Delay in the Court's Order</title>
    <meta content="Y14STE$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207303"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="U.S. VS. MICROSOFT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Attorneys General</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Microsoft Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jackson, Thomas Penfield (Judge)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Text</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Attorneys General</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E2D7123EF937A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="3799" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Microsoft's Arguments Seeking a Delay in the Court's Order</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Excerpts from motion filed by Microsoft Corp for stay of judgement against it in federal antitrust suit; photo</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Following are excerpts from a motion filed yesterday by Microsoft for a stay of the judgment against it in a federal antitrust suit:</p>
        <p>Microsoft's stay motion has been pending for nearly a week, and the district court has ''failed to afford the relief requested'' by the  motion. Accordingly, Microsoft now asks this court to stay the judgment pending appeal. Time is of the essence here. Many extreme provisions of the judgment start to take effect 90 days after its entry, and Microsoft must begin preparing immediately if it is to be in compliance with the judgment in 84 days. Microsoft therefore respectfully requests that the court set an expedited briefing schedule on Microsoft's motion so that it can be resolved as soon as possible. Microsoft will promptly advise the  court if, contrary to all expectations, the district court grants Microsoft's stay motion now that a notice of appeal has been filed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Following are excerpts from a motion filed yesterday by Microsoft for a stay of the judgment against it in a federal antitrust suit:</p>
        <p>Microsoft's stay motion has been pending for nearly a week, and the district court has ''failed to afford the relief requested'' by the  motion. Accordingly, Microsoft now asks this court to stay the judgment pending appeal. Time is of the essence here. Many extreme provisions of the judgment start to take effect 90 days after its entry, and Microsoft must begin preparing immediately if it is to be in compliance with the judgment in 84 days. Microsoft therefore respectfully requests that the court set an expedited briefing schedule on Microsoft's motion so that it can be resolved as soon as possible. Microsoft will promptly advise the  court if, contrary to all expectations, the district court grants Microsoft's stay motion now that a notice of appeal has been filed.</p>
        <p>INTRODUCTION</p>
        <p>. . . Microsoft's appeal will present an overwhelming case for reversal of the judgment based on an array of serious substantive and procedural errors that infected virtually every aspect of the proceedings  below. These flaws culminated in the entry of unprecedented relief that extends far beyond the case that was presented, without  affording Microsoft an evidentiary hearing on the terms of one of the most complex antitrust decrees in history. Based on six hearsay declarations submitted by plaintiffs, the district court ordered that Microsoft be split into two companies, disclose its valuable intellectual property to competitors, redesign all of its operating system software to plaintiffs vague specifications and reprice that software according to an arbitrary court-imposed formula.</p>
        <p>Although final implementation of the breakup is stayed pending appeal, the judgment's other extreme provisions take effect 90 days after entry. Absent a stay from this court, these provisions will (i) result in a confiscation of large amounts of Microsoft's  intellectual property, (ii) interfere with Microsoft's release of new products such as its Windows Millenium operating system, (iii) require Microsoft to redesign all of its existing operating systems within six months of the judgment's effective date or else withdraw them from the marketplace, (iv) force Microsoft immediately to divert vast resources from software development to complying with the judgment and formulating the required breakup plan, and (v) make it difficult for Microsoft to conduct business in the highly competitive, fast-moving software industry at a critical time when software is being transformed from standalone products to Web-based services. The effect of these provisions will be devastating, not only to Microsoft, but also to its employees,  shareholders, business partners and customers, and could have a significant adverse impact on the nation's economy. A stay pending appeal is necessary to prevent these far-reaching and irreversible consequences of a profoundly flawed ruling.</p>
        <p>STATEMENT OF THE CASE  The Trial</p>
        <p>At trial, the district court largely suspended application of the Federal Rules of Evidence, admitting into evidence numerous  newspaper and magazine articles and other rank hearsay. For example, sixty-nine paragraphs of the written direct testimony of James Barksdale, then chief executive officer of Netscape and plaintiffs' first witness, contained large amounts of inadmissible hearsay, oftentimes multiple levels of hearsay. Yet, the district court denied Microsoft's motion in limine to exclude such hearsay statements.</p>
        <p>In the middle of trial, an event occurred that completely changed the competitive landscape of the software industry. On Nov. 24, 1998, America Online, a Microsoft competitor that provided plaintiffs' second witness, agreed to acquire Netscape -- the  company plaintiffs claimed had been fatally injured by Microsoft's conduct -- in a stock acquisition valued at $10 billion at the time of closing. In a related transaction, AOL entered into a three-year ''strategic alliance'' with Sun, another competitor of Microsoft that likewise provided plaintiffs with a trial witness.</p>
        <p>Findings of Fact</p>
        <p>The district court bifurcated briefing on findings of fact and conclusions of law, and issued its findings of fact on Nov. 5, 1999. Although 412 paragraphs long, the court's findings do not contain a single citation to the record, making it impossible to ascertain the purported basis for many findings and thereby compounding the many evidentiary errors at trial. The court also did not make any specific credibility determinations, and many of its ''findings'' consist of nothing more than sweeping, conclusory assertions. What is more, the court simply ignored vast amounts of uncontradicted evidence submitted by Microsoft, including Microsoft's explanation of why it did not charge separately for Internet Explorer and Microsoft's detailed description of the many  benefits flowing from the integrated design of Windows that cannot be duplicated by combining an operating system with a stand-alone browser like Navigator. . . .</p>
        <p>Conclusions of Law</p>
        <p>The parties subsequently submitted their proposed conclusions of law. Over Microsoft's objection, the district court invited  Prof. Lawrence Lessig, the same professor whom this court prevented from acting as special master in the prior consent decree  action, to participate as amicus curiae. In overruling Microsoft's objection, the court stated that Professor Lessig would ''submit his views exclusively on the issue of technological tying,'' a subject on which the court said he was ''uniquely qualified to offer advice.'' In his amicus brief, Professor Lessig stated that the district court's ''opinion in the summary judgment stage of this case seemed to indicate'' that the standard articulated by this court in its June 1998 decision governs the ''separate product'' issue, which lies at the heart of the tying claim.  After discussing this court's decision, Professor Lessig concluded that ''under the Court of Appeals test, Microsoft must prevail.''</p>
        <p>In its conclusions of law entered on April 3, 2000, the court nevertheless decided that Microsoft violated Section 1 of the Sherman Act by unlawfully tying Internet Explorer to Windows. The court, however, rejected plaintiffs' exclusive dealing claim, holding that the challenged agreements with various third parties ''did not foreclose enough of the relevant market to constitute a violation.'' The court also determined that Microsoft had violated Section 2 by maintaining a monopoly in operating systems and by attempting to monopolize Web browsing software, despite the fact that distribution foreclosure is a central premise of both violations in this case. . . .</p>
        <p>The Final Judgment</p>
        <p>On June 7, 2000, the district court signed plaintiffs' proposed final judgment as ultimately proffered without a single substantive change. The court thus entered radical and unwarranted permanent injunctive relief in these actions without granting Microsoft leave to conduct discovery and without making findings of fact or creating an evidentiary record on the issue of remedies. In ordering the breakup of Microsoft -- which, until the court entered its findings of fact, had the largest market capitalization in the world -- the court did not even grant Microsoft leave to depose the six individuals who  submitted declarations in support of plaintiffs' proposed remedies.</p>
        <p>Together with its final judgment, the district court issued a remarkable six-page memorandum that purports to explain the basis for its entry of the sweeping relief requested by plaintiffs. The memorandum is bereft of even a single citation to case law or evidence. According to the court, ''a structural remedy has become imperative'' because ''Microsoft does not yet conceded that any of its business practices violated the Sherman Act.''</p>
        <p>Despite the court's criticism of Microsoft for being ''unwilling to accept the notion that it broke the law,'' it should go without  saying that Microsoft's exercise of its appellate rights provides no conceivable basis for imposing punitive sanctions.</p>
        <p>Rather than finding that the judgment would increase competition, the court remarked that even ''purportedly knowledgeable people'' do not know what ''may or may not ensue,'' and the court dismissed the  notion of having an evidentiary hearing to explore that question because ''testimonial predictions of future events'' are ''less reliable even than testimony as to historical fact.'' In an astounding abdication of the judicial function, the court offered the following reason for its entry of the final judgment served up by plaintiffs:</p>
        <p>''Plaintiffs won the case, and for that reason alone have some entitlement to a remedy of their choice. Moreover, plaintiffs'  proposed final judgment is the collective work product of senior antitrust law enforcement officials of the United States Department of Justice and the attorneys general of 19 states, in conjunction with multiple consultants. These officials are by reason of office obliged and expected to consider -- and act in -- the public interest;  Microsoft is not.''</p>
        <p>The court was even more blunt in the many press interviews it gave about the case, both before and after entry of final judgment. For instance, The Wall Street Journal quoted the court as giving the following explanation for its refusal to provide Microsoft with any process before entering relief: ''It's procedurally unusual to do what Microsoft is proposing -- are you aware of very many cases in which the defendant can argue with the jury about what an appropriate sanction should be? Were the Japanese allowed to propose the terms of their surrender? The government won the case.''  And The Washington Post quoted the following explanation for why the court adopted  plaintiffs' proposed relief without modification: ''I am not an economist. I do not have the resources of economic research or any  significant ability to be able to craft a remedy of my own devising.''</p>
        <p>Perhaps most shocking, however, are the remarks attributed to the court in an article in The New York Times. When asked about the possibility of a breakup of Microsoft during a February 2000 interview -- which was described as ''a rare audience with a sitting judge during the course of a trial'' -- the court is quoted as saying, ''I am not sure I am competent to do that.'' The court apparently echoed that sentiment in a later interview. When asked why it had simply rubber-stamped plaintiffs' Draconian remedies, the court is quoted as responding: ''I am not in a position to duplicate that and re-engineer their work. There's no way I can equip myself to do a better job than they  have done.'' Lastly, in a repudiation of the most fundamental tenet of American jurisprudence, the court is quoted as offering the following explanation for its rejection of Microsoft's pleas for an evidentiary hearing on relief, ''I am not aware of any case authority that says I have to give them any due process at all. The case is over. They lost.''</p>
        <p>ARGUMENT  Microsoft Will Prevail on the Merits</p>
        <p>As the preceding discussion makes clear, the proceedings below went badly awry from the outset. The district court's many serious substantive and procedural errors are fatal to its conclusion that Microsoft violated the antitrust laws and to the relief entered.</p>
        <p>Before listing some of the district court's more egregious errors, two general observations illustrate how misguided the decision below is.</p>
        <p>First . . . adding Internet support to Windows cannot violate the antitrust laws, no matter what Microsoft's ''intent'' was in doing so. Indeed, Microsoft's addition of such functionality to Windows was but a single instance of a pervasive practice in  high-technology industries -- the improvement of a product through the integration of new functionality previously provided by separate products.</p>
        <p>To hold that efforts to improve a product in response to consumer demand and competitive pressures and to distribute those  improvements broadly to consumers violate the antitrust laws is to turn those laws on their head. The record here demonstrates that Microsoft's inclusion of Internet support in Windows made it easier for thousands of software developers to write Internet-enabled applications that rely on platform services provided by the Internet Explorer components of the operating system and for millions of consumers to access the Internet. Even the district court recognized  that Microsoft's ''inclusion of Internet Explorer with Windows at no separate charge increased general familiarity with the Internet and reduced the cost to the public of gaining access to it.''</p>
        <p>At the same time, Microsoft did nothing to exclude Netscape from the marketplace. . . .  Absent a showing of actual exclusion -- precluded by these undisputed facts -- no antitrust issue is even presented.</p>
        <p>Second, accepting, arguendo, plaintiffs' theory of the case, there is no antitrust violation. Plaintiffs' theory was that Microsoft attempted to impede the distribution of Navigator because it threatened to reduce (through a long, speculative and unproven chain of causation) the hypothesized ''applications barrier to entry'' into the market for ''Intel-compatible PC operating systems.'' There is no dispute, however, that Microsoft entered the alleged market for Web browsing software at a time when Netscape was dominant. It is also undisputed that Microsoft's efforts to develop, promote and distribute Internet Explorer resulted in lower prices, greater innovation and increased distribution of Web browsing software. In  fact, the district court found that Microsoft's actions ''contributed to improving the quality of Web browsing software, lowering its cost, and increasing its availability, thereby benefiting consumers.'' Unambiguously procompetitive conduct in one supposed market does not become an antitrust violation simply because that conduct allegedly had collateral effects in another supposed market. . . .</p>
        <p>Microsoft Will Suffer Irreparable Injury Absent a Stay</p>
        <p>Although the district court's judgment provides that the actual dismemberment of Microsoft is stayed pending appeal, the judgment's other extreme provisions take effect 90 days after entry. Absent a stay, those provisions will inflict massive and irreparable injury on Microsoft, possibly resulting in the company's demise as an  effective competitor in the software industry. Indeed, the court itself recognized in its June 7, 2000, memorandum that absent appellate intervention, the relief entered will quickly become ''irreversible as a practical matter.''</p>
        <p>The nonbreakup provisions of the judgment reflect three primary objectives, none of which is warranted by the violations found by the court and none of which serves a legitimate purpose under the antitrust laws. First, the judgment reflects a profound hostility to Microsoft's efforts to improve Windows by adding new features and  functionality. The judgment treats Windows not as a single product, but rather as a combination of (i) software that fits plaintiffs' narrow (and static) definition of an ''operating system'' and (ii) an indeterminate set of separate technologies (dubbed ''middleware products'') that OEM's may elect to turn on or off, or delete altogether, as they choose. By prohibiting Microsoft from maintaining the consistency of Windows as a platform for software development, the judgment will destroy the principal value of a product that Microsoft has spent billions of dollars developing and that has played a major role in the personal computer revolution.</p>
        <p>Second, for the proffered purpose of promoting ''interoperability,'' the judgment will effect a confiscation of Microsoft's intellectual property in its operating systems by requiring disclosure of proprietary information -- an extreme remedy that is unrelated to any of the claims alleged in the complaints and that applies to products that were not even part of this case. Third, the judgment will effectively compel Microsoft to treat all OEM's and ISV's, among others, exactly the same in all respects, whether or not such third parties have the capability or desire to work closely with Microsoft. This will make it virtually impossible for Microsoft to continue to collaborate with a broad array of OEM's and ISV's to develop and market innovative new technologies.</p>
        <p>Some examples of the serious injury that will befall Microsoft if a stay is not granted are discussed below.</p>
        <p>*The judgment will require Microsoft to disclose large amounts of proprietary information about its operating systems and other products to competitors, the ultimate penalty for a company whose business is based entirely on intellectual property. . . .</p>
        <p>Once that intellectual property is disclosed, the loss will be irretrievable.</p>
        <p>*The judgment will result in a direct and immediate intrusion into Microsoft's product design decisions. . . . The effect of this interference with Microsoft's development of new products during the pendency of an appeal will be irremediable even if Microsoft prevails.</p>
        <p>*The judgment will result in fragmentation of the Windows platform. A primary benefit of Windows is that it provides a  consistent platform for software developers and users. . . .</p>
        <p>*The judgment will require Microsoft to relinquish its rights under federal trademark and copyright laws. . . . The damage to Microsoft's copyright and trademark rights will not be curable even if Microsoft prevails on this appeal.</p>
        <p>*The judgment will prevent Microsoft from releasing new and innovative operating systems in a timely manner, and may require Microsoft to halt distribution of its currently shipping operating systems. . . .</p>
        <p>*The judgment will require Microsoft to modify its existing license agreements with the top 20 OEM's, wreaking havoc with  Microsoft's relationships with those companies. . . .</p>
        <p>*The judgment will make it virtually impossible for Microsoft to work with and assist software developers and hardware vendors seeking to create products for use with Windows. . . .</p>
        <p>*The judgment will prevent Microsoft from entering into routine cross-promotional and joint development agreements, even plainly procompetitive ones. . . .</p>
        <p>*The judgment will require Microsoft to submit a ''proposed plan of divestiture'' not later than four months after its entry. Requiring Microsoft to submit such a plan will cause a huge diversion of effort by Microsoft's executives at a critical time when Microsoft is attempting to change its entire business and programming model to remain competitive in the Internet age. This diversion (and the adverse effect on employee morale when the plan is submitted) will be entirely pointless even in the event that the decreed breakup is affirmed -- given the lightning pace of change in the software industry, any ''proposed plan of  divestiture'' created four months after entry of judgment will be out of date when it comes time actually to implement the plan.</p>
        <p>*The judgment will require Microsoft to freeze its internal organization. . . . This requirement will make it difficult for Microsoft to adapt its organization to the ever-changing needs of its business. .</p>
        <p>.</p>
        <p>In sum, compliance with the terms of the judgment, which touch upon virtually every aspect of Microsoft's business, will be impossible despite Microsoft's best efforts. The provisions of paragraph 3, read in conjunction with the definitions of the numerous defined terms (many of which are contrary to normal industry usage), are hopelessly vague and ambiguous. Moreover, the distraction that inevitably will flow from efforts to comply with the judgment will  damage Microsoft's most important asset -- its ability to recruit, retain and motivate creative people. As an intellectual property  firm, Microsoft's entire business depends on that asset. The judgment also will prevent Microsoft from working closely with other  companies in the industry to deliver innovative computing solutions unless Microsoft is willing to work with all companies -- including its competitors -- on identical terms. Simply stated, Microsoft cannot operate its business under the terms of the judgment.</p>
        <p>No Other Parties Will Be Harmed by a Stay</p>
        <p>No other parties interested in the proceeding will be harmed if the court grants a stay, much less suffer injury that would outweigh the serious and irreparable injury Microsoft will suffer absent a stay. Plaintiffs cannot claim that they themselves will be harmed in any respect by a stay. Nor can they contend that other interested parties -- i.e., the Microsoft competitors that convinced them to bring this lawsuit and seek Draconian structural relief -- will be injured in any legal sense if relief in these actions is stayed pending appeal.</p>
        <p>Nothing in the district court's findings of fact and conclusions of law suggests that any other party will suffer immediate, tangible harm if the relief in these actions is stayed pending appeal. The vague ''consumer harm'' identified in the court's findings consists primarily of speculation about unspecified innovations that might have come to market and competition that might have existed but for Microsoft's alleged conduct. . . .</p>
        <p>In contrast to the vague and speculative harm to consumers and competitors discussed in the court's findings, if the judgment is not stayed, Microsoft, its employees, its shareholders, its business partners and customers and the consuming public will suffer certain, definite and immediate harm. That harm clearly outweighs any  speculative injury that others with an interest in the proceedings might suffer if a stay is granted.</p>
        <p>The Public Interest Weighs Strongly in Favor of a Stay</p>
        <p>The public interest requires a stay of the judgment pending appeal. The devastating effects of the judgment will not be felt by  Microsoft and its employees and shareholders alone. Tens of thousands of computer manufacturers, software developers, system integrators and resellers that have built their entire businesses on Windows, as well as the millions of consumers who use Microsoft's products, will also suffer grievous injury absent a stay. Indeed, the entire United States economy may suffer if Microsoft is irreparably injured while it prosecutes this appeal. . . . There can be no doubt that the public interest weighs heavily in  favor of a stay. Even plaintiffs admit that the judgment will have profound and uncertain effects on the high-technology sector of the United States economy. There is no reason to subject the nation's economic well- being to such risks before this court has had an opportunity to review the fatally flawed decision below.</p>
        <p>Terms of the Trade</p>
        <p>ISV -- Independent software vendor.  OEM -- Original equipment manufacturer (PC maker).  Internet Explorer -- Microsoft's browser.  Navigator -- Internet browser from Netscape Communications, now a unit of America Online.  OS -- Operating system.</p>
        <p>U.S. VS. MICROSOFT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
