<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Excerpts From Gore's Remarks on Bush, the Presidential Race and the Issues</title>
    <meta content="Y14VTEX" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207282"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Text</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E4D9123EF937A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2768" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Excerpts From Gore's Remarks on Bush, the Presidential Race and the Issues</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Excerpts from Vice Pres Al Gore's interview by New York Times editorial board members, reporters and editors (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Following are excerpts from the interview of Vice President Al Gore yesterday by members of the editorial board and reporters and editors of The New York Times:</p>
        <p>Q. Your opponent, not so much on his vulnerability on the issues, but just as a candidate, is he -- do you find that he has strengths you didn't anticipate or is he competitive down to the wire?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Following are excerpts from the interview of Vice President Al Gore yesterday by members of the editorial board and reporters and editors of The New York Times:</p>
        <p>Q. Your opponent, not so much on his vulnerability on the issues, but just as a candidate, is he -- do you find that he has strengths you didn't anticipate or is he competitive down to the wire?</p>
        <p>A. I think that -- I don't know him very well. And it's possible to assess sort of the campaign team, but as far as him personally I've had such brief exchanges, no more than 10 words back and forth. Now I have, perhaps to excess, challenged him to debate, but I still would like to have a different kind of campaign and have regular debates twice a week, once a week. I would love to do that. I've recommended that the two of us go together to open meetings with undecided voters that both campaigns pick together so that they're not obvious ringers in there, and then just answer their questions. I'd be willing to travel from city to city.</p>
        <p>And if we had regular debates I would be able to answer your question a lot better. I don't really have a way of telling you what I think about him as a person. . . .</p>
        <p>I think that the debate that starts today will say a lot about the way the country looks at the two alternatives before them. We face a brand-new situation that we've never faced in our country's history, the prospect of very large surpluses stretching out as far as the eye can see. . . .</p>
        <p>There are two alternative courses of action. Governor Bush already assumed the large increase in the surplus a month ago and used it for his tax-cut proposal and his Social Security-privatization proposal. The estimates of the so-called Star Wars proposal are not even included yet, but before the midsession review is completed, before either the Congress -- Congressional Budget Office or the O.M.B. released a new estimate, Governor Bush's budget proposals have already completely spent all of that and more: 1.6 trillion for the tax cuts and one trillion for Social Security privatization to make up the amount lost to the trust fund in the next 10 years. That does not include all the new defense spending and the new proposals that he's made, but it's clear from his own numbers that his plan, even with the large increase in the surplus, predicted with the new numbers coming out soon, even with them, by his own numbers, he is way over and beyond that amount.</p>
        <p>I'm starting today a three-week set of speeches offering my recommendations for what I think the country ought to do with this surplus. I think we should, first of all, do for Medicare what we've done for Social Security and take it off budget. This will have the effect of protecting it against the kind of unwise changes to teaching hospitals, for example, that we saw in the 1997 balanced budget debate. It will also have the effect of paying down our national debt more quickly. I will propose later today that we eliminate the national debt completely by 2012.</p>
        <p>The forward movement in reducing debt is, in my opinion, a very sound strategy in an era when we have far more productive uses for capital than locking it up in government paper. . . .</p>
        <p>Further, I will propose that we give a new savings incentive to give Americans the option for tax-free, voluntary savings accounts over and above Social Security. And I will call it Social Security Plus, and it will be in sharp contrast to Governor Bush's proposal, which I think can be described as Social Security Minus, because his proposal would come with a price tag of a trillion dollars and with the risk that bad investments would be subtracted from the Social Security foundation. . . .</p>
        <p>Third, I want to create three new national trusts to boldly take on the most serious challenges we have for the future. We're in an information age. We need to revolutionize public education. I will propose a national education trust to reduce the size of classes, enhance the quality of our schools, new accountability and new resources, incentives to hire more teachers, tougher standards, all the rest that I have poorly described, but this will give new resources and new certainty to those resources to have the boldest plan ever to dramatically improve our public schools.</p>
        <p>Second, a health care trust to position us to take advantage of one of the most important events in the history of humankind, which will occur this summer, perhaps sooner rather than later, and that is the completion of the first rough draft of the human genome. We will be able to unlock the secret codes that diseases use to transmit messages from cell to cell. It is a perfect time to take advantage of this fantastic new era to find cures for diseases and to expand the access of the health care. . . .</p>
        <p>Q. We asked you to categorize your opponent. Just drawing on what you've said so far, I think -- how about, are you saying the ant versus the grasshopper here, or are you saying wasteful and profligate versus prudent and cautious? Or what labels -- how would you do it?</p>
        <p>A Well, I choose not to attach any elegant epithets to my opponent.</p>
        <p>Q. Do you share the conventional wisdom, though, that Governor Bush and his campaign have made better use of the last two months than you and your campaign?</p>
        <p>A. No, I don't, because I think it's impossible to make that judgment from day to day. When you plant seeds you don't know what the crop will be like just by the way the planting has occurred. You have to wait to see how the ideas develop.</p>
        <p>Q. Mr. Vice President, your references to Star Wars . . . sounded pretty negative. Are you telling us that you would advise President Clinton not to proceed in the decision that awaits him on missile defense?</p>
        <p>A. First of all, they're two separate -- they're two separate proposals entirely. The long-term threat that began in 1947 with the arms race still leaves us with thousands of nuclear warheads aimed at the United States and the necessity of protecting our country and our people through the best means available to us. And deterrence has proven to be a durable strategy. Before we discard that strategy we should have a high level of assurance that its successor would be at least as good, if not better.</p>
        <p>To base such a decision on ideology rather than tested science and considered strategy would be foolhardy, to say the least. One can wish for a perfect space-based Star Wars shield, but wishing does not make it so. And to draw an ideological line in the sand to say that those who wish it are inherently right is self-delusional. We have been aggressively researching and testing all of the technologies that would have to be used in order to construct such an option.</p>
        <p>We have also been giving a lot of thought to the interaction of that hypothetical option with the dynamics, the internal dynamics, of the arms race, which is now more of a static relationship between the United States and Russia. I was one of those who negotiated the removal of all nuclear weapons from Ukraine. We have also removed them from Kazakhstan and from Belarus. They are all now concentrated in Russia. We have been able to transform the nature of the strategic relationship by concentrating on civility, namely by taking away any possible advantage from first strike by either side. . . .</p>
        <p>If by introducing a comprehensive space-based Star Wars shield we drove a perception in the Russian high command that they now had to worry about losing the deterrence which has kept things calm all these years, then we would introduce a brand-new and volatile element into the equation, both inside the Russian internal debate and in the U.S.-Russian debate.</p>
        <p>Now, I'm sorry to belabor this, there's really no way to do this really quickly. The second system that we have been exploring is designed to counter a very different threat, not the massive strike that has dominated discussions during the cold war, but the prospect that a rogue state, like North Korea -- and, of course, it's welcome news today, the tone of the summit meeting between the two Korean leaders is really very, very positive -- but if a rogue state managed to get a handful of weapons, then the political utility of that small arsenal in the hands of a wild card state would be very destabilizing and dangerous. Is there a very limited system that falls far short of what could moot deterrence? Falls far short of what would destabilize the Russian attitude and Chinese attitude, but would nevertheless give us the chance to stop a handful of missiles in the threat that now is clearly a possibility 10 to 15 years from now? That would be useful to us. And it could be accomplished with relatively small changes to the A.B.M. treaty, whereas the Star Wars space-based shield would require complete scrapping of the treaty.</p>
        <p>The discussions in Moscow two weeks ago were characterized in various ways, but I can tell you that the possibility of Russian acquiescence in limited changes to the treaty is still very much there because they, too, face a similar threat 10 to 15 years from now on their southern rim.</p>
        <p>I'm sorry to be long-winded about this, but the decision as to how and when to proceed on what course toward that second option has not yet been made, and I'm not going to say something to forestall any of the president's options or the test of the technology coming up soon. And I think that I'm going to hold off on that. . . .</p>
        <p>Q. Let's talk a little bit about judicial appointments, the difference in your approach and your opponent, and what are the implications of that?</p>
        <p>A. Well, my opponent has had meetings with Jerry Falwell and Pat Robertson, and I don't know what went on in the meeting, but I do know that in the aftermath of the discussion both Reverend Falwell and Reverend Robertson said that they were happy as clams about what they heard. And I infer from that that the basic arrangement is that the agenda per noted in the closing days of the Republican primary contest, it's still very much the real agenda. At least where the Supreme Court appointments are concerned, and that those who are most interested in that agenda have agreed to be completely silent about it during this period of the campaign. And that they feel comfortable in doing so because they have heard something that gives them a feeling of assurance that there will be a return to that agenda openly in the event that they're successful in the election. I mean, that's what I infer. . . .</p>
        <p>My own philosophy is that this is one of the most important issues in the campaign. The next president will appoint three, perhaps four, justices of the Supreme Court, probably. Governor Bush has said his favorite justice is Antonin Scalia. Mine would be Thurgood Marshall. I think that the appointments by the president will surely determine the way our Constitution is interpreted for the next 30 to 40 years, not only concerning a woman's right to choose but also on issues like privacy, more broadly defined, civil rights, federalism, individual rights, environmental rights. The violence against women act was just struck down on a 5-to-4 vote with all the usual suspects lined up on both sides. And it was reintroduced yesterday, incidentally, to try to reclaim it. Why shouldn't a woman be able to sue in such circumstances? I agree with the four justices who affirmed what the Congress said.</p>
        <p>What would the difference be between my appointments and those of my opponent? I think it's very, very clear. I'm not in favor of specific, narrow litmus tests, but we all know that there are ways to ascertain with high confidence the general approach that potential justices will take to the Constitution. I believe it's a living and breathing document, and I don't think it should be narrowly constrained to the meaning of words 200 years ago -- 211 years ago -- as Justice Scalia and, apparently, Governor Bush would. . . .</p>
        <p>Q. In your list of issues that could come before the courts in the coming years, conspicuously absent is capital punishment. And it's something that obviously Governor Bush has had to talk about a lot so far this year. You've been largely silent on it. My question is that through a whirlwind, is there any substantive difference between your position on capital punishment and Governor Bush's?</p>
        <p>A. I have supported capital punishment. And there have been a number of cases where proposals came before the House of Representatives and the Senate when I voted against capital punishment. But those votes were the exception rather than the rule. I have insisted upon certain criteria before I'm willing to support the death penalty. But where those criteria are present I have always supported it.</p>
        <p>There are many who bring an understandable passion to the new debate over capital punishment that arises from their fundamental moral opposition to the penalty itself. I deeply respect that position. I do not share it. And the new debate is a means of reawakening and reinvigorating that old debate on the basic proposition of whether there should be capital punishment in the United States. I do think that that penalty should be available.</p>
        <p>Now on the new debate, DNA testing brings into focus the new ways that mistaken convictions can be uncovered. The debate over racial profiling has brought into new focus the long-held belief by many that race has played a role in producing the disproportionate applications of the death penalty to African-Americans and other minorities. And I think those questions are deserving of a full and thorough investigation and hearing. If there were, for example, in the federal courts the kind of record that Governor Ryan found in Illinois, I would support a federal moratorium pending improvements . . . I do not believe the evidence shows that's the case. Thus, at this point I do not support a federal moratorium.</p>
        <p>Now, the Columbia University study of state court judgments around the nation was extremely provocative. And I think there is a very careful continuing analysis. And if it justifies further steps, I have an open mind about it.</p>
        <p>Finally, the question of racial disparity is right now being investigated thoroughly within the Justice Department. And I await the findings that they have. I have to believe that the kinds of factors found in the Columbia study -- incompetent defense council, inadequate defenses put forward, clear mistakes prejudicial to the defendant by the prosecution -- are the kinds of mistakes that could conceivably have a connection to racial attitudes in aggregate. . . .</p>
        <p>I don't think anybody's comfortable with the death penalty, regardless of your position. And if there is a study that shows a large number of mistakes, that has to make you uncomfortable.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
