<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Devils Take a Lap In Ranger Country</title>
    <meta content="14DEVI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207289"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Jersey Devils</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yannis, Alex</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New Jersey Devils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500EED9123EF937A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="629" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Devils Take a Lap In Ranger Country</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEX YANNIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Yannis, Alex</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New Jersey Devils Stanley Cup celebrations described; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Devils continued their Stanley Cup celebration yesterday in, of all places, Rangers territory.</p>
        <p>The captain, Scott Stevens, accompanied by his teammates Scott Gomez and Jay Pandolfo and the club publicist Rich Minch, pounded the gavel to close the New York Stock Exchange and then headed uptown for an appearance on ''Late Show With David Letterman.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Devils continued their Stanley Cup celebration yesterday in, of all places, Rangers territory.</p>
        <p>The captain, Scott Stevens, accompanied by his teammates Scott Gomez and Jay Pandolfo and the club publicist Rich Minch, pounded the gavel to close the New York Stock Exchange and then headed uptown for an appearance on ''Late Show With David Letterman.''</p>
        <p>Stevens, holding the cup above his head, was greeted by cheers of ''Let's go, Devils'' and loud applause from traders, many of them reaching out to touch the silver trophy.</p>
        <p>As the close of the trading session drew near, Stevens, Gomez and Pandolfo, all wearing their red Devils sweaters, joined the president of the New York Stock Exchange, William R. Johnston, and at 4 p.m. they rang the bell and Stevens banged the gavel.</p>
        <p>Afterward, outside the exchange, a small crowd gathered to watch the triumphant threesome hold the Stanley Cup over their heads.</p>
        <p>Signing autographs as they made their way to a black limousine en route to the Letterman show, they were greeted by more applause.</p>
        <p>''Hey, you ruined my summer,'' yelled one man, obviously a Ranger fan.</p>
        <p>The visit to the stock exchange was a first for the Devils, who visited Letterman after they captured their first Stanley Cup, in 1995. They were also honored at a reception at the White House, which they are expected to do again.</p>
        <p>Stevens, Gomez and Pandolfo were joined by Jason Arnott, Martin Brodeur, Ken Daneyko, Brian Rafalski, Randy McKay and Brad Bombardir at the Letterman show.</p>
        <p>They entered through a side door, wearing their sweaters with the cup aloft, and then paraded up and down the aisles before departing for the All Star Cafe for dinner.</p>
        <p>Every member of the team will take part in today's victory celebration -- don't call it a parade, pleaded a member of the team's public relations department -- in the parking lot outside Continental Arena, where the Devils will ride around in their cars with family and friends.</p>
        <p>Official ceremonies will begin at 7:30 p.m., but according to the Devils, fans will be allowed to enter the lot at 4. There will be games, food and beverages. Parking and the celebration are free.</p>
        <p>Fans will be asked to park in the Giants Stadium parking lots, where they will be shuttled by bus to the Continental Arena's parking lot No. 22.</p>
        <p>The shuttle buses will leave from the front of the enclosed overpass over Route 120.</p>
        <p>The ceremonies will include season video highlights, player introductions and the presentation of the Stanley Cup. A fireworks display will end the celebration.</p>
        <p>SLAP SHOTS</p>
        <p>CLAUDE LEMIEUX, SERGEI NEMCHINOV and VLADIMIR MALAKHOV, are the prominent names on the list of Devils players available for next week's expansion draft. The three will become unrestricted free agents on July 1. It is unlikely they will be selected by either the Columbus Blue Jackets or the Minnesota Wild, the league's two expansion teams. Unrestricted free agents do not usually get selected because they are free to negotiate with any team, and on Monday all three expressed the wish to stay with the Devils. . . . BRAD BOMBARDIR, STEVE KELLY and STEVE BRULE are three of the players the Devils could lose in the expansion draft.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
