<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Chile Military To Search For Victims Of Its Rule</title>
    <meta content="Y14CHI$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207300"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Missing Persons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Chile</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Krauss, Clifford</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pinochet Ugarte, Augusto (Gen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Chile</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Chile</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Missing Persons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E5D7123EF937A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="725" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Chile Military To Search For Victims Of Its Rule</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFFORD KRAUSS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Krauss, Clifford</byline>
      <dateline>BUENOS AIRES, June 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Chilean military reaches accord with moderate human rights lawyers to search for remains of 1,200 dissidents who disappeared, 1973-90, during Gen Augusto Pinochet's dictatorship; accord is not likely to lead to new prosecutions of human rights offenders, but is first time that military has admitted role in disappearances (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Chilean military agreed today to search for the remains of 1,200 dissidents who disappeared during the dictatorship of Gen. Augusto Pinochet from 1973 to 1990.</p>
        <p>It is doubtful that the accord between the military and moderate human rights lawyers will result in new prosecutions of human rights offenders. But it is the first time that the military has acknowledged responsibility for the disappearances of several thousand people.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Chilean military agreed today to search for the remains of 1,200 dissidents who disappeared during the dictatorship of Gen. Augusto Pinochet from 1973 to 1990.</p>
        <p>It is doubtful that the accord between the military and moderate human rights lawyers will result in new prosecutions of human rights offenders. But it is the first time that the military has acknowledged responsibility for the disappearances of several thousand people.</p>
        <p>The agreement, reached after 11 months of negotiations, gives the military six months to find information that can lead to finding the bodies of dissidents believed to be buried around the country. Those military or police personnel who come forward as witnesses to crimes will not be identified, a stipulation that has come under heavy criticism from some Chilean rights groups.</p>
        <p>''This agreement permits us to make a solemn and sure compact that we all form part of the same fatherland,'' President Ricardo Lagos said as he warmly welcomed the agreement at a ceremony in La Moneda presidential palace that top military personnel and conservative politicians attended. Mr. Lagos that the pact would help assure that ''in Chile dissidents will never again be assassinated and made to disappear.''</p>
        <p>Information gathered by the military will be given to Mr. Lagos, who can turn over the findings to the Supreme Court for further investigation. If Mr. Lagos, who is the first Socialist to govern Chile since the bloody ouster of Dr. Salvador Allende in a coup in 1973, is not satisfied with the results of the inquiry, he can extend the investigation by six months.</p>
        <p>Experts on the disappeared said they thought that the accord had the potential of finding the whereabouts of half the missing. Others will probably remain missing because they were victims of General Pinochet's secret police, whose officers retain  their code of silence, or because they were killed by right-wing landholders who took the law into their own hands in the months after the coup to punish squatters.</p>
        <p>''It is a step forward, as long as the armed forces fulfill its commitment,'' said Jose Miguel Vivanco, director for the Americas division of Human Rights Watch. ''The big question is how much information they will be able to produce, when and what will be the quality of the information.''</p>
        <p>The negotiations started as General Pinochet was under house arrest outside London on a Spanish warrant that sought his extradition  in a human rights case. The talks nearly broke down when the former dictator received a hero's welcome from the military on his return to Santiago in March after British authorities decided that he was to infirm to stand trial.</p>
        <p>But last week, the dialogue made rapid progress after a decision by the Appeals Court that stripped General Pinochet of his senatorial immunity and opened the way to a trial in Chile. The general's lawyers are appealing the decision to the Supreme Court.</p>
        <p>While implicitly agreeing that its officers had information about missing dissidents, the top brass of the military was happy that the brief document allotted responsibility for the coup not only to the military but also to a general chaotic political situation caused by both the left and the right.</p>
        <p>The military was given added incentive to come to an agreement when the courts ruled last year that an amnesty decreed during the Pinochet dictatorship for most political crimes could not apply to cases where people were still missing. The courts decided that people who were missing could still be alive as victims of continuing kidnappings and that their cases could therefore not be considered closed.</p>
        <p>Before the new accord takes effect, the Congress would have to change a law stipulating that military personnel who have information about crimes pass it directly to prosecutors. But because the agreement has the support of Mr. Lagos and the high command, experts generally say the Congress will agree to let soldiers and officers give information to their superiors anonymously.</p>
        <p>Ricardo Israel, a political scientist at the University of Chile, predicted,  ''This agreement will be a catalyst for constitutional change.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
