<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Counting the Till, Then Trolling for New Accounts</title>
    <meta content="Y14PERK" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207237"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MANAGEMENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Fifth Third Bancorp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sweeney, Paul</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Koch, Katherine J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE4DF123EF937A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1276" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Counting the Till, Then Trolling for New Accounts</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAUL SWEENEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sweeney, Paul</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Fifth Third Bank in Cincinnati focuses on incentives offered to employees who are able to get new customers for bank; says sales employees can earn as much as 125 percent over their base salary in profit sharing, incentive pay, stock options and other sweeteners; Katherine J Koch, who manages branch bank, comments; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>At her church, at meetings of her husband's Delta Air Lines retired pilots' group and even on her morning commute, Marybeth Harbaugh tells anyone who will listen about the great deals at Fifth Third Bank in Cincinnati.</p>
        <p>Ms. Harbaugh, 58, is an administrative secretary in the trust department at the bank. Outside of the office, though, she becomes an unofficial evangelist for its products.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>At her church, at meetings of her husband's Delta Air Lines retired pilots' group and even on her morning commute, Marybeth Harbaugh tells anyone who will listen about the great deals at Fifth Third Bank in Cincinnati.</p>
        <p>Ms. Harbaugh, 58, is an administrative secretary in the trust department at the bank. Outside of the office, though, she becomes an unofficial evangelist for its products.</p>
        <p>''They know me on the bus,'' she said, reporting with satisfaction that she recently directed a fellow commuter who was having a problem with his mortgage loan to a bank representative who could solve it.</p>
        <p>''It's word of mouth,'' she added. ''I sell Fifth Third Bank. Funnel a lead to me and I'll take the ball and run with it.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Harbaugh is not an eccentric; she is the norm at this bank. It is part of Fifth Third Bancorp, which imbues its affiliate banks in the Midwest, Florida and Arizona with a go-for-it, hit-the-ground-running culture, fueled by an array of bonuses, awards and other incentives, that makes it the envy of the banking world. Employees often spend their lunch hours, evenings, weekends and holidays blitzing neighborhoods, knocking on the doors of businesses and importuning people over the phone to sign up as customers.</p>
        <p>Katherine J. Koch, 27, the manager of a bank branch at a Kroger supermarket in suburban Cincinnati, is a shining example. When there is a promotion on, she makes half-hour announcements over the public address system to food shoppers -- fertile ground, as 80 percent of Kroger shoppers are not Fifth Third customers, surveys show -- promoting the bank's special rates on loans, checking accounts and other services.</p>
        <p>She follows up by prowling the aisles, prospecting for customers. ''The work is challenging,'' Ms. Koch said. ''It takes 10 no's before you get a yes.'' She has her sights set at the moment on a police officer who shops at Kroger, regularly greeting him with the salutation, ''Ready for that new car loan yet?''</p>
        <p>Hardly anybody within earshot of a Fifth Third employee is safe from a sales pitch. About a month ago, Douglas Barnaclo, 37, the No. 1 mortgage-loan originator in Cincinnati for the last three years, was having dinner at a restaurant in Charlotte, N.C., and didn't let the distance to his home territory deter him. No sooner had the waitress commented on the bank's odd name on his credit card than he began urging her to apply for one. ''She's got my business card,'' he said with a chortle. (The corporate name, which even some top officers acknowledge as homely, resulted from a merger.)</p>
        <p>Why do Fifth Third's 12,000 employees run so hard? They are driven in part by a corporate credo that enshrines hustle and is reinforced regularly at pizza-and-Pepsi bowling parties and summer barbecues and softball games, where the chairman and chief executive, George A. Schaefer, a West Point graduate, gives Knute Rockne-style pep talks.</p>
        <p>The main motivator, however, seems to be the incentives. Fifth Third sales employees can earn as much as 125 percent over their base salary in profit sharing, incentive pay, stock options and other sweeteners, said Salil T. Mehta, an analyst who follows the financial services industry for bankstocks.com. That compares with a ceiling of 30 to 50 percent elsewhere, Mr. Mehta said.</p>
        <p>''Most banks don't reward and recognize their employees for working hard and selling,'' he said. ''They breed mediocrity. Employees stop producing -- which is why so many banks are revenue-challenged.''</p>
        <p>Not Fifth Third. Its 26 consecutive years of record earnings have made it a darling of Wall Street. And its gung-ho culture makes it very un-banklike.</p>
        <p>''Most banks are not sales organizations,'' said Charles Wendel, president of Financial Institutions Consulting in New York. ''They are bureaucratic control organizations that often regard customers as an inconvenience. Fifth Third is more like Southwest Airlines or Nordstrom than a bank in terms of its customer service and sales culture.''</p>
        <p>Just about every employee, even security guards, can pick up extra cash, prizes and rewards: $15 to $25 for persuading somebody to apply for a credit card; $25 for a mortgage application and an additional $50 if it is approved; $25 for a consumer loan that is approved; and $500 for bringing in a new hire who stays for at least 90 days. The bank even gives rewards based on the size of accounts referred to its investment arm, Fifth Third Securities, or its trust department.</p>
        <p>Ms. Harbaugh recently snagged the Apex Award, which entitled her to dinner for two at the Palomino Restaurant. She was also one of 10 employees honored with a framed share of Fifth Third stock at a gala bank ceremony. (The stock, which closed yesterday at $67.75 a share, down from its 52-week high of $75.4375, is ''one of the few growth stocks that also happens to be a bank,'' said Joseph C. Duwan, an analyst at Keefe, Bruyette &amp; Woods.)</p>
        <p>Managers and bank officers make the most extra money. Ms. Koch, the Kroger branch manager, earned an extra 20 percent over her salary last year for meeting all her branch's goals on new accounts, deposits and loans. She also got 14 percent above her salary in profit sharing. For meeting third-quarter loan goals, she and other top managers will be treated this summer to an afternoon at Keeneland, the racetrack in Kentucky.</p>
        <p>As one of the 75 top-producing  branch officers for 1999, Ms. Koch won perhaps the bank's most coveted prize: an all-expenses-paid trip for two to the Camelback Inn, a five-star resort in Arizona. ''All my friends think I'm a workaholic,'' said Ms. Koch, who took her best friend along. ''But the trip shows that the company appreciates you.''</p>
        <p>Including a friend or a spouse also builds up Fifth Third's bottom line. Julie Broadwell, who manages another Kroger branch, has been putting her husband, William, to work. An insurance claims specialist, he is psyched up for next year's prize, a golfing adventure in the Caribbean. ''I try to come up with ideas of who she can contact,'' Mr. Broadwell said. ''The whole family is with Fifth Third.''</p>
        <p>Because many rewards are for group efforts, those who don't pull their weight often hear about it. ''If I deliver a client to my business partner and he or she doesn't think of me for 30 days or so, then it's time to sit down and have a talk,'' said Thomas F. Stoll, a mortgage officer based at a suburban banking center.</p>
        <p>The bank regularly publishes performance lists for each branch and monthly scorecards of winners and losers; it also asks mortgage loan officers to state their results at a public forum each month, usually with Mr. Schaefer, the chairman, in attendance. ''It's a high-pressure environment,'' said Shane Johnson, a finance expert at the College of Business Administration at the University of Cincinnati.</p>
        <p>That is fine with Mr. Schaefer, a Vietnam veteran. ''This isn't a social-service agency,'' he said. ''It's capitalism.''</p>
        <p>For loyalists who embrace Fifth Third's values, he added, rewards for referrals continue even after retirement. ''They maintain contacts,'' he said, chuckling. ''We want them selling right to the grave.''</p>
        <p>MANAGEMENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
