<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Metro Briefing</title>
    <meta content="14MBRF$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207376"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E4DD133EF937A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1857" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Metro Briefing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by Anthony Ramirez</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NEW YORK</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: LAZIO ON RADIO  Representative Rick A. Lazio, the Republican nominee for the Senate, spent about 20 minutes yesterday in playful banter with the radio talk show host Don Imus. The highlights included Mr. Lazio passing a pop quiz on New York trivia that included questions on the length of a mile in Manhattan blocks (about 20) and who Major Deegan was (an architect). Mr. Lazio said that he expected to be outspent by Hillary Rodham Clinton, and that he planned to raise $15 million, compared with her goal of $25 million.</p>
        <p>Randal C. Archibold (NYT)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NEW YORK</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: LAZIO ON RADIO  Representative Rick A. Lazio, the Republican nominee for the Senate, spent about 20 minutes yesterday in playful banter with the radio talk show host Don Imus. The highlights included Mr. Lazio passing a pop quiz on New York trivia that included questions on the length of a mile in Manhattan blocks (about 20) and who Major Deegan was (an architect). Mr. Lazio said that he expected to be outspent by Hillary Rodham Clinton, and that he planned to raise $15 million, compared with her goal of $25 million.</p>
        <p>Randal C. Archibold (NYT)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: UNION MEMORIAL  Six bronze relief panels depicting a 1909 garment factory strike and other milestones in the 100-year history of the International Ladies Garment Workers Union are being mounted in Union Square. The bronzes, by the sculptor Greg LeFevre, will be placed in the southwest corner of the square, where 30,000 laborers rallied in 1882. That rally was the basis of the eventual Labor Day holiday. The $30,000 cost of the sculptures was paid by the Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees, which was created by a merger of the garment workers and another union five years ago.</p>
        <p>Barbara Stewart (NYT)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: HOSPITAL PROTEST  New York City's largest union of health care workers has scheduled two rallies this week to protest plans to lay off several hundred workers at Beth Israel Medical Center and St. Luke's-Roosevelt Hospital Center. The union, Local 1199 of the National Health and Human Service Employees Union, plans to demonstrate today at noon at St. Luke's (114th Street and Amsterdam Avenue), and tomorrow at noon at Beth Israel (10 Union Square East). Union officials said they hoped to pressure Continuum Health Partners, which runs the hospitals, to consider other ways to reduce its budget deficit.</p>
        <p>Steven Greenhouse (NYT)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: NEW STATE PARK  Gov. George E. Pataki said yesterday that the state had bought seven acres of blighted waterfront in Williamsburg, Brooklyn, for a new state park to be shared by the public and New York University. He said the land, known as the Eastern District Terminal, had cost $9.3 million. New York University said it had agreed to pay for construction of practice and playing fields for student recreation during the school year, and to allow public use of the park at other times.</p>
        <p>Thomas J. Lueck (NYT)</p>
        <p>THE BRONX: CHARGE IN BABY'S DEATH  A 22-year-old man was charged yesterday with killing his girlfriend's 8-month-old daughter, the police said. The man, Miguel Martinez of 2676 Grand Concourse in the Fordham section, took the unconscious infant, Nia Gay, to Montefiore Medical Center on Saturday, telling doctors that she had fallen off the bed, said Lt. Dennis Cirillo, a police spokesman. The baby never regained consciousness, and died on Monday night. The medical examiner's office ruled the death a homicide, caused by ''fatal child abuse syndrome with whiplash shaking and multiple blunt impact injuries to head, torso and extremities.'' Mr. Martinez was charged with second-degree murder, Lieutenant Cirillo said.</p>
        <p>Andy Newman (NYT)</p>
        <p>ALBANY: BELL ATLANTIC RULING  New York's highest court ruled yesterday that Bell Atlantic must repay $19.5 million to its state customers in the form of a credit of about $2.50 per customer on phone bills. The State Public Service Commission had ruled in 1997 that Nynex had to distribute to its customers the $19.5 million, a share of its profit from the sale of Bell Communications Research, a company owned by the baby Bells. Nynex, later bought by Bell Atlantic, sued to challenge the ruling. Yesterday, the Court of Appeals upheld the ruling, overturning a decision by the Appellate Division.</p>
        <p>Richard Perez-Pena (NYT)</p>
        <p>GARDEN CITY: NASSAU BAILOUT PLAN  Nassau County came a step closer to receiving a state bailout last night when its Legislature endorsed several aspects of Gov. George E. Pataki's fiscal recovery plan. The Legislature unanimously passed a resolution asking the state to create a seven-member board to refinance the county's debt, monitor its budgets and, if the county fails to live within its means, take over its finance. Since negotiations in Albany were not complete on the second half of the plan, which calls for giving the county $105 million in state aid during the next five years, the Legislature is to meet again today to ask for more state action.</p>
        <p>Michael Cooper (NYT)</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY</p>
        <p>TRENTON: MOTOR VEHICLE CHIEF MOVING  Richard Kamin, the former director of the state's Division of Motor Vehicles, is taking another job with the Whitman administration after receiving most of the blame for the auto emissions debacle, the governor said yesterday. Albert Ari, a 40-year state transportation department veteran, has been named acting D.M.V. director. A report released last week laid blame for the Parsons Infrastructure auto inspections mess largely at the feet of Mr. Kamin and the state project director, Carl Passeri, who announced his resignation last week.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>CONNECTICUT</p>
        <p>BRIDGEPORT: BOY SCOUTS SUE  The Boy Scouts of America have filed a federal lawsuit against the state comptroller and the Connecticut State Employee Campaign Committee, asserting that the group was discriminated against when it was removed from a list of charities eligible for state payroll deductions. Last month the Commission on Human Rights and Opportunities excluded the Boy Scouts from a list of charities that get money from payroll deductions because the Scouts' policy against gays violates state law. The suit was filed in District Court in Bridgeport on Monday.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>CALENDAR</p>
        <p>Tomorrow</p>
        <p>HEARING ON L.I.R.R. LINK  The Metropolitan Transportation Authority is to hold a public hearing in Manhattan at 6 p.m. at M.T.A. Headquarters, 347 Madison Avenue, at 44th Street, on a plan to link the Long Island Rail Road to Grand Central Terminal. Information: (212) 878-7483.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
