<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Marines in a Grim and Forgotten War</title>
    <meta content="14BERN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207223"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Korean War</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brady, James (Writer)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bernstein, Richard</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Marines of Autumn, The (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Korean War</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E4D7153EF937A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1004" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Marines in a Grim and Forgotten War</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD BERNSTEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bernstein, Richard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Richard Bernstein reviews book The Marines of Autumn by James Brady; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE MARINES OF AUTUMN  By James Brady  Thomas Dunne Books/St. Martin's Press. 274 pages. $24.95.</p>
        <p>It's fair to say that the Korean War does not occupy a pivotal place in the collective American memory, certainly not compared with the sweep of World War II or the national preoccupation with the war in Vietnam. But it was a grim and unrelenting contest, twice almost lost, once almost won before it ended in a negotiated stalemate whose on-the-ground results endure today. Of course those who fought in Korea, like James Brady, author of ''The Marines of Autumn,'' do not share the national amnesia. Mr. Brady's novel about the war is almost brought down by the weight of stock war-novel devices. Even so, it transforms his bitter memory of the conflict into a gritty reconstruction of one of the war's most harrowing moments.</p>
        <p>That was the Chinese attack on American Marine and Army divisions that were proceeding foolishly past the earlier Korean line of demarcation at the 38th parallel all the way to the border with China. Again, it is probably safe to say that the site of the Chinese attack, which began around the Chosin Reservoir in the rugged, snowy Taibaik Mountains, is pretty much unknown to most Americans. Mr. Brady brings the battle there vividly to life, and death, in a novel that is more like a fictionalized documentary than a full-fledged work of the imagination.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE MARINES OF AUTUMN  By James Brady  Thomas Dunne Books/St. Martin's Press. 274 pages. $24.95.</p>
        <p>It's fair to say that the Korean War does not occupy a pivotal place in the collective American memory, certainly not compared with the sweep of World War II or the national preoccupation with the war in Vietnam. But it was a grim and unrelenting contest, twice almost lost, once almost won before it ended in a negotiated stalemate whose on-the-ground results endure today. Of course those who fought in Korea, like James Brady, author of ''The Marines of Autumn,'' do not share the national amnesia. Mr. Brady's novel about the war is almost brought down by the weight of stock war-novel devices. Even so, it transforms his bitter memory of the conflict into a gritty reconstruction of one of the war's most harrowing moments.</p>
        <p>That was the Chinese attack on American Marine and Army divisions that were proceeding foolishly past the earlier Korean line of demarcation at the 38th parallel all the way to the border with China. Again, it is probably safe to say that the site of the Chinese attack, which began around the Chosin Reservoir in the rugged, snowy Taibaik Mountains, is pretty much unknown to most Americans. Mr. Brady brings the battle there vividly to life, and death, in a novel that is more like a fictionalized documentary than a full-fledged work of the imagination.</p>
        <p>He portrays the Americans advancing north, despite intelligence information that large numbers of Chinese troops had infiltrated the Korean border region. He then describes the grim American retreat to safety at the North Korean port of Hungnam in such bitter cold that doctors were unable to take off their gloves to treat the wounded. At his best, Mr. Brady, who published a volume of Korean War memoirs, ''The Coldest War,'' in 1990, keeps a tight grip on the mind. He has a fine ear for the soldiers' pungent vernacular, and he offers us three well-rounded fictional characters whose experiences have a realistic bite.</p>
        <p>The chief of these characters is Thomas Verity, a tested veteran of World War II who is called back to service in Korea because, having grown up in China, where his father was a businessman, he speaks several dialects of Chinese. Verity is sent to join up with a Marine division commanded by Gen. Oliver P. Smith.  By listening to Chinese radio broadcasts, he is supposed to find out if Chinese troop movements are ''just saber rattling or something substantive.'' Verity doesn't want to go to Korea. His young and beautiful wife has just died, leaving him to care for their 3-year-old daughter. In light of his personal circumstances, he is told that all he need do is make his report, and then he can return home.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brady's handling of Verity's dead wife and baby daughter is what mainly threatens his otherwise hardnosed novel with an aura of wartime melodrama. Interspersed with scenes of Verity in Korea are maudlin fragments -- flashbacks to his life with his breezily charming wife and the adorable daughter who waits for him back home in Washington. ''Oh, I wish Poppy could see it,'' the daughter tells her governess about a snowfall in Washington, even as Verity is suffering frostbite in North Korea.  ''He loves snow, too.'' It is as though Mr. Brady didn't trust us to get the point about the absurdity of war without tossing these Hollywoodian elements onto the story.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Brady knows war, the smell and the feel of it, and when we get to the main action of his book, that knowledge more than makes up for his lapses of prefabricated sentiment. He shows men doubled over with cramps from eating frozen food, or relieving themselves with their uniforms unremoved because the fantastic cold made it impossible to do otherwise. ''The marines wore their canteens inside their shirts against their bellies to keep the water liquid and drinkable,'' he writes.  ''This gave slim young men the bulbous look of the old and obese, of women late in pregnancy.''</p>
        <p>Verity, arriving in Korea, teams up with a gunnery sergeant named Tate and a driver named Izzo, and the three stay together in classic wartime buddy style through the rest of the story. Needless to say, Verity's intelligence-gathering in North Korea becomes superfluous when the Chinese attack in massive force, driving the Americans ahead of them. Reluctantly, convinced that he will never see his daughter again, Verity becomes part of the conflict and the retreat, with his companions, Tate and Izzo crustily showing their valor along the way.</p>
        <p>Here and there, Mr. Brady, clearly his own narrator, cuts in fragments of Gen. Douglas MacArthur and the Chinese leaders making decisions as their troops suffer and die in the cold.  One of these fragments shows the two main Chinese commanders, Peng Dehuai and Lin Biao, returning to China after failing to wipe out the American army and being ''fastened to wooden posts and shot.'' This is odd because the historical record shows nothing of the sort happening, though both Lin and Peng lost out to China's supreme leader, Mao Zedong, in later power struggles.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brady portrays MacArthur as a careless, self-important, slightly mad genius, decidedly not as a hero.  Nor are some of his closest aides. ''We're still attacking and we're going all the way to the Yalu,'' one commanding general tells the commander of a regimental task force that he has ordered to march toward the Yalu. ''Don't let a bunch of Chinese laundrymen stop you.''</p>
        <p>It is not clear that that sort of comment was made in that context.  Still, Mr. Brady's documentary-novel persuades us that American blindness arose at least partly from that sort of racist hubris, and demonstrates just how high the cost of that blindness was.</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
