<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Poached Chicken Takes Flight</title>
    <meta content="14MINI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207210"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE MINIMALIST"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Poultry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bittman, Mark</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Columns/The Minimalist</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Poultry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEFDA153EF937A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="756" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Poached Chicken Takes Flight</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Mark Bittman</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bittman, Mark</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Minimalist column by Mark Bittman suggests poached chicken in soy sauce; recipe (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ROY IP, who owns Le Petit Cafe in Branford, Conn., grew up eating chicken poached in soy sauce in Hong Kong, and it is still an important part of his home repertory because it is so easy and delicious. In less than half an hour on the stove, the bird takes on dark, rich flavors from not just soy sauce but also ginger, scallions, star anise and an unusually fragrant wine. It's the antithesis of the usual poached chicken, in which all the bird's flavor leaches into the cooking liquid. Instead, the meat takes on a powerfully complex taste from the seasonings.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ip serves the chicken straight out of the stockpot with the liquid as a sauce. But I like to finish it in a hot oven, where it develops a crispy, dark brown crust that takes roast chicken to another level.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ROY IP, who owns Le Petit Cafe in Branford, Conn., grew up eating chicken poached in soy sauce in Hong Kong, and it is still an important part of his home repertory because it is so easy and delicious. In less than half an hour on the stove, the bird takes on dark, rich flavors from not just soy sauce but also ginger, scallions, star anise and an unusually fragrant wine. It's the antithesis of the usual poached chicken, in which all the bird's flavor leaches into the cooking liquid. Instead, the meat takes on a powerfully complex taste from the seasonings.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ip serves the chicken straight out of the stockpot with the liquid as a sauce. But I like to finish it in a hot oven, where it develops a crispy, dark brown crust that takes roast chicken to another level.</p>
        <p>The sauce can be made with common ingredients, but it's worth your while to visit an Asian market for three that Mr. Ip uses that are unusual but inexpensive. His base is mushroom soy sauce, which has a strong, dark quality. (A lighter, more elegant and far more expensive Japanese soy sauce would be wasted here.) Mr. Ip also uses yellow rock sugar, a not especially sweet, lumpy sugar that must be broken up with a hammer before it's added to the sauce.</p>
        <p>But the dish's exotic flavor comes from mei kuei lu chiew, or rose wine. This is not the familiar (and uninteresting) shao xing cooking wine, but a lovely, floral one that smells like rose water and could have a period as a fashionable aperitif, especially at $2 a bottle. It makes the simmering liquid a joy to inhale, and also adds complexity to the final dish.</p>
        <p>Preparation is simple. You first boil the soy and wine along with some water and the crushed sugar, adding star anise, ginger and some whole scallions. The chicken is boiled too -- not simmered, but really boiled -- for 10 minutes only; it finishes cooking in the liquid with the heat turned off. Cut-up chicken or Cornish hens can be cooked the same way; the total time will be somewhat less.</p>
        <p>The chicken can be browned in the oven right away or cooked in advance and roasted a few hours later. In either case, be sure to make plenty of white rice to serve with it. Just before serving, reheat the cooking liquid and add a few minced scallions. Spoon some of this sauce over the chicken and pass some at the table for the rice.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ip saves the cooking liquid to reuse repeatedly. ''I don't know how long you can keep this sauce,'' he said. ''In China, people without refrigerators used to keep it for a long, long time, and use it whenever they could get a chicken. It gets better with age.''</p>
        <p>The liquid does improve with each use, although I would strain it and replace the ginger, scallions and star anise each time, adding extra liquid. I also recommend freezing it between uses, or refrigerating it and bringing it to a rolling boil every few days.</p>
        <p>SOY-POACHED ROAST CHICKEN  Time: 40 minutes</p>
        <p>3 cups mushroom soy sauce  3 cups mei kuei lu chiew or any floral off-dry white wine, like gewurztraminer or muscat  2 star anise  1 14-ounce box yellow rock sugar, crushed, or 1 cup white sugar  3 ounces ginger, cut into slices and bruised with side of knife  10 scallions  1 chicken, 2 1/2 to 3 pounds.</p>
        <p>1. In stockpot or narrow 6-quart pot, combine soy sauce, rice wine, 2 cups water, star anise, sugar and ginger. Bring to rolling boil. Add 6 scallions. Lower chicken gently and slowly into liquid, breast side down.</p>
        <p>2. Bring back to boil, and cook steadily for 10 minutes. Turn off heat, and turn chicken over. Let sit in hot liquid 15 minutes.</p>
        <p>3. Meanwhile, trim and mince remaining scallions and preheat oven to 500 degrees.</p>
        <p>4. Carefully remove chicken from liquid, and put in skillet or roasting pan. Roast 5 minutes, or until nicely browned; keep an eye on it -- it can burn easily. Meanwhile, reheat liquid. When chicken is ready, carve and serve with a few spoonfuls of sauce over it. Put minced scallions into a cup of sauce; pass at table to go over white rice.</p>
        <p>Yield: 4 servings.</p>
        <p>THE MINIMALIST</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
