<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Policy Change, House Republicans Call for Government Guarantee of Drug Benefits</title>
    <meta content="Y14DRU$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207335"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Health Insurance</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pear, Robert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Thomas, Bill (Repr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Health Care Policy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Pharmaceutical, Biotechnology and Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E6DE133EF937A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1005" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Policy Change, House Republicans Call for Government Guarantee of Drug Benefits</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT PEAR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pear, Robert</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>House Republicans, after insisting for months that private insurance is only way to provide prescription drug benefits to elderly, hold federal government must be insurer of last resort to guarantee that drug coverage is available to all Medicare beneficiaries; says they will draft bill under which government will offer private insurers subsidies to cover drug costs for people on Medicare and provide coverage where no private insurers enter market; Rep Bill Thomas, who leads Republican efforts to write bill, comments; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After insisting for months that private insurance was the only way to provide prescription drug benefits to the elderly, House Republicans announced today that the federal government must be ''the insurer of last resort,'' to guarantee that drug coverage was available to all Medicare beneficiaries.</p>
        <p>The Republicans said they had nearly finished drafting a bill under which the government would offer subsidies to private insurers to cover drug costs for people on Medicare. But, they said, in places where no private insurers enter the market, the government itself should assume the financial risk and the responsibility for providing such coverage.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After insisting for months that private insurance was the only way to provide prescription drug benefits to the elderly, House Republicans announced today that the federal government must be ''the insurer of last resort,'' to guarantee that drug coverage was available to all Medicare beneficiaries.</p>
        <p>The Republicans said they had nearly finished drafting a bill under which the government would offer subsidies to private insurers to cover drug costs for people on Medicare. But, they said, in places where no private insurers enter the market, the government itself should assume the financial risk and the responsibility for providing such coverage.</p>
        <p>''The federal government, under our bill, will be the insurer of last resort,'' said Representative Bill Thomas of California, who is leading Republican efforts to write the legislation. ''Our plan does not leave seniors out in the cold if private insurance companies don't participate. Private insurers can do a great job. But we should never leave it totally to the private sector.''</p>
        <p>Republican leaders said they intended to push the legislation through the House later this month, before lawmakers go home for the Fourth of July holiday.</p>
        <p>The Senate has held many hearings on drug benefits, but has not taken any action. Senators are looking to the chairman of the Finance Committee, William V. Roth Jr. of Delaware, to lead the way.</p>
        <p>The House Republicans' decision to give the government a new role, as insurer of last resort, is a significant political step, intended to meet criticism of their earlier proposals. The criticism came from Democrats, advocates for the elderly and the Health Insurance Association of America, which said its members did not want to sell insurance covering drug costs for the elderly.</p>
        <p>The change permits Republicans to assert, as Mr. Thomas did today, that drug benefits would be ''an entitlement, available in every corner of the United States.'' But Republican leaders could lose the support of some conservatives, who are apprehensive about any expansion of the federal role in Medicare or other domestic programs.</p>
        <p>Mr. Thomas, who is chairman of the Ways and Means Subcommittee on Health, issued a summary of his proposal, which said, ''Beneficiaries will have a choice between at least two private sector drug plans.''</p>
        <p>If the options did not materialize in rural areas or other places, Mr. Thomas said, federal officials would negotiate with private insurers to get them to offer drug benefits. If such negotiations failed, he said, the government would offer drug coverage under Medicare's original fee-for-service program.</p>
        <p>Chris Jennings, the health policy coordinator at the White House, said it was difficult to assess the proposal because House Republicans had not yet introduced a bill.</p>
        <p>''Without detailed language,'' Mr. Jennings said, ''it is impossible to tell whether all Medicare beneficiaries would have access to an affordable drug benefit. We're hopeful, but dubious.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Jennings said he worried about the equity of the Republican proposal because beneficiaries in different states might have to pay very different premiums for the same drug benefits.</p>
        <p>Medicare beneficiaries now pay the same premium, $45.50 a month, for coverage under the federal program. But premiums for private insurance to fill gaps in Medicare vary widely.</p>
        <p>Ari Fleischer, a spokesman for Gov. George W. Bush of Texas, the likely Republican nominee for president, said Mr. Bush hoped Congress and the president could agree on a way to provide drug benefits this year.</p>
        <p>House Republicans said the details of drug coverage could vary from one insurance plan to another. But under a typical or standard plan, they said, a Medicare beneficiary would pay a premium of $35 to $40 a month and would have to pay the first $200 to $250 of drug expenses in a year. The government would then pay half of the next $2,000 or $2,200 of drug expenses, and the beneficiary would pay the other half.</p>
        <p>Beneficiaries would have to incur several thousand dollars of drug costs before the government provided further protection. There would be a limit on the beneficiary's out-of-pocket costs, $5,000 to $6,000 a year.</p>
        <p>By contrast, President Clinton proposed an initial premium of $26 a month, starting in 2003. Medicare would pay half the cost of each prescription, with no deductible. The premium would rise gradually, to $48 a month in 2009, and so would the basic benefit. The maximum federal payment would be $1,000, for a person with drug expenses of $2,000 or more in 2003. The maximum payment would rise to $2,500 in 2009, for a person with expenses of $5,000 or more.</p>
        <p>Mr. Thomas said it made sense for beneficiaries to pay a little more up front, so they could get more adequate coverage of high expenses. ''Most seniors are worried not about the first dollar, but about the last dollar'' of drug expenses, he said.</p>
        <p>Two conservative Democrats, Representatives Collin C. Peterson of Minnesota and Ralph M. Hall of Texas, joined Republicans in supporting Mr. Thomas's bill. Many Democrats criticized it. Mr. Clinton said it ''claims to offer something to everybody and is a false hope to most and, therefore, inadequate.''</p>
        <p>In another demonstration of the significance of the issue to lawmakers, the House today overwhelmingly passed legislation offered by Representative Bernard Sanders, a Vermont Independent, that would require ''reasonable pricing'' on drugs developed through collaboration between the National Institutes of Health and pharmaceutical companies.</p>
        <p>The legislation, a response to charges that drug companies are overcharging patients for drugs developed in part with federal money, does not establish a specific formula for pricing the drugs. But it is intended to lower some drug prices. Its prospects in the Senate are unclear.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
