<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Syrians Bury Only Leader Many of Them Ever Knew</title>
    <meta content="Y14SYR$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207288"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">France-International Relations-Syria</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Syria</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">France</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Damascus (Syria)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sachs, Susan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Assad, Hafez Al- (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chirac, Jacques (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Syria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Syria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Syria/Damascus</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01EED9123EF937A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="787" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Syrians Bury Only Leader Many of Them Ever Knew</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUSAN SACHS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sachs, Susan</byline>
      <dateline>DAMASCUS, Syria, June 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Syrian Pres Hafez al-Assad is buried in hometown of Qardaha after daylong rites across nation; funeral procession, which began in Damascus, draws tens of thousands of people; French Pres Jacques Chirac is only Western head of state to attend; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hafez al-Assad was buried today in his hilltop hometown after daylong ceremonies across the country. Wailing countrymen mourned him as the father of modern Syria.</p>
        <p>The late president, who died three days ago at the age of 69, was eulogized as the guardian of stability and Arab pride in the country he ruled for 30 years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Hafez al-Assad was buried today in his hilltop hometown after daylong ceremonies across the country. Wailing countrymen mourned him as the father of modern Syria.</p>
        <p>The late president, who died three days ago at the age of 69, was eulogized as the guardian of stability and Arab pride in the country he ruled for 30 years.</p>
        <p>Here where a vast majority of people are not yet 30, Mr. Assad was the only leader many Syrians knew.  Over the years he developed a personality cult that proclaimed him as indispensable to the nation.</p>
        <p>His funeral procession, which began in Damascus and ended in his hometown of Qardaha, 200 miles to the north, drew tens of thousands of people, some fainting in the heat.</p>
        <p>''I had to come out of love for the president,'' said Sana Asse, a 32-year-old housewife who stood unsteadily in the blinding sunlight in hopes of catching a glimpse of Mr. Assad's coffin.</p>
        <p>''It's the duty of all Syrians to say goodbye to our father,'' she added. ''He is the big father to all of us.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Assad's death, like that of a family patriarch, represented the end of an era. During much of his rule, cold war politics defined Arab relations with the outside world, and power changed hands through assassination, coups and subterfuge.</p>
        <p>Mr. Assad was an absolute monarch in all but name, and his successor seems likely to follow that pattern. In the days since his death, the machinery of his tightly controlled one-party state has been set in motion to see that his son Bashar succeeds him. The younger Assad, a 34-year-old ophthalmologist, acted as unofficial head of state in welcoming foreign leaders and diplomats who came to pay respects to his father.</p>
        <p>Hafez al-Assad was the last of a small club of leaders who commanded troops in the 1967 Arab-Israeli war -- the defining event that redrew the map of the Middle East -- and who were forever haunted by its consequences. Syria lost the Golan Heights. Mr. Assad was minister of defense at the time.</p>
        <p>Egypt, under Anwar el-Sadat, made peace with Israel and recovered the Sinai. Jordan, under King Hussein, relinquished claims to the West Bank and made peace.</p>
        <p>But Syria under Mr. Assad made it a point of pride to resist any peace that did not meet its conditions for a full return of every inch of the Golan Heights. In the waning years of his rule, Mr. Assad's insistence did not bring him the admiration of the Arab world that it once did.</p>
        <p>The price to Syria was evident at the state funeral. Unlike the funeral of King Hussein, attended by many world leaders, only one Western head of state, President Jacques Chirac of France, came to Damascus. President Clinton sent Secretary of State Madeleine K. Albright.</p>
        <p>Some Syrians said they felt hurt, but also insisted that they did not care. ''Okay, too bad for Clinton,'' said Zohair Ibrahim, a 37-year-old government worker who traveled from the city of Tartus to see the funeral procession in the capital.  Then he added: ''I believe Clinton really wanted to come but the Jewish lobby and the election campaign prevented him.''</p>
        <p>For many people, Mr. Assad was revered because he changed their lives. Although Syria lags behind many of its Middle East neighbors because the president was reluctant to discard its socialist-style economy, older Syrians said they judge their progress on a longer timeline.</p>
        <p>Ali Hassan, a 50-year-old farmer from the city of Homs, said he walked 100 miles from his home to the last stop of Mr. Assad's cortege.  He said he remembers the pre-Assad days in Syria, when 14 presidents came and went in the space of 23 years. But the 15th, Mr. Assad, stayed in power and brought electricity and schools to the rural areas.</p>
        <p>''Before him we lived in darkness,'' Mr. Hassan said. ''I had to go to sleep at sunset because we had no electricity. Now I can stay up and read and my sons can study for school and we have fresh water.</p>
        <p>''Before him,'' he added, ''there were always coups and we were always living in insecurity and instability. President Assad turned Syria into a secure and modern country. Although we have economic problems, there are those problems all over the world.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
