<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Italians Grant Pardon to Turk Who Shot Pope</title>
    <meta content="14ITAL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207298"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Assassinations and Attempted Assassinations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Amnesties and Pardons</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Italy</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Turkey</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Roman Catholic Church</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pope (John Paul II)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stanley, Alessandra</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ciampi, Carlo Azeglio (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Agca, Mehmet Ali</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Turkey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Turkey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Amnesties and Pardons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Assassinations and Attempted Assassinations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E6D7123EF937A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1080" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Italians Grant Pardon to Turk Who Shot Pope</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALESSANDRA STANLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stanley, Alessandra</byline>
      <dateline>ROME, Wednesday, June 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Italian Pres Carlo Azeglio Ciampi, acting at Vatican urging, has pardoned Mehmet Ali Agca, Turkish gunman who tried to kill Pope John Paul II in May 1981; Agca is extradited to Turkey, where he could face more prison time for 1978 murder; Vatican has made forgiveness Holy Year theme; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The president of Italy on Tuesday pardoned Mehmet Ali Agca, the Turkish gunman who tried to kill Pope John Paul II on May 13, 1981, clearing the way for his extradition to Turkey.</p>
        <p>As President Carlo Azeglio Ciampi signed the order, the Italian Justice Ministry put the extradition in motion. Mr. Agca, 42, was convicted in absentia in Turkey of the murder of a Turkish journalist in 1978, and could face more prison time there.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The president of Italy on Tuesday pardoned Mehmet Ali Agca, the Turkish gunman who tried to kill Pope John Paul II on May 13, 1981, clearing the way for his extradition to Turkey.</p>
        <p>As President Carlo Azeglio Ciampi signed the order, the Italian Justice Ministry put the extradition in motion. Mr. Agca, 42, was convicted in absentia in Turkey of the murder of a Turkish journalist in 1978, and could face more prison time there.</p>
        <p>He left Italy late Tuesday and arrived at Ataturk International Airport in Istanbul early this morning.</p>
        <p>''This is a dream, I cannot believe it,'' Marina Magistrelli, Mr. Agca's lawyer, quoted him as saying on Tuesday when she told him the news. He had long hoped to be sent back to Turkey to finish paying his legal debt and retire to a rural village, she said. She said he thanked ''the Holy Father, the Vatican and the president of the republic.''</p>
        <p>The pardon, presented as a ''humanitarian'' act by the government, seemed prompted by Italy's close relations with the Vatican, which has campaigned for Mr. Agca's release and made forgiveness a theme of this Roman Catholic Holy Year.</p>
        <p>The clemency was granted exactly one month after the Vatican revealed the so-called Third Secret of Fatima, saying that the long-suppressed prophecy by the Virgin of Fatima foretold the 1981 attempt on the pope's life.</p>
        <p>The Vatican spokesman, Joaquin Navarro-Valls, said, ''The pardon, which took place during the celebration of the Holy Year, makes the personal satisfaction of the Holy Father even greater.''</p>
        <p>Under Italian law, the Justice Ministry could not extradite Mr. Agca until he had served his full sentence  or been pardoned. But the Italian government made it clear that the pardon was largely inspired by the Vatican. ''In the last few days, the Holy See confirmed its favor for the clemency act,'' a Justice Ministry statement said today.</p>
        <p>Mr. Agca has been in jail since 1981 and was convicted in 1986 of shooting John Paul II at close range during a general audience of 10,000 people in St. Peter's square. He was sentenced to life in prison, and had most recently been in Montacuto prison near Ancona.</p>
        <p>Mr. Agca, his mother and his lawyer had lobbied the Vatican and the  government for years. Mrs. Magistrelli began legal procedures in 1994.</p>
        <p>The pope forgave his would-be assassin from his hospital bed in 1981 and visited Mr. Agca in his cell in 1983. At their meeting, Mr. Agca kissed the pope's ring. In March, 1999, church officials formally let Italian authorities know that the Vatican would favor Mr. Agca's release.</p>
        <p>The pope, who was severely wounded by a shot to the abdomen, recovered from the attack, and credited the Virgin of Fatima, whose feast day falls on May 13, the day of the assassination attempt, for saving his life. In May, he made his third pilgrimage to the shrine of Fatima.</p>
        <p>There, the pope's secretary of state revealed the so-called ''third secret'' of Fatima, what believers say was an undisclosed prophecy revealed to three Portuguese shepherd children by an apparition of the Virgin Mary in 1917. Cardinal Angelo Sodano said the prophecy foretold an attack on a ''bishop clothed in white,'' which the Vatican interpreted as a prediction of the 1981 assassination attempt. The Vatican said it would release the full message soon.</p>
        <p>The Vatican interpretation of the secret was happily accepted by Mr. Agca, who among many conflicting claims in his 1983 trial, said the shooting ''is connected to the third secret of the Madonna of Fatima.'' Mrs. Magistrelli said he felt ''he was part of a larger design.''</p>
        <p>But the erratic defendant also at one point claimed during his trial, ''I knew that the K.G.B. wanted to kill the pope.'' Italian prosecutors tried to pin down reports that Mr. Agca, who escaped in 1979 from a Turkish prison where he was being held on the earlier charges, had ties to Bulgarian secret agents and may have been acting for the Soviet Union, but were unable to prove the charges.</p>
        <p>Mr. Agca had ties during his student days to a nationalist neofascist group in Turkey, the National Action Party, and the gun used to kill the editor, who was known to have politically liberal views, had been supplied by the party's youth wing.</p>
        <p>Mr. Agca was originally given the death penalty for the 1978 murder, but his sentence was reduced during a 1991 amnesty. Eight years remain in his sentence, he said. News reports in Turkey on Tuesday suggested that Mr. Agca might benefit from a new amnesty and could soon be released.</p>
        <p>John Paul II, who turned 80 last month, plans to visit a Roman prison next month and say Mass there as part of a Jubilee day devoted to prisoners. It is likely that the pope will call for better conditions and clemency for some prisoners.</p>
        <p>Cardinal Camillo Ruini, leader of the Italian bishops' conference, gave a kind of preview of Vatican thinking last month, when he called for ''more humane'' treatment of prisoners and ''measures of clemency.''</p>
        <p>The pope has frequently spoken out on the dignity of prisoners and their rights. Italy's prisons are overcrowded, and there have been a few riots during the last year. But the government's decision to pardon Mr. Agca is not out of the legal norm.</p>
        <p>Many Italian prisoners are released before serving full sentences. Most of the Red Brigades terrorists who were convicted in the 1980's of bombings and assassinations, for example, have been set free or allowed to enter work-release programs.</p>
        <p>''All the conditions were there to release Agca,'' Rosario Priore, a prominent Italian judge who worked as an investigative prosecutor on cases linked to Mr. Agca, told the news service ANSA. ''The pope's forgiveness, his long stay in jail. No one stays 20 years in prison.'' He added, however, that he was not satisfied that the full story had come out.</p>
        <p>Dr. Navarro-Valls said on Tuesday, ''as to the truth of what happened on May 13, 1981, history can still uncover many things.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
