<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Filmmaker Without Honor Or Outlets in Her Own Land</title>
    <meta content="14CIVI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207239"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ARTS ABROAD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Civilized People, A (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E0DF123EF937A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1190" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Filmmaker Without Honor Or Outlets in Her Own Land</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN RIDING</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, June 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alan Riding Arts Abroad column discusses film A Civilized People, which will open Human Rights Watch International Film Festival in New York; photo; Randa Chahal Sabbag says her account of Lebanese civil war is meant to remind her compatriots that they are all responsible for collective madness that led to 17 years of kiling each other; film has not been shown in Lebanon because Sabbag rejected censorship cuts (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Randa Chahal Sabbag insists that her new film about the Lebanese civil war, ''A Civilized People,'' was not designed to shock. Rather, she says, she simply wanted to remind her compatriots of the collective madness that led them to spend the best part of 17 years killing one another and destroying their country. Of course this filmmaker also wanted to air a few thoughts of her own.</p>
        <p>''It angers and disgusts me to hear Lebanese saying that they were only victims of the war,'' Mrs. Sabbag, who was born in Tripoli, explained in an interview in her home in Paris, where she lives with her husband and three children. ''It was our war, and we should not play the innocent. I tell my story through people of all classes and religions as a way of saying that all Lebanese are responsible for the war. Unless we accept responsibility for every bullet, we will never become a nation.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Randa Chahal Sabbag insists that her new film about the Lebanese civil war, ''A Civilized People,'' was not designed to shock. Rather, she says, she simply wanted to remind her compatriots of the collective madness that led them to spend the best part of 17 years killing one another and destroying their country. Of course this filmmaker also wanted to air a few thoughts of her own.</p>
        <p>''It angers and disgusts me to hear Lebanese saying that they were only victims of the war,'' Mrs. Sabbag, who was born in Tripoli, explained in an interview in her home in Paris, where she lives with her husband and three children. ''It was our war, and we should not play the innocent. I tell my story through people of all classes and religions as a way of saying that all Lebanese are responsible for the war. Unless we accept responsibility for every bullet, we will never become a nation.''</p>
        <p>This is a proposition, however, that the Lebanese have been unable to debate. When Mrs. Sabbag submitted her drama for approval by Lebanon's Interior Ministry last year, she was told that the film would give the country a bad image abroad, that it used excessively vulgar language, and that it insulted both Islam and Christianity. The ministry's military censors then proposed cuts representing about 50 minutes of the 97-minute film. Mrs. Sabbag refused to accept them.</p>
        <p>Still unseen in Lebanon, ''A Civilized People'' has been chosen to open the Human Rights Watch International Film Festival at 9:15 on Wednesday night in the Walter Reade Theater at Lincoln Center. Further screenings will take place at 3:45 p.m. on Thursday, 6:30 p.m. on Friday and 1 p.m. on Monday. Mrs. Sabbag, 45, is also to be awarded the Nestor Almendros Prize for courage in filmmaking, named after the Academy Award-winning Cuban cinematographer who spoke out against human rights abuses in his country.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Sabbag's film is not itself overtly political: it addresses neither the merits of the numerous factions engaged in the war nor the 1991 peace accord that proclaimed no winners or losers and enabled innumerable war crimes to go unpunished under a general amnesty. The film's purpose, though, is political: by revisiting the hatred that drove the conflict, she hopes that her countrymen (and women) can draw some conclusions about their behavior, she said.</p>
        <p>Adopting something of the soap-operatic structure of Pedro Almodovar movies, ''A Civilized People'' dwells on a dozen or so characters whose lives are variously battered and twisted by the war. These include not only Christian and Muslim combatants (Samir, a particularly deranged Christian sniper, is played by Mrs. Sabbag's brother, Tamim Chahal) but also a private chauffeur whose son has been kidnapped, a wealthy woman who arrives from France to rejoin her lover, a Christian girl who falls for a Muslim fighter and children who urge their elders to kidnap foreigners for ransom.</p>
        <p>The film's opening sequence well illustrates the cheapness of life in the 1980's in Beirut: two young men blow themselves up while tying explosives on the back of a cat. The only ''civilized people'' in the movie are maids from Egypt, Sri Lanka and the Philippines who have been left in charge of homes abandoned by bourgeois Lebanese exiles. A French volunteer from Doctors Without Borders, on the other hand, is portrayed as an unwelcome interfering foreigner.</p>
        <p>Most of the objections presented by the Lebanese censors relate to language and scenes thought to be offensive to religious groups, not only religious and sexual expletives but also one scene in which a coffin is kicked into an open grave and another in which the crazed Samir shoots a Catholic priest. The censors also complained about the portrayal of physical affection between two Egyptian maids who are lesbians.</p>
        <p>After the censors published their list of proposed cuts, Mrs. Sabbag was denounced in some Beirut mosques, and she and her crew were subjected to death threats. She also found much of the Beirut press lined up against her, with the local English-language newspaper, The Daily Star, saying she had no reason ''to expect the authorities in her troubled homeland to subject a still-recovering populace to the shocking scenes and repulsive profanity that mar her latest effort.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Sabbag said that only after a few journalists saw the film on cassette did some begin to defend her. She also began negotiating with Sunni Muslim leaders -- she is herself Sunni -- and agreed to cover four offensive passages with bleeps. ''I did so to save the film and protect my family and also because my lawyers told me there is a law of blasphemy in Lebanon,'' she explained. But so far the French-financed film has only been released, to mixed reviews, in France.</p>
        <p>''I think the film is very sweet, much sweeter than many American films,'' Mrs. Sabbag said. ''How can I make a film about war without any images of violence or insults or blood? How can you make a film about life without showing life? Or it is because I am a woman that they want me to make something different? I didn't try to provoke. I could have made something far more provocative.''</p>
        <p>Certainly ''A Civilized People'' is infinitely less violent and blasphemous than what occurred during the Lebanese civil war. On the other hand, while Lebanon is not the first country to opt for amnesia over self-examination after emerging from a period of fratricidal, ethnic or religious conflict, the controversy surrounding the film is a measure of the fragility of its current peace, a peace that has still not turned Lebanon into a fully democratic and independent nation.</p>
        <p>For Mrs. Sabbag, though, the film is also a reminder that she has become something of an outsider in her own country. Although she frequently visited Lebanon to film during the civil war, she has kept a home in Paris since she moved here to study cinema in 1972. Furthermore, while her documentary ''Nos Guerres Imprudentes'' and her two previous dramatic feature films, ''Ecrans de Sable'' and ''Les Infideles,'' dealt with Middle Eastern subjects, they have only been seen in France and at film festivals.</p>
        <p>Yet if her family and career are in France, her heart is still in Lebanon, she said. Before flying to New York for Wednesday's screening of her movie, she spent a week in southern  Lebanon filming the aftermath of the Israeli withdrawal.</p>
        <p>''I've been following a woman who for 10 years was a prisoner of the South Lebanon Army,'' she said. ''I'm thinking of making a documentary about her.''</p>
        <p>ARTS ABROAD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
