<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Liberties; Belaboring, Not Bedazzling</title>
    <meta content="14DOWD$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207317"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dowd, Maureen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/Maureen Dowd</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E7DF133EF937A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="758" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Liberties; Belaboring, Not Bedazzling</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MAUREEN DOWD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dowd, Maureen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Maureen Dowd Op-Ed column on Vice Pres Al Gore's performance in his interview with New York Times writers and editors; cites what she perceives as his long-winded evasion of questions; complains both Gore and Gov George W Bush never say anything, Gore because he knows a lot but is afraid to damage his campaign and Bush because he does not know much and lets others script opinions that will not mar campaign (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Al Gore met yesterday with Times writers and editors. The first question put to him was: How do you assess George W. Bush as a candidate?</p>
        <p>The vice president spoke 1,565 words, really, really slowly, with glacial pauses between each word. He propounded and expounded for more than 15 minutes, touching on such diverse topics as the human genome, the ice-free future of the Arctic Ocean, the ''Star Wars'' journey, the climate of New York City, federal entitlements, the climate of Atlanta, embassy security, the climate of Illinois, Individual Development Accounts, the climate of Oklahoma and the state of the U.S. economy in 1835. But despite some prodding, he never did get around to answering.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Al Gore met yesterday with Times writers and editors. The first question put to him was: How do you assess George W. Bush as a candidate?</p>
        <p>The vice president spoke 1,565 words, really, really slowly, with glacial pauses between each word. He propounded and expounded for more than 15 minutes, touching on such diverse topics as the human genome, the ice-free future of the Arctic Ocean, the ''Star Wars'' journey, the climate of New York City, federal entitlements, the climate of Atlanta, embassy security, the climate of Illinois, Individual Development Accounts, the climate of Oklahoma and the state of the U.S. economy in 1835. But despite some prodding, he never did get around to answering.</p>
        <p>He simply kept exhaustively not answering in that formal voice that sounds as though he has to guide his listeners by the hand, no matter how well they know the subject.</p>
        <p>All . . . those . . . drawn . . . out . . . syllables . . . signifying . . . nothing . . . had . . . a . . . soporific . . . effect . . . on . . . me. But when I snapped back to attention, I hadn't missed a thing.</p>
        <p>The vice president was apologizing for being long-winded and belaboring points, even as he continued to belabor long-winded points.</p>
        <p>Once eyes began to glaze, Mr. Gore happily slipped in his new happy maxims: ''Prosperity and progress,'' ''Ideas and not insults,'' the Popeyesque ''I am who I am,'' and, on his lack of appeal to women, ''All in due time.''</p>
        <p>Asked if Governor Bush had made better use of the last two months, Farmer Al sanguinely offered this Chauncey Gardiner moment: ''When you plant seeds you don't know what the crop will be like just by the way the planting has occurred.''</p>
        <p>It was enough to make you miss the old slashing Al.</p>
        <p>One editor tried to get past the filibuster by asking: ''Well, is campaigning going to be about ideas or is it going to be about mostly personality and character?''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore replied with a treatise on post-World-War-II America and another plug for his plans for clean air, clean energy and health care.</p>
        <p>And that's the problem with this race. One guy says a lot but never says anything. The other guy doesn't say a lot and never says anything.</p>
        <p>One knows a lot but is afraid to offer opinions that will mar his chance to be president. The other doesn't know a lot so he just lets his brain trust script opinions that will not mar his chance to be president.</p>
        <p>An individual who overcalculates versus a group that overcalculates.</p>
        <p>Take the death penalty. Mr. Bush opened himself up on the issue by first bragging that all the prisoners executed on his watch in Texas were guilty. Then he issued his first reprieve in a move that seemed politically inspired.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Gore is so afraid of reviving the old Democratic label of being soft on capital punishment that he can't capitalize on the issue despite fresh evidence that the administration of the death penalty is seriously flawed. A new Columbia University study found that two of every three death sentences are overturned on appeal.</p>
        <p>Asked repeatedly at The Times whether he is comfortable with the death penalty now, Mr. Gore weaved and waffled.</p>
        <p>On his way out he was asked by Brent Staples, an editorial writer: What margin of error for mistaken executions could you accept?</p>
        <p>That should be easy to answer,  even for someone who likes to hedge: Zero. But Mr. Gore simply reiterated that he thought the level of error was low.</p>
        <p>One question he answered succinctly and maybe even candidly. After some frustrating exchanges on missile defense and the death penalty, Michael Oreskes, the Washington bureau chief, asked him: ''Is it possible for a candidate to be too careful?''</p>
        <p>''Yes,'' Mr. Gore said, adding carefully: ''Did my answer sound too careful?''</p>
        <p>He was asked if he noticed a ''disconnect'' between what he was talking about and what Americans are interested in. Napoleon, the questioner said, observed that if you position yourself on the right ground, you win the battle.</p>
        <p>''Napoleon,'' Mr. Gore shot back, ''also invented canned food.''</p>
        <p>At long last, an answer that didn't sound canned.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
