<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Everyone Talks About Sosa as He Helps Cubs Beat Mets</title>
    <meta content="14METS$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207374"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Chicago Cubs</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kepner, Tyler</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Chicago Cubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E4DD133EF937A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1192" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Everyone Talks About Sosa as He Helps Cubs Beat Mets</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kepner, Tyler</byline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO, June 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Chicago Cubs defeat New York Mets, 4-3; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The question is on  everyone's mind here  what is going to happen with Sammy Sosa? -- and when the man himself was asked it, his reply said everything and nothing all at once.</p>
        <p>''What's going to happen,'' said Sosa, the Cubs' outfielder who may soon be on the move, ''is I have to play tonight at 7:05 and I have to get ready.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The question is on  everyone's mind here  what is going to happen with Sammy Sosa? -- and when the man himself was asked it, his reply said everything and nothing all at once.</p>
        <p>''What's going to happen,'' said Sosa, the Cubs' outfielder who may soon be on the move, ''is I have to play tonight at 7:05 and I have to get ready.''</p>
        <p>The Mets were in town, and, yes, Sosa's Cubs had a game to play in a few hours. The Cubs would win, 4-3, when Kurt Abbott threw wildly to first in the eighth inning, costing the Mets an inning-ending double play and bringing in the go-ahead run off John Franco, the loser.</p>
        <p>But the off-field story was most intriguing. The Cubs are exploring the possibility of trading their franchise player, and they had two scouts in Norfolk, Va., last night to watch a game between the Mets' and Yankees' Class AAA teams.</p>
        <p>When swarmed by reporters before the game, Sosa said repeatedly that he had ''no control'' over what would happen. But as a player with 10 years of service and the last five with the same team, Sosa must approve a trade.</p>
        <p>''I'll hopefully stay here,'' he said, ''but if it's not going to work out, something's going to happen.''</p>
        <p>His teammates have no idea what is on his mind. But considering all Sosa has done for baseball, outfielder Henry Rodriguez said, he deserves to get what he wants. And Sosa would seem very likely to accept a trade to New York, which he again referred to today as his ''second home,'' the first being his native Dominican Republic.</p>
        <p>''Last year, they honored him with the key to New York City, and he felt great -- we talked about that and he was just crazy about it,'' Rodriguez said. ''After he came back from New York, he was talking about how they treated him, how they honored him, all those great things. He said he liked it. If he goes there, I'm sure he's going to like it.''</p>
        <p>But if Sosa was talkative about New York last year, he has not told his teammates much about his current situation.</p>
        <p>''I always have fun; I hope Sammy's having fun,'' first baseman Mark Grace said. ''That's all I want -- I just want Sammy to be happy.''</p>
        <p>Sosa said he is happy. ''I'm just happy to be alive,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But what drives him? In his locker, he has a photo of the Yankees celebrating their 1998 World Series title, perhaps a reminder that the goal is to win. But he would also like a contract extension, and might command up to $20 million a season for five or six years.</p>
        <p>''They've got some idea, but I don't think that's what it's about,'' Sosa's agent, Adam Katz, said about the slugger's position on a contract. ''If they want to do a deal, it can be done. They have to make a decision on which road they want to go down.''</p>
        <p>Katz, who said there were no active negotiations with the Cubs right now, said Sosa's preference is to stay with the Cubs and that Sosa has not requested a trade.</p>
        <p>''I don't want to be the one to look like the bad guy,'' Sosa said. ''I don't have anything to do with it. I just want to play my game.''</p>
        <p>General Manager Ed Lynch -- who would seemingly be the ''bad guy'' if Sosa were traded -- said, ''I don't have a strong appetite to move him, but it's my job to listen to any deal that could make us measurably better.''</p>
        <p>The Mets have inquired -- General Manager Steve Phillips called Lynch last Friday -- but they now believe it is up to the Cubs to make the next move. While acknowledging Sosa's veto power over trades, Lynch outlined his options with a player whose contract expires after next season.</p>
        <p>''We trade him, we extend him or we let the contract run out,'' Lynch said. ''At this point, any of the three is a possibility.''</p>
        <p>Sosa was 1 for 4 tonight, lining a double to left in the first and scoring when Grace doubled. Those were the only extra-base hits Rick Reed allowed on a night when he issued no walks in six and two-thirds innings.</p>
        <p>Reed said he watched video of himself from his first start of the year, and found he was doing ''a million things'' wrong mechanically. He corrected those flaws and was satisfied with the effort.</p>
        <p>Abbott thought he did nothing wrong on the decisive wild throw. With one out and runners on first and second, first baseman Todd Zeile fielded a Glenallen Hill grounder and fired to second for a force. Franco raced for first, and his momentum pulled him toward the base, making him unable to reach across his body for Abbott's throw inside the bag.</p>
        <p>Before Rey Ordonez's name was mentioned afterward, Abbott invoked it himself. He is filling in for Ordonez for another month while the Gold Glove shortstop recovers from a broken bone in his forearm.</p>
        <p>''Abbott makes error to lose game,'' Abbott said, trying to predict the headline. ''If Ordonez was here, he'd still be playing.''</p>
        <p>Abbott said: ''That's how I think people are thinking. I don't know if that's being insecure, but that's probably how it is.''</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>ADAM KATZ, who represents the Mets' No. 1 draft choice, the Loyola Marymount left-hander BILLY TRABER, said negotiations with the Mets were ''slow going so far.'' . . . The Class AAA right-hander PAUL WILSON worked six strong innings tonight, allowing one run on four hits and no walks in Norfolk's 5-1 loss to Columbus. . . . Hoping to take advantage of JAY PAYTON's power with the wind blowing out at Wrigley Field tonight, Mets Manager BOBBY VALENTINE put Payton in the leadoff spot for the first time this season. Payton went 0 for 4. Left fielder JASON TYNER batted eighth. . . . BENNY AGBAYANI has not started since May 31, and he called Phillips on Monday to tell him of his frustration. ''I just explained I thought I should be playing,'' Agbayani said.'' . . . The Mets recovered their official 1986 World Series championship banner, which was stolen on opening day of 1987 and was found Tuesday when the police seized it at a Queens auction house. The Mets plan to raise their real flag for the first time next week.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
