<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Russian Officials Flesh Out Alternative Antimissile Proposal</title>
    <meta content="Y14MOS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207302"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Missiles and Missile Defense Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Arms Control and Limitation and Disarmament</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gordon, Michael R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Putin, Vladimir V (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sergeyev, Igor (Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cohen, William S (Sec)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Missiles and Missile Defense Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Arms Control and Limitation and Disarmament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E3D7123EF937A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="828" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Russian Officials Flesh Out Alternative Antimissile Proposal</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL R. GORDON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gordon, Michael R</byline>
      <dateline>MOSCOW, June 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Russian Pres Vladimir V Putin and Defense Min Igor Sergeyev describe for Defense Sec William S Cohen system Russia develops that could protect both Russia and United States by shooting down missiles soon after they are launched; also propose use of 'theater' anitimissile systems to protect Europe; these systems, used to shoot down short- and medium-range missiles, are allowed by 1972 Antiballistic Missile Treaty (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Russian officials have told the United States that they are developing a system that is capable of shooting down ballistic missiles soon after they are launched, a senior United States official said today.</p>
        <p>Moscow has yet to provide details about the new system, but after weeks of vague and confusing statements, the Russians have finally begun to flesh out their plan in meetings here with Defense Secretary William S. Cohen.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Russian officials have told the United States that they are developing a system that is capable of shooting down ballistic missiles soon after they are launched, a senior United States official said today.</p>
        <p>Moscow has yet to provide details about the new system, but after weeks of vague and confusing statements, the Russians have finally begun to flesh out their plan in meetings here with Defense Secretary William S. Cohen.</p>
        <p>''Things have become a bit clearer,'' a senior Pentagon official said. ''The Russians claim they have a new system under development that focuses on intercepting missiles in the boost phase,'' or shortly after they have been launched.</p>
        <p>The two sides, however, still have strong and potentially unbridgeable differences about how to defend against a missile threat posed by nations like North Korea, Iran and Iraq, and the seriousness of the threat.</p>
        <p>The Russian plan, first floated as an idea by President Vladimir V. Putin on the eve of a summit meeting with President Clinton, represents an important evolution in Moscow's political strategy to counter the Clinton administration's antimissile defense plan.</p>
        <p>The Kremlin has steadfastly opposed Washington's proposal to deploy 100 interceptors and a battle-management radar system in Alaska and has insisted that it would violate the Antiballistic Missile Treaty the United States signed with the Soviet Union in 1972.</p>
        <p>On that point the Clinton administration agrees, but it has asked the Russian government to amend the treaty to accommodate the American plan. While Washington insists that its plan could not neutralize Russia's large nuclear force, Moscow fears that it is a first step toward a grander American antimissile scheme.</p>
        <p>Recently, however, Moscow decided that the best way to argue against the American position was not simply to give a flat ''no,'' but to propose an alternative -- one which would have little ability against Russian strategic forces but which would still protect the United States from emerging missile threats.</p>
        <p>At first, United States officials complained that the Russian plan was distressingly vague. But President Putin and Defense Minister Igor Sergeyev clarified the Russian thinking today with Secretary Cohen. According to Mr. Cohen, there are two main elements to the Russian plan. One would create a system to protect American and Russian territory by shooting down missiles as they are launched. In the case of North Korea, for example, antimissile interceptors would be deployed near the Korean peninsula and destroy North Korean missiles as they ascend.</p>
        <p>The second element of the Russian plan would use ''theater'' antimissile systems to protect Europe. These are systems that are allowed by the 1972 treaty, and which are used to shoot down short- and medium-range missiles.</p>
        <p>Regarding the so-called boost-phase approach, the Russians say they are developing a new defensive system. And some American scientists, including Richard L. Garwin of the Council on Foreign Relations, have also argued that such an approach is more promising than the Clinton administration's plan.</p>
        <p>They say it is easier to hit a large missile as it ascends than to intercept fast-flying warheads in space, as the White House has proposed. And they have also argued that a boost-phase approach could be the basis of a political compromise between Moscow and Washington.</p>
        <p>Still, the Pentagon remains skeptical. Mr. Cohen said he doubted that the Russian system could be developed by 2005, the deadline for the first phase of the antimissile program planned by the Clinton administration. ''We are willing to listen to proposals about a boost-phase intercept system, but our understanding is that it requires a great deal of technical challenge,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Among the difficulties, Mr. Cohen asserted that it would be hard to develop an interceptor that could distinguish between a missile's flame and the missile itself and hit it in time.</p>
        <p>American and Russian experts plan to meet to discuss antimissile technology in more detail. Pentagon officials insist that the discussions indicate that the two sides are approaching the missile defense issue in a business-like manner.</p>
        <p>But Moscow and Washington still have huge differences. For one thing, the Russians view their plan as a substitute for the American system, while the Pentagon says that it is, at best, a supplement.</p>
        <p>For another, Russia continues to oppose the Clinton administration's insistence that the ABM treaty be amended to permit the testing and deployment of a national missile defense system. The Russians also say the two sides should put more emphasis on political efforts to dissuade third world nations from building long-range missiles.</p>
        <p>''Pulling out of the 1972 ABM commitment would amount to restarting the arms race," Marshal Sergeyev said today.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
