<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Captain Is Back Where He Belongs</title>
    <meta content="13MESS$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/13/sports/13MESS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230177"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Rangers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lapointe, Joe</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Messier, Mark</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nedved, Petr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000913T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE0DD1438F930A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1731" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Captain Is Back Where He Belongs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE LAPOINTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lapointe, Joe</byline>
      <dateline>BURLINGTON, Vt., Sept. 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mark Messier's relations with other New York Rangers seem cordial, despite past rift with Petr Nedved, at time when his interactions with other players are likely to affect bid to revive team; Messier lauds Nedved; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Between most hockey players, it would have been just a routine encounter in the corridor on the first day of training camp. But Mark Messier is not like most players. Even his small gestures carry nuance and significance.</p>
        <p>So when Petr Nedved walked by the seated Messier, tapped him on his padded leg and used the nickname ''Mess'' as his pleasant greeting, you couldn't help notice that Messier responded by looking up toward Nedved and saying, in his deep voice, ''Hey, how are ya?'' in a friendly sort of way.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Between most hockey players, it would have been just a routine encounter in the corridor on the first day of training camp. But Mark Messier is not like most players. Even his small gestures carry nuance and significance.</p>
        <p>So when Petr Nedved walked by the seated Messier, tapped him on his padded leg and used the nickname ''Mess'' as his pleasant greeting, you couldn't help notice that Messier responded by looking up toward Nedved and saying, in his deep voice, ''Hey, how are ya?'' in a friendly sort of way.</p>
        <p>When these two centers first played together on the Rangers, in 1994-95, Messier doubted Nedved's competitive fire, despite Nedved's elite talent. Messier's animosity resulted in Nedved's trade to Pittsburgh. In a game soon after that, Messier speared Nedved. As time passed, Messier left New York in 1997 for three seasons in Vancouver; Nedved returned to the Rangers in a trade in 1998; and Messier also came back, this time as an unrestricted free agent in the summer.</p>
        <p>How Messier interacts with Nedved -- and just about everyone else in the organization -- will affect this season's comprehensive attempt to revive the Rangers, who have missed the playoffs in the three seasons of Messier's exile. So far, the vibrations are good and Nedved is the personification of it.</p>
        <p>''It's water under the bridge,'' Nedved said, referring to their past difficulties. ''I was happy that the Rangers signed him. I'm looking forward to working with him and playing with him. He's going to make our team that much more dangerous. He's a great leader.''</p>
        <p>Regarding Nedved, Messier said he had researched the subject by talking with Adam Graves, Mike Richter and Brian Leetch, the only three Rangers remaining from the 1994 team that Messier led to the Stanley Cup. Those veterans praised Nedved.</p>
        <p>''Everybody here who has seen him play over the past couple years can admire his courage, his heart,'' Messier said of Nedved. ''He was battered from pillar to post without receiving the proper protection a player of his caliber should. He has played hard, game in and game out.''</p>
        <p>Messier, Nedved, Graves, Leetch and Richter should make up one-quarter of the 20-man roster being shaped by Glen Sather, the new general manager, and Ron Low, the new coach. And the presence of Sather and Low should suit Messier, whose disapproval of past coaches has led to their dismissal.</p>
        <p>Sather was the young general manager and coach in Edmonton when Messier broke into the National Hockey League as an 18-year-old rookie in 1979. Low was a veteran goalie then, assigned by Sather to be Messier's roommate on the road. Low watched him develop.</p>
        <p>''Mark was a pretty rawboned kid at that time,'' Low recalled after practice the other day at Gutterson Field House. ''He did a lot of pretty crazy things as a player. He made some horrific mistakes in his own end. But you could always count on him coming back and doing something in the other end -- the good end. He was never afraid to take a chance, to try something.''</p>
        <p>Messier is not so raw anymore and he is definitely not a kid. He is 6 feet 1 inch and listed as 210 pounds, although he appears heavier. Still bold, he is much balder and much older, among the senior athletes in professional sports. Messier will celebrate his 40th birthday in January, midway through his 22nd N.H.L. season. He is the only player still active from the World Hockey Association, which folded in 1979.</p>
        <p>In training camp, Messier appears to be gradually working himself into shape. In a scrimmage on Monday, Nedved's line dominated Messier's line with skating speed and puck movement. Perhaps this was a meaningless workout, but it also encouraged speculation about how much Messier has left. He left today's practice early with a sore groin; the injury is not serious.</p>
        <p>In his final season with the Rangers, Messier scored 36 goals. In three seasons with Vancouver, he accumulated only 52. Despite changes of coaches, general managers and players, some of them urged by Messier, the Canucks never made the playoffs while he was their captain.</p>
        <p>They could have kept Messier this season, but they chose to buy out his option and let him leave with no compensation. For the Canadian Olympic team of 1998, Messier was not selected. Although his age, diminishing production, dominant personality and $5.5 million salary would make Messier an awkward fit with some teams now, the Rangers talk as if they are the right team at the right time, just as they were in 1991 when he first came to New York from Edmonton at age 30.</p>
        <p>''It's good to have him back where I think he belongs,'' said Leetch, who gave back the captain's ''C'' to Messier. ''The Ranger jersey looks the best on him. I never really lost hope. It's going to be a big boost to a lot of veterans around here. He's a one-of-a-kind person and he certainly wears his emotions on his sleeve.''</p>
        <p>Certainly this is true: he epitomizes hockey passion. Think of Messier images over the years: stretching back his head and laughing to celebrate six Stanley Cup championships, five of them with Edmonton; or glaring, shouting and swinging at opponents during angry confrontations on ice; or wiping tears from his eyes in a Vancouver uniform during his first return to Madison Square Garden.</p>
        <p>''He never really wanted to leave New York,'' Leetch said.</p>
        <p>But he did depart after a contract tiff with Neil Smith, the former general manager, and Dave Checketts, the president of the Garden. They felt Messier had become overbearing. His departure seemed to sap the spirit of Leetch, Richter and Graves. Recently, in a Burlington restaurant, Messier, Richter and Leetch could be seen dining and discussing the team's past, present and future.</p>
        <p>''He seems the same,'' Richter said of Messier. ''Mark brings an awful lot to this locker room. And that comes down to character. We need it.'' But even a disciple like Richter senses some unease. ''At this point in his career, with the type of player that he is, it's not easy to jump teams,'' Richter said.</p>
        <p>In the hallways outside the locker rooms, Messier's presence dominates the mood. He exudes relaxed authority. Rookies like Jamie Lundmark, from junior teams, and minor league hopefuls like Dale Purinton follow Messier with their eyes as he makes his casual rounds. And people instinctively step aside when Messier walks past, just as players do when he skates on the ice. Sandy McCarthy, a fistfighting expert acquired over the summer, discussed how Messier intimidates opponents without having to throw punches the way he once did.</p>
        <p>''Everybody knows he's big and tough and you are going to get something if you mess around with him, if not a stick, an elbow,'' McCarthy said. ''That's why he gets room on the ice.''</p>
        <p>Physical intimidation was one of the topics Messier addressed while standing near the door to the coach's room for a news conference. ''Toughness and sticking up for each other is something that comes from within a team,'' Messier said. ''It does not come from individuals. Part of the problem last year was the team was fragmented, for whatever reason. The other team can sense it. They know you are not together and you are not willing to fight for each other. The whole situation last year got to be in such a downward spiral that it really just spun out of control for everybody. Nobody really knew where to turn to or what to do.''</p>
        <p>He also said players must abide by a ''code of loyalty'' that keeps internal discord private. This applied particularly to Stephane Quintal, a defenseman suspended late last season for saying he would like to leave the Rangers. Messier has granted Quintal his forgiveness.</p>
        <p>''I think the important thing for Stephane is to realize he made a mistake,'' Messier said. ''He put the integrity of the organization in jeopardy and it had to be dealt with and it was dealt with.'' According to Quintal, Messier told him: ''Don't worry about it. Go have fun.'' They should play golf or have lunch, Messier told Quintal.</p>
        <p>Messier understands mistakes: even he makes them, Messier said, ''I've made plenty of mistakes in my career and so has everyone else, and I'll continue to make mistakes.'' He said he puts them behind and lives in the present. And he also told the reporters that they, too, were part of his equation for winning.</p>
        <p>''We want to shed a good light for the public through the media,'' Messier said. ''We need to be as open and as honest as we possibly can. We want to be proud of ourselves on and off the ice. And the way to do that is for us to handle the media properly so that we convey a good message. Obviously, we did a good job of that in the years I was here. And it's important to get back to that.''</p>
        <p>He also chatted casually about returning to Manhattan and seeking an apartment on the Upper West Side he used to know. Prices are way up in this prosperous era, he said.</p>
        <p>As the day drew to a close, a black Jeep pulled up near the locker room door, his special transport to the nearby hotel through the crowd of fans waiting for autographs. Some of them wore blue and white Ranger jerseys with the name Messier and his number 11 on the back. The charismatic man who once guaranteed a victory in a crucial playoff game was not making any grand promises for the first season of his second coming to New York. Not yet, anyway.</p>
        <p>''I'm not coming back with the idea that things are going to be the same,'' Messier said. ''In a way, it's good. It keeps it exciting. Things will be different, but I think different in a good way. We want to win. The sooner the better.''</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
