<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Akron, the Talk Is About Treads</title>
    <meta content="Y13AKRO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/13/business/13AKRO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230165"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tires</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trade Shows and Fairs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recalls and Bans of Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobile Safety Features and Defects</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bridgestone Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ford Motor Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barboza, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Safety Features and Defects</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recalls and Bans of Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tires</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trade Shows and Fairs</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000913T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E0DE1438F930A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="853" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Akron, the Talk Is About Treads</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID BARBOZA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barboza, David</byline>
      <dateline>AKRON, Ohio, Sept. 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Some 2,500 people gather for International Tire Exhibition and Conference in Akron, Ohio; though scientists and industry officials gather to deliver papers that deal with tire failures and tread separation, which is at heart of Bridgestone/Firestone recall, few will speculate about what went wrong; several participants say they were legally advised not to speak about Bridgestone/Firestone and even to delete term 'tread separation' from presentations; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When the International Tire Exhibition and Conference opened here today, more than 2,500 people gathered in small meeting rooms to listen to scientists deliver papers on ''Metallic Coagents for Bonding Rubber to Metal and Synthetic Fibers'' or ''Tire Shearography.''</p>
        <p>But try as they might to focus on such topics, they could not help talking about the Firestone controversy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When the International Tire Exhibition and Conference opened here today, more than 2,500 people gathered in small meeting rooms to listen to scientists deliver papers on ''Metallic Coagents for Bonding Rubber to Metal and Synthetic Fibers'' or ''Tire Shearography.''</p>
        <p>But try as they might to focus on such topics, they could not help talking about the Firestone controversy.</p>
        <p>Though scientists and industry officials are gathering for this three-day conference to deliver papers that deal with tire failures and tread separation, which is at the heart of the huge recall, few will speculate about what went wrong.</p>
        <p>Several participants said they were legally advised not to speak about Bridgestone/Firestone and even to delete the term ''tread separation'' from presentations.</p>
        <p>Others said they had noticed a growing interest in X-ray and laser equipment that might be used to detect problems.</p>
        <p>Several executives said tire makers use such equipment in plants only sporadically because it is too expensive to test every tire. But that may be changing, they said.</p>
        <p>''The truck industry X-rays 100 percent of their tires, but the margins aren't in passenger tires to be able to X-ray each one,'' said Ted Neuhaus, a tire consultant at Laser Technology Inc. in Norristown, Pa. ''Now, though, the fear is that if it happened to one company, it could also happen to others.''</p>
        <p>Conference organizers held a news briefing this afternoon calling for the creation of a commission made up of government and industry officials to gather information about tire safety.</p>
        <p>Robert Simmons, publisher of Rubber and Plastics News, which organized the conference with its parent company, Crain Communications, said that creating such a commission would avoid greater government regulation.</p>
        <p>''My concern is that if the tire industry does not take quick, responsible action, someone else will do it for us,'' Mr. Simmons said.</p>
        <p>Many here said the Firestone brand name had been irreparably damaged.</p>
        <p>''People are talking about sooner or later this name will disappear,'' said John Choi, who sells tire-making machinery in Korea. ''People don't want tires made by Firestone.''</p>
        <p>Others suggested that the problem could be poor maintenance of the tires and the discrepancy between the inflation levels recommended by Firestone and Ford, which equipped its Explorers with the tires.</p>
        <p>Many industry officials stressed how complicated the tire-making process was and how sophisticated tires had become.</p>
        <p>In the exhibition hall, industry officials talked about how far the industry had come from the days when Charles Goodyear invented vulcanization, which helped transform Akron into the industry's birthplace.</p>
        <p>''We have doubled the life of the tire and provided all-weather traction,'' a Goodyear Tire and Rubber spokesman told a television crew.</p>
        <p>Many at the conference -- not naming names -- pointed the finger at automakers, which have pushed to keep tire prices low, and a public unwilling to pay top dollar.</p>
        <p>''People here buy tires that are cheaper than sneakers and then drive 70 miles per hour on them,'' said Jorg Jetter, who was on duty at the exhibition booth of Jet Lasersysteme, which makes equipment for the industry.</p>
        <p>Truck tires, many delegates said, are much more expensive and largely better made because of the liabilities associated with the industry.</p>
        <p>Few, though, were willing to point too harshly at Firestone, at least publicly. Several meetings, after all, were held in the Harvey S. Firestone room, and the loudspeaker announced at noon that a complimentary luncheon was sponsored by Bridgestone/Firestone.</p>
        <p>After delivering a paper on the bonding of steel cords to rubber -- the issue many investigators said might be the problem -- William J. van Ooij, a professor at the University of Cincinnati and an expert in rubber adhesion in tires, said he would not speculate about the cause of tread separation.</p>
        <p>''It's theoretically possible, but I think it's highly unlikely that it was a design problem,'' he said. ''I know Firestone, and it wouldn't be design.''</p>
        <p>Suresh Sethi, an executive at Modi, a tire equipment company in India, said that makers of autos and tires around the world were overly concerned about price and market share. Not enough thought had been given to safety, he said. ''You buy a $30,000 vehicle,'' he said, ''and what does the tire cost? The companies were trying to save $1 per tire because $1 per tire adds up to a lot. That is responsible for this.''</p>
        <p>Gunter Maass, an executive at Erhardt &amp; Leimer, a tire equipment company in Germany, said the recall was about technology. He said this would not happen in Europe.</p>
        <p>''As far as I understand, this is not the first time,'' he said, referring to a 1978 Firestone recall.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
