<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Chronicle of Uneasy Access</title>
    <meta content="13WCOL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Workplace" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Job Market" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/13/business/13WCOL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230099"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="LIFE'S WORK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Belkin, Lisa</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000913T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E4DE1638F930A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="857" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Chronicle of Uneasy Access</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LISA BELKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Belkin, Lisa</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Life's Work column bemoans author's interminable waiting for installation of digital subscriber line (DSL) and its subsequent failure to perform as expected; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR the last six months, I have been stalled on the entrance ramp to the information superhighway. Back in February I signed up for my very own digital subscriber line, or D.S.L., an Internet connection so fast that it leaves last century's must have, the 56K modem, in the dust. At least that's what the ads say. When and if I ever get D.S.L., I hope it's faster than the companies that supply it.</p>
        <p>The arc of all technology is from indulgent to indispensable. In between there is an interminable moment when everyone must have ''it'' but not everyone can get ''it,'' when the potential becomes bogged down by the infrastructure. That's why we all listened to endless busy signals on AOL several years ago.. And now that we've all become more computer savvy -- spoiled by ISDN lines and T-1 lines at the office and impatient to bring that speed home -- many of us have war stories to tell about the wait for D.S.L.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR the last six months, I have been stalled on the entrance ramp to the information superhighway. Back in February I signed up for my very own digital subscriber line, or D.S.L., an Internet connection so fast that it leaves last century's must have, the 56K modem, in the dust. At least that's what the ads say. When and if I ever get D.S.L., I hope it's faster than the companies that supply it.</p>
        <p>The arc of all technology is from indulgent to indispensable. In between there is an interminable moment when everyone must have ''it'' but not everyone can get ''it,'' when the potential becomes bogged down by the infrastructure. That's why we all listened to endless busy signals on AOL several years ago.. And now that we've all become more computer savvy -- spoiled by ISDN lines and T-1 lines at the office and impatient to bring that speed home -- many of us have war stories to tell about the wait for D.S.L.</p>
        <p>When I first sent my deposit to Flashcom, my D.S.L. provider, they told me that because of high demand, my installation would be scheduled in six to eight weeks. The visit would not be from Flashcom, but Northpoint, because, in this complicated D.S.L. world, it takes three separate companies to install any one line. So I waited two months, only to learn that the wires to my house were not up to grade.</p>
        <p>It seems this happens a lot. On average, 40 percent of would-be customers, whose computers are within proper range of a D.S.L.-equipped central telephone office, run into wiring complications. I learned this from a very nice executive way up the management ladder at Flashcom who prefers I don't use his name because the company is -- natch -- in the midst of going public. (He also directed me to a Web site, www .DSLreports.com, one of a number of sites that have sprung up for trading gripes about D.S.L. providers across the country. It made me feel much less alone.)</p>
        <p>But I'm getting ahead of my story. Flashcom sent a ''trouble ticket'' to what, way back then, was still Bell Atlantic. They are the third company in this dance, because they own the actual wires. Although I never saw any evidence that Bell Atlantic had been by, I received an e-mail message weeks later saying that the problem had been fixed and that I was scheduled for a two-hour appointment -- with Northpoint again -- to install a lot of hardware through my walls and onto my computer. When the very nice technician was finished, my desk was decorated with a pretty D.S.L. modem. Unfortunately, the lights on the modem, which were supposed to turn green, stayed red and orange instead.</p>
        <p>The problem -- surprise! -- was still the outside wires. Another ''trouble ticket'' was sent, and then Flashcom and I spent several months exchanging e-mail messages. Theirs were upbeat and peppy, saying that my outside wiring was now complete and it was time for my inside wiring. Mine were less than upbeat, saying that no, the inside wiring had already been installed, but the outside wiring was still a problem.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Bell Atlantic became Verizon, went on strike, settled and bought a 55 percent stake in Northpoint. The only thing they didn't do was fix my wires. I, on the other hand, decided to give up, get back my deposit and remain in the Stone Age. But I wouldn't go out quietly. So I called Verizon and Flashcom and asked them to comment, for this column, on why it takes more than six months to get D.S.L. service.</p>
        <p>Both companies agreed they were having growing pains. The entire industry is only two years old, explained the Flashcom executive (who does not have D.S.L. at his own house because he doesn't want to go to the trouble of getting his sub-par inside wiring replaced.) Joan Rasmussen of the public relations department at Verizon compared this to the early days of electricity, when homeowners kept their gas lamps installed  because the newfangled wiring failed so often.</p>
        <p>It might have been coincidence, but within 24 hours of my call there was a very nice Verizon technician on the pole outside my house. (A technician, by the way, who had given up on getting D.S.L. for his own house after waiting three months.) By the end of the day the lights on my modem had turned green, and it was left to me to make a few small adjustments to my computer. These didn't make my D.S.L. work, but it did disable my existing dial-up modem, leaving me with no Internet connection at all.</p>
        <p>As I write this, there is an exceedingly nice technician from Northpoint in my office, where he has been the last two hours. My D.S.L. modem works when connected to his laptop, he says, which means the problem is now my computer, and he suggests I go out and buy a new Ethernet card. While I'm out, I think I might pick up a gas lantern, just in case.</p>
        <p>LIFE'S WORK This column about the intersection of jobs and personal lives appears every other week. E-mail: Belkin@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">This column about the intersection of jobs and personal lives appears every other week. E-mail: Belkin@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
