<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Europe Lifts Sanctions on Austria, but Vows Vigilance</title>
    <meta content="Y13AUS$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/13/world/13AUST.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230180"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Austria</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">European Union</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Haider, Jorg</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Daley, Suzanne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Austria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Austria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000913T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E5DC1438F930A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1152" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Europe Lifts Sanctions on Austria, but Vows Vigilance</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUZANNE DALEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Daley, Suzanne</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, Sept. 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>European Union lift sanctions against Austria, seven months after hurriedly imposing diplomatic freeze on Vienna for bringing rightist party into governing coalition; photo; European officials warn they remain deeply concerned about Jorg Haider's Freedom Party and vow 'particular vigilance' (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The European Union lifted its sanctions against Austria today, seven months after hurriedly imposing a diplomatic freeze on Vienna for bringing a rightist party into its governing coalition.</p>
        <p>But the Europeans said they remained deeply concerned about the  Freedom Party's role in the government and vowed to maintain a ''particular vigilance.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The European Union lifted its sanctions against Austria today, seven months after hurriedly imposing a diplomatic freeze on Vienna for bringing a rightist party into its governing coalition.</p>
        <p>But the Europeans said they remained deeply concerned about the  Freedom Party's role in the government and vowed to maintain a ''particular vigilance.''</p>
        <p>The lifting of the sanctions came four days after a panel of experts issued a report on human rights and political life in Austria. The report recommended an end to the sanctions, which had increasingly become an embarrassment to the European Union.</p>
        <p>Austrian officials quickly welcomed the news.</p>
        <p>''This is a great success for Austria resulting from our patience and firmness,'' Austria's chancellor, Wolfgang Schussel, said on national television soon after the sanctions were lifted.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schussel said there had been efforts behind the scenes to suspend the measures rather than lift them and to keep them in place for a longer time or to set up a monitoring mechanism. Ultimately, all those efforts were dropped.</p>
        <p>Although the sanctions were adopted unanimously by Austria's 14 European Union partners, enthusiasm for them waned quickly as they threatened to strengthen opposition to the group and to a common European currency, particularly in a crucial referendum on the euro in Denmark this month.</p>
        <p>The sanctions -- which included a boycott of cultural exchange programs and military exercises -- did not amount to much more than a crimp in the social life of Austria's ambassadors. But critics said the sanctions went too far: they represented an unparalleled intrusion into the internal affairs of a member country and they infuriated the Austrians.</p>
        <p>Predictions that the boycott would affect tourism or the Austrian economy never came to pass. But early on the sanctions did cause some awkward diplomatic moments as various officials did their best to avoid their Austrian counterparts. At a summit meeting of the European Union in Portugal, for instance, the usual group picture was done away with because various leaders, including France's president, Jacques Chirac, did not want to be seen standing next to Mr. Schussel.</p>
        <p>In Washington today, a State Department official said that the United States was examining the European Union report but would maintain the modest diplomatic sanctions that it imposed in February to ''limit'' contacts with Austrian officials.</p>
        <p>''Our policy has not changed,'' the official said. ''We remain concerned about the Freedom Party's participation in the Austrian government.''</p>
        <p>[Canada followed the Europeans' lead, lifting its sanctions against Austria on the ground that it no longer feared Vienna would adopt policies that infringed on human rights, Reuters reported.]</p>
        <p>Throughout the weekend it seemed clear that many European Union members were eager for the sanctions to be lifted immediately. But France, which had led the move to impose the freeze and which now holds the group's rotating presidency, refused to be rushed. Its officials hinted that a monitoring system was still needed.</p>
        <p>France, however, was apparently forced to settle for the vague promise of ''vigilance.''</p>
        <p>In lifting the sanctions, the 14 members issued a joint statement in Paris this evening. ''The measures taken by the 14 were useful,'' the statement said. ''They can now be lifted.'' But the statement added:  ''The nature of the Freedom Party and its uncertain evolution remains cause for serious worry. The 14 consider that a particular vigilance should be exercised with regard to this party and the influence it exerts on the government it is a part of.''</p>
        <p>At the sanctions continued month after month, it became clear that some of the smaller European member countries felt threatened by what was happening to Austria. In Denmark, for instance, some experts believe that lifting the sanctions can help make sure that Danes vote to adopt the euro when the issue goes to a referendum on Sept. 28. Even before the joint statement was issued this evening, Danish officials were promising that the sanctions would be gone by the end of the day.</p>
        <p>By the begining of summer, signs of a thaw were already apparent. On Bastille Day, the Austrian ambassador was among the dignitaries sharing a reviewing stand with Mr. Chirac. The Belgians extended a similar invitation to their Austrian ambassador. Meanwhile, European Commission officials, trying to build a face-saving way to wriggle out of the sanctions, appointed a three-member panel to assess human rights and political life in Austria before making a recommendation on lifting the freeze.</p>
        <p>The report, issued last Friday, found that the sanctions had served a useful purpose by focusing attention on common values in the European Union and increasing the Austrian government's self-awareness. But the report said that prolonging the sanctions would be counterproductive by creating ill will from Austrians.</p>
        <p>The three experts -- Prof. Jochen Frowein, the director of the Max Planck Institure in Germany; Martti Ahtisaari, the former president of Finland, and Marcelino Oreja, a former Spanish government minister -- also gave the Schussel government high marks for taking concrete steps to fight racism, xenophobia and anti-Semitism.</p>
        <p>But they called the Freedom Party, which was led by the controversial Jorg Haider until he stepped aside in February, ''a right-wing populist party with radical elements.'' Some of its members continued to use xenophobic, even racist,  language and were not reproached in any way, they said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Haider's party became part of the current Austrian government when Chancellor Schussel and his People's Party decided that a coalition was the only way to end months of a political stalemate after the October elections.</p>
        <p>Since the sanctions were imposed, Mr. Haider has several times lashed out at Mr. Chirac. This weekend, he  stepped up his attacks, calling Mr. Chirac ''a pocket-sized Napoleon'' who had just met his ''Waterloo.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Chirac has not spoken on the issue, though other French officials have scoffed at the remarks.</p>
        <p>''Whatever decision is made by the 14, it is not a question of giving absolution'' to the Freedom Party, said the French minister for European affairs, Pierre Moscovi, on Monday. ''I don't see how the party can be exonerated.''</p>
        <p>In their statement today, the 14 European Union members also noted that the panel of experts had recommended that they develop a mechanism within the group to monitor and evaluate the commitment and performance of individual member countries with respect to ''common European values.'' And the members said they would continue to study how best to monitor, analyze and act in similar situations in the furure.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
