<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; Gaze Will Carry Flag And Hopes of Australia</title>
    <meta content="13RHOD$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/13/olympics/13RHOD.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230182"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Summer Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sydney (Australia)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Australia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rhoden, William C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gaze, Andrew</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/William C Rhoden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004/Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia/Sydney</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000913T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E2DC1438F930A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="973" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; Gaze Will Carry Flag And Hopes of Australia</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM C. RHODEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rhoden, William C</byline>
      <dateline>SYDNEY, Australia</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William C Rhoden Sports of The Times article on choice of basketball team capital Andrew Gaze to be Australia's flag-bearer during Olympic Games opening ceremony; cites reasons he is viewed as national treasure in Australia; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LAST evening, in the heart of the Olympic Village, a thousand well-wishers stood in the grand lobby of the Super Dome for an emotional send-off for the Australian Olympic team.</p>
        <p>This was an evening drenched in history: Australia was one of only five countries to play host to at least two Games, and the athletes were part of the largest team Australia (628) has ever fielded.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LAST evening, in the heart of the Olympic Village, a thousand well-wishers stood in the grand lobby of the Super Dome for an emotional send-off for the Australian Olympic team.</p>
        <p>This was an evening drenched in history: Australia was one of only five countries to play host to at least two Games, and the athletes were part of the largest team Australia (628) has ever fielded.</p>
        <p>The athletes, wearing smart olive green blazers, stood with team officials and family members as John Coates, president of the Australian Olympic Committee, talked about the continent's unbroken history of Olympic participation. They watched as previous flagbearers were introduced and came down a steep escalator. They watched a film of the country's flagbearers, from 1924 to 1996, making the famous walk around Olympic stadiums. Coates reminded the audience that athletes were the soul of the Games.</p>
        <p>Finally, the moment that everyone was waiting for: who would carry the Australian flag?</p>
        <p>Andrew Gaze.</p>
        <p>The crowd erupted in cheers, his basketball teammates slapped him on the back. Finally, after nearly three minutes of applause, Gaze, the captain of the basketball team, leaped onto the podium, hugging and kissing everyone on the dais.</p>
        <p>''This is a very, very humbling experience,'' Gaze said. ''When you walk around and see all the volunteers and you see the flag raised, you see what it means to them and see how passionate they are and how revved they are just to see you and say, 'G'day.' That makes you feel very welcome and very proud to be an Australian.''</p>
        <p>Gaze may have clinched the honor three days earlier during Australia's warm-up game against the heavily favored United States, when he got into a scuffle with Vince Carter, the young American superstar. Officials would chastise both players, but the truth is that the audience at Melbourne Park indoor stadium for the game against the Americans appreciated Gaze's show of defiance.</p>
        <p>Gaze's life is a basketball life, representing a combination of team, country, family and a sense of national pride that is difficult to understand in the United States, where profit consumes and defines right and wrong, loyalty and motivation.</p>
        <p>In Australia, Gaze, a five-time Olympian, is a national treasure.</p>
        <p>In the United States, he has a different image.</p>
        <p>For many critics in 1989, Gaze became a symbol of a win-at-all-costs hypocrisy that defines big-time collegiate sports. He went to Seton Hall in October 1988, after having played for Australia in the Seoul Olympics. He averaged 13.6 points for the Pirates, who lost the national championship game to Michigan, 80-79, in overtime. Four days later, Gaze left Seton Hall to return to Australia, prompting critics -- I was one of them -- to call him and Seton Hall partners in a mercenary alliance to win a championship.</p>
        <p>His short stay and the circumstances of his participation in an Australian professional league raised questions about amateur and professional distinctions and the recruitment of top international talent by major American universities.</p>
        <p>At the time, Gaze said he had decided to leave school when he learned he would be ineligible at Seton Hall if he played another season for the Melbourne Tigers, the team coached by his father, Lindsey.</p>
        <p>At the time, no one in the States understood -- or particularly cared -- about Melbourne. Last night, as Gaze emotionally accepted the honor, talked to teammates about responsibility, playing hard and working hard, the deep roots of loyalty became much clearer.</p>
        <p>After he left Seton Hall, Gaze went home, joined the Australian national league season and resumed his career with Melbourne. He averaged 34 points for the Tigers in 1989. Then his life took a sharp turn, which in many ways led to yesterday's emotional honor. Nearly 10 years to the day, Sept. 11, 1990, Gaze became seriously ill and was hospitalized with a blood clot in his right shoulder just before the finals of the 1990 Australian season. He missed a tryout with the Portland Trail Blazers and missed his league's playoffs.</p>
        <p>At that point, Gaze began to rearrange his priorities. Winning and losing was not the motivation; he no longer felt the need to prove himself.</p>
        <p>''When you are lying in bed wondering what is going to happen,'' Gaze said, ''you rethink things. Yes, basketball is very, very important, but it's a game. The world is not going to fall in, and you are not going to die tomorrow if you don't win the game.''</p>
        <p>In 1992, Gaze earned more than $130,000 in Italy. But he turned down a lucrative offer to return to Australia to play for Melbourne.</p>
        <p>His father coached the Tigers for nothing, he had always played for or coached the club. Andrew was a Tiger since he could dribble a ball. Loyalty.</p>
        <p>He explained to journalists that playing for more money in Italy would have meant missing the last half of the Tigers' National Basketball League campaign.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, as Gaze, age 35, accepted the Australian flag, he smiled, held back tears and dedicated the honor to the blood of his country, the blood of his family.</p>
        <p>''I feel like a bit of an imposter up here,'' Gaze said. ''My dad played in the 1960, '64, '68 Olympics and coached in the '72, '76, '80 and '84 Olympics. If anyone deserves an honor like this, it would be him.''</p>
        <p>Gaze stopped, composed himself and blushed. ''I'll certainly be carrying this flag for my dad,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
