<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. and Lawyers for Scientist Battle Over Plea Deal</title>
    <meta content="Y13LAB$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/13/national/13LAB.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230172"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Plea Bargaining</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Espionage</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Los Alamos National Laboratory</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lee, Wen Ho</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sterngold, James</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Plea Bargaining</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Espionage</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000913T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E4DD1438F930A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1035" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. and Lawyers for Scientist Battle Over Plea Deal</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES STERNGOLD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sterngold, James</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, Sept. 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Federal government and defense lawyers continue 11th-hour battle on interpreting plea agreement in which Wen Ho Lee, former Los Alamos scientist, has admitted one count of improperly downloading nuclear secrets in return for getting out of jail; photo; officials also begin finger-pointing on collapse of government's case (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The government and defense lawyers continued their 11th-hour battle today over how to interpret a plea agreement in which Wen Ho Lee, the former Los Alamos scientist, has admitted to one count of improperly downloading nuclear secrets in return for his freedom.</p>
        <p>At the same time, officials began rounds of finger-pointing for the virtual collapse of the government's case.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The government and defense lawyers continued their 11th-hour battle today over how to interpret a plea agreement in which Wen Ho Lee, the former Los Alamos scientist, has admitted to one count of improperly downloading nuclear secrets in return for his freedom.</p>
        <p>At the same time, officials began rounds of finger-pointing for the virtual collapse of the government's case.</p>
        <p>John Kelly, the former United States attorney in Albuquerque who indicted Dr. Lee, and then left government to run for Congress, said in an interview that the indictment, which has been all but abandoned, had been approved not just by him but also by senior officials at the Justice and Energy Departments. It was a ''team decision,'' Mr. Kelly said.</p>
        <p>Some government officials blamed the Federal Bureau of Investigation for providing false testimony at pretrial hearings, which ultimately hurt the government's case. And one government lawyer said the Los Alamos National Laboratory had harmed the case by giving deeply conflicting views of the value of the weapons information Dr. Lee improperly downloaded.</p>
        <p>In Albuquerque, the focus remained on negotiations over Dr. Lee's plea agreement.</p>
        <p>Officials close to the case said several questions were still being debated: Can the investigators ask about any efforts by China to steal nuclear secrets? And can Dr. Lee be prosecuted for any other crime that comes to light in discussions with investigators?</p>
        <p>The two sides in the case had made a surprise announcement on Sunday that the government was dropping 58 of its 59 charges against Dr. Lee in return for his agreement to plead guilty to the one felony charge of having illegally gathered and retained nuclear weapons secrets.</p>
        <p>Under the agreement, Dr. Lee would be sentenced to the time he had already served in prison, nine months since he was arrested, but would serve no probation. He also agreed that he would cooperate with investigators and explain why he downloaded a huge amount of nuclear data and what he did with seven computer tapes of the information that have disappeared.</p>
        <p>Judge James A. Parker set a hearing for 2 p.m. Monday in Federal District Court in Albuquerque, during which Dr. Lee had been expected to enter his plea and then walk free. But this routine hearing was twice delayed and then postponed until Wednesday morning because, the lawyers said, more details needed to be worked out.</p>
        <p>Lawyers on both sides have refused to comment on their unexpected battle, but people with knowledge of the problem say it relates not to the terms of the actual agreement, which was already signed on Sunday, but to competing views of what Dr. Lee would tell the government investigators and what legal risks he might face for those disclosures.</p>
        <p>In making the plea agreement final, Dr. Lee's attorneys made what is called a proffer, a description of what, in general terms, he would tell the investigators. Several people said the disagreement holding up Dr. Lee's release related to how far afield the government could go in its questioning.</p>
        <p>Dr. Lee's lawyers have sought the narrowest interpretation of the deal, and have sought to protect him against additional prosecution, people with knowledge of the talks said. From the defense perspective, they said, it appeared that the government was trying to stiffen the terms of the deal at the last minute in order to avoid criticism that it gained little from this long and divisive case.</p>
        <p>The government has insisted that Dr. Lee has to answer all questions and should be vulnerable to prosecution if he admits crimes outside of the downloading charge he is pleading guilty to, people close to the talks said.</p>
        <p>Either way, Judge Parker hinted on Monday that if the two sides could not close this gap, he might simply order the government to live up to the signed plea deal, allow Dr. Lee to make his plea in court, and then free him.</p>
        <p>With the perception growing that the case, in which Dr. Lee was initially suspected of being a spy for China, has collapsed under the weight of defense attorney attacks, many people sought to shift blame.</p>
        <p>In another instance of finger-pointing, today in Virginia, Notra Trulock,  who had investigated Dr. Lee for several years as the head of counterintelligence at the Energy Department, filed a defamation suit against Dr. Lee for having introduced affidavits accusing Mr. Trulock of singling out Dr. Lee because he is Chinese-American.</p>
        <p>While the suit is aimed at Dr. Lee, Larry Klayman, the chairman of Judicial Watch, the conservative group that filed the suit, said its real focus was the Energy Department, which he said had unfairly smeared Mr. Trulock and bungled the investigation.</p>
        <p>''This should scare the heck out of the Energy Department,'' Mr. Klayman said.</p>
        <p>Stu Nagurka, a department spokesman, said, ''The department is not a party to this lawsuit, and therefore we do not think it is appropriate to express our views about it.''</p>
        <p>Brian Sun, one of Dr. Lee's attorneys, said he had not yet seen the suit.</p>
        <p>But in general, Mr. Sun said, ''We do not place much stock in an effort that has more of a political motive.''</p>
        <p>In Albuquerque, Mr. Kelly, the former United States attorney, showed up in court on Monday to watch Dr. Lee's hearing and offered his own defense.</p>
        <p>He described the plea deal as an ''excellent outcome'' because it forced Dr. Lee to answer questions about what he was doing with the secret data. But, he added, ''It was a very painful prosecution in a lot of ways,'' and he insisted that the decision to initiate it was shared.</p>
        <p>''I don't want to point a finger,'' said Mr. Kelly, who is now running for office in part on his record as the United States attorney. ''I accept responsibility, but it was a team decision to move ahead on this.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
