<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Most British Gas Stations Close as Protests Grow</title>
    <meta content="13EURO$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/13/world/13EURO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230216"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trucks and Trucking</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Germany</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Netherlands</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Belgium</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Brussels (Belgium)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blair, Tony (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Elizabeth Ii, Queen of Great Britain</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lyall, Sarah</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Belgium</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Netherlands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Netherlands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Belgium</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Belgium/Brussels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trucks and Trucking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000913T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804EFDA1438F930A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1266" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Most British Gas Stations Close as Protests Grow</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SARAH LYALL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lyall, Sarah</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, Sept. 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Spreading protests over high fuel prices all but halt gasoline deliveries across Britain, forcing most service stations to close for lack of fuel, and sending frantic motorists on fruitless searches; ambulance, fire, trains and postal services are affected; similar anger continues in western Europe, with truck drivers, farmers and small-business people forming impromptu coalitions to protest crippling fuel costs and taxes that make up most of prices; truck drivers halt traffic in Brussels and blockade fuel depots, Dutch protesters block tunnels and German convoy drives across country; photos; Britain is most suddenly affected by panic buying of fuel and food staples; Prime Min Tony Blair promises fuel deliveries in 24 hours but rules out capitulating to demands to lower 76.2 percent fuel tax, highest in Europe; Queen Elizabeth II grants government special power to force oil companies to provide fuel for essential services; Blair's own car is pummeled by protesters (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Spreading protests over high fuel prices all but halted gasoline deliveries across Britain today, forcing most service stations to close for lack of fuel.</p>
        <p>As panicked motorists set out on frantic, often fruitless, hunts for gasoline, ambulance companies and fire departments began cutting back services. Many hospitals canceled all but essential procedures, and some diesel train lines were canceled altogether. The Royal Mail said many of its delivery trucks had just a day's worth of fuel left.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Spreading protests over high fuel prices all but halted gasoline deliveries across Britain today, forcing most service stations to close for lack of fuel.</p>
        <p>As panicked motorists set out on frantic, often fruitless, hunts for gasoline, ambulance companies and fire departments began cutting back services. Many hospitals canceled all but essential procedures, and some diesel train lines were canceled altogether. The Royal Mail said many of its delivery trucks had just a day's worth of fuel left.</p>
        <p>As Prime Minister Tony Blair struggled to contain his worst domestic crisis, similar anger continued to spread through Western Europe, where truck drivers, farmers and small-business people formed impromptu coalitions to protest cripplingly high fuel prices, and the taxes that make up much of the cost.</p>
        <p>In Belgium, truck drivers kept traffic at a standstill in Brussels for the third day in a row and blockaded three fuel depots in the south. In the Netherlands, protesters blocked two tunnels near Amsterdam and Rotterdam at the height of the rush hour.</p>
        <p>In Germany, a convoy of 100 buses, trucks and taxicabs drove from the French border to the State Parliament Building in Saarbrucken to demand that the government lower fuel prices. Farmers and truck drivers in Ireland, Italy, Poland and Spain threatened to mount actions within the week if their price-cutting demands were not met.</p>
        <p>But as discontent spread around the continent, Britain held the dubious honor of being the country most flattened by the protests. Although its refineries and storage depots are full of fuel, the country has been prevented by blockades from delivering the fuel to service stations.</p>
        <p>People waited for hours today to buy gasoline, and those unable to buy said they might have to stay home from work on Wednesday. The shortages struck so quickly because people rushed to the pump in an effort to refuel before it was too late. Around the country, there were scattered reports of people who were stealing fuel from empty cars in parking lots.</p>
        <p>In South Wales, the Spar supermarket chain said there had been a 300 percent increase in purchases of staples like bread and milk by people worried that supplies would run out or that they would be unable to get to the store.</p>
        <p>The director of the Petrol Retailers' Association, Roy Holloway, warned that there might be no fuel left for sale anywhere by Wednesday. ''In the next 24 hours,'' Mr. Holloway said, ''it is unlikely that we will see any retail fuel sales in the U.K.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Blair sought to appease an increasingly restive electorate by promising that essential services would continue and saying that he expected deliveries of fuel to start again ''in the next 24 hours.''</p>
        <p>He also firmly ruled out capitulating to the protesters' demands that he lower the 76.2 percent fuel tax, the highest in Europe and the main reason that gasoline in Britain costs $4.37 a gallon.</p>
        <p>Late Monday, Queen Elizabeth II met a representative of the Privy Council, a panel of senior politicians, judges and church leaders, and granted the government ''exceptional powers'' under a 1976 law to force oil companies to provide fuel to services like hospitals and schools. It was unclear whether the government would move to use such powers.</p>
        <p>After emergency meetings with his cabinet and with Britain's largest oil companies today, Mr. Blair said that the companies had pledged to do all that they could to start deliveries moving from their blockaded depots and refineries, provided that their drivers were guaranteed police protection. But though there were signs that small numbers of oil trucks were carrying fuel from depots late tonight and though there has been no violence, many companies seemed reluctant to order drivers to cross the protesters' informal picket lines.</p>
        <p>''For us, the issue has always been the safety of our drivers,'' a spokesman for Shell Oil said. ''They have said they don't feel comfortable, that they don't feel safe.''</p>
        <p>The protesters are a mixture of truck, bus and taxicab drivers, farmers and small-business owners, all of whom say the increasing cost of fuel threatens their livelihoods. Not organized by a union or any one group, they have joined together out of a common desperation.</p>
        <p>''I'll come down every day if I have to, until I run out of fuel myself,'' Derek Wood, a hauling contractor who was protesting at the gasoline depot for the Total oil company in Leeds, told the BBC. ''Our lads have nothing to lose.''</p>
        <p>Public opinion about the protesters, their tactics and the government's responsibility to resolve the problem is sharply polarized. Many Britons appear inclined to agree with William Hague, leader of the Conservative opposition, who said he did not think that Mr. Blair ''has got a grip on the situation or understands how angry people are about taxes being loaded on and on to fuel.''</p>
        <p>In a sign of the unhappy mood, The Mirror published an enormous photograph of the prime minister as he passed a line of cars at a service station on Monday on his way to a meeting under the headline, ''I'm All Right Jag.''</p>
        <p>''Tony Blair glides past petrol-starved drivers in his Jaguar,'' the newspaper said, noting that the prime minister ''will always have a full tank,'' no matter who else is waiting for gasoline.</p>
        <p>Mr. Blair's car was pummeled by protesters later, the paper noted with some glee, and a blockade by trucks, trailers and taxicabs prevented him from attending a dinner on Monday night for his deputy, John Prescott. Such images resonate with people like Colin Palmer, a taxicab driver in London who said that fuel was prohibitively expensive and that it was the government's fault.</p>
        <p>''This job is getting unviable,'' said Mr. Palmer, 45. ''If Blair doesn't listen to people protesting about the price of fuel, we're going to be worse off than we were under the Conservative government.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Blair made it clear today -- as did Germany and the Netherlands -- that Britain would not capitulate to protesters' demands that it lower gasoline taxes. Last week, after widespread protests in France, the government there agreed to lower its fuel tax 15 percent.</p>
        <p>''I believe that whatever the rights and wrongs of the argument over fuel duty, we cannot accept as a government or as a nation that policy should be dictated by illegal blockades, pickets or direct action,'' Mr. Blair told a news conference late this afternoon. ''Whatever the strength of the feeling, there can be no excuse whatever for this type of action, which is hurting our people, businesses and emergency services severely.''</p>
        <p>Some consumers agreed, saying they supported the protesters' goals, but could not countenance their methods.</p>
        <p>''At the moment, people are queuing for a half-hour to get fuel,'' said Brian Shapiro, another London cabdriver, who said he had enough fuel to keeping running through Wednesday. ''Tomorrow,'' Mr. Shapiro said, ''when there's no fuel, when people are struggling to get to work, to get their kids to school, you'll see how quickly public opinion shifts.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
