<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CAMPAIGN BRIEFING</title>
    <meta content="13CAMP$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/13/politics/13CAMP.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230260"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000913T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E1D81438F930A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="656" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CAMPAIGN BRIEFING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by B. Drummond Ayres Jr.</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE REPUBLICANS</p>
        <p>BUSH AND THE HANDSHAKE -- Gov. George W. Bush said he would have tried to avoid a handshake with President Fidel Castro of Cuba, unlike President Clinton at a United Nations summit last week. ''It broke a long tradition of signaling opposition to Castro,'' Mr. Bush said on Monday while in Florida, a state where Cuban-American relations are a major issue. But he stopped short of directly criticizing Mr. Clinton. ''The president did what he did,'' Mr. Bush said. ''I would have tried to avoid the handshake.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton and Mr. Castro shook hands and exchanged brief greetings after a lunch on the first day of the United Nations Millennium Summit. It was the first time they had met and apparently the first time Mr. Castro had ever shaken hands with a sitting American president.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE REPUBLICANS</p>
        <p>BUSH AND THE HANDSHAKE -- Gov. George W. Bush said he would have tried to avoid a handshake with President Fidel Castro of Cuba, unlike President Clinton at a United Nations summit last week. ''It broke a long tradition of signaling opposition to Castro,'' Mr. Bush said on Monday while in Florida, a state where Cuban-American relations are a major issue. But he stopped short of directly criticizing Mr. Clinton. ''The president did what he did,'' Mr. Bush said. ''I would have tried to avoid the handshake.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton and Mr. Castro shook hands and exchanged brief greetings after a lunch on the first day of the United Nations Millennium Summit. It was the first time they had met and apparently the first time Mr. Castro had ever shaken hands with a sitting American president.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>DEMOCRATS</p>
        <p>LIEBERMAN TO JOIN HILLARY CLINTON -- From the day last month that Senator Joseph I. Lieberman was selected as the Democratic vice-presidential candidate, Hillary Rodham Clinton has said she would like to campaign with him as she runs for a Senate seat in New York. On Friday, she will get her chance. Mr. Lieberman will campaign with Mrs. Clinton in New York City.</p>
        <p>His aides say the events have not been determined, but this much is known: Mrs. Clinton and her aides have said they hope that some of Mr. Lieberman's popularity will rub off, particularly with Jewish voters. Polls have Mrs. Clinton, who is in a tight race with Representative Rick A. Lazio, leading among Jewish voters by a margin smaller than New York Democrats usually need to win statewide races.</p>
        <p>Richard Perez-Pena (NYT)</p>
        <p>GORE IS DEFENDED ON TEMPLE VISIT -- The California woman who helped organize Vice President Al Gore's 1996 visit to a Buddhist temple in California where campaign money was illegally raised says Mr. Gore should ignore criticism about the visit and instead should be proud that he did it. The woman, Maria Hsia, who was found guilty in March of making false statements about the event, argues in an interview in The New Yorker magazine that Mr. Gore should tell his critics that his visit was ''no different from people visiting the black churches or any churches or a Jewish temple.''</p>
        <p>More than $100,000 was illegally raised for Democrats during the event, and Republicans have made Mr. Gore's attendance an integrity issue. Ms. Hsia, who is awaiting sentencing for causing false statements to be filed with the Federal Election Commission, could receive up to 25 years in prison. A Justice Department task force continues to investigate the temple event, as well as other 1996 campaign finance activities involving Mr. Gore.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>CONCERT RAISES $1 MILLION -- Vice President Al Gore and his wife, Tipper, last night attended a fund-raising concert in Camden, N.J., that collected $1 million for the Democratic National Committee.</p>
        <p>It was the first of three fund-raising events for the Democrats this week, to be followed by a concert in Boston on Wednesday night and one at Radio City Music Hall in New York City on Thursday night. The Camden concert included a tribute to Mr. Gore by former Senator Bill Bradley, who was defeated in this year's Democratic primary.</p>
        <p>Kevin Sack (NYT)</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
