<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush Says Rats Reference In Ad Was Unintentional</title>
    <meta content="Y13BUS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/13/politics/13BUSH.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230171"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE TEXAS GOVERNOR"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Daily News</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bruni, Frank</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000913T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6DD1438F930A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1232" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush Says Rats Reference In Ad Was Unintentional</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANK BRUNI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bruni, Frank</byline>
      <dateline>ST. LOUIS, Sept. 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>George W Bush defends Republican television commercial that, in attacking Al Gore's plans for health care, includes fleeting, almost undetectable, image of word 'rats'; denies intending sublimal message; aides counter with complaint about Democratic ad containing altered New York Daily News page; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As yet another of his campaign days skidded onto unexpected ground, Gov. George W. Bush today defended a Republican television commercial that, in attacking Vice President Al Gore's plans for health care, includes a fleeting, almost undetectable image of the word ''rats.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush said that the word, which is on screen for one-thirtieth of a second and can be seen with clarity only by freezing a videotape of the advertisement, was a fluke, not a deliberate subliminal message to voters about his opponent.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As yet another of his campaign days skidded onto unexpected ground, Gov. George W. Bush today defended a Republican television commercial that, in attacking Vice President Al Gore's plans for health care, includes a fleeting, almost undetectable image of the word ''rats.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush said that the word, which is on screen for one-thirtieth of a second and can be seen with clarity only by freezing a videotape of the advertisement, was a fluke, not a deliberate subliminal message to voters about his opponent.</p>
        <p>''Conspiracy theories abound in American politics,'' Mr. Bush said early this morning at an airport news conference in Orlando, Fla., trying to make light of the situation. But, he added, ''I am convinced that this is not intentional.''</p>
        <p>He also emphasized his belief that because the word appeared for only the tiniest fraction of the 30-second commercial, it could not have had any great purpose or impact.</p>
        <p>''One frame out of 900 is hardly a conspiracy, it seems like to me,'' Mr. Bush said.</p>
        <p>His aides later elaborated that the commercial, produced and released several weeks ago by the Republican National Committee, incorporated a computer editing device that makes portions of words pop onto or skitter across the screen, a kind of visual spice. ''Rats'' simply happened to be the last four letters of ''bureaucrats,'' they said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's aides also sought to turn the tables on the Gore campaign, which alerted The New York Times about the ''rats'' reference, by pointing to a Democratic advertisement released a week ago that they considered misleading. That advertisement, which criticized Mr. Bush over health care in Texas, used a headline from The New York Daily News in such a way that made it look as if it were on the front page when in fact the article ran inside the paper.</p>
        <p>''I would say that this is a case of somebody doing something that was a) deliberate and b) clearly designed to mislead,'' said Mr. Bush's chief media adviser, Mark McKinnon.  ''Because of that the D.N.C. ad should be subject to much greater scrutiny.''</p>
        <p>Rick Hess, a spokesman for the Democratic Party, insisted that the commercial was fair because Mr. Bush's photograph and a smaller headline about the article did appear on the cover of The Daily News.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Bush and his aides dismissed the ''rats'' detail of the Republican commercial as unintentional and unimportant, their need to explain it underscored the difficulties he has faced in recent weeks.</p>
        <p>Every several days, with uncanny regularity, Mr. Bush has found himself dealing with surprises, errors or distractions, sometimes of his own making, that throw his campaign off course and threaten to blunt his efforts to regain some of the ground he seems to have lost to Mr. Gore.</p>
        <p>It happened last week with the debate over presidential debates and with an incident in which Mr. Bush, unaware that a nearby microphone was working, uttered a vulgarity about a reporter whose coverage he deemed unfair.</p>
        <p>It happened the week before that, when the Republican National Committee released a commercial, with the Bush campaign's permission, that challenged Mr. Gore's truthfulness and political consistency.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush woke up this morning with the intention of focusing on his health care proposals at events in Orlando and St. Louis. Both Florida and Missouri are crucial battlegrounds in the presidential election, and Mr. Bush's onetime lead in polls in those states has vanished.</p>
        <p>But almost instantly, he was entangled in questions about the commercial, first on the ABC News program ''Good Morning, America'' and then at the news conference.</p>
        <p>And beyond that topic lay another that had nothing to do with the issues that Mr. Bush wanted to discuss. A profile of him in Vanity Fair suggests that he mixes up words from time to time because he has dyslexia.</p>
        <p>The first dozen or so questions at his news conference were about the Republican commercial. The next several were about the magazine article. Mr. Bush said that he does not have dyslexia. ''Amazing what happens when you run for president,'' Mr. Bush said, reflecting on the questions coming his way.</p>
        <p>By the time he reached his next event today, a panel discussion with doctors at a medical center in Orlando, it was almost as if he had consigned himself to the eclipsing of the day's theme. The discussion lasted all of 18 minutes.</p>
        <p>But later, at a town-hall-style meeting in St. Louis, Mr. Bush seemed buoyant as he talked for a full hour about a variety of issues. It provided a marked contrast to his demeanor earlier, when he at times showed signs of shakiness.</p>
        <p>On ''Good Morning, America,'' he first told Diane Sawyer that he had not known about the controversy over the word ''rats'' in the advertisement until that moment. Then, when she expressed skepticism, he clarified that he meant he had not known about it until waking up to the news this morning.</p>
        <p>At the news conference, he said the word ''subliminal'' four times and each time garbled it, giving it an extra syllable in the form of the suffix ''-able.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore's aides, barely able to contain their delight over the latest distraction to bedevil the Bush campaign, jumped on the news about the commercial, which was reported this morning.</p>
        <p>Today, they criticized Mr. Bush for not issuing a direct apology for the commercial. One senior aide said he was convinced that the fleeting reference to rats was not accidental.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore, campaigning in Ohio with his running mate, Senator Joseph I. Lieberman of Connecticut, told reporters, ''I think it's a disappointing development.''</p>
        <p>In Orlando, Mr. Bush said he did not condone subliminal advertising, but did not think it was the aim of this commercial and would not order the commercial pulled because it was already scheduled to conclude its run on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush said he had seen the commercial several weeks ago and had not noticed the word rats.</p>
        <p>''We don't need to play cute politics,'' Mr. Bush said, seeming to mean both that the party did not have to and that it should not. ''I'm going to win this election based upon issues.</p>
        <p>''But nevertheless, in order to put people's minds at ease, I will say loud and clear this kind of practice is not accepted,'' Mr. Bush said.</p>
        <p>He later reiterated, ''I want to make clear to people that the idea of putting subliminal messages into ads is ridiculous.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush seemed to be commenting not just on the theoretical practice of such a device but on any insinuation that he and other Republicans were using it. In West Palm Beach, Fla., where he began his day, a woman in a diner that he visited mentioned the brewing controversy.</p>
        <p>''They read everything into anything, don't they?'' Mr. Bush told her, apparently referring to reporters.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE TEXAS GOVERNOR</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
