<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Patients' Rights Bill Revised In Bid for Passage in Senate</title>
    <meta content="Y13HEAL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/13/politics/13HEAL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230275"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Health Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Health Maintenance Organizations and Managed Care</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pear, Robert</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Health Care Policy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000913T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E4D71438F930A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1006" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Patients' Rights Bill Revised In Bid for Passage in Senate</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT PEAR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pear, Robert</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Sept. 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Congressional supporters of patients' bill of rights revise House-passed bill to win few more Republican votes in Senate (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Congressional supporters of a patients'  bill of rights said today that they had revised the legislation passed by the House last year, in a bid to win the votes of a few more Senate Republicans needed to enact the measure this fall.</p>
        <p>The House and the Senate have passed different versions of the bill to define patients' rights, but efforts to negotiate a compromise have collapsed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Congressional supporters of a patients'  bill of rights said today that they had revised the legislation passed by the House last year, in a bid to win the votes of a few more Senate Republicans needed to enact the measure this fall.</p>
        <p>The House and the Senate have passed different versions of the bill to define patients' rights, but efforts to negotiate a compromise have collapsed.</p>
        <p>Supporters of the legislation said they had given up on trying to reach an agreement with Senate Republican leaders. Instead, they are trying to revise the House legislation to address the concerns of Senate Republicans.</p>
        <p>Four Republican senators have previously voted with Democrats on patients' rights. The 46 Senate Democrats hope they can pick up the votes of a few more Republicans in view of the fact that Vice President Al Gore, the Democratic presidential nominee, and Democratic candidates for Congress hammer the issue almost every day.</p>
        <p>The new effort is being led by three House champions of patients' rights -- Representatives Charlie Norwood, Republican of Georgia; John D. Dingell, Democrat of Michigan, and Greg Ganske, Republican of Iowa -- and by a leading Senate critic of managed care, Senator Edward M. Kennedy, Democrat of Massachusetts.</p>
        <p>The compromise is supported by the American Medical Association, whose members complain that their professional judgments are often overridden by health maintenance organizations.</p>
        <p>The four lawmakers and the doctors' association are trying to woo Republican senators running for re-election, including Senators Rick Santorum of Pennsylvania, Spencer Abraham of Michigan, Slade Gorton of Washington, John Ashcroft of Missouri and Conrad Burns of Montana. Democrats reckon they have already picked up a vote with the arrival of a Democrat, Zell Miller, to replace Senator Paul Coverdell of Georgia, a Republican who died in July.</p>
        <p>The compromise bill would set standards for all private health insurance, protecting at least 160 million Americans, or more than three times as many as would be covered by the Senate bill.</p>
        <p>The compromise tries to address the concerns of Senate Republicans who want to protect states' rights, notably the right of states to regulate health insurance.</p>
        <p>If a state could show that its insurance laws were ''at least substantially equivalent'' to the new federal standards, the state law would remain in effect, and state officials could enforce the patient protections of state law.</p>
        <p>On another issue, the compromise bill would allow some lawsuits to be filed against health plans in state court, but would require others to be filed in federal court.</p>
        <p>This would codify the emerging consensus of many judges, who have suggested in decisions over the past five years that injured patients can sue H.M.O.'s in state court in disputes over the quality of medical care -- traditional malpractice cases.</p>
        <p>Under the compromise bill, a patient could sue in state court if a health plan denied a claim for benefits on the ground that a service was not medically necessary or that a treatment was experimental.</p>
        <p>But patients would have to sue in federal court if they wanted to challenge an administrative decision to deny benefits, a decision involving no question of medical judgment.</p>
        <p>Finally, the compromise bill seeks to allay Republican concerns that employers might be saddled with immense new costs if patients could sue them for damages arising from care provided through an employer-sponsored health plan.</p>
        <p>The revised legislation says employers may not be held liable unless they directly participated in a decision to deny benefits, as a result of which a patient was injured or killed.</p>
        <p>Even then, defendants could not be required to pay punitive damages unless they showed ''willful or wanton disregard for the rights or safety'' of patients.</p>
        <p>Dr. D. Ted Lewers, chairman of the American Medical Association, said: ''The A.M.A. strongly supports the revised version of the bipartisan patient's bill of rights. It covers all Americans and holds health plans accountable for actions that harm patients.''</p>
        <p>John E. Stone, a spokesman for Dr. Norwood, said the congressman had presented the proposed compromise to the speaker, J. Dennis Hastert, to the White House and to ''a number of Republicans'' in the Senate.</p>
        <p>''We want to hold together the coalition we have in favor of the Norwood-Dingell bill, while doing what we can to bring in some reluctant Senate supporters,'' Mr. Stone said.</p>
        <p>The compromise bill includes several tax incentives to make health insurance more available and affordable. To win Republican votes, Democrats said they would consider allowing an expansion of a pilot program that lets people set aside money for medical expenses in tax-sheltered accounts known as medical savings accounts.</p>
        <p>Representative Bill Archer, the Texas Republican who is chairman of the Ways and Means Committee, said the encouragement of such accounts was a top legislative priority.</p>
        <p>The Senate passed a Republican version of the patients' bill of rights in July 1999, and the House passed the Norwood-Dingell bill, with bipartisan support, in October 1999. Negotiators from the two chambers met for the first time on March 2 and later reached agreement on a few issues.</p>
        <p>In drafting the new compromise bill, lawmakers borrowed language developed in the conference committee, headed by Senator Don Nickles of Oklahoma, the assistant Republican leader.</p>
        <p>They accepted language suggested by Mr. Nickles to establish an administrative appeals process for patients denied benefits by H.M.O.'s.</p>
        <p>The compromise also adopts legislative language similar to that proposed by Republicans to ensure that patients have timely access to medical specialists and that doctors can prescribe ''medically necessary'' drugs, regardless of restrictions imposed by H.M.O.'s.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
