<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Judge Bars Testimony of 3 Psychiatrists in Murder Case</title>
    <meta content="13PSYC$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/13/nyregion/13PSYC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230254"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Snyder, Leslie Crocker (Justice)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bierenbaum, Robert (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Katz-Bierenbaum, Gail</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Finkelstein, Katherine E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000913T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE2D81438F930A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="887" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Judge Bars Testimony of 3 Psychiatrists in Murder Case</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHERINE E. FINKELSTEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Finkelstein, Katherine E</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Manhattan Judge Leslie Crocker Snyder, holding law must not intrude on confidential doctor-patient relationship, bars testimony of three psychiatrists about violent impulses of Dr Robert Bierenbaum, whom they treated briefly in 1983; he is charged with murdering wife, Gail Katz-Bierenbaum, who disappeared in 1985; they admitted in pretrial hearings that they warned her at time that she was in danger; psychiatric groups hail decision; Snyder rules other witnesses can testify about psychiatrists' concerns; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Manhattan judge ruled yesterday that the law must not intrude on the confidential doctor-patient relationship and excluded the testimony of three psychiatrists about the violent impulses of a young man they treated 17 years ago who is now facing a murder trial.</p>
        <p>Psychiatric groups hailed the ruling in the case, in which Dr. Robert Bierenbaum, a successful plastic surgeon, is accused of murdering his wife, as an important victory for the practice of psychiatry, which relies on the guarantee of confidentiality to  foster trust.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A Manhattan judge ruled yesterday that the law must not intrude on the confidential doctor-patient relationship and excluded the testimony of three psychiatrists about the violent impulses of a young man they treated 17 years ago who is now facing a murder trial.</p>
        <p>Psychiatric groups hailed the ruling in the case, in which Dr. Robert Bierenbaum, a successful plastic surgeon, is accused of murdering his wife, as an important victory for the practice of psychiatry, which relies on the guarantee of confidentiality to  foster trust.</p>
        <p>The judge in the case, Leslie Crocker Snyder of Manhattan Criminal Court, said she was distressed that she had to exclude testimony that the three psychiatrists were ''impressed'' by the ''danger posed by the defendant.'' And she said that even though it was disturbing to limit the ''truth-finding function'' of the court, she had to carefully balance that function against protections similar to those that exist between a lawyer and his client.</p>
        <p>The three psychiatrists, who treated Dr. Bierenbaum briefly in 1983, when he and his wife lived on the Upper East Side, warned his wife at the time that she was in danger. While they have reluctantly acknowledged, in pretrial hearings, that they contacted her, they have also said they were obliged to safeguard Dr. Bierenbaum's privacy. Dr. Bierenbaum's wife, Gail Katz-Bierenbaum, vanished in 1985 and her body has never been found.</p>
        <p>While the judge's decision was an evident blow for the prosecutors, she also made some decisions favorable to them, said a spokeswoman for the Manhattan district attorney's office. The judge ruled that she would permit other witnesses to testify about the psychiatrists' concerns, which will allow the prosecution to paint a portrait of a rocky marriage laced with violence and fear.</p>
        <p>The judge's major ruling, which was closely watched in legal and psychiatric circles, navigated thorny new territory in New York State law;  namely, whether the confidentiality in a doctor-patient relationship is still protected in a courtroom if a psychiatrist has warned intended victims of potential harm.</p>
        <p>During the pretrial hearings, prosecutors have argued that Dr. Bierenbaum had waived his right to confidentiality by allowing his psychiatrists to speak about his treatment with his parents and his wife. The three psychiatrists testified that after consulting with Dr. Bierenbaum, they warned his wife that her life might be in danger; as one letter shows, one doctor even put this in writing to her.</p>
        <p>But in a lengthy brief, two groups that opposed the prosecutors' efforts, the New York State Psychiatric Association and the American Psychoanalytic Association, argued that the waiver of confidentiality that allows psychiatrists to warn third parties of potential harm by a patient ends when the threat of imminent harm ends.</p>
        <p>''When a doctor makes a warning, he's violating confidentiality for a certain purpose and a certain period of time,'' said Seth P. Stein, general counsel of the state Psychiatric Association and an author of the brief.  ''And once that purpose and period of time have elapsed, the privilege is fully restored.''</p>
        <p>He added, ''The goal of the warning is to protect people, not to prosecute them,'' and if that balance were changed, patients would be far more reluctant to discuss their violent thoughts and feelings.</p>
        <p>Psychiatric experts not connected with the case also applauded the ruling. Dr. Paul S. Appelbaum, chairman of the department of psychiatry at the University of Massachusetts medical school, said, ''Were privilege statutes to be waived merely because of the disclosure of information,'' they ''would all but become worthless.''</p>
        <p>Prosecutors did get some welcome news yesterday. Judge Crocker Snyder said she would allow testimony about the psychiatrist's warning letter, and about Dr. Bierenbaum's past acts of violence against his wife.</p>
        <p>Expected to testify are Hillard Wiese, a lawyer and cousin of Ms. Katz-Bierenbaum. Mr. Wiese has told prosecutors that he received a phone call from his cousin, who sounded distressed, one day in the fall of 1983, and that she said her husband had choked her into unconsciousness the day before.</p>
        <p>When she came to, according to Mr. Wiese, Dr. Bierenbaum was standing over her and begging her forgiveness, Judge Crocker Snyder said in the course of her ruling yesterday.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wiese then urged her to leave right away, before her husband got home, the judge added.</p>
        <p>Another expected witness is a psychologist and friend of Ms. Katz-Bierenbaum's. The judge will allow the psychologist to testify that in late 1984, Ms. Katz-Bierenbaum showed her a letter written to her by Dr. Michael Stone, who briefly consulted with Dr. Bierenbaum.</p>
        <p>Dr. Stone has testified that he determined Dr. Bierenbaum was potentially violent and warned Ms. Katz-Bierenbaum her life was in danger. This testimony could still be quite damaging to Dr. Bierenbaum, legal experts said yesterday.</p>
        <p>''The defense is still going to be faced with a situation where the jury may infer that the psychiatrist believes that the doctor was a danger,'' said a Manhattan defense lawyer, Gerald Shargel. ''But it is better than facing the live testimony of three psychiatrists drawing that conclusion in front of the jury.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
