<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BULLETIN BOARD</title>
    <meta content="13BULL$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/13/nyregion/13BULL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Education Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230151"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Scholarships and Fellowships</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Kpmg Consulting</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Yale University</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Gates, Bill and Melinda, Foundation</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">community studies</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holloway, Lynette</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wilgoren, Jodi</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wyatt, Edward</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fass, Allison</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pollak, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Levy, Harold O (Chancellor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lindsay, John V</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education/Columns/Bulletin Board</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Scholarships and Fellowships</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Scholarships and Fellowships</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000913T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E6DF1438F930A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="569" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BULLETIN BOARD</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYNETTE HOLLOWAY, JODI WILGOREN, EDWARD WYATT, ALLISON FASS and MICHAEL POLLAK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pollak, Michael; Wilgoren, Jodi; Wyatt, Edward; Holloway, Lynette; Fass, Allison</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York City Schools Chancellor Harold O Levy, irked when he was unable to reach several Education Board administrators by phone, has hired KPMG Consulting to learn how many officials do not answer their phones; Yale University creates public service fellowship honoring John V Lindsay; NYC Education Board schedules six days of professional development for teachers at elementary, middle and junior high schools and five days for high school teachers and will hold no classes on those days; Bill &amp; Melinda Gates Foundation to donate $4.2 million to Community Studies, nonprofit New York education group; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It Was No Busy Signal</p>
        <p>Schools Chancellor HAROLD O. LEVY was irked recently when he tried to reach several Board of Education administrators by telephone and got their voice mail instead.</p>
        <p>So he hired a firm, KPMG Consulting, to learn just how many officials at the board's headquarters at 110 Livingston Street in downtown Brooklyn do not answer their phones.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It Was No Busy Signal</p>
        <p>Schools Chancellor HAROLD O. LEVY was irked recently when he tried to reach several Board of Education administrators by telephone and got their voice mail instead.</p>
        <p>So he hired a firm, KPMG Consulting, to learn just how many officials at the board's headquarters at 110 Livingston Street in downtown Brooklyn do not answer their phones.</p>
        <p>Mr. Levy said that if he was getting voice mail, he had ''to think that parents are getting it and must be frustrated.''</p>
        <p>The study will be used in reviewing the quality of the board's staff when he begins an effort to trim the bureaucracy. He had planned to complete a full-scale review in June, but he said in July he needed more time to examine the roles of the 32 district superintendents and their staffs.</p>
        <p>A John Lindsay Fellowship</p>
        <p>More than half a century after he graduated and 27 years after he stepped down as mayor, JOHN V. LINDSAY, left, is being honored by Yale Law School, which has created a public service fellowship in his name. Lindsay fellows will work in government agencies, nonprofit organizations or public-interest law endeavors in New York City, and fellowship stipends will pay part of their salaries.</p>
        <p>The first recipient is STEPHAN PRYOR, who graduated from Yale Law in 1998 (and Yale College in 1993) and is now executive director of Breakthrough for Learning, a program in two Brooklyn school districts that uses merit bonuses and other incentives to improve teaching. Mr. Lindsay, 78, who graduated from Yale Law in 1948 (and Yale College in 1944), has Parkinson's disease and lives in a retirement community on Hilton Head Island, S.C.</p>
        <p>A Few Days Off From School</p>
        <p>Parents, call your baby sitters: the Board of Education has scheduled six days of professional development for teachers at elementary, middle and junior high schools and five such days for high school teachers. Students will have no school on those days while teachers attend training programs.</p>
        <p>For elementary, middle and junior high school students, the days off are Sept. 28, Oct. 19, Nov. 7, Dec. 7, Feb. 8 and March 22. High school students will have those same days off, except for Feb. 8, when regular classes will be conducted.</p>
        <p>11 Education Grants</p>
        <p>The Bill &amp; Melinda Gates Foundation in Seattle has announced 11 grants across the United States, including a $4.2 million donation to a nonprofit New York educational organization, Community Studies. The money will be used to support the New York Performance Standards Consortium, a network of 40 small schools throughout the state, and the Center for Inquiry in Teaching and Learning, a professional development center for teachers.</p>
        <p>Community Studies will also try to develop systems for assessing student performance and will offer technical assistance at schools in New York, New Jersey and Connecticut.</p>
        <p>Help for Putting Courses on the Web</p>
        <p>Yale University Press is bringing out a book to help  teachers who are considering putting all or part of a course online. The book, ''Web Teaching Guide: A Practical Guide to Creating Course Web Sites,'' is scheduled for publication in November.</p>
        <p>It covers making existing course material compatible with the Web, selecting software packages, putting administrative details like scheduling and office hours online, and combining texts, illustrations and lecture notes.</p>
        <p>LYNETTE HOLLOWAY, JODI WILGOREN, EDWARD WYATT, ALLISON FASS and MICHAEL POLLAK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
