<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Volunteers in White Collars With Political Stripes</title>
    <meta content="Y13SAV$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/13/business/13SAVV.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230132"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MANAGEMENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">White Collar Workers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Volunteers</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Goldman Sachs Group</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Abueva, Jobert E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Forquet, Jose</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">White Collar Workers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Volunteers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000913T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E3D81738F930A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1062" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Volunteers in White Collars With Political Stripes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOBERT E. ABUEVA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Abueva, Jobert E</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Volunteer services of white-collar workers have become highly prized by political campaigns; business professionals exhibit qualities that political candidate value most: nuts-and-bolts organizational skills, management savvy and address books crammed with contacts; Jose Forquet of Goldman Sachs, who is co-founder of database used by Republican Party, comments; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Every Thursday evening, Marilyn Robinson, executive director of the Nashville Minority Business Center, drives from her office to the Gore-Lieberman campaign headquarters and works the phones for three hours, canvassing voters throughout the country.</p>
        <p>''Most of what I do at work is persuading others to fund and support our various programs. It's no different with potential voters,'' said Ms. Robinson, who also puts in a Saturday morning shift at Gore headquarters. ''I like that I bring what I do best, selling and speaking, into the political process.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Every Thursday evening, Marilyn Robinson, executive director of the Nashville Minority Business Center, drives from her office to the Gore-Lieberman campaign headquarters and works the phones for three hours, canvassing voters throughout the country.</p>
        <p>''Most of what I do at work is persuading others to fund and support our various programs. It's no different with potential voters,'' said Ms. Robinson, who also puts in a Saturday morning shift at Gore headquarters. ''I like that I bring what I do best, selling and speaking, into the political process.''</p>
        <p>And those are not the only management skills she taps into. She also enlists help from her network of friends and business associates, including members of 100 Black Women, a local social group.</p>
        <p>For all the frenzied fund-raising by Democrats and Republicans this year, candidates for offices from the the White House to the local school board know one thing is even more important than money: volunteers.</p>
        <p>And while these unpaid armies are made up mostly of students and retired people, it is business professionals who exhibit the qualities that political candidates value most: nuts-and-bolts organizational skills, management savvy and address books crammed with contacts.</p>
        <p>To campaign managers, these executives are golden because they can get things done. Consider Jose Forquet, a 34-year-old vice president at Goldman, Sachs in New York, and Joe Bogosian, a 35-year-old lawyer at McGuire Woods Consulting in Washington. A couple of years ago, Mr. Forquet, an independent, and Mr. Bogosian, a Republican, each had a plan to promote George W. Bush for president by creating advocacy groups -- of Hispanic executives in Mr. Forquet's case, and of young professionals in Mr. Bogosian's.</p>
        <p>But then the men were introduced to each other in late 1998 by a mutual friend who knew of their political activism, and before long they had developed a more ambitious project. Working with a Bush campaign official, they drafted a proposal for creating an e-mail database to recruit corporate managers, lawyers and other young professionals to take part in fund-raisers and other activities for the Republican Party.</p>
        <p>In March 1999, they traveled at their own expense to Mr. Bush's campaign headquarters in Austin, Tex., to seek its official endorsement.  ''The exact same skills required of selling a start-up firm to venture capitalists applied'' in winning over the Bush camp to the idea, Mr. Bogosian said.</p>
        <p>They got the green light, and YP4W.com -- or Young Professionals for George W. Bush -- was born, along with a national networking organization of the same name with chapters in 30 cities.</p>
        <p>''We knew from our research that there were many people out there like us,'' Mr. Forquet said. ''A market clearly existed.''</p>
        <p>The site was so successful, in fact, that the Bush campaign took it over and now runs it out of Austin as part of a coalition of Web sites and voter groups. Mr. Forquet and Mr. Bogosian continue to head the New York and Washington chapters of the networking organization.</p>
        <p>While few managers can boast of such influence on a national scale, most can have a big impact on the state or local level. Laura Dambier, a senior strategist for the Lincoln Financial Group in Hartford, for example, has no doubts that she is making a difference in the re-election effort of State Representative Jessie Stratton, a Democrat. Ms. Dambier spent the greater part of Labor Day assigning volunteers to task forces and revising calendars for the final stretch of the campaign.</p>
        <p>''I definitely draw from a wide repertory of skills,'' Ms. Dambier said. She was active in numerous political races in the past, she said, and the two biggest tasks in almost every case were the same ones that corporate managers face every day: setting priorities and motivating people.</p>
        <p>'As you enter the final, crucial weeks, volunteers may begin to lose interest and therefore need to be refocused on the mission of our campaign beyond simply garnering votes,'' she said. ''In some cases, you might reassign duties.''</p>
        <p>The growing presence of business professionals is not lost on campaign managers and indeed presents them with something of a challenge. ''Working volunteers come into a campaign motivated but are extremely busy people themselves. They want their investment in time and effort to pay off,'' said Catherine Shaw, the Democratic mayor of Ashland, Ore., and the author of a how-to book on conducting local campaigns. ''Campaign managers need to know what competencies and connections they bring to the table.''</p>
        <p>To illustrate her point, Ms. Shaw described how a volunteer, a manager in the hospitality industry, recently pulled disparate databases and segmented voters for follow-up direct-marketing efforts.</p>
        <p>Even political neophytes have high expectations of themselves if they have a business background. Rochelle Pachtman, founder of the public relations firm Pachtman Communications in Manhattan, says she jumped into the fray just a few weeks ago to lend a hand to the Gore campaign because the race was so tight and she thought she might actually make a difference.</p>
        <p>''I'm waiting for my marching orders,'' Ms. Pachtman said. When she gets them, she says, she believes she will be able to leverage her communications skills as well as tap into her expertise in the industries and issues she has researched over time on behalf of her clients. For example, she says, she could coach campaign volunteers on how to put their points across when they are making phone calls or knocking on doors to get out the vote.</p>
        <p>''Volunteers, especially inexperienced ones, want feedback on how they are performing,'' Ms. Pachtman said, ''to know that they are doing a good job and find ways to improve on it.''</p>
        <p>MANAGEMENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
