<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With Tua Next Up, Lewis Keeps to His Busy Schedule</title>
    <meta content="13FITE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/13/sports/13FITE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230153"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BOXING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lewis, Lennox</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brown, Clifton</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tua, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000913T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E2DF1438F930A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="685" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With Tua Next Up, Lewis Keeps to His Busy Schedule</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFTON BROWN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brown, Clifton</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lennox Lewis, World Boxing Council and International Boxing Federation heavyweight champion, is in New York to promote Nov bout against David Tua, his fourth bout in 12 months (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Nobody can accuse Lennox Lewis of resting on his laurels.</p>
        <p>In an age when some boxers spend more time in trouble than in training, Lewis has spent the last few years fighting regularly, and winning regularly. Lewis, the World Boxing Council and International Boxing Federation heavyweight champion, was in Manhattan yesterday to promote his next bout, on Nov. 11 against David Tua at the Mandalay Bay Resort and Casino in Las Vegas. For Lewis, (37-1-1, 29 knockouts), it will be his fourth bout in the last 12 months, and he will enter the ring riding a 13-fight winning streak.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Nobody can accuse Lennox Lewis of resting on his laurels.</p>
        <p>In an age when some boxers spend more time in trouble than in training, Lewis has spent the last few years fighting regularly, and winning regularly. Lewis, the World Boxing Council and International Boxing Federation heavyweight champion, was in Manhattan yesterday to promote his next bout, on Nov. 11 against David Tua at the Mandalay Bay Resort and Casino in Las Vegas. For Lewis, (37-1-1, 29 knockouts), it will be his fourth bout in the last 12 months, and he will enter the ring riding a 13-fight winning streak.</p>
        <p>Tua (37-1, 32 knockouts) represents a serious threat to Lewis's titles, as well as his equilibrium. A 27-year-old native of Samoa, Tua has pounded his way up the ranks with devastating punching power, knocking out his last eight opponents. Tua's powerful left hook has carried him to a title shot, and he vowed not to be intimidated by his underdog status, or by his talented opponent.</p>
        <p>''I earned the right to be here, and I've waited for this opportunity,'' said Tua, who at 5 feet 10 inches will be at a severe height and reach disadvantage against Lewis, who is 6-5. ''I'm the underdog in this fight, but that's cool. This is the happiest I've ever seen Lennox the last few days. I don't know if it's because he's looking past David Tua, or what. But I guarantee I'll be ready Nov. 11.''</p>
        <p>Lewis looked confident and relaxed, and for good reason. His last fight was one of his most impressive, a second-round technical knockout over Francois Botha, punctuated by a beautiful combination to Botha's head that left him floored, and soon defeated. Lewis turned 35 this month, but he appears to be reaching his peak at an age when some boxers lose their skill rapidly.</p>
        <p>Lewis has not lost since September 1994, when Oliver McCall scored a surprising second-round knockout, flooring Lewis with a right hand. Tua will surely point to that bout as evidence that he can knock out Lewis as well, but Lewis sees it differently.</p>
        <p>''One guy got lucky,'' Lewis said of his loss against McCall. ''All Tua has is a left hook. You know what's coming. He's not going to outbox me. I see him as one-dimensional. I've never been floored by a left hook before. People talk about what they're going to do to me. But many have tried, and many have failed.''</p>
        <p>Many of Lewis's doubters were convinced by his two performances against Evander Holyfield last year. The first Lewis-Holyfield fight was scored a controversial draw at Madison Square Garden, but an overwhelming majority thought Lewis had won. In the rematch eight months later, Lewis scored a unanimous 12-round decision, to win the undisputed heavyweight title.</p>
        <p>Even though he relinquished the World Boxing Association title this year to fight Michael Grant, whom Lewis stopped in the second round, Lewis still views himself as the undisputed champion, because he did not lose the W.B.A. title in the ring. And while Holyfield has won back the W.B.A. title, the fight for Lewis that would hold the most allure would be against Mike Tyson, if Tyson can get past Andrew Golota next month.</p>
        <p>Lewis, however, sounded unconvinced that he and Tyson would ever come together.</p>
        <p>''Mike Tyson doesn't want to fight me,'' Lewis said. ''He's unstable. Anyone who bites people's ears, talks about eating your children and punches people well after the bell is unstable. If he could get himself together, it would be a huge fight.''</p>
        <p>In the meantime, Lewis will train for Tua, figuring that the busier he stays, the better.</p>
        <p>''I'm staying busy, because I find that I'm improving with each fight,'' he said. ''I can't tell you how long I'll fight. But I'm going to keep fighting until I'm satisfied.''</p>
        <p>BOXING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
