<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Poll Shows Gore Overcoming Voter Concerns on Likability</title>
    <meta content="13POLL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/13/politics/13POLL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230205"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE POLLS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions, National (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vice Presidents and Vice Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Times/cbs News Poll</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lieberman, Joseph I (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Elder, Janet</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berke, Richard L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/Joseph I Lieberman</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vice Presidents and Vice Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000913T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E7DA1438F930A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="2566" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Poll Shows Gore Overcoming Voter Concerns on Likability</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD L. BERKE with JANET ELDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Elder, Janet; Berke, Richard L</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Latest New York Times/CBS News Poll shows that Vice Pres Gore has shaken persistent sense that he is not particularly likable and is now as highly regarded as rival George W Bush on matters of character, leadership and overall personal popularity; 44 percent of those polled now have favorable opinion of Gore, to 42 percent for Bush; graph; table; poll shows neck-and-neck presidential race, with 42 percent of voters backing Gore if election were today to 39 percent for Bush, four percent for Ralph Nader and two percent for Patrick Buchanan; 47 percent of Gore supporters and 38 percent of Bush backers acknowledge reservations; 63 percent of public thinks Gore cares about problems of ordinary people; many also cite Democratic convention and choice of Joseph Lieberman as running mate (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Vice President Al Gore has shaken the persistent sense that he is not particularly likable and is now as highly regarded as Gov. George W. Bush on matters of character, leadership and overall personal popularity, the latest New York Times/CBS News Poll shows.</p>
        <p>Now that public opinion has settled somewhat since the Democratic convention nearly four weeks ago, and voters say they are far more interested in the race, the survey makes clear that Mr. Gore's enhanced fortunes are deeper and more sustained than a postconvention glow.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Vice President Al Gore has shaken the persistent sense that he is not particularly likable and is now as highly regarded as Gov. George W. Bush on matters of character, leadership and overall personal popularity, the latest New York Times/CBS News Poll shows.</p>
        <p>Now that public opinion has settled somewhat since the Democratic convention nearly four weeks ago, and voters say they are far more interested in the race, the survey makes clear that Mr. Gore's enhanced fortunes are deeper and more sustained than a postconvention glow.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore has achieved substantial gains among women, independent voters and those from middle-income groups. While Mr. Bush's support has diminished somewhat over all, he retains the overwhelming support of men, Midwesterners and Southerners.</p>
        <p>The poll shows that the presidential race is neck and neck and that Mr. Bush and Mr. Gore are facing off in the tightest competition just after Labor Day in 20 years.</p>
        <p>Forty-two percent of registered voters said they would back Mr. Gore if the election were held today, and 39 percent said they would vote for Mr. Bush. Four percent said they would back Ralph Nader, the Green Party nominee, and 2 percent would favor Patrick J. Buchanan of the Reform Party.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore has gained on Mr. Bush in recent weeks, but not to a degree that is statistically significant. The nationwide telephone poll, conducted Saturday through Monday with 843 registered voters, has a margin of sampling error of plus or minus three percentage points.</p>
        <p>And there was some encouraging news for Mr. Bush in the numbers. Forty-seven percent of Mr. Gore's supporters said they had reservations about him; only 38 percent of Mr. Bush's backers registered concerns about their candidate.</p>
        <p>By far the most pronounced shift in the survey is the marked improvement in the public's perceptions of Mr. Gore.</p>
        <p>For months, Americans said they found Mr. Gore's positions on various issues more appealing than Mr. Bush's, but the vice president's most persistent problem was that voters said they had significant misgivings about him on issues of character.</p>
        <p>Now, while Mr. Bush has held his own in retaining impressive favorability ratings, Mr. Gore's favorability ratings have increased substantially -- to the point where the two men are now equally popular. Forty-four percent of voters say they have a favorable view of Mr. Gore, while 29 percent have an unfavorable view. Mr. Gore has not done that well by this measure for years. In recent months, the public either had more negative views of Mr. Gore than positive ones, or, more recently, had given him positive ratings that equaled his negatives.</p>
        <p>In a striking example of how perceptions have transformed, voters no longer view Mr. Bush as the runaway winner in the November election. They are now split on whether Mr. Gore or Mr. Bush will make it to the White House. As recently as two months ago, Mr. Bush led Mr. Gore on this question by more than 20 percentage points.</p>
        <p>Voters are also more confident in Mr. Gore's ability to deal wisely with an international crisis. Forty-nine percent said they were confident in Mr. Gore, a gain from 43 percent in a Times/CBS poll in July. Mr. Bush's standing on that issue has remained steady at 46 percent.</p>
        <p>While 63 percent of the public thinks Mr. Gore cares about the needs and problems of ordinary people -- a figure that has not changed since July -- Mr. Bush has shown some slippage. Forty-nine percent say that Mr. Bush cares about ordinary people, a decline from 55 percent in July.</p>
        <p>It is not altogether clear what has prompted the more kindly feelings toward Mr. Gore. But in follow-up interviews yesterday, many voters who now back Mr. Gore said they were impressed by what they saw at the Democratic convention. Repeatedly, they said, Mr. Gore seemed to be coming into his own and moving out of President Clinton's shadow.</p>
        <p>''At the convention, he did a better job of concealing anything that was negative, if he had anything to begin with,'' said Wilma Akins, 69, a retired office manager in Statesboro, Ga. ''He made me feel hopeful and optimistic about the future.''</p>
        <p>Joyce Taylor, 46, a grocery store manager in Philadelphia, said: ''He's become stronger and seems to be speaking out more since the convention. He's becoming his own man now, and he's not as stiff as he once was.''</p>
        <p>Although there is still not a single overwhelming issue that defines the race -- as the economy has in the past -- the survey found that the closest contender this year was health care, and the related matter of Medicare. Nearly two-thirds of voters said the high cost of prescription drugs for the elderly was quite important to them personally.</p>
        <p>Voters said they thought the government -- not insurance companies -- would do a better job of providing coverage to the elderly for prescription drugs. Mr. Gore was seen as more likely than Mr. Bush to succeed in reducing the cost of prescription drugs for the elderly. Mr. Bush has proposed allowing private insurance companies to compete for Medicare clients, while Mr. Gore has proposed adding a subsidy for prescription drug coverage to the current Medicare plan.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Bush has recently accused the administration of presiding over a weakening of the military, the issue did not register much with voters. And many seemed confused about the state of the nation's missile defense capability.</p>
        <p>Half the voters agreed with Mr. Bush's assertion that the military has weakened under Mr. Clinton. Just under half said it had either strengthened or stayed the same over the last eight years.</p>
        <p>But half the voters said they thought that the United States had a missile defense system, although it does not; only 28 percent knew that the country does not have one. One explanation may be that nearly 7 of 10 respondents said they had not heard or read much about the debate over proposals for a missile defense system.</p>
        <p>Even so, 4 of 10 voters said it was very important that the United States try and build a missile defense system; two-thirds said they favored such an effort, even though the government has already spent $60 billion trying to develop one.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Bush has repeatedly called upon Mr. Gore to elevate the discourse and not sink to harsh commercials, voters gave the vice president higher marks for his advertising campaign. Two-thirds of voters said Mr. Gore was spending more time explaining what he would do as president than he was spending attacking Mr. Bush; half said the same of Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>More than a third of voters have seen advertisements for Mr. Bush, and they are divided over whether they mostly explain things about Mr. Bush or attack Mr. Gore. About a third have seen advertisements for Mr. Gore. But those viewers, decisively, say Mr. Gore's commercials explain things about Mr. Gore rather than attack Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>In the voter interviews, many said Mr. Gore's selection of Senator Joseph I. Lieberman of Connecticut spiced up the ticket, especially when Mr. Lieberman was compared with Dick Cheney, who even many Republicans say has not been as beneficial to Mr. Bush as a running mate.</p>
        <p>''The move to choose Lieberman took a lot of guts and was brilliant,'' said Nati Gottlieb, 53, an insurance salesman in Philadelphia. ''That move stopped Bush dead in his tracks and started his current momentum.''</p>
        <p>Despite such comments, the poll reinforced the accepted wisdom that running-mate choices do not matter much. Mr. Cheney and Mr. Lieberman are each well liked, and each is about twice as likely to be viewed favorably as unfavorably. But most people still have no opinion of them. And more than half of the voters said the selections did not make them any more, or less, inclined to vote for Mr. Bush or Mr. Gore.</p>
        <p>Voters did not sound exercised about the frequent references to his faith by Mr. Lieberman, an Orthodox Jew. Voters said it was perfectly appropriate for candidates to discuss their religious beliefs, and a majority said none of the Democratic or Republican candidates had used their religion improperly.</p>
        <p>On the topic of televised debates, a subject that has dominated much of the campaign news in recent weeks, 49 percent said they believed Mr. Gore and Mr. Bush wanted to debate; 21 percent said only Mr. Gore wanted to debate and 10 percent said only Mr. Bush wanted to take part. Eighty-six percent said the bipartisan Commission on Presidential Debates should hold the events; the Bush campaign had earlier sought other sponsors.</p>
        <p>This is only the third time in 40 years that a presidential contest has been this close immediately after Labor Day, and that may be why more voters now say the race is interesting -- and not dull. Fifty-three percent say it is interesting; 39 percent say it is dull.</p>
        <p>A continuation of such interest  could spur turnout in the range of 50 percent to 55 percent, slightly higher than in 1996.</p>
        <p>In 1980, the contest between Jimmy Carter and Ronald Reagan was a dead heat at this point, with Mr. Reagan pulling ahead only over the final weekend. In 1960, the match-up between Richard M. Nixon and John F. Kennedy was equally tight at this stage, and stayed that way until Mr. Kennedy's narrow victory.</p>
        <p>''It's going to be one of the best horse races we've had in the country since Kennedy and Nixon,'' said Senator Peter G. Fitzgerald, Republican of Illinois. ''The Bush campaign is going to have to do most everything right between now and November to win. And it will not be easy.''</p>
        <p>Paul Maslin, a Democratic pollster, put it this way: ''This race is shaping up to be more like Kennedy-Nixon than anything else, mostly because of the closeness but also because of the dynamics of an incumbent hanging on with the country in pretty good shape but against a tough challenger.''</p>
        <p>How the Poll Was Conducted</p>
        <p>The latest New York Times/CBS News Poll is based on telephone interviews conducted Saturday through Monday with 1,050 adults throughout the United States. Of these, 843 said they were registered to vote.</p>
        <p>The sample of telephone exchanges called was randomly selected by a computer from a complete list of more than 42,000 active residential exchanges across the country.</p>
        <p>Within each exchange, random digits were added to form a complete telephone number, thus permitting access to both listed and unlisted numbers. Within each household, one adult was designated by a random procedure to be the respondent for the survey.</p>
        <p>The results have been weighted to take account of household size and number of telephone lines into the residence and to adjust for variations in the sample relating to geographic region, sex, race, age and education.</p>
        <p>In theory, in 19 cases out of 20 the results based on such samples will differ by no more than three percentage points in either direction from what would have been obtained by seeking out all American adults.</p>
        <p>For smaller subgroups, the margin of sampling error is larger.</p>
        <p>In addition to sampling error, the practical difficulties of conducting any survey of public opinion may introduce other sources of error into the poll. Variations in the wording and order of questions, for example, may lead to somewhat different results.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE POLLS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
