<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="13FSUM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230223"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000913T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E3D91438F930A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1129" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-14</p>
        <p>Fuel Price Protests Are Squeezing Britain  Protests over high fuel prices all but halted gasoline deliveries across Britain, forcing most service stations to close for lack of fuel. Ambulance and fire services were cut back and many hospitals canceled all but essential procedures. Some diesel train lines were canceled. The protests continued to spread through Western Europe, where truck drivers, farmers and small-business people have formed impromptu coalitions to protest high fuel prices.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>No Attack to Force Inspections  Secretary of State Madeleine K. Albright, speaking with reporters after addressing the opening session of the United Nations General Assembly, said the United States would not use force to make Iraq allow international arms inspections to resume.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-14</p>
        <p>Fuel Price Protests Are Squeezing Britain  Protests over high fuel prices all but halted gasoline deliveries across Britain, forcing most service stations to close for lack of fuel. Ambulance and fire services were cut back and many hospitals canceled all but essential procedures. Some diesel train lines were canceled. The protests continued to spread through Western Europe, where truck drivers, farmers and small-business people have formed impromptu coalitions to protest high fuel prices.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>No Attack to Force Inspections  Secretary of State Madeleine K. Albright, speaking with reporters after addressing the opening session of the United Nations General Assembly, said the United States would not use force to make Iraq allow international arms inspections to resume.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Annan Presses U.N. to Act  Secretary General Kofi Annan told the opening session of General Assembly that he wanted action to reorganize and strengthen peacekeeping operations and to enlarge the Security Council to give it a stronger voice for developing nations.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Sanctions on Austria Lifted  The European Union lifted its sanctions against Austria, seven months after hurriedly imposing a diplomatic freeze on Vienna for bringing a rightist party into its governing coalition. But the Europeans said they remained concerned about the party's role in the government and vowed to stay vigilant.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Protests at Australia Forum  Thousands of protesters tried to sabotage the meeting of the World Economic Forum in Melbourne, a few days before the Olympics are to open there, clashing with riot police and blocking the conference site.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>Holocaust Settlement Plan  A special master appointed by a federal judge overseeing a class action lawsuit has submitted a plan for distributing $1.25 billion in settlement payments from Swiss banks to Holocaust victims who have fought for decades to recover their savings.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A17-21</p>
        <p>Race is Neck-and-Neck As Gore Gains, Poll Shows  A New York Times/CBS News Poll shows 42 percent of registered voters favoring Vice President Al Gore and 39 percent favoring Gov. George W. Bush. Mr. Gore is now as highly regarded as Mr. Bush on matters of character, leadership and personal popularity. Mr. Gore has made substantial gains among women, independent voters and middle-income groups. While Mr. Bush's support has ebbed somewhat overall, he has the overwhelming support of men, Midwesterners and Southerners.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush said the brief appearance of the word ''rats'' in a campaign commercial was a fluke and not an attempt to send a subliminal message about Mr. Gore.</p>
        <p>A19</p>
        <p>Moral Victory for Buchanan  The F.E.C. issued an ''initial determination'' upholding Patrick J. Buchanan's claim to $12.6 million in disputed federal campaign funds earmarked for the Reform Party nominee, though the money was withheld pending a final determination.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>Effort on Patients' Rights Bill  Congressional supporters of a patients' bill of rights said they had revised the legislation passed by the House last year, to win the votes of a few more Senate Republicans.</p>
        <p>A21</p>
        <p>Wrangling in Secrets Case  The government and defense lawyers continued arguing over a plea agreement in which the former Los Alamos scientist Wen Ho Lee admits to one count of improperly downloading nuclear secrets in return for his release. And government officials began finger-pointing over the virtual collapse of their case.</p>
        <p>A17</p>
        <p>U.S. Death Penalty Review  Attorney General Janet Reno ordered United States attorneys to help explain stark racial disparities in federal death penalty cases.</p>
        <p>A17</p>
        <p>A Black Mayor for Selma  James Perkins Jr. defeated Joseph T. Smitherman, the former segregationist who has been mayor of Selma, Ala., since the 1960's.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>Limits on R-Rated Movies' Ads  Walt Disney said it would no longer accept advertising for R-rated movies on any programs on its ABC television network that are broadcast before 9 p.m., Eastern time.</p>
        <p>A21</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-9</p>
        <p>A Crime Alarm System For a Whole City Block  An Upper East Side block, 77th Street between Second and Third Avenues, will soon test a new anti-crime technology that lets residents use a small electronic device to set off an outside siren and lights and notify the police of a crime.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Surviving in the City  An economic study found that, depending on where in New York City a family lives, bare-bones needs for a family with children cost two to five times more than the $14,150 national poverty level set for a family of three by the federal government.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton Wins Primary  Hillary Rodham Clinton easily beat Dr. Mark S. McMahon for the Democratic Senate nomination. Representative Michael P. Forbes, a Democrat from Long Island who quit the Republicans in 1999, faced a strong challenge from Regina Seltzer.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>B10</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>B11</p>
        <p>CUNY Enrollments Are Up  The number of new freshmen at City University senior colleges rose 5 percent this fall, and at some campuses by more than 20 percent, despite predictions that ending remedial instruction would cut enrollment.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-14</p>
        <p>SCIENCE/HEALTH</p>
        <p>Evidence of a Great Flood  Scientists said a well-preserved structure, possibly thousands of years old, lies in the Black Sea off Turkey. It could prove that people thrived on an ancient shoreline before a great flood, perhaps the flood that inspired the story of Noah.</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>New Class of Black Hole  Astronomers cited evidence of a new class of black holes -- bigger than those formed from collapsed stars but much smaller than the giants found at the centers of galaxies.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-32</p>
        <p>Chase-Morgan Merger Talks  Chase Manhattan was expected to announce it was acquiring J. P. Morgan for $30.9 billion in stock.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Psst, Pay Less Tax! Pass It On  A company called Tax People, which teaches tax-avoidance techniques to ordinary taxpayers, says it has signed up 50,000 people who want to learn how to set up and use a home business to pay less taxes -- that business being the teaching of tax-avoidance techniques to others.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Falling Out Between Partners  Ford and Firestone traded accusations at a Senate hearing over responsibility for deaths from rollovers involving Ford Explorers and Firestone tires.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-10</p>
        <p>House Arrest for Strawberry  Darryl Strawberry was sentenced to two years' house arrest in Tampa, Fla., for violating his probation.</p>
        <p>D3</p>
        <p>DINING</p>
        <p>F1-14</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>22-23</p>
        <p>Editorials: The latest oil shock; Congress's obligation to nature; subliminal headache for Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>Columns: Paul Krugman, Maureen Dowd.</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E6  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E13  Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2  Weather</p>
        <p>D9</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
