<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Accusations of Misconduct In 2 Justice Dept. Programs</title>
    <meta content="Y13JUS$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/13/national/13JUST.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230219"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Justice Department</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marquis, Christopher</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reno, Janet (Atty Gen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Grassley, Charles E (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Braff, Robert K</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lake, Joseph R Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000913T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E5D91438F930A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="644" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Accusations of Misconduct In 2 Justice Dept. Programs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER MARQUIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Marquis, Christopher</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Sept. 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Report by Justice Department inspector general details 'egregious misconduct' by several department officials, including visa-fraud scheme to slip Russian girlfriends into US; recommends discipline against several managers of overseas training programs with regard to abuse of visa procedures, mishandling of classified documents, unauthorized travel and favoritism in hiring and promotions; programs train foreign police agencies and instruct foreign prosecutors and judges; Sen Charles Grassley has pressed Atty Gen Reno for crackdown; many of charges involve Robert K Braff, who served in various management roles from 1992, and Joseph R Lake Jr, now retired; Bratt denies misconduct (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Top Justice Department officials responsible for teaching foreigners about American-style justice and democracy engaged in ''egregious misconduct,'' including a visa-fraud scheme to slip Russian girlfriends into the United States, according to a report by the department's inspector general.</p>
        <p>In a report released to Congress today, the inspector general recommended discipline against several managers of the overseas training programs in abuse of visa procedures, mishandling classified documents, traveling by business class without authorization and practicing favoritism in hiring and promotions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Top Justice Department officials responsible for teaching foreigners about American-style justice and democracy engaged in ''egregious misconduct,'' including a visa-fraud scheme to slip Russian girlfriends into the United States, according to a report by the department's inspector general.</p>
        <p>In a report released to Congress today, the inspector general recommended discipline against several managers of the overseas training programs in abuse of visa procedures, mishandling classified documents, traveling by business class without authorization and practicing favoritism in hiring and promotions.</p>
        <p>The accusations span several years of the mid-1990's at the two programs: the International Criminal Investigative Training Assistance Program, which trains foreign police agencies in newly democratic nations, and the Office of Overseas Prosecutorial Development, Assistance and Training, which instructs foreign prosecutors and judges.</p>
        <p>Both programs are part of the Justice Department's criminal division, though they are financed through the State Department.</p>
        <p>Senator Charles E. Grassley, an Iowa Republican who has pressed Attorney General Janet Reno to crack down on the police training program since a whistleblower first raised concerns three years ago, called the report ''merely the latest example of how the Justice Department is a real mess.''</p>
        <p>Myron Marlin, a Justice Department spokesman, declined to say what action, if any, would be taken against the managers criticized by the inspector general.</p>
        <p>Many of the accusations involve Robert K. Bratt, a senior Justice Department official who enjoyed the confidence of Ms. Reno to the extent that she subsequently tapped him to help overhaul the Immigration and Naturalization Service in 1997.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bratt, who served in various management roles with the two training programs, beginning in 1992, made four trips to Russia in 1996 and 1997, the report said. During those visits, he met two women, one or both of whom became his ''Russian girlfriends,'' the inspector general said.</p>
        <p>The report asserted that Mr. Bratt and an associate, Joseph R. Lake Jr., who retired in 1997, used Mr. Bratt's authority to bypass the normal procedures to get United States visas for the women, which typically involved long lines at the American Embassy in Moscow and an interview by an embassy official.</p>
        <p>The Russian women were granted visas in April 1997, through a process reserved for special humanitarian cases or those involving an American government interest, it said.</p>
        <p>Despite assertions by Mr. Lake that the women had worked for Mr. Bratt, the report found, ''Both women socialized extensively with Bratt during his visits to Moscow, but Bratt did not have a professional relationship with them.'' Rather, the report said, they met Mr. Bratt through a Russian translator who ran a matchmaking service.</p>
        <p>Although neither of the women visited the United States using the visas, the report asserted that Mr. Bratt and Mr. Lake had committed ''egregious conduct.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bratt issued a statement today denying any abuse of his position. He portrayed himself as the target of an inspector general, whom he called ''out of control.''</p>
        <p>''After more than three and half years of intense investigation, 42 hours of interrogation into every aspect of my personal and professional life, and eight investigators harassing dozens of my friends and colleagues, the inspector general could not find a flyspeck of evidence of any illegality on my part,'' Mr. Bratt said.</p>
        <p>The report recommended several Justice Department managers for discipline, including Joseph Trincellito, the associate director of the police training program, for mishandling classified documents; Janice Stromsem, a former director of the program, for violating security regulations and personnel rules; and Cary Hoover, a special assistant, for sharing classified material with uncleared parties.</p>
        <p>The report said the inspector general would have recommended ''significant discipline'' for Mr. Bratt including ''possible termination,'' but noted that he retired last month.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
