<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Burst of Diversity Reanoints a Center</title>
    <meta content="13ALLI$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/13/arts/13ALLI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230120"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE REVIEWS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Anderson, Jack</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bragg, Osceola</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000913T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907E7D91738F930A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="481" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Burst of Diversity Reanoints a Center</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK ANDERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Anderson, Jack</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jack Anderson reviews performances in Y Dance! series, offered in tribute to Osceola Bragg at Sol Goldman YM-YWHA of Educational Alliance; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''Y Dance!'' exclaimed the title of the dance series offered last weekend at the Sol Goldman Y.M.-Y.W.H.A. of the Educational Alliance. If there was a question implied by those words, the reason for the performances soon became clear.</p>
        <p>They showed that this East Village Y is once again a lively dance center. The programs honored Osceola Bragg, who served as the Y's imaginative dance director from 1979 to 1994 and who is now the managing director of the American Repertory Ballet in New Jersey.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''Y Dance!'' exclaimed the title of the dance series offered last weekend at the Sol Goldman Y.M.-Y.W.H.A. of the Educational Alliance. If there was a question implied by those words, the reason for the performances soon became clear.</p>
        <p>They showed that this East Village Y is once again a lively dance center. The programs honored Osceola Bragg, who served as the Y's imaginative dance director from 1979 to 1994 and who is now the managing director of the American Repertory Ballet in New Jersey.</p>
        <p>There has been little dance activity at the Y in recent years and its building, on 14th Street near First Avenue, was long closed for renovations. But Tracy Kyle Present, its new dance coordinator, plans to make dance a major attraction there once again. The program on Saturday night suggested that she is continuing Ms. Bragg's policy of encouraging variety.</p>
        <p>A veteran modern dancer and three young ballet dancers contributed some of the evening's most satisfying pieces.</p>
        <p>Beverly Blossom, 73, an alumna of the Alwin Nikolais company, presented ''Sorry, Miss,'' a bittersweet solo in which she portrayed a downcast-looking, frumpily dressed woman who swayed sadly to a recording of Sibelius's ''Valse Triste.'' As she moved she recited a monologue recounting how the life and ambitions of the woman she portrayed were forever changed when she was rejected at a Broadway audition.</p>
        <p>Youthful glee and idealism were celebrated by Anna Gerberich, Carli Samuelson and Grant DeLong, ballet students from the Central Pennsylvania Youth Ballet who danced Melissa Stafford's sprightly ''Enjoue'' to Handel. All three seemed eager, gracious and very well trained.</p>
        <p>Amy O'Brien and Matthew Hope offered dancing of a more blustery no-nonsense sort in Ms. O'Brien's ''Bottleneck Blues,'' to a suite of blues recordings. This duet, showing two people trying to get along, was interesting for its choreographic contrasts between moments of concealing and moments of showing effort.</p>
        <p>Two other works were strongly performed, but less choreographically well focused. In ''The Stage,'' Hiroko Ishimura moved in a frenzied manner to mysterious piano music composed and played by Anthony Coleman and a raucous boogie-woogie recording by Shizuko Kasagi. Ms. Ishimura, who also choreographed this multimedia solo, compulsively tore strips of white paper, attacked images of herself in a film by Tomoaki Kosai and bathed in a metal pail, as if in a purification ritual.</p>
        <p>Kraig Patterson's ''Crackhead Waltz'' made Jennifer Howard, Eden Mazer and the choreographer stagger and twitch like drug addicts to a recording by Chance O. Both this dance and ''The Stage'' obviously concerned serious mental and physical disturbances. But because they offered little insights into the lives of their troubled characters, they remained emotionally uninvolving.</p>
        <p>DANCE REVIEWS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
