<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Journey to the Planet Brasserie</title>
    <meta content="13REST$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/13/living/13UNDE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230103"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="RESTAURANTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Brasserie 8 1/2 (NYC Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Grimes, William</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Columns/Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000913T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05EFDD1738F930A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1188" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Journey to the Planet Brasserie</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By William Grimes</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Grimes, William</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William Grimes reviews Brasserie 8 1/2, Manhattan restaurant; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MY vote for the hardest-working banana split in town goes to Brasserie 8 1/2. It's a strenuously conceptual dessert, a plateful of allusions, feints and inside jokes, the main one being the almost total absence of banana. From right to left, one encounters a small dome of caramelized banana on a quarter-size sable pastry disk, a medium-size puck of strawberry ice cream topped with strawberry slices and a large stack that begins with caramelized pineapple and ascends, in many chapters, through vanilla ice cream, almond sable, chocolate ice cream and chocolate syrup, with fascinating asides. If a split could sweat, this would be a three-towel production.</p>
        <p>Signs of overachievement are everywhere on the menu, and it is easy to understand why. The food has to go a long, long way to take anyone's mind off the design. Visually, Brasserie 8 1/2 is a knockout, a double surprise after the design assault unleashed this year at the Brasserie, the other below-ground restaurant operated by Restaurant Associates. If New York thought the last word in descending-staircase glamour had been uttered, it thought wrong.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MY vote for the hardest-working banana split in town goes to Brasserie 8 1/2. It's a strenuously conceptual dessert, a plateful of allusions, feints and inside jokes, the main one being the almost total absence of banana. From right to left, one encounters a small dome of caramelized banana on a quarter-size sable pastry disk, a medium-size puck of strawberry ice cream topped with strawberry slices and a large stack that begins with caramelized pineapple and ascends, in many chapters, through vanilla ice cream, almond sable, chocolate ice cream and chocolate syrup, with fascinating asides. If a split could sweat, this would be a three-towel production.</p>
        <p>Signs of overachievement are everywhere on the menu, and it is easy to understand why. The food has to go a long, long way to take anyone's mind off the design. Visually, Brasserie 8 1/2 is a knockout, a double surprise after the design assault unleashed this year at the Brasserie, the other below-ground restaurant operated by Restaurant Associates. If New York thought the last word in descending-staircase glamour had been uttered, it thought wrong.</p>
        <p>The downward swoosh at Brasserie 8 1/2 is a circular staircase in thick salmon carpeting. Taking a half turn, it winds down through an enormous hole in the floor to a low-slung illuminated onyx bar and an open-plan lounge, where deeply cushioned black leather chairs cluster.</p>
        <p>The anteroom feels like the departure lounge for the space shuttle. The dining room could be a galactic mess hall, with a white terrazzo tile floor, black leather booths and walls covered in a gray-green silk that looks like brushed steel. At the far end of the room, a stained-glass mural by Leger makes almost no impression. There's too much competition.</p>
        <p>Julian Alonzo, formerly the executive chef at Cafe Centro, obviously took one look at the playing field and decided that it would take audacity to win the day. The name of the restaurant -- which sounds Felliniesque but actually refers to the building that surrounds it, 9 West 57th Street -- demanded a brasserie menu, but Mr. Alonzo has taken liberties, some inspired, others puzzling and still others downright annoying.</p>
        <p>A frequently served amuse-bouche manages to be all three at once. Packaged in a V-shaped aperitif glass, it is a hearty, heady oxtail jus thick enough to hold tiny cheese ravioli in suspension. A thick layer of garlicky potato foam sits on top like the head on a pint of Guinness. It is a ravishing dish, in its way, but far too substantial in flavor, texture and portion to qualify as a palate-tickler. Finish it, and you're ready for a scoop of sorbet and the check.</p>
        <p>The traditional brasserie menu can be seen in a mostly standard raw bar selection (oysters, shrimp, clams), an iced seafood platter and a weekly rotation of specials like bouillabaisse on Fridays and confit of suckling pig on Thursdays. Wednesday deserves a check on the calendar. The plat du jour is a thick slab of Muscovy duck breast, coyly listed as a ''steak,'' with a crisp, golden skin outside, pink, oozing meat inside and a sweet, sticky fig compote on the side. A perfectly fine steak au poivre, mussels mariniere and a wonderfully gamy hanger steak round out the week.</p>
        <p>Familiar dishes incorporate inventive touches, like poached quail eggs,  which come with a frisee-lardons salad. A side dish of haricots verts, bright green and crunchy, comes with a luxurious coating of macadamia butter, simple but brilliant. A bristling sea urchin shell, balanced on a bed of salt and filled with a hefty chowder of urchin, clams, potatoes, peas and bacon bits, catches the eye and rewards the palate with its interplay of brine and earth.</p>
        <p>The flourishes can be beside the point, like dried shards of prosciutto, which come with duck steak, or an oxtail marmalade that partners the hanger steak, like a mini-portion of sweet barbecue that wandered over from another recipe. Tempura-fried squash blossoms do not need goat-cheese stuffing. The tempura batter is a mere wisp, the squash blossoms are fresh and flavorful -- what more could anyone ask for? A little less would add up to a little more.</p>
        <p>As part of the all-out effort, Brasserie 8 1/2 prepares the way for dessert with pre-dessert and punctuates the experience with a post-dessert. Pre-dessert, even at a high-tone French restaurant, often strikes me as overkill. At a brasserie, it seems utterly out of character, but I have to say, the little slice of apple strudel that came my way one evening made me abandon my principles. Topped with shavings of a smoky, nutty, slightly butterscotch aged Gouda, it made a nice little interlude before the tangled mysteries of the banana split. Or the superior sorbets, luscious fig tart, ''reverse'' chocolate souffle (a kind of molten chocolate cake) or the arresting milk-chocolate creme brulee, iced with a rose marmalade and surrounded by candied rose petals like Mena Suvari in ''American Beauty.''</p>
        <p>There is a design flaw. The booths in the center of the room are so deep that most waitresses cannot reach the diners on the inside. This fact has produced interesting socioeconomic results. It has placed a premium on male waiters with long arms, who are constantly called on to help. It makes ''pardon my reach'' the mantra for the evening.</p>
        <p>And it encourages diners to help clear the table rather than watch their waitress suffer. This in turn promotes a feeling of camaraderie and in the end, I suspect, bigger tips. The communal table has probably peaked. The double-wide booth looks like the coming thing.</p>
        <p>Brasserie 8 1/2  *  [Rating: one star]  9 West 57th Street; (212) 829-0812.</p>
        <p>ATMOSPHERE: Traditional and internationally accented brasserie dishes served in a stunningly designed undergroud room.  SOUND LEVEL: Not too loud.  RECOMMENDED DISHES: Potato and roasted garlic soup, hanger steak with oxtail marmalade, filet mignon au poivre, duck steak with figs, haricots verts with macadamia butter, milk chocolate creme brulee, fig tart.  SERVICE: Eager to please, casual and a bit amateurish.  WINE LIST: An eclectic international list of about 150 wines, with a dozen half bottles and wines by the glass.  PRICE RANGE: Lunch, appetizers, $8 to $15; entrees, $15 to $29; desserts, $8. Dinner, appetizers, $8 to $16; entrees, $18 to $30; desserts, $8.  HOURS: Breakfast, Monday through Friday, 7 to 10 a.m. Brunch, Saturday and Sunday, 11 a.m. to 3:30 p.m. Lunch, Monday through Friday, 11:30 to 3. Dinner, Monday through Saturday, 5:30 to midnight; Sunday, to 10.  CREDIT CARDS: All major cards.  WHEELCHAIR ACCESS: Elevators to dining room; restrooms via corridor.</p>
        <p>What the stars mean:</p>
        <p>(None) Poor to Satisfactory  * Good  ** Very Good  *** Excellent  **** Extraordinary</p>
        <p>Ratings reflect the reviewer's reaction primarily to food, with ambiance and service taken into consideration. Menu listings and prices are subject to change.</p>
        <p>Past restaurant reviews from the New York Times, with additional capsule reviews by Times critics, are available on New York Today: www.nytoday.com</p>
        <p>RESTAURANTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
