<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Black Bear Hunt Is Canceled After the Governor Intervenes</title>
    <meta content="13BEAR$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/13/science/13BEAR.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230221"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hunting and Trapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bears</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hanley, Robert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Whitman, Christine Todd (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hunting and Trapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000913T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E4D91438F930A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="645" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Black Bear Hunt Is Canceled After the Governor Intervenes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT HANLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hanley, Robert</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New Jersey Fish and Game Council, acceding to Gov Christine Todd Whitman's wishes, votes 6-4 to cancel state's first black bear hunt since 1970; narrow vote suggests dissenters see little wisdom in Whitman's plan for killing only aggressive bears (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>New Jersey's first black bear hunt since 1970 was canceled yesterday as the state agency that sets hunting rules acceded, with some unwillingness, to Gov. Christine Todd Whitman's wishes and voted narrowly to ban it.</p>
        <p>Governor Whitman asked the agency, the Fish and Game Council, for the cancellation on Friday, and she prevailed yesterday, but not before dissidents on the council who favored the hunt nearly inflicted a blow to her powers of persuasion.  The vote for cancellation was 6 to 4, the minimum needed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>New Jersey's first black bear hunt since 1970 was canceled yesterday as the state agency that sets hunting rules acceded, with some unwillingness, to Gov. Christine Todd Whitman's wishes and voted narrowly to ban it.</p>
        <p>Governor Whitman asked the agency, the Fish and Game Council, for the cancellation on Friday, and she prevailed yesterday, but not before dissidents on the council who favored the hunt nearly inflicted a blow to her powers of persuasion.  The vote for cancellation was 6 to 4, the minimum needed.</p>
        <p>''I see it more as a political decision than a wildlife management decision,'' one of the four dissenters, George P. Howard, said after the vote. He said the council traditionally drafted hunting regulations based on scientific analysis of the need to control the growth of various species. This time, he said, growing opposition to hunting in the state prompted the council to cancel the bear hunt.</p>
        <p>''The bear problem is just going to get worse,'' he said. ''Until we reduce them, we're going to have more and more problems.''</p>
        <p>As it was, the vote suggested that the dissidents took a dim view of the governor's request. Over the years, the council, an obscure, part-time panel with unpaid members, has enacted the state's hunting regulations with little political interference. But a coalition opposed to hunting mounted a campaign after the council first proposed the bear hunt in March.</p>
        <p>Governor Whitman finally asked the council on Friday to acknowledge the opposition and ban the hunt. The council, at her request, had already unanimously voted to cut the number of bears to be killed from 350 to 175.</p>
        <p>The split vote yesterday also suggested the council's dissenters saw little wisdom in Governor Whitman's counterproposal for a bear-control plan aimed only at killing bears that break into homes, attack pets, kill livestock or threaten people. Eliminating the most aggressive bears, Mrs. Whitman said Friday, was a better public safety measure than a random hunt.</p>
        <p>Early last night, the council's chairman, John W. Bradway, one of the six members voting for the ban, issued a statement expressing hope that the governor's new plan ''will help address bear safety problems in the near future.'' But Mr. Bradway said it was too early to know if the plan would be sufficient to address the steadily increasing numbers of conflicts between humans and bears.</p>
        <p>In a terse statement, the governor thanked the council for changing its position on the hunt, which was to start Monday. One element of her plan requires state wildlife agents to teach local police how to euthanize the most dangerous bears. Routinely, as the state's black bear population has grown from near extinction in 1971 to an estimated 1,000 now, local police have done little more than refer complaints to wildlife agents.</p>
        <p>Jayne O'Connor, a spokeswoman for the governor, said yesterday that the new plan called for spending $1 million in coming months to double the size of the state's bear-control unit to 14 agents and provide extra equipment for euthanizing.</p>
        <p>Although leaders of the anti-hunt coalition were overjoyed by the cancellation, some residents yesterday questioned whether the governor's plan would work.</p>
        <p>Rebecca Goldsworthy of Lafayette, a small Sussex County town, whose two pet goats were killed by bears in March 1999, said she doubted that local police would be effective against bears.</p>
        <p>''All my attacks happened at night,'' she said. ''By the time you call the police and they get out here, the bears are gone.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
