<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Working to Stop Suicides of Teenagers</title>
    <meta content="30TEEN$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218692"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suicides and Suicide Attempts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lynch, Mary Anne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Suicides and Suicide Attempts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suicides and Suicide Attempts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CEEDF163DF933A05754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1408" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Working to Stop Suicides of Teenagers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARY ANNE LYNCH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lynch, Mary Anne</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on rise in number of suicides and attempted suicides by teenagers in America and in Connecticut, which had second lowest suicide rate in country in 1997; experts comment on what drives teens to attempt suicide and possible adverse impact of suicide prevention programs; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOUR adolescents, ages 11, 13, 14 and 15, killed themselves in Connecticut in the first five months of this year. The deaths shook up the state and spurred prime-time television announcements from the State Department of Children and Families, community-wide suicide awareness forums, and questions about prevention tactics and possible trends.</p>
        <p>''This is a dicey issue to talk about,'' said Sue Eastgard, president-elect of the American Association of Suicidology. ''This is an issue that makes a lot of school administrators nervous and a lot of parents nervous.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOUR adolescents, ages 11, 13, 14 and 15, killed themselves in Connecticut in the first five months of this year. The deaths shook up the state and spurred prime-time television announcements from the State Department of Children and Families, community-wide suicide awareness forums, and questions about prevention tactics and possible trends.</p>
        <p>''This is a dicey issue to talk about,'' said Sue Eastgard, president-elect of the American Association of Suicidology. ''This is an issue that makes a lot of school administrators nervous and a lot of parents nervous.''</p>
        <p>The number of suicides within the 10-to-14-year-old age group had climbed nationally from 165 in 1981 to 303 in 1997, the most recent year for which records are available from the National Centers for Disease Control and Prevention.</p>
        <p>In the C.D.C. survey, suicide had hovered between the second and third leading cause of death for 10 to 14 year olds in Connecticut since 1991. In 1997, it was also the fourth leading cause of death among 15 to 19 year olds. ''Suicide rates are not too stable for the younger age group in Connecticut,'' said Keri Lubell, a behavioral scientist with the C.D.C. ''The numbers are so small that the slightest increase can appear to be a large percentage leap.''</p>
        <p>Connecticut had the second lowest suicide rate in the country in 1997, but, Ms. Lubell said, ''Suicide is clearly undercounted. Research shows that different communities are less likely to report or code something as a suicide.'' For every completed suicide, there are 10-15 attempts, health experts said.</p>
        <p>Twelve percent of the state's seventh-grade girls and eight percent of boys attempted suicide, according to responses on the 1996 Voice of Connecticut Youth survey, which was administered by the State Department of Public Health. The department said about 12,000 students responded to the survey. The figures were highest for high school freshman girls, 14 percent of whom reported attempting suicide, double the rate of their male classmates, said Mary Adams of the community health division of the health department, which initiated the study but lacks funds for follow-up testing.</p>
        <p>In the C.D.C.'s 1997 survey of Connecticut's high school girls, 27.5 percent reported that they seriously considered attempting suicide, 19.9 percent made a suicide plan, and 12.5 percent attempted suicide one or more times. On the same Youth Risk Behavior survey, 15.7 percent of high school boys indicated they considered suicide, 13.4 percent made a plan and 5.6 percent attempted it.</p>
        <p>Thirty of the 35 suicides committed by Connecticut's 10 to 14 year olds between 1985 and 1997 were committed by boys, Ms. Lubells said. Among 15 to 19 year olds, 164 out of 202 suicides were by boys.</p>
        <p>''Adolescence is a really bad time for depression,'' said Dr. David Shaffer, a professor at Columbia University and president of the American Foundation for Suicide Prevention. Investigating youth suicides, Dr. Shaffer found, ''Over 90 percent of those who committed suicide were suffering from mental illness.'' Clinical depression was the predominant illness among girls, but boys manifest two different behaviors, he said.</p>
        <p>Most common are boys who are very impulsive or excitable. Their suicides nearly always happen shortly after they've gotten into trouble or argued with a girlfriend, Dr. Shaffer said. Another group of boys who commit suicide are very anxious, perfectionists.</p>
        <p>''They always imagine the worst, even though they very often do very well,'' Dr. Shaffer said. They commit suicide before an event they fear, and both groups tend to get depressed before their deaths, he said.</p>
        <p>No one recognized that Craig Toribara was depressed before he committed suicide, said Christie Toribara, his mother. He was a good student, musician and athlete, awaiting calls from university coaches, one of which came from the soccer coach at Johns Hopkins University the day after Craig died.</p>
        <p>The night her son died, the police wanted to send away some of his classmates who had gathered outside her house, but she said she wanted to talk with them. ''We could not be silent,'' she said. ''We made our public statement saying as much as we love him, we disagree with what he did.''</p>
        <p>Cluster suicides occur 3 to 5 percent of the time with young people.</p>
        <p>''It is a real public health phenomenon among 15 to 19 year olds,'' said Dr. Madelyn Gould, epidemiologist at Columbia University, one of the country's largest suicide research centers. The rates are underestimated because three or more suicides must occur within a limited time and place to be counted as a cluster. The suicides of a middle school boy and a high school boy in North Branford this year and the joint suicides in East Haddam of two teenagers could not be counted as clusters, even though the two boys in East Haddam acted together. Preliminary research suggests that in most cluster suicides the children only knew each other in a very distant way, Dr. Gould said.</p>
        <p>Studies from around the world also show a significant increase in the number of suicides after newspaper articles about a specific person, Dr. Gould said. ''The amount of the increase is proportional to the magnitude of the coverage,'' she said. ''Front-page coverage showed a bigger increase.''</p>
        <p>Subtle components of a story might give an unintended message that there are rewards from suicide, such as getting attention or getting back at someone, she said.</p>
        <p>Separate brain studies of those who committed suicide show alterations in the number of serotonin receptors, which appear to play a role in controlling impulses, said Dr. David Brent, psychiatrist and professor at the University of Pittsburgh Medical Center.</p>
        <p>Dopamine, which transmits nerve pulses in the central nervous system and is thought to play a role in a number of psychiatric disorders, was significantly lower in 12 to 26 year olds who attempted suicide, said Dr. Laurence Greenhill, investigating at Columbia University.</p>
        <p>While scientists explore the nuances of the brain, others are examining prevention programs and resources, and finding they may not always help those most in need. Connecticut was the first state to implement a statewide crisis information hot line, 211, which received 1,500 suicide-related calls last year, said Ms. Mary Drexler, vice president of United Way, which runs the Infoline.</p>
        <p>When a large suicide awareness program was studied by Dr. Shaffer for its impact on students in New York, it was found that the program itself upset a minority of those who were previously depressed.</p>
        <p>''We didn't find it had any good effect,'' said Dr. Shaffer, who favors individually screening each student.</p>
        <p>Cromwell High School held a student-designed suicide awareness assembly in May. Ms. Drexler, who discussed suicide behaviors and resources at the assembly and who trains all age groups, said, ''We've been getting more and more requests to go to middle schools and high schools.''</p>
        <p>Children bring up the topic, said Dr. Steven Durham, superintendent of schools in East Haddam. ''Kids have a curiosity and need to know. It is appropriate to be factual and to be sensitive in responding to them.''</p>
        <p>In May, East Haddam hosted an assembly on suicide and grieving for adults, with small group sessions for children. North Branford also held a community-wide session and is designing a character Development curriculum for kindergarten through 12th grade, said Ms. Joan Follo, town curriculum director.</p>
        <p>Many practitioners who work with youths recommend small classroom discussions that address depression, mental health and problem-solving, rather than a unit on suicide. ''We have to be careful about how we frame it,'' said Ms. Lubell, who is studying prevention practices for C.D.C.</p>
        <p>Over the summer, while researchers sift out answers, the state's public service announcements will remind parents, children and friends that help is available at child guidance centers located throughout the state and through 211.</p>
        <p>''We want people to understand, they do not need to confront a crisis  alone,'' said Gary Kleeblatt, a spokesman for the State Department of Children and Families.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
