<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Time for Island's Soccer Fans to Step Up</title>
    <meta content="30JOUR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218664"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="LONG ISLAND JOURNAL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Longevity</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parties (Social)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nursing Homes</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fischler, Marcelle S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nursing Homes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parties (Social)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Age, Chronological</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E6DF1F3AF933A05754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1655" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Time for Island's Soccer Fans to Step Up</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARCELLE S. FISCHLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fischler, Marcelle S</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Long Island Journal column: soccer is booming on island; Junior Soccer League reports that more than 70,000 youths between ages 5 and 18 are on traveling or intramural teams, 40 percent of whom are girls; in addition, there are more than 300 adult teams; 65 residents of United Presbyterian Residence in Woodbury, all of them over 95, join five centenarians celebrating their birthdays; list; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ROB MURPHY, 12, hadn't had enough. He started playing soccer at 9 a.m. on Monday, dribbling, passing and shooting the hours away. But when the clinics at his camp, the Paul Riley Soccer School of Excellence, ended at 4 p.m., Rob didn't take off his cleats.</p>
        <p>Clutching an orange soccer ball, Rob -- who practices separately for the Port Washington Blue Storm, a travel team, and is in training for a soccer tournament in Canada next month through Liberty Soccer in Copiague -- waited by the stands at the Mitchel Athletic Complex in Uniondale. The MetroStars, the New Jersey-based Major League Soccer team, were coming to practice for a U.S. Open Cup challenge against the Tampa Bay Mutiny. And though he had another soccer practice later that evening, Rob wanted to watch and get their autographs first.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ROB MURPHY, 12, hadn't had enough. He started playing soccer at 9 a.m. on Monday, dribbling, passing and shooting the hours away. But when the clinics at his camp, the Paul Riley Soccer School of Excellence, ended at 4 p.m., Rob didn't take off his cleats.</p>
        <p>Clutching an orange soccer ball, Rob -- who practices separately for the Port Washington Blue Storm, a travel team, and is in training for a soccer tournament in Canada next month through Liberty Soccer in Copiague -- waited by the stands at the Mitchel Athletic Complex in Uniondale. The MetroStars, the New Jersey-based Major League Soccer team, were coming to practice for a U.S. Open Cup challenge against the Tampa Bay Mutiny. And though he had another soccer practice later that evening, Rob wanted to watch and get their autographs first.</p>
        <p>''Soccer is my No. 1,'' said Rob, who lives in Bohemia. ''There's the competition, the movement of the ball, the combination plays, the teamwork. It's fluid. I love the game.''</p>
        <p>On Tuesday night, Rob was back at the field with his dad, Bob Murphy, and Rob's teammate, Brett Heyder, 11, a striker and center midfielder from Bayport. They were among the 5,183 fans watching the first match between two Major League Soccer teams played on Long Island.</p>
        <p>''Playing is better,'' Rob said, pointing out combination plays. ''But it's good to try and learn from this kind of stuff.''</p>
        <p>Soccer on Long Island is booming. According to the Long Island Junior Soccer League, more than 70,000 youths between the ages of 5 and 18 play soccer, including 20,000 to 25,000 children on 1,400 travel teams and about 50,000 enrolled in intramural play. Forty percent of the players are girls, with 474 female travel teams. It is believed to be the largest youth soccer league in the country.</p>
        <p>Additionally, there are more than 300 adult teams, including the Long Island Men's Soccer recreational league, the Long Island Soccer Football League and the Long Island Ladies Soccer League, which began 21 years ago when a group of soccer moms decided to kick the ball themselves. The L.I. Lady Riders, a semi-professional team, and L.I. Rough Riders, a minor league team, woo crowds. And Back of the Net, a Web site catering to local youth soccer, gets two million hits a month, according to its owner, Larry Miller.</p>
        <p>Soccer is the sport of choice for youngsters, said Octavio Zambrano, the MetroStars' head coach. And it is the success of local youth soccer that convinced MetroStars' management, as well as broad support among the ethnic community, that a grass-roots effort was the way to build enthusiasm for the New Jersey franchise among Long Island fans.</p>
        <p>''These are the guys growing up with the sport,'' Mr. Zambrano said. ''They will understand later on what the game is really about, how to play it, what the rules are, the passion that it brings out, the preparation that it takes to compete. We are in many ways pioneers of the sport. Ten to 20 years from now, this sport will have its niche in the sports landscape of this country.''</p>
        <p>Already, 14 players in Major League Soccer grew up playing in the Long Island Junior Soccer League, including Metros forward Julian Gomez, defender Mike Petke and defender Mark Semioli.</p>
        <p>Unlike their children, most baby boomers did not grow up with soccer, said Tricia Rudd, director of the North Hempstead Cup, a new Columbus Day weekend tournament expected to draw 250 youth teams, and a host of a local soccer radio show, ''Just Kickin' It.'' So on a spectator level, they are often reluctant participants.</p>
        <p>''The generation after them and this generation are going to be the ones who are going to bring it all together,'' Mr. Zambrano said. ''They are the ones who will be ready to embrace the sport wholeheartedly.''</p>
        <p>Like many fathers, Mr. Murphy, 52, couldn't wait until his son was old enough to have a catch. But when Rob was 7 years old, he told his father he hated baseball. He wanted to play soccer.</p>
        <p>''I was destroyed,'' Mr. Murphy said. ''I wanted him to play baseball. He wanted to play soccer. He just seemed to like kicking the ball. Just because of the excitement of watching him play I fell in love with the game. I'm still a Yankees fan, but not so actively.''</p>
        <p>Along with the rest of his teammates, Brendan Baker, 10, came to the cup in his Rockville Centre soccer uniform.</p>
        <p>''I like playing soccer 99 percent and I like watching it 99 percent,'' he said, jumping up and down as the players ran down the field toward the goal. ''It's really fun when you hear the crowd scream when there's a goal -- Ole! Ole! Ole!''</p>
        <p>But the draw is not just for children. Since the MetroStars began playing five years ago, Jeff Orland, 33, of Wayne, N.J., has only missed two games. One for a funeral, one for a wedding. So there was no way he wasn't going to drive to Uniondale after work as a computer consultant in Manhattan and watch the match.  ''Diehard fan,'' Mr. Orland said as  fans stamped their feet against the metal bleachers. ''I enjoy the games at Giants Stadium, but this is more personal,'' he said. ''You are a little closer to the field.''</p>
        <p>And to the players. When the bus carrying the team pulled up on Tuesday, Jessica Cruz, 24, of Uniondale, was waiting by the fence, hoping to see Mr. Petke.</p>
        <p>''I've got goosebumps,'' she screeched. ''He's so scrumptious. This is going to be really good.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Cruz and her husband, Edgar, have been following the MetroStars since the league formed five years ago. Three times this season, they took the 45-minute-to-two-hour trip -- depending on traffic -- to Giants Stadium. The prospect of a game only a mile from their home seemed almost too good to be true.</p>
        <p>''If there's good soccer, the fans will come,'' said Mr. Cruz, 26. ''For us, this is great. We are two minutes away. We can practically see the house from the stands.''</p>
        <p>Dressed in a red soccer jersey, Kelly Hendricken, 11, of Oceanside ran after the MetroStars as they headed toward the field, trying to get autographs.</p>
        <p>''I watch a little bit of rugby sometimes and baseball too, but soccer is on top,'' said Kelly, who plays on a girls' travel team and attended soccer camp this summer.</p>
        <p>Kelly's enthusiasm is infectious.  Since she started playing, her mother, Jeanne Hendricken, 36, also follows the games.</p>
        <p>''I even watch them on Telemundo in Spanish,'' Mrs. Hendricken said. ''We just don't listen to the commentary. We can't understand it.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Hendricken said she would like to see a Major League Soccer team based on Long Island. ''It's a pain having to go all the way to Jersey,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The MetroStars won 3-0, advancing to the quarterfinals against the Columbus Crew, another MLS team. The U.S. Open, the oldest cup competition in American soccer, is open to any affiliated amateur or professional team in the United States. The winner gets $200,000.</p>
        <p>Ms. Cruz stood by the locker room door, camera in hand, waiting for Mr. Petke. She begged for his shirt. She begged for his socks. She snapped his photograph. He handed another fan his cleats. Never mind. There would be other chances. The soccer match had still captured her heart.</p>
        <p>''It was awesome. Awesome, awesome,'' Ms. Cruz said.</p>
        <p>100 Years Young</p>
        <p>The party was billed as ''Stars Among Us: A Celebration of Age.'' Admission was strictly limited. Only those 95 and older were allowed in.</p>
        <p>For the 65 residents of the United Presbyterian Residence in Woodbury who made the cut, cake and Champagne was served under a pastel balloon arch in the Arlington Chapel at the skilled nursing facility recently as five centenarians celebrated their birthdays.</p>
        <p>The Tangerine band was playing ''Let Me Call You Sweetheart.'' And Frances Cascio, who turns 100 on Aug. 22, wanted to dance. ''I'm here and I'm the party girl,'' Ms. Cascio said. ''They don't want me to walk without a walker. They should see how I can run.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Cascio, who was born in New York four months after her mother arrived from Italy, hoped that the Nassau County executive, Thomas Gulotta, would be her dance partner.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gulotta demurred. Alluding to two left feet, he gave Ms. Cascio a kiss. Ralph Caruso, deputy commissioner of senior affairs for Nassau County, danced with Ms. Cascio instead.</p>
        <p>Jean Carras, who turned 100 on July 20, sang and swayed to the music from her wheelchair. Katherine Debona, who reached her 100th birthday in June, enjoyed a few sips of Champagne. Rose Teseo, who turns 100 on Oct. 22, was also being honored.</p>
        <p>Out of 642 residents at the residence, 15 are 100 years old or older, said Kelly Brady, 31, director of recreation therapy. Seventy-seven belong to the 95-plus club. The oldest resident, Carmen Peterin, is 109.</p>
        <p>''No matter how old you are, there's still quality of life,'' Ms. Brady said. ''You're still learning. You're still growing.''</p>
        <p>The secret to a long life? ''Live and be merry,'' said Ms. Cascio, who enjoys game shows on television and says the rosary every day. ''What will be will be. Throw it over your shoulder. Tomorrow is another day.''</p>
        <p>LONG ISLAND JOURNAL E-mail address: lijournal@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail address: lijournal@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
