<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Leviathan</title>
    <meta content="30DACOST" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218534"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Da Costa, Erica</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hardwick, Elizabeth</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Melville, Herman (1819-91)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Herman Melville (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06EFD81F3BF933A05754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="699" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Leviathan</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Erica Da Costa</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Da Costa, Erica</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Erica Da Costa reviews book Herman Melville by Elizabeth Hardwick (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HERMAN MELVILLE</p>
        <p>By Elizabeth Hardwick.</p>
        <p>161 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Lipper/Viking. $19.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HERMAN MELVILLE</p>
        <p>By Elizabeth Hardwick.</p>
        <p>161 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Lipper/Viking. $19.95.</p>
        <p>EVERY biographer of Herman Melville embarks on an impossible journey. The aggressive obscurity of Melville's life, particularly the last 19 years, spent in a clerkship at a Custom House, makes his story as impenetrable as it is tantalizing. His youthful voyage on the ship Acushnet, which provided the basis for his greatest fiction, is a maddening void, with not even a logbook surviving. Fewer than 300 letters have been found to document his 72 years, from 1819 to 1891, which concluded with a period famously known as his ''withdrawal.'' Even to his ubiquitous aristocratic family, he was a mystery.</p>
        <p>When his fiction was rediscovered in the 1920's, beginning with the publication of Raymond Weaver's ''Herman Melville: Mariner and Mystic'' in 1921, the investigative dissection began. Despite the scarcity of documentary evidence, Melville scholars have obsessively pursued the minutiae of his life. Hershel Parker managed to produce a 941-page book in 1996 as merely the first of a two-volume biography. Where there were no facts to rely on, Parker necessarily imagined plausible scenarios.</p>
        <p>Elizabeth Hardwick's biography of Melville is not a scholarly chronicle but a literary critique couched in terms of a life. Hardwick, a literary critic as well as a novelist and the author of the essay ''Bartleby in Manhattan,'' is so enamored of her subject, however, that she glides along in a mode of repetitive superlatives, describing ''Moby-Dick'' as ''grand,'' ''unparalleled,'' ''incomparable'' -- all in the space of three pages. That Melville is a great writer hardly need be said, but to explain why he is a great writer requires a perception less adoring and more attentive to the knotty nature of greatness. Hardwick's ''Herman Melville'' is long on adoration and short on critical attention.</p>
        <p>Melville was the grandson of well-to-do Revolutionary War heroes on both sides of his family, and thus the inheritor of accompanying expectations and privileges. Before he was 13 years old, however, gentility had become genteel poverty. His father had died, but not before plunging all eight of his children and their mother into fathomless debt. As a young man coming of age, Melville dived headlong into what would take him farthest from the familial decay around him: whaling. This experience produced the novels ''Typee'' (1846) and ''Omoo'' (1847), which were his most commercially successful books -- a fact he both bitterly resented and eventually embraced. ''Moby-Dick'' (1851) would sell fewer than 10,000 copies in Melville's lifetime.</p>
        <p>Melville's fiction so eclipses the few knowable facts of his life that Hardwick's decision to focus primarily on his work seems wise. The life and work rarely show a link in any concrete way, and so Hardwick dispenses almost entirely with biographical detail. A mere paragraph is given to the suicide of Melville's oldest son, Malcolm. The chapter entitled ''Hawthorne'' touches briefly on the profound friendship between the two writers, described in a letter from Melville to Hawthorne: ''I feel the Godhead is broken up like the bread at the Supper, and that we are the pieces. Hence this infinite fraternity of feeling.'' In the same chapter, Hardwick returns, as if by uncontrollable reflex, to worship at the altar of ''Moby-Dick.'' In fact, there is little about Hawthorne in the chapter that bears his name.</p>
        <p>It is interesting to observe the fusing of Hardwick's sumptuous style with a subject of such elusive grandeur, but the innumerable expressions of pure devotion take up valuable room in a short book. ''Ahab: nothing to stand with him in our literature before or after. His character at once enclosed by obsession and then again regal in complication, his being scarred like his face when Ishmael at last sees him, scarred from a wound or a birthmark, nature's inexpungible marking.'' Despite Hardwick's stylistic elegance, we are left with the notion that Melville was a great writer and an obscure man -- not a remarkable insight. We still want to know, why, as Hawthorne notes in a journal, had Melville ''made up his mind to be annihilated''?</p>
        <p>Erica Da Costa writes about literature and film.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Erica Da Costa writes about literature and film.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
