<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Jenifer Ringer, James Fayette</title>
    <meta content="30RING$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Society Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218745"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="WEDDINGS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEDDINGS AND ENGAGEMENTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">RINGER, JENIFER ELLEN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FAYETTE, JAMES LAWRENCE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Weddings and Celebrations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E6D8163DF933A05754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="669" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Jenifer Ringer, James Fayette</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jenifer Ellen Ringer and James Lawrence Fayette, dancers at the New York City Ballet, were married yesterday at the Cathedral Church of St. John the Divine in New York. Canon Jonathan King, a retired Episcopal priest, performed the ceremony, with the Rev. Charles Kullmann, a Roman Catholic priest, participating.</p>
        <p>The bride, 27, is a principal dancer for the company; the bridegroom, 29, is a soloist.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jenifer Ellen Ringer and James Lawrence Fayette, dancers at the New York City Ballet, were married yesterday at the Cathedral Church of St. John the Divine in New York. Canon Jonathan King, a retired Episcopal priest, performed the ceremony, with the Rev. Charles Kullmann, a Roman Catholic priest, participating.</p>
        <p>The bride, 27, is a principal dancer for the company; the bridegroom, 29, is a soloist.</p>
        <p>Ms. Ringer, who will continue to use her name professionally, graduated summa cum laude from Fordham University. She is a daughter of Scharlene and Carl Douglas Ringer of Chattanooga, Tenn.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fayette, who has also danced in, and directed, his own ballet productions, is chairman of the New York City Ballet Dancers' Committee, the dancers' union liaison. He is a sophomore at Fordham. He is the son of Benita and James Fayette of Valencia, Spain.</p>
        <p>The couple met in 1988, as students at the School of American Ballet in New York, where Mr. Fayette recalls first seeing Ms. Ringer at a pas de deux class. He says he noticed her sweetness and generosity.</p>
        <p>''When you are working as partners in pas de deux class, there is lots of give and take,'' he said. ''Some dancers can become very dominating. Her attitude was, 'What can I do to help you make this move better?' ''</p>
        <p>He began inviting her on group outings with his friends, but she never accepted.</p>
        <p>''I was always half afraid of him,'' Ms. Ringer said. ''We didn't hang out together, because he was in the cool crowd. He had a bunch of friends, and they would go out together and have fun. I was more nerdy and stayed at home. I didn't think he would be interested in an introverted girl.''</p>
        <p>The next year, Ms. Ringer became an apprentice at the City Ballet, and they didn't see one another again until 1990, when Mr. Fayette joined the company as an apprentice. Eventually, they found themselves rehearsing and performing together.</p>
        <p>Nearly every pas de deux has some romantic aspect to it, but no sparks flew between them outside the studio for close to seven years. Finally, in August 1997, they traveled together to Vermont and Nantucket to perform in dances directed by Mr. Fayette.</p>
        <p>''We started getting to know one another as people rather than just dancers,'' Ms. Ringer said. ''I liked his honesty. He didn't play games. And he treated me like a normal girl. I was used to being treated like a ballet dancer, like I was made of porcelain.'' Yet, she had misgivings about a romance with a dancer.</p>
        <p>Then, in December 1997, he called and suggested they get together. Ms. Ringer recalled: ''At first, I thought we were going to rehearse. And then he said, 'I'll pick you up,' and I knew it was a date. I was pleasantly surprised.'' That night after ice-skating at Wollman Rink, they looked at the Christmas lights at Rockefeller Center, where Mr. Fayette took her hand romantically for the first time.</p>
        <p>''What is different about being a dancer is that there is a certain physical familiarity,'' Mr. Fayette said, explaining the significance of such a small gesture among dancers. ''When you take that outside the studio, it has a very different meaning.''</p>
        <p>On Aug. 18, 1999, after an excursion to Fire Island, they returned to Manhattan, where Mr. Fayette surprised Ms. Ringer by proposing at sunset as they sat on a bench in Riverside Park.</p>
        <p>''I used to say that I would never date or marry a dancer,'' Ms. Ringer said. ''Now I can't imagine not being married to one. They understand your aches and pains. And if you are in the same company together, you are not separated for long periods of time. You have the same time on and off. If he bangs up his back, I can help him ice it.''</p>
        <p>WEDDINGS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
