<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Almanac Documents Life on the Hudson River</title>
    <meta content="30ALMA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Books; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218645"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ENVIRONMENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Hudson River</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Purple Mountain Press</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Environmental Conservation Department (NYS)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ames, Lynne</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Hudson River Almanac (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E5D91E3AF933A05754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1492" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Almanac Documents Life on the Hudson River</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYNNE AMES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ames, Lynne</byline>
      <dateline>WAPPINGER FALLS</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Volume five of Hudson River Almanac, produced by New York State Department of Environmental Conservation's Hudson River Estuary Project, has been published by Purple Mountain Press; book documents life in and around Hudson River from one spring equinox to next; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ABOUT two years ago, hundreds of alewives and striped bass, 17 small blue crabs and one 3 1/2-inch killifish with iridescent blue bands were spotted on the Hudson River near Kowawese state park in New Windsor, N.Y. This minute natural occurrence, like thousands of other such small events, was in itself far from earth shattering. But taken in context, it is a tiny piece of the sprawling mosaic that is life in and around the river.</p>
        <p>That life is documented day by day, year by year, in The Hudson River Almanac. Produced by the New York State Department of Environmental Conservation's Hudson River Estuary Program, published by Purple Mountain Press in Fleischmanns, N.Y., the almanac has been available annually since 1994. The one being sold now for $10 in bookstores is Volume V, which spans the year between spring equinoxes 1998 and 1999. Volume VI, March 20, 1999, through March 21, 2000, will be published this fall. Entries for Volume VII have been recorded since March 20 of this year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ABOUT two years ago, hundreds of alewives and striped bass, 17 small blue crabs and one 3 1/2-inch killifish with iridescent blue bands were spotted on the Hudson River near Kowawese state park in New Windsor, N.Y. This minute natural occurrence, like thousands of other such small events, was in itself far from earth shattering. But taken in context, it is a tiny piece of the sprawling mosaic that is life in and around the river.</p>
        <p>That life is documented day by day, year by year, in The Hudson River Almanac. Produced by the New York State Department of Environmental Conservation's Hudson River Estuary Program, published by Purple Mountain Press in Fleischmanns, N.Y., the almanac has been available annually since 1994. The one being sold now for $10 in bookstores is Volume V, which spans the year between spring equinoxes 1998 and 1999. Volume VI, March 20, 1999, through March 21, 2000, will be published this fall. Entries for Volume VII have been recorded since March 20 of this year.</p>
        <p>The unusual spring equinox to spring equinox way of marking a year is a deliberate choice on the part of the almanac's editor, Tom Lake, a 51-year-old writer, scientist, educator, researcher and fisherman who lives on an escarpment above the river here. ''If I was going to be true to the theme of continuity of life, to the theme of natural history, it didn't make sense to impose an anthropomorphic artifact like a man-made calendar,'' he said. ''That seems a little arrogant. We are only one member of the continuity of life; other species did not vote on the calendar.''</p>
        <p>This respect for natural phenomena is at the almanac's core, and is reflected in entries by Mr. Lake and dozens of others. Contributors include teachers, commercial and recreational fishermen, scientists, conservationists, designers of nature programs for nonprofit agencies, schoolchildren and a variety of Hudson River Valley residents. They live anywhere from the Adirondacks, where the river begins at Lake Tear-of-the-Clouds, to Staten Island, where, 325 miles south of its origins at Mount Marcy, it empties into the sea. Entries range from a few words to a few hundred; each observation includes the place name and the ''H.R.M.'' -- Hudson River Mile -- number at which it occurred.</p>
        <p>It was the multiplicity of river-related phenomena that led to the almanac's inception in 1993. The Department of Environmental Conservation asked Mr. Lake if he would edit a journal which would encompass the entire body of water and the land along its shores.</p>
        <p>''So many people along the river were seeing so many different things, were observing so many important moments that were not being shared with anyone but their neighbors,'' Mr. Lake said. ''If you live in a Westchester river town, for example, and someone tips your garbage can over at night, chances are its a skunk or a raccoon. If you're in the Adirondacks, it's a black bear.'' Because the river is tidal until Troy, N.Y., and has some salt in it 75 miles north in Poughkeepsie, he added, ''people in the lower river towns sometimes see harbor seals and porpoises that people in the Adirondacks never get to see; there are so many stories that need to be shared.''</p>
        <p>''We have the opportunity to tell those stories because of support from Governor Pataki's Estuary Program.''</p>
        <p>Among the frequent contributors is Christopher Letts, a 58-year-old Cortlandt Manor resident who is the naturalist and river teacher for the Manhattan-based, nonprofit Hudson River Foundation for Scientific Research. Thirty years ago, Mr. Letts recalled, ''I was a freshly minted graduate student who bad-mouthed'' the Hudson's pollution: ''All I'd ever seen in it were condoms and toilet paper.'' He became a convert when a lifelong fisherman challenged him to take an extended ride. ''I saw them put 4,000 pounds of shad, striped bass and herring on that boat.''</p>
        <p>Now he cannot get enough of the life and lore of the river that has become his profession and his personal cause. ''The almanac has made me a better observer. Having to write things down in readable form has made me observe them more closely. It is a great way for people to participate in their own lives.''</p>
        <p>Those interested in contributing should mail articles or photographs to Tom Lake, 7 Steinhaus Lane, Wappinger Falls, N.Y., 12590, or send them by fax to (914) 297-8935 or e-mail to trlake7@aol.com. To order the almanac, the number to call is (800) 325-2665.</p>
        <p>In volume V, there are 700 or so written entries, and approximately 100 black-and-white photographs. Among the first is one from Mr. Lake, dated March 20, 1998, recorded on the Hudson River at Calamity Brook, Hudson River mile 310. (In official records, miles begin at zero at the battery.) ''It may seem irreverent,'' he writes, ''but I go to 'church' once a year, at the vernal equinox, to the high peaks of the Adirondacks where our river is born. There is no grander cathedral within or without human culture to match the origin of our river as winter wanes.''</p>
        <p>Four days later, Mr. Lake and his wife, Phyllis, recorded this entry from Cedarcliff, a spot in Orange County at Hudson River mile 67.5: ''The mated bald eagle pair was still with us. The warm early spring day had melted much of the snow and was now giving way to a colorful sunset. Reflected in its glow were our pair of eagles, perched side by side in their red oak at Cedarcliff. The slightly larger, and probable female, eagle, had the southern exposure and the warm rays of the setting sun. This would be the last we would see them this season. The next morning they were on their way north -- to nest, to breed, to fledge young. It would be eight months before we would see them again.''</p>
        <p>See them again they did, on Christmas Day, 1998. In his entry from Farmer's Landing, a half mile from his house, Hudson River mile 67, Mr. Lake writes about watching a bald eagle swoop down on a fish, and notes, ''Bald eagle field identification is not difficult once you have seen one; eagles soar on flat wings the size of ironing boards. Vultures, osprey and harriers all fix their broad wings in a dihedral. Eagles are the largest bird in the sky and when you see them perched along the river you will see a posture, an expression, that says, 'I own this spot.' ''</p>
        <p>Mr. Letts also observed the species, on Feb. 23, from Croton Bay, Hudson River mile 34: ''Holly Near sings wonderfully about 'sky dancing,' and Aldo Leopold described the mating flight of the woodcock using that phrase. If these wintering bald eagles aren't sky dancing, I would not know what to call it. At midday, nine eagles were in view all at once, all but one of them immatures. Four of the young birds were very active in the high wind performing aerial maneuvers that would have been the envy of a stunt pilot. They were practicing their fishing, or perhaps were guilty of playing with their food. Over and over, one would scoop up a sizable fish, climb and fly with it for a short distance and then drop it. Then it was another's turn to do the same.''</p>
        <p>The sighting of bald eagles -- ''the centerpiece of the winter season,'' Mr. Lake said -- is particularly significant because it indicates the returning ecological health of the river and its environs. Mr. Lake is also drawn to phenomena that reflect the seasonal cycles of life in and around the Hudson.</p>
        <p>Included in the journal are descriptions of late summer blue crabs, early autumn migrating monarch butterflies, and spring shad.</p>
        <p>Nor are all natural occurrences benign. Mr. Lake's 27-year-old son, Christopher, assistant editor of the almanac, writes that on June 21, 1998, near New Hamburg, N.Y., Hudson River mile 66.5, ''a huge black, anvil-shaped cloud edged across the Hudson toward us, absorbing daylight like a black hole.'' Minutes later, a tornado was spotted near Hopewell Junction.</p>
        <p>All manifestations, however, are significant, Mr. Lake believes. From the most dramatic to the most subtle, each can elicit proprietary feelings in the human observer. ''If people are able to establish a relationship with the world around them, they are more likely to assume stewardship and keep a concerned eye on it.''</p>
        <p>ENVIRONMENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
