<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush's Stance on Education Prevails in Battle on Plank</title>
    <meta content="30PLAT$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218930"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE REPUBLICANS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Education Department (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Toner, Robin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7DB123DF933A05754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1016" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush's Stance on Education Prevails in Battle on Plank</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBIN TONER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Toner, Robin</byline>
      <dateline>PHILADELPHIA, July 29</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Republicans complete work on platform that embraces much of presidential candidate George W Bush's educational agenda, over objections of some conservatives; photo; document drops call for abolishing Education Department; conservatives do prevail on array of social issues, from gays in the military to contraceptive counseling in school-based clinics and opposition to choice on abortion (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Republicans finished work today on a platform that embraces much of Gov. George W. Bush's educational agenda, over the objections of some conservatives who warned that the party was breaking with the get-the-government-off-our-backs philosophy of the Reagan revolution.</p>
        <p>But conservatives held sway on an array of social issues, from gays in the military to contraceptive counseling in school-based clinics.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Republicans finished work today on a platform that embraces much of Gov. George W. Bush's educational agenda, over the objections of some conservatives who warned that the party was breaking with the get-the-government-off-our-backs philosophy of the Reagan revolution.</p>
        <p>But conservatives held sway on an array of social issues, from gays in the military to contraceptive counseling in school-based clinics.</p>
        <p>The 107-member platform committee voted against a call to abolish the Department of Education, and in favor of Mr. Bush's education principles, which conservatives had resisted in early subcommittee action. Bush allies termed both votes a major victory, emblematic of their candidate's efforts to create a new Republican Party with more appeal to the voters in the center. The platform will be considered by the full convention on Monday.</p>
        <p>Gov. Tommy G. Thompson of Wisconsin, chairman of the committee, declared the document ''very visionary, very exciting,'' and a platform that Mr. Bush and other Republican candidates can run on comfortably.</p>
        <p>While the platform reflects a shift on issues like education, there was no shift on abortion, gay rights or many other issues important to social conservatives. Elmer Rumminger, a staunch conservative from South Carolina, said after the platform was completed this afternoon that he was pleased with the results. ''I don't think the conservative vision has changed,'' he said. ''I think the conservative rhetoric has changed to make it more conciliatory.''</p>
        <p>Still, the tension between Mr. Bush's reach for the center on education, and the ideological pull of his party's base was apparent throughout debate during the morning. ''When you say the abolishment of the Department of Education,'' said Senator Bill Frist of Tennessee, a Bush ally, what many people hear is ''that we don't care about education -- and if there's one thing Republicans care about, it's kids.''</p>
        <p>Cheryl Williams of Oklahoma, who pushed for the abolition, argued, ''We need to remain true to what President Reagan began with our revolution in the 80's; that the government is too large, too costly, and control needs to be returned to the states.'' Representative Sue Myrick of North Carolina countered, ''We deal every day with people who are scared to death that Republicans want to do away with education.''</p>
        <p>But Gayle Ruzicka of Utah noted that the Republican platform has opposed the Department of Education for many years, and demanded, ''Why are we suddenly backing away from this?'' One delegate after another railed about the intrusiveness of the federal government, and demanded a return to local control of schools. In the end, conservatives had to settle for a platform that called for the federal education role to be ''progressively limited.''</p>
        <p>After the votes, a Bush spokesman, Ari Fleischer, declared it a ''marked departure from the '96 platform,'' adding, ''We did make it clear to delegates that this was a crucial issue to Governor Bush.''</p>
        <p>With only brief debate, the platform committee reasserted that ''homosexuality is incompatible with military service,'' overwhelmingly rejecting efforts to remove that plank. Mr. Fleischer noted that this was not Mr. Bush's position, adding, ''The governor believes 'don't ask, don't tell' is the appropriate policy and he supports that.''</p>
        <p>The committee also rejected an attempt to defend contraceptive counseling in school-based clinics. Philip Hellreich of Hawaii, the committee member who offered the amendment, argued that as a doctor, he saw too many young teenagers with unwanted pregnancies. ''Without the appropriate use of contraceptives,'' he argued, ''we will have many, many more unwanted pregnancies.'' Opponents, who asserted that abstinence was the appropriate course for teenagers, easily prevailed.</p>
        <p>While the party's platform does not call for the abolition of any federal agencies -- four years ago, it called for several -- it still reflects a party deeply suspicious of the federal government and the courts.</p>
        <p>The power of conservatives was perhaps most clear on the issue of abortion. Long before the committee met, Mr. Bush and Republican leaders had announced that they wanted the abortion plank, which calls for a ban on abortion, left alone. Abortion rights supporters tried on several occasions to remove the plank or add a provision recognizing and expressing respect for Republicans who hold different views on the issue, but they were decisively beaten each time. They were struggling tonight to build support for a minority report on abortion, or to get a majority of six state delegations, the first step to bringing the issue to the floor.</p>
        <p>The committee's final action was the approval of a preamble that sounds the themes for the Bush campaign -- ''bold reforms in education,'' ''saving and strengthening Social Security,'' ''tax reforms that will sustain our nation's prosperity and reflect its decency.'' It also talks about a vision of ''a welcoming society,'' and then tries to strike the balance between reaching out and reaffirming core principles.</p>
        <p>''The diversity of our nation is reflected in this platform. We ask for the support and participation of all who substantially share our agenda. In one way or another, every Republican is a dissenter.''</p>
        <p>Gary Bauer, a leading conservative, said in an interview that he was pleased with the platform. ''On the sanctity of life, it's solid and consistent with the past,'' he said. ''I think it's a strong conservative platform.''</p>
        <p>Phyllis Schlafly, another veteran conservative advocate, said, ''I think it's wordier and not as good as '96. Of course, we kept the pro-life plank, but I thought the '96 platform was better.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE REPUBLICANS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
