<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Man Behind the Butter Pat Now Lets You Hold the Mayo, One-Handed</title>
    <meta content="30SQUI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218833"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Containers and Packaging</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mitsubishi Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Redmond, Sanford, Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hesser, Amanda</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Redmond, Sanford</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Containers and Packaging</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E0DC143DF933A05754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1306" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Man Behind the Butter Pat Now Lets You Hold the Mayo, One-Handed</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AMANDA HESSER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hesser, Amanda</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sanford Redmond, who in 1959 designed the machine that automated the production and packaging of butter pats, is negotiating with Mitsubishi International for joint venture in US to license new line of condiment packaging, dubbed dispenSRpak II; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SANFORD REDMOND was peering in at his latest invention, a machine that cranks out small plastic containers, more than a thousand every minute. It was clapping, stamping and swooshing with a roar that could make a dog hide under a bed. But Mr. Redmond stood still, looking on with the placid expression of a man admiring his grandchildren.</p>
        <p>Mr. Redmond, now 75, is best known for designing the machine that automated the production and packaging of butter pats -- those thin squares of butter sandwiched between two pieces of paper that can be found in diners and cafeterias.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SANFORD REDMOND was peering in at his latest invention, a machine that cranks out small plastic containers, more than a thousand every minute. It was clapping, stamping and swooshing with a roar that could make a dog hide under a bed. But Mr. Redmond stood still, looking on with the placid expression of a man admiring his grandchildren.</p>
        <p>Mr. Redmond, now 75, is best known for designing the machine that automated the production and packaging of butter pats -- those thin squares of butter sandwiched between two pieces of paper that can be found in diners and cafeterias.</p>
        <p>That was 1959.</p>
        <p>Now, instead of ending his career as a one-hit wonder and resting on his royalties, Mr. Redmond is back in the game with a whole new line of condiment packaging. He is negotiating with Mitsubishi International for a joint venture in the United States to license patents for the packaging worldwide. If the deal goes through, the packaging, inexpensive and extremely light in weight, could take hold at a time when pressure is growing on American manufacturers to reduce waste. Just this month, he received an American patent for some of the packages.</p>
        <p>A few years ago, Mitsubishi bought patent rights to another package, called the dispenSRpak, designed by Mr. Redmond. The plastic pack looks like two plastic cream dispensers joined on one edge. To open the pack, you fold at the seam until it snaps, then squeeze out the contents. It can all be done with one hand without any squirting or mess. Mr. Redmond won the DuPont packaging award, a leading prize in the industry, for the design in 1986 and a place in the permanent collection of the Museum of Modern Art. Mitsubishi, which fills the packs with ketchup, mayonnaise, soy sauce and soft chocolate, now produces 250 million of them for Japan each year. Other companies produce them throughout Asia and in Australia and Mexico.</p>
        <p>Mr. Redmond's latest inventions are a new generation of this package, called the dispenSRpak II, as well as a number of other packages -- some for condiments, some for medicines.</p>
        <p>The creation of one successful machine would be a great accomplishment for any inventor. But with Mr. Redmond, a small man who at an interview wore a brown herringbone vest buttoned at every hole and a white dress shirt rolled up at the sleeves, you get the feeling that he would have invented many more had he not been held back.</p>
        <p>Mr. Redmond invented his first machine, a high-speed wrapping machine for frozen foods, when he was still in his teens. While in the Army during World War II, he worked on a team designing a high-speed camera for use in the nuclear development project at Los Alamos, N.M. After the war, he moved back to New York City to work for his father, who owned Dexter Bishop Inc., a wholesale restaurant food supply business. The company packaged butter pats for restaurants and institutions.</p>
        <p>AT the time, butter pats were arranged in rows on large pieces of greaseproof paper, then folded and sold by the pound. Restaurants would then unfold the paper and transfer the pats one by one onto paper cards.</p>
        <p>In 1959, Mr. Redmond reconfigured the machine to put the pats on small squares of paperboard, cover them with greaseproof paper and stack them so that they could be sold in packs. His machine, which saved time and money for restaurants, airlines, hotels and other customers, was an instant hit.</p>
        <p>But trouble began just as Mr. Redmond started work on designing a machine that would load the stacks onto trays. Mr. Redmond's father sued him, contending waste of money and mismanagement. The case dragged on for 11 years, ending in a settlement. In the meantime, his royalties from his butter pat machine patent grew to $80 million.</p>
        <p>After his father died in 1982, Mr. Redmond created the dispenSRpak, but operating the family business would often distract him from pursuing other inventions. He gradually downsized the business from 50 to 6. ''I want to get out of running a business,'' he said. ''I'm lousy at it.''</p>
        <p>His company, Sanford Redmond Inc., created after his settlement, has remained in a rundown building in the Mott Haven neighborhood in the South Bronx. Its large machine shop, with just two workers, feels like a graveyard. The fields of offices are empty. Mr. Redmond and his relentless flurry of ideas are its pulse, however faint.</p>
        <p>His new packaging designs are promising: they are much less expensive to produce than current designs and use much less plastic.  ''The way to help the environment is not to recycle,'' he said. ''It is to use less plastic.''</p>
        <p>That is also the general philosophy of environmental groups. ''In a case like food packaging, especially condiment packaging,'' said Richard Denison, a senior scientist at Environmental Defense, an advocacy group in Washington, ''using the least amount of materials is really the optimal approach.'' Chances for recycling are minimal for most condiment packages, each of which is used just once, usually outside the home.</p>
        <p>Mr. Redmond's designs are also timely, as a European trend toward reducing packaging waste is picking up speed in the United States.</p>
        <p>HIS dispenSRpak II, for instance, uses much less plastic than his original and costs less than one-third as much to produce. Then there are the cream dispensers. Current varieties have aluminum-coated paper tops; Mr. Redmond was unhappy with the way the liquid squirts upon opening them and then spills over when set down. To use his version, you just snap the corner of the lid, then squeeze the desired amount through a valve. When you stop, it doesn't drip. Even if you shake it, no liquid spills out. A similar design, with a slightly larger valve, can be used for jellies, jams, even liquid laundry detergent.</p>
        <p>He has also come up with a new  ketchup packet that has a snap in the corner instead of a tear line. If you don't use all the ketchup, you can reseal the snap.</p>
        <p>''His packages are very innovative and very interesting,'' not only for the design, but for the cost saving potential, said Koji Goto, the manager of the paper and packaging department of Mitsubishi.</p>
        <p>For now, the likelihood of a lone inventor joining forces with this corporate giant is uncertain. If Mr. Redmond fails, he plans to build the machines himself and try to sell them. Or -- he winced at the thought  -- retire to his home in Connecticut and collect royalties on the butter pat machine, which he says amount to roughly $2 million a year.</p>
        <p>Sitting behind his desk, leaning back in his tattered orange leather chair with his arms crossed above his head, it was easy to see that this is not what he wants. His grandfather was an inventor, too. It is in Mr. Redmond's blood. He loves machines -- large, complex machines -- and would not settle for tinkering with gadgets at home. He is much more concerned about creating machines than in what they produce. He doesn't even eat butter.</p>
        <p>BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
