<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>He Missed a Season, But Not One Beat</title>
    <meta content="30ONPR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218937"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Jets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Orleans Saints</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Testaverde, Vinny</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Freeman, Mike</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New Orleans Saints</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E0DB123DF933A05754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="893" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>He Missed a Season, But Not One Beat</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Mike Freeman</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Freeman, Mike</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>On Pro Football comment on Vinny Testaverde's return to Jets for exhibition game against New Orleans (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Vinny Testaverde's first completion happened hours before last night's exhibition against New Orleans, the first game for Testaverde since his Achilles' tendon exploded in the season opener last September. He walked into Giants Stadium with his pal Wayne Chrebet. That's what a smart quarterback does -- stay close to your best wide receiver.</p>
        <p>Testaverde stuck to that philosophy once the game began. On the first play of the Jets' third possession, Chrebet faked out both safeties with a cut move inside, then darted the opposite way. Not bad for a guy who supposedly has no speed. Testaverde lobbed a perfect bomb, complete with tight spiral. Chrebet caught the pass near midfield and cruised into the end zone for a 75-yard touchdown. The only thing missing from that scene was a Hollywood slow-motion shot and the score from ''Chariots of Fire.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Vinny Testaverde's first completion happened hours before last night's exhibition against New Orleans, the first game for Testaverde since his Achilles' tendon exploded in the season opener last September. He walked into Giants Stadium with his pal Wayne Chrebet. That's what a smart quarterback does -- stay close to your best wide receiver.</p>
        <p>Testaverde stuck to that philosophy once the game began. On the first play of the Jets' third possession, Chrebet faked out both safeties with a cut move inside, then darted the opposite way. Not bad for a guy who supposedly has no speed. Testaverde lobbed a perfect bomb, complete with tight spiral. Chrebet caught the pass near midfield and cruised into the end zone for a 75-yard touchdown. The only thing missing from that scene was a Hollywood slow-motion shot and the score from ''Chariots of Fire.''</p>
        <p>Or Keyshawn Johnson breaking down the play with one of those Telestrator gizmos. But we digress.</p>
        <p>The touchdown was especially important because on the previous series, Testaverde, while trying to lob a screen pass to fullback Richie Anderson, underthrew the ball by a few inches. Safety Sammy Knight made an outstanding athletic play by picking off the pass and running 65 yards for the touchdown. Testaverde was in pursuit of Knight the entire time, and you can bet Coach Al Groh was screaming inside for Testaverde to cease his Michael Johnson imitation.</p>
        <p>Two important things about that play: During it, Testaverde was not shy about testing his Achilles' tendon by sprinting down the field chasing after Knight. That no body parts fell off can only be encouraging. And on the very next series, Testaverde rebounded well from that embarrassing interception with the Chrebet touchdown. ''It showed we could come back with a big play,'' Testaverde said.</p>
        <p>All eyes were on Testaverde for this game, and he did not disappoint. In many ways he looked like a quarterback who had missed no time. In fact, the entire Jets offense clicked. Chrebet was sharp, running back Curtis Martin ran through obscenely large holes and the play calling of Dan Henning was smart.</p>
        <p>Testaverde had a solid night. He completed 5 of 9 passes for 130 yards and a touchdown.</p>
        <p>No one should be surprised if Testaverde looks as if he has barely missed a beat when the Jets open against Green Bay on Sept. 3. A quarterback, of course, needs to be in sync with his team, and that is what Testaverde fears losing the most. When the season begins, will his passes sail north when his receivers skate south?</p>
        <p>But Testaverde is a veteran. Those synapses inside his head will again begin firing quickly, and he will recapture that delicate flow. It's already happening.</p>
        <p>The retired Miami quarterback Dan Marino had an injury similar to Testaverde's, and after it, was never quite the same. The difference is that Marino had more knee surgeries than zeroes on his fat paychecks. His legs were gone. Testaverde showed last night that his legs were still strong. His dropbacks were crisp, his mechanics smooth, his arm still a cannon.</p>
        <p>''Things are coming,'' Testaverde said. ''I feel much more comfortable now standing here than before the first snap. But I'm happy with how things went.''</p>
        <p>His Achilles' tendon should not be a concern. I officially give him a clean bill of health. Yet his future with the Jets, and the team's future at the position, well, that is a different story.</p>
        <p>This off-season, Testaverde told a former Jets teammate that he wanted to finish his career near his Florida home, preferably with the Tampa Bay Buccaneers, either after this season or the next.</p>
        <p>But Testaverde's contract with the Jets runs through the 2005 season. Chances are that Testaverde, who turns 37 this year, will not complete his contract anyway. So whether he leaves New York or retires from football altogether, he will be gone in a few years, maybe less. That is where things will get quite cloudy for the franchise.</p>
        <p>The Jets made a smart move in drafting a quarterback to replace Testaverde, and Chad Pennington, one of their four first-round picks, was judged by most league scouts to be the best available in this year's draft. He had better be. Because once Testaverde leaves, the team will be Pennington's. General Manager Bill Parcells and Groh apparently think -- mistakenly -- that the backup Ray Lucas is only that, a backup. Lucas will most likely leave the Jets after this season.</p>
        <p>It is difficult to tell if Pennington is a franchise player based on a few throws in a preseason game against the Saints.</p>
        <p>One concern has to be Parcells' record as a talent evaluator. When he was with the New England Patriots, Parcells at first favored picking Rick Mirer over Drew Bledsoe. Thank goodness he was talked out of that potential disaster.</p>
        <p>There is the distinct possibility that after this season, Testaverde and Lucas could be gone. That would leave the most critical position on the field in a major state of flux.</p>
        <p>For now, all Testaverde and his teammates care about is the present. The Jets still don't have a pass rush, they had four turnovers against the Saints, and the schedule is brutal. But their biggest concern coming into this game, Testaverde's health, is a concern no more.</p>
        <p>Vinny's back.  ON PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
