<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSH, IN ADDRESS, WILL MAKE APPEAL BEYOND THE G.O.P.</title>
    <meta content="30CONV$11" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218932"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE CONVENTION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions, National (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Kentucky</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berke, Richard L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Kentucky</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Kentucky</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Kentucky</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E6DB123DF933A05754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2069" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSH, IN ADDRESS, WILL MAKE APPEAL BEYOND THE G.O.P.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD L. BERKE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Berke, Richard L</byline>
      <dateline>PHILADELPHIA, July 29</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gov George W Bush says he will try to appeal directly to Democrats and independents in his speech to Republican National Convention, interview; says message that he is inclusive will be low key but unmistakable; cites his insistence on harmonious convention; defends decision to keep some hard-edged conservatives off stage; photo of Bush campaigning in Kentucky (M)/</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. George W. Bush said today that in his speech to the Republican National Convention he would go out of his way to break through party lines and appeal directly to Democrats and independents.</p>
        <p>In an interview, Mr. Bush said he was determined for the country to see that he is inclusive. Mindful, perhaps, that this pitch beyond his party could be unsettling to conservatives, Mr. Bush said his remarks would be low key -- but unmistakable.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gov. George W. Bush said today that in his speech to the Republican National Convention he would go out of his way to break through party lines and appeal directly to Democrats and independents.</p>
        <p>In an interview, Mr. Bush said he was determined for the country to see that he is inclusive. Mindful, perhaps, that this pitch beyond his party could be unsettling to conservatives, Mr. Bush said his remarks would be low key -- but unmistakable.</p>
        <p>''There's not a sentence in the speech that looks in the camera and says, 'I want you!' '' said Mr. Bush, speaking from Joplin, Mo., before crisscrossing Kentucky as he made his way through states that voted for President Clinton four years ago. [Page 23.] ''But the speech itself should do that. The speech, if it's done right, and I think it will be, will send a broadened message.''</p>
        <p>To do that, he said, he will tell the nation about the late Bob Bullock, a Democrat who was his lieutenant governor in Texas and with whom he had forged such a close working relationship that Mr. Bullock endorsed him when he ran for re-election. He also said he had no intention of assailing Hillary Rodham Clinton, a favorite target at Republican gatherings, saying that the convention was not the proper forum for attacks.</p>
        <p>As Republicans in red, white and blue boaters and embroidered ''Bush for President'' shirts jammed into this city today for the convention's opening on Monday, Mr. Bush said he realized that the usual suspense may be gone because he has already announced his running mate, Dick Cheney.</p>
        <p>He also said the American people should not expect political fisticuffs because he has followed an ''iron-fist rule'' to make sure there is a harmonious show. As part of that effort, Mr. Bush defended his decision to keep some hard-edged conservatives off stage, saying there were ''no slights intended.'' He was determined, he explained, to avert a repetition of the scene at the Houston convention in 1992, which is remembered not for his father's re-election drive but for scathing speeches.</p>
        <p>''A lot of people said the '92 convention set a negative tone, and that it set a divisive message for the country,'' Mr. Bush said. ''I didn't see it that way at the time. People felt it was part of a dismal political year. This is a different time, a different approach, in the sense that we are trying to limit the amount of time that elected officials are speaking relative to the amount of time that we spell out policy.'' He added: ''This is not a divisive moment. This is a uniting moment.''</p>
        <p>Yet Mr. Bush acknowledged that all the happy talk could limit the drama, as well as the public's interest in the convention. Asked whether he was worried about the possible lack of excitement, he laughed and said: ''That's a pretty legitimate question. I hope, I think, if there is any suspense it will be in the roll-out of ideas. Hopefully, people will be interested in what I have to say. I hope we can get enough people to pay attention to it.''</p>
        <p>Other Republican presidential candidates have sought to reach beyond their own party; to capture the White House, of course, no candidate can rely solely on his or her own party. Bob Dole four years ago declared in his acceptance speech, ''The Republican Party is broad and inclusive.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Bush made clear that he intended to go further than Republicans have in the past, especially in appealing to Democrats. To drive that message home, Mr. Bush will be introduced at the convention by Mr. Bullock's widow, Jan. And all week long, the stage will showcase women and people from minority groups, faces that are not usually highlighted at Republican conventions.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's effort is reminiscent of what Bill Clinton did in his acceptance speech in 1992. ''The choice we offer is not conservative or liberal,'' Mr. Clinton said then. ''In many ways it's not even Republican or Democratic. It is different. It is new. And it will work.''</p>
        <p>In the interview today, Mr. Bush said he would emphasize how he had worked with Democrats. ''One of the things that people don't really know about me is that I've been good about bringing people together to get things accomplished in Texas,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush would not speak directly about how crucial it was in his address on Thursday night, which he said he was ''still massaging,'' to allay concerns that he might not be ready to be president.</p>
        <p>''It's hard for me to answer because I literally don't pay attention to a lot of these polls and focus groups,'' he said. ''But to the extent that people wonder whether I can speak before a national audience and speak from my heart -- hopefully the speech will answer that.''</p>
        <p>The Texas governor said his campaign's ability to restrict who can speak and who cannot and to limit dissension was ''an indication of the Republican Party's desire to win.''</p>
        <p>Taking issue with conservatives and many members of Congress who were not invited to speak, he said: ''Not everybody's going to be given a speaking role because of the limitation in time. There's room for many voices in our party.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush scoffed at criticism from some moderates that his choice of Mr. Cheney underscores that he is more concerned with burnishing his credentials on the right. ''To the extent that there's people out there carping,'' he said, ''that's just normal.''</p>
        <p>He also said he was not worried that in picking a running mate with far more government service he would draw attention to his own lack of national experience. ''I'm a secure enough fellow to understand that picking a very strong candidate like Dick Cheney is the right thing to do,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Refusing to say how serious he had been about turning to a running mate who backed abortion rights, like Gov. Tom Ridge of Pennsylvania or Gov. George E. Pataki of New York, Mr. Bush would only say, ''I considered a lot of people.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush said he was not worried about advisers who have warned that the campaign is squandering a prime opportunity by not sharply repudiating Democrats on stage. ''I will needle my opponent, but we don't have a let's-tear-down night or a slash-and-burn night, or a night that subjects the other side to public ridicule,'' he said. ''And I'm not going to talk about Mrs. Clinton. She is running for the United States Senate and has her hands full in the great state of New York.''</p>
        <p>Still, even as he himself intends to stay above the partisan fray, Mr. Bush acknowledged that not every speaker will give the Democrats a pass. ''I'm sure people are going to get up there and say some things about the pitfalls of our opponent's record.'' Aware, no doubt, that President Clinton remains popular among many voters, he said, ''By the way, the opponent is not President Clinton. The opponent is Vice President Gore.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush sounded defiant about the criticisms that he has relied on his father, the former president, for guidance in picking Mr. Cheney and in making other decisions. Governor Bush is clearly taking the offensive on that count, and said that in his acceptance speech he planned ''to say how much I love my family -- how much I respect my father.''</p>
        <p>The Texas governor has the luxury of being upbeat in his address on Thursday because many Republicans said they could not recall such a united party since President Ronald Reagan's re-election campaign in 1984.</p>
        <p>''I've never seen since '84 this degree of unity and enthusiasm through the ranks left and right of our party,'' said Senator Mitch McConnell of Kentucky. ''We're hungry for victory like the Democrats were in 1992.''</p>
        <p>John Hancock, executive director of the Missouri Republican Party, said the tone of this convention was strikingly different from ones of the past. ''The goal for the past ones was to come out unified,'' he said. ''And now we already have that.''</p>
        <p>The Bush campaign and the convention planners took great care to make sure that when viewers tune in they will see only harmony on stage, and a message of moderation and inclusion. People familiar with the discussions said that while there was no choice but to let Senator John McCain speak on Tuesday evening, given that he emerged from his losing primary fight with quite a following, the Bush campaign did not want its message delivered by more conservative, and perhaps, outspoken party members who opposed him, like Alan Keyes and Steve Forbes.</p>
        <p>Mr. Forbes, in an interview, insisted that he was not offended. ''In terms of speaking, realistically, how many people are going to listen unless you're William Jennings Bryan?'' He said Mr. Bush's acceptance speech ''towers over everything else'' and any other speech delivered this week. Moreover, Mr. Forbes said he was reassured by Mr. Bush's decision to pick a conservative as his running mate. ''His choosing Cheney speaks volumes,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Many Republicans said by far the most attention will be on Mr. Bush's address. It will be the first time for millions of Americans to get a close look at Mr. Bush -- and for him to appeal beyond the party faithful.</p>
        <p>Michael K. Deaver, who was President Reagan's image consultant, said Mr. Bush has much the same challenge that his boss had in 1980 at the convention in Detroit, when he used his speech to reassure the public that he had the breadth and command to be president.</p>
        <p>''Reagan was a likable guy, people genuinely had a positive impression of him through Hollywood and through his governor's days,'' Mr. Deaver said. ''But they really weren't sure this guy had any depth or any original thoughts. That impression began to change with the speech he gave. Bush is in a similar position.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush and his advisers have sought to play down how much of a political lift they will draw from the convention. They note that polls show that Republican voters are already much more enthusiastic about their candidate than Democrats are about Al Gore -- so they have less room to gain.</p>
        <p>In an interview, Karl Rove, Mr. Bush's chief strategist, said of Mr. Gore: ''I think he'll get a bigger bounce out of the convention than we will. There's very little more we can gain by consolidating our base. Our view is that he's going to essentially get twice the bounce out of the convention than we're going to. We're going to find ourselves in a very tight race after Labor Day.''</p>
        <p>Asked how much Mr. Bush might gain in the opinion polls after the convention, he said, ''You can pick up four or five points.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Rove said he did not see any particular issue defining the contest. ''We're in an environment where several issues matter,'' he said. ''Reducing Social Security, national defense -- we're not in an election where the race is dominated by one overriding issue.''</p>
        <p>He said he was not worried about Patrick J. Buchanan, the conservative who is expected to run as the Reform Party nominee, siphoning votes from Mr. Bush. ''He's something always to watch but he is diminished,'' Mr. Rove said. ''He's not grown in stature or grown in impact as the years have gone on. Why? Because he's Pat Buchanan.''</p>
        <p>The Bush campaign and his supporters do not seem worried that Mr. McCain will try to upstage the nominee when he speaks here.</p>
        <p>''If he looks like he's a spoiler in some fashion against George Bush,'' said Pat Robertson, the founder of the Christian Coalition and a foe of Mr. McCain, ''it will destroy him.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush is clearly delighting in this opportunity for him to be glorified all week. Asked what will be the convention's best moment, he referred to his speech, saying, ''It's when, from my selfish perspective, it's walking out on that stage.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE CONVENTION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
