<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pentagon Assailed for a Philadelphia Display</title>
    <meta content="Y30PEN$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218887"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions, National (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Philadelphia (Pa)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Defense Department</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Skelton, Ike (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Myers, Steven Lee</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cohen, William S (Sec)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Abercrombie, Neil (Repr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Pennsylvania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Pennsylvania/Philadelphia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DEED9153DF933A05754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="562" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pentagon Assailed for a Philadelphia Display</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN LEE MYERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Myers, Steven Lee</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 29</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Rep Ike Skelton scores Pentagon's decision to send array of military hardware to three-day exhibition, Philadelphia, timed to Republican National Convention, letter to Defense Sec William S Cohen; Rep Neil Abercrombie echoes criticism, interview; Cohen defends decision (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Republicans in Congress have long chided their Democratic colleagues for ignoring shortfalls in the defense budgets, but the Pentagon's decision to send a display of some of the military's latest hardware to the Republican National Convention gave the Democrats a golden opportunity to turn the tables.</p>
        <p>Two Democratic congressmen sharply criticized the Pentagon's decision to send an array of weapons and other equipment to the former Philadelphia Naval Shipyard for a three-day exhibition that begins today, saying the money would be better spent on repairs or benefits for service members and their families.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Republicans in Congress have long chided their Democratic colleagues for ignoring shortfalls in the defense budgets, but the Pentagon's decision to send a display of some of the military's latest hardware to the Republican National Convention gave the Democrats a golden opportunity to turn the tables.</p>
        <p>Two Democratic congressmen sharply criticized the Pentagon's decision to send an array of weapons and other equipment to the former Philadelphia Naval Shipyard for a three-day exhibition that begins today, saying the money would be better spent on repairs or benefits for service members and their families.</p>
        <p>Despite the Pentagon's policy barring the military from involvement in partisan political activities, Secretary of Defense William S. Cohen approved a request to ship the weapons -- at taxpayers' expense -- to the shipyard, where about 100 Republican members of Congress are staying during the convention.</p>
        <p>Pentagon officials said they could not yet estimate the cost of moving all the equipment to Philadelphia, though the Air Force estimated that its share would be at least $100,000.</p>
        <p>In a pointed letter to Mr. Cohen on Friday evening, Representative Ike Skelton of Missouri, the ranking Democrat on the House Armed Services Committee, dismissed the Pentagon's arguments that the display did not represent a partisan event.</p>
        <p>''While I recognize that the department has attempted to make sure that its activities in Philadelphia will not be interpreted as associating the department with any partisan political causes, issues or activities, this will be, frankly, a difficult distinction for many people to make,'' Mr. Skelton wrote. ''There is no event in American politics more partisan than a national political convention.''</p>
        <p>The criticism, echoed by Representative Neil Abercrombie of Hawaii in an interview, came too late to have any effect on the display, which will remain at the shipyard until Monday as a centerpiece of a series of events there, including a fund-raiser by Representative Curt Weldon, a Republican who represents suburban Philadelphia and who requested the hardware show.</p>
        <p>But the Democrats criticized the decision to send the materiel, and more than 150 service members, and attacked their Republican colleagues for ignoring more pressing needs. Their criticisms were echoed by some service officials, including one senior officer who referred to the display as ''the Philadelphia fiasco.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Cohen defended his decision to sidestep the Pentagon's strict policy against military involvement in political activities, saying that the display was not, literally, at the convention. He also said two Philadelphia Democrats, Representative Robert A. Brady and Mayor John F. Street, supported Mr. Weldon's request.</p>
        <p>''We're very proud of the men and women who are serving us and the equipment that they use, and we're not hesitant about showing it to general members of the public, as well as people who are attending the convention,'' Mr. Cohen said on Friday. The display at the shipyard is not scheduled to be open to the public.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cohen also extended an invitation to the Democrats to play host to a similar display at their convention in Los Angeles next month, but Mr. Skelton and Mr. Abercrombie dismissed that, saying they would not support such a request. ''It's open to misinterpretation and gives the appearance of impropriety,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
