<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Baryshnikov Gets Innovatively Pedestrian</title>
    <meta content="30BARY" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218716"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">White Oak Dance Project</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Baryshnikov, Mikhail</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E6DB163DF933A05754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="879" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Baryshnikov Gets Innovatively Pedestrian</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LESLIE KANDELL</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ariticle on Mikhail Baryshnikov and his White Oak Dance Project, who are joining colleagues and members of Princeton community to present old and new dances that focus on walking at McCarter Theater; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MIKHAIL BARYSHNIKOV'S theory is that anyone who can walk can dance -- well, maybe with a broad enough view of dance and an hour or two of rehearsal. To prove the point, he is to join colleagues and assorted members of the Princeton community when he returns this week with old and new dances, made mostly from walking.</p>
        <p>The residency at the McCarter Theater and its four resulting performances are the first stop on a nationwide tour called ''Past Forward.'' It represents a reunion of the experimental choreographers of Judson Dance Theater, who worked and performed in a Greenwich Village church in the early 1960's. It also gathers dancers in Mr. Baryshnikov's 10-year-old White Oak Dance Project.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MIKHAIL BARYSHNIKOV'S theory is that anyone who can walk can dance -- well, maybe with a broad enough view of dance and an hour or two of rehearsal. To prove the point, he is to join colleagues and assorted members of the Princeton community when he returns this week with old and new dances, made mostly from walking.</p>
        <p>The residency at the McCarter Theater and its four resulting performances are the first stop on a nationwide tour called ''Past Forward.'' It represents a reunion of the experimental choreographers of Judson Dance Theater, who worked and performed in a Greenwich Village church in the early 1960's. It also gathers dancers in Mr. Baryshnikov's 10-year-old White Oak Dance Project.</p>
        <p>''It's an extraordinary investigation of pedestrian mentality,'' Mr. Baryshnikov said on the telephone from his Manhattan apartment. ''Even professional dancers get nervous. People in the audience will understand how to be onstage. How the stage affects being onstage is very revealing. To watch this person take choices -- the way a person stands or looks, their sense of comfort or fear is very obvious. They've never been onstage. The way they walk onto the stage becomes the way they walk, onstage.''</p>
        <p>Judson Dance focused on stylistic possibilities of walking, climbing, skipping and similar everyday movements. This week's seven choreographers are together again, with Mr. Baryshnikov introducing or appearing in their reconstructed short works or newest ones, or both. Hence the ''Past'' and the ''Forward.'' (The White Oak company's five present dancers are the core unit.)</p>
        <p>David Gordon's new ''For the Love of Rehearsal,'' for instance, contrasts with ''The Chair'' and ''The Matter,'' from the 1970's, while Yvonne Rainer's new collage, ''Mat; Chair/Pillow; Nabokov,'' introduced last month at the Brooklyn Academy of Music, is paired with ''Trio A Pressured No. 3,'' from 1966.</p>
        <p>McCarter Theater contacted members of community groups to join Simone Forti's ''Huddle'' and ''Scramble,'' and Steve Paxton's walking piece, ''Satisfyin' Lover.'' These dances have no music. Ms. Forti says hers last 10 minutes: ''Someone has a watch.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Baryshnikov, 52, defected from the Soviet Union 25 years ago.</p>
        <p>Starting in his new homeland as a principal dancer with American Ballet Theater, he became its director for almost 10 years, bringing teachers from Russia and putting his stamp on classical ballets. He also acted in films, including ''The Turning Point'' and ''White Nights.'' Diving into the world of American moderns, he narrowed the distance between modern and classical styles, in the process attracting the ballet public to modern dance. (Mr. Gordon, who directs this week's performances, is one of the choreographers he commissioned.)</p>
        <p>''I was drawn to new things,'' Mr. Baryshnikov said. ''I didn't want to be a slave to 19th-century traditional productions of Taglione, Bournonville and Petipa. I wanted to work with choreographers of the present. We knew turn-of-the-century choreographers, but we read magazines and saw photos of American dancers: Duncan, St. Denis, Limon, Paul Taylor, Merce Cunningham. Alvin Ailey came. I knew my love affair with classical ballet would sooner or later be over, and I wanted to continue.''</p>
        <p>In addition to joining some of the dances, Mr. Baryshnikov is to introduce them and put them in context, making connections, with the possible addition of musical video, or perhaps voiceovers. (They'll worry about exactly what closer to the moment.)</p>
        <p>''He is going to want to give the idea of what was happening in the world,'' Ms. Forti said. ''The dances were made at a time when these artists were interested in getting away from the idea that only highly skilled, technically trained people would be interested to see their work.''</p>
        <p>Both of Ms. Forti's works involve people in basic movements. Like ''Scramble,'' ''Huddle'' predates the Pilobolus company, which fascinates with athletic group intertwinings, but ''Huddle'' uses people to form a mass by climbing around each other. Ms. Forti instructs participants to wear comfortable clothes ''in black, white or gray because I felt you would get the effect of mass better if the color was unified. In 'Scramble' I ask them to wear colors. It spreads out more, like birds flocking.''</p>
        <p>Some people feel uneasy and decide to back out while rehearsing ''Huddle,'' because they don't feel like doing it, Ms. Forti said. ''It takes being ready to be clambered on. You have to try to get into the mass, take turns climbing over the mass, get to the other side, then sidle up into the mass. You climb on people, pull with your hands, step up on them.''</p>
        <p>The accessibility and revelation of these dances is of paramount interest to Mr. Baryshnikov at the moment. He said recently thathe was getting rid of what he finds no longer necessary -- namely mannerisms.</p>
        <p>''Extra theatricality,'' he said. ''You kind of selectively clean up your act. I'm more available for audience participation. I'm more transparent, more to the point.''</p>
        <p>The way walking is.</p>
        <p>PAST FORWARD  White Oak Dance Project.</p>
        <p>McCarter Theater, 91 University Place, Princeton.</p>
        <p>Thursday through Saturday at 8 p.m., next Sunday at 2 p.m.  (609) 258-2787.</p>
        <p>DANCE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
