<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Fixture in Need of Some Fixing</title>
    <meta content="30EPST$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218695"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="IN BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Uniforms</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Camps and Camping</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Epstein's (Department Store) (Tuckahoe, Ny)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wincele, Steven</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Epstein, Mark</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">West, Debra</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Camps and Camping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Uniforms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E7DE163DF933A05754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="806" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Fixture in Need of Some Fixing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DEBRA WEST</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">West, Debra</byline>
      <dateline>TUCKAHOE</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Epstein's, mom-and-pop department store founded by Max Epstein in 1933 in Tuckahoe, NY, faces hard times as competition from large discount stores increases; partners Mark Epstein and Steven Wincele, in effort to keep store viable, branch out into specialty items, open Web site and continue to offer customers personal service; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE mayor here, Philip A. White, was a 50-cents-a-week boy back in the Depression.</p>
        <p>Like just about every other family in this tiny village, Mr. White's family would buy his clothes at Epstein's, the department store on Columbus Avenue, and pay for them in small weekly installments. Max Epstein never pushed, never threatened, never demanded payment. Often he looked the other way and fitted families for a new season's worth of clothes knowing the old debt still lingered.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE mayor here, Philip A. White, was a 50-cents-a-week boy back in the Depression.</p>
        <p>Like just about every other family in this tiny village, Mr. White's family would buy his clothes at Epstein's, the department store on Columbus Avenue, and pay for them in small weekly installments. Max Epstein never pushed, never threatened, never demanded payment. Often he looked the other way and fitted families for a new season's worth of clothes knowing the old debt still lingered.</p>
        <p>''He was too nice,'' Mayor White, 71, recalled. ''If he got all the money that was owed to him, he could have been rich. But I'm sure he never got it all.''</p>
        <p>In hard times, Epstein's thrived. But the boom times have been tougher.</p>
        <p>Tuckahoe, first known for its marble quarries and later for its factories, is now, like much of Westchester, a shimmering landscape of wealth. It is no longer the kind of village where people stop by to trade the latest gossip, buy on credit or have tailoring performed -- just so -- by the man who tailored their grandparents' clothes. And Epstein's is feeling the change.</p>
        <p>''When we had more striations of a middle class, we had a healthier traffic flow,'' said Mark Epstein, 47, whose grandfather Max founded the store in 1933. ''The discounting was something that kept us in a certain stead for many years. Word of mouth said this was a good place to come for good prices. But now everybody discounts.''</p>
        <p>Epstein's, which has two floors and 14,000 square feet crammed with everything from shoes and underwear to jeans and school uniforms is finding the competition from discounters like Old Navy and Bob's tougher than ever. And that's not even counting the damage that the never-ending sales at department stores like Macy's and Lord &amp; Taylor have inflicted on mom and pop stores, or the way big-box stores like Costco are hacking through the retail industry like machetes in a rain forest.</p>
        <p>''For 65 years we went ahead every year,'' Mr. Epstein said. ''For the last two years it's been going the other way.''</p>
        <p>At its height in 1992, Epstein's sales totaled $5.75 million. Last year, sales dropped to $4 million, Mr. Epstein said.</p>
        <p>''Our ace in the hole is that we own the building,'' said Mr. Epstein, who brought in an old high school buddy, Steven Wincele, as a partner a few years ago. ''If we can stabilize the volume and cut the bleeding, we can stay in business. I've got to. I've got kids to send to college.''</p>
        <p>For now, the tourniquet Mr. Epstein and Mr. Wincele plan to use to keep their business healthy is good service.</p>
        <p>On a recent day the store had more employees than customers. But more than that the store is branching out into camp supplies and school uniforms. Epstein's now provides everything children need to take to summer camp and will sew name labels in all the children's clothes. So far, so good. Two years ago, they sold and labeled camp clothes for 150 children. This year they provided camp gear for 350 children. They hope to do the same for school uniforms.</p>
        <p>The store has started a Web site, but it is far from the flashy design of many retail pages (www.campsupply.com or www.Epsteinsonline.com). Instead, the Web site offers no-nonsense price lists of what Epstein's has for sale.</p>
        <p>Still, there are days when Mr. Epstein wishes he had followed his early inclinations and become a rabbi or a teacher.</p>
        <p>''The lure of the family business is tough to ignore,'' said Mr. Epstein, whose tortoise shell glasses and easy demeanor make him seem more counselor than boss to the store's 40 employees.</p>
        <p>Judy Badman, a clerk at the store for 20 years, said of the Epsteins: ''They are very nice people. They treat you like family. They care about their employees.''</p>
        <p>She is not the only one who thinks so.</p>
        <p>''I've worked for them for 50 years,'' said Phil DeSantis, the store's tailor. ''How many people can say that about a company?''</p>
        <p>Through the years there were many opportunities to expand the store, but Mr. Epstein's father, Milton, who died this month, and his mother, Phyllis, 80, who still works in the store three days a week, were content with improving what they had.</p>
        <p>''My father never wanted more,'' the younger Mr. Epstein said. ''He grew up here. He graduated from Tuckahoe High School. There was a certain status attached to the store. Everywhere he went people knew what Epstein's was.''</p>
        <p>And people still do.</p>
        <p>''Epstein's is Tuckahoe and Tukahoe is Epstein's,'' Mayor White said.</p>
        <p>IN BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
