<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Winner Is . . . Indexing</title>
    <meta content="30BACK$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218633"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEFDD1E3AF933A05754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="519" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Winner Is . . . Indexing</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>I was most disappointed to read of the premature demise of the contest you established in mid-1993, comparing the results of mutual fund portfolios managed by five respected investment advisers (''A Seven-Year Lesson in Investing: Expect the Unexpected, and More,'' Mutual Fund Quarterly, July 9).</p>
        <p>Each of the five advisers started the contest with a hypothetical investment of $50,000; the portfolios were originally intended to grow for 20 years. Over the seven years of the contest, their portfolios grew to $138,500, on average. (The range was $111,800 to $155,000.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>I was most disappointed to read of the premature demise of the contest you established in mid-1993, comparing the results of mutual fund portfolios managed by five respected investment advisers (''A Seven-Year Lesson in Investing: Expect the Unexpected, and More,'' Mutual Fund Quarterly, July 9).</p>
        <p>Each of the five advisers started the contest with a hypothetical investment of $50,000; the portfolios were originally intended to grow for 20 years. Over the seven years of the contest, their portfolios grew to $138,500, on average. (The range was $111,800 to $155,000.)</p>
        <p>The contest was intended to see if fund advisers could outpace the market, and you noted that the comparative standard, the Vanguard Index 500 fund, returned 277.51 percent over the period. But you did not list the final value of a $50,000 investment in it: $188,750 -- a total that not a single adviser even approached.</p>
        <p>Put another way, the advisers earned a seven-year profit for their retirement plan investors of $88,500, compared with $138,750 for the index fund. That $50,000 difference is enormous -- equal to the entire initial investment. But it understates the reality. For, given the magic of compounding, even if the fund advisers and the index fund were to earn an identical, say, 10 percent a year over the next 13 years, the final value in 2013 would be: average adviser, $478,000; index fund, $652,000.</p>
        <p>It would take a Herculean leap of faith to forecast that the advisers, having fallen so far behind the index fund in the past, would start playing par golf in the future, particularly when we examine the reasons they fell so far short. It comes down largely to a single factor: cost.</p>
        <p>The annual returns of the advisers and the index fund can be calculated  at 15.7 and 20.9 percent respectively, a gap of 5.2 percentage points. Of that difference, fully 3.2 percentage points are represented by the estimated costs incurred by the funds selected by the advisers (an expense ratio of 1.2 percent, a portfolio turnover cost of 1 percent and an opportunity cost from not being fully invested in stocks of 1 percent).</p>
        <p>So what is billed as a ''seven-year lesson in the unexpected'' proves to be a lesson in the expected: Costs are predictable, and they matter; swapping funds doesn't work very well; index funds are hard to beat.</p>
        <p>I urge you to let the race continue. That is the best way to drum home the real message: the challenges and frustrations that even experts face when managing fund portfolios to outpace an unmanaged index.</p>
        <p>JOHN C. BOGLE  Valley Forge, Pa., July 18</p>
        <p>The writer is the founder of the Vanguard Group and of the Vanguard 500 Index fund.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
