<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Giving, Once a Year for 35 Years</title>
    <meta content="30BLOO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000806T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218674"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MILESTONES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blood</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Peters, John (Det)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ames, Lynne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Blood</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Transplants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blood</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04EEDF1F3AF933A05754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1014" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Giving, Once a Year for 35 Years</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYNNE AMES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ames, Lynne</byline>
      <dateline>VALHALLA</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on annual blood drive at Westchester County police academy in Valhalla, NY, where Detective John Peters is donating his 35th pint; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT was Detective John Peters's 35-year anniversary donating blood, but he wasn't about to make a fuss over it.</p>
        <p>''It's no big deal,'' Detective Peters, 53, said. He is with the Westchester County police, and he was standing in line at a blood drive at the police academy here. ''I do it once a year. It's simply the right thing to do. There are so few ways you can really help people who've been in serious accidents, or who are undergoing major surgery. This is one way you can really do something.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT was Detective John Peters's 35-year anniversary donating blood, but he wasn't about to make a fuss over it.</p>
        <p>''It's no big deal,'' Detective Peters, 53, said. He is with the Westchester County police, and he was standing in line at a blood drive at the police academy here. ''I do it once a year. It's simply the right thing to do. There are so few ways you can really help people who've been in serious accidents, or who are undergoing major surgery. This is one way you can really do something.''</p>
        <p>Detective Peters added with a laugh that his motives were not always so pure.</p>
        <p>''I was in the Army in 1965, stationed first in Germany, then at Fort Dix, N.J.,'' he said. ''If you donated blood, you got to take the day off. The days were hard and long -- 14 hours -- and as I recall there was a line out the door to donate.''</p>
        <p>The pint Detective Peters was giving will help ease a serious blood shortage. July and August are traditionally slow months because potential donors are away, said Cindy Sadrakula, senior manager, Donor Services, Hudson Valley Blood Services, which is a division of the New York Blood Center.</p>
        <p>Hudson Valley Blood Services provides blood and blood products to 48 hospitals in Westchester, Putnam, Dutchess, Rockland, Orange, Ulster and Sullivan Counties and the Bronx. Last year, it collected 74,000 units, or pints; this year, it needs 84,000. To meet this figure it must collect 350 pints a day, a goal made harder by the fact that this summer supplies cannot be augmented with blood from other parts of the United States or Europe, because these areas are also experiencing shortages.</p>
        <p>''We have been operating hand to mouth all summer long, with only a one-  or two-day supply of some types of blood,'' Ms. Sadrakula said. ''This is far below the five-day supply typically required.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Kathleen Grima, medical director for Hudson Valley Blood Services, said transfusions are given to trauma patients, people who require certain types of surgery and others. Red cells, which carry oxygen through the system, and platelets, which promote clotting, are generally the most in demand.</p>
        <p>Summer is a difficult time not only because donors go on vacation but also because more people are on the road.</p>
        <p>''Your inventory gets whittled down,'' Dr. Grima said. Priority must be given ''to the kid who cracked his car up and is bleeding all over the E.R.'' Elective surgical procedures that require transfusions may have to be postponed.</p>
        <p>Hudson Valley Blood Services organizes drives in schools, churches and synagogues, businesses and fraternal organizations. It also has a center in Elmsford for people who want to donate. The number to call to organize a drive is (914) 784-4639.</p>
        <p>Some drives begin out of the need to help a specific person, and they become annual traditions. The one at the police academy, called the ''Community Heroes Drive,'' was started three years ago to get blood for a police officer. It now takes place every year.</p>
        <p>In the room at the academy, technicians set donors up on stretchers, talked and joked with them, drew blood and later offered juice and cookies to offset any weakness. Each donor filled out a health history form. (All blood is sent to laboratories to be tested for H.I.V. and various types of hepatitis virus; donors do not get results for four to six weeks.)</p>
        <p>Detective Peters said the procedure feels completely routine for him now. ''The first time, all those years ago, I was apprehensive, but the Army did it real quick.'' The technicians at Hudson Valley Blood Services have considerably more bedside manner: Delepse (Pinky) Morales, a technician, bids farewell to each donor by laughing and saying, ''Thank you for bleeding with us.''</p>
        <p>The detective also said that ''putting a face to it'' -- knowing there is a specific person whose life may depend on your donation -- heightens the emotional impact.</p>
        <p>This year that person may be Bryan Woodruff, a 37-year-old county police officer who has a potentially fatal liver disease, primary sclerosing chollangitis. Officer Woodruff, who came to say hello to his fellow officers, is waiting for a liver transplant, surgery that requires lots of blood. ''He's a very nice, very well-liked person, and we are all very motivated to try to help him,'' Detective Peters said.</p>
        <p>Other officers were there making donations as well. Detective Dolph Tutoni, for instance, said this was his 10th in as many years. For 20-year-old Adam Cococcia, a rookie park ranger, the day was also significant -- it was the first time he donated blood.</p>
        <p>Nor were all donors police officers. Vinni Genovese-Shek, administrative director of the Transplant Center, was making her 30th donation. Her blood is type O -- the so-called universal donor, which can be given to anyone -- making her a particularly useful donor. She gives every two months, the maximum recommended by doctors. ''Why not,'' she said. ''Blood renews itself. Everyone should give.''</p>
        <p>To Donate Blood</p>
        <p>The following are some blood drives scheduled for this week. For information on any of them, call Hudson Valley Blood Services at (800) 933-2566.</p>
        <p>*Tomorrow, Putnam Hospital Center, Carmel, 3:30 to 9 p.m.</p>
        <p>*Northern Westchester Hospital Center, Mount Kisco, 1:30 to 8:30 p.m.</p>
        <p>*Tuesday, Hudson Valley Blood Services, 525 Executive Blvd. Elmsford, noon to 7 p.m.</p>
        <p>*Tuesday, Court Sport, 1 Odell Plaza, Yonkers, 1 to 6:30 p.m.</p>
        <p>*Wednesday, Hudson Valley Blood Services, Elmsford, 7:30 a.m. to 2:30 p.m.</p>
        <p>*Next Saturday, Hudson Valley Blood Services, Elmsford,  7:30 a.m. to 2:30 p.m.</p>
        <p>*Next Sunday, Grace Baptist Church, 52 South Sixth Avenue, Mount Vernon, 8 a.m. to 1 p.m.</p>
        <p>MILESTONES  Correction:  August 6, 2000, Sunday  A picture caption last Sunday with an article about a blood drive at the Westchester County Police Academy in Valhalla misidentified a blood donor. He was Detective Dolph Tutoni, not Detective John Peters.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: August 6, 2000, Sunday</p>
        <p>A picture caption last Sunday with an article about a blood drive at the Westchester County Police Academy in Valhalla misidentified a blood donor. He was Detective Dolph Tutoni, not Detective John Peters.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
