<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Amtrak's New Approach Comes With a Guarantee</title>
    <meta content="30REP.$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218584"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TRAVEL ADVISORY: CORRESPONDENT'S REPORT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Railroads</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Amtrak (National Railroad Passenger Corp)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wald, Matthew L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Railroads</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E4DC133AF933A05754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="875" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Amtrak's New Approach Comes With a Guarantee</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wald, Matthew L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Amtrak announces new policy under which railroad 'guests' are asked to make complaints on the spot to conductor or other employee; customers will be offered certificates for future travel; ticket sales increase 17 percent, to $8.3 million, in first 15 days after guarantee announcement (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TRAIN late? Service staff rude or unhelpful? Cafe car out of food? Amtrak says it wants to make things right, and, if it fails, wants to make sure passengers get their money's worth, by giving them a certificate for future travel.</p>
        <p>Under a new policy announced this month, passengers -- whom the railroad now refers to as ''guests'' -- are asked to make their complaint on the spot, to a conductor or other Amtrak employee. But even if a disgruntled passenger feels shortchanged and calls the national reservation number instead, the railroad will offer a certificate to take the trip again free, said George Warrington, the president.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TRAIN late? Service staff rude or unhelpful? Cafe car out of food? Amtrak says it wants to make things right, and, if it fails, wants to make sure passengers get their money's worth, by giving them a certificate for future travel.</p>
        <p>Under a new policy announced this month, passengers -- whom the railroad now refers to as ''guests'' -- are asked to make their complaint on the spot, to a conductor or other Amtrak employee. But even if a disgruntled passenger feels shortchanged and calls the national reservation number instead, the railroad will offer a certificate to take the trip again free, said George Warrington, the president.</p>
        <p>''There is no small print,'' he said. The railroad may give away some certificates for trivial complaints, he acknowledged, but it will build loyalty among riders. ''This is about the long haul, not about short-term hand wringing,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Thinking about the long haul is a change for Amtrak, which has led a hand-to-mouth existence for the last few years, its recent history a ''Perils of Pauline'' saga in which  the onrushing train, not the damsel on the tracks, is in danger.</p>
        <p>Its strategy, as described by Mr. Warrington, was to ''cut its way into profitability'' by slicing off more and more service. Instead, the railroad, created by Congress in 1971 as a way to preserve the passenger service that the investor-owned railroads were closing down, was decimating itself, he said.</p>
        <p>But Amtrak has recently shifted its focus, deciding to add trains and readjust schedules to permit connections, making its system work like an integrated network, as the airlines do. The satisfaction guarantee follows training for its 25,000 employees in customer service, and a long effort to make sure its trains are ''right and ready'' for each run.</p>
        <p>It also comes at a time of success for the railroad, which is beginning to partake of the travel boom that has come along with sustained national prosperity. Bookings are at a nine-year high, the railroad said, with passenger loads up 7 percent for the four months ending June 30, compared with a year earlier. Passenger traffic on its four daily all-electric Acela Regional trains between Washington and Boston is up 40 percent over the older trains they replaced, the railroad said.</p>
        <p>''This is a real bump up,'' said Mortimer Downey, the Deputy Secretary of Transportation. The additional passengers are coming out of planes and automobiles, not other trains, he said.</p>
        <p>The railroad intends to introduce its high-speed Acela service, with a top speed of 150 miles an hour (30 m.p.h. faster the current top speed), later this summer. That had been scheduled for last year, but a variety of problems surfaced in the new trains during testing. In recent post-test inspections, for example, some bolts were missing from the new trains, but technicians have installed longer, stronger ones, Mr. Downey said.</p>
        <p>Officials said that aside from a late start to the new service, they did not expect any significant problems.</p>
        <p>Railroad officials also say, without mentioning the airlines directly, that it is not hard to do better at customer service than their main competitors.</p>
        <p>''Consumers want travel that's going to improve their quality of life,'' said Mr. Warrington, discussing the new guarantee with reporters. That means warm personal contact, he said, and help that can sometimes be quite simple. If a train is running late, he said, it could be something like giving out a phone card so the passenger can call ahead, at Amtrak's expense, to tell waiting relatives of the delay.</p>
        <p>In a sign that Amtrak said showed the policy was working, ticket sales in the first 15 days after the guarantee announcement were $57.6 million, up $8.3 million, or 17 percent, above the same period last year.</p>
        <p>Amtrak has been promising free tickets to dissatisfied customers for the last three years on a single train, the Coast Starlight, which runs between Los Angeles and Seattle. It has given them to fewer than one passenger in 100,000.</p>
        <p>But that train is ''one of our gems,'' as Mr. Warrington put it, and railroad officials expect far higher rates systemwide. They are aiming for one in 1,000.</p>
        <p>In the first 15 days, the railroad issued 2,987 service guarantees, or about 3 for every 1,000 passengers. They were worth $228,000, about 0.4 percent of sales. The average value of a certificate was $76. The most common reason was lateness, said Bill Schulz, a spokesman.</p>
        <p>Airlines sometimes placate irate passengers with discount coupons for future travel, or a gift of frequent-flier miles, but industry experts doubt any will follow Amtrak's lead with a guarantee.</p>
        <p>''Margins are so tight,'' said David A. Fuscus, a spokesman for the Air Transport Association, a trade group, who said that if an airline makes a profit of 5 cents per dollar of revenue, ''people are doing cartwheels down the middle of the street.'' And the airlines are hundreds of times bigger than Amtrak, he said, so offering guarantees could mean enormous liabilities.</p>
        <p>TRAVEL ADVISORY: CORRESPONDENT'S REPORT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
