<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Liberty Late, Then Great In Victory Against Rockers</title>
    <meta content="30LIBE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218973"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="WOMEN'S BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Liberty</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cleveland Rockers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Williams, Lena</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504EFDA123DF933A05754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="752" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Liberty Late, Then Great In Victory Against Rockers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LENA WILLIAMS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Williams, Lena</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Liberty defeats Cleveland Rockers, 81-67; photo (M)0</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Before they met the Cleveland Rockers last night, the Liberty players were confronted with daylong flight problems and a delay of their game at Madison Square Garden by more than an hour.</p>
        <p>But then the Liberty shook off its jet lag and the Rockers, the team that has been fighting New York for first place in the Eastern Conference of the Women's National Basketball Association. The Liberty defeated the Rockers, 81-67, despite having spent most of yesterday trying to get from Charlotte, N.C., to New York because of stormy weather and having no time to practice or unwind, let alone unpack.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Before they met the Cleveland Rockers last night, the Liberty players were confronted with daylong flight problems and a delay of their game at Madison Square Garden by more than an hour.</p>
        <p>But then the Liberty shook off its jet lag and the Rockers, the team that has been fighting New York for first place in the Eastern Conference of the Women's National Basketball Association. The Liberty defeated the Rockers, 81-67, despite having spent most of yesterday trying to get from Charlotte, N.C., to New York because of stormy weather and having no time to practice or unwind, let alone unpack.</p>
        <p>The weather and flight problems delayed the start of the game by 76 minutes. Half the Liberty players had made it back in time, but most of the starters had not. They arrived in time for the game to begin at 8:46 p.m. Crystal Robinson led six Liberty players in double figures, scoring a game-high 17 points. The victory after the many snags earned the players a day off today. It also helped the Liberty (17-10) increase its lead to two and a half games with five games remaining. Cleveland (14-12) is tied with the Orlando Miracle (14-12) for second in the East with six games to play.</p>
        <p>''We had some great offensive shows,'' Coach Richie Adubato said. ''We shot 53 percent. It was a must game for us, for the simple reason that we are only a game and a half ahead of them and if we lose tonight we're only a half-game ahead of them and they have the tie breaker because they had us, 2-0.''</p>
        <p>The Liberty did not get to the Garden in time for the scheduled 7:30 p.m. start because the team's 9:50 a.m. flight from Charlotte, where the team played on Friday night, was delayed and then canceled. The players and coaching staff wound up on three different flights to New York.</p>
        <p>Some wound up in Nashville and then took a charter to New York. Had they relied on commercial flights, Adubato said, they would not have made it.</p>
        <p>Sue Wicks, the Liberty's All-Star power forward, tried to keep her teammates focused as they waited for the starters to arrive. It was close to 8:30 p.m., and Wicks, Olga Firsova, Marina Ferragut, Shea Mahoney and Jessica Bibby were the only Liberty players in shooting distance of a basket.</p>
        <p>The core of the Liberty's starting lineup -- Teresa Weatherspoon, Tari Phillips, Becky Hammon and Whitmore -- plus Robinson and Adubato were still missing.</p>
        <p>Looking like the lonesome five, Wicks gathered her teammates in a semicircle, smiled for the Garden crowd and tried to act as if the Liberty was not minutes from being forced to forfeit a game or take the court with only five players and hope for reinforcements.</p>
        <p>One final glance toward the tunnel from the locker room and Wicks was able to breathe a sigh of relief.</p>
        <p>''They're here,'' she mouthed to her teammates, who quickly looked toward the tunnel. Hammon emerged first to cheers that grew louder as Robinson, Whitmore, Weatherspoon and Phillips followed.</p>
        <p>For the first 10 minutes, the Liberty played like a team suffering jet lag.</p>
        <p>Cleveland held a 16-6 lead 13 minutes into the game. Then Robinson, who led the league in 3-point percentage last season but has struggled to regain her shooting range this year, came off the bench and hit a 21-foot jump shot to close the gap to 16-9 and followed it with a 6-foot jumper.</p>
        <p>Whitmore played an inspired first half, leading all scorers with 12 points, and with 1 minute and 43 seconds left in the half tied the score at 31-31 on a one-hand shot while falling toward the basket. The Liberty got its first lead of the game, 33-31, on a 12-foot jumper from Phillips, and led Cleveland, 35-33, at the half. The Liberty led by 57-51 midway through the second half when it went on an 11-2 run. That was capped by Weatherspoon's steal and layup for a 68-53 lead. ''The thing about this team is that we don't quit,'' said Whitmore, who scored 14 points. ''We're playing well right now and we are all contributing.''</p>
        <p>WOMEN'S BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
