<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Tolerance at an Old Tradition</title>
    <meta content="30INDI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218790"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: FLATIRON"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Indian-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parades</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">South Asian Lesbian and Gay Assn</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lee, Denny</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parades</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE4D6173DF933A05754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="429" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Tolerance at an Old Tradition</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DENNY LEE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lee, Denny</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York City's India Day Parade, under compromise prompted by local residents, is slated for August 20 and will probably include members of South Asian Lesbian and Gay Assn; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For the last seven years, gay South Asians have stood on the sidelines while thousands of other Indian-Americans marched down Madison Avenue in the India Day Parade to celebrate their homeland's freedom from British rule.</p>
        <p>This year, under a compromise prompted by local residents, the parade, to be held on Aug. 20, will probably include members of the South Asian Lesbian and Gay Association, or Salga, marching under their own banner. But parade organizers said the group could participate only if it agreed to abide by certain conditions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For the last seven years, gay South Asians have stood on the sidelines while thousands of other Indian-Americans marched down Madison Avenue in the India Day Parade to celebrate their homeland's freedom from British rule.</p>
        <p>This year, under a compromise prompted by local residents, the parade, to be held on Aug. 20, will probably include members of the South Asian Lesbian and Gay Association, or Salga, marching under their own banner. But parade organizers said the group could participate only if it agreed to abide by certain conditions.</p>
        <p>''We are not going to take any obscene stuff or have them walking around with provocative clothing,'' said Vijay Gupta,  vice president of the Federation of Indian Associations, which organizes the event.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gupta also said the gay group's banner would have to be consistent with the parade's overall message. ''Some nice things like 'Long Live India' or 'Salga Is Proud of a Multifaceted Indian Community,' '' he suggested.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gupta pointed out that his organization is private and can exclude those with opposing messages, according to a 1995 United States Supreme Court ruling that a gay group could be excluded from marching in a Boston St. Patrick's Day parade under a banner of Irish gay pride.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gupta said that only the South Asian gay group would be required to sign the rules, which are expected to be decided soon. More than 60 groups and many politicians are expected to march.</p>
        <p>Javed Syed, a spokesman for Salga, said he was delighted by the invitation to march, but concerned about the conditions.</p>
        <p>''What do they mean by obscene?'' he asked. ''Does that include holding hands or transgendered people?''</p>
        <p>Gay advocates also expressed concern that Salga, considered mainstream by some, was being singled out.</p>
        <p>''The additional rules are unnecessary and highlight the need for education,'' said Urvashi Vaid, director of the National Gay and Lesbian Task Force Policy Institute.</p>
        <p>Ms. Vaid marched in the parade in 1992, the only time in the parade's 20 years that gay South Asians were allowed. Since 1992, organizers have barred the gay group or ignored its applications.</p>
        <p>This year, the group approached Community Board 5, which offered support. Although the board has no control over the event, the organizers reconsidered. But the controversy could return, since any agreement would be limited to this year. ''It's ironic that a celebration of freedom has become a battleground about homophobia,'' Mr. Syed said.</p>
        <p>DENNY LEE</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: FLATIRON</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
