<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The World; The Plane That Time Passed By</title>
    <meta content="30WALD$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218852"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Concorde Airplane</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Paris (France)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Air France</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Boeing Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wald, Matthew L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France/Paris</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E7DC153DF933A05754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="810" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The World; The Plane That Time Passed By</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wald, Matthew L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Concorde supersonic jet still flies twice as fast and twice as high as conventional jets, but it has been overtaken by safety, comfort and reliability of Boeing 747, which was originally intended as stopgap until supersonic jets could take place at center of commercial aviation; July 25 Concorde crash outside Paris may mark end of an era; of 20 Concordes built, only 12 remain; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A PLUME of fire about to consume a marvel of aviation, a moment of horror frozen forever in a stunning image; to Prof. W. David Lewis, who studies the history of technology, the burning Concorde looked like a zeppelin for the new century.</p>
        <p>''It's haunting,'' said Mr. Lewis, a historian at Auburn University. ''That long fiery path in the sky, it reminds me, not in detail but in overall symbolic concept, of the Hindenburg.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A PLUME of fire about to consume a marvel of aviation, a moment of horror frozen forever in a stunning image; to Prof. W. David Lewis, who studies the history of technology, the burning Concorde looked like a zeppelin for the new century.</p>
        <p>''It's haunting,'' said Mr. Lewis, a historian at Auburn University. ''That long fiery path in the sky, it reminds me, not in detail but in overall symbolic concept, of the Hindenburg.''</p>
        <p>But it is not just that both had a fiery end, the Air France jet as it took off near Paris on Tuesday and the giant German zeppelin as it was being moored in Lakehurst, N.J., on May 6, 1937. Both supersonic jet and zeppelin, Mr. Lewis pointed out, were symbols of national pride. Each offered luxury service for a wealthy few, and both operated at times of rapid technological change that made their futures uncertain.</p>
        <p>And both, it seems, are instructive about the difficulties of predicting technological progress. It remains to be seen whether the accident last week, which killed 114 people including 5 on the ground, will kill the supersonic transports the way the Hindenburg ended the promise of the dirigible, when it crashed killing 35 people on board and one on the ground. But progress -- including, perhaps, progress in safety -- has bypassed both.</p>
        <p>In its day, the Concorde was the ne plus ultra of technology, the edge of the envelope in speed and altitude. Thirty years later, the envelope has stretched a great deal, but in other directions, notably toward safety, comfort and reliability. And though the Concorde still flies twice as fast and twice as high, the question is whether it has been left behind.</p>
        <p>Predicting technological change is hard, and the airlines and plane builders are not good at it. When the Concorde was new, Boeing was turning out 747's, the world's largest plane, as a stopgap until supersonics could become the mainstay of commercial aviation, and Pan Am was talking about carrying passengers to the moon. The moon is still there but now is unvisited even by astronauts. Pan Am is gone. The 747 has only grown to carry more people more miles, and the Concordes are dwindling like the last of an endangered species: 20 were built; 12 remain. There are more of every high-profile thing that flies, except maybe for the space shuttles and the Goodyear blimps.</p>
        <p>Technology has advanced in ways almost unimaginable in 1976, when the Concordes entered commercial service to the United States. And while expectations may have scaled back in some areas, like trips to the moon, they have grown in other ways, almost without our noticing, especially in the ubiquity and safety of air travel. In 1969, the year the Concorde first broke the sound barrier, the total number of people carried on planes in the United States was less than the country's population. This year, the number of passengers is more than double the population.</p>
        <p>New planes carry entertainment screens in every seat-back. The Concorde's design does not allow even an in-flight movie. Makers of new planes boast that they will fly almost continuously, day after day. The typical Concorde, in contrast, flies 3 hours a day or less.</p>
        <p>The Concorde is one of the few examples in history of a technology whose successor was slower. It bears a passing resemblance to the American nuclear power industry, which used a technology that looked advanced and attractive in the 1960's and 70's, only to seem, 20 years later, esoteric and not worth the bother and expense. It is as if the airlines have decided the tortoise is sexier than the hare.</p>
        <p>Flying is now safer than driving, taking the train or walking, and almost safer than staying home. One  reason is that airplanes are now mass produced, and their failures protect each other. There are, for example, about 2,600 Boeing 737's in service, and every now and then, somebody finds something worrisome in one of them, like a power conduit inside a fuel tank that has short-circuited and is giving off sparks. But the result is a swift order to inspect the other thousands for the same problem and fix it. In contrast, if the cause of the Concorde crash turns out to be a generic flaw, the population protected will be the remaining 12 airplanes.</p>
        <p>But in the grand sweep of technological progress, that may not be a fair way to consider safety, or even a sensible one. ''If you do take that approach, we'll never have any advances,'' said John R. Deakin, a veteran Boeing 747 pilot and safety expert. ''Somebody has to be out there on the bleeding edge.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
