<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Unhappy Hour: Waiting for Takeoff, Drink in Hand</title>
    <meta content="30BARS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218798"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: BENDING ELBOWS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bars</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Kennedy International Airport (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Concorde Airplane</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Paris (France)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Greenwich Village Bistro (Nyc Bar)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leduff, Charlie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France/Paris</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bars</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E7DF143DF933A05754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="578" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Unhappy Hour: Waiting for Takeoff, Drink in Hand</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLIE LEDUFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Leduff, Charlie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bending Elbows column describes scene at Greenwich Village Bistro above Air France terminal at Kennedy International Airport same day that Concorde jet crashed and burned in Paris suburb; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The supersonic Concorde jet sat abandoned like an empty wheelchair on the tarmac at Kennedy International Airport on Tuesday afternoon. It was visible to all the summer travelers staring out the window of the Greenwich Village Bistro above the Air France terminal.</p>
        <p>Air France had indefinitely grounded the jet as a precaution, because three hours earlier one of these planes, which had been chartered by a German tourist group and was New York bound, crashed and burned in a suburb of Paris, killing all 109 on board and 5 other people who were in a hotel when the plane hit it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The supersonic Concorde jet sat abandoned like an empty wheelchair on the tarmac at Kennedy International Airport on Tuesday afternoon. It was visible to all the summer travelers staring out the window of the Greenwich Village Bistro above the Air France terminal.</p>
        <p>Air France had indefinitely grounded the jet as a precaution, because three hours earlier one of these planes, which had been chartered by a German tourist group and was New York bound, crashed and burned in a suburb of Paris, killing all 109 on board and 5 other people who were in a hotel when the plane hit it.</p>
        <p>But the plane on the runway did not seem to bother the patrons drinking here, nor did the looping reports of the crash that played incessantly on the television screens above the bar. By far the most frightening thing, the international travelers said, were the dozen or so reporters who scurried around like squirrels trying to ferret out some acorn of a quote before airport security kicked them out.</p>
        <p>''Disgusting,'' hissed Adam Dakki, 30, who was on his way to Morocco, flying on Johnnie Walker Black. He was going back to the homeland with two pieces of luggage and the knowledge that when it's time to go, it's time to go.</p>
        <p>''I, personally, am not afraid of flying,'' Mr. Dakki said while looking over his shoulder at the scene as though he expected to be arrested at any minute. ''I am not afraid of dying. But the media, they scare me. Some television reporter asked me to come outside. Can you believe that? For what? I mean, the crash happened in Paris. What do I know?''</p>
        <p>Only during tragedies do you realize how gross the media truly can be, said Mr. Dakki, a swarthy, handsome man with a clipped mustache. Not so much spiritually, he said. He already knew members of the media were self-indulgent gasbags.</p>
        <p>''You would have thought J. F. K. Jr. was the King of Siam,'' he offered as reference.</p>
        <p>What Mr. Dakki did not know until now was how truly physically repulsive the members of the media tend to be. Overweight. Balding. Psoriatic. Nail-bitten. Shabby. Unwholesome. Noxious. Halitosic. Whiny. And they came in all packages, colors, languages, ethnicities.</p>
        <p>They spoiled the drinks.</p>
        <p>This baleful nugget was dispensed by a reporter for the BBC and overheard at the bar: ''Normally when there is an air crash, I think: 'Oh, good! Clam chowder,' because I get sent to New England.''</p>
        <p>A little while later this same reporter came to sit at the bar. ''The clam chowder was rotten, like wallpaper, really,'' he complained to his colleagues. And then the ghoulish little man said something tasteless about the German race. Mr. Dakki took his bags and slipped away.</p>
        <p>The bar itself is a dreary place lit in neon. People came here to drink for two reasons: fear and boredom. They stared at the strange coins as if there was something to be augured from them. They smoked.</p>
        <p>Around 7 P.M. the floodlights in the terminals went on, drowning the place in a harsh, bitter light. A few slightly soused reporters remained. But they asked no questions. What more could possibly be said?</p>
        <p>CHARLIE LEDUFF</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: BENDING ELBOWS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
