<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Magician Is Still a Handful, but Primarily on the Racetrack</title>
    <meta content="30BREE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218972"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HARNESS RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Breeders Crown Trot</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Popper, Steve</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE0DA123DF933A05754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="608" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Magician Is Still a Handful, but Primarily on the Racetrack</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVE POPPER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Popper, Steve</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., July 29</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Moni Maker and Magician are clear choices in $1 million Breeders Crown Trot at Meadowlands (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As they stepped up to the starting gate tonight, Moni Maker and Magician were the clear choices in the $1 million Breeders Crown Trot final, a far cry from the diverse paths they had taken to reach that point.</p>
        <p>It was about three years ago, when Moni Maker was grabbing headlines as she approached $1 million in earnings, that Magician's owner, William Augenstein, called his trainer in Florida with questions about whether his horse would ever make it onto the track. Magician had been acting up, and the trainer, Jim Cruise Jr., could not get the horse to train.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As they stepped up to the starting gate tonight, Moni Maker and Magician were the clear choices in the $1 million Breeders Crown Trot final, a far cry from the diverse paths they had taken to reach that point.</p>
        <p>It was about three years ago, when Moni Maker was grabbing headlines as she approached $1 million in earnings, that Magician's owner, William Augenstein, called his trainer in Florida with questions about whether his horse would ever make it onto the track. Magician had been acting up, and the trainer, Jim Cruise Jr., could not get the horse to train.</p>
        <p>But Cruise made some changes to get the horse racing, and tonight David Miller guided Magician to a three-length victory over Moni Maker to win the Breeders Crown Trot in 1:531/5 .</p>
        <p>It was the first time in four attempts that Magician had got the best of Moni Maker, the two-time defending Horse of the Year. Moni Maker, who has the highest career earnings for a standardbred, would have gone over the $5 million mark with a victory.</p>
        <p>While the path has still been bumpy, Magician has made his way into the upper echelon of trotters, entering tonight's race with $1,004,385 in earnings before winning another $500,000. That did not seen possible early in his career.</p>
        <p>Augenstein said Cruise told him, ''I can't get him on the track and he can't train.''</p>
        <p>''Two or three months went by and it was the same thing,'' Augenstein said. ''I said, 'I can't keep getting these bills if there's no hope.' ''</p>
        <p>Hope came soon, and Magician made it onto the track that year.</p>
        <p>''He's gotten over a lot of those problems,'' said Earl Cruise, who is Jim Cruise's brother and who now handles the training chores. ''He hasn't done anything this year.''</p>
        <p>Earl Cruise said that if before the race someone had written him a check for $250,000 -- second-place money -- ''I'd have taken it, but thank God we didn't do that.''</p>
        <p>Miller, Magician's driver, said: ''He's acted up on me twice, so you still have to be careful with him. When I started driving him last year, he already had made $300,000, so he's always been a good horse to me.''</p>
        <p>It is a far cry from the difficult beginnings for the 5-year-old bay gelding, who was purchased in 1996 for $11,000. And it was a difficult second-place finish for Moni Maker, who won the Breeders Crown in 1998 and was expected to be the favorite to defend the title last year.</p>
        <p>When Moni Maker returned to the United States to prepare for the race, however, troubles surfaced. In a Titan Cup elimination, she struggled and the driver Walter Hennessey eased up; tests found that she was dehydrated and had had an irregular heartbeat. Moni Maker was sidelined for the race and did not return to action for more than two months.</p>
        <p>Western Ideal set a world record for an older pacing horse in the $440,000 Breeders Crown Open final, getting the best of a duel with Dragon Again and winning in 1:48. Western Ideal has already captured the Haughton Memorial and the Graduate this year. This race had torrid splits, with Dragon Again leading at the quarter-mile in 26.0 and at the half in 52 2/5.</p>
        <p>HARNESS RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
