<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Shrubs for Beauty and Health</title>
    <meta content="30CUT.$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218811"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="CUTTINGS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blueberries</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Taylor, Patricia a</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden/Columns/Cuttings</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fruit</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401EEDF143DF933A05754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="891" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Shrubs for Beauty and Health</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICIA A. TAYLOR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Taylor, Patricia a</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on care and maintenance of blueberry bushes; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>JULY is often promoted as national blueberry month, and across the nation, festivals and pick-your-own farms beckon and tempting recipes appear in newspapers and magazines.</p>
        <p>In Japan, says Al Murray of the New Jersey Agriculture Department, the fruit is being consumed in record amounts. This increase is due in no small part to findings published last September by James A. Joseph and Barbara Shukitt-Hale of the United States Agriculture Department's Human Nutrition Center on Aging at Tufts University. Their research on rats led them to conclude that daily consumption of one-half to one cup of fresh or frozen blueberries could slow or even reverse the effects of aging.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>JULY is often promoted as national blueberry month, and across the nation, festivals and pick-your-own farms beckon and tempting recipes appear in newspapers and magazines.</p>
        <p>In Japan, says Al Murray of the New Jersey Agriculture Department, the fruit is being consumed in record amounts. This increase is due in no small part to findings published last September by James A. Joseph and Barbara Shukitt-Hale of the United States Agriculture Department's Human Nutrition Center on Aging at Tufts University. Their research on rats led them to conclude that daily consumption of one-half to one cup of fresh or frozen blueberries could slow or even reverse the effects of aging.</p>
        <p>Closer to home, blueberries' popularity was confirmed this month when the squirrels beat out both the birds and my husband by stripping my semidwarf plants bare before the berries ripened. That did not deter my husband, who went out and picked 25 pounds at a nearby orchard. Thus, I have been making jam, baking and freezing many blueberry muffins, and serving blueberry pancakes as a treat on weekends.</p>
        <p>I look forward to August and the end of this hoopla. It means I can return to simply treasuring blueberries as one of the most handsome, maintenance-free shrubs.</p>
        <p>As the great horticulturist Liberty Hyde Bailey wrote a century ago: ''The plant is beautiful when in flower; the fruit is attractive and of the best quality, and the bright scarlet and crimson effects in late autumn, rivaling the sumach in brilliancy, are unsurpassed. As an ornamental plant, the species deserves a place in every garden.''</p>
        <p>High praise indeed. And it actually neglects the pink blush on the long-lasting creamy white, one-third-inch, bell-shaped spring flowers and the red sheen on the bare winter stems. The stems are particularly lovely when powdered with light snow.</p>
        <p>Blueberries are rather temperature-specific. Low-bush blueberries (Vaccinium angustifolium) thrive in Zones 2 to 6, high-bush (V. corymbosum) in Zones 5 to 7, and rabbiteye (V. ashei) in Zones 6 to 9. Though Bailey was referring to the high-bush berry, all three exhibit the same beautiful ornamental qualities. All three, said a Canadian government food researcher, Wilhelmina Kalt, bear berries with anti-aging properties.</p>
        <p>Despite Bailey's praise, blueberries have consistently been grown for their fruit rather than for their appearance. Elizabeth White, whose family ran a cranberry operation in the New Jersey Pinelands, can take a lot of credit for that. In 1911, she contacted Dr. Frederick Coville at the Agriculture Department and asked about his research on the feasibility of cultivating blueberries. White believed that such cultivation would be a profitable second crop, one occurring a month before the cranberry harvest.</p>
        <p>In 1916, five years after the two joined forces, the first cultivated blueberry was produced and an agricultural industry was born. Dr. Coville provided the scientific expertise to propagate and hybridize the berries. Ms. White contributed the plants, calling on local ''Pineys'' to search the area for bushes with the most promising berries.</p>
        <p>Ms. White paid $2 for every bush that bore berries at least five-eighths of an inch in diameter and named each bush for its finder. When Rube Leek of Chatsworth found a promising one, a quandary arose. Leek wasn't a suitable name, and Rube didn't convey the plant's usefulness. Dr. Coville christened it Rubel; it became a key commercial blueberry parent and is still sold.</p>
        <p>I've had blueberries in my borders for 20 years. I started with two five- to six-foot-tall high-bush cultivars -- Bluecrop and Jersey -- because two varieties are needed for good pollination and both are suitable for my central New Jersey area. All they required were well-drained, acidic soil, a weekly watering in dry periods, and a mostly sunny location to produce summer berries.</p>
        <p>Over time, as birds devoured the berries despite a netting over the bushes, I began to admire the shrubs more for their looks than for their produce. Five years ago, I did away with the netting and the big bushes and placed Friendship and Northblue, semi dwarf plants known as half highs, in a mixed border. These multiseasonal plants grow about four feet tall and, if netted, can each produce seven pounds of berries. But I chose them for their handsome look.</p>
        <p>There are signs researchers are falling in love with blueberries' ornamental qualities. About 10 years ago, breeders at Michigan State University introduced a high-bush-low-bush cross -- Top Hat. Forming a two-foot dense mounded plant, it is perfect for containers and as a bonsai subject.</p>
        <p>And Dr. Nicholi Vorsa, director of the Rutgers University blueberry and cranberry research laboratory, is evaluating some beautiful high-bush forms for release. One has corkscrew-type stems; another, closely packed green leaves iny that they reflect the powder blue of the berries.</p>
        <p>While blueberry bushes might not ultimately prove to be a fountain of youth, they certainly can constitute an oasis of beauty and contentment in the garden.</p>
        <p>A wide variety of blueberries are sold by Forestfarm, 990 Tetherow Road, Williams, Ore. 97544; (541) 846-7269; catalog $4; and Hartmann's Nursery, Box 100, Lacota, Mich. 49063; (616) 253-4282; free catalog.</p>
        <p>CUTTINGS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
