<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Simsbury, the View Is of the Bridge</title>
    <meta content="30BRID$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218647"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bridges and Tunnels</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Old Drake Hill Flower Bridge (Simsbury, Conn)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Simsbury (Conn)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Farmington River (Conn)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stowe, Stacey</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bridges and Tunnels</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E3D91E3AF933A05754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1316" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Simsbury, the View Is of the Bridge</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STACEY STOWE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stowe, Stacey</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Old Drake Hill Flower Bridge, metal truss bridge that has spanned Farmington River in Simsbury, Conn, since 1892 and now is open only to pedestrians; this bridge has been replaced with metal bridge that is festooned with baskets and boxes of 148 varieties of flowers; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IF you drive the requisite 25 miles per hour on Riverside Road, a curving, country road in Simsbury, you'll be rewarded with a fine glimpse of it, a riot of color amid the cool green along the riverbank. From the west, crossing over the new bridge on Drake Hill Road from the town's center and looking south, you'll have a more leisurely view. But whatever you do, don't miss it.</p>
        <p>It is a metal bridge, over the Farmington River, that has geraniums and ivy nestled in wooden boxes on its railing and petunias and sweet potato vines spilling out of baskets strung from its girders. Cottage gardens of dahlias, shrub roses and snap dragons mark its east and west sides. People around here call it ''the flower bridge,'' and it is one of those places, saved from the wrecking ball although it had outlived its usefulness, that is emblematic of a small town and the people who live and volunteer there.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IF you drive the requisite 25 miles per hour on Riverside Road, a curving, country road in Simsbury, you'll be rewarded with a fine glimpse of it, a riot of color amid the cool green along the riverbank. From the west, crossing over the new bridge on Drake Hill Road from the town's center and looking south, you'll have a more leisurely view. But whatever you do, don't miss it.</p>
        <p>It is a metal bridge, over the Farmington River, that has geraniums and ivy nestled in wooden boxes on its railing and petunias and sweet potato vines spilling out of baskets strung from its girders. Cottage gardens of dahlias, shrub roses and snap dragons mark its east and west sides. People around here call it ''the flower bridge,'' and it is one of those places, saved from the wrecking ball although it had outlived its usefulness, that is emblematic of a small town and the people who live and volunteer there.</p>
        <p>''It's just a beautiful spot with the river below and the colors and fragrance from the flowers,''said Jane Hannah, one of the volunteers who cares for the flowers. ''It's a destination for people in town.''</p>
        <p>Before its reincarnation as the Old Drake Hill Flower Bridge, the circa 1892 metal truss bridge in this suburb of Hartford was used to carry horses and carriages and then automobiles in a single lane over the river. Until 1988, it was a spot that fairly demanded patience as people had to slow down and wait their turn if someone was crossing from the opposite side. Now, it is only open to pedestrians.</p>
        <p>''Neighbors would see each other and give a little wave as they drove past,'' said Alan Yates, a retired engineer who designed a pulley system to ease watering the hanging baskets. Today, people slow down because they want to.</p>
        <p>On a recent summer afternoon, a man in-line skated over the wooden planked bridge and another kayaked under it. A woman took her lunch break with a book and a lemonade at a shaded picnic table.</p>
        <p>The bridge spans 183 feet and carries a 12-foot road suspended 18 feet over the river, Mr. Yates said. He and his wife, Marilyn, have lived in town 36 years. They are the kind of people who don't vacation in summer because they believe their town is too pretty to leave.</p>
        <p>''We have 148 varieties of flowers and 1,000 plants here,'' said Mrs. Yates, a septuagenarian who loves gardening and Simsbury with equal doses of zest and gratitude. She absently deadheaded a lavender mist petunia as she spoke, flicking the spent blossom into the river below. It is Mrs. Yates, a member of the Federated Garden Clubs of Connecticut, who orchestrates the transformation of the bridge every spring. She orders the plants throughout the winter and spring, hovers over them in the cooler months in a donated greenhouse in Avon called the Pickin' Patch, and supervises the planting of the 48 boxes and 32 hanging baskets.</p>
        <p>''Even with the automatic watering system (50 minutes each side per day), we still need to water by hand, especially during a drought,'' Mr. Yates said.</p>
        <p>Before the iron bridge was built, people crossed the river over a timber one. In 1890, it was determined that the wooden bridge needed replacement, said Dawn Bobryk, president of the Simsbury Historical Society. According to town archives, residents asked selectmen to issue $10,000 worth of bonds to pay for the construction of an iron bridge.</p>
        <p>Throughout the 1900s, residents debated the merit of a single lane bridge and whether improvements to it would affect the rural character of the area. By the 1980's, it was clear the town needed to replace the existing bridge or build another nearby. In 1983 taxpayers voted to spend $400,000 to build a new Drake Hill Bridge and improve connecting roads; the new bridge opened in 1992.</p>
        <p>In 1988, the old bridge was closed and if the cost of demolishing it weren't so high, it might have been destroyed after a new concrete one a short distance away replaced it. In 1991, Anita Mielert, now Simsbury first selectman, read about a federal grant that provided 80 percent of the money for restoration of historic transportation structures. She convinced the town council to save the bridge for several reasons: it was historically important; it is along the Farmington Valley Canal Green Way, a 22-mile bicycle and walking path; the new bridge did not have a sidewalk, and it would have cost the town $220,000 to tear the bridge down versus the $95,000 portion of the $575,000 total for restoration.</p>
        <p>''I live on the eastern side of the river and crossed it to get into town every day,'' Ms. Mielert said. ''Maybe because I relied on the bridge every day I saw the need to preserve it as a piece of history.''</p>
        <p>The town council agreed. Lead-paint had to be removed in keeping with strict environmental guidelines (for example, no paint chips could fall in the river). Rust was removed, abutments repaired and blacktop replaced with wood planks.</p>
        <p>When the restoration was complete in 1995, the bridge, painted a milky green, was a picturesque finely made thing from another century, but Dominque Avery believed it could be more. Inspired by a 50-year-old flower bridge in Shelburne Falls, Mass., Ms. Avery, then chairman of the town recycling committee, made a few phone calls to members of the town chamber of commerce, garden committee, parks and recreation and engineering departments.</p>
        <p>''There was tremendous interest,'' said Ms. Avery. ''After just three meetings, we had a plan.''</p>
        <p>One year later, high school students in the school industrial arts program made four flower boxes and a coalition of stores donated money to pay for landscaping. A plumbing company, called B &amp; E, provided free labor to install a water line. Northeast Utilities hooked up electrical power. Fund-raising efforts began in earnest.</p>
        <p>Today, the bridge is just about covered with flower boxes, each bearing a tiny plaque with a donor name or message. (One reads, ''Isn't this a beautiful bridge!'') There is a little bit of railing left to lean against as you watch boys and girls from Simsbury High School crew in the tea-colored water beneath the bridge.</p>
        <p>There is a persistent whoosh of cars passing on the nearby roads and across the other bridge and some times a car pulls into the small parking lot next to the bridge, but it is a peaceful place, just a little spot. There are shaded picnic tables. There's a big willow tree to lean against.</p>
        <p>Ask a volunteer about what they do for the bridge and they are more apt to mention someone else rather than tick off their own list of accomplishments. An arborist, Brian Watkins, donates his services. Mrs. Yates said she rarely has a problem finding people to volunteer or donate.</p>
        <p>''Sometimes I call in a favor, but usually I start by saying, ''Will you serve your community?'' she said, peering out from under a broad-brimmed straw hat.</p>
        <p>Lucille Bartolomo, a volunteer who completed her weekly watering of the eastern cottage gardens, said people are very appreciative of the bridge.</p>
        <p>''One day, a woman drove up, rolled down her window and shouted 'Thank you!' and then just drove off,'' she said, smiling at the recollection and bending to snatch a weed near a batch of pansies.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
