<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Adding to, and Subtracting From, Coward</title>
    <meta content="30THEA$18" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218739"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Montclair State University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Klein, Alvin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Newman, Geoffrey</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Coward, Noel (1899-1973)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">High Spirits (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E2D9163DF933A05754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="957" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Adding to, and Subtracting From, Coward</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALVIN KLEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Klein, Alvin</byline>
      <dateline>MONTCLAIR</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alvin Klein reviews Theaterfest revival of High Spirits, musical adaptation of Noel Coward play Blithe Spirit; musical is directed by Geoffrey Newman at Montclair State University; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN the conductor strikes up the six-man band at the top of ''High Spirits'' in the Theaterfest revival at Montclair State University here, the pulse quickens. Ah, the blessed sound of a big, brassy Broadway show.</p>
        <p>It isn't long before that old saying  ''count your blessings'' no longer works at Theaterfest. Even when you're counting, six men, out of sync, provide a pained lesson on how less is really less. One man in tune would be better. No more illusions; blessings turn into curses.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN the conductor strikes up the six-man band at the top of ''High Spirits'' in the Theaterfest revival at Montclair State University here, the pulse quickens. Ah, the blessed sound of a big, brassy Broadway show.</p>
        <p>It isn't long before that old saying  ''count your blessings'' no longer works at Theaterfest. Even when you're counting, six men, out of sync, provide a pained lesson on how less is really less. One man in tune would be better. No more illusions; blessings turn into curses.</p>
        <p>The overture isn't even over and you've landed with a thud. Those good old days are really over. Wouldn't it have been lovely if Theaterfest brought them back for two and a half hours?</p>
        <p>Otherwise, why produce ''High Spirits''? Even though it does not represent the best of golden times, it is a reminder of a bygone era when going to a Broadway show was the thing to do, and doing it came naturally. We're talking 1964.</p>
        <p>To add to the puzzlement, the show is playing in Theaterfest's small space, not on the mainstage. And it could work far better as a small show. The director, Geoffrey Newman, muffs the chance to dispose of a disposable chorus. Instead, silly dances are tossed in by Roger Bennett Riggle.</p>
        <p>Portentiously, as it turns out in this inept staging, the story is about ghosts, poltergeists and seances. ''High Spirits'' is a flaccid adaptation of Noel Coward's classic charade about Charles, a dapper novelist, and his two wives: Elvira, dead five years, now the ''Blithe Spirit'' of the play's title, and Ruth, still alive, for the moment. The ending is changed -- they all die, which violates Coward's point about man, free at last, from the bondage of women, both of these being literal homewreckers.</p>
        <p>No longer does Charles flee in triumph.</p>
        <p>With an unintegrated un-Cowardy score and a superfluous chorus, the musical nevertheless had the playwright's blessing.</p>
        <p>In Mr. Newman's spooked staging, the worst, even when you're convinced it has just materialized, is unfailingly yet to come. If you can, just follow Madame Arcati's advice and ''go into your trance.'' Arcati's songs have never been dopier, though ''Something Is Coming to Tea'' has comic possibilities. But if Barbara Spiegel is actually remembering her lines and her lyrics, that is not a good idea. If she is not, a flair for the daft is not discernible.</p>
        <p>From her entrance on a bicycle, singing ''The Bicycle Song,'' Madame Arcati is a fabulous character, reduced by Hugh Martin and Timothy Gray, who collaborated on music, lyrics and book, to a foolish one. To make her more foolish, Mr. Newman staged that entrance behind tacky rippling fabric, spanning the width of the stage, meant to suggest a hedge.</p>
        <p>Above it, the medium and chorus, all at chin level, at times holding up handlebars, look out at what must be a stupefied audience. No, folks, this is not an apparition. It would be an excessively charitable stretch to suggest that Mr. Newman had an ingenious conception in mind, even if it doesn't work. But it is simply inane by professional theater standards, perhaps acceptable at an elementary school level, but this theater is linked to a university, where Mr. Newman is the Dean of the School of the Arts.</p>
        <p>In scenic design, there is no aesthetic touch in sight. The inescapable portrait of Ruth, Charles's soon to be dead wife, is so unsightly, one wonders if Mr. Newman means to impart a haunting Coward might not have had in mind. The portrait hangs -- no, it hovers -- in the drawing room. It is impossible to blank it out, yet bizarrely, that room, the plot's master room, is set way back, presumably to provide for the nonexistent bicycles, concealed up front. Actually, Arcati's is real, not that she rides it. Ms. Spiegel simply allows us a peek, as she exits upstage, carrying it.</p>
        <p>In a cast most conspicuous for being ill at ease, only Andrea Bianchi as Edith, the jumpy maid, seizes her moments without strangling them. Although Michael Ricciardone (Charles) and Martina Vidmar (Ruth) sing the beguiling ballad, ''If I Gave You,'' with affection and grace, Mr. Ricciardone appears to sense that maintaining an overly blase demeanor is the only way to brave a catastrophe and Ms. Vidmar is exasperated as Ruth. If she turned around to look at the portrait, Ruth would die sooner.</p>
        <p>The star of the nonoccasion is best reserved for last. Kim Zimmer, of the daytime drama ''Guiding Light,'' is an Elvira whose astro-voyage was ticketed for the red-eye from Palm Springs, and it was not a first-class booking. After descending from that noncelestial space, Ms. Zimmer gives a brassy, inelegant, self-conscious show-biz account of a now ethereal being who was once an ''overpoweringly demure'' life force. Ms. Zimmer is overpowering in all the wrong stylistic ways, playing to the gallery (when there is none) while winking at the front rows, indicating every detail in an obvious quest for approval.</p>
        <p>No doubt, she gets the approval of the audience, if not the meaning of the part. People long to see a soap opera queen in the flesh.</p>
        <p>HIGH SPIRITS  Theaterfest.</p>
        <p>Montclair State University, Valley Road and Normal Avenue, Upper Montclair.</p>
        <p>Through Aug. 6. Today and next Sunday at 3 p.m., Tuesday through Saturday at 8 p.m., Wednesday at 2 p.m.  (973) 655-5112.</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
