<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bosnians, Ending Exile, Cope With Old Hatreds</title>
    <meta content="30SARA$17" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218906"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Bosnia and Herzegovina</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sarajevo (Bosnia)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gall, Carlotta</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E7DE123DF933A05754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1667" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bosnians, Ending Exile, Cope With Old Hatreds</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CARLOTTA GALL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gall, Carlotta</byline>
      <dateline>SARAJEVO, Bosnia and Herzegovina</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>First Muslims</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Five years after the bloodshed and ethnic cleansing that tore apart Bosnia's communities of Serbs, Muslims and Croats, the first Muslims are now heading home to areas of eastern Bosnia that were the scene of some of the war's worst atrocities.</p>
        <p>Serbs, too, are returning to Muslim-dominated Sarajevo, a capital once known for its multiethnicity but subjected to three and a half years of Serbian siege and shelling in the 1992-95 war.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Five years after the bloodshed and ethnic cleansing that tore apart Bosnia's communities of Serbs, Muslims and Croats, the first Muslims are now heading home to areas of eastern Bosnia that were the scene of some of the war's worst atrocities.</p>
        <p>Serbs, too, are returning to Muslim-dominated Sarajevo, a capital once known for its multiethnicity but subjected to three and a half years of Serbian siege and shelling in the 1992-95 war.</p>
        <p>The homecomings -- largely spontaneous but helped by international officials who run Bosnia, enforcing laws on returning property to original owners -- are beginning to remedy a cardinal failure of the uneasy peace: the inability of those officials to overcome local hatreds and fears, or to return refugees to areas dominated by ethnic foes.</p>
        <p>Hundreds of thousands of Bosnians remain refugees, and foreign officials have not dented the vivid hatreds that continue to feed murder and expulsion not far away in Kosovo. But each refugee who comes home to Bosnia without major mishap -- particularly to the strongholds of hard-core Serbian nationalists in eastern Bosnia -- can help persuade others to follow.</p>
        <p>Visnja Trkulja, a Serbian schoolteacher, has been back in Sarajevo for nearly a year, living quietly in her apartment house in the suburb called Ilidza. As she greets visitors, she explains that her wing is almost back to its prewar makeup: six Serbian families, two Muslim families and two more Serbian families expected back soon.</p>
        <p>''No one likes refugees,'' she said. ''I knew I wanted to go home when I realized no one wanted me.''</p>
        <p>''This was where my friends were, my first loves, my parents' graves,'' she went on. ''This is my Mount Igman, my sky,'' she said in a gesture to the Sarajevo landscape.</p>
        <p>During the war, Ilidza was under Serbian control and Muslims had to flee. Then, when the 1995 Dayton peace accords ended the fighting, it was the Serbs' turn to run.</p>
        <p>In an exodus that was partly orchestrated by the Serbian leadership and partly panic, 100,000 Serbs abandoned their homes in the suburbs of Sarajevo. The peace deal gave the Muslim-Croat Federation jurisdiction over the whole city, including the Serbian suburbs, and all but a few thousand Serbs moved out.</p>
        <p>Now, they are filtering back, reclaiming their houses from Muslims who have occupied them and returning to the capital some of its former multiethnic atmosphere.</p>
        <p>About 15,000 Serbs have returned to the Sarajevo area in the last 18 months, nudging displaced people to return to other regions around the country. In the first five months of this year, 15,665 people registered after returning home across Bosnia.</p>
        <p>The change is largely due to property laws introduced in 1998, which international officials at the Office of the High Representative -- the powerful civilian authority -- are using to bulldoze local obstructions. Using law alone, they want to reverse the ethnic polarization that makes Bosnia barely workable as a country.</p>
        <p>''Our policy is ruthless implementation so that all property is returned to its owner. We are using the law to subvert ethnic territorialism,'' said David Stewart-Howitt, a former British Army officer who coordinates the property returns at the Office of the High Representative. ''What we have to ensure is a blending that can allow this country to knit together.''</p>
        <p>The authorities are evicting people from homes so owners can reclaim their property. There are 25 to 45 evictions every week in Sarajevo, Mr. Stewart-Howitt said. ''Muslims are being evicted here, the local police are dragging people out, war veterans get involved, then we have street protests,'' he said. ''It's happening all over the country. It's a very difficult process but it's happening.''</p>
        <p>The chairman of the multiethnic presidency of Bosnia, Alija Izetbegovic, originally opposed the idea and his adviser, Mirza Hajric, blames the evictions for the recent fall in the popularity of Mr. Izetbegovic's Muslim party, the Party of Democratic Action. The paucity of returns of Muslims to Serbian areas, while Sarajevo has welcomed so many Serbs, is one reason that Mr. Izetbegovic, 75, says he will resign from office in October, Mr. Hajric said.</p>
        <p>Leaders in the Serbian half of Bosnia have long blocked returns but have grown more compliant since Wolfgang Petritsch, the high representative, began firing local officials for obstructing the Dayton peace plan, including 22 officials on one occasion last fall.</p>
        <p>Fear and intimidation also hamper movement. Ms. Trkulja said she was the only Serb in a refugee center in the eastern town of Foca brave enough to return. ''Many said they did not want to be the first,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Of 750,000 people displaced in Bosnia, about 220,000 have made claims for the return of their homes under the property laws. To date, 17 percent of those claims in the Muslim-Croat federation have been settled and 7 percent so far in the Serbian entity, known as Republika Srpska.</p>
        <p>Although few Muslims are returning to Serb-dominated areas, officials say that even there the trend is upward and the flow will increase rapidly over the summer.</p>
        <p>Serbian officials in Pale, the former ski resort outside Sarajevo that Serbian leaders proclaimed their capital during the war, and in Foca and Rogatica in eastern Bosnia, where Muslims were ruthlessly murdered and expelled, have freed up dozens of apartments belonging to Muslims.</p>
        <p>At a joint news conference this month with his Muslim counterpart from Sarajevo, the Serb who is mayor of Pale guaranteed security for all returning Muslims. Fifty families are being taken back to Pale, Foca and Rogatica in coming weeks, said Mr. Stewart-Howitt. ''I find that pretty revolutionary. It would have been unthinkable even last year.''</p>
        <p>The Croat-run areas of Bosnia are showing the least movement, and 7 of the 10 municipalities with the worst record on returns are Croat, he said. Despite the new mood of cooperation in Croatia itself since President Franjo Tudjman died and was replaced by more moderate leaders, foreigners have yet to observe much change among Bosnian Croat nationalists on the ground.</p>
        <p>House burnings and intimidation still occur every week in every region across Bosnia, although officials insist that violence is declining.</p>
        <p>And yet, refugees are on the move. Villagers all over are traveling back to their homes to test the atmosphere and negotiate for their houses.</p>
        <p>Since April, 400 families have gone back to villages around Foca and more than 100 Serbs have returned to their nearby village of Ustikolina in the Muslim-Croat Federation.</p>
        <p>The Serbian police have freed up 36 apartments in Foca, handing over the keys to returnees, and other families are back in the Muslim quarter rebuilding destroyed homes.</p>
        <p>But it is Sarajevo, always renowned for its tolerance and diversity -- its ancient mosques jostle with Orthodox and Catholic churches in the old part of the city -- that has led the way. The scars of war are still evident. Smashed buildings and bullet-pocked walls still mark the old front line. ''Sarajevo roses,'' the shell craters etched in the sidewalks and now filled with red rubber, are reminders of the years under siege and fire from Serbian artillery. Today Serbs walk freely downtown and eat in Muslim-run restaurants.</p>
        <p>In exile, Ms. Trkulja said, she realized she was a Sarajevan first and had little in common with the Serbian nationalists who dominated Foca. ''We here have the same sense of humor,'' she said. ''We do the same things. I do not have to explain to someone who I am.''</p>
        <p>It is mostly older people and those without children who are returning, and the women come back first to test the water, says Bozidar Stanojevic of the Democratic Initiative for Sarajevo's Serbs, an organization that helps Serbs return.</p>
        <p>There are few jobs for Serbs and continuing discrimination, and some just reclaim a house in order to sell it, he said. Young Serbs, especially those who served in the army, remain scared to return, he added. ''But it is not an objective fear,'' he said. ''We have received threats but nothing happened.''</p>
        <p>Seven Serbs have been killed in the last 18 months, but appear to have been victims of personal score-settling, rather than attacks aimed at deterring Serb returns.</p>
        <p>Sretko Tambur, 60, is a Serbian laborer who returned with his wife, Joka, in January to Blazuj, on the edge of Sarajevo. Pausing from chopping wood with a young Muslim worker in his front yard, Mr. Tambur said: ''I've never had any trouble since I came back. It's the best thing, living at home.''</p>
        <p>His village was once all Serbian, but now Muslims, refugees from other parts of Bosnia, live in his neighbors' homes.</p>
        <p>''The first days the women next door, refugees, provoked me, saying they would blow my house up,'' he said. ''But nothing happened.''</p>
        <p>Serbs had tried to deter him from going home too. ''I did not listen to anyone,'' he said. ''People from both sides are scared.''</p>
        <p>The local police checked on them regularly, his wife said. And the local Muslim shopkeeper offered credit for months until their pensions came through, Mr. Tambur said. He praised Mr. Petritsch for pushing the returns. ''We had Yugoslavia before and it was great,'' he said. Banging his fist on the table, he went on: ''Someone has to say, 'You all have to live together.' ''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
