<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Things People Choose to Fear; Usually They Are Unknown and Uncontrolled, Not Near and Dangerous</title>
    <meta content="30FEAR$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218920"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Psychology and Psychologists</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fear</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Encephalitis</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">West Nile Virus</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mosquitoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pesticides</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnson, Kirk</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Encephalitis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Psychology and Psychologists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/West Nile Virus</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Encephalitis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mosquitoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Psychology and Psychologists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">West Nile Virus</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Emotions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pesticides</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insects</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Viruses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E3DC123DF933A05754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1367" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Things People Choose to Fear; Usually They Are Unknown and Uncontrolled, Not Near and Dangerous</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KIRK JOHNSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Johnson, Kirk</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Experts say people as a society and as individuals choose, from an endless menu of things to fear, what to fret over and what to shrug off; say people tend to fear the unfamiliar and uncontrolled more than the dangers that they know, regardless of real degree of threat; unattractive choice between fear of toxins and fear of disease raised by West Nile Virus spraying in New York City discussed; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Most people do not sit down with statistical charts and decide on the basis of the evidence what specter of death or calamity should most fill them with dread. If they did, they would be pacing the floor at night over cardiovascular disease. Clogged arteries and bad hearts carry off nearly a million Americans a year, about as many as all other diseases and disasters combined.</p>
        <p>But no. On some deep level, social researchers and psychologists say, people as a society and as individuals choose, from an endless menu of things that go bump in the night, what to fret over and what to shrug off.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Most people do not sit down with statistical charts and decide on the basis of the evidence what specter of death or calamity should most fill them with dread. If they did, they would be pacing the floor at night over cardiovascular disease. Clogged arteries and bad hearts carry off nearly a million Americans a year, about as many as all other diseases and disasters combined.</p>
        <p>But no. On some deep level, social researchers and psychologists say, people as a society and as individuals choose, from an endless menu of things that go bump in the night, what to fret over and what to shrug off.</p>
        <p>Only neurotics tackle every item on the list, and only Alfred E. Neuman of Mad magazine blithely ignores them all. But the things that push the human panic button have distinct patterns, experts say. The specters that haunted last week's news -- the crash of the Concorde in France, the discovery of West Nile-infected mosquitoes in Central Park, the failed hijacking at Kennedy International Airport -- were similar in one respect: they were loaded with the mysterious freight of fright that can seize one, whether it makes scientific sense or not. ''People climb mountains and expose themselves voluntarily to all kinds of risks, but they don't like risk inflicted upon them that they don't understand or have control over, like West Nile,'' said Dr. Roger E. Kasperson, director of a risk study center at Clark University in Worcester, Mass.</p>
        <p>Sudden catastrophes like the Concorde crash tend to set human nerves jangling even more. ''If you kill people one by one, people tend to be very tolerant, but if you kill people in large numbers in a single event, we don't like it,'' Professor Kasperson said. ''Those events are very scary, and they get our attention.''</p>
        <p>People's formulations of fear are also framed and focused, risk analysts say, by the peculiarities of culture. The great mythological symbol of America -- the lone-wolf individual, out there challenging the world and all comers -- makes Americans devalue some kinds of risks and elevate others. In surveys, most Americans say they feel fairly safe in their cars, for example, because they feel in control behind the wheel. They feel much less safe in planes, because someone else is at the controls and passengers cannot do much about altering their odds. The fear persists even though planes crash far less often than cars.</p>
        <p>There is also a contradictory mix of impulses that may be at play, particularly in how people react to the West Nile virus and the efforts to fight it.</p>
        <p>Partly because Americans have not had to suffer the worst effects of the world's most devastating wars, plagues and famines of the last 100 years, they have a deep sense of optimism, and a belief in the perfectibility of the world that risk experts say plays heavily into the theater of fear. They tend to despise fatalistic acceptance and believe that all problems probably have solutions.</p>
        <p>If there are bad mosquitoes, that line of risk management goes, then let's wipe them out. But at the same time there is also a deep strain of distrust toward experts and politicians who might purport to know all the facts about fighting mosquitoes or the relative safety of the pesticides used in the battle. The various ''right to know'' laws that have been passed in recent years, covering everything from food ingredients to the known addresses of sex offenders, all center on the idea that individuals are best equipped to assess their own risk tolerance.</p>
        <p>''It's a paradox of our society,'' said Dr. Donald G. MacGregor, a senior research associate at Decision Research, a private, nonprofit research institute in Eugene, Ore., that studies public perception of environmental health and safety. ''Our historical perspective is that of the frontiersperson, but at the same time we want structures to protect us so that while we're out there practicing our frontier individualism we don't get hurt. We want all the upside and we want to factor out the downside; we want 15 percent annualized return on our portfolios in the stock market, but not take on any risk.''</p>
        <p>Often, the result is a three-corner misunderstanding that can leave scientists, policy makers and ordinary people taking completely different views of the same thing. Many Americans, for example, routinely disregard the medical establishment's constant refrain about the dangers of unprotected sex. On the other hand, many people remain deeply anxious about nuclear energy, even though from a strictly technical analysis, scientists say, it is probably one of the safest, cleanest ways ever devised to generate electricity.</p>
        <p>Some researchers say that while they must occasionally fight the impulse to write off ordinary people as fools, they also sometimes find that the lay individual's assessment of risk, while perhaps not strictly rational, has something that mere numbers cannot catch.</p>
        <p>''Often the public is onto something,'' said Dr. Elizabeth L. Anderson, the former director of risk assessment for the federal Environmental Protection Agency and now an environmental science consultant in Washington. ''But you can't get lost in the public perception and lose what the science informs.''</p>
        <p>What seems risky is also often no accident or happenstance of evolutionary psychology. Risk has its hangers-on, a kind of infrastructure of anxiety that includes various special-interest groups trying to shape the public sense of risk to suit their own agendas, as well as media organizations and politicians who sustain themselves with anxiety's bracing energies.</p>
        <p>The public debate over smoking is considered, in risk management circles, a case in point. For years, the American Cancer Society's preachy message that people should stop smoking for the sake of their health mostly did not work. It was rejected because it ran up against the American credo of personal control: that an individual's decision to smoke was an act of free will and no one else's business. Only when the risks were reframed, centering instead on the dangers of passive, secondhand smoke, which resulted from someone else's actions, did clean-air and indoor-smoking laws become common.</p>
        <p>''I don't believe these changes happen by themselves,'' said Dr. M. V. Rajeev Gowda, a professor of public policy at the University of Oklahoma who studies how people and societies make decisions about risk. ''Everything involved here has a political interest group dimension to it, and part of their effort is to capture the framing.''</p>
        <p>And some players just want a piece of the action. Howard J. Rubenstein Associates, for example, the big New York public relations firm better known for representing high-gloss celebrities, began calling reporters last week with a whispered tip about a new turn in the virus story: a mosquito infected with West Nile that apparently feeds during the day had just been discovered by researchers at Fordham University.  The researchers themselves were a bit more circumspect; they said they were not sure yet how common their new mosquito, Aedes japonicus, is; how well it transmits the virus; or whether it even bites people.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
