<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Democrats Pick an Odd Time To Fight Over a Distant Race</title>
    <meta content="30POL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218707"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON POLITICS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Peterson, Iver</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcgreevey, James (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Torricelli, Robert (Sen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04EFDE163DF933A05754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="907" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Democrats Pick an Odd Time To Fight Over a Distant Race</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Iver Peterson</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Peterson, Iver</byline>
      <dateline>TRENTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Iver Peterson On Politics column on fight among Democrats, paricularly front runner, Mayor James McGreevey of Woodbridge and Sen Robert Torricelli, over gubernatorial candidacy in New Jersey despite fact that election will not be held until 2001 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Leave it to those fractious Democrats to remind everyone what is important in New Jersey politics.</p>
        <p>Anyone who gave even a thought to politics in midsummer might have believed that the important events on the landscape were the presidential campaign and the race for the United States Senate between Representative Robert D. Franks and Jon Corzine.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Leave it to those fractious Democrats to remind everyone what is important in New Jersey politics.</p>
        <p>Anyone who gave even a thought to politics in midsummer might have believed that the important events on the landscape were the presidential campaign and the race for the United States Senate between Representative Robert D. Franks and Jon Corzine.</p>
        <p>Wrong. The important race is for governor, the one job in the state with real power, and Senator Robert Torricelli, who is still in his first term, reminded voters of that this month when he decided that he wanted the job after all.</p>
        <p>Until now, the Democratic front-runner had been James McGreevey, the mayor of Woodbridge and the man who came within a percentage point of beating Governor Whitman in 1997 when other incumbent Republicans in the Northeast were winning by 20 percent. Mr. McGreevey has been assiduously raising money and corralling support for a second try ever since, and it seemed to be working -- until the man they call the Torch lit things up.</p>
        <p>Until 10 days ago, Senator Torricelli had said he was interested only in running the Democratic Senatorial Campaign Committee, of which he is chairman, apparently because he believed there would be plenty of time to toy with the race for governor before next April's primary filing deadline. But Mr. McGreevey was rapidly sewing up the nomination and Mr. Torricelli evidently decided that he could not wait.</p>
        <p>''He saw that he was crossing the Rubicon,'' State Senator Ray Lesniak, a long-time McGreevey supporter, said. ''McGreevey was about to lock up the nomination -- he had raised more than $3 million for the party and the major counties were coming out for him.''</p>
        <p>But it was probably not only Mr. Torricelli who was suddenly interested in the governorship. The outpouring of support for him from around the state, from the leadership of Bergen and Somerset Counties, from -- of all people -- a roster of South Jersey Democrats appealing to the Bergen County man to run, suggest that, once the senator had informally announced, the party leadership was ready to rally to his side in the belief that Mr. Torricelli had the best chance to win.</p>
        <p>''When the people in South Jersey said we like this guy from North Jersey, our ears picked up,'' said Rocco A. Mazza, executive director of the Democratic Committee of Bergen County. ''We don't know of many times when that's happened.''</p>
        <p>So the Bergen Democrats, including Joseph Ferriero, the county chairman, issued a statement last Wednesday calling on Mr. Torricelli to announce formally and implicitly gave him their endorsement. The Somerset County Democrats, eager for a candidate who could pull swing voters from their suburban county, also jumped on board.</p>
        <p>And in Hudson County, Robert C. Janiszewski, the county executive who is a rising power in the state Democratic Party, switched sides and came out for Mr. Torricelli. This prompted Mr. McGreevey to try to take back the appointment of Mr. Janiszewski's wife, Beth, to the $95,000-a-year job as director of the state committee on the ground that he had raised the money for her salary.</p>
        <p>Significantly, Thomas P. Giblin, the state party chairman and originally a McGreevey supporter, denied the request.</p>
        <p>Mr. Torricelli's backers say nice things about Mr. McGreevey on the record and less nice things about him under the shadow of anonymity. Publicly, they say the wholesale abandonment of Mr. McGreevey's camp owes simply to the view that Mr. Torricelli, a national figure with statewide recognition, is most likely to win, particularly if his opponent is another Italian-American, Donald DiFranceso, president of the state Senate.</p>
        <p>''The party senses that McGreevey would make a fantastic candidate,'' Mr. Mazza said, ''but the difference is that Torricelli has statewide stature and national stature, and is far superior in the gravitas department. It's the difference between filet mignon and New York strip steak.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Mazza said the choice amounted to having a good chance with Mr. McGreevey and a sure thing in Mr. Torricelli, and a sure thing is particularly what the Democrats say they need next year. For one thing, they believe that the Whitman administration has proved that, barring scandal or economic recession, a competent Democratic administration is good for at least eight years and in all likelihood a majority in the Legislature.</p>
        <p>By last Thursday, Mr. McGreevey had regrouped his forces at a rally in Newark, which was attended by about 200 supporters from his core constituencies in unions and in the cities. They were loud in their support for the man who took on Mrs. Whitman in 1977, and loud in their contempt for Mr. Torricelli, who they say is dropping out of the sky at the last moment to reap what Mr. McGreevey has sown.</p>
        <p>So the Democrats will end up with the one thing they did not want next year, a divisive primary fought out between the party leadership backing Mr. Torricelli and grass-roots sentiment for Mr. McGreevey.</p>
        <p>Senator Lesniak seemed resigned to the idea that Democrats would fight among themselves, as they so often had, if only they would do it in the proper election cycle.</p>
        <p>''We all wish this didn't happen,'' Mr. Lesniak said, ''but we also wish that if there was going to be a fight, it would wait until after November, and after we've elected Al Gore and Jon Corzine.''</p>
        <p>ON POLITICS Iver Peterson reports from New Jersey for The New York Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Iver Peterson reports from New Jersey for The New York Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
