<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Calling 'Creekkeepers' to Blow the Whistle</title>
    <meta content="30CREE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218652"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Volunteers</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Peconic Bay (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rather, John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Anderson, John M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcallister, Kevin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Volunteers</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E4D81E3AF933A05754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1285" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Calling 'Creekkeepers' to Blow the Whistle</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN RATHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rather, John</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on work of John M Anderson and scores of volunteers who are signing up for 'creekkeeper' program conceived by Kevin McAllister, Peconic Baykeeper; creekkeepers are charged with keeping watchful eye on creeks, harbors, bays and beaches along Long Island's East End to protect them from activities that could lead to their decline; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SINCE 1928, the year he first laid eyes on the East End of Long Island as a small child, John M. Anderson of Noyac has been a witness to transformations great and small in the bays and creeks of the Peconic Bay estuary, and lately he has noticed much that is disturbing.</p>
        <p>''I have seen the terrible changes in the environment out here, especially around the water,'' Mr. Anderson said. ''Now I have a chance to do something about it and give something back.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SINCE 1928, the year he first laid eyes on the East End of Long Island as a small child, John M. Anderson of Noyac has been a witness to transformations great and small in the bays and creeks of the Peconic Bay estuary, and lately he has noticed much that is disturbing.</p>
        <p>''I have seen the terrible changes in the environment out here, especially around the water,'' Mr. Anderson said. ''Now I have a chance to do something about it and give something back.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Anderson is among scores of volunteers who are signing up for a ''creekkeeper'' program conceived by Kevin McAllister, the Peconic Baykeeper.</p>
        <p>Mr. McAllister, a coastal biologist from Quogue who has worked for more than two years in the nongovernmental advocacy post of baykeeper, said the volunteers would help to halt ''death by a thousand cuts'' to an estuary that has been declining incrementally and is now in crisis.</p>
        <p>From widely different backgrounds, the volunteers are united by an urge to protect the water and an eagerness to know how. They range in age from retirees like Mr. Anderson, who is 75, to younger people like Jessica Walter, 21, of Riverhead, who will fit creekkeeping into her five-day-a-week job schedule.</p>
        <p>The creekkeepers' charge, as set forth in workshops Mr. McAllister has been holding in East End towns, is straightforward and simple. ''Through grass-roots involvement, citizens will keep a watchful eye over creeks, harbors, bays and beaches to protect them from activities that can lead to their decline,'' the mission statement says.</p>
        <p>Mr. Anderson, who grew up in North Sea and attended Southampton public schools, lived for years in Westbury but always spent time on the East End and moved back permanently with his wife, Elsie, after retiring 11 years ago from a food brokerage business he owned.</p>
        <p>Now he looks forward to adding new purpose to long hours on the water. ''I'm on the water anyway, and I'm hot to trot, and Mr. McAllister knows it,'' said Mr. Anderson, who moors his 25-foot sports cruiser with its 200-horsepower engine in Noyac Creek.</p>
        <p>He said he read about the creekkeeper program in a local newspaper and then heard Mr. McAllister speak about it. ''That's what really got me interested,'' he said. ''I am not a scientist, but I can report what I see.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Anderson said he had noticed with alarm the disappearance of eelgrass on the bottom of Noyac Creek. ''My little creek here used to be full of eelgrass,'' he said. ''No more.''</p>
        <p>As a member of a South Fork groundwater protection group and now as a creekkeeper, Mr. Anderson said he aspired to be ''a needle in the side of these politicians, to get them to do something.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Walter, who grew up by the Peconic River, had been wondering if all the muck she felt on the river bottom when swimming was natural or something new. ''The water just seems to be a lot grungier now than it used to be,'' she said. ''It's just not appealing anymore.''</p>
        <p>She sent the baykeeper program a small donation, got back a letter inviting her to be a creekkeeper, and jumped at the chance. ''I don't know exactly what I'll have to do, but I just figured I'd like to see the options,'' she said. She said she will watch the river when she is not at her job as an administrative assistant in a Riverhead real estate office.</p>
        <p>Mr. McAllister said one place to keep watch was by an underwater pipe that drained effluent from the Riverhead sewage treatment plant directly into the river. Earlier this summer Mr. McAllister sounded an alarm about what he and others said appeared to be fecal material and tiny shreds of toilet paper surfacing above the underwater pipe. Dr. Robert Nuzzi, chief of the marine resources bureau for the Suffolk County Department of Health Services, said Mr. McAllister might have mistaken a lettuce-like white algae for toilet paper, a frequent mistake.</p>
        <p>Mr. McAllister bristled at the suggestion that he would not know the difference. The sewage plant, currently being upgraded, has been out of compliance with its state discharge permit for more than a year.</p>
        <p>Mr. McAllister said he was gratified so many volunteers had decided to accept the creekkeeper mission. ''People are leaving the meetings very pumped up,'' he said. ''And I need the help.''</p>
        <p>At a recent workshop in the Southold town hall, about 35 people, most middle-aged or older, listened intently as Mr. McAllister described the program for an hour and then peppered him with questions. All of them signed on as creekkeepers.</p>
        <p>Mr. McAllister said creekkeepers would watch for illegal wetland filling, trophy lawns intruding into natural-vegetation shoreline buffer zones, beach-obliterating new bulkheads, bilge-purging pleasure boats, chain-saw wielding tree-cutters on creek banks, and the signs -- and odors -- of failed septic systems fouling the water.</p>
        <p>He said he envisioned that the network of monitors would also scan legal notices and attend planning board and town trustees meetings where creek and bay-altering developments and permit requests first emerge.</p>
        <p>''I want to take it beyond someone dipping a test tube in the water,'' he said. ''This program is to empower people.''</p>
        <p>Many shoreline alterations exceed permit limits, violate laws and regulations or slip unnoticed by government enforcers, Mr. McAllister said. He will arm creekkeepers with the right numbers to call, including his own, when they suspect such offenses.</p>
        <p>Creekkeepers will also be equipped with one-time-use cameras and aerial maps to help in spotting changes both abrupt and incremental in shoreline areas.</p>
        <p>Robert P. Fisher, 76, moved to New Suffolk from Scarsdale after retiring from the silk yarn industry, taking up full-time residence in a family house on Kimogener Point near the shores of West Creek.</p>
        <p>He has known the creek since childhood, when he clambered along its banks in the 1920's with his father, and finds it has changed remarkably little in all that time.</p>
        <p>''The changes have really been insignificant,'' he said. ''I'd certainly like to maintain it that way.'' He met Mr. McAllister two years ago and recently read about the creekkeeper program, and quickly signed up.</p>
        <p>Robert E. Ruesch, 58, a high school English teacher for 31 years, retired with his wife to Southampton, where they had summered for years, and took to the water. He recently heard Mr. McAllister address a fishing club to which he belongs. He was impressed enough to volunteer as a creekkeeper.</p>
        <p>''Now I have the time to devote my energy to something that is very important to me,'' he said. He envisioned using his 18-foot power boat for some of his duties, but will switch to his kayak in shallow water.</p>
        <p>The Peconic Baykeeper program is part of a national program, The Water Keeper Alliance begun by Robert F. Kennedy Jr. Mr. McAllister, 41, who grew up near the water in Center Moriches, studied marine biology and holds a master's degree in coastal zone management. He said the Peconic Baykeeper program had about 500 members and an annual budget of about $100,000. Money came from foundation grants, membership and special events, he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. McAllister has assured volunteers that becoming creekkeepers will neither consume all their time nor bring them into angry conflict with neighbors and local government officials. ''All I'm asking is the heads-up,'' he said at the workshop in Southold. ''I'm not looking for someone to lead the charge.'' That job he reserves for himself.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
