<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Schumer Urges Power Plants Be Built</title>
    <meta content="30SCHU$11" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218986"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shortages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Factories and Industrial Plants</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City Metropolitan Area</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lueck, Thomas J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schumer, Charles E (Repr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Factories and Industrial Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shortages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6D9123DF933A05754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="474" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Schumer Urges Power Plants Be Built</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS J. LUECK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lueck, Thomas J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sen Charles E Schumer, warning of looming electrical power shortage in New York City and its suburbs, issues report recommending large new investment in power plants, transmission lines and alternative energy sources; chart of rising electric demand since 1995 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Warning of a looming electrical power shortage in New York City and its suburbs, a report to be issued today by Senator Charles E. Schumer recommends large new investment in power plants, transmission lines and alternative energy sources.</p>
        <p>The report, coming at time when unusually cool weather has dampened the traditional surge in the demand for power to run air-conditioners, concludes that other factors have caused electrical use to keep climbing over a six-year period. The factors include more computers and other high-tech equipment.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Warning of a looming electrical power shortage in New York City and its suburbs, a report to be issued today by Senator Charles E. Schumer recommends large new investment in power plants, transmission lines and alternative energy sources.</p>
        <p>The report, coming at time when unusually cool weather has dampened the traditional surge in the demand for power to run air-conditioners, concludes that other factors have caused electrical use to keep climbing over a six-year period. The factors include more computers and other high-tech equipment.</p>
        <p>Using data from Consolidated Edison and Keyspan, the report says electrical use on a typical summer day has increased 20 percent in New York City and 23 percent on Long Island since 1995.</p>
        <p>''We need to face the music,'' Mr. Schumer said. ''If we ignore the looming, chronic energy shortage, we risk the economic well-being of the entire region.''</p>
        <p>The report by Mr. Schumer, an advocate of deregulating the electric power industry and of cleaner power plants, recommends that new plants be built in the New York region. It does not address the politically divisive question of where to build them, and he could not be reached yesterday for further comment.</p>
        <p>Some city officials, including City Council Speaker Peter F. Vallone, and utility executives have repeatedly urged new power plant construction. Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani has charged that the utilities fail to buy enough backup power from other producers, as is allowed under industry deregulation. But the mayor has not said whether he favors new power plant construction in the region.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schumer's report recommends other new investments in transmission lines that would better connect the New York utilities to sections of the country where electricity is more plentiful, and in fuel cells and other alternative energy sources. He also calls for financial incentives for businesses and homeowners to reduce use.</p>
        <p>The analysis by Mr. Schumer's staff, which incorporates data from the National Weather Service, concludes that residents and businesses have increased the use of electricity for appliances other than furnaces and air-conditioners and that spikes in demand are now less closely associated with the weather.</p>
        <p>It found, for example, that New York City residents used 11,231 megawatts of power on the day in June when the temperature reached 88 degrees. But city residents used only 10,551 megawatts on a summer day in 1995 when the temperature soared to 95 degrees, the report says.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
