<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; Trades Are a Symptom of the Game's Inequities</title>
    <meta content="30VECS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218899"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trades (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Montreal Expos</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vecsey, George</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/George Vecsey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Chicago White Sox</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Seattle Mariners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trades (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E0D7153DF933A05754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="986" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; Trades Are a Symptom of the Game's Inequities</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By George Vecsey</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Vecsey, George</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>George Vecsey Sports of The Times column says real inequity in baseball stems from division of local television revenue; notes New York Yankees get $175.94 million while Montreal Expos get $11.97 million; says this inequity is most evident at this time of year, during trades, when weak teams cough up expensive players; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THERE is a little general manager in every sports fan. If you don't think so, check out the ravers and the ranters, the schemers and the dreamers, on talk radio.</p>
        <p>While weaving through traffic, these people call up and propose the most outrageous trades. Someday soon I fully expect to hear a collision live on WFAN.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THERE is a little general manager in every sports fan. If you don't think so, check out the ravers and the ranters, the schemers and the dreamers, on talk radio.</p>
        <p>While weaving through traffic, these people call up and propose the most outrageous trades. Someday soon I fully expect to hear a collision live on WFAN.</p>
        <p>''Dawg, what about Clay Bellinger and Wilson Delgado for Edgar Martinez? That seems fair to me. I mean, the Yankees need a better D.H. (sounds of shearing metal and shattering glass). Oops, Dawg, gotta go. I just rear-ended a Beamer.''</p>
        <p>Even with both hands on the wheel and both eyes on the road, fans love trades, except when their own favorite player is exiled. Then it gets personal.</p>
        <p>I will never forget the morose sound of our third child, muttering, ''It stinks, it just stinks'' when the Mets traded his scuzzy idol, Lenny Dykstra, for a mope named Juan Samuel. It turned out to be the third-worst trade in Mets history (right behind the ones that ditched Nolan Ryan and Amos Otis), and it is a safe bet the Mets are not promoting that blatant miscalculation among the 10 greatest moments in history on Old-Timers Day today.</p>
        <p>The fact is, when old-timers lumber back for their reunions, most of them feel withdrawal pangs from the way they left in the first place -- some sheepish clubbie sidling over to them and whispering, ''Hey, could you see the G.M. out in the hallway?''</p>
        <p>There have always been trades, so try as I might I cannot work up severe bombast about the assorted comings and goings the past few days.</p>
        <p>When players like Curt Schilling and Mike Bordick start flying around in the closing hours of the baseball trading period, it just seems like business as usual.</p>
        <p>The rich get richer; what else is new? The Arizona Diamondbacks now go into the postseason throwing Randy Johnson and Schilling in every series. Schilling won his first start Friday night and chortled more about his double than his pitching.</p>
        <p>It seems downright unfair for a first-place team to be able to afford a horse like Schilling. However, the real inequity in baseball stems from the division of local television revenue, according to a recent so-called blue-ribbon panel. (Just what is a blue-ribbon panel? Is that like the first prize in the breeder pig category at the county fair?)</p>
        <p>Anyway, these blue-ribbon experts determined that baseball was operating with a tilted table because the Yankees realized $175.94 million in so-called local revenues while the Expos were pulling in only $11.97 million in local revenue.</p>
        <p>No wonder the Yankees were twirling their gold chain like a latter-day Sportin' Life in ''Porgy and Bess,'' crooning, ''There's a jet that's leaving soon for New York,'' trying to lure Rondell White from the destitute denizens of La Belle Provence.</p>
        <p>Weak teams cough up expensive players this time of year. Get used to it. Then there is the sad drama of useful players caught in the crossfire. No doubt Mets fans are mourning the exile of Melvin Mora, the soulful utility man who was shuttled off to barren Baltimore in the rent-a-shortstop move for Bordick.</p>
        <p>Poor Mora. He loves New York, loves Bobby Valentine, loves the Mets, and now he has been dealt to the latter-day 25-man, 25-cabs ice age of the Orioles, the most sour and solipsistic rich team on the face of the earth, in the last decade or two of the Cal Ripken era.</p>
        <p>But as the man said in the movie, there's no crying in baseball -- and no loyalty in sports. Certainly not at those prices. Disloyalty runs both ways. Players bolt teams. Teams discard players. And the fans would trade anybody, too. Just listen to them.</p>
        <p>It seems like a sharp elbow in the nose of Phillies fans to unload Schilling with more than two months left in a season, but where were the Phillies going, anyway? Besides, teams have come back from the bitterness of these late-July discount sales.</p>
        <p>It was only three years ago that the Chicago White Sox divested themselves of just about their entire pitching staff. Words like ''travesty'' and ''contempt'' were bandied about, some of them in this very space. The White Sox management was spitting in the face of its fans, cutting the payroll, cheating the ticket-holders. All of the above. Yet these are the very same White Sox so far ahead of Cleveland that the Indians themselves were making deals just to prove they exist.</p>
        <p>Or, what about the Seattle Mariners? They have survived twin disasters. This is the second anniversary of the vanishing of Randy Johnson, a spectral presence in the Mariners' dugout one inning, on a jet to the National League the next inning.</p>
        <p>Last year Ken Griffey Jr. left the Mariners in midseason, although his uniform remained active until the final day of the season. This year Junior is presiding over the downfall of the Reds. Meanwhile, the Mariners are once again in first place, using good young players obtained in the Johnson deal, and hoarding money from Junior's departure that they will try to use to retain Alex Rodriguez, probably in vain.</p>
        <p>Still, for the moment, Seattle is competitive. This year is all that matters. In the long run, local revenue separates winners from losers (except for the Orioles, of course). Lack of money does indeed guarantee failure. We already knew that, long before the blue-ribbon panel told us.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
