<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Four Corners; When Shifting Groups of Immigrants Compete for the Same Turf, Even an Intersection Can Become Contested Ground</title>
    <meta content="30FEAT$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218812"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pakistani-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Minorities (Ethnic, Racial, Religious)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Italian-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Albanian-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Korean-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Chinese-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Puerto Ricans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mexican-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Russian-Americans</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Siegal, Nina</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mexican-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DEEDF143DF933A05754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="3068" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Four Corners; When Shifting Groups of Immigrants Compete for the Same Turf, Even an Intersection Can Become Contested Ground</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NINA SIEGAL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Siegal, Nina</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on phenomenon, which sociologists call ethnic succession, by which older ethnic groups in city are slowly pushed out and replaced by newer ones and importance that street corners play when ground is contested; focuses on changes at four corners: Coney Island Avenue and Glenwood Road in Brooklyn, where Pakistanis are replacing Russians, Arthur Avenue and 186th Street in Bronx, where Albanians are displacing Italians, Main Street and Maple Avenue in Flushing, Queens, where Koreatown is becoming Chinese and 116th Street and Third Avenue in Harlem, where Puerto Ricans are being displaced by Mexicans; photos; maps (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THERE is a saying among urban historians: You can always tell how a neighborhood is changing. The name of the outgoing ethnic group is on the funeral homes, and that of the incoming group is on the grocery stores.</p>
        <p>In New York, ethnic groups move like tectonic plates, drifting land masses, sometimes colliding at their edges with unhappy consequences, sometimes  slipping past one another with relative ease.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THERE is a saying among urban historians: You can always tell how a neighborhood is changing. The name of the outgoing ethnic group is on the funeral homes, and that of the incoming group is on the grocery stores.</p>
        <p>In New York, ethnic groups move like tectonic plates, drifting land masses, sometimes colliding at their edges with unhappy consequences, sometimes  slipping past one another with relative ease.</p>
        <p>The signs of shift are everywhere. In the span of a few years, a Little Italy, a Koreatown or a Little Odessa is newly defined by the Mexican bodegas or Chinese shoe stores or Indian delis that press at its borders.</p>
        <p>The phenomenon, which sociologists call ethnic succession, is as old as the city itself and may be heightened in New York because of its size and the multiplicity of ethnic groups jostling for the same turf.</p>
        <p>A single street corner can become central to a group's identity.</p>
        <p>''In New York, because we live so much of our life in public and the sidewalk plays such a role in our perception of the city, busy street corners demarcate territory in a way that may be much more significant than in other cities,'' said Philip Kasinitz, a professor of sociology at Hunter College who specializes in immigration issues. ''People feel an allegiance to a stretch of businesses or a corner because that's where the community is defined most publicly.''</p>
        <p>So, 20 years ago, Puerto Ricans in East Harlem knew that if they walked east past Third Avenue on East 116th Street, which was controlled by Italians, they faced the threat of physical violence. Today, the same corner is dominated by Mexicans, who were just as wary of the corner a decade ago when Puerto Ricans held sway there.</p>
        <p>To outsiders, these shifts may be all but invisible. Sometimes the two groups occupying the same turf share physical attributes and speak the same language. But the differences are all too evident to groups trying to forge or maintain an identity.</p>
        <p>The result can be out-and-out conflict, but more often it is a fluid process that involves intricate cultural negotiation. Here are four corners where those delicate negotiations are taking place today.</p>
        <p>In Flatbush,  Russian Jews and Pakistanis</p>
        <p>Yakov Semichan, 56, a Russian Jew whose barbershop has been at Coney Island Avenue and Glenwood Road in the Flatbush section of Brooklyn for nine years, was fighting the crosscurrents.</p>
        <p>In the last five years, his original customer base, Orthodox and Russian Jews whose synagogues and kosher restaurants once dominated the corner, has been departing for wealthier sections of Flatbush. Pakistani immigrants and businesses that catered to them were replacing them.</p>
        <p>But when two Pakistani barbershops opened across the street from Mr. Semichan's shop during the last six years, his business began to suffer.</p>
        <p>Mr. Semichan, who has piercing blue-gray eyes and a gap-toothed grin, had bought Al's Barber Shop from another Russian Jewish barber in 1991, when he moved to Brooklyn from Moldova in the former Soviet Union, and renamed it Yakov's. At first, the shifting population did not affect his business. He  was still the only barber on the strip.</p>
        <p>''Hair is hair,'' he said over his shoulder as he passed the afternoon playing checkers with Nikolay Banov, a friend and customer from Kiev. ''Jewish hair, Pakistani hair, it's all the same.''</p>
        <p>But Asghar Choudhri, president of the Pakistani American Federation of New York, whose headquarters is up the block, said many new immigrants saw otherwise.</p>
        <p>''The Pakistanis all went to their own places,'' Mr. Choudhri said. ''They stayed with their own. When the second Pakistani barber opened, that's when his business really went down.''</p>
        <p>In 1996, a Pakistani immigrant named Shabbir Hussain, who had owned four barber shops in his native city of Lahore, had arrived in Flatbush and was looking for a job. Mr. Semichan offered Mr. Hussain the battered red barber's chair in the front of the shop and put a bright green sign in the window advertising, ''We speak Russian, English and Yiddish,'' along with Mr. Hussein's name translated into Urdu, the Pakistani language.</p>
        <p>The two men now cut hair side by side in Yakov's Barber Shop, and the shop seems busy. But their situation is unusual. Although many elderly Jews still live on side streets like Glenwood Road and Avenue H, the two groups enjoy little interaction.</p>
        <p>On Coney Island Avenue between Glenwood and Avenue H, almost all the businesses are owned by Pakistanis, Bangladeshis or other Muslims. These include Urdu Bazzar, a 99-cent store; Asian Grocery Halal Market; Bukhara Restaurant, which serves Pakistani, Indian and Bangladeshi cuisine, and Raheela Beauty Parlor. Children wear shalwar kameez, traditional Muslim garb.</p>
        <p>But one block from Glenwood, the scenery changes. Just across Avenue H, the streets are populated by Hasidic Jews in black coats and hats. Though the two communities lead separate lives, they share certain traits. Both groups are religious and conservative, both observe restricted diets, and in both communities, women assume traditional roles. Both groups have had tense relationships with blacks and Hispanics in surrounding areas. On a recent afternoon, Mr. Choudhri of the Pakistani American Federation spent the afternoon on the telephone, complaining to the police that African-American teenagers were throwing bottles and rocks at a new mosque and cursing its congregants.</p>
        <p>The Jews and Pakistanis lead largely separate lives.</p>
        <p>''There has been no real interaction, except on the leadership level,'' said Rabbi Yechezkel Pikus, executive director of the Council of Jewish Organizations of Flatbush. ''There's a sort of tolerance. You mind your business and I'll mind mine.''</p>
        <p>In Belmont,  Albanians Displace Italians</p>
        <p>Felix Mastro, a former prizefighter, stood with his buddies, Sal, Johnny D., Guido and Mikey, in the blue light filtering through a canopy outside the Cosenza Fish Market at Arthur Avenue and 186th Street.</p>
        <p>The four men were downing clams on the half shell and reminiscing about the old days, 80 years ago -- before any of them were born -- when pushcarts selling Italian goods rumbled along Arthur Avenue, the heart of the Belmont section of the Bronx.</p>
        <p>''It all changed in 1933, when they opened the Arthur Avenue Retail Market,'' said Mr. Mastro, 70, still dapper in his brown sports jacket, who has lived in the neighborhood all his life. ''They closed the last place where you could buy live chickens on the street over here just a couple of years ago. Very few Italians are left here now.'' It is a daily lament at this intersection.</p>
        <p>At first glance, the Italian presence  seems as bright as ever. Along Arthur Avenue, banners on lampposts proclaim ''Welcome to Little Italy in the Bronx,'' beside Italian bakeries, meat markets and cheese stores. But in the last five years, as Italians have left Belmont for the suburbs, they have been replaced by Albanians.</p>
        <p>Many Roman Catholic Albanians first moved to Belmont in the 1980's, when those who suffered under their country's fanatical Communist regime fled to the United States. The recent wars that drove thousands of Albanians from Kosovo produced the latest wave of immigration, which began about three years ago.</p>
        <p>Albanians felt comfortable in an Italian neighborhood because Albanians and Italians are neighbors in Europe. They eat and drink similar foods, and they look somewhat alike. But the two groups have not always mingled peacefully, as shown by life on this corner. At Mike's Deli, an Italian specialty store inside the Arthur Avenue market, three of the countermen are Italian and three are Albanian. All the Albanian employees have adopted Italian-style nicknames -- Milane is Milano, Keno is Nino -- and each speaks some Italian.</p>
        <p>''The Albanians get along fine with the Italian-Americans,'' David Greco, a second-generation Italian-American, said. ''But the Italians from Italy feel as if the Albanians invaded Italy, so they're a bit hostile. One of my guys is constantly calling them ignorant. If I wasn't there, there would be a fight every day.''</p>
        <p>One combatant is Qamil Osmani, who goes by the nickname Ossie. Mr. Osmani, who worked for his country's Ministry of Defense under a previous regime, came to the United States in March to seek political asylum. He settled in Belmont because he knew that Albanians lived there and he had come to know Italians when he was serving in the Albanian Army a decade ago.</p>
        <p>As for the Italian counterman who calls Albanians ignorant, he said: ''I tell him, I'm not coming from the street. I have stayed with much better people than him.''</p>
        <p>Similar skirmishes are played out along Arthur Avenue between 186th and 187th Streets, which has become home to half a dozen Albanian stores, including the Kosova Commerce Corporation, which sells Albanian video and audio tapes and specialty goods; the Gurra Cafe, which serves Albanian cuisine; and the All Star Cafe, where the specials include typical Albanian dishes like  chevapi and beef sausage.</p>
        <p>Even though many Italians have left the neighborhood, they return to buy their prosciutto and osso buco. And some of the vendors of those items are now Albanian. George Dedvukaj, who was born in a small town in Montenegro, owns and runs Giovanni's Restaurant on Arthur Avenue near 186th Street, which serves brick-oven pizza in the Italian style. He bought the business two years ago from another Albanian.</p>
        <p>''I think the Albanians helped the area,'' said Peter Servidio, an Italian-American who owns Peter's Meat Market across the street but moved to Westchester a few years ago. ''They buy a lot, like the Italians used to, by the bucket. And as far as business is concerned, Italians are going to be here for years and years.''</p>
        <p>In Flushing,  Koreatown Becomes Chinese</p>
        <p>The pungent scent of cilantro accompanied Sean Lee, wearing a cut-off T-shirt and a baseball cap, as he wandered through Green Farm, a Korean-owned greenmarket at Main Street and Maple Avenue in Flushing, Queens, furiously directing the movement of crates of watermelons and okra.</p>
        <p>During a break, Mr. Lee, who has lived in the neighborhood for 20 of his 32 years, pointed to the last vestiges of the old Koreatown at the edge of Flushing's shopping district. ''Rose Handicraft was the first Korean store,'' Mr. Lee said, pointing toward a  shop that rents traditional Korean kimonos. ''Over here, the pharmacy is Korean and the stationery store is Korean.''</p>
        <p>In the last five years, many of the names on businesses on the corner have switched from Korean to Chinese, as Korean businesses have moved 10 blocks north to Northern Boulevard.</p>
        <p>''This has become like a second Chinatown,'' Mr. Lee said. ''They're bringing a lot of money from Hong Kong and China and investing it in this neighborhood.''</p>
        <p>Two factors are cited to explain the departure of Korean-owned stores.</p>
        <p>''It's possible they've been pushed out because of the increase in Chinese business,'' said Daeyoung Kim, who is studying Korean-Americans at the Center for Urban Research at the CUNY Graduate Center. ''But it also could be because the Korean stores have become more diversified.'' As business owners diversified the products they sold, Mr. Kim said, they needed more space, and moved to a part of the neighborhood where larger, cheaper stores were still available.</p>
        <p>Green Farm, which opened 20 years ago, is now encircled by Chinese businesses. Across the street is China Trust Bank, housed in a modernistic glass structure. Next door is Tai Pan Bakery. Just above Green Farm, restaurateurs from Hong Kong are putting the finishing touches on East Buffet and Restaurant, an ornate, 17,000-square-foot restaurant and catering hall. The three-floor restaurant, whose decor includes a sweeping marble staircase, a wrought-iron banister from Greece and a 120,000-piece crystal chandelier, is the third establishment created by the group, which also runs a wildly popular Chinese restaurant in Huntington, N.Y.</p>
        <p>''Most Chinese work late hours, and if you get off at 8 p.m., they can't get out there before we are closed,'' said Betty Cheng, one of the partners, explaining the decision to open in Flushing.</p>
        <p>Although East Buffet will concentrate on Chinese food, it will also offer sushi, Korean food and European specialties.</p>
        <p>Local residents remember that East Buffet occupies a site that once housed a successful Korean restaurant called South River, and that a Korean restaurant up the block experienced what Ms. Cheng called ''another Chinese takeover.'' But she said she and her Korean neighbors, like those downstairs at Green Farm, get along well.</p>
        <p>''They speak in their language, which I don't understand,'' she said, ''but they eat at our places and we eat at theirs.''</p>
        <p>But Sung Soo Kim, president of the Korean American Small Business Service Center of New York, is less sanguine.</p>
        <p>''It is a bad thing that's happened here,'' Mr. Kim said. ''Koreans have been pushed out by other ethnic groups. Landlords kick them out to get higher rents. We used to have 80 stores in that area. Now we have three or four.''</p>
        <p>In East Harlem,  Puerto Rican Into Mexican</p>
        <p>Minutes after Mario Olmedo dropped his suitcase on the floor of his cousin's apartment in East Harlem 15 years ago, he heard a knock at the door. When he opened it, he said, three men assaulted him and robbed him of his watch, the only valuable he had brought from his home in Mexico City. Based on the tint of their skin and the cadence of their Spanish, Mr. Olmedo concluded that his attackers were Puerto Rican.</p>
        <p>Whether or not he was correct, the encounter left him feeling that he had entered hostile territory. Until just about six years ago, Spanish Harlem was just one kind of Spanish, Puerto Rican. The corner of 116th Street and Third Avenue, where Mr. Olmedo opened a taco stand 13 years ago, was dominated by Puerto Rican-owned bodegas.</p>
        <p>Puerto Ricans, in turn, had supplanted Italians, who first settled in East Harlem in the 1880's and numbered 80,000 by the 1930's. Conflicts erupted between Italians and Puerto Ricans as early as the 1920's. By 1930, most of the city's Puerto Ricans lived in the neighborhood, and the tensions between the two groups were legendary. Efrain Suarez, owner of Made in Puerto Rico Products, which sells CD's, books, coffee and other items from the island, stood on the corner and pointed east toward Second Avenue.</p>
        <p>''When the Italians were here, Puerto Ricans couldn't go down that block,'' said Mr. Suarez, 55, who has worked in the neighborhood for three decades. ''The farther you went down the street, the worse it got. If you went past Second Avenue, you were beaten up.''</p>
        <p>Until six years ago, it was Mexicans who had to confine their movements to the blocks west of Third Avenue. In the early 1990's, Mr. Olmedo bought a bodega owned by a Puerto Rican in the heart of the contested territory and replaced it with a tacqueria, La Hacienda, possibly the first Mexican restaurant in the neighborhood. ''We used to see a lot of Puerto Ricans chasing Mexican guys down the street to beat them up,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Olmedo now owns a second Mexican restaurant, La Tacquicanda, just down the block, as well as an apartment building. But  it took time to catch on. ''People used to pass by and make nasty faces,'' said his teenage son, Omar, a younger, Americanized replica of his father.</p>
        <p>That has changed, and no one chases Mexicans away from the corner anymore. After Mr. Olmedo opened his first restaurant, other Mexican immigrants started asking for advice on starting their own. Along 116th Street between Second and Third Avenue, Mexicans have made inroads. Amid 14 Puerto Rican flags hung from windows and fire escapes are at least eight Mexican-owned stores, among them Mexico Shoes, Azteca Unisex barbershop, Taco Mix taqueria and the Mexico Discount Center, a 99-cent store.</p>
        <p>A vast majority of recent Mexican immigrants to El Barrio came from Puebla, a state in northern Mexico that has been battered by economic troubles and natural disasters.</p>
        <p>Mexicans feel more welcome today. As if to prove the point, Mr. Olmedo gestured toward the back of his restaurant, where three men were eating together. ''One is Mexican, one is Dominican and one is Puerto Rican,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But resentment still festers in the hearts of some Puerto Ricans, who feel they have lost control.</p>
        <p>''Puerto Ricans still consider El Barrio 'la cuna,' the cradle of Puerto Rican experience,'' said Henry Calderon, president of the East Harlem Chamber of Commerce.</p>
        <p>Pepe Castillo, a Puerto Rican musician who works at Made in Puerto Rico, stood at  116th Street and Third Avenue gazing east, his brow furrowed as he extolled the virtues of ''hard working Mexicans'' who now dominate the block. ''And it all started with the guy selling tacos on the corner,'' he said, in a tone tinged with loss.</p>
        <p>Mr. Suarez sighed.</p>
        <p>''What can you do?'' he said. ''The Puerto Ricans created a vacuum here. The original Puerto Ricans who came here have now retired, moved to Rockland County, Florida or back to Puerto Rico. Their children are professionals.''</p>
        <p>But, he added, ''there is no decent housing here for them.''</p>
        <p>And though the mix on the corner has changed, the tension is nowhere near as fierce as it was when Italians and Puerto Ricans were the two groups.</p>
        <p>''There is the fact that we would prefer it to remain Spanish Harlem,'' Mr. Suarez said. ''And if the Mexicans keep coming, it will be Spanish Harlem. It will be a different kind of Spanish, but still Spanish Harlem.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
