<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Middlesboro Journal; Relishing Nicotine, Come What May</title>
    <meta content="Y30SMOK" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218849"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Smoking and Tobacco</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nicotine</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Chewing Tobacco</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Snuff</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Appalachian Region</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Southern States (US)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Rocky Mountain States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kilborn, Peter T</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Smoking and Tobacco</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501EFDD153DF933A05754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1235" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Middlesboro Journal; Relishing Nicotine, Come What May</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER T. KILBORN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kilborn, Peter T</byline>
      <dateline>MIDDLESBORO, Ky.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Use of tobacco, much of it in</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>At Cuz's Tobacco Outlet, one peculiar item looks like a length of brown rope folded into the shape of a large lollipop. A customer can grip it like a lollipop, and perhaps some do. Most, however, break off a bit and chew it a while, spit, and have another bit.</p>
        <p>This item is called a twist. A section of wall is packed with different brands of cellophane-wrapped Red Ox twists, Hornet twists and Grizzly Sweet twists. Places like Cuz's also sell moist and dry snuff; plugs, which resemble dense black brownies; Apple Jack, Trophy and Rough Country chewing tobacco; Red Man totems, which are wrapped like candy bars; Bugler, Stoker's and Zig-Zag loose-leaf tobacco for roll-your-own cigarettes; and carton upon carton of cigarettes that cost as little as half as much as a ''premium'' brand, like Marlboro.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>At Cuz's Tobacco Outlet, one peculiar item looks like a length of brown rope folded into the shape of a large lollipop. A customer can grip it like a lollipop, and perhaps some do. Most, however, break off a bit and chew it a while, spit, and have another bit.</p>
        <p>This item is called a twist. A section of wall is packed with different brands of cellophane-wrapped Red Ox twists, Hornet twists and Grizzly Sweet twists. Places like Cuz's also sell moist and dry snuff; plugs, which resemble dense black brownies; Apple Jack, Trophy and Rough Country chewing tobacco; Red Man totems, which are wrapped like candy bars; Bugler, Stoker's and Zig-Zag loose-leaf tobacco for roll-your-own cigarettes; and carton upon carton of cigarettes that cost as little as half as much as a ''premium'' brand, like Marlboro.</p>
        <p>In these days of indisputable evidence of health hazards, of multibillion-dollar settlements against the leading cigarette makers, of declining smoking rates nationwide, the consumers hustling into Cuz's are a remarkable sight.</p>
        <p>The use of tobacco, much of it in smokeless forms like snuff, plugs and chewing tobacco, remains firmly entrenched in Appalachia and in parts of the South and the Rocky Mountain states.</p>
        <p>Along the main drags of the pillowy, kudzu-sculptured Cumberland hills of Appalachian Kentucky, Tennessee and Virginia and in West Virginia, shops like Cuz's are rural siblings of the wood-paneled pipe and cigar emporiums that survive in many cities. These stores, and the convenience stores that sell wide varieties of cheap tobacco products, are as common as churches.</p>
        <p>They cater to older farmers and coal miners with plugs, twists and chewing tobacco; to younger customers with moist snuff -- the one growing segment of the national tobacco market -- and to both with discount cigarettes.</p>
        <p>Except for the women who buy the cigarettes, the stores' customers are men. ''Men don't like women to chew tobacco,'' said Mable Partin, a manager at Cuz's. ''You spit with all of it.''</p>
        <p>The shops sustain a subculture that still relishes nicotine, come what may.</p>
        <p>Workplace smoking bans? Paying $16.06 for a carton of discount Maverick cigarettes and $3.06 for a pouch of Tennessee Chew, Earl Brimm explained that he works in a factory where he cannot smoke.</p>
        <p>One chew lasts about an hour and a half, he said, and ''it stops the craving for cigarettes.'' Spit, unlike smoke, has not been an issue at work. ''I always have a box with some sawdust in it,'' Mr. Brimm said.</p>
        <p>Cancer, strokes and heart attacks? ''I had a heart attack,'' said Gillis Noe, 70, who was buying some twists and a $17.98 carton containing 12 three-ounce packs of Taylor's Pride chewing tobacco. ''It destroyed 40 percent of my heart. I've had four bypasses.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Noe said his health problems plunged him into a funk. ''Smoking was took away from me,'' he said, ''and everything I like to eat. I can't get much to enjoy.'' So his cardiologist in Nashville let him run the risk of mouth cancer. ''He told me to chew all I want to chew,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Tobacco consumption nationwide has been dropping for decades. Smoking per capita plunged from 4,345 cigarettes a year in 1990 to 2,146 last year, the United States Department of Agriculture has reported. The Centers for Disease Control and Prevention says that the number of adults who smoke has dropped from 42 percent 35 years ago to 25 percent today. Use of chewing tobacco has declined even more.</p>
        <p>Consumption of smokeless tobacco has been sliding for years, said Robert Maples, president of the Smokeless Tobacco Council, but it remains a sizable business, accounting for $2.3 billion a year in sales because of its strength in communities like Middlesboro.</p>
        <p>And one widely used form of smokeless tobacco, the moist Copenhagen, Skoal and Kodiak snuff that comes in a tin the size and shape of a hockey puck, is still going strong. From 1990 to 1999, the United States Department of Agriculture reports, annual snuff production surged from 46 million pounds to 63 million.</p>
        <p>One source of tobacco's perseverance is Kentucky, where 31 percent of the adults smoke, the highest rate in the nation. Another is West Virginia, which has the highest per capita use of smokeless tobacco.</p>
        <p>While 1 percent or less of adult men in New York, Connecticut, New Jersey, Massachusetts and Rhode Island use it, the C.D.C. says, nearly 16 percent use it in West Virginia, 9 percent in Tennessee and 8.5 percent in Kentucky.</p>
        <p>Compared to most of the rest of the country, the Appalachian states have also been reluctant to curb an industry that underpins their economies. Kentucky and Tennessee are the nation's second-  and third-largest tobacco producers, after North Carolina, and the leading producers of the leaves used for smokeless tobacco.</p>
        <p>To keep it cheap, Kentucky charges an excise tax of three cents on a pack of cigarettes, Tennessee 13 cents, and West Virginia 17 cents.</p>
        <p>Connecticut, New York and New Jersey all tax cigarettes at least 50 cents a pack. Alaska's tax is $1.</p>
        <p>Virginia, Kentucky and West Virginia are also among nine states that do not tax smokeless tobacco at all. Earlier this year, the West Virginia Legislature foiled the efforts of Gov. Cecil H. Underwood, a Republican, to tax snuff and chewing tobacco.</p>
        <p>Like the industry itself, tobacco users around here no longer pretend that smoking and chewing tobacco or dipping snuff are harmless, and any who do are reminded of the dangers with every item they buy.</p>
        <p>A 16-ounce bag of Apple chewing tobacco warns, ''This product may cause gum disease and tooth loss.'' The wrapping on King B twist reads, ''This product is not a safe alternative to cigarettes.''</p>
        <p>Instead of denying the risks, users defend their habit as an expression of personal liberty. Ms. Partin, who is 43, said she would like very much to stop smoking, but she enjoys it. ''I've smoked since I was 8 years old,'' she said. ''My mother died from emphysema from smoking. She was 60. That was her choice.''</p>
        <p>Whatever the national trends, the tobacco stores around here say they are doing good business.</p>
        <p>Eleven miles north of Middlesboro, in Pineville, Glen and Shannon Sexton have an auto repair shop. Next door was a tobacco shop where business was slow because, they figured, the owner had lost interest and kept irregular hours. ''So we bought the place,'' Ms. Sexton said.</p>
        <p>Clean and fully stocked, the shop is thriving. But the Sextons are a little troubled about their new venture.</p>
        <p>''We don't even smoke,'' Mr. Sexton said. ''Or chew,'' Ms. Sexton added. ''We don't know if we did a good deed or not,'' Mr. Sexton said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
