<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Deep-Water Discovery; Virtually Unknown a Few Years Ago, The Stonington Red Is Catching On</title>
    <meta content="30SHRI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218642"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fishing, Commercial</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shrimp</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bomster, Bill</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wojtas, Joe</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shrimp</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fishing, Commercial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E7D91E3AF933A05754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1934" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Deep-Water Discovery; Virtually Unknown a Few Years Ago, The Stonington Red Is Catching On</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE WOJTAS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wojtas, Joe</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on royal red shrimp, species of deep-water shrimp known as Stonington Reds, that are being caught by just a handful of boats in Northeast and only one in Connecticut, the Neptune, run by scallop fisherman Bill Bomster; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FROM November to June, customers hound Jo Bomster of Stonington Seafood Harvesters for what the locals call ''Stonington Reds.''</p>
        <p>''They think we're hiding it in here. They think we've got secret pockets or something,'' said Ms. Bomster, whose family operates a wholesale and retail seafood operation near the Town Dock in the borough.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FROM November to June, customers hound Jo Bomster of Stonington Seafood Harvesters for what the locals call ''Stonington Reds.''</p>
        <p>''They think we're hiding it in here. They think we've got secret pockets or something,'' said Ms. Bomster, whose family operates a wholesale and retail seafood operation near the Town Dock in the borough.</p>
        <p>What people are clamoring for are royal red shrimp, a species that lives in such deep water that they are caught by just a handful of boats in the Northeast and only one in Connecticut. The shrimp was almost unheard of before 1995, but since its discovery word of the shrimp has spread. They have increasingly been turning up on dinner tables and in restaurants around the region, where, chefs say, the Red's higher fat content make them sweeter and more tender than Gulf Coast shrimp.</p>
        <p>The shrimp can be found at the Daniel Packer Inne in Mystic and on the fruits de mer platter, as a fancy garnish, or as part of a ceviche in a large martini glass at London Lennie's in Forest Hills, N.Y. They're being sold at Citarella, a gourmet food store in Manhattan and the Hamptons. And at Rent A Chef, an upscale fish market with four locations in northwestern Connecticut, they're being bought by customers, many of them New Yorkers who have weekend homes in the area.</p>
        <p>''We buy 200 to 300 pounds at a time,'' said Carol Herman, the owner of Rent A Chef. ''One lady buys four or five pounds a week from us.''</p>
        <p>The shrimp became available in the state out of pure economic necessity, when Ms. Bomster's husband, Bill, a scallop fisherman who was worried about his dwindling catch, decided to search for another way to make a living from the sea.</p>
        <p>He obtained a $118,000 federal grant to look for scarlet shrimp, which were known to live in deep water off the coast of New England. With stocks of cod and other popular species overfished, the National Marine Fisheries Service was giving grants to Northeast fishermen to find and market so-called underutilized species.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bomster headed to the Atlantic with his crew and also on board was a scientist from the University of Connecticut to help identify whatever Bomster found. He found few scarlet shrimp, but thousands of its cousin, the royal red shrimp. When he and others tasted the surprise catch, they knew they were on to something.</p>
        <p>Distributors such as Gambardella Wholesale Fish Dealers of Stonington and East Haven, and Emerald Seafood in New York City's Fulton Fish Market, are trying to get the word out about the shrimp to restaurants and fish markets in the tri-state area. Greater demand may convince other fishermen to make the $50,000 to $100,000 initial investment for the nets, gear, freezers and other processing equipment needed to catch and process the shrimp.</p>
        <p>''People love them. Especially the high-end restaurants. They remember them from last year and they ask for them,'' said Thomas Flanigan,  president of Emerald Seafood. ''I could sell them all year long if I could get them.''</p>
        <p>But Alan Chaplaski, captain of the Stonington-based fishing boat, Neptune, who is renting Mr. Bomster's shrimping gear, can only fish the area from June through November because it is reserved for offshore lobster gear the rest of the year. Mr. Chaplaski, the only Connecticut fisherman catching the shrimp, would be unable to tow a shrimp net through the area during those times without damaging lobster pots.</p>
        <p>Michael Gambardella, whose company sells about 20,000 pounds of the shrimp each year, said it has been a little bit of a battle to introduce a product most people have never seen. Much of the demand has been local and distributors have been trying to introduce the shrimp to the rest of the state and to New York.</p>
        <p>''We've been doing it in bits and pieces,'' Mr. Gambardella said.</p>
        <p>Nancy Balcom, the extension educator with the Sea Grant College program at the University of Connecticut in Groton, helped write the report about Mr. Bomster's grant results. She said there are not enough shrimp in the area Mr. Bomster explored to support a large number of boats. She is not surprised more fishermen have not started to catch the shrimp because of the expense of new gear and the uncertainty of finding new areas.</p>
        <p>If the popularity of red shrimp increases, Ms. Balcom said more fishermen may decide to catch the shrimp, especially on a part-time basis. She said some red shrimp are also caught in the deep water of the Gulf of Mexico, but they are not sent to other parts of the country. In both places, they are found in about 50-degree water.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bomster received the grant to locate areas where scarlet shrimp and other deep-water species live and do a marketing study and a scientific analysis. The goal of the study was to determine if there were enough scarlet shrimp to sustain a commercial fleet.</p>
        <p>The grant paid for deep-water nets, almost two miles of wire need to tow it and other gear. It also paid for his crew, fuel, food, ice and the salary of a scientist who accompanied the crew. Without the grant, Mr. Bomster would not have been able to afford the search.</p>
        <p>''We didn't have to worry about making money. We could move around and try different depths and different places,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bomster and the crew of the Patty Jo made three 10-day trips in 1995, covering an area from Block Island, R.I. to Virginia. Mr. Bomster hauled up few of the scarlet shrimp. But what he did find in his nets were hundreds of pounds of royal red shrimp. The shrimp, which can be as long as 10 inches, were mostly found in a 20-mile-long by half-mile wide stretch of the Continental Shelf about 100 miles southeast of Stonington. The focus of the grant quickly shifted to the royal red shrimp and the results were reported in a detailed booklet.</p>
        <p>Today, the 50-year-old Mr. Chaplaski fishes that same 1,200-foot-deep stretch of ocean, leasing the gear and nets from Mr. Bomster, who returned to scalloping when that fishery improved.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chaplaski and his three-man crew begins the four-day shrimp trips by steaming 12 hours to the fishing grounds. His crew works long hours with only a few short breaks for sleep. With no freezer capability on board, he must put the shrimp on ice and get them back to the dealer before they spoil.</p>
        <p>He and his crew spend four days in port unloading shrimp, doing repairs and loading supplies before heading out to sea again.</p>
        <p>Catching red shrimp is hard work for the crew. After they haul the bottom trawling net on board, they chill the shrimp and break off their heads by hand. They sort, wash and place the shrimp in a solution that prevents unsightly black spots from forming on their shells. They then put the shrimp back on ice. At the dock the crew has to remove the shrimp from the ice, wash and sort through them on a conveyor belt, weeding out damaged ones. On a typical trip, the crew will handle 80,000 shrimp.</p>
        <p>The shrimp also move around the fishing grounds. This forces Mr. Chaplaski, who had been fishing his whole life and has associate degrees in science, engineering and commercial fishing, to make an educated guess about where they have gone.</p>
        <p>''Learning their spots is a trade secret,'' he said with a smile.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chaplaski said he knows of only two other boats, one each from New Jersey and Massachusetts, that catch red shrimp. He said there might soon be another Connecticut boat joining the group.</p>
        <p>''It's a lot of work and people are making money doing other things,'' said Mr. Chaplaski, who catches squid, whiting and fluke the rest of the year. ''Some people are also not as adventurous. They like doing something more conservative.''</p>
        <p>He decided to lease the equipment from Mr. Bomster in 1997 when fishing became poor in the summer.</p>
        <p>''It looked like something good. I said, ''This is a chance for me to get in on the ground floor,'' he said, referring to boats that typically flock to a new fishery once they see others being successful.</p>
        <p>Ms. Balcom of the University of Connecticut said there has to be a steady supply to make the shrimp popular with consumers.</p>
        <p>''If you can't meet the demand continuously, people tend to lose interest in a product,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Balcom said a scientist at the University of Connecticut is hoping to obtain some live red shrimp from Mr. Chaplaski so he can attempt to raise them in an aquaculture setting. That could result in a more steady supply.</p>
        <p>Mr. and Ms. Bomster freeze some of the shrimp and sell it to local restaurants and individual consumers. The shrimp is also sold at the Stonington Farmer's Market every Saturday morning and sells out quickly. Consumers can also buy it off the dock when it arrives.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gambardella is selling it to restaurants and fish markets along the Connecticut coast. He has also shipped some to Spain and is trying to break into the trendy Los Angeles market.</p>
        <p>Michael Stafford, the executive chef at the Daniel Packer Inne in Mystic, has been serving the shrimp ever since Mr. Bomster first caught them.</p>
        <p>''Everyone who has them just loves them,'' he said. ''On the menu I say they are 'amazingly sweet and incredibly tender.' Nobody has ever called me a liar.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Stafford serves the shrimp lightly sauteed with sundried tomato pesto, fresh Swiss chard, roasted garlic, Chardonnay and angel hair pasta. Others say the shrimp are so flavorful they eat them plain.</p>
        <p>Royal red shrimp cooks much quicker than Gulf shrimp. Searing takes just 90 seconds. Mr. Chaplaski drops them in boiling water and then removes them when the pot boils for a second time. It's easy to overcook the shrimp, turning them to mush.</p>
        <p>Some factors preventing the shrimp from making a big splash have been the limited supply and higher price. Without expensive freezing equipment on board, boats have to return quickly to sell the shrimp. This also limits the money boats can earn.</p>
        <p>For the shrimp to really catch on with the public, Mr. Flanigan from Emerald Seafood, said the price would have to drop about 30 percent from it current $8 to $9 a pound.</p>
        <p>''It's a nice item, but it's still pricey,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gambardella said that if a few high-profile New York chefs tried the Stonington Reds, they would become the next big thing.</p>
        <p>''But we'll get it to the next level. I'm confident we'll do it,'' Mr. Gambardella said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
