<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Summer Veteran Gets New Life</title>
    <meta content="30SIMO$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218607"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Westport Country Playhouse</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Woodward, Joanne</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Simonson, Robert</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/Companies and Organizations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/Companies and Organizations/Westport Country Playhouse</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00EFDF113AF933A05754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1657" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Summer Veteran Gets New Life</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT SIMONSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Simonson, Robert</byline>
      <dateline>WESTPORT, Conn.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Westport Country Playhouse, summer stock theater in Westport, Conn, which is being revived with help of new leadership team headed by actress Joanne Woodward; team hopes to honor classics, foster new material, retain summer season and preserve building's character while transforming it into up-to-date theater; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE audience buzzes about, taking in the cool New England summer air before excitedly filing into the theater. There is not a ticket to be had. Looking at the program, it's no wonder. The cast includes Joanne Woodward, Paul Newman, Swoosie Kurtz, James Naughton and Paul Rudd.</p>
        <p>Sold-out productions, superior theater talent, Yankee environs -- looks like another night at the Williamstown Theater Festival in Massachusetts. But no. Earlier this month that was the scene at the Westport Country Playhouse, a fabled monument to summer stock whose glittering past has been somewhat dulled by a recent string of lackluster seasons.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE audience buzzes about, taking in the cool New England summer air before excitedly filing into the theater. There is not a ticket to be had. Looking at the program, it's no wonder. The cast includes Joanne Woodward, Paul Newman, Swoosie Kurtz, James Naughton and Paul Rudd.</p>
        <p>Sold-out productions, superior theater talent, Yankee environs -- looks like another night at the Williamstown Theater Festival in Massachusetts. But no. Earlier this month that was the scene at the Westport Country Playhouse, a fabled monument to summer stock whose glittering past has been somewhat dulled by a recent string of lackluster seasons.</p>
        <p>Ms. Woodward's name is all over the playhouse's programs these days. Not only did she act in A. R. Gurney's ''Ancestral Voices'' that night, but she directed the season's opening production, ''The Constant Wife'' by W. Somerset Maugham, and she is the co-chairwoman of the playhouse's artistic advisory council. In fact, Ms. Woodward, who lives in the area, is part of a recently created leadership team that hopes to bring the theater into a new era artistically (a fresh commitment to first-time works), financially (a multimillion-dollar development plan) and architecturally (a revitalized facility).</p>
        <p>''Westport Country Playhouse seemed to have sunk into an old-fashioned summer-stock theater idea,'' said June Havoc, whose own acting career in the area has ranged from ''They Knew What They Wanted'' in 1946 to ''Annie'' in 1983 at the playhouse, as well as shows at another well-known Westport institution, Lucille Lortel's White Barn Theater. ''I think the playhouse has been timid up until now. Audiences have been panting for new plays.''</p>
        <p>The recent plans have aroused interest -- subscriptions are up, by nearly 50 percent, to more than 5,700 -- and there is little question about the impact of Ms. Woodward's presence. ''I think I have a name value and that was helpful in getting this thing to coalesce,'' the actress cheerfully allowed in an interview. ''I love theater. So when this opportunity came along, I thought, 'Why not?' ''</p>
        <p>Clearly she had a hand in the season's biggest casting coup, Mr. Newman's appearance in ''Ancestral Voices.'' Ms. Woodward said she had no trouble persuading her husband to appear in Mr. Gurney's family drama in which actors are armed with scripts. Asked about the chances of Mr. Newman's starring next season in a standard play, sans book, she laughed heartily. ''No, believe me, this is the best way for Paul to be onstage -- with a script in his hand!''</p>
        <p>When Ms. Woodward and Mr. Newman don't come to the theater, the theater comes to them. ''We bring in actors and then we have to find places for them to stay,'' Ms. Woodward said. ''I've found that my barn is full of actors. I've had actors sleeping on sofas. They come over to swim. It's become a boardinghouse. I'm the campus, if you will.''</p>
        <p>Attempting to reinvent the playhouse is in many ways a balancing act. The team -- Anne Keefe, the co-chairwoman with Ms. Woodward; Elissa O. Getto, the C.E.O. and executive director, and Janice Muirhead, the artistic manager -- hopes to honor the classics while fostering new material; retain the summer season cherished by loyal patrons while eventually expanding to a year-round schedule; and preserve the folksy, inviting character of the building while transforming it into an up-to-date theater.</p>
        <p>The group has already leaped its first financial hurdle -- a $1.2 million fund-raising drive to pay for setting up the administration, salaries and consultants. (The budget for the current summer season is slightly more than $2 million.) The next test is likely to be a $10 million-plus campaign to renovate the theater. Ms. Muirhead said they intend to preserve the flavor of the one-time barn, well known for its wraparound porch and red-cushioned pews. ''But,'' she added, ''if we are to present in that space and get wonderful people to perform for us, we have to have very good systems.'' Though the sound system has been upgraded, the wish list includes renovated heating, better lighting and an orchestra pit.</p>
        <p>The hope is that eventually the playhouse's future will do justice to its past.</p>
        <p>That past is a glorious one. In 1930, Laurence Langner, co-founder of the Theater Guild, and his wife, Armina Marshall, residents of nearby Weston, bought an old red barn along the Post Road in Westport, then a bucolic summer community. Only a decade earlier, F. Scott and Zelda Fitzgerald had holed up in a farmhouse in Westport to escape the distractions of the city. Langner hired the theatrical designer Cleon Throckmorton to convert the barn into a working theater.</p>
        <p>The Westport Country Playhouse opened in 1931 with Dion Boucicault's ''Streets of New York'' starring Dorothy Gish. The play transferred to New York, a pattern that would be repeated over the years, perhaps most famously with William Inge's ''Come Back, Little Sheba'' in 1949 and Leonard Gershe's ''Butterflies Are Free'' 20 years later. If the Westport's plays weren't always memorable, the performers usually were: Ethel Barrymore, Eva Le Gallienne, Bert Lahr, Tyrone Power, Paul Robeson, Henry Fonda, Jessica Tandy, Tallulah Bankhead.</p>
        <p>In recent decades, however, the playhouse has faced difficulties. The era of the grand theater stars passed, hurried along by the ascent of film and television. At the same time, the straw-hat circuit, largely dependent on touring vehicles and increasingly forced to compete with other forms of entertainment, dwindled to a handful of stages. All the while, real estate values in Westport were rising steadily, rendering the property vulnerable to developers.</p>
        <p>Though the playhouse has persevered, few would say it has thrived. Recent seasons typically presented familiar, if faded, performers from television and retreads of Broadway and Off Broadway successes.</p>
        <p>''People thought that a change had to be made,'' Ms. Keefe said, ''that some serious revitalization had to happen if we wanted to keep this going.''</p>
        <p>The opportunity came when James McKenzie, who joined the playhouse as manager in 1959 and  ran it for 41 years, resigned in January. The four women who now run the theater are complimentary of Mr. McKenzie's long tenure, and particularly applaud his ability to keep the playhouse afloat almost solely on box-office receipts, but it was apparent that a new blueprint was needed. Ms. Woodward and Ms. Keefe, already playhouse board members, decided in January -- with the backing of the board -- to become co-chairwomen of the newly formed artistic advisory council. Ms. Muirhead was invited to join the theater in February; Ms. Getto was brought aboard in March.</p>
        <p>''Just as we have different phases of our lives, so do institutions,'' Ms. Keefe said. ''I think there is an excitement about the fact that it isn't going to be the same-old, same-old.''</p>
        <p>The four other productions for Westport's 2000 summer season, which began on June 12 and runs through Sept. 9, involve three plays and one musical: ''Orson's Shadow'' by the actor and playwright Austin Pendleton (it completed its run on July 8); ''Triangles for Two'' by David Wiltse (it closes on Saturday); ''Morphic Resonance'' by Katherine Burger, which was seen last year at the Donmar Warehouse in London (Aug. 7-19), and ''Nicolette and Aucassin,'' a musical based on an ancient French tale, with music by David Friedman and book and lyrics by Peter Kellogg (Aug. 28-Sept. 9).</p>
        <p>Instead of calling on television stars for these productions, the playhouse seems to be drawing its talent from seasoned theater circles. Jayne Atkinson (a Tony Award nominee this year for ''The Rainmaker'') stars in ''Triangles''; Mr. Naughton, an actor who also directs (''The Price,'' first at Williamstown and then on Broadway last season) will direct ''Morphic Resonance.''</p>
        <p>Another change involves the playhouse's relationship with other theaters. In the past, Westport would have been a partner on a show with, perhaps, the Cape Playhouse in Dennis, Mass., another survivor of summer stock's heyday. This year, ''Orson's Shadow'' (which began life with the Steppenwolf Theater Company in Chicago) is a co-production with the Williamstown Theater Festival -- a relationship Ms. Woodward, who has directed there, hopes will continue. The comic drama (a meditation on fame and art, as told through a semi-fictional encounter between Orson Welles and Laurence Olivier), has attracted the attention of New York producers, Ms. Woodward said, and may be the first Westport production in many years to go on to Manhattan.</p>
        <p>''Joanne's intention is to make Westport more than just a summer stock theater,'' said Michael Ritchie, producer of the Williamstown Theater Festival. ''She wants to develop new pieces and challenge audiences.''</p>
        <p>Each of the theater's four governing members has strong ties to the region. Ms. Woodward has had a home in the area since the early 1960's. Ms. Muirhead was director of production at the nearby Long Wharf Theater in New Haven (where she worked with both Ms. Woodward and Ms. Keefe). And Ms. Getto, recently president of the Cincinnati Arts Association, was a Connecticut resident for 17 years. They are also -- it is hard not to notice -- all women, as are the theater's longtime general manager, Julie Monahan, and the president of the theater's board, Elisabeth Morten.</p>
        <p>Does an administration composed entirely of women make a difference? ''I think in many institutions,'' Ms. Muirhead said, ''women are sometimes not heard. That is not the case here.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Woodward agreed. Referring to the feminist ideas in ''The Constant Wife,'' she laughed and asked, ''Didn't you just see the play I directed?''</p>
        <p>THEATER Robert Simonson is the editor of Playbill On-Line. His play ''Cafe Society'' will be presented this fall by the Mill 6 Cooperative in Boston.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Robert Simonson is the editor of Playbill On-Line. His play ''Cafe Society'' will be presented this fall by the Mill 6 Cooperative in Boston.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
