<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Yankees Lose Pitching Duel As Bullpen Misfires</title>
    <meta content="30YANK" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218974"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Minnesota Twins</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olney, Buster</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Minnesota Twins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DEFDA123DF933A05754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1015" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Yankees Lose Pitching Duel As Bullpen Misfires</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olney, Buster</byline>
      <dateline>MINNEAPOLIS, July 29</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Minnesota Twins defeat New York Yankees, 6-2; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Yankees were swinging and missing a whole lot against the Twins' Eric Milton tonight, and Roger Clemens figured he could not concede anything, not a single pitch. For more than half the game, there were no hits by either side.</p>
        <p>Clemens, who sometimes throws upward of 130 pitches, was tired after seven innings, after 109 pitches, and usually reliable middle relievers assumed the slim lead Clemens fostered.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Yankees were swinging and missing a whole lot against the Twins' Eric Milton tonight, and Roger Clemens figured he could not concede anything, not a single pitch. For more than half the game, there were no hits by either side.</p>
        <p>Clemens, who sometimes throws upward of 130 pitches, was tired after seven innings, after 109 pitches, and usually reliable middle relievers assumed the slim lead Clemens fostered.</p>
        <p>Usually reliable. But not this time. Five relievers and five trips to the mound by Manager Joe Torre and the pitching coach Mel Stottlemyre were required to get three outs, and by the time that happened, the Twins had scored all their runs in a 6-2 victory.</p>
        <p>Ramiro Mendoza (7-4), who allowed the tying and go-ahead hits, was charged with the loss. Milton, the former Yankees farmhand traded to Minnesota in the Chuck Knoblauch deal two years ago, struck out 10 over eight innings and prevailed in his exceptional duel with Clemens.</p>
        <p>The Yankees' Paul O'Neill believes Milton's stuff was the best by any left-hander he has seen this year. ''That's about as good as it gets for a left-hander,'' O'Neill said.</p>
        <p>Chuck Knoblauch and Scott Brosius sat out with injuries, and David Justice was given the day off by Torre, whose lineup had a bootleg quality. Jose Vizcaino was the leadoff hitter, Glenallen Hill was the designated hitter, Ryan Thompson started in left field and Clay Bellinger played third.</p>
        <p>Milton reigned over the Yankees in the first three innings, like a Little Leaguer who reached puberty faster than his opponents, striking out two in the first, two in the second and three more in the third inning. All of the strikeouts were on swings and misses, on failed attempts to hit his 94-mile-an-hour fastball. Milton reached a two-ball count just once in the first three innings.</p>
        <p>Milton, who threw a no-hitter against Anaheim last September, had no-hit stuff, similar to the left-handed repertory David Wells had when he pitched against the Twins May 17, 1998. ''Milton was just mowing people down and daring you to hit him,'' Torre said.</p>
        <p>Clemens was almost as good, his fastball sizzling, his splitter diving, his slider spinning tightly and veering; Milton said it was as good as he had seen from Clemens. He walked three batters in the second, refusing to give in, and threw 35 pitches in that inning. Neither pitcher had allowed a hit through four innings.</p>
        <p>Before each pitch, Clemens stood erect on the mound, looming like a skyscraper. He holds his pitching hand and glove in front of his face as he prepares to throw each pitch. His cap, drawn low on his forehead, casts a half-moon shadow over that part of his face the hitter can see, the area around his eyes; it looks as if Clemens has donned war paint.</p>
        <p>Milton stood slightly to the third-base side of the pitching rubber, turned at a 45-degree angle to the hitter, his glove held at his right hip, and his Popeye forearms covered in sweat. A gold neck chain often escaped the confines of his jersey, hanging over the collar of his uniform.</p>
        <p>Milton set down the Yankees in order in the fifth, needing only 10 pitches, but with two outs in the bottom of the fifth, the Twins' Cristian Guzman -- the 36th batter of the game -- lined a single.</p>
        <p>Jose Vizcaino had the Yankees' first hit with one out in the top of the sixth, a single.  And the Yankees scored two runs in that inning, the runs batted in by Derek Jeter and O'Neill. Clemens shut out the Twins in the sixth and seventh, but he was shortening his motion, and he was tired, and Torre pulled him.</p>
        <p>Mike Stanton, who had not allowed an earned run in 11 appearances, allowed a leadoff single and, with one out, a ground-rule double. The switch-hitting Denny Hocking was announced as the pinch-hitter for Corey Koskie, and Torre called for Mendoza, explaining afterward that he just thought Stanton's stuff was not sharp. ''That's an excuse,'' Stanton said. ''I just didn't get the job done. Bottom line.''</p>
        <p>It was Mendoza's first appearance since June 24 -- he was placed on the disabled list the next day -- and he walked Hocking to load the bases. Mendoza struck out the pinch-hitter Midre Cummings. Two outs. But Jacque Jones laced a single to right, scoring the tying runs; Jones pumped a fist as he rounded first.</p>
        <p>''He gave me the ball, and I felt good,'' said Mendoza, before adding that his control was suffering, that he had not thrown in three days and was throwing his changeup too low.</p>
        <p>The rookie catcher Chad Moeller hit a sinking liner to left, where Ryan Thompson charged and dove for the ball, trying to make the catch that would end the inning and keep the score tied. But he missed the ball, which bounced past him and all the way to the wall, and Moeller sprinted around the bases and crossed home plate before the relay from the outfield for his first major league home run. ''If I'm going to go for it, I've got to catch it,'' Thompson said.</p>
        <p>The Yankees would make three more pitching changes before the inning ended. This was the kind of loss, Torre said, that stung.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>Reliever JEFF NELSON walked the only batter he faced in the eighth inning tonight, and later, Nelson acknowledged he was perturbed that Manager JOE TORRE took him out after only one hitter. ''I was frustrated, I was upset that I came out,'' Nelson said. ''It is frustrating.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
