<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Clinton Defies Republicans On Buyback Of Weapons</title>
    <meta content="Y30GUN$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218888"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Firearms</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gun Control</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Housing and Urban Development Department</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dao, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Firearms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gun Control</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E0D8153DF933A05754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="740" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Clinton Defies Republicans On Buyback Of Weapons</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES DAO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dao, James</byline>
      <dateline>CLEVELAND, July 29</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Clinton, plans to defy Congressional Republicans and continue paying local governments to buy back guns from private owners; plans statement rejecting stand of House budget appropriators that Housing and Urban Development Department lacks authority to fund program, aimed at reducing gun violence around public housing projects (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Defying Congressional Republicans, the Clinton administration says it will continue paying local governments to buy back guns from private owners despite orders from House budget appropriators to end the program.</p>
        <p>Known as Buyback America, the $15 million program is intended to reduce gun violence in cities, particularly around public housing projects, by helping the local police and housing authorities purchase firearms for about $50 each, no questions asked.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Defying Congressional Republicans, the Clinton administration says it will continue paying local governments to buy back guns from private owners despite orders from House budget appropriators to end the program.</p>
        <p>Known as Buyback America, the $15 million program is intended to reduce gun violence in cities, particularly around public housing projects, by helping the local police and housing authorities purchase firearms for about $50 each, no questions asked.</p>
        <p>Since President Clinton unveiled the program last September, 70 cities, including San Francisco, Hartford, Atlanta, Baltimore, Newark and Houston, have spent $3.5 million to buy more than 17,300 guns, most of which have been destroyed.</p>
        <p>But from its inception, the program has been sharply criticized by the National Rifle Association and by opponents of gun control in Congress, as a waste of money that leaves guns in the hands of criminals.</p>
        <p>In June, Representative James T. Walsh, a Republican of Syracuse,  chairman of the House appropriations subcommittee that oversees the Department of Housing and Urban Development, told the agency's  secretary, Andrew M. Cuomo, to stop financing the program.</p>
        <p>In a letter to Mr. Cuomo, Mr. Walsh said that existing law did not authorize such spending, a position supported by the General Accounting Office, a nonpartisan Congressional research agency. Programs in at least 30 cities have been put on hold because of the dispute.</p>
        <p>But in a statement he plans to release on Sunday, President Clinton asserts that the housing department has clear legal authority to finance the program, which he contends will help prevent ''an untold number of gun accidents, suicides and crimes.''</p>
        <p>''Despite HUD's clear authority to carry out this important program, the gun lobby and other opponents of common-sense gun safety measures continue to challenge this initiative,'' Mr. Clinton says in the statement. ''Congress should put the public safety interests of American families above those of the gun lobby and support these efforts instead of working to undermine them.''</p>
        <p>The fight over Buyback America comes at a time when gun control is playing an increasingly prominent role in the fall elections. The N.R.A. and the gun industry, as well as gun control groups, are promising to spend record amounts helping to elect their allies.</p>
        <p>The Democrats also say they expect to use the issue to underscore sharp ideological differences between Vice President Al Gore and Gov. George W. Bush. Mr. Gore, the presumptive Democratic presidential nominee, supports an array of tougher gun laws, while Mr. Bush, the likely Republican candidate, opposes most new gun restrictions and has been a strong ally of the N.R.A.</p>
        <p>In a telephone interview, Mr. Walsh denied that he had been pressured by the N.R.A. or its allies in Congress. The Republican whip, Representative Tom DeLay of Texas, a leading supporter of the rifle association, sits on Mr. Walsh's subcommittee. And its ranking Democrat, Representative Allan B. Mollohan of West Virginia, who cosigned the letter to Mr. Cuomo, is considered a loyal ally of the rifle association by gun-control advocates.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Walsh said he acted on his own because he believed that federal money was being misspent, draining money from a program to fight drugs in public housing projects.</p>
        <p>''The Clinton administration has found the gun lobby to be an excellent whipping boy,'' he said. ''But I have not consistently supported or opposed the gun lobby. This is just an appropriators' responsibility to make sure that funds are spent appropriately.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Cuomo disputed that, saying in an interview, ''I have no doubt the N.R.A. and like groups are behind many of these anti-gun safety maneuvers.''</p>
        <p>Asked what would happen if the buyback program continued, Mr. Walsh said that housing officials could be fined or even jailed. But he said he was not sure he was prepared to seek such penalties.</p>
        <p>The buyback program has proven very popular in many cities. In Corpus Christi, Tex., officials spent their entire grant of $19,500 to buy 260 guns in just one day, turning away more than 100 people the next morning. In Davenport, Iowa, a $21,000 grant was spent in under three hours to buy 420 guns.</p>
        <p>Supporters of the program said each gun purchased removed a serious hazard. But the N.R.A. contends most of the guns bought back are old, cheap weapons that are unlikely to be used in crimes.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
