<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Liberties; Not Our Class, Darling</title>
    <meta content="30DOWD$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218883"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dowd, Maureen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/Maureen Dowd</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E5D9153DF933A05754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="738" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Liberties; Not Our Class, Darling</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MAUREEN DOWD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dowd, Maureen</byline>
      <dateline>PHILADELPHIA</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Maureen Dowd Op-Ed column contends George W Bush's Republican presidential candidacy reflects deep-seated elitist sense that important decisions should be left to those bred to make them (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It would be fun to see what John O'Hara would make of the Republicans' restoration convention.</p>
        <p>The writer from a small town outside Philadelphia was so fixated on social mores, on the unspoken rules of class among the Main Line types, that Ernest Hemingway once cracked, ''Let's start a bloody fund to send John O'Hara to Yale.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It would be fun to see what John O'Hara would make of the Republicans' restoration convention.</p>
        <p>The writer from a small town outside Philadelphia was so fixated on social mores, on the unspoken rules of class among the Main Line types, that Ernest Hemingway once cracked, ''Let's start a bloody fund to send John O'Hara to Yale.''</p>
        <p>The novelist of manners called his fictional town outside Philadelphia Gibbsville, and he wrote about ''the persona gratas of the inner sanctum,'' as he called the swells of the country club set.</p>
        <p>''Any member of the club could come to the dance, but not everyone who came to the dance was really welcome in the smoking room,'' he wrote in ''Appointment in Samarra.'' The smoking room was for ''the spenders and drinkers and socially secure, who could thumb their noses and not have to answer to anyone except their own families.''</p>
        <p>Mr. O'Hara, who savored the self-destructive streak among the pampered, would have enjoyed Bushville as much as Gibbsville: a millennial convention rooting for the goof-off son of the fired boss to get the big job. It is the old-boy network writ large, a bunch of mostly rich, white, male, older delegates pouring into the city of underdog ''Rocky'' to see two overdog oilmen who got to go to Yale preach about a more democratic Republican Party.</p>
        <p>The writer who always had his nose pressed up against the glass would have understood perfectly why George Walker Bush did not scrutinize Dick Cheney's voting record before anointing him -- just as George Herbert Walker Bush never sat down with J. Danforth Quayle to have a substantive conversation about issues, principles or beliefs before anointing him.</p>
        <p>It would have been rude. As Bush family icon Henry Stimson, F.D.R.'s secretary of war, put it, ''Gentlemen do not read each other's mail.''</p>
        <p>The Bushes feel you should trust them to choose trustworthy seconds from the club.</p>
        <p>The arrival of Dick Cheney, with his ''Dr. No'' voting record strafing the little folk, may give Prince Albert more credibility as a populist.</p>
        <p>President Clinton, the darling of the meritocracy, jumped on the class issue at a Boston fund-raiser on Friday. W.'s only message, he mocked, is ''My daddy was president.''</p>
        <p>The two George Bushes are engaging and unpretentious. But deep down in their genes is that elitist sense that the important decisions should be made by those who are bred to make them. Their ideology is friendship. They equate integrity with loyalty to them. They are genuinely surprised when someone accuses them of callousness -- whether it is the Willie Horton issue with the father or the relentless Texas death-row executions with the son -- because their perspective is, ''I know I'm honorable, therefore I'm best accountable to myself.''</p>
        <p>The family code is rooted in the noblesse oblige air of Prescott Bush, a craggy senator and a Wall Street executive who inhabited the partners' room at Brown Brothers Harriman, a rarefied wood-paneled universe filled with Skull and Bones men and roll-top desks and a sense that the fate of the nation was best left in their hands over cigars and brandy.</p>
        <p>Newsweek reports today that W. was always ''somewhat oblivious to the political power of his family ties.'' Running for Congress in 1978, he went to a Republican candidates' school. ''David Dreier, now a Republican congressman from California,'' Newsweek says, ''recalls young Bush excitedly telling him, 'I've got the greatest idea of how to raise money for the campaign. Have your mother send a letter to your family's Christmas card list. I just did and I got $350,000!' It doesn't seem to have occurred to Bush that not everyone has Barbara Bush's Rolodex full of senators and statesmen and G.O.P. fat cats.''</p>
        <p>It is disturbing the way W. first ignored and then defended Dick Cheney's Draconian anti-woman, anti-child, anti-senior, anti-black, anti-environment, anti-poor voting record in the House in the 80's.</p>
        <p>W. took full advantage of his unlimited second chances and family connections. The people hurt by Mr. Cheney's reactionary votes had only one chance, or no chance.</p>
        <p>Asked by Peter Jennings on Friday if it was politically advantageous to be George Bush's son, W. replied, ''No.'' Piffle.</p>
        <p>Asked about his political relationship with his father, the son replied, ''There is no political relationship.''</p>
        <p>Double piffle.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
