<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Taking the Slow Lane, for Tea and Sweets</title>
    <meta content="30TEA.$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218667"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tea</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Liebenson, Bess</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E4DF1F3AF933A05754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1721" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Taking the Slow Lane, for Tea and Sweets</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BESS LIEBENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Liebenson, Bess</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bess Liebenson reviews Connecticut's tea shops and tearooms; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CONNECTICUT, however close to New York, has its own ways. Take tea, for example. In New York, teatime is celebrated at hotels like the Plaza, the Pierre and the Carlisle. It's another way to entertain business clients, a chance to get off one's feet while shopping or doing the galleries. But in Connecticut there are gardens, a flourishing selection of distributors, retail shops and tearooms, tea caterers, art museum teas, a magazine called Tea, a tea calendar and a new tea school.</p>
        <p>The idea, then, is to set out as on a wine trail, to learn about tea, and, yes, to indulge in the specialty sandwiches and sweets served as well.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CONNECTICUT, however close to New York, has its own ways. Take tea, for example. In New York, teatime is celebrated at hotels like the Plaza, the Pierre and the Carlisle. It's another way to entertain business clients, a chance to get off one's feet while shopping or doing the galleries. But in Connecticut there are gardens, a flourishing selection of distributors, retail shops and tearooms, tea caterers, art museum teas, a magazine called Tea, a tea calendar and a new tea school.</p>
        <p>The idea, then, is to set out as on a wine trail, to learn about tea, and, yes, to indulge in the specialty sandwiches and sweets served as well.</p>
        <p>A first stop might be the tea purveyors HARNEY &amp; SONS (11 Brook Street, Salisbury; 800-832-8463; Monday-Saturday 10 a.m. to 5 p.m., Sunday 11 to 4), which has held court in a long low-slung gray building bedecked with potted flowers and garden furniture for three years.</p>
        <p>''We have gone around the world,'' Michael Harney said, ''and seen our friends and competitors do their tea shops in Austria, Hong Kong, England and Paris, dealt with producers and brokers of tea and translated their experience here.'' Michael Harney is vice president of the family-run company that includes his father, John, brother Paul and Michael's French wife, Brigitte, who runs the tasting room. ''People can count on trying different teas here,'' Michael Harney continued. ''We don't charge for tastings.'' The tasting room is filled with teapots, teas, fancy foods, accessories, antique hotel silver, a collection of needlepoint, cottage-themed cozies and garden benches.</p>
        <p>The Harney company produces, flavors and markets teas. ''The tasting room was originally designed for the wholesale trade,'' Michael Harney said. ''But people kept coming in.'' One wall has more than 150 varieties in gold-labeled black canisters. For tasting, canisters are arranged on two long counters, dry leaves in front on labeled covers, then small bowls to drink from.</p>
        <p>SIMPSON &amp; VAIL (3 Quarry Road, Brookfield; 800-282-8327; summer hours Monday-Friday 9 a.m. to 5:30 p.m.) overlooks a lime rock quarry and a pond stocked with trout, bass and carp. The owners, Jim and Joan Harron, live over the sandstone brick office, warehouse and retail showroom. Mr. and Mrs. Harron bought the circa-1904 tea-coffee business more than 20 years ago; they moved from Westchester County to Brookfield three and a half years ago.</p>
        <p>''In 1991 when the National Institute of Health came out with findings that green tea was an anti-carcinogenic and could prevent cancer, there were 18 people in the specialty tea business,'' Mr. Harron said. ''Today there are in excess of 500. Total tea sales then were about three-quarters of a billion dollars, including Lipton and Nestle's. The business today is about $8 billion and growing.''</p>
        <p>The 800-square-foot, sleek pine-floored showroom has a long counter with two shelves beneath double-stacked with silver tins of 160 types of tea. Above, against the wall, are burlap sacks of coffee. And throughout the room there are displays of food including chutneys, mustards and sauces from around the world, tea accessories -- all-over floral, solid and other patterned teapots, cups and children's tea sets.</p>
        <p>Pearl Dexter, the editor and publisher of Tea: A Magazine, operates the OLDE ENGLISH TEAROOM (3 Devotion Road, Scotland; 888-456-8651) in a flower-emblazoned circa-1759 gray house overlooking the village green. Tea is served daily except Sunday, by reservation only. The quarterly magazine not only emphasizes the beverage but also publishes related artiles on health, art, music, literature and travel.</p>
        <p>Ms. Dexter is also the author, with Beulah Munshower Sommer, of ''Tea with Presidential Families'' (1999). And last November Ms. Dexter established a tea school. Its third session, at the Celebrations Inn in Pomfret, takes place on Aug. 17 and 18. Lecture topics include tea's health benefits, history, the tea trade today and fund-raising with tea.</p>
        <p>Ms. Dexter serves tea in a wood-paneled keeping room with a seven-foot fireplace. Up to 30 people can be seated at tables covered in maroon and green cloths overlaid with lace. A full afternoon tea ($25) consists of sandwiches -- cucumber and dill, cheddar cheese with walnuts and apple, and curried egg salad. Seasonal desserts of shortbread or tea bread and fruit are served with scones, jam, cream and handmade white chocolate mints made by Reva Paul, a New York sugar artist.</p>
        <p>Gardens and tea are the twin attractions at SUNDIAL GARDENS (Brault Hill Road extension, off Route 81 in Higganum; 860-345-4290), where three formal gardens can be toured: the main garden surrounding a sundial, the ribbonlike knot garden, and the topiary with fountain, arbors and allees. An herb and tea shop is housed in a restored 18th-century barn.</p>
        <p>Ragna Tischler Goddard -- an herbalist, garden designer and lecturer on tea and gardens -- recently completed writing and photographing ''Celebrating Tea,'' a 2001 calendar (Tide-Mark Press Ltd., East Hartford, $11.95). Ms. Goddard and  her husband, Tom Goddard, a pastry chef at the Sundial, offer group teas and garden tours on Sundays by reservation.</p>
        <p>Another garden-and-tea experience takes place at CAPRILANDS HERB FARM (534 Silver Street, Coventry; 860-742-7244), a few miles from the Nathan Hale Homestead and the University of Connecticut. Self-guided tours of more than 35 gardens are coupled with what are called high teas on Sundays at 2 p.m. Canapes, bread, soup, salad, sandwiches, tea, wine and desert are served for $12. ''It's like a luncheon except the main course is sandwiches -- pretty hardy for tea,'' said Edward Cook, widower and executor of the estate of Adelma Grenier Simmons, a farmer, herbalist and prolific author who died at the age of 93 in 1997. The tea is held in a 1740's farmhouse, floors strewn with rose petals. Each table is decorated with fresh flowers, old-fashioned antique roses when in season. Reservations are required.</p>
        <p>Museum teas have become quite the rage as well as proven fund-raising events. The caterer Carol Timpanelli of the ROYAL TEA COMPANY (5628 Main Street, Trumbull; 203-452-1006) said her scone recipe comes from the chef at Balmoral Castle, and a farmer in Oregon grows the marionberries for the jam. An authentic English afternoon tea includes sandwiches, scones with jam and cream, trifle and a signature cookie. Ms. Timpanelli also caters an annual art lovers' tea at the Discovery Museum in Bridgeport.</p>
        <p>Gracing art and other museum events with tea more or less formally is also being done at the Bruce Museum in Greenwich, the New Canaan Historical Society, Roseland Cottage in Woodstock, and the Peabody Museum of Natural History in New Haven.</p>
        <p>Tearooms also exist for pure indulgence, where the lines have blurred between teatime and lunch.</p>
        <p>Barbara and John Jago-Ford started a shop offering British food and teas, then expanded the concept to include a tearoom in the circa-1690 Meigs Bishop House (45 Wall Street, Madison; 203-245-4521). They call it the FRONT PARLOUR of the BRITISH SHOPPE. ''Because of demand we serve afternoon tea from 11:30 to 4 Monday through Saturday,'' Mr. Jago-Ford said. Walls are decorated with lithographs of English royalty; lace valences trim the windows and lace cloths top those patterned with cabbage roses. ''Our lunches are the sort you would have if you were traveling through England and stopped at a nice country pub,'' Mrs. Jago-Ford said. The Duchess of Bedford Afternoon Tea, the most comprehensive ($17.95), includes tea sandwiches: curried egg and mango chutney, herbed butter and cucumber, smoked salmon and dill and creamed Stilton with fresh pear, followed by a hot scone served with clotted cream and strawberry jam, and a slice of cake, all with a choice of brewed tea.</p>
        <p>About one mile off Antiques Row on Route 6 in Woodbury is MRS. WHITE'S TEA ROOM (308 Sherman Hill Road; 203-263-6022). Inside the circa-1920's house with flowered window boxes is a Victorian oasis. Mauve and white toile wallpaper, red shades and hand-crocheted valences set a scene reminiscent of grandmother's house with a collection of teapots, mirrors, portraits, a dollhouse, and a mixture of tables and chairs. Stacey Gardner, owner and a caterer for 15 years, offers a choice of 25 teas; each is served in antique flowered and gold-fluted teapots, each different as are the teacups. Everything is made on the premises, starting with cranberry scones served with whipped butter and cream. A three-tiered china stand holds tea sandwiches presented with carrot-raisin salad and fresh fruit. A pedestal bearing a centerpiece of strawberry-blueberry shortcake is surrounded by lemon curd tarts, brownies, rugelach and yellow roses ($15.95). Hours for breakfast, lunch and tea are Tuesday through Saturday 9 a.m. to 4:30 p.m. and Sunday 9 a.m. to 2 p.m.</p>
        <p>MAINLY TEA (221 Main Street, Old Wethersfield; 860-529-9517), a tea parlor and gift shop that opened at the end of April. Its three owners -- Aileen McDonough and Karen Memmott, formerly tea party caterers, and Dana Spicer, owner of Heart of the Country craft shop -- joined forces and contributed family heirlooms: an Empire sofa, wing chairs and sets of Sheraton fancy and other chairs. Pale lemon walls, grass green carpeting and indoor trees offer a sunny backdrop for an antique chest harboring an old clock and teacups and floral floor-length cloths overlaid with white scalloped toppings. Luncheon tea ($14.50), served Wednesday through Saturday noon to 3 p.m. (less inclusive afternoon tea is served 2 to 5 p.m.), includes a pot of brewed tea served in rose or mint cozies, with little sandwiches and roll-ups surrounding fresh fruit and mint, followed by scones with double cream and jam and a trio of dessert bars.</p>
        <p>Wearable-art sweaters and vests with tea themes, English bone china teacups and pots, tea towels and more are sold in the shop in front; there is also a party room in the back. ''There are enough fast food places around,'' Ms. Memmott said. ''We wanted a slow quiet area for a restful interlude.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
