<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>July 23-29; Smile When You Downsize the Name, Partner</title>
    <meta content="30BOXA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218846"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807E0D6143DF933A05754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="361" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>July 23-29; Smile When You Downsize the Name, Partner</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM L. HAMILTON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Before signing on to the Republican Party ticket with Gov. George W. Bush, Dick Cheney should have read the small print -- it's his own name.</p>
        <p>On the new campaign placard unveiled at the candidates' first appearance in Wyoming, Mr. Cheney's name was two-thirds the size of Mr. Bush's -- on a second, lower line.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Before signing on to the Republican Party ticket with Gov. George W. Bush, Dick Cheney should have read the small print -- it's his own name.</p>
        <p>On the new campaign placard unveiled at the candidates' first appearance in Wyoming, Mr. Cheney's name was two-thirds the size of Mr. Bush's -- on a second, lower line.</p>
        <p>Though running mates, they are not co-stars, at least in Hollywood terms.</p>
        <p>''When you've got co-stars, you've got them on the same line, same size,'' said Elaine Goldsmith-Thomas, a senior vice president at International Creative Management, and Julia Robert's agent. ''What's the message? Cheney needs a new agent. They're not sharing the bill.''</p>
        <p>What's true for Harrison and Michelle in this summer's ''What Lies Beneath'' -- co-stars, pica for pica -- was also true for Ike-Dick, McKinley-Roosevelt, Clinton-Gore, Lincoln-Johnson and Reagan-Bush.</p>
        <p>The exception to the graphic democracy of the last two centuries --  President Bush in 1992. Dan Quayle's name was downsized from 30 to 50 percent.</p>
        <p>Other examples are rare, if they exist at all, said Larry Bird, curator of the political history campaign collection at the Smithsonian's National Museum of American History, whose materials date from colonial times. ''Traditionally they're co-equals in point size,'' he said. ''That's the message of the signage -- that there is a collective responsibility for perpetuating the office of the presidency.''</p>
        <p>Ray Sullivan, a spokesman for the Bush campaign, said there was no intention in the official campaign image beyond the solution of a design problem, and no nervousness about unintended interpretations.</p>
        <p>''Number one -- because of the large block font used to spell out 'Bush' and 'Cheney,' our graphic artist suggested making 'Bush' larger to make the sign easier to read,'' Mr. Sullivan said. ''Number two -- Governor Bush is the nominee for president.''</p>
        <p>WILLIAM L. HAMILTON</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
