<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Look for a Board With a Lot to Lose</title>
    <meta content="MB005501" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218871"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="INVESTING: DIARY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Boards of Directors</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lyons, Patrick J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boards of Directors</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E1DB153DF933A05754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="420" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Look for a Board With a Lot to Lose</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Patrick J. Lyons</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lyons, Patrick J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Study of 40 pairs of companies and their performance from 1987 to 1996 finds outside directors at best-performing companies owned average $470,000 of company stock, or 1.3 percent stake, while those at laggard companies owned average of just $80,000 of company stock, or 0.1 percent stake (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Outside directors who hold significant stakes in the company's stock are widely regarded as a good sign for investors; the thinking is that they will be motivated to watch out for shareholder interests, especially when they conflict with the interests of insiders.</p>
        <p>But can the presence of such directors actually have much positive effect on the company's performance? Few analysts have thought so.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Outside directors who hold significant stakes in the company's stock are widely regarded as a good sign for investors; the thinking is that they will be motivated to watch out for shareholder interests, especially when they conflict with the interests of insiders.</p>
        <p>But can the presence of such directors actually have much positive effect on the company's performance? Few analysts have thought so.</p>
        <p>Now, though, comes a bit of evidence that they might after all.</p>
        <p>Two researchers at Columbia University's Graduate School of Business, Donald C. Hambrick and Eric M. Jackson, studied 40 pairs of companies and their performance from 1987 to 1996.</p>
        <p>For each pair, companies were selected that were in the same industry and began the period at about the same size and performance, but deviated thereafter, with one turning in sterling total returns -- at least 10 percent better than the median for their industry -- while the other fell far behind -- at least 10 percent worse than the median.</p>
        <p>On average, the researchers found, each outside director at the companies that turned out to be stars began the study period owning an average of almost six times as much company stock as did those at laggard companies -- $470,000 versus $80,000. The difference in the fraction of total company equity held was even more striking -- 1.3 percent at the stars, 0.1 percent at the laggards.</p>
        <p>Star company boards were one and a half times as likely as laggard boards to have a director holding $500,000 in stock or more, and almost three times as likely to have two such directors, according to the study, which will be presented at the annual meeting of the Academy of Management in Toronto next month.</p>
        <p>Curiously, the researchers found no similar pattern for inside directors and their holdings. Neither did they find any relationship between company performance and other board characteristics, like the number of seats, the proportion of outside directors, directors' average ages or average length of tenure.</p>
        <p>Somewhat clouding the usefulness of the results for current investors is the practice, common today but rare in 1987, of compensating directors with significant stock grants. The authors warn that in such cases, ''share ownership may be largely a result of the company's superior performance, rather than a cause.''</p>
        <p>Patrick J. Lyons</p>
        <p>INVESTING: DIARY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
