<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Use of 'Affirmative Insurance'</title>
    <meta content="30QAQA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218630"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="Q &amp; A"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Q and A</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E2DD1E3AF933A05754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="650" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Use of 'Affirmative Insurance'</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Q What does it mean when a mortgage lender insists that a title company provide ''affirmative insurance'' before allowing a property to close? . . . Karl Anichev, Kew Gardens, N.Y.</p>
        <p>A John Martin, general counsel for All New York Title Agency, a title insurance concern based in White Plains, said that when a title company issues title insurance, it usually issues two policies: one for the owner and another for the mortgage lender. The reason for the lender's coverage, he said, is to ensure that the lender is protected in the event a flaw in title has rendered the mortgage unenforceable and the borrower has stopped making payments.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Q What does it mean when a mortgage lender insists that a title company provide ''affirmative insurance'' before allowing a property to close? . . . Karl Anichev, Kew Gardens, N.Y.</p>
        <p>A John Martin, general counsel for All New York Title Agency, a title insurance concern based in White Plains, said that when a title company issues title insurance, it usually issues two policies: one for the owner and another for the mortgage lender. The reason for the lender's coverage, he said, is to ensure that the lender is protected in the event a flaw in title has rendered the mortgage unenforceable and the borrower has stopped making payments.</p>
        <p>For example, Mr. Martin said, if a deed to a particular piece of property was forged, the person who ended up with that deed -- typically, an unsuspecting purchaser -- would not have legal title to the property. And since only the legal owner of a property can agree to allow a mortgage to be placed on the property, the mortgage executed by the unsuspecting purchaser would not be a valid lien on the property.</p>
        <p>In such a case, Mr. Martin said, the mortgage lender would not be able to foreclose on the property if the unsuspecting purchaser stopped making mortgage payments.</p>
        <p>If that happened, he said, and the lender was covered by title insurance, then the amount due on the loan would be paid by the title insurance company.</p>
        <p>Not all flaws in title, however, are the result of forgery, and not all have such clear ramifications. For example, Mr. Martin said, some deeds contain provisions known as covenants and restrictions that limit the use of a particular piece of property. Some deeds, for example, prohibit the owner from using the property for business purposes.</p>
        <p>It is also fairly common for deeds to contain provisions relating to easements or rights of way that give a third party the right to use a portion of the property. It is in such contexts, he said, that affirmative insurance is required by lenders.</p>
        <p>For example, Mr. Martin said, a lender will typically demand affirmative insurance -- in other words, a specific written representation from the title company -- that violation of a particular covenant or restriction will not result in the loss or impairment of the lender's lien on the property.</p>
        <p>Most lenders will also demand similar explicit assurances -- in the form of affirmative insurance -- for easements and rights of way.</p>
        <p>Who Pays for The Paint Job?</p>
        <p>Q Under New York City's law on lead-based paint hazards, if a tenant paints his own apartment but a subsequent inspection by the landlord reveals peeling paint, must the tenant pay for another paint job to correct the situation? . . . Sidney Hidge, Manhattan.</p>
        <p>A Peter Schwartz, a Manhattan real estate lawyer, said that under current New York City law, if an apartment contains peeling lead-based paint, it is the landlord's responsibility to correct the problem. Generally speaking, he said, that would involve removing all peeling paint and then repainting the surfaces that were repaired -- regardless of whether the walls had originally been painted by the tenant or the landlord.</p>
        <p>In any event, Mr. Schwartz said, the New York City Housing Maintenance Code requires landlords to paint tenants' apartments at least once every three years.</p>
        <p>He pointed out that all lead-based paint remediation work must be done in accordance with strict environmental regulations. Those regulations require, among other things, wet-scraping of the peeling paint, so as to prevent dust and chips from migrating into other parts of the apartment and building, and the vacuuming of all surfaces with a high-efficiency HEPA vacuum.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schwartz added that under current New York City law, there is an explicit presumption that buildings built before 1960 contain lead-based paint.</p>
        <p>Q &amp; A</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
