<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>President at Center of Venezuela's Delayed 'Mega-Election'</title>
    <meta content="30VENE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218911"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Venezuela</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rohter, Larry</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chavez, Hugo (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Venezuela</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Venezuela</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E0DE123DF933A05754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="860" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>President at Center of Venezuela's Delayed 'Mega-Election'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LARRY ROHTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rohter, Larry</byline>
      <dateline>CARACAS, Venezuela, July 29</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Venezuela is set to hold mega-election in which thousands of candidates, from Pres Hugo Chavez down to state legislators, are competing; Chavez is expected to win by wide margin, while races for 23 governorships and 165 seats in new one-house National Assembly are expected to be somewhat closer; Chavez is expected to fall short of two-thirds majority he needs for quick approval of his far-reaching social and economic reforms; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two months after a first attempt collapsed in ineptitude and scandal, Venezuela will try again on Sunday to hold the biggest vote in its history, a ''mega-election'' in which thousands of candidates, from President Hugo Chavez down to state legislators, are competing.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chavez himself is the only real issue in the vote, which he called in hopes of winning a new six-year term. Despite an economy that shrank by more than 7 percent last year, record unemployment and a big jump in crime, public opinion polls are unanimous in predicting a Chavez romp by a margin of 15 percentage points or more.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Two months after a first attempt collapsed in ineptitude and scandal, Venezuela will try again on Sunday to hold the biggest vote in its history, a ''mega-election'' in which thousands of candidates, from President Hugo Chavez down to state legislators, are competing.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chavez himself is the only real issue in the vote, which he called in hopes of winning a new six-year term. Despite an economy that shrank by more than 7 percent last year, record unemployment and a big jump in crime, public opinion polls are unanimous in predicting a Chavez romp by a margin of 15 percentage points or more.</p>
        <p>The battle for 23 governorships and 165 seats in a new one-house National Assembly is expected to be somewhat closer, with most opinion surveys predicting that Mr. Chavez will fall short of the two-thirds majority he will need to gain quick approval of his far-reaching social and economic reform program. Such a result could force him to pursue a more moderate course and negotiate with the opposition.</p>
        <p>Those races are expected to be particularly close in areas where the multiparty coalition supporting Mr. Chavez was unable to unite behind a common candidate, possibly splitting the pro-Chavez vote and allowing his opponents to win.</p>
        <p>Since he was first elected in December 1998, Mr. Chavez has blamed a ''rancid oligarchy'' of political and business interests for the country's malaise. In a typically fiery speech on Wednesday ending his campaign, he asked his followers for a landslide victory to ''liquidate our adversaries from the field of battle'' once and for all and allow him finally to carry out the ''peaceful social revolution'' he has long promised.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chavez's main challenger is Francisco Arias Cardenas, who, like Mr. Chavez, is a former army colonel who took part in a coup attempt in 1992. The men then spent two years in jail together and were friends and political allies until early this year, when Mr. Arias angrily accused the president of concentrating all power in his own hands, alienating the United States and falling under the spell of Fidel Castro.</p>
        <p>Venezuela has become ''a de facto dictatorship,'' Mr. Arias charged at a news conference here on Friday. ''Corruption, poverty and unemployment are accelerating,'' he said, because the Chavez administration has ''violated all the norms and protocols'' of good government and pursued economic policies that were hostile to free enterprise.</p>
        <p>There is also a third candidate, the former Caracas mayor, Claudio Fermin. He has no chance of winning, and has come under pressure from the Arias camp to withdraw, but chose to remain in the race because, he said, he did not think the choices available to voters should be limited to two military officers who have tried to overthrow the government.</p>
        <p>This will be Venezuela's sixth vote in less than two years, including three to draft and ratify a new Constitution expanding presidential powers, and voters are showing signs of boredom and impatience. On Friday, Foreign Minister Jose Vicente Rangel predicted to reporters that half of the 11.8 million eligible voters would stay home because of ''voter fatigue'' and a lack of suspense about the outcome.</p>
        <p>''Frankly, I'm getting tired of having to cast a ballot every few months or so,'' said Zoila Chacon Jimenez, a sales clerk in a department store here. ''Democracy is great, but what we really need is for somebody to do something about the economy, and the quicker the better.''</p>
        <p>Sunday's vote was originally scheduled for May 28. But when the National Electoral Council, dominated by inexperienced Chavez supporters, proved unable to provide the ballot information needed for new computerized voting machines, Mr. Chavez reluctantly urged a postponement rather than running the risk of seeing the legitimacy of his expected landslide victory tarnished.</p>
        <p>Council members at first sought to blame an American company hired to supply the technology for the vote, but that explanation convinced no one here, and a public furor forced the entire commission to resign. This week, the country's chief prosecutor filed corruption charges against five former members of the council.</p>
        <p>Mr. Arias and other opposition figures have complained of irregularities in the new council's organization, saying oversight measures that ''would have generated confidence have been eliminated.'' But international observers maintain that although some technical flaws remain, they can find no evidence of a government effort to steal votes.</p>
        <p>''We have no concern that the integrity of the election has been endangered at all,'' former President Jimmy Carter, leading a 48-member observer delegation, said at a news conference here Friday. Ruben Perina, head of an Organization of American States observer team, added, ''We see this vote very differently from the May process.'' He attributed the accusations to a growing ''polarization and mistrust in the political culture here.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
