<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pentimento</title>
    <meta content="30TEACH" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218543"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Feigen, Richard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Teachout, Terry</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Tales From the Art Crypt (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405EFD71F3BF933A05754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1136" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pentimento</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Terry Teachout</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Teachout, Terry</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Terry Teachout reviews book Tales From the Art Crypt: The Painters, the Museums, the Curators, the Collectors, the Auctions, the Art by Richard Feigen; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TALES FROM THE</p>
        <p>ART CRYPT</p>
        <p>The Painters, the Museums,</p>
        <p>the Curators, the Collectors,</p>
        <p>the Auctions, the Art.</p>
        <p>By Richard Feigen.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 296 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Alfred A. Knopf. $30.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TALES FROM THE</p>
        <p>ART CRYPT</p>
        <p>The Painters, the Museums,</p>
        <p>the Curators, the Collectors,</p>
        <p>the Auctions, the Art.</p>
        <p>By Richard Feigen.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 296 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Alfred A. Knopf. $30.</p>
        <p>ART dealing, like lawyering, is one of the equivocal professions. It is inescapable and indispensable, but its very existence reminds us that art is a business, a mundane reality that has never gone down smoothly with those romantics who prefer to suppose that artists dine thrice daily on manna, or starve uncomplainingly. Even today, when what the Manhattan dealer Richard Feigen calls the monetization of art has reached unprecedented heights, there are no superstar dealers, only superstar artists. Of course the people behind the great galleries are well known to insiders and gallerygoers, but ask an ordinary stargazer to name an art dealer and he will probably mention Christie's or Sotheby's -- or eBay.</p>
        <p>I wonder if this is at least partly responsible for the fact that Feigen, who has led a most interesting life, nonetheless chose to write not a formal memoir but a loosely knit collection of semiautobiographical essays. Perhaps he questioned whether anyone would really care about how a bright young man from Chicago came to be a buyer and seller of paintings and sculpture. I would have liked to read that book, but the one he has chosen to write instead is both involving and revealing.</p>
        <p>The 15 chapters of ''Tales From the Art Crypt'' cover an exceptionally wide variety of topics, ranging from the scholarly misattribution of paintings by well-known artists to the roundabout way in which social anti-Semitism led to the faulty restoration of several of the Art Institute of Chicago's greatest masterpieces (including, ironically, Manet's ''Christ Crowned With Thorns''). All are written from the point of view of an unabashed elitist secure in the knowledge that some connoisseurs, himself among them, are more equal than others: ''Although it has to be trained and honed, an 'eye' seems to be born, not made. Many people become art historians, even well-known ones, without being so endowed.''</p>
        <p>Not surprisingly, Feigen thinks poorly of many of his colleagues, and is happy to give their names and addresses. Lincoln Center's ''bad architecture'' is ''the offspring of powerful, arrogant, tasteless people''; the Metropolitan Museum's willingness to intersperse exhibitions devoted to the likes of Gianni Versace among its more elevated offerings reminds him of ''a nice girl of good family who just once in a while goes out and turns tricks for some pocket change.'' He discusses with comparable bluntness how the infusion of vast amounts of new money into the art market led inexorably to a scorched-earth battle over ''the very concept of a museum's mission -- the old model, a temple of connoisseurship and scholarship, called 'elitist' by its antagonists; or the new, an entertainment palace and elementary art school, called 'populist.' ''</p>
        <p>Needless to say, this is familiar stuff, but rarely has it been voiced with such fervor, and it is particularly useful to hear Feigen explain how such old-school institutions as Fort Worth's acclaimed Kimbell Museum of Art have managed to stand aloof from the mad dash for cash: ''It is not because the Kimbell has such a huge endowment and so much money for acquisitions. It has the money because a few donors are so proud of what the former director, Edmund Pillsbury, did, and had such confidence in his taste, that they funded his projects. The objects generated the money, not the money the objects.''</p>
        <p>Feigen's insistence on the corrupting power of money may sound slightly off key, coming as it does from a big-ticket dealer whose most recent venture into the public eye was the sale of Saul Steinberg's art collection. That thought has presumably crossed his own mind, for lurking on every page of this book is the implicit claim that its urbane author is no Joseph Duveen, touching up old masters to lure the freshly monied, but a gentleman dealer. This haughty pose can become a teeny bit risible. I smiled at his recollection of the day in the late 60's when he took the Belgian sculptor Nadine Effront to ''21'' for lunch. ''Not my favorite restaurant,'' he sniffs retrospectively, ''but appropriate for a mondaine foreign visitor.''</p>
        <p>Still, it is plain to see that he belongs among the ranks of those aesthetes whom he describes as ''surviving dinosaurs of the old order, connoisseurs+who love objects,'' and who shall blame him for contriving to make a living off his love? Further evidence of his genuineness is found in the fact that he does not allow his urbanity to mask his anger. The change-and-decay-in-all-around-I-see mood of ''Tales From the Art Crypt'' is reminiscent of Evelyn Waugh at his most Pinfoldian, and it is never merely curmudgeonly; rather, it reflects his absolute conviction that something is rotten in the world of art.</p>
        <p>It is worth noting the unacknowledged conflict between Feigen's aesthetic sensibilities and his oft-repeated political views. Clearly, it is hugely important to him that we know he declined ''to rise for 'The Star-Spangled Banner' during 10 years of the Vietnam atrocity,'' even though he just as clearly believes some paintings great and others lousy. Back in the days when Clement Greenberg was laying down the law in the pages of The Nation, one could still be both a political leftist and an artistic elitist -- what Richard Taruskin has called ''a rightist of the left.'' But that caravan long ago moved on: many leftists today take a rigorously egalitarian view of art, and their radical pluralism cannot be reconciled with Feigen's enduring faith in the god of quality.</p>
        <p>I myself find his cranky insistence on the limits of pluralism to be bracing, though his yardstick has a few crooked places in it, especially in the field of modern art. He would doubtless bristle at being compared to Greenberg, whom he regards as a theory-mad tyrant who foisted abstract art on a gullible public; Feigen's idea of a really good American artist is Ivan Albright, the fellow who painted the oh-so-creepy picture of Dorian Gray in the 1945 Hollywoodization of Oscar Wilde's novel. But Feigen's own defects of taste do not diminish the force of his assault on the nihilistic egalitarianism that now runs rampant in the art world. Because somebody is wrong about something does not mean that nobody can be right about anything.</p>
        <p>Terry Teachout, the music critic of Commentary and a contributor to Time magazine, is writing ''H. L. Mencken: A Life.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Terry Teachout, the music critic of Commentary and a contributor to Time magazine, is writing ''H. L. Mencken: A Life.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
