<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Expatriate at War</title>
    <meta content="30EDERLT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218535"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hemon, Aleksandar</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eder, Richard</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Question of Bruno, The (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801EFD81F3BF933A05754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1425" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Expatriate at War</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Richard Eder</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eder, Richard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Richard Eder reviews book The Question of Bruno by Aleksandar Hemon; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Question of Bruno</p>
        <p>By Aleksandar Hemon.</p>
        <p>230 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Nan A. Talese/Doubleday. $22.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Question of Bruno</p>
        <p>By Aleksandar Hemon.</p>
        <p>230 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Nan A. Talese/Doubleday. $22.95.</p>
        <p>Aleksandar Hemon came to the United States in 1992 as a young tourist; while he was here, the civil war broke out in his native Bosnia. He stayed, he took odd jobs, he learned to write English remarkably well. In this remarkable English he wrote the seven stories and the novella that have now been published as ''The Question of Bruno.''</p>
        <p>Several of the shorter pieces are so good as to make the reader feel certain of having discovered not just an extraordinary story but an extraordinary writer: one who seems not simply gifted but necessary. In retrospect, you begin to worry about what could so easily have been lost. What if Hemon had stayed in Sarajevo and suffered a momentary cramp -- nonwriter's -- crossing Sniper's Alley?</p>
        <p>The alley is a place to start. In quite different ways, all of the collection deals with Bosnia, or with the Yugoslavia that dominated Hemon's childhood, back when Bosnia was rather a hopeful place (not yet having been elevated into a tragedy). The novella and one of the stories evoke the displacement felt by a young Bosnian -- a partly fictional version of the author -- who finds himself struggling to get by in Chicago while so many terrible things are happening in Sarajevo. How can you be an island when the bell incessantly tolls 5,000 miles away and makes all American sounds a meaningless cacophony?</p>
        <p>The novella labors over the theme with limited success. The story ''A Coin'' accomplishes it dazzlingly. It is a series of undelivered, perhaps unwritten letters, between the Chicago expatriate and Aida, who edits film for the foreign television crews in Sarajevo. In her voice, it begins:</p>
        <p>''Suppose there is a Point A and a Point B and that, if you want to get from point A to point B, you have to pass through an open space clearly visible to a skillful sniper. You have to run from Point A to Point B and the faster you run, the more likely you are to reach Point B alive.''</p>
        <p>That ''suppose'' turns testimony into art, and invites us in instead of confronting us. Its hypothetical conditional awakens and incites the imagination, so easily shut down by the graphic detail in journalism's indicative. It makes a place in our heart for Aida's lacerating details.</p>
        <p>Among them the mournful things that the alley sprinters have dropped: ''A black leather wallet, probably empty. A purse, agape like a mouth. A white plastic water vessel, with a bullet hole in its center. A green-red-brown shawl ornamented with snowflakes, dirty. A wet loaf of bread, with busy ants crawling all over it.'' There is Aida's aunt, choking to death when snipers keep her from going out for her asthma medicine. Her body rots in the family apartment for the same reason, until her relatives wrap it in a sheet and topple it out the window.</p>
        <p>There is Aida's insistence that what filmed horrors tell is not the real story but a voyeur story of their own. She edits out the most gruesome footage. In effect, it is her protest to the world audience: My tragedy is not your three minutes of horrified compassion. There is her comfortless affair with a veteran British cameraman. He films the bloody stumps of a woman whose arms were blown off, instead of putting the camera down to help her. Filming is how he helps, he says. But why the close-up? ''He said he didn't do it. It was his camera that did it, he just held it.''</p>
        <p>Aida's resonant voice finds a hollow counterpoint in her nameless Chicago interlocutor. His anguish is partly the contrast of Aida's ordeal with his own safe if menial existence. Instead of snipers, he deals with cockroaches. In fact, using a slipper and a knife, he is the cockroaches' sniper. (In civil war can there be an absolute difference between ''them'' and ''us''?) But his specific anguish is the separation of distance and time: the uncertain and circuitous route for letters in and out of Sarajevo.</p>
        <p>''What terrifies me is that, as I rip the exhausted envelope, she may be dead,'' he says. ''And I'm reading her letter as if she were alive, her voice ringing in my brain, her visions projected before my eyes, her hand shaping curved letters. . . . I dread the fact that life is always slower than death.''</p>
        <p>What ''A Coin'' does in 15 pages, the novella -- Blind Jozef Pronek &amp; Dead Souls'' -- attempts to do in 75. The barely sketched exile with an unforgettable voice becomes a longer but not well fleshed-out version. Flesh muffles spirit.</p>
        <p>Hemon tells Pronek's story as the missteps and misapprehensions of an immigrant whose arrival is only physical; his mind and heart are elsewhere. The author uses the third person, as if to stress the remove. But there is too much remove and it is expounded in too much detail. We get a great deal of cartoonish surface skating in Pronek's reactions to America: his girlfriend, her family and a restaurant manager who fires him for ignoring the difference between romaine and iceberg lettuce. Pronek sees, but seeing does not lead to transformation. Rather, it transforms downward, to the facile cliches of ''how strange these Americans be.'' His hunger is not for knowing but for not knowing, and it is too easily satisfied.</p>
        <p>Hemon's own appetite, in most of the pieces, is insatiable and wild. ''The Life and Work of Alphonse Kauders'' is a wacky scrapbook of sayings by or about an imaginary character who, Zelig-like, inserts his visage alongside any number of history's consequential personages. Kauders tells ''Dr. Joseph Goebbels'' that writing is as useless as signing molecules of gas. ''Well, listen,'' Goebbels retorts, ''that differs from a gas to a gas.'' Kauders ''was the first to tell Joseph V. Stalin: 'No!' ''(Stalin had asked him if he wore a watch.) Kauders bucks up Gavrilo Princip, who wets his pants as Archduke Franz Ferdinand's carriage and World War I roll down the street: ''Shoot, brother, what kind of Serb are you?''</p>
        <p>The assassination is the subject of another story. Moments before, the archduke sees a man with an accordion. This is almost all. Verging on literary miracle-working (something that must be read because there is no way to convey or explain it), Hemon takes four pages to link world history to the history of his country, his family (his great-grandfather bought an accordion in Sarajevo that day) and his own emigre life.</p>
        <p>Except for the Kauders story, Hemon draws on his own life for the pieces in ''The Question of Bruno,'' though most are partly fictional. An exception, possibly, is the family reunion in ''Exchange of Pleasant Words,'' which has the largeness of a great memoir. Memoirs are sunset light; shadows of poetic and historic gravity lengthen out of the buoyant comedy.</p>
        <p>This one starts as a jocular history of the Hemon family, which moved to Bosnia from the Ukraine early in the century. According to legend, the original Hemon was a French soldier on Napoleon's retreat from Moscow. A Ukrainian peasant girl found him frozen in the woods, rescued and married him. In the 1960's a French visitor mentioned that there were Hemons in Brittany: this match-sliver of fact ignited a genealogical conflagration. Aleksandar's father organized a ''Hemoniad,'' a grand clan reunion on a family property in Bosnia before the war.</p>
        <p>Hemon gives us the feasting, the post-gorge somnolence, the flies ''greasing themselves to dazzling summer-fly glitter'' and speech after speech of Hemon family bragging. Cutting through is the skeptical voice of Aleksandar's mother, who comes to sit beside him. The tragic mask slips over the comic as she tells a story.</p>
        <p>During World War II a Muslim neighbor, pursued by the Serbian Chetniks, came to beg her father for his horse. The father, a Serb, gave it without a word. The Chetniks arrived, demanded the whereabouts of ''the circumcised dog,'' beat the father savagely and threatened to kill him. Again, not a word. It is a different kind of Balkan heroism, this double silence: one unknown or ignored in our contemporary annals. It is not broken so much as confirmed by the father's great and prophetic rant. He curses ''this world and the bloody sun and this country where everyone needs my horse.''</p>
        <p>Richard Eder writes book reviews and articles for The Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Richard Eder writes book reviews and articles for The Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
