<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Reviving a Neglected Art: Stenciling</title>
    <meta content="LICLINIC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218761"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HOME CLINIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOME REPAIR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E4D8173DF933A05754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="861" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Reviving a Neglected Art: Stenciling</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWARD R. LIPINSKI</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>STENCILING is an old art form. Neanderthal artists created patterns using their hands as stencils. They blew powdered pigment across their hands to capture the outline of their fingers on the walls of caves in Lascaux, France.</p>
        <p>Stenciling continued to be used throughout history as a decorating device to relieve the monotony of plain painted surfaces on walls, floors, furniture, paper and fabric surfaces.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>STENCILING is an old art form. Neanderthal artists created patterns using their hands as stencils. They blew powdered pigment across their hands to capture the outline of their fingers on the walls of caves in Lascaux, France.</p>
        <p>Stenciling continued to be used throughout history as a decorating device to relieve the monotony of plain painted surfaces on walls, floors, furniture, paper and fabric surfaces.</p>
        <p>In Colonial America, stenciling was a popular decorating technique because other forms of decoration -- paintings and wallpaper -- were unavailable.</p>
        <p>Colonial artists did not have access to the vibrant pigments readily available in Europe, so they created a softer, mellow palette from natural dyes obtained from indigenous plants and minerals.</p>
        <p>Stenciling gradually lost favor in homes as printed wallpaper and mass-produced lithographs became readily available in stores and mail-order catalogs. Now decorators and homeowners are rediscovering it as a way to add decorative accents to rooms and furniture.</p>
        <p>The creative do-it-yourselfer will find that it can be a rewarding hobby as well as a decorating technique.</p>
        <p>While stenciling may appear difficult, it is really an easy craft to learn and does not require any artistic ability or arcane skills. However, it does require patience in cutting the stencil, precision in aligning the patterns and care in applying the paint. Only a few simple and inexpensive tools are required: stencil paper, a stencil knife, paint applicators and, sometimes, a chalk line for aligning the patterns.</p>
        <p>Stencil paper has to be durable and paint-resistant. You can buy ready-made stencil paper, a thick plastic-coated stock, at large art supply stores or from stencil suppliers. (One supplier is the Stencil Collector, 1723 Tilghman Street, Allentown, Pa. 18104.) You can also make stencil paper out of manila file folders. Coat the paper with linseed oil or varnish it to make it paint-resistant.</p>
        <p>A craft knife with replaceable blades makes a suitable and inexpensive stencil-cutting knife. Beware a dull blade; you could end up tearing the stencil. Besides the cutting knife, you will need a surface to cut the stencils on. The best is a self-healing cutting mat (available at art supply stores).</p>
        <p>The traditional paint applicator for stencil work is a stiff-bristled stencil brush. It is important when applying paint to hold the brush vertically. This will create a stippling effect and allow you to blend tones together. The vertical posture will also keep the bristles from creeping under the stencil.</p>
        <p>The mistake most beginners make is in loading too much paint on the bristles. Dip only the tip of the brush in the paint, and before applying the paint to the stenciled area, do a test on a piece of scrap paper. Ideally, the paint should dry almost instantly; if not, there is too much paint on the brush. Wipe off the excess then try again.</p>
        <p>Almost any type of paint can be used for stencil work. First, check the label on the container to be sure the paint will adhere to the surface you intend to decorate. Satin finish water-based paints (available at home centers and paint stores) work well on most surfaces. Artists' liquid acrylic paints (available in jars at artist supply stores) are also good for stencil work on walls, but they do not adhere well to glossy or metal surfaces.</p>
        <p>You can also use paint in spray cans, but you must take care to mask surrounding areas from overspray. Also, spray-painting can present a safety hazard, so work in a well-ventilated area and wear a respirator designed for spray work.</p>
        <p>At first, you may find it difficult to design your own stencils, but there are a number of books in the library and from stencil suppliers that feature a variety of patterns suitable for walls, floors and furniture. Use a copy machine to reproduce them to an appropriate size, then mount them onto the stencil paper with rubber cement. Cut through the copy and the stencil paper to make your stencil.</p>
        <p>While you are applying the paint, you can hold small stencils in place with your hand or with masking tape, but large stencils are difficult to keep in position.</p>
        <p>A good way keep these pieces immobile as you work is by spraying the back with a repositionable adhesive. (One brand is 3M-Remount.) The stencil will be tacky enough to stay in place, but you can still peel it off the surface to reposition it if necessary. If possible, use this spray out of doors, because the overspray can make walls and surrounding surfaces sticky.</p>
        <p>Your first stenciling project should be a design on a small flat surface, like the lid of a chest or a door panel. As you gain confidence and your skills improve, you can work on a larger area, like a wall or a floor.</p>
        <p>HOME CLINIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
