<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Can She Stand the Heat?</title>
    <meta content="30PURNICT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218540"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Purnick, Joyce</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clift, Eleanor</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brazaitis, Tom</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Madam President: Shattering the Last Glass Ceiling (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505EED81F3BF933A05754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1130" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Can She Stand the Heat?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Joyce Purnick</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Purnick, Joyce</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Joyce Purnick reviews book Madam President: Shattering the Last Glass Ceiling by Eleanor Clift and Tom Brazaitis (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Madam President</p>
        <p>Shattering the Last Glass Ceiling.</p>
        <p>By Eleanor Clift and Tom Brazaitis.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 349 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>A Lisa Drew Book/Scribner. $26.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Madam President</p>
        <p>Shattering the Last Glass Ceiling.</p>
        <p>By Eleanor Clift and Tom Brazaitis.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 349 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>A Lisa Drew Book/Scribner. $26.</p>
        <p>A WOMAN president some day? Well, sure. What fair-minded American could object? But what kind of woman? Ah, now it gets tougher. Let's see: She should be attractive but not too attractive (might not be taken seriously). She has to be brainy but not come across that way. (Too threatening.) She can't be combative, like Harry Truman (unladylike); or blunt, like Lyndon Baines Johnson (ditto); or tacky, like Bill Clinton (imagine). She should be a centrist, to undercut the suspicion that a woman is soft on issues. And be married (or widowed), to demonstrate her family values and avoid the inevitable lesbian rumors. Having a few children is a good idea, too -- grown children, so she won't be accused of ignoring them in favor of her career. And oh yes, ending her sentences with question marks is good: it's feminine to sound apologetic.</p>
        <p>You get the picture. Sounds like a gross exaggeration. But it is reality, reflected in political life as we know it -- and in ''Madam President,'' the latest examination of the status of women in American politics. The Washington wife-and-husband writing team of Eleanor Clift and Tom Brazaitis have done a most comprehensive job, and a most depressing one, though that was clearly not their intention. They sunnily predict that a woman will be president ''soon,'' but then lay out the difficulties in exhaustive detail. Which is not hard to do.</p>
        <p>Consider this summer's national party conventions, starting tomorrow when the Republicans meet in Philadelphia. The only woman presidential hopeful crashed long ago (Elizabeth Dole), and no woman has been on either George W. Bush's or Al Gore's short list of likely running mates for months. It's revealing that 16 years after Geraldine A. Ferraro became the first woman to run for vice president on a major party ticket, she has had no successor. Her troubled race hardly inspired imitation. But there are more fundamental reasons for the paucity of female heavy hitters in politics. It's because of who we are.</p>
        <p>This anything-but-a-beach book, which looks at just about every woman in contemporary American politics, reminds us that we are still profoundly confused about women's roles. For instance, Clift and Brazaitis cite a recent poll showing that 90 percent of American voters say they could support a woman for president. Then, as they document the demands on women in public life, you wonder what woman could last long enough to run credibly for the White House. Women have to deal with everything from the timing of childbearing to proving they can raise the big bucks. A woman's looks are still so important that even after Clift and Brazaitis point out the media's obsession with appearance, their own portraits of women politicians repeatedly include descriptions like ''bouncy shoulder-length brown hair and dimples.''</p>
        <p>Women are forced to prove themselves in ways men are not. ''Everybody assumes that George Bush is going to be tough on criminals. I have to prove that I'm going to be tough,'' Ann Richards, the former governor of Texas, observes. ''You see the difference? And being tough doesn't ring any bell with women voters.'' A no-win. Same for politics and families. It's quite the irony that the average male politician parades his wife and children, while ''women always campaign alone,'' Senator Dianne Feinstein of California notes; most political husbands have independent careers and avoid the campaign trail. The book shows how rough women are on one another -- the first to complain (usually to a man) when another woman falters, and rarely willing to put sisterhood ahead of politics.</p>
        <p>Women are criticized for classic political ambition, as Elizabeth Holtzman was in 1992, when she wouldn't bow to Ferraro in New York's Democratic Senate primary. (A man won.) Who's the last male politician denounced for challenging a fellow man? Not that women are blameless. They can be nave and presumptuous. Why would Dole think she could run successfully for president, never having run for office before? Why was Ferraro offended by the interest in her life and investigative incursions into her family's finances? And why should Hillary Rodham Clinton get away with running in an adopted state as a first-time candidate for the Senate? At least Robert F. Kennedy had been attorney general of the United States.</p>
        <p>These problems have more than theoretical impact. It's no surprise that no woman emerged as an obvious vice-presidential candidate this year. Not enough women are in the pipeline. A vice-presidential candidate has to be a seasoned, appealing vote-getter, in a powerful enough position to attract votes. Today, only 3 of 50 elected governors are women. Only 9 of 100 senators are women; 56 of 435 members of the House of Representatives. More women are working their way up, being elected and appointed to administrative, deputy-+ and vice-something political jobs because men are more conscious of needing women in visible positions. Nineteen women are lieutenant governors, and 22.5 percent of the country's state legislators are women -- an increase of more than fivefold since 1969. Jane Swift of Massachusetts ran for lieutenant governor in 1998 when she was pregnant, and won; her pregnancy helped. Kathleen Kennedy Townsend, Maryland's lieutenant governor, has an enlightened husband willing to take an active role in raising their children and running their household.</p>
        <p>But the central question remains whether enough women will be elected to higher office to create a critical mass. Because only then will the country accept that women politicians can be just as good, bad and in-between as most men politicians. In 1956, John F. Kennedy wrote that the first woman president would need the wisdom of Eleanor Roosevelt, the leadership of Joan of Arc, the compassion of Queen Victoria, the cleverness of Clare Boothe Luce, the determination of the polio nurse Sister Kenny and the courage of Helen Keller. Kennedy might update a few of those names today, but the sentiment would surely be the same: A woman president? Another woman vice-presidential candidate? Fine. Some day? Of course. But what a good bit of luck that along with cornering the market on what we are told is that most female trait -- intuition -- women have learned patience.</p>
        <p>Joyce Purnick writes the Metro Matters column for The Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Joyce Purnick writes the Metro Matters column for The Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
