<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>FOLLOWING UP</title>
    <meta content="30FOLL$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218913"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fires and Firemen</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forest and Brush Fires</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Pine Barrens (Li)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Suffolk County (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Wildfire and Incident Management Academy</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Brookhaven National Laboratory</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kelley, Tina</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Following Up</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forest and Brush Fires</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02EEDE123DF933A05754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="712" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>FOLLOWING UP</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TINA KELLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kelley, Tina</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Wildfire and Incident Management Academy at Brookhaven National Laboratory was created following 1995 wildfires that destroyed thousands of acres of Suffolk County pine barrens; academy is now training hundreds of firefighters from all over East Coast; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Suffolk Wildfires Spawn A Firefighting Academy</p>
        <p>More than just the usual greenery among the cinders has sprung up after the 1995 wildfires that destroyed almost 7,000 acres of Suffolk County pine forests and damaged more than a dozen buildings. The Island now boasts something usually associated with ponderosa pines and majestic mountains: a national wildfire academy, the second in the country.</p>
        <p>Last year, 250 firefighters from all over the East Coast headed to the New York Wildfire and Incident Management Academy at the Brookhaven National Laboratory in Upton. The academy, now in its third year, is supported by tuition and the Pine Barrens Commission.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Suffolk Wildfires Spawn A Firefighting Academy</p>
        <p>More than just the usual greenery among the cinders has sprung up after the 1995 wildfires that destroyed almost 7,000 acres of Suffolk County pine forests and damaged more than a dozen buildings. The Island now boasts something usually associated with ponderosa pines and majestic mountains: a national wildfire academy, the second in the country.</p>
        <p>Last year, 250 firefighters from all over the East Coast headed to the New York Wildfire and Incident Management Academy at the Brookhaven National Laboratory in Upton. The academy, now in its third year, is supported by tuition and the Pine Barrens Commission.</p>
        <p>At the academy, firefighters study topics with titles like ''Fire Operations and Urban Interface,'' ''Cause Determination'' and even ''Firing Methods.''</p>
        <p>''By that we don't mean, 'Hey, pack up your stuff,' '' said David H. Fischler, the Suffolk County commissioner of fire, rescue and emergency services, but ''to burn off an area in front of a wildfire so the fire self-extinguishes because there's no more fuel in front of it.'' As for cause determination, fire officials were able to pinpoint, within three feet, where part of the 1995 fire started -- in a patch of cigarette butts outside a building where workers smoked.</p>
        <p>The fires also spawned the Wildfire Task Force, bringing together 30 fire departments in the pine barrens, as well as state agencies and ecology groups. The task force encourages good construction practices and sufficient clearances between trees and houses. It also works on firefighting tactics and ecological concerns.</p>
        <p>Happily Back at Work After Harassment Case</p>
        <p>In 1995, 15 women who worked at Del Laboratories on Long Island felt vindicated when they were awarded $1.185 million in a sexual harassment case against the company and its chief executive. At the time, the settlement against Del Labs, a cosmetics and pharmaceutical company based in Farmingdale, was the largest ever obtained by the federal Equal Employment Opportunity Commission.</p>
        <p>Although the company and the chief executive, Dan K. Wassong, admitted no wrongdoing, all employees were required to have training about sexual harassment in the workplace.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wassong's secretaries brought the suit, accusing him of grabbing the breast of one worker, conducting office business with his fly open and routinely using vulgar and abusive language.</p>
        <p>For one plaintiff, it is far easier to go to work every day now. Jonneigh Adrion, 31, of Sayville, N.Y., now has a 4-year-old son, is working again after difficulties with another boss and is planning to study law. She said she was interested in employment law -- she found only two Long Island lawyers with that specialty when she started her own case -- and might eventually specialize in sexual harassment cases.</p>
        <p>''I always wanted to be a lawyer, in high school, but after going through the case, I didn't want to do law at all,'' she said. ''I was fed up with it. When it doesn't involve you, it's easier to digest.''</p>
        <p>She is now an office manager for a lawyer she describes as appreciative and ''a real absolute doll.''</p>
        <p>Even after leaving Del Laboratories in 1992, she encountered another difficult working situation, this time involving a woman who supervised her at Estee Lauder, she said. ''I had a boss that cut my hair,'' she said. The supervisor, she said, believed that Ms. Adrion's hair was too long to look professional, and as Ms. Adrion was arranging it in a barrette, the supervisor snipped three or four inches off. Ms. Adrion said she had wanted to file charges, but did not.</p>
        <p>''You know, you feel like everyone is going to think you're like a complainer,'' she said. Besides, it was right after the Del case had been settled. ''After you've been through that, that seemed like nothing compared to what I went through with Mr. Wassong.'' He is still the company's chief executive.</p>
        <p>TINA KELLEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
