<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Defibrillators: Airline Update</title>
    <meta content="30PRAC$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218590"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRACTICAL TRAVELER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Defibrillators</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Heart</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nytravel</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Aviation Administration</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wade, Betsy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Columns/Practical Traveler</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Defibrillators</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Heart Disease</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Anatomy and Physiology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E7DA133AF933A05754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1170" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Defibrillators: Airline Update</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BETSY WADE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wade, Betsy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Betsy Wade Practical Traveler column update on heart defibrillators aboard US airlines; Federal Aviation Administration, concluding after yearlong survey that devices can save lives of unconscious people in cardiac arrest, drafts rule requiring airlines to buy buttery-driven defibrillators for all planes able to carry at least 30 passengers and one flight attendant; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HEART defibrillators are likely to be required aboard all big United States airliners within three years. The Federal Aviation Administration, acting on the basis of a one-year survey of 15 airlines' in-flight illnesses among passengers and crew, concluded that the devices, which can save lives of people who are unconscious in cardiac arrest, would be worth the cost.</p>
        <p>In May, the F.A.A. said it had drafted a rule requiring airlines to buy battery-driven defibrillators for all planes able to carry at least 30 passengers and one flight attendant. After 120 days for public comment, the rule -- which may be modified in that time -- is scheduled to take effect in September. The airlines are allowed three years to buy the devices and train crew to use them, although they can also be operated by untrained people because an electronic voice gives instructions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HEART defibrillators are likely to be required aboard all big United States airliners within three years. The Federal Aviation Administration, acting on the basis of a one-year survey of 15 airlines' in-flight illnesses among passengers and crew, concluded that the devices, which can save lives of people who are unconscious in cardiac arrest, would be worth the cost.</p>
        <p>In May, the F.A.A. said it had drafted a rule requiring airlines to buy battery-driven defibrillators for all planes able to carry at least 30 passengers and one flight attendant. After 120 days for public comment, the rule -- which may be modified in that time -- is scheduled to take effect in September. The airlines are allowed three years to buy the devices and train crew to use them, although they can also be operated by untrained people because an electronic voice gives instructions.</p>
        <p>Of the 10 major United States airlines, eight either have defibrillators on all their planes already or expect to by the end of the year. Only Trans World Airlines and America West have not begun the process.</p>
        <p>American Airlines, which was in the vanguard of domestic airlines with defibrillators, began putting the devices, about the size and weight of a desk dictionary, aboard its planes in 1997. According to John Hotard, a spokesman, all of its planes were equipped by March 1999. Alaska Airlines has completed the process, as have Delta and United. US Airways is 97 percent complete, according to David A. Castelveter, a spokesman, with fewer than 10 planes without defibrillators. All of the line's 50 new Airbuses have the devices, he said. Northwest Airlines reports it is about 50 percent complete and expects to finish by the end of the year. Southwest Airlines says the same, as does Continental, which adds that all of its 777's are now outfitted.</p>
        <p>A Work in Progress for Some</p>
        <p>T.W.A. has not begun the process. Christine Kelly, a spokeswoman, said: ''T.W.A. is evaluating various equipment options to determine the specific characteristics offered by the various manufacturers so that should the rule be officially issued, we would be ready to comply.''</p>
        <p>America West likewise has not begun installation, although it has selected the model it will buy. Its spokeswoman, Janice Monahan, said it expected to have installation on its 135 planes completed ''by the fall.''</p>
        <p>No one is keeping formal track of foreign airlines with defibrillators, although Dr. Claude Thibeault, the medical director of Air Canada, said that an informal group of airline medical directors had a general picture of which lines were equipped. He said that Qantas, Virgin Atlantic, British Airways, Air Zimbabwe, Swissair and Varig were known to have them. Air Canada is in process, he said.</p>
        <p>In introducing the forthcoming regulation in a radio speech in May, President Clinton said that the F.A.A. survey of in-flight illnesses from July 1998 through June 1999, which was initiated by the Aviation Medical Assistance Act of 1998, showed automatic external defibrillators' value. ''A.E.D.'s have proven effective in saving lives,'' he said, ''and I believe that all airline passengers should have access to this life-saving technology.''</p>
        <p>In defibrillation, the restarting of a heart that has stopped or has begun ineffective beating, known as ventricular fibrillation, time is of the essence. Medical studies show that chances of survival decrease 10 percent with each minute that passes without circulation of blood. Quick application of cardiopulmonary resuscitation, or CPR, can force blood into the body, particularly the brain, as a holding action, but the heart must be started again. The defibrillator does that, and all the television dramas showing interns running to a bedside with equipment emphasize this need for speed. Diversion of an airplane to the nearest airport may help in other cases, but takes way too long to help in cardiac arrest.</p>
        <p>Fifteen airlines carrying 85 percent of American domestic passengers contributed data to the one-year Government study; they submitted 188 usable ''medical event'' reports: 177 that occurred on board planes -- in flight, at the gate or in taxiing; 10 in the boarding ramp or the terminal, and 1 in a cab to the airport.</p>
        <p>Of the 177 events, 119 were thought to involve the heart; the average age of these passengers was 62. Sixty-four of the 119 died; 10 were known to have survived, and the other outcomes were unknown.</p>
        <p>While the study was going on, of course, airlines were phasing in defibrillators. In 14 on-board events and 3 on the ground, the devices were used, and four of the victims survived; the F.A.A. checked later and found these passengers still alive. For the on-board cardiac events, the report said, an A.E.D. was reported ''not available'' in 40 cases and ''not needed'' in 12. There were 74 aircraft diversions reported because of passenger medical emergencies; 52 involved cardiac events.</p>
        <p>American Airlines gathered data before and after the Government study. Dr. David McKenas of its corporate medical department, testifying in Congress, said that defibrillators saved 11 lives over three years.  He said the results were ''spectacular'' in comparison with those that emergency medical services on the ground reported.</p>
        <p>Despite gaps in its data, the F.A.A. said it concluded that ''deaths occur on air carriers and certain medical interventions . . . may change the outcome for some.'' Projecting ''conservatively'' against a potential total of 7.58 billion passengers in the next 10 years, it concluded that 55 outcomes of future medical events might be changed by defibrillators.</p>
        <p>The draft rule also requires additions to the standard medical kit carried on board. It also carries a good Samaritan provision protecting those who help from random prosecution.</p>
        <p>The F.A.A. voiced some caution about its steps. ''The intent of the regulation is to provide options for treatment,'' it said, ''not to raise expectation in the passenger or physician community regarding the level of medical care available in flight.''</p>
        <p>Comments on the draft regulation may be mailed in duplicate to Department of Transportation Dockets, Docket FAA-2000-7719, 400 Seventh Street SW, Room Plaza 401, Washington, D.C. 20590. Instructions for electronic filing may be found at dms.dot.gov/.</p>
        <p>Sending an EKG by Satellite</p>
        <p>In the meantime, two overseas airlines, British Airways and Virgin Atlantic, which both have defibrillators on their fleets, announced plans to add an additional medical device, one that can transmit an electrocardiogram by satellite from a conscious but ill passenger to a medical center on the ground.</p>
        <p>Dr. Michael Bagshaw, head of medical services for British Airways, said that the Micromedical Biolog monitor, about the size of a deck of cards, could be linked to the seatback telephone that transmits to a satellite and then to a 24-hour medical team in Arizona called Medlink. The team may recommend aspirin, nitroglycerin or diversion of the plane, Dr. Bagshaw said. The Biolog device is distributed by Medtronic Physio-Control in Redmond, Wash. Virgin Atlantic is using a device called Tempus 2000, made by Remote Diagnostic Technologies in Hampshire, England.</p>
        <p>PRACTICAL TRAVELER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
