<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The World; Ulster Finds Its Way Out of One Maze</title>
    <meta content="30HOGE$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218861"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Northern Ireland</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Maze Prison (Northern Ireland)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hoge, Warren</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/Northern Ireland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E2DC153DF933A05754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1029" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The World; Ulster Finds Its Way Out of One Maze</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WARREN HOGE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hoge, Warren</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>More than 400 prisoners have been released from Northern Ireland's Maze prison, which at one time held as many as 1,800 inmates and over time held nearly 30,000 prisoners; 15 prisoners remain, and prison is set to close at year's end; among former Maze inmates are many of the men now trying to guide Northern Ireland's political future; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THOUGH the Maze prison takes its name from the suburban village outside Belfast where it is located, it is an apt word for a place that is so representative of the perverse paths Ulster has  followed in its struggle to find its way from war to peace.</p>
        <p>The brutalist fortresslike building ringed by rusted barbed wire and studded with searchlights and watchtowers has drawn the world's eye for its hunger strikes, riots, killings, mass escapes, posturing paramilitary fighters and alumni like Gerry Adams, president of Sinn Fein, the political party of the Irish Republican Army. It held more guerrillas than any other prison in the world, and the ruthlessness and political commitment of its inhabitants made it a place where guards were often more endangered than inmates.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THOUGH the Maze prison takes its name from the suburban village outside Belfast where it is located, it is an apt word for a place that is so representative of the perverse paths Ulster has  followed in its struggle to find its way from war to peace.</p>
        <p>The brutalist fortresslike building ringed by rusted barbed wire and studded with searchlights and watchtowers has drawn the world's eye for its hunger strikes, riots, killings, mass escapes, posturing paramilitary fighters and alumni like Gerry Adams, president of Sinn Fein, the political party of the Irish Republican Army. It held more guerrillas than any other prison in the world, and the ruthlessness and political commitment of its inhabitants made it a place where guards were often more endangered than inmates.</p>
        <p>It has at once embodied Ulster's most evil instincts and shaped many of the men now trying to guide its political future. Five members of the new Northern Ireland Assembly were Maze inmates; in a society of 1.6 million, nearly 30,000 were prisoners. Behind the 1998 accord that has brought stability to Northern Ireland is a conviction that these people, once perpetrators of mayhem, can be a significant constituency for calm.</p>
        <p>Eighty-seven guerrillas walked free last week in the last stage of the pact's early release program, under which more than 400 prisoners have been let out. The Maze prison, which has held as many as 1,800 inmates, now houses 15 and is to close at year's end.</p>
        <p>Seeing the bombers and killers come out the Maze's turnstile exit is dreadfully hard for many residents of Northern Ireland, since most of the crimes were recent, and for victims' families the memories are fresh. The released do not express regret or remorse. Instead, they say they were participating in a war and trying to protect their communities.</p>
        <p>Still, the question most longingly asked these days by the citizens of Northern Ireland is whether the war that has cost 3,600 lives is finally over, and they may find some reassurance in the shuttering of the Maze and the freeing of inmates who always insisted on being considered prisoners of war.</p>
        <p>The Maze began as a prisoner-of-war camp on the site of Long Kesh Royal Air Force Base to handle the hundreds of people arrested and interned without trial in the early 1970's. Its Nissen huts and tents made way several years later for eight stolid H-blocks, so-called because of their shape, housing 100 cells each and suitable for keeping members of murderously opposing paramilitary groups segregated from one another.</p>
        <p>In 1976, a decision by the British government to treat inmates not as prisoners of war but as criminals led to riots and a period when the distinctive aerial photo of the jail became a norm on television news. Inmates went ''on the blanket,'' wearing bedclothes instead of  prison uniforms, and started their ''dirty protest'': refusing to bathe, littering their cells and corridors with broken furniture and smearing walls with their feces.</p>
        <p>In 1981, Bobby Sands, a convicted I.R.A. bomber, started a hunger strike that 66 days later cost him his life. Nine other inmates starved themselves to death before the protest was dropped, but Mr. Sands became a republican hero and brought international scrutiny of ''the troubles,'' as the Catholic-Protestant sectarian violence is commonly called.</p>
        <p>Another aspect of the Sands case pointed to the future. A month before his death, Mr. Sands was elected a member of the British parliament from Northern Ireland -- the first indication that Sinn Fein might be able to attract widespread political support.</p>
        <p>While the Maze -- or Long Kesh, as inmates often still insist on calling it to emphasize its prisoner-of-war origins -- remained a chaotic and violent place through the 1980's and 1990's, it also provided many guerrillas with their first education since grade school. The men largely studied political and social issues and emerged from prison with so-called Free University degrees. The Shankill Road, the principal avenue of Protestant Belfast, and the Falls Road, the main street through the largest Catholic neighborhoods, are now home to scores of storefront community action organizations run by former prisoners who are trying to keep youths from perpetuating sectarian violence.</p>
        <p>Through these years, the Maze developed into prisons within a prison, with entire H-blocks in the control of the paramilitary inmates. Prisoners elected their own leaders who negotiated conditions directly with the prison governor. Prisoners won the right not to be locked in their cells, and guards were forbidden to search their quarters without gaining the commanders' approval and a day's notice. In an unsuccessful prison break three years ago, I.R.A. men managed to keep undetected the 13 tons of earth they had dug up while making a tunnel.</p>
        <p>Inmates showed their growing power in ways ranging from the cooperative to the menacing. During the last two decades, 22 guards and a deputy governor of the Maze were killed outside the prison by guerrillas acting on information from inside. In recent years, leaders inside the Maze gave the political parties representing paramilitary groups the necessary go-ahead to participate in the talks that produced the 1998 settlement.</p>
        <p>Talk has already begun about what to do with the  Maze. Suggestions range from destroying every gray brick of it to preserving it as a museum, as was done in South Africa with the Robben Island jail, where Nelson Mandela was held. Whatever the outcome, the closing is a powerful symbol and may provide a hopeful answer to a question posed at the end of a popular republican song of the 1970's. ''And will the last obscenity,'' it concluded, ''be the grim H-block cell?''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
