<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Way We Live Now: 7-30-00: Map; Attack of the Killer Bunnies</title>
    <meta content="WLN112734" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218595"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Insects</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Newman, Andy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insects</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E6D9103AF933A05754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1601" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Way We Live Now: 7-30-00: Map; Attack of the Killer Bunnies</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Andy Newman</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Newman, Andy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on variety of insects and other pests that are overrunning various communities across the country; map; drawings (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>What with killer mosquitoes stalking the streets of the city, disease-bearing ticks haunting the summer house, rats wilding through housing projects (and even Gracie Mansion), New Yorkers may feel singled out by the forces of nature. But while we spray and swat, citizens of towns all across America are also fending off unwanted fauna, from swarms of marauding insects to the hundreds of thousands of mice that overran Apopka, Fla., after the state flooded 14,000 acres of abandoned farmland, sending the local rodents scurrying for higher ground. Herewith, a quick tour of what's plaguing our nation:</p>
        <p>Seal Beach, Calif.  Cottontail rabbits recently became improbable figures of terror when thousands of them overran the Leisure World retirement community in Orange County, digging up gardens and creating fresh hazards on the golf course. The population had grown since wildlife officials removed the foxes that used to live in the area, and had been forced into the open since developers had cut down local woodlands. ''They're everywhere,'' says Bill Narang, Leisure World's administrator. ''Some of these rabbits are entering people's homes, leaving droppings. Wild rabbits are on the walkways when people are walking there. You can see they have no fear. And the average resident here is 79 years old, so you can see why some of them are having a hard time with it.'' Leisure World's proposal to shoot the rabbits has so far succeeded in flushing out only angry animal rights advocates.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>What with killer mosquitoes stalking the streets of the city, disease-bearing ticks haunting the summer house, rats wilding through housing projects (and even Gracie Mansion), New Yorkers may feel singled out by the forces of nature. But while we spray and swat, citizens of towns all across America are also fending off unwanted fauna, from swarms of marauding insects to the hundreds of thousands of mice that overran Apopka, Fla., after the state flooded 14,000 acres of abandoned farmland, sending the local rodents scurrying for higher ground. Herewith, a quick tour of what's plaguing our nation:</p>
        <p>Seal Beach, Calif.  Cottontail rabbits recently became improbable figures of terror when thousands of them overran the Leisure World retirement community in Orange County, digging up gardens and creating fresh hazards on the golf course. The population had grown since wildlife officials removed the foxes that used to live in the area, and had been forced into the open since developers had cut down local woodlands. ''They're everywhere,'' says Bill Narang, Leisure World's administrator. ''Some of these rabbits are entering people's homes, leaving droppings. Wild rabbits are on the walkways when people are walking there. You can see they have no fear. And the average resident here is 79 years old, so you can see why some of them are having a hard time with it.'' Leisure World's proposal to shoot the rabbits has so far succeeded in flushing out only angry animal rights advocates.</p>
        <p>California  The glossy-winged sharpshooter, a half-inch-long, fast-flying brown-shelled pest, is spreading through the vineyards of California. When it feeds, by sucking on grapevines, it leaves behind bacteria that cause the plant to shrivel up and die. Having laid waste to about a quarter of the vineyards in Temecula Valley, southeast of Los Angeles, the bugs are now working their way north toward the heart of wine country. In June, the U.S.D.A. declared an agricultural emergency in the state. Earlier this month, a swarm of sharpshooters was found 10 miles from a cluster of vineyards worth $100 million a year.</p>
        <p>Las Vegas  Continuing their inexorable northward march, Africanized honeybees -- more commonly known as killer bees -- have begun to make their presence felt on the Strip. In recent months, a dog was stung to death, a man was stung 30 times and a 77-year-old woman was stung 500 times. (Paramedics stanched the attack by dousing her with water; while an ambulance sped her to the hospital they scooped bees out of her mouth.) Scientists say the subspecies -- which escaped from a lab in Brazil in 1957 and crossed into the United States in 1990 -- cannot be stopped but can be controlled. ''What Las Vegas is basically doing is keeping its citizens educated and stressing the fact that we don't want Africanized bees in an urban neighborhood,'' says Gina Stoneking Gray, the bee coordinator for the Nevada Department of Agriculture.</p>
        <p>Marshall, Tex.  While most towns try to stamp out their pests, others have embraced them. Hidalgo, Tex., where killer bees first entered the country, has erected a monument to the yellow menace. In another corner of the state, Marshall, a city of 25,000, holds a Fire Ant Festival every October. ''If you can't get rid of them, why not do a festival about them, something wild and crazy, try to make money off it?'' reasons Pam Whisenant, the local tourism director. The fair features a roundup, in which contestants covered in protective clothing try to fill a jug with ants, and an ant-calling contest, with junior and senior divisions. ''We have no idea what a fire ant call actually sounds like,'' she admits, ''so people have had to get creative. Some people have gotten to where they dress up like fire ants and do little jingles.''</p>
        <p>Naples, N.Y., and Marston, Md.  Twice this year, flies have materialized in awesome numbers and overwhelmed small farming areas. In early April, a farmer in Marston spread wagonloads of chicken feces over his hayfields; soon after came the flies, blackening ceilings and screen doors and eventually forcing the cancellation of graduation parties. Then in late May, an egg farmer in Naples dumped 200 tons of chicken manure on some fields. Within days, clouds of flies formed and swarmed over nearby homes. Dead flies lay several inches deep around the houses, whose human residents were forced to flee. Both infestations settled down with a few weeks of spraying and swatting, but it has happened yet again in a nearby town. ''If you're going to spread chicken manure in the summertime,'' says Barry Fortune, a local county health official, ''you're asking for trouble.''</p>
        <p>Pennsylvania  Gypsy moths, whose leaf-devouring blue-and-red-dotted caterpillars were, during the 1980's, as much a part of the Northeast suburban landscape as Duran Duran posters, are back with a vengeance. The moths were knocked out for much of the 90's by a fungus called Entomophaga maimaiga, but it was so successful it ate itself out of a food source and fell dormant. The moths quickly rebounded. Pennsylvania suffered gypsy-moth damage to 280,000 acres of forest in 1999 and as many as 1.5 million acres this year. ''There are entire ridge tops that for miles have been stripped bare,'' says Larry D. Rhoads, the chief entomologist at the state's Division of Forest Pest Management. New Jersey, Virginia and West Virginia have also been hit hard.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
