<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Keep Your Eye on the ... Golfwear</title>
    <meta content="30INTE$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218801"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="COUNTERINTELLIGENCE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Romana, Claudia</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Witchel, Alex</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6DF143DF933A05754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1515" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Keep Your Eye on the ... Golfwear</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEX WITCHEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Witchel, Alex</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on golf fashions designed by Claudia Romana, who models them at Poxabogue Golf Center in Bridgehampton, NY; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LET'S just say that golf is not my sport. First of all, my hand-eye coordination is bad enough that I still button my shirt wrong. Second, the idea of getting up at dawn for anything is out of the question. And third, do I have to even say it? Those clothes! Bathroom wallpaper with collars for the women, not to mention lime green pants for the men, with navy whales -- or ducks -- embroidered on them. And all in the name of a sport, to hear devotees describe it, that is the ultimate contest of man versus himself. Well, here's a news flash. With ducks on your pants, you just lost. Both of you.</p>
        <p>Which is why I wasn't surprised last week at the Poxabogue Golf Center in Bridgehampton, N.Y., when a woman on the driving range took one look at Claudia Romana and said loudly to her pro: ''Who is she? I like her shirt.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LET'S just say that golf is not my sport. First of all, my hand-eye coordination is bad enough that I still button my shirt wrong. Second, the idea of getting up at dawn for anything is out of the question. And third, do I have to even say it? Those clothes! Bathroom wallpaper with collars for the women, not to mention lime green pants for the men, with navy whales -- or ducks -- embroidered on them. And all in the name of a sport, to hear devotees describe it, that is the ultimate contest of man versus himself. Well, here's a news flash. With ducks on your pants, you just lost. Both of you.</p>
        <p>Which is why I wasn't surprised last week at the Poxabogue Golf Center in Bridgehampton, N.Y., when a woman on the driving range took one look at Claudia Romana and said loudly to her pro: ''Who is she? I like her shirt.''</p>
        <p>She and everyone else. Ms. Romana, 36, is one of a new breed of golfwear designers who realize that the women who wear Armani in the boardroom have no intention of taking to the course dressed like Emmett Kelly. There is also a new generation of Tiger Woods disciples, young urbanites (read from minorities) and increasing numbers of women, who are coming to the game with no frame of reference for country club frump. And where there's a market, there are companies like Gucci, Prada and Tommy Hilfiger all jumping on it. In that regard, Ms. Romana's timing is impeccable: this is her second season in a business where demand for her simple, elegant clothes designed mostly in neutral tones instead of pastels has steadily grown. The line, sold under the label Golf by Claudia Romana (www.golfbycr.com), is also affordable: capri pants, trousers, skorts, tops and dresses sell in the $55-to-$85 range.</p>
        <p>Rona Cherry, editor in chief of Golf Digest Woman, said the changes in wardrobe were long overdue: ''Golf clothes have been totally out of sync with fashion. We've noticed a big change this year with more form-fitting clothes, cutout backs. At the U.S. Women's Open, Pearl Sinn, a young Korean player, was wearing a white sheer top and you could see the bra. Today, you don't have to be stuck with Bermuda shorts anymore.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Romana takes it even further. ''Golf clothes should look like streetwear but still be active,'' she said. ''So many of these companies think golfers have naturally bad taste, selling all that canary yellow and powder puff blue. I was playing with an attractive woman recently who looked like a mad bird-watcher. I said, 'Honey, let me help you.' You have to have all your senses together to play golf.'' Which Ms. Romana does diligently, at this course among others, public and private, in the New York metropolitan area. I joined her here to 'play Pox' as people say of this hip public course, which despite -- or maybe because of -- its inherent democracy, attracts celebrities like Cindy Crawford.</p>
        <p>On this particular day, Ms. Romana was by far the best-dressed woman around, in her stone-colored capri pants and black top with white piping and tee holders, which are her trademark. She was also wearing men's black Nike shoes. ''I like them better than the women's,'' she said. ''I think the white ones look dorky and they make your feet look huge.''</p>
        <p>Her designs include a detachable pouch for balls, so that form-fitting outfits stay that way. Despite my better judgment, I put on a skort (a combination of shorts and skirt -- think culottes) and a top. I looked like a quasi-hip suburban mom. The good news was that the skort's accommodating stretch made it almost as comfy as a pair of pj's.</p>
        <p>But as Ms. Romana stepped up to the first hole to practice her swing, I had that sinking sensation from gym classes past and knew I'd never make it, no matter what I was wearing. A couple appeared behind us. The woman was dressed in Gap khakis and a white T-shirt and looked as miserable as I did. I brightened. ''I'll try to be fast,'' I said, and she shook her head. ''Don't worry, I'm not good,'' she said. I smiled. ''It's hard to be worse than me.'' She grimaced. ''I'll give it a shot.''</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Ms. Romana, looking like an advertisement, hit her ball into the wild blue yonder. The most I can say for myself was that I was brilliant -- had we been playing miniature golf.</p>
        <p>After butchering the first hole, I decided that to truly test the give in the skort, I needed to sit down immediately, preferably with an iced tea. The woman behind us looked longingly as we turned tail and headed for the restaurant, a superior vantage point, I decided, to scope out the general state of golf course fashion. It was truly ghastly. The women looked like boxy boys, in long baggy shorts and long short-sleeved T-shirts. Ms. Romana agreed. ''I can wear my golf trousers on the plane, just take the pouch off, and they're fine,'' she said. ''If you're afraid to stop and get gas on the way to the course, you're wearing a funny outfit. If it screams golf, it's not comfortable.''</p>
        <p>Michael Caruso, editor in chief of Maximum Golf, a new monthly magazine, agreed, when I reached him by phone. ''As golf has gotten younger, with the advent of Tiger Woods,'' he said, ''it has also gotten sexier. For the first time, 57 percent of players are under 40. Younger men don't have the gender barriers that older guys have, the ones who are usually playing to escape their wives. There's a lot more flirting out on the course. People are finding golf sexy.''</p>
        <p>So much so that Maximum Golf will sponsor a singles event, Golf in the City, at Chelsea Piers on Sept. 21. ''It'll be like an episode of 'Sex in the City' with golf clubs,'' Mr. Caruso predicted.</p>
        <p>Still, golf has not become as oversexed as say, tennis, whose professional players, like Anna Kournikova, have recently been criticized for wearing skimpy outfits. ''Golf is not about showing panties,'' Ms. Cherry said. ''For four hours you've got to feel comfortable and look good, a woman first and foremost.''</p>
        <p>Why has golf's fashion revolution taken so long? ''Women had other battles to fight,'' she explained. ''We had to get on the course first, and once we were there, we wanted to fit in. Look at the working world in the 70's, with women wearing the suits and bow-tie blouses. But now, the clothes are sophisticated, sporty and functional.''</p>
        <p>Of course, as Ms. Romana points out, the country club culture still holds sway in the golf world. ''A lot of clubs are restrictive about dress codes,'' she said. ''General dress code is collar or sleeves for women and men both, and in some clubs men have to wear pants, no shorts. Regulation length has to hit no more than two inches above the knee. I had much shorter things, which people liked, but they can't wear them in their clubs. And a lot of them require that the clothes carry their logos.'' She shrugged. ''Does everyone really want to look like a souvenir?''</p>
        <p>Though Ms. Romana has a solid handle on her market, she has only lived here for 12 years. Originally from Germany, where her parents own a resort hotel, she was introduced to golf by a former boyfriend during a trip to Portugal. ''I couldn't afford to play in Germany because you had to be a member,'' she said. ''I found an antique set of wooden clubs at a flea market and practiced in my backyard at 5 a.m.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Romana (she uses her mother's maiden name) has had a variety of fashion jobs in New York, including designing men's wear for J. Crew. One of her happiest discoveries here has been public courses, not only for the joy of playing, but to build her client base. She has never advertised, relying instead on word of mouth, and women seeing how good she looks. Beside her Internet business, she has started doing trunk shows at country clubs, and a dozen  club pro shops now carry her line.</p>
        <p>''Most of my customers are professional women who have to go on company outings,'' Ms. Romana said. ''One customer said, 'I can't play, but they all loved me because I looked good.' '' She smiled. ''I always say, 'I can't promise to improve your game but I can promise you'll look better no matter how you play.' ''</p>
        <p>Well, even if all you're doing is drinking iced tea, that is the American way, isn't it?</p>
        <p>COUNTERINTELLIGENCE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
