<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BEHIND THE WHEEL/Porsche Boxster S -- 2 German Makers Go Separate Ways on Muscle vs. Mass; Added Power Fulfills a Promise</title>
    <meta content="30PORS$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218796"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Porsche Ag</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Passell, Peter</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DEED6173DF933A05754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="905" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BEHIND THE WHEEL/Porsche Boxster S -- 2 German Makers Go Separate Ways on Muscle vs. Mass; Added Power Fulfills a Promise</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER PASSELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Passell, Peter</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Behind the Wheel report on Porsche Boxster S; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NEW! Improved! Few products deserve those exclamation points, but the Porsche Boxster S is an exception. What began as a fun roadster has been transformed into a serious sports car, at the added expense of a relatively modest $9,000.</p>
        <p>The plain-vanilla Porsche Boxster came to America in 1997, just as Mercedes-Benz and BMW were landing their own pricey little roadsters. All three found enthusiastic, if somewhat different, customers. The Mercedes SLK230, with its soft ride, automatic transmission, retractable hardtop and candy colors, attracted women buyers. The BMW Z3, with its elegant retro looks and initially tame engine, picked up a preppier suburban crowd. Meanwhile, the Boxster, with its swoopy futuristic sheet metal and austere ride, was slotted as the roadster for real drivers -- those who craved an entry-level sports car rather than a touring vehicle for weekends in Napa or the Hamptons.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NEW! Improved! Few products deserve those exclamation points, but the Porsche Boxster S is an exception. What began as a fun roadster has been transformed into a serious sports car, at the added expense of a relatively modest $9,000.</p>
        <p>The plain-vanilla Porsche Boxster came to America in 1997, just as Mercedes-Benz and BMW were landing their own pricey little roadsters. All three found enthusiastic, if somewhat different, customers. The Mercedes SLK230, with its soft ride, automatic transmission, retractable hardtop and candy colors, attracted women buyers. The BMW Z3, with its elegant retro looks and initially tame engine, picked up a preppier suburban crowd. Meanwhile, the Boxster, with its swoopy futuristic sheet metal and austere ride, was slotted as the roadster for real drivers -- those who craved an entry-level sports car rather than a touring vehicle for weekends in Napa or the Hamptons.</p>
        <p>I fit myself in the last category, but was a bit frustrated by the original Boxster's elusive hints of greatness. And $40,000-plus seemed high for a roadster of modest comfort, whose performance was so overshadowed by the muscular Porsche 911. The company didn't have any trouble selling the cars, and still doesn't, but it went back and finished the job. The Boxster S is everything I wanted the first time around.</p>
        <p>How did Porsche accomplish this transformation? The engineers started with the same horizontally opposed six-cylinder engine that sits just forward of the rear wheels in both models. But they increased the engine's displacement from 2.5 liters (in the 1999 Boxster) to 3.2 liters, giving it 250 horsepower as compared with 201 horsepower. (For 2000, the standard-issue Boxster has 217 horsepower.) The greater displacement, complemented by improvements in both the air-intake system and the electronics, also raised the maximum torque by 25 percent, to a hefty 225 foot-pounds. Most of that torque, by the way, is available at relatively low engine speeds.</p>
        <p>Of course, it takes a lot more than muscle to make a sports car. A perfectly adequate five-speed manual transmission has been replaced by the mechanically tougher six-speed gearbox from the 911. The 16-inch wheels were replaced by 17-inch ones that carry wider, lower-profile speed-rated rubber. The big disc brakes were replaced with even bigger disc brakes (again, from the 911 parts bin). And the suspension was beefed up to improve high-speed cornering stability.</p>
        <p>The visual cues distinguishing the Boxster S are, to say the least, discreet: a third air intake at the front bumper, twin tailpipe outlets, different wheels to show off the big brake calipers painted red. The interior plastic and leather are highlighted with aluminum trim.</p>
        <p>The ergonomics are excellent, with comfortable, supportive bucket seats and a mix of dials, digital readouts and idiot lights that minimizes distractions from the road. But Porsche made some improvements for the S version, notably a height adjustment for the seats and a steering wheel that telescopes as well as tilts. The power softtops on the two models are nearly identical, but Porsche added padding to the inside of the top on the Boxster S, which provides significant sound insulation to an already nicely fitted top. A removable aluminum roof is an option on both Boxsters.</p>
        <p>All this amounts to preface. What counts in deciding whether the S is worth the extra bucks is how the new version compares on the road. And here, there's just no contest. The engine on the ordinary Boxster still feels a touch sluggish in hard acceleration. The Boxster S may be less than a second faster to 60 miles per hour (5.7 seconds versus 6.4) but feels much stronger at engine speeds below 4,000 r.p.m. Indeed, the S engine offers so much torque across so wide a band that its feels fine in third gear anywhere from 20 to 80 miles an hour -- a flexibility that pays off in heavy traffic where frequent shifting can be a big bore.</p>
        <p>The differences in steering and handling are yet more impressive. While both Boxsters offer marvelous road manners and both have rear spoilers that extend automatically at 75 m.p.h. to offset the tendency of the body to take off, the S is more the master in a variety of driving situations. It stays heavier and more stable on rough roads, yet takes corners at higher speeds without a hint of roll.</p>
        <p>Both Boxsters come with an optional traction control system that uses both the brakes and the engine to prevent the rear wheels from sliding on slippery surfaces. Those who want to corner using controlled oversteer can shut off the system with a button. But the fat tires on the S are so grippy that aggressive ''throttle-steering,'' pushing the car hard enough so that the rear wheels slide, would probably not be practical in real-world situations for any but the most skilled drivers.</p>
        <p>Complaints? Just a few. The interior seems a bit cheesy for a $50,000 car: in my otherwise delightful week of driving the Boxster S, two pieces of interior plastic trim self-destructed and one idiot light refused to go off. This shouldn't surprise; the original Boxster proved to be far from 100 percent reliable in long-term tests conducted by several magazines.</p>
        <p>By the same token, too many things that should be standard on a car this expensive are options: cruise control, premium sound, leather, wind deflector and cassette and CD storage units for the dash.</p>
        <p>INSIDE TRACK: Magic the second time around.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
