<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Balancing Snack Food and Muslim Culture</title>
    <meta content="30DIVE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="A Diverse Island" name="series_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218660"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Convenience Stores</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Trinidad and Tobago</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">India</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Pakistan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Syosset (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Seven-Eleven Stores</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mir, Shamina Khan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Saslow, Linda</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Pakistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Trinidad and Tobago</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Trinidad and Tobago/Trinidad</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Trinidad and Tobago/Tobago</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E6D61E3AF933A05754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1314" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Balancing Snack Food and Muslim Culture</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LINDA SASLOW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Saslow, Linda</byline>
      <dateline>SYOSSET</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article in series on relationships between Long Island natives and immigrants profiles Shamina Khan Mir, Muslim and native of Trinidad who owns 7-Eleven convenience store in Syosset; his six workers are also Muslim and all natives of India or Pakistan; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN customers come into the 7-Eleven in North Syosset to buy a cup of coffee, lottery tickets or a Slurpee, few of them recognize the owner.</p>
        <p>''Many customers know my face, but don't know that I'm the boss because I usually try to hide,'' said Shamina Khan Mir, a native of Trinidad who bought the convenience store in 1980. ''I like to keep a low profile.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN customers come into the 7-Eleven in North Syosset to buy a cup of coffee, lottery tickets or a Slurpee, few of them recognize the owner.</p>
        <p>''Many customers know my face, but don't know that I'm the boss because I usually try to hide,'' said Shamina Khan Mir, a native of Trinidad who bought the convenience store in 1980. ''I like to keep a low profile.''</p>
        <p>But behind the first impression of a modest woman is an ambitious, successful entrepreneur who single-handedly runs the bustling store, one of 82 7-Elevens in Nassau County and one of seven owned by women.</p>
        <p>A resident since 1966, a citizen since 1970 and a Long Islander since 1974, Ms. Mir has become Americanized, but at the same time retains her West Indian identity.</p>
        <p>''I live according to the specific circumstances,'' she said. ''When I come to work, I wear Western clothing and eat American foods, including Slurpees. But when I go to a religious function, I usually dress in a shalwar, which is a long dress with pants underneath, and I wear a veil, as is the custom among Muslim women. Then I'm also more likely to eat the foods of our culture.''</p>
        <p>On a recent morning at her 7-Eleven, fashionably dressed in a red summer dress with sandals, her hair casually styled and nails perfectly manicured, Ms. Mir -- typically -- kept behind the scenes, changing the filters on the coffee makers, for example, while her employees helped customers lined up at the register. The store has a staff of six, all natives of India or Pakistan.</p>
        <p>''It didn't start out that way,'' she said. ''When I first came here, I had American college students working for me. But then they went back to school, and I had to replace them.</p>
        <p>Through her husband, who is Pakistani, Ms. Mir heard of someone looking for a job. ''Once I hired him, he knew someone else, who knew someone else,'' she said. ''I never even had to put up a sign in the window, and before I knew it, I had a great staff of hard-working people.''</p>
        <p>Although her customers might not understand the easy fit between a boss from the West Indies and her staff of Indians and Pakistanis, there are more similarities than meet the eye, Ms. Mir explained: ''We are all Muslims. We eat the same foods and share many of the same customs.'</p>
        <p>Jyoti Bhagat, who has been working at the 7-Eleven for a year, is a native of India and a resident of Merrick. Though Ms. Bhagat's two children, ages 20 and 13, are American-born, she has not become an American citizen.</p>
        <p>Behind the register, Ms. Bhagat is a visible blend of two cultures. Dressed in the store's red uniform jacket, speaking to customers in perfect English, she also wears a small red dot between her eyebrows, the bindi, an age-old Indian tradition that means she is a married woman.</p>
        <p>''Some customers are curious and ask me why I wear the dot,'' Ms. Bhagat said. ''Only once in a while, I hear a snide comment.'</p>
        <p>Ethnic slurs from customers are rare, Ms. Mir said, but do happen. ''We've had staff meetings to discuss how to handle these incidents,'' she said. ''The best response is no response. You put a smile on your face, ignore any negative comments and just walk away.'</p>
        <p>For Ms. Mir, the fifth of eight children, the journey from one culture to another began after she finished college in 1966, when she moved from Trinidad to New York City, where several members of her family had already immigrated seeking better job opportunities. Life in the United States began in an apartment on 92nd Street in Manhattan while working part time as a secretary, first in the Garment District and then on Wall Street, and taking business courses.</p>
        <p>Unlike many other immigrants, she never faced a language barrier because in Trinidad English is the primary language.</p>
        <p>''At first, adjusting to a new culture was difficult,'' Ms. Mir said. ''I had never worked before, and that was probably the biggest change. But I got used to it pretty quickly.''</p>
        <p>In 1974, while pregnant with her first child, Ms. Mir and her husband moved to Huntington, then seven years later to Woodbury, where she raised her three children, who all graduated from Syosset High School. She now lives in Hicksville.</p>
        <p>''Born American, none of my kids ever faced any ethnic issues,'' she said. ''They always felt that they fit right in and were friendly to everyone. Especially my son,'' she added with a laugh, ''who was always a bit too social.''</p>
        <p>''As adults, my kids are as ambitious as their mother,'' Ms. Mir said. Today her older daughter, Falina, 26, is a registered nurse, married with two children, who lives in Queens and works at a methadone clinic. The younger daughter, Nadia, 24, also lives in Queens and works as a junior equity analyst for a company in Manhattan. Her son, Javaid, 21, who lives at home in Hicksville, works part time for a local business and is studying computer graphics.</p>
        <p>Ms. Mir vacations in Trinidad twice a year to visit her mother and three siblings, but the Island ''is now home, mostly because my kids are here.''</p>
        <p>Deciding to buy a 7-Eleven 20 years ago was a family matter, with a down payment borrowed from a close relative. Since then she has evolved into an entrepreneur who is comfortable with her role as boss and proud of her independence. ''When I first bought this store, I had no idea what to expect,'' Ms. Mir said.</p>
        <p>The parent company, then the Southland Corporation, now 7-Eleven Inc., helped her find a suitable location and provided a comprehensive training program.</p>
        <p>''The best part of becoming a business owner has been the sense of security and independence that have made me feel really good about myself,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The worst part, she admitted, is the long hours, often necessary when running a store open 24 hours a day.</p>
        <p>The steady customer traffic includes many regular customers whose names -- or at least faces -- Ms. Mir has gotten to know. There are the police officers who come for coffee when they get off duty, the workers from the local area who stop by for breakfast, the teenagers and families who come regularly for coffee, Slurpees, lottery tickets and snacks. On any given day, Ms. Mir might be found behind the register, at the computer in her office or making fresh coffee for the more than 15,000 cups that she sells weekly.</p>
        <p>While she is the store's sole owner, Ms. Mir never feels alone, she said, thanks to trustworthy managers and ongoing help from the company.</p>
        <p>Bee Chan, 7-Eleven's local field consultant, comes to the store about twice a week to offer assistance with any problems that might arise. Last year, when the store became computerized, another company representative helped train Ms. Mir and her employees. And every two months there are meetings among the 82 franchisees in Nassau to discuss new items and marketing strategies.</p>
        <p>''We are a diverse mix of Americans and immigrants,'' Ms. Mir said, ''but I'm the only Nassau County 7-Eleven owner from Trinidad.''</p>
        <p>A Diverse Island</p>
        <p>Articles in this series are looking beyond the stereotypes that sometimes taint relations between immigrants and native-born Long Islanders. Future articles will examine immigrants' lives and how they are being woven -- or not -- into the social and economic fabric. Previous articles examined the lives and aspirations of Muslims on the Island, a Korean nail-salon owner and her American-raised son, a Colombian landscaping entrepreneur and an Indian liquor store owner.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
