<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Three Revisits That Were Worth the Trip</title>
    <meta content="30DINE$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218636"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DINING OUT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Chez Noue (Ridgefield, Conn, Restaurant)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Rebeccas (Glenville, Conn, Restaurant)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">West Street Grill (Litchfield, Conn)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brooks, Patricia</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E0DB1E3AF933A05754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="908" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Three Revisits That Were Worth the Trip</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICIA BROOKS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brooks, Patricia</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Patricia Brooks revisits Chez Noue restaurant in Ridgefield, Conn, Rebeccas in Glenville and West Street Grill in Litchfield (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NOTHING about a restaurant is preserved in amber. The kitchen may become stale, or newly inspired. A chef leaves, another arrives. Owners sell or become absentee. Even the food is subject to the vagaries of fads and fashions.</p>
        <p>That is why we occasionally revisit some restaurants that were noteworthy in times past. Are they still Excellent or Very Good? Has complacency set in? Here are the reports of a current round of revisits.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NOTHING about a restaurant is preserved in amber. The kitchen may become stale, or newly inspired. A chef leaves, another arrives. Owners sell or become absentee. Even the food is subject to the vagaries of fads and fashions.</p>
        <p>That is why we occasionally revisit some restaurants that were noteworthy in times past. Are they still Excellent or Very Good? Has complacency set in? Here are the reports of a current round of revisits.</p>
        <p>It has been four years since we reviewed CHEZ NOUE in Ridgefield. In the interim, we learned, one of the two French brother-owners had left; the other, Jehan de Noue, is still very much in charge. On a recent visit, we were delighted to find the surroundings, in the stone cellar of a 200-year-old building, cozy and romantic as ever. There are changes in the casual French menu, as you would expect, and prices have edged up -- natural after four years -- but Chez Noue continues to provide fine value, with many entrees under $20.</p>
        <p>Among the stand-out dishes were several starters, notably ratatouille gratine (bubbly and oven-hot), escargot Chez Noue in puff pastry (an aromatic medley of snails, garlic, leeks, shallots, tomatoes and herbs in a white wine- cream sauce), and wild mushroom and chevre strudel (phyllo-wrapped, served on a mesclun bed with a light balsamic reduction). Sole meuniere shone above all our entrees, simple perfection. Other dishes -- baked salmon with pesto crust, pan-seared sole with mussels and shrimp in a saffron cream infusion, and duck cassoulet -- also lived up to our high expectations. Desserts at Chez Noue are not flashy, but the chocolate mousse was as seductive as we remembered it. All in all, the Very Good rating for this charming hideaway is as enthusiastically deserved now as it was in 1996.</p>
        <p>Dinner entrees $16.95 to $29.95. All major credit cards accepted; reservations recommended. Chez Noue, 3 Big Shop Lane, Ridgefield (203) 894-8522.</p>
        <p>When REBECCAS opened in Glenville in 1998, it was widely acclaimed, not just by local people. New York friends called to rave about this sophisticated establishment, the creation of a knowledgeable husband-and-wife team, Reza Khoshidi and Rebeccas Kirhoffer. A recent return visit confirmed that Rebeccas continues its high standards and still deserves its Excellent rating, despite ear-splitting noisiness at peak hours. As mid-week diners, we enjoyed a conversational sound level.</p>
        <p>The food is as elegant and gracefully presented as ever. The two soups in one bowl concept, a Rebeccas signature, consists this summer of yellow and red gazpacho with a jumbo lump crabmeat island in the center. Other appetizers of note were a threesome of ravioli (lobster, shrimp and crabmeat in a shimmery lobster sauce) and duck foie gras with caramelized mango and ginger (exquisite!).</p>
        <p>Entrees were also memorable, especially the seared Muscovy duck breast, served sliced, along with Swiss chard, Bosc pear, a wild rice blini and intense black plum sauce. Almost as tasty was the pan-seared medallion of veal with nubbins of artichoke heart gnocchi and shaved asparagus stalks. One entree that raised the price bar was Kobe beef at $60 for a 12-ounce portion, $75 for 16 ounces. The fine-textured, flavorful Japanese beef, came as a thick slab of rib-eye. This majestic piece of beef was enriched further by a lustrous red Bordeaux reduction and a heap of haricots verts.</p>
        <p>Desserts play a huge role in the Rebeccas repertory, and we were more than happy with a mango tatin, creme brulee with a supreme of fresh fruit, and profiteroles with three scoops of ice cream in a velvety chocolate sauce. Adding to Rebeccas' allure is its expertly chosen wine list beginning at $28 and going up, up, up, with some splendid choices from France, California, Australia and New Zealand.</p>
        <p>Dinner entrees $27 to $75. All major credit cards accepted; reservations recommended. Rebeccas, 265 Glenville Road, Greenwich; (203) 532-9270.</p>
        <p>WEST STREET GRILL in Litchfield has been humming along successfully for 10 years. This snappy celebrity magnet seems to have dominated the area's restaurant scene for eons, not a mere decade. Chefs have come and gone, but the Grill continues merrily in its same center-of-town locale. The casual, always-intriguing bistro menu speaks of natural fresh ingredients, and the food, never fancy, remains Excellent. Sunday brunch recently yielded several yummy dishes, notably fried eggs with wild rice-and-dill fritters, buttermilk biscuit and bacon, asparagus, mushroom and Cheddar frittata with house-made blueberry-orange scone and home fries, and fresh peach-stuffed French toast, with bacon, whipped cream, and peach and maple syrup.</p>
        <p>At dinner, we savored the crisp flavors of a starter of beetroot tartare and panko-crusted Brie in a creamy buttermilk dressing, followed by spinach and Gorgonzola cheese ravioli in a fresh basil and tomato veloute, as well as orange-and-thyme-infused roasted chicken with sweet onions, whipped potatoes and haricots verts. Wholesome, fresh, creative. Maybe the reason West Street Grill continues to thrive is that it never stands still.</p>
        <p>Dinner entrees $17 to $34. All major credit cards accepted. Reservations recommended. West Street Grill, 43 West Street, Litchfield. (860) 567-3885.</p>
        <p>DINING OUT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
