<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Yes, Giants Win</title>
    <meta content="30SCRI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218935"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Giants</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pennington, Bill</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E3DB123DF933A05754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="418" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Yes, Giants Win</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL PENNINGTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pennington, Bill</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, July 29</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Giants' scrimmage at training camp described (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was the best of both worlds for Coach Jim Fassel during the Giants' annual intrasquad scrimmage today. In the opening moments of the 41-play scrimmage, the first-string defense dominated the second-string offense.</p>
        <p>But when the Giants' first offensive unit got on the field several plays later, quarterback Kerry Collins looked sharp, completing 4 of 5 passes for 87 yards, including a 60-yard touchdown to Amani Toomer. Meanwhile, the rookies Ron Dayne and Ron Dixon displayed no stage fright as each scored a touchdown.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was the best of both worlds for Coach Jim Fassel during the Giants' annual intrasquad scrimmage today. In the opening moments of the 41-play scrimmage, the first-string defense dominated the second-string offense.</p>
        <p>But when the Giants' first offensive unit got on the field several plays later, quarterback Kerry Collins looked sharp, completing 4 of 5 passes for 87 yards, including a 60-yard touchdown to Amani Toomer. Meanwhile, the rookies Ron Dayne and Ron Dixon displayed no stage fright as each scored a touchdown.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the best news was that the Giants' revamped offensive line provided good protection for Collins and opened holes for Dayne and Tiki Barber, who led rushers with 24 yards on three explosive carries.</p>
        <p>The offensive starters were going against the second-string defense, which is especially inexperienced on the line. But the new and improved offense the Giants have promised did indeed look new and improved. It was just a scrimmage, but three years ago in this scrimmage, the defense outscored the offense.</p>
        <p>Dayne, who gained 17 yards on 4 carries, showed the skills that made him attractive to the Giants. Although he was stopped for a 1-yard loss on his first carry, Dayne, the team's top draft pick out of Wisconsin, ran for 5 yards on his next carry and then ran for 12 yards -- breaking through three arm tackles as he dashed around the left end.</p>
        <p>Later, on third down at the 1-yard line, Dayne took a handoff from Collins, paused behind the pile at the line of scrimmage, then bulled easily into the end zone over right guard. The wherewithal to wait and see a developing hole impressed Fassel.</p>
        <p>''The play was actually called to the left,'' Fassel said. ''But Ron knows how to press a hole and make the cut. That showed a lot of instinctive patience, and his patience is one of his best attributes.''</p>
        <p>Dixon caught a 25-yard touchdown pass from Mike Cherry, the third-string quarterback, bursting alone into the end zone on an out-and-up route. Dixon, a third-round draft pick from Lambuth University, dropped the first pass Cherry threw to him, but later caught a 17-yard pass over the middle.</p>
        <p>Ike Hilliard also had 2 receptions for 24 yards and Joe Jurevicius caught 2 passes for 11 yards. Joe Montgomery carried the ball 5 times for 16 yards. Defensively, linebackers Pete Monty and Ryan Phillips were credited with sacks, as was defensive tackle Frank Ferrara.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
