<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Piling On Amazon's Stock, After the Fact</title>
    <meta content="30WATC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218829"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MARKET WATCH"/>
      <identified-content>
        <org class="indexing_service">Amazon.com Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Morgenson, Gretchen</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Gretchen Morgenson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CEFDD143DF933A05754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="674" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Piling On Amazon's Stock, After the Fact</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GRETCHEN MORGENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Morgenson, Gretchen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gretchen Morgenson Market Watch column ponders outlook for Amazon.com in light of analysts' recent downgrading of their ratings on company stock; speculates Amazon may move to retire some of its convertible debt, which is trading at depressed levels; graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>RATS leaving a sinking ship.</p>
        <p>That unfortunate metaphor sprang to mind last Thursday when a pack of formerly bullish stock analysts suddenly cooled on the shares of Amazon.com.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>RATS leaving a sinking ship.</p>
        <p>That unfortunate metaphor sprang to mind last Thursday when a pack of formerly bullish stock analysts suddenly cooled on the shares of Amazon.com.</p>
        <p>After the close of trading on Wednesday,  Amazon reported its second-quarter results. With remarkable synchronicity, 6 of the 35 analysts who follow Amazon cut their ratings on the stock the next morning. Even Henry Blodget, Amazon's big believer at Merrill Lynch, allowed that the company was going through ''an awkward transition.'' Mr. Blodget opined that intermediate-term investors should no longer ''buy'' the stock; they should ''accumulate'' it.</p>
        <p>Why the turnabout among Wall Street's finest analytical minds? In Mr. Blodget's case, the company's revenues in the quarter missed his estimate by $7 million.</p>
        <p>Even in this weird investment age, it is hard to believe that one equity analyst, forget the throng, would turn tail on a stock because its revenues came in at $578 million rather than $585 million -- a difference of 1 percent. What scared the analysts -- just a guess -- was Amazon's falling stock.</p>
        <p>That is not surprising. Academic research shows that equity analysts generally react to changes in stock prices rather than cause them. Luckily for investors, the same cannot be said for debt analysts.</p>
        <p>It has been about a month since Ravi Suria, a convertible bond analyst at Lehman Brothers, penned his blistering report on Amazon's prospects using words -- like distressed, deteriorating and woeful -- that are rarely seen in equity reports. The stock fell 19 percent in the wake of the report, but most equity analysts stayed positive on the company. Until last week.</p>
        <p>Of course, not all equity analysts are down on Amazon's shares. Mary Meeker, the Internet analyst at Morgan Stanley Dean Witter remains bullish. Her 12-page report on Amazon's second-quarter results included such calculus as ''Notable Quotables From Jeff,'' three paragraphs of bon mots from Mr. Bezos. Example: ''We have a great team. We have a common set of objectives. We have a plan to reach those objectives.'' Research? Stenography might be a better word.</p>
        <p>Morgan Stanley may feel that bullish is the only way to be on Amazon, because it is the company's investment banker and likely holds a barrel of the company's convertible bonds, which are trading in the cellar. The firm is the major market maker in the debt.</p>
        <p>Ms. Meeker did not return a phone call seeking comment.</p>
        <p>Amazingly, Wall Street's remaining optimists could still be trying to attract investment banking business. Sure, a new stock or bond issue may not fly, but Amazon might want to retire its $1.9 billion in convertible debt. And it would need a banker's help.</p>
        <p>To be sure, such deals are usually done by companies in dire straits, not a place Amazon finds itself now. And Amazon says it does not discuss its financing plans.</p>
        <p>But a company whose convertible debt is trading at depressed levels can retire it by paying holders of the debt a fat premium to the price the bonds fetch. The company pays bondholders in common stock.</p>
        <p>Many convertible holders are eager to sell at a slight gain. They wouldn't be taking on additional risk by getting more shares in the company, because convertible holders are usually short the underlying stock to hedge the equity position their bonds represent.</p>
        <p>The only losers, of course, are the shareholders, whose stakes are diluted by the issuance of shares to retire the debt. But maybe they won't mind. After all, to many investors, Amazon has never been just a stock. It's a religion.</p>
        <p>MARKET WATCH</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
