<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Low Boil, Schools Chief Makes a Huffy Court Exit</title>
    <meta content="28EDUC$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218308"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wyatt, Edward</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Levy, Harold O (Chancellor)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000728T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E5D8173DF93BA15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="509" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Low Boil, Schools Chief Makes a Huffy Court Exit</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWARD WYATT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wyatt, Edward</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>in low boil, schools chief makes a huffy court exit**New York City Schools Chancellor Harold O Levy, angered by New York State's final arguments in landmark suit charging state shortchanges city's schoolchildren in financing of public schools, storms out of visitor's gallery, loudly banging door (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was a short day in court yesterday for Schools Chancellor Harold O. Levy -- 13 minutes, to be exact.</p>
        <p>That is how long he listened to final arguments in the landmark lawsuit over the state's financing of New York City schools before he angrily stalked out of Justice Leland DeGrasse's courtroom in State Supreme Court in Manhattan, loudly banging doors and drawing the ire of a court officer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was a short day in court yesterday for Schools Chancellor Harold O. Levy -- 13 minutes, to be exact.</p>
        <p>That is how long he listened to final arguments in the landmark lawsuit over the state's financing of New York City schools before he angrily stalked out of Justice Leland DeGrasse's courtroom in State Supreme Court in Manhattan, loudly banging doors and drawing the ire of a court officer.</p>
        <p>Mr. Levy, a lawyer himself, arrived yesterday morning at the courtroom not as a participant but as a spectator, there to witness what nominally passes for theater in the legal world: closing arguments in a high-profile case.</p>
        <p>In this instance, it was the Campaign for Fiscal Equity v. the State of New York, pitting a group that contends that the city's schoolchildren, and therefore the state's minority students, are being shortchanged by hundreds of millions of dollars a year, against the state and its elected officials.</p>
        <p>While the Board of Education is not a party to the lawsuit, it has supported the effort. Mr. Levy, who formerly was on the State Board of Regents, has been intimately involved in many of the issues being debated in the case.</p>
        <p>He had barely settled into his seat in the visitors' gallery yesterday morning, however, before representatives of Attorney General Eliot L. Spitzer's office began assaulting the Board of Education as ''the biggest laggard in the state when it comes to spending on education'' and a hotbed of ''waste, fraud and corruption.''</p>
        <p>If that was not enough, the state's lawyer recounted that Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani told the Legislature early this year that he could not promise that any education money given the city by the state would be used effectively by the Board of Education.</p>
        <p>Martin Bienstock, an assistant attorney general, invoked Mr. Levy's name, noting that as a witness in this case, Mr. Levy ''swore under oath'' that he believed the city had ''the finest urban public school system in the U.S.'' Mr. Bienstock called the Board of Education ''a system that despite itself provides a sound basic education,'' and therein lay the apparent source of Mr. Levy's huffy exit.</p>
        <p>For evidence of that ''sound basic education,'' the state, in its court filings, points to evidence that 90 percent of the city's students meet the Regents' competency standards, which demonstrate that the students can read on at least an eighth-grade level.</p>
        <p>In a statement yesterday afternoon, Mr. Levy said he was ''offended by the actions of the defense that suggest that New York City children are entitled only to an eighth-grade education.'' Trouble is, that is not what the state's lawyer was saying when Mr. Levy stormed out of court.</p>
        <p>Mr. Levy was traveling late yesterday and was unavailable for further comment.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
