<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Men's Health, Trying to Win Youth Back, Names Editor</title>
    <meta content="Y28MAG" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218214"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Men's Health (Magazine)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barringer, Felicity</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zinczenko, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000728T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E2DF173DF93BA15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="318" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Men's Health, Trying to Win Youth Back, Names Editor</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FELICITY BARRINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barringer, Felicity</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>David Zinczenko is named editor in chief of US edition of Men's Health magazine (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Men's Health magazine, the onetime upstart that rocketed to the top of the men's magazine world during the 1990's before stalling, is turning to a 30-year-old editor to help it win younger readers from surging competitors like Maxim.</p>
        <p>David Zinczenko, who has spent the last two years in Europe tending to the growth of some of the magazine's 21 foreign offshoots, was named editor in chief of the United States edition yesterday by Steven Murphy, president and chief operating officer of Rodale, Inc., which owns Men's Health.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Men's Health magazine, the onetime upstart that rocketed to the top of the men's magazine world during the 1990's before stalling, is turning to a 30-year-old editor to help it win younger readers from surging competitors like Maxim.</p>
        <p>David Zinczenko, who has spent the last two years in Europe tending to the growth of some of the magazine's 21 foreign offshoots, was named editor in chief of the United States edition yesterday by Steven Murphy, president and chief operating officer of Rodale, Inc., which owns Men's Health.</p>
        <p>In the United States, Men's Health has a circulation of 1.6 million, but the number of advertising pages has declined in the last year, according to Cory Shield, a spokesman for Rodale, which is based in Emmaus, Pa.</p>
        <p>The appointment of Mr. Zinczenko is the second top-level management change at Men's Health since Mr. Murphy joined Rodale from the Walt Disney Company's Disney Publishing Worldwide, where he was managing director, three months ago. A week ago, Paul J. Turcotte was appointed vice president and publisher of the magazine.</p>
        <p>The biggest challenge for Men's Health, Mr. Murphy said yesterday, was ''the temporary advertising love affair with the lad magazines'' -- a British slang term for magazines like Loaded, Maxim and FHM, newer entries in a field that Men's Health helped create when it was started in newsletter form in 1988.</p>
        <p>Asked what changes he would make in Men's Health, Mr. Zinczenko said yesterday: ''The magazine's pretty buff already. There's no reason to go into wholesale changes. I do want to bring in fresh voices, fresh points of view.'' Mr. Murphy, in a separate interview, said, ''David's Rolodex of writers includes a new generation -- folks who, 10 years from now, will be names.''</p>
        <p>The magazine's focus, Mr. Murphy added, would continue to be on health, fitness, sex and relationships, with an added emphasis on personal finance.</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
