<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Matthaus Is Talking About Playoffs Already</title>
    <meta content="28SOCC$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218269"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SOCCER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yannis, Alex</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Matthaus, Lothar</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000728T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805EFDA173DF93BA15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="587" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Matthaus Is Talking About Playoffs Already</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEX YANNIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Yannis, Alex</byline>
      <dateline>COLUMBUS, Ohio, July 27</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>MetoStars soccer player Lothar Matthaus discusses team's chances to advance to Major League Soccer playoffs (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lothar Matthaus met some of his teammates and members of the MetroStars coaching staff today for the first time in a month and vowed a full commitment to them when he returns from an injury.</p>
        <p>Although he has not played for a month, Matthaus was voted by the fans to be a starter on the East squad in Saturday's All-Star Game. A slipped disk will keep the 39-year-old Matthaus on the sideline.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Lothar Matthaus met some of his teammates and members of the MetroStars coaching staff today for the first time in a month and vowed a full commitment to them when he returns from an injury.</p>
        <p>Although he has not played for a month, Matthaus was voted by the fans to be a starter on the East squad in Saturday's All-Star Game. A slipped disk will keep the 39-year-old Matthaus on the sideline.</p>
        <p>''I want to do for this team what I did in Milan and Munich and everywhere I played,'' Matthaus said. ''I hope I can give my best in the finals,'' he said, referring to the playoffs. ''This is what I learned in my 21 years in soccer, to do well in the finals. The regular season is O.K., but you start the finals with zero.''</p>
        <p>The MetroStars have played well without Matthaus in the regular season. They are 3-6-1 with him in the lineup and 10-1-1 without him. Their 13 victories are the most in the league and they are tied with Kansas City for the most points (41).</p>
        <p>This is, however, the time for Matthaus to come to the aid of the MetroStars. In Tuesday's MetroStars' victory over Tampa Bay in the United States Cup, Daniel Hernandez, the backbone of the defense, tore the anterior cruciate ligament in his right knee and will be lost for the season.</p>
        <p>Matthaus hugged Hernandez the moment he saw him on crutches today and told him that he suffered the same injury when he was with Inter in Italy about 10 years ago. ''It will take you four months and you'll be O.K.,'' he told Hernandez.</p>
        <p>''We're looking for a great player to step in and replace another great player,'' MetroStars Coach Octavio Zambrano said today of Matthaus taking Hernandez's place in the middle of the MetroStars' defense. ''That's the spot for Lothar and we expect him to step in and take it.''</p>
        <p>Matthaus said: ''I hope they need me in general, not because of the injury to Hernandez. I want to help the team, but I will need about 10 to 14 days to get ready. I've been running in Central Park and working in the gym for the last 10 days and I will practice with the team on Monday.''</p>
        <p>One thing Zambrano said that he does not want to do is use Matthaus too soon. Matthaus will have a magnetic resonance imaging test on Monday before he practices.</p>
        <p>''I want him to be 100 percent when he returns,'' Zambrano said about Matthaus this afternoon, before selected players participated in the skills competition at Crew Stadium, the first stadium in the country built exclusively for soccer.</p>
        <p>The MetroStars know they will need Matthaus's experience in the playoffs if they are to seriously challenge for the title. Several league executives here for league meetings feel the MetroStars cannot become champions without Matthaus, who has played in five World Cups and was Germany's captain in its 1990 World Cup triumph.</p>
        <p>Matthaus created a rift with the MetroStars and the league, which owns all player contracts, when he was photographed with his girlfriend on the beach in St. Tropez earlier this month at a time he was supposedly rehabilitating his back in Germany.</p>
        <p>''It's all in the past,'' Matthaus said. ''We had a good meeting last Friday and everything is O.K. I want to start playing and I want to win very badly. Winning is the most important thing for me, not money.''</p>
        <p>SOCCER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
