<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'Neo'</title>
    <meta content="RV230613" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218270"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ART IN REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Park, Eung Ho</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnson, Ken</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000728T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07EFDA173DF93BA15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="508" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'Neo'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEN JOHNSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Johnson, Ken</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ken Johnson reviews group exhibit Neo at Exit Art; photo of installation by Eung Ho Park (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Exit Art/The First World  548 Broadway, between Prince and Spring Streets  SoHo  Through Aug. 19</p>
        <p>''Neo'' is exactly what you want in an exhibition of young or underexposed artists: it is bursting with imaginative energy and reckless ambition. Don't look here for subtle refinement; Jeanette Ingberman and Papo Colo, the curators and the proprietors of Exit Art, have erred on the side of sensational and surrealistic excess. You get that right at the start of the show, where Eung Ho Park has suspended from the ceiling a towering three-dimensional grid of chained-together bowling balls.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Exit Art/The First World  548 Broadway, between Prince and Spring Streets  SoHo  Through Aug. 19</p>
        <p>''Neo'' is exactly what you want in an exhibition of young or underexposed artists: it is bursting with imaginative energy and reckless ambition. Don't look here for subtle refinement; Jeanette Ingberman and Papo Colo, the curators and the proprietors of Exit Art, have erred on the side of sensational and surrealistic excess. You get that right at the start of the show, where Eung Ho Park has suspended from the ceiling a towering three-dimensional grid of chained-together bowling balls.</p>
        <p>Not necessarily the best, but epitomizing the spirit of the show, is a huge sculpture made collaboratively by Anna Ehrsam and Hilary Koob-Sassen. Stretched out in the air within a 20-foot framework of steel I-beams is a multimedia assemblage of bewildering complexity; it might be an insectoid monster giving explosive birth at one end to a heroic woman. At once sophomoric and visionary, this piece suggests the artists could have a future designing sets for science fiction movies.</p>
        <p>The sculpture of Scott Reynolds is more convincingly focused in its use of neatly built wood grids that call Sol LeWitt to mind. Yet far from Minimalist sobriety, Mr. Reynolds's work is animated by an antic, hyperintellectual wit. A pyramidal wall-hung structure containing an inflated and illuminated white balloon with a pair of teatlike elements protruding at the front is titled ''A Re-creation of the Custom Window Treatments at the Freud Institute for Architectural Research.''</p>
        <p>Painting as plain old flat painting is entirely absent, but several artists offer dimensionally enhanced pictorial works. Michael Zansky aggressively gouges big, heavy wood panels to create violent, semi-abstract images of gnarly branch forms and crisscrossing beams against silvery blue skies. Han Sam Son accumulated and distressed with a knife great quantities of corrugated cardboard to produce a wall that is like the bark surface of an enormous tree. Marked by high-tech smoothness, on the other hand, Peter Coe's triptych of white panels with raised cellular forms and design elements neatly painted in color exude a trippy retro-futurism. Video and computer art are scarce, but Elka Krajewska's odd little movies seen through a crude viewing tube attached to a laptop are interesting, and the computer program in Yucef Merhi's ''Poetic Clock'' generates better LED screen poetry than does Jenny Holzer.</p>
        <p>Other works of note include David Henderson's swelling topographies in laminated wood; Francis Palazzolo's ''Modern-Postmodern Proposition,'' which allegorizes the society of the spectacle as a ramshackle aluminum projection machine on wheels; a giant foot turned into a miniature snowy mountainscape by David Opdyke; and an installation by Woo Song Bang that fills its space with peanut shell clusters hanging above miniature, illuminated igloos that are surrounded by fields of salt. What the latter work means is anyone's guess, but like much else in the show, it gives the wildly improbable a richly palpable presence.</p>
        <p>KEN JOHNSON</p>
        <p>ART IN REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
