<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Warm, Sly or Mysterious, Many Faces of the Blues</title>
    <meta content="28BLUE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218164"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="JAZZ REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, Carrie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hyman, Dick</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ratliff, Ben</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000728T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E5DB163DF93BA15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="688" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Warm, Sly or Mysterious, Many Faces of the Blues</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN RATLIFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ratliff, Ben</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ben Ratliff reviews blues music performed by Dick Hyman, Carrie Smith and others, as part of Jazz in July series at 92d Street Y; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The blues is commonly described as a particular feeling, an emotional tincture in music. But that's only half the picture, since the chord sequence that is the blues form can be put to so many different feelings. What the pianist Dick Hyman set out to prove in ''Blues After Dark,'' a concert he produced on Wednesday as part of his annual Jazz in July series at the 92nd Street Y, was that the blues is merely a familiar device in musical language; the associations it provokes depend entirely on context.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hyman can replicate an impressive number of different jazz piano styles. But he brought in another pianist, Bill Charlap, to split the concert's duties and used more than a dozen other musicians in a revolving cast.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The blues is commonly described as a particular feeling, an emotional tincture in music. But that's only half the picture, since the chord sequence that is the blues form can be put to so many different feelings. What the pianist Dick Hyman set out to prove in ''Blues After Dark,'' a concert he produced on Wednesday as part of his annual Jazz in July series at the 92nd Street Y, was that the blues is merely a familiar device in musical language; the associations it provokes depend entirely on context.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hyman can replicate an impressive number of different jazz piano styles. But he brought in another pianist, Bill Charlap, to split the concert's duties and used more than a dozen other musicians in a revolving cast.</p>
        <p>The concert shuffled the blues through various guises. First Mr. Hyman played with surety through Little Brother Montgomery's ''Vicksburg Blues,'' in an outgoing country-blues piano style that approximated singing, with rushed, nearly bending bunches of notes. Then Bill Charlap, with a sextet, played ''All Blues,'' from Miles Davis's ''Kind of Blue'' record -- a modal blues, contemplative and mysterious -- and Charlie Parker's ''Au Privave'' and ''Bloomdido.'' Mr. Charlap played fine, delicate, rapidly articulated solos; he drew the audience in.</p>
        <p>In Mr. Hyman's concerts music is generally infused with a bit of light teaching, and he showed the parallels between the bass line in W. C. Handy's ''Aunt Hagar's Blues'' and Gershwin's Second Prelude. And he chose the Handy song to play in a spangled, arpeggio-stuffed but still somehow relaxed Art Tatum style, to demonstrate how it is possible (as he put it) to play ''fancy'' on the blues form.</p>
        <p>A couple of items on the program were more complicated. One was a curious experiment: to have a big band, with a 12-piece horn section, in a duet against the famous 1928 recording of ''West End Blues'' by Louis Armstrong and his Hot Five. The musicians played along with the first chorus of the recording, then played an original arrangement without the tape behind them. The Armstrong recording was reintroduced for Earl Hines's piano solo (with Mr. Hyman playing along); then the tape dropped out again for more new arrangements, and so on. The pulse stayed continuous through the segues, since the rhythm-section players wore headphones and were listening to a click-track.</p>
        <p>Toward the end the band introduced key modulations, moving the final choruses up a few steps and then dropping back into the key of recording for the finish. It's hard to say what it meant. (And -- just checking in with jazz politics here -- wasn't Kenny G reviled without pity not long ago for daring to play a duet against a different Louis Armstrong recording?) But it was a curious bit of tinkering, done for the sake of doing it, and technically it worked without a hitch.</p>
        <p>The concert's second half was taken up by the premiere of Mr. Hyman's new work, ''The Longest Blues in the World,'' a 45-minute composition for an 18-piece band. It was a pastiche piece, demonstrating, essentially, what the blues form can do. Different sections reflected different styles of writing and arrangement: there was a mid-career Ellington moment on a slow ballad featuring the saxophone section, a richly orchestrated Woody Herman-ish moment, a Machito moment of Afro-Cuban jazz, a Bessie Smith moment (featuring the singer Carrie Smith), a Herbie Hancock moment.</p>
        <p>There were major and minor blues, and frequent changes of rhythm, and then the piece finally wound around to a restatement of its opening motif. At least as impressive as the piece's catholic reach was its execution, not just as sheet music but as a concert; the large band was comfortably rehearsed, and the acoustics at the Tisch Center for the Arts auditorium made the music sound warm and detailed.</p>
        <p>JAZZ REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
