<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Breaking Down the Barriers With Hand Clapping and Prancing</title>
    <meta content="28ABSO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000803T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218153"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Absolute Ensemble (Music Group)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tommasini, Anthony</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000728T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E1DD163DF93BA15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="564" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Breaking Down the Barriers With Hand Clapping and Prancing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY TOMMASINI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tommasini, Anthony</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anthony Tommasini reviews new-music performance by Absolute Ensemble; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Over the years many new-music ensembles have tried to break down categories between contemporary concert music on the one hand and, on the other, rock, jazz and all the idioms that are dubbed ''popular,'' for want of a better term. The Absolute Ensemble has joined the cause. This New York-based ensemble first appeared a few seasons back as a traditional contemporary chamber group, directed by a young Estonian-born conductor steeped in the classical tradition, Kristjan Jarvi, whose father is the noted conductor Neeme Jarvi.</p>
        <p>But the Absolute Ensemble has reconceived itself as an electro-acoustic band that performs a wide range of 20th-century and contemporary works without regard to category. If this sounds gimmicky, the bracing concert the ensemble presented at Joe's Pub in the East Village on Monday night showed how serious these young musicians are about what they do.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Over the years many new-music ensembles have tried to break down categories between contemporary concert music on the one hand and, on the other, rock, jazz and all the idioms that are dubbed ''popular,'' for want of a better term. The Absolute Ensemble has joined the cause. This New York-based ensemble first appeared a few seasons back as a traditional contemporary chamber group, directed by a young Estonian-born conductor steeped in the classical tradition, Kristjan Jarvi, whose father is the noted conductor Neeme Jarvi.</p>
        <p>But the Absolute Ensemble has reconceived itself as an electro-acoustic band that performs a wide range of 20th-century and contemporary works without regard to category. If this sounds gimmicky, the bracing concert the ensemble presented at Joe's Pub in the East Village on Monday night showed how serious these young musicians are about what they do.</p>
        <p>Of course, they are not so serious that they didn't give the crowd that packed the place a good time. As the lights dimmed and people settled into their seats, drinks in hand, the sounds of rhythmic clapping could be heard from the lobby. It was the members of the ensemble as they walked in performing Steve Reich's ''Clapping Music,'' a mesmerizing wave of complex, pulsating rhythmic patterns performed by hand clapping and, here, from memory, which could not have been easy.</p>
        <p>This led without pause into Michael Daugherty's ''Dead Elvis,'' a joyously raucous piece that mixes tidbits of Presley tunes, even the pop standards he sang like ''It's Now or Never,'' together with the funereal ''Dies Irae'' chant motif, scored for screeching brass and winds, rock drums and an earthy acoustic bass. The King himself is represented by a wailing solo bassoon, here performed by David Rozenblatt as an Elvis impersonator prancing about the pub floor in glittery Las Vegas duds.</p>
        <p>After two more works that drew heavily on jazz and rock styles, Erkki-Sven Tuur's ''Symbiosis'' and Gene Pritsker's kinetic ''Fix'' (receiving its New York premiere), the ensemble made its one miscalculation of the evening, performing the ''Petit Chorale'' from Stravinsky's ''Soldier's Tale'' in an arrangement that included pummeling rock drumming. Performed straight, this poignant work would have provided a welcome moment of repose. Stravinsky can hold his own in any new-music evening. Later, the tango, waltz, and ragtime dances from ''The Soldier's Tale'' were performed essentially as written, and in this context the music seemed more bold and dangerous than ever.</p>
        <p>The world premiere performance of Charles Coleman's impressive ''Rut Strut'' suggested that audiences who listen mostly to rock and pop will accept a considerable amount of atonal dissonance, complex counterpoint and metric dislocation if the music is laid atop a pulsating rhythm section. There were engaging works by Ray Noble along with Francisco Repilado's ''Chan Chan'' from the ''Buena Vista Social Club.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Jarvi conducted everything with acute skill and plenty of funk. He has recently been appointed the music director of the Noorlands Symphony Orchestra and Opera Company in Sweden. But, intent on an unconventional career, he remains committed to the Absolute Ensemble and its mission.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW  Correction:  August 3, 2000, Thursday  A music review in Weekend on Friday about the Absolute Ensemble's concert at Joe's Pub in the East Village misidentified the bassoon soloist in Michael Daugherty's ''Dead Elvis.'' He was Martin Kuuskmann;  David Rozenblatt was the drummer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: August 3, 2000, Thursday</p>
        <p>A music review in Weekend on Friday about the Absolute Ensemble's concert at Joe's Pub in the East Village misidentified the bassoon soloist in Michael Daugherty's ''Dead Elvis.'' He was Martin Kuuskmann;  David Rozenblatt was the drummer.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
