<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Who Would Oppose a Gun Ban Near Schools? Maybe Neighbors</title>
    <meta content="28GUNS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218241"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Firearms</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gun Control</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Roseland (NJ)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Rifle Assn</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">DeBell, Louis (Mayor)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Firearms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gun Control</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000728T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E2DC173DF93BA15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="666" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Who Would Oppose a Gun Ban Near Schools? Maybe Neighbors</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>ROSELAND, N.J., July 27</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>National Rifle Association affiliate is suing to overturn new Roseland ordinance, believed to be first of its kind in New Jersey, that bans guns near schools and other public property; Mayor Louis DeBell defends law; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gun violence involving children -- or any gun crime, for that matter -- has not been a problem in this quiet middle-class suburb 10 miles west of Newark. And the Borough Council moved last month to keep it that way, passing an ordinance that makes it illegal to have a gun within 1,000 feet of a school, park, playground or library.</p>
        <p>But the state's affiliate of the National Rifle Association has sued to overturn the law, charging that the council has no right to regulate guns. And it is not clear whether the local Police Department will even try to enforce the ban.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gun violence involving children -- or any gun crime, for that matter -- has not been a problem in this quiet middle-class suburb 10 miles west of Newark. And the Borough Council moved last month to keep it that way, passing an ordinance that makes it illegal to have a gun within 1,000 feet of a school, park, playground or library.</p>
        <p>But the state's affiliate of the National Rifle Association has sued to overturn the law, charging that the council has no right to regulate guns. And it is not clear whether the local Police Department will even try to enforce the ban.</p>
        <p>Robert Carroll, 64, a retired supervisor for Public Service Electric and Gas who lives across Passaic Avenue from the borough's only school, said today that he feared he could be  arrested for simply carrying his gun out to his car. ''The law says 1,000 feet,'' Mr. Carroll noted, ''and I am within 1,000 feet.''</p>
        <p>But proponents of the ban said any such arrest would be unlikely.</p>
        <p>On June 7, the Borough Council adopted an ordinance establishing zones within 1,000 feet of schools, parks and other public property where guns would be forbidden, with violations punishable by up to 90 days in jail and a fine of $1,000. A state law sets penalties for gun crimes or possession on school property, and there are now at least four bills pending in the Legislature that would ban guns in zones that extend outside schools or public property.</p>
        <p>But the state attorney general's office said today that it believed Roseland was the first New Jersey municipality to create such zones.</p>
        <p>Mayor Louis DeBell, the chief proponent of the ordinance, and the lawyers who wrote it say the ordinance is permissible because it simply expands on the state law that bans guns in schools.</p>
        <p>Nancy Ross, a spokeswoman for the Association of New Jersey Rifle and Pistol Clubs, the N.R.A. affiliate  that sued in State Superior Court in Newark last week, contends that such laws only hurt law-abiding gun owners and that the ordinance treads on the state's authority to regulate handgun possession.</p>
        <p>Mayor DeBell said the law was not intended to penalize licensed gun owners. Nonetheless, the ordinance states that anyone who possesses a gun within the designated zones ''without the written permission of the Borough Police Department'' will be subject to the penalties ''irrespective of whether such person possesses a valid permit to carry the firearm.''</p>
        <p>Asked how the police would enforce the ordinance, Richard McDonough, the acting chief, said, ''Basically, at this stage of the game, if there were a weapons violation committed in the Borough of Roseland, the person would be charged under the state statute.''</p>
        <p>Mayor DeBell said the ordinance was inspired by a parent's question on opening day of the local Little League: Why were there no signs posted designating schools as drug-free zones? The mayor said it made him wonder why there were no signs marking gun-free zones as well.</p>
        <p>''How can you object to doing something that would protect the safety and welfare of children and residents?'' the mayor asked. ''It doesn't infringe on anyone's rights.''</p>
        <p>But it does, countered Ms. Ross. ''I read that the mayor said they don't intend to arrest people,'' she said. ''But intentions have nothing to do with the fact that they passed an illegal ban. I think it's another one of these issues that are highly political, so they do things that aren't very smart and have repercussions on their citizens.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
