<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sailing Poetically Into the Hip-Hop Paradox</title>
    <meta content="28SURF$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218174"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">New York Hip-Hop Theater Festival</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jones, Sarah</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bruckner, D J R</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Surface Transit (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000728T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00EEDA163DF93BA15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1175" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sailing Poetically Into the Hip-Hop Paradox</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By D. J. R. BRUCKNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bruckner, D J R</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>D J R Bruckner reviews Surface Transit, written and performed by Sarah Jones; photo; one-woman show is presented as part of first New York Hip-Hop Theater Festival (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was smart of the organizers of the first New York Hip-Hop Theater Festival to make Sarah Jones's one-person play ''Surface Transit'' the centerpiece of its presentations at P. S. 122 through Aug. 26. Ms. Jones first presented it a couple of years ago in the East Village, and since then she and the play's director have continued working on it; she and the show have grown, and she is a tremendous draw with the downtown crowd. Since she performed her solo show ''Women Can't Wait'' at the United Nations for its international conference on women in early June, she has also grown a bit beyond the neighborhood. But, more important for this festival, among artists most respected by other hip-hop poets and performers, she has the clearest sense of distance; she can satirize the phenomenon in ways that open it up for people who think there is something mysterious about it.</p>
        <p>One of the characters in ''Surface Transit'' is an octogenarian who burns with the desire to be with it, whatever ''it'' is. She asks a teenager, ''Why don't you buy clothes that fit you?'' And, a minute later: ''What do you mean, it's a black thing and I wouldn't understand? You're not black.'' The festival is being pitched to the young; but if that woman were not already in the play, I would encourage her to go to it. In less than two hours she would understand enough of hip-hop to pick up all the rest in no time on her own. And there is a lot to be said for a popular cultural movement in which to be a real neophyte you have to be old.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was smart of the organizers of the first New York Hip-Hop Theater Festival to make Sarah Jones's one-person play ''Surface Transit'' the centerpiece of its presentations at P. S. 122 through Aug. 26. Ms. Jones first presented it a couple of years ago in the East Village, and since then she and the play's director have continued working on it; she and the show have grown, and she is a tremendous draw with the downtown crowd. Since she performed her solo show ''Women Can't Wait'' at the United Nations for its international conference on women in early June, she has also grown a bit beyond the neighborhood. But, more important for this festival, among artists most respected by other hip-hop poets and performers, she has the clearest sense of distance; she can satirize the phenomenon in ways that open it up for people who think there is something mysterious about it.</p>
        <p>One of the characters in ''Surface Transit'' is an octogenarian who burns with the desire to be with it, whatever ''it'' is. She asks a teenager, ''Why don't you buy clothes that fit you?'' And, a minute later: ''What do you mean, it's a black thing and I wouldn't understand? You're not black.'' The festival is being pitched to the young; but if that woman were not already in the play, I would encourage her to go to it. In less than two hours she would understand enough of hip-hop to pick up all the rest in no time on her own. And there is a lot to be said for a popular cultural movement in which to be a real neophyte you have to be old.</p>
        <p>Ms. Jones began as a performance poet at Lower East Side slams, and it is hard to imagine her acting this play except in front of a voluble crowd; the noise of the auditorium seems part of the act. The eight characters she creates are built of carefully realized detail -- no line is wasted -- but they are much larger than their lines. There are rough spots: one accent is audibly uncertain; a few themes are worn; and one role, a Southern racist looking for recruits, seems entirely out of place in this group of odd people whom any of us would recognize instantly as New Yorkers.</p>
        <p>If some of them are stock characters, she gives all but a couple a self-awareness that makes them richly entertaining in an ornery way. And she has a good poet's sense of when to leave a message unspoken, for example, when a Russian immigrant braiding her small black daughter's hair tries to persuade her to ignore racial slurs hurled at her by their Flatbush neighbors.</p>
        <p>Yet that scene is not as painful or thought-provoking as one involving a West Indian black woman with a British accent who pops into a studio for an MTV spot audition. The defining character here is unseen: Ms. Jones's recorded voice as the woman in the control booth, whose confident coarseness is a fine foil to the aspiring star's laughable but contagious nervousness as she reveals some truly repulsive interracial sexual encounters as part of the true-life skits she is required to create for her audition tape.</p>
        <p>A white policeman who abuses women and hates gay men is a ridiculous figure as he feints and parries with a psychiatrist to whom he has been sent after he broke the collarbone of a gay man he was arresting. (''Hey, it was like he was throwin' himself against the wall.'') He could not possibly have anything against gays because his best friend from childhood ''is one of those.''</p>
        <p>And while he talks you recall that the octogenarian woman (her New Yorkese is so delicious we should be able to break off bits and taken them home) who couldn't grasp hip-hop had a son who is a policeman and gay. She doesn't ''have anything against him for that,'' but she has definite ideas about ''how they get that way.'' Prejudices and idiosyncrasies do not alone define roles in this play; it is far too intelligent for that.</p>
        <p>Unquestionably the funniest and most penetrating scene finds a manic rapper, Rasheed, initiating a 12-step program to cure an unruly crowd of compulsive wordsmiths of rhyme. The vast list of references he drops could be an encyclopedic dictionary of hip-hop, and the rhythm of his patter is so finely modulated that his 10-minute speech sounds like a grand aria of rap. A reverberating whisper runs through it all like the whisk of a brush across a cymbal in a musical set; he's saying, ''You know what I'm saying?,'' but for the first few passes it sounds like ''no-ee-see-yeah.'' The beat requires the extreme elisions and only a performance poet would get the rhythm right.</p>
        <p>Rasheed doesn't get the last word on himself, however. His ex-girlfriend is waiting at a bus stop (it's been there all along, emblematic of the play's title), fending off men in cars with her Metrocard and filling us in on the shortcomings of wise dudes like Rasheed. Her quiet, triumphant feminism is wonderfully eloquent in a precise way and wholly unthreatening to anyone who isn't rushing her. Besides that, she defends standard English, as when she says to a man who has pulled up to the curb with his car's sound system blasting: ''No, we can't.'' (Pause) ''Because 'conversate' is not a word, OK?'' He and his sound drop dead.</p>
        <p>Ms. Jones may embody the best of hip-hop, but she makes fun of it at the beginning and end -- in the voice of an ancient black homeless woman who has lived so long she ''can see through all this stuff'' even before the show starts and who has a shrewd eye for the comedy of coffee bars and cellular phones.</p>
        <p>At the end, as she shuffles to the door, she objects that none of what went on made sense. ''They talkin' about their jiggy food and jiggy music. . . . What the hell is jiggy? Makin' up their own language, that's it. . . . damn 'em all.'' Then she's gone. And when Ms. Jones is gone, a big room jammed with cheering people can seem quite empty.</p>
        <p>SURFACE TRANSIT</p>
        <p>Written and performed by Sarah Jones; directed by Gloria Feliciano. General manager, Clyde Valentin; lighting by Frank Dendanto; sound by Ms. Jones and Jimmie Lee. Presented by Danny Hoch. At P. S. 122, 150 First Avenue, at Ninth Street, East Village.</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
