<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Deutsche Telekom May Dilute German Government Stake</title>
    <meta content="Y28WIRE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218201"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Germany</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Deutsche Telekom</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Voicestream Wireless Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Romero, Simon</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sommer, Ron</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000728T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E7D6163DF93BA15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="706" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Deutsche Telekom May Dilute German Government Stake</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SIMON ROMERO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Romero, Simon</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Deutsche Telekom chairman Ron Sommer says company is considering ways to reduce German government's stake in company as it prepares to wage behind-the-scenes political battle to win approval of its plan to buy VoiceStream Wireless Corp; US lawmakers have opposed acquisition of American telecommunications company by corporation controlled by foreign government, erecting significant hurdle to American expansion of Deutsche Telekom; one option would be to acquire one or more additional telecommunications companies, either in US or elsewhere, worth as much as $100 billion, which would lower German government's overall stake (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Deutsche Telekom is considering ways to reduce the German government's stake in the company as it prepares to wage a behind-the-scenes political battle to win approval of its plan to buy the VoiceStream Wireless Corporation, the company's chief executive said yesterday.</p>
        <p>United States lawmakers have opposed the acquisition of an American telecommunications company by a corporation controlled by a foreign government, erecting a significant hurdle to the American expansion of Deutsche Telekom, Europe's largest phone company. Existing law generally puts the limit of foreign government ownership at 25 percent.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Deutsche Telekom is considering ways to reduce the German government's stake in the company as it prepares to wage a behind-the-scenes political battle to win approval of its plan to buy the VoiceStream Wireless Corporation, the company's chief executive said yesterday.</p>
        <p>United States lawmakers have opposed the acquisition of an American telecommunications company by a corporation controlled by a foreign government, erecting a significant hurdle to the American expansion of Deutsche Telekom, Europe's largest phone company. Existing law generally puts the limit of foreign government ownership at 25 percent.</p>
        <p>One option, which illustrates how Deutsche Telekom's $50.7 billion offer for VoiceStream is unlikely to satisfy the company's appetite for expansion, would be to acquire one or more additional telecommunications companies, either in the United States or elsewhere, worth as much as $100 billion, which would lower the German government's overall stake.</p>
        <p>''If I were to buy today a company about the size of Deutsche Telekom, that would dilute the government's stake down to about 22 percent, it's that simple,'' Ron Sommer, Deutsche Telekom's chairman, said in an interview.</p>
        <p>Of course, few companies rival the size of Deutsche Telekom, the second-largest telephone company after Nippon Telegraph and Telephone of Japan. That is why the German company is expected to pursue several acquisitions at once, analysts said.</p>
        <p>Another option, seemingly less predictable, would be the sale of Germany's shares in the company. The German government owns about 58 percent of Deutsche Telekom's stock but has pledged to decrease its holdings. If Deutsche Telekom succeeds in buying VoiceStream, based in Bellevue, Wash., the German government's stake would fall to 45 percent.</p>
        <p>Unlike other European countries such as France, Germany does not have legislation that prevents the government from reducing its stake in its national telecommunications company. Nor are there rules that give the government a ''golden share,'' allowing it to veto certain management decisions, as there are in Spain and Italy.</p>
        <p>Still, the sale of the government's stake would depend on the price. ''We always said the government would sell according to market conditions,'' Mr. Sommer said.</p>
        <p>Given political opposition to Deutsche Telekom's expansion in the United States, it is important for Mr. Sommer to underscore the German government's intent to decrease its ownership.</p>
        <p>In Europe, Deutsche Telekom could try to buy Telefonica S.A. of Spain, whose chairman, Juan Villalonga, resigned on Wednesday, or make another bid for Telecom Italia, said Bob House, a vice president in the London office of Renaissance Strategy, a telecommunications consulting firm.</p>
        <p>In the United States, a handful of large telecommunications companies have been mentioned as potential takeover targets for Deutsche Telekom, including WorldCom Inc., which recently failed in its bid to acquire the Sprint Corporation, and Global Crossing, based in Hamilton, Bermuda, which has a growing global fiber optic network.</p>
        <p>''There are political complexities in these moves, but Deutsche Telekom knows that they are all in play,'' Mr. House said.</p>
        <p>As the company debates its options, Mr. Sommer said that much of Deutsche Telekom's energy in the United States would be focused on securing approval in Washington to buy VoiceStream. To do so, Deutsche Telekom has hired several lobbying and law firms.</p>
        <p>Lobbying is expected to focus on thwarting legislation sponsored by Senator Ernest F. Hollings, Democrat of South Carolina, and supported by several Congressional leaders, which would block Deutsche Telekom's takeover of VoiceStream.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sommer's comments came after Deutsche Telekom released results yesterday showing that its second-quarter profit declined by nearly half, to 200 million euros, or about $188 million, after the company spent heavily to expand its mobile phone operations, most recently in Britain and Austria. Shares of Deutsche Telekom fell 1.17 euros, or 2.3 percent, to 49.50 euros. The stock has declined more than 34 percent since June.</p>
        <p>''I admire what Deutsche Telekom is doing to expand, but I prefer smaller, faster-growing companies,'' said Michael Eggly, co-manager of the Northern Global Communications Fund in Chicago. ''The former national telephone company of Germany isn't attractive to us.''</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
