<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gunman Frees Hostage Pilots After Escape Of Passengers</title>
    <meta content="28HOST$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000802T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218323"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Kennedy International Airport (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hostages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airports</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Argentina</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Airlines</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Newman, Andy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dewan, Shaila K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Argentina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hostages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000728T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DEFD8173DF93BA15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="911" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gunman Frees Hostage Pilots After Escape Of Passengers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDY NEWMAN and SHAILA K. DEWAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Newman, Andy; Dewan, Shaila K</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Man carrying gun boards National Airlines jet at Kennedy International Airport, shushes passengers and walks into cockpit, taking pilot and co-pilot hostage; passengers flee unharmed; gunman releases pilot with list of demands, including wish to speak with someone from Argentine Consulate, and later releases co-pilot; apparently ran past security workers at metal detector near jetway before boarding plane (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A man carried a handgun onto a National Airlines jet at Kennedy International Airport at 10:15 last night, shushed the passengers and walked calmly into the cockpit, taking the pilot and co-pilot hostage for two hours, passengers and the authorities said. Neither the seven crew members nor the 143 passengers were injured in the incident, the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey said.</p>
        <p>The gunman released the pilot around midnight with a list of demands, including his wish to speak to someone from the Argentine Consulate, the police said. An off-duty officer at the Argentine Consulate, Beatriz Bustos, said that a police officer called and asked her to put him in touch with the Argentine ambassador, Guillermo McCough. She said she passed the message on, but had no further information.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A man carried a handgun onto a National Airlines jet at Kennedy International Airport at 10:15 last night, shushed the passengers and walked calmly into the cockpit, taking the pilot and co-pilot hostage for two hours, passengers and the authorities said. Neither the seven crew members nor the 143 passengers were injured in the incident, the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey said.</p>
        <p>The gunman released the pilot around midnight with a list of demands, including his wish to speak to someone from the Argentine Consulate, the police said. An off-duty officer at the Argentine Consulate, Beatriz Bustos, said that a police officer called and asked her to put him in touch with the Argentine ambassador, Guillermo McCough. She said she passed the message on, but had no further information.</p>
        <p>The gunman released the co-pilot around 1 a.m., the authorities said.</p>
        <p>After seeing the man with the gun heading for the cockpit, all the passengers rushed off the plane and escaped unharmed, passengers and Greg Trevor, a Port Authority spokesman, said.</p>
        <p>As of 1:30 this morning, the authorities said, the gunman was alone on the plane, a Boeing 757 that was to have left for Las Vegas.</p>
        <p>Many passengers described scenes of pandemonium. ''I sat down, got buckled up and the next thing I know everybody was screaming,'' said Misty Nichols, 27, a nurse from Carmel, N.Y., who was leaving for a vacation.</p>
        <p>Then, she said, people started rushing to get off the plane. A little girl next to her was knocked over, she said, but an older man picked her up and helped her.</p>
        <p>Ms. Nichols said she later tried to retrieve some of her belongings, but someone yelled, ''Get off the plane -- your life is more important than your stuff.''</p>
        <p>Marcus Weiss, another passenger, told CNN that he was sitting near the front of the first-class section when he ''heard a voice, a very low voice, saying 'Be quiet.' '' He said that he looked up and saw ''a dark-skinned man in his late 20's with a 10- to 12-inch gun in his right hand, walking very briskly toward the cockpit.''</p>
        <p>''He walked into the cockpit and closed the door,'' Mr. Weiss said. The man was wearing a white long-sleeved shirt and did not appear to be an airline employee, at least not one in uniform, Mr. Weiss and some other passengers said.</p>
        <p>The gunman apparently made his way onto the plane, at Gate 33 of Terminal 4W, simply by running past security workers, Mr. Trevor of the Port Authority said.</p>
        <p>Passengers said they had to pass through only one metal detector before boarding the plane, and it was located right before the jetway. .</p>
        <p>Witnesses said the suspect pulled his gun out right before the metal detector, told four elderly people to get out of his way and boarded the plane.</p>
        <p>CNN reported that a National Airlines spokesman had said the gunman was a ticketed passenger on the flight.</p>
        <p>Moments after all the passengers left the plane, several police officers with ''big guns'' boarded, Ms. Nichols said.</p>
        <p>The flight, National Airlines Flight 19, a Boeing 757, was scheduled to take off at 9:30 p.m. but did not begin boarding until after 10 p.m., passengers said.</p>
        <p>One passenger, who was not identified, told ABC News that the man held the gun down in front of him with both hands to make it clear to passengers that he was armed.</p>
        <p>''He told me to be quiet,'' the passenger said. I grabbed my friends and we just piled off the plane.''</p>
        <p>Another passenger, Frank Clark, 30, a computer engineer from Brooklyn, was in first class and had just been served a drink when he heard the commotion and saw the gunman enter the cockpit. The passenger sitting next to Mr. Clark said, ''The guy's got a gun.''</p>
        <p>''That's all it took,'' Mr. Clark said. ''It was a road race from there.''</p>
        <p>Not all the passengers appeared to panic, however.</p>
        <p>''The guy sitting next to me really tripped me out because he kept his drink,'' Mr. Clark said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clark said that airline employees and security personnel at the terminal seemed completely baffled by the situation.</p>
        <p>''The passengers were running down the jetway, and the two airline people at the ticket counter were bugged out,'' he said. ''They had no idea what to do. There was security guy was waving people towards an exit, the other one was just standing there like he just steppped on a rake.''</p>
        <p>National, formed a year ago and based in Las Vegas, is a small airline, with a fleet of 11 Boeing 757-200's flying nonstop between Las Vegas and eight other cities. But it is growing fast.</p>
        <p>It began turning a profit in March, after only 10 months in the air, becoming one of the fastest new airlines in history to make money, according to Aviation Daily, a trade publication.</p>
        <p>National operates four flights a day from Kennedy Airport to Las Vegas.</p>
        <p>The airline itself declined to comment on the crisis. But CNN reported that a National Airlines spokesman had said the gunman was a ticketed passenger on the flight.</p>
        <p>Correction:  August 2, 2000, Wednesday  An article on Friday about a man who took hostages on a plane at Kennedy International Airport and demanded to speak to someone from the Argentine Consulate misspelled the surname of the consul general. He is Guillermo J. McGough, not McCough.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: August 2, 2000, Wednesday</p>
        <p>An article on Friday about a man who took hostages on a plane at Kennedy International Airport and demanded to speak to someone from the Argentine Consulate misspelled the surname of the consul general. He is Guillermo J. McGough, not McCough.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
