<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A City With Too Much Housing; Syracuse Hopes to Clear Deserted Eyesores From Streets</title>
    <meta content="28SYRA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="THE OTHER ECONOMY: Struggling Against Blight" name="series_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218316"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Syracuse (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eaton, Leslie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/Upstate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Finger Lakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Finger Lakes/Syracuse</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000728T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE3D8173DF93BA15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2272" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A City With Too Much Housing; Syracuse Hopes to Clear Deserted Eyesores From Streets</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LESLIE EATON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eaton, Leslie</byline>
      <dateline>SYRACUSE</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>As many as 2,200 of houses in Syracuse, NY, are empty or abandoned, more than 10 percent of city's houses; boarded-up houses mar some of city's nicest neighborhoods and fill blocks in some of worst; problem is so bad that civic and government leaders and public back efforts to raze, not rebuild, houses; map; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If only it were near New York City, 403 Rowland Street might be a handy home-buyer's dream. Sure, the side porch is collapsing, the chimney is crumbling, and the big front windows have been replaced by small squinty ones. But the vintage charms of this turn-of-the-century house, including sturdy construction and gingerbread trim, would probably look alluring to the housing-hungry hordes in southern New York State.</p>
        <p>The view is quite different here, near the center of the state, near the center of Syracuse, near the center of a working-class neighborhood known as Skunk City. So it is hard to argue with Millie Compeau, sitting on the porch of the tidy house where she has lived for 89 of her 92 years, when she peers across Rowland Street at No. 403 and decrees, ''That house should come down.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If only it were near New York City, 403 Rowland Street might be a handy home-buyer's dream. Sure, the side porch is collapsing, the chimney is crumbling, and the big front windows have been replaced by small squinty ones. But the vintage charms of this turn-of-the-century house, including sturdy construction and gingerbread trim, would probably look alluring to the housing-hungry hordes in southern New York State.</p>
        <p>The view is quite different here, near the center of the state, near the center of Syracuse, near the center of a working-class neighborhood known as Skunk City. So it is hard to argue with Millie Compeau, sitting on the porch of the tidy house where she has lived for 89 of her 92 years, when she peers across Rowland Street at No. 403 and decrees, ''That house should come down.''</p>
        <p>A lot of people are starting to agree. That is because Syracuse has more houses -- a lot more houses -- than its 152,000 citizens need or want. Like the place on Rowland Street, as many as 2,200 of them are empty or abandoned, more than 10 percent of the houses within the city limits.</p>
        <p>Boarded-up houses mar some of Syracuse's nicest neighborhoods and fill blocks in some of the worst. Skunk City, where residents say the namesake critters still roam at night, is somewhere in between: a well-kept house is followed by a rundown place, then another nice one, then an abandoned wreck -- or two or three.</p>
        <p>The problem is so bad that last fall, government and civic leaders began the Syracuse Neighborhood Initiative to try to bring back blighted areas of the city. Representative James T. Walsh, a Republican on the House Appropriations Committee, whose father grew up in Skunk City, has already gotten $15 million in federal financing for the initiative.</p>
        <p>As part of the project, many in Syracuse are embracing an idea that has long been anathema to almost everyone trying to save urban areas: demolishing houses -- and not rebuilding them.</p>
        <p>''The truth is, getting money to do tear-downs is very hard,'' said Allison Lee, a senior official in the Albany office of the federal Department of Housing and Urban Development. But after touring areas where problem properties have been knocked down, she said, ''I have to tell you, the neighborhoods are better.''</p>
        <p>Syracuse is not the only place upstate suffering from abandoned housing, which afflicts almost every old city east of Detroit. But perhaps because Syracuse is so small and is not a corporate or government center, the problem seems more overwhelming than in other cities.</p>
        <p>''Ours is the most serious problem because we have the least resources,'' said Eric Mower, an advertising executive who is chairman of the initiative.</p>
        <p>How Syracuse came to such a pass is a tangled tale of failures in public policies and changes in private tastes, but most of all, of economics. The 1991 recession that hit all of New York State came to Syracuse and would not leave. Long after the economy began to rebound to the south, central New York stagnated.</p>
        <p>That is no longer true, at least on paper. New jobs have been sprouting here at a faster pace than almost anywhere else north of New York City, and unemployment is only 3.7 percent, well under the national average of 4.2 percent.</p>
        <p>The housing market is improving, too, after dropping sharply in the mid-1990's and treading water for years. Last year, the number of houses sold in and around Syracuse rose more than 10 percent, according to the Greater Syracuse Association of Realtors, and the median price edged up to $82,500 (which is still less than the median in 1994).</p>
        <p>Within the city, however, house prices still seem to be dropping, according to a study by the federal Neighborhood Reinvestment Corporation for the Syracuse Neighborhood Initiative. That is, when houses sell at all. In Skunk City, there were just four regular sales last year, according to the report. Tax auctions and foreclosure sales have become the norm.</p>
        <p>City inspectors report that more than 1,000 houses in the city remain vacant, and the number has been rising. Minchin G. Lewis, the city auditor, says that the correct figure is more like 2,200, based on the number of water meters that have been unused for a year.</p>
        <p>The vacant houses that people see all over the city remind them of the terrible economic times they have endured -- and help explain why the good news announced by economists does not seem to have sunk into the psyche of Syracuse's citizens. ''They're shellshocked from the decline that has taken place,'' Mr. Lewis said.</p>
        <p>That was clear at a city council hearing, held on July 19 to discuss plans to build a big mall in the city. Dozens of residents spoke, and many described Syracuse in apocalyptic terms.</p>
        <p>''This city is in a real crisis,'' said Melanie Duer, 43, who after a disabling accident used her insurance settlement to buy and fix up a small apartment building in Skunk City, near where she grew up. In 1994, she told city officials, there were 6 vacant houses on the main road between her building and downtown; today, she said, there are 36.</p>
        <p>In a later interview, Ms. Duer expressed frustration with politicians who, she said, find it easy to overlook her neighborhood. When President and Hillary Clinton visited Syracuse last year, the president played golf less than a mile away from her building, ''but it might as well have been in Zimbabwe,'' she said. ''They could really make a difference if they walked on this street. I'm just one voice with a weed whacker.''</p>
        <p>On the surface, Skunk City does not look like a slum. Each one- or two-family house has a little strip of grass in the front and a plot in the back, with just enough room for a shed or a garage. Many of the houses are trim and tidy. Marigolds and petunias edge walks. Children of all colors ride their bicycles up and down the streets.</p>
        <p>Hang around for a while, however, and problems appear. Drug dealers, for instance.</p>
        <p>On Rowland Street, a young man announces, ''I'm gonna cop,'' and with money in his hand crosses to the corner where a couple loiter. A block away, there is a lot of furtive activity around a pay phone on the corner. Down the street, a high-stakes craps game continues in one driveway. Residents complain that illegal car-repair joints sprout on the bigger streets.</p>
        <p>And on almost every block, like a bruise, is an unkempt house with a sagging porch, a trash-filled yard, a pile of old dumped tires, or broken windows partly boarded up.</p>
        <p>There have been some shootings and stabbings, said Richard Puchalski, who as executive director of Syracuse United Neighbors seems to know every block of Skunk City. ''A lot of folks who have lived here 40 or 50 or 60 years are finding it difficult to maintain their houses,'' he said. ''They are being pressured by their siblings, who say, 'You'd better get the hell out of there.' ''</p>
        <p>Even in its heyday, Skunk City was not the fanciest part of town. It was too close to the swamp; developers crammed as many houses as possible in narrow lots along the new sewer line. In more recent decades, the threat of a highway project discouraged people from moving in.</p>
        <p>But to the people who lived there, it was a ''garden spot of Eden,'' according to the yellowing newspaper clippings preserved at the Onondaga Historical Association. For the children, there was fishing and skating and swimming; for the adults, there were plenty of saloons and a movie house.</p>
        <p>The men in the neighborhood had steady jobs at the post office, the railroad or the auto plants. Some were more colorful: Florence Joslin's father sang on the radio, while the Schwald boys' dad had been a roller skater in a vaudeville act, the Whirling Hamilton Trio, before he settled down to raise a family.</p>
        <p>''When we were kids, 15, 16 years old, our father could leave the car in the driveway with the keys in it,'' said Dennis J. Schwald Sr., 58. ''Nobody touched nothing.''</p>
        <p>Back then, said his brother William, 61, ''everyone owned their own home.'' He added, ''We've seen it gone down and down.'' Both men, who retired from the Carrier air-conditioner plant, still live on Hartson Street, as did their parents and in-laws; now, Dennis's son owns two houses on the street.</p>
        <p>But such roots have gone out of fashion, even in Syracuse. Today, many young families -- and older ones, too -- prefer to live out in the suburbs, where the houses are newer, the lots bigger and the schools better. The amount of developed land around the city has almost doubled in the last decade, said Vito Sciscioli, the city's commissioner for community and economic development.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the region's population has been shrinking, with most of the drain coming from within the city limits. From 1990 to mid-1999, the population of Onondaga County shrank by 13,000, with 12,000 of the drop occurring in Syracuse, according to federal census estimates.</p>
        <p>That left Syracuse with ''a brutal oversupply of housing,'' said Eric Hangen, who wrote the report for the Syracuse Neighborhood Initiative. People who wanted to sell could not. People who wanted to fix up their homes would not because they feared rightly that they could not recoup their investments, he said.</p>
        <p>Desperate homeowners took to renting out their unwanted houses, or selling them to slum lords, or abandoning them altogether because they could not pay the mortgages. Or the taxes, especially after the city started seizing delinquent properties a couple of years ago.</p>
        <p>The Department of Housing and Urban Development alone now lists about 50 houses for sale in the city. Some of them are priced at less than $15,000, which is roughly what it would cost to knock them down.</p>
        <p>In the 1980's, the Syracuse Model Neighborhood Corporation, a housing group, built houses on vacant lots and sold them for $78,000, but no more.</p>
        <p>''In the last two years I've built one house,'' said Thomas Francis, who runs the group. ''There's no demand, and I can't afford to hold on to them.''</p>
        <p>Fundamentally, Mr. Francis said, ''there just are not enough people.''</p>
        <p>Ergo, demolition -- or de-densifying, as some people call it. The idea is to tear down not only those abandoned houses that threaten to collapse on their own, but also those that are simply unneeded and uneconomical. The land could be split between the remaining nearby houses, to give them bigger yards, or driveways, or garages (popular in snowy Syracuse). Big tracts could be turned into parks.</p>
        <p>The plan, in other words, is to make the city more like the suburbs.</p>
        <p>''The suburbs are the best part of America,'' said Greg G. Smith, a landlord with 60 units on the west side of the city. ''Everybody loves having a decent-size yard and off-street parking. They want breathing room enough that when somebody's alarm clock goes off, it doesn't wake you up.''</p>
        <p>If the houses that get knocked down are simply replaced, he added, ''you're preserving the streetscape that everybody hates.'' As part of the neighborhood initiative, he is hoping to get financing for a master plan and small grants to try out this idea on the west side of town.</p>
        <p>Exactly how much housing will be demolished in Syracuse remains unclear. Each of the city's neighborhoods gets to make recommendations about what improvements it would like. In some of the more prosperous areas, residents are calling for improvements like period streetlights or a new botanical garden.</p>
        <p>Representative Walsh said that no more than a third of the federal money, $5 million so far, could be used for demolition; at $12,000 a pop, the city's estimate, that would be about 417 houses.</p>
        <p>No one is suggesting that demolition will solve all the problems in Syracuse's neighborhoods. ''It's good to have that strategy,'' said Mr. Sciscioli, the city commissioner, ''but if you don't address basic services, you can kiss it all goodbye.''</p>
        <p>Back in Skunk City, however, longtime residents like Patricia D. Masters are looking forward to some demolition. ''I'd like to see them do it a little quicker,'' she said. ''How long do you have to have a dead house on your street?''</p>
        <p>The Other Economy</p>
        <p>Upstate New York, a vast, diverse landscape of old cities, small towns, farms and forests stretching from Buffalo to Albany and north to the Canadian border, was once one of the most populous and prosperous regions of the country. But the national economic boom that swept into New York City and its suburbs passed it by. This is the fourth in a series of articles examining the region's quest for prosperity.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
