<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>ART GUIDE</title>
    <meta content="28ART" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="33" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218142"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000728T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E3DB1E3AF93BA15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="4444" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>ART GUIDE</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A selective listing by critics of The New York Times of new or noteworthy art, design and photography exhibitions at New York museums and art galleries this weekend. Addresses, unless otherwise noted, are in Manhattan. Most galleries are closed on Sundays and Mondays, but hours vary and should be checked by telephone. Gallery admission is free. * denotes a highly recommended show.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A selective listing by critics of The New York Times of new or noteworthy art, design and photography exhibitions at New York museums and art galleries this weekend. Addresses, unless otherwise noted, are in Manhattan. Most galleries are closed on Sundays and Mondays, but hours vary and should be checked by telephone. Gallery admission is free. * denotes a highly recommended show.</p>
        <p>Museums</p>
        <p>* ''THE ART OF WILLIAM EDMONDSON,'' Museum of American Folk Art, 2 Lincoln Square, (212) 595-9533 (through Aug. 27). All creatures, celestial, human and animal, find their way into the limestone sculpture of Edmondson (1874-1951) and the results feel like an epic folk opera: score by Scott Joplin, libretto by Aesop, choreography by the great master dancers of Yorubaland. This exhibition also includes photographs of the artist by Edward Weston, Consuelo Kanaga and Louise Dahl-Wolfe, showing him at home in Nashville, where, at 59, he began to carve gravestones and garden ornaments for the local African-American community. In 1937 he made a solo debut at the Museum of Modern Art, and he has been part of the American pantheon ever since. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, 11:30 a.m. to 7:30 p.m. Free (Holland Cotter).</p>
        <p>''BEADS, BODY AND SOUL: ART AND LIGHT IN THE YORUBA UNIVERSE,'' Museum for African Art, 593 Broadway, near Houston Street, SoHo, (212) 966-1313 (through Aug. 27); Studio Museum in Harlem, 144 West 125th Street, (212) 864-4500 (through Sept. 17) The Yoruba beading tradition and the religious faith it reflects are the subjects of this opulent, edifying two-museum exhibition. Downtown, where the material is mostly African, an array of beaded ritual objects, sculptures, royal regalia and personal shrines illuminate both the indigenous tradition and its expansion by the arrival of brightly colored beads from Europe. At the Harlem museum, the exhibition follows this tradition to the Americas, where it thrives among Afro-Cuban, Afro-Brazilian and African-American devotees of Santeria and Candomble. It is a story of inspiring persistence and fascinating permutation, told by one of the most entrancing, universally beloved artistic materials (Smith).</p>
        <p>''THE BIRTH OF BAROQUE: CARRACCI AT THE METROPOLITAN,'' Metropolitan Museum of Art, Fifth Avenue at 81st Street, (212) 535-7700 (through Sept. 17). If the family known as Carracci -- Annibale (1560-1609), his brother Agostino (1557-1602) and their cousin Ludovico (1555-1619) -- didn't exactly invent the dynamic art known as Baroque, they gave their all to it. Ludovico developed an important academy that sought to correct what he considered the distortions of the prevailing Mannerist style by returning to natural forms and the heritage of the great Italian masters like Correggio, Veronese and Titian. Annibale, considered one of the greatest draftsmen of the age, was helped by Agostino in his creation of a highly influential fresco cycle for the ceiling of the Farnese Palace in Rome that brought back the Renaissance love of human drama and emotion. This small but illustrious show of paintings, drawings and prints from the Metropolitan's own collection of Carracci works offers paintings like Ludovico's innovative ''Lamentation'' (1582), a shockingly realistic Pieta scene, and Annibale's ''Coronation of the Virgin'' (about 1596), a symmetrical composition showing the Virgin crowned Queen of Heaven by Jesus and God the Father that reflects the classicism of Annibale's Roman style. But the Carracci powers of observation and ability to handle complicated narratives is best seen in their drawings and prints, which range from Annibale's charmingly intimate ink with wash, ''A Domestic Scene'' (probably early 1580's), in which a mother warms her child's nightgown before a fire, to Ludovico's ambitious ''Last Communion of St. Jerome'' (no date), a tightly composed altarpiece proposal. Hours: Sundays and Tuesdays through Thursdays, 9:30 a.m. to 5:15 p.m.; Fridays and Saturdays until 8:45 p.m. Admission: $10; $5, students and the elderly (Grace Glueck).</p>
        <p>* CHARDIN, Metropolitan Museum (through Sept. 3). This retrospective doesn't tell us much that wasn't already known about Jean-Simeon Chardin, but there's nothing wrong with being reminded occasionally of what great painting is. The art, by contrast with so much Rococo art, is about love, not sex. Quiet and deliberation were Chardin's essential ingredients, combined with a perfect mastery of abstract form. He was the best still-life painter ever because he made the most of the least, his work focusing on the same humble cups and pans in one painting after another, one decade after another. The result was a compilation of precise little observations that together make as true a record of the value of seeing as exists in the history of art. Hours and admission: See above (Michael Kimmelman).</p>
        <p>''GLASS WORKS: EMERGING ARTISTS,'' Brooklyn Museum of Art, 200 Eastern Parkway, (718) 638-5000 (through Sept. 3). Thirteen Brooklyn artists were each invited to produce a glass artwork in response to a piece from the permanent collection. Their creations are distributed throughout the museum, each presented near the work that inspired it. Highlights include Robert Panepinto's heavy blown-glass vase with the image of an Indian deity traced inside; a thick, frosted tortoise shell shield by Himiko Ohta; Beth Lipman's three-dimensional copy of a complicated 19th-century American still-life painting; and Jeff Zimmerman's mirrored, suspended bulbous form, a deliberately contrary response to Arthur Fitzwilliam Tait's sentimental painting of a girl and a fawn. Hours:  Wednesday through Friday, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; first Saturday of each month, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Sunday, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. Admission, $4. Hours and admission: See above (Ken Johnson).</p>
        <p>BARBARA KRUGER, Whitney Museum of American Art, 945 Madison Avenue, at 75th Street, (212) 570-3600 (through Oct. 22). A lot has changed about the art world in the 20 years or so since Barbara Kruger came onto the scene with her snappy photomontages, but a lot has not changed about her work. Her trademark red, white and black text-and-photograph montage is a brand product of the immediate past. Dense and noisy, this retrospective, including audio embellishments, has an intended carnival atmosphere without frivolity. Your reaction will necessarily depend upon a blend of generational sympathy, political concord, aesthetic expectation and tolerance for sarcasm. Ms. Kruger was one of the 80's artists adapting Conceptualism via mass media forms for political ends, thereby helping to broaden the purview of contemporary art and make the art world more sex-balanced. Young artists today reacting against her sort of political stridency now explore subtler, more aesthetically varied routes toward expressions of selfhood. Ms. Kruger, in a sense, helped to pave the way for her own diminished currency, which for a political artist like her may be viewed as a kind of success.  Hours: Tuesdays, Wednesdays and Fridays through Sundays, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Thursdays, 1 to 8 p.m. Admission: $12.50; $10.50, students and the elderly (Kimmelman).</p>
        <p>''MANHATTAN CONTRASTS: 20TH-CENTURY PAINTINGS OF NEW YORK,'' New-York Historical Society, 2 West 77th Street, (212) 873-3400 (through Aug. 27). This modest show of 20th-century paintings of New York from the society's collections focuses on painting as documentary representation. This means mostly pictures of buildings seen from near and far, along with a few genre scenes. Quality ranges from journeyman competence to high academic proficiency. But the show is also meant to prompt thought about the society's future collecting, and its most recent acquisition -- a neo-Pop work by Martin Wong -- suggest a promising expansion of parameters. It is exciting to imagine what this show could look like in the year 2100. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. Admission: $5; and $3 for students and seniors (Johnson).</p>
        <p>* ''MAXFIELD PARRISH, 1870-1966,'' Brooklyn Museum of Art (through Aug. 6). A romantic fabulist who painted in a tight, finicky mode that left out no detail, Parrish (1870-1966) was a highly accomplished illustrator who could be considered the father of Norman Rockwell. He also pursued a never-never world of chaste but titillating young women and knightly men in pastoral landscapes that melded medieval towers with New England forests, Western gorges and the deep blue skies of fairy kingdoms. This show of more than 140 paintings, drawings, prints, illustrations and ephemera ranges from such well-known Parrish chestnuts as ''Daybreak'' (1922), depicting a young woman's ecstatic awakening to an erotically symbolic dawn, to his coy, cartoonish ''Old King Cole'' mural of 1894. Aside from its campy entertainment value, there is enough here -- particularly his graphic art and some fine landscapes -- to sustain the revival of interest in his work that began with the Pop Art era. Hours and admission: See above (Glueck).</p>
        <p>''ROBERT RAUSCHENBERG: SYNAPSIS SHUFFLE,'' Whitney Museum of American Art (through Oct. 8). Robert Rauschenberg's latest divertissement -- if one may use that word for such a dull performance -- is a group of 52 panels, the number alluding to a full deck of cards, each bearing a mix of photographic images taken by the artist and transferred to the panels' polylaminate surfaces. The images include objects, street scenes, people and natural phenomena, along with snippets from advertising, magazines and newspapers. Involved with the notion of audience participation in his art for many years, Mr. Rauschenberg invited 12 fellow celebrities to ''compose'' their own works, creating ''new'' ones by selecting from several of the panels and placing them in whatever juxtaposition came to mind. The celebrities obliged, among them the television journalist Mike Wallace, the soprano Renee Fleming, the choreographer Merce Cunningham and the talent agent and art collector Michael Ovitz. But aside from the fact that it's a little hard to buy the premise that anyone can create a new work simply by pushing around the artist's components, they had cliched material to work with. The pretentiousness of ''Synapsis Shuffle,'' the celebrity-kissing self-promotion it has involved, and the wasteful allotment of nearly 6,000 square feet of gallery to it at the space-challenged Whitney are not cause for celebration. Hours and admission: See above (Glueck).</p>
        <p>* ''WITHOUT SANCTUARY: LYNCHING PHOTOGRAPHY IN AMERICA,'' New-York Historical Society (through Aug. 13). This exhibition scrutinizes a painful chapter in American history with heart-rending clarity: small black-and-white photographs of lynchings that took place between 1880 and 1960: mostly in the South, nearly always with African-American victims. Even more disturbing than the sight of the limp, often tortured and mutilated bodies is the sight of the crowds of white people milling about, sometimes smiling into the camera as if they were at a church picnic or state fair. The extent to which the events were condoned or at least tolerated by society is indicated by accompanying material, including facsimiles of newspapers announcing possible lynchings, and by the images often being sold as postcard mementos. Hours and admission: See above (Smith).</p>
        <p>Galleries: Uptown</p>
        <p>JAMES LEE BYARS: ''THE POETIC CONCEIT AND OTHER BLACK WORKS,'' Michael Werner Gallery, 4 East 77th Street, (212) 988-1623 (through summer). Relentlessly pursuing perfection, the conceptualist James Lee Byars (1932-1997) was a performer and object maker in the tradition of Duchamp. His influences included Zen philosophy and Noh drama, and his work ran to austere shapes of gold, marble, glass and paper. In his legendary performances he did things like enveloping 100 nude volunteers in a single overall garment, and arranging in an exactly symmetrical pattern 100 white marbles on the floor of an all-white room. His favorite colors were red, gold, black and white, but this small show is devoted to works in black, including ''The New Moon'' (1993), a poetic wall arrangement of seven black crescents cut from silk paper, each covered by a crescent of glass that gives it a silvery edge. Byars's own presence was very much part of his work, and it's not at all surprising that his fey anima still seems to inhabit it (Glueck).</p>
        <p>Galleries: 57th Street</p>
        <p>BRIAN KENNY, DC Moore Gallery, 724 Fifth Avenue, (212) 247-2111 (through July 28). Any artist who arranges objects within small, elegant glass-fronted wooden boxes cannot escape the long shadow of Joseph Cornell, and Mr. Kenny is no exception. His carefully made containers, resembling 19th-century clock cases and other period furniture forms, are often quaintly lined with printed papers in French and other languages, inflected by a tasteful postage stamp or two pasted on them. They contain assortments of sometimes distasteful things, like cicada carcasses, along with bone fragments, wine glasses (broken and whole), old shoe trees, antlers and wishbones. The show, Mr. Kenny's first solo exhibition in New York, is saved from preciousness by the contrast between the cases and their content (Glueck).</p>
        <p>Galleries: SoHo</p>
        <p>RAOUL HAGUE, Lennon Weinberg, 560 Broadway, at Prince Street, (212) 941-0012 (through next Friday). The five monumental sculptures here, each cut from a single piece of walnut, are like Abstract Expressionist paintings turned to living wood; they strongly imply human figures. Carving aggressively but in sympathy with the undulant form and serpentine grain of the log, Hague (1904-1993) created these powerful weddings of art and nature between 1969 and 1978. Here they ride on the wheeled dollies he favored for storage, giving the massive forms a curious lightness and mobility (Johnson).</p>
        <p>GERALD KAMITAKI, Staff USA, 495 Broadway, at Broome Street, (212) 925-9700 (through Aug. 26) For his second New York solo show, Mr. Kamitaki has performed a clever, exhaustive exercise in the deconstruction of an art magazine. First he removed every page of the May 2000 issue of Artforum; then he cut neat circles into each and rotated the rings, creating kaleidoscopic alterations. Hung in numerical order, the pages generate an interesting tension between art and journalism (Johnson).</p>
        <p>MASATOMO KURIYA, Yancey Richardson, 560 Broadway, at Prince Street, (212) 343-1255 (through Aug. 25) There is a certain undeniable beauty in this Japanese photographer's richly colored images of carefully arranged flowers in antique containers. Early Modernists like Weston and Strand come to mind, but the pictures also hover uncomfortably close to the line between art and high-end kitsch (Johnson).</p>
        <p>''THE LOWER EAST SIDE: 1906-1993,'' Susan Teller, 568 Broadway, at Prince Street, (212) 941-7335, (through Aug. 24) Among more than 40 social realist images of Lower East Side life in this print and drawing exhibition, a few gems stand out: a densely etched nocturnal view from Willamsburg Bridge by Martin Lewis; a Piranesian construction site in drypoint by G. L. Briem; a delicate silverpoint drawing of a spacious park by Edith Kramer; and masterly, postcard-size wood engravings by Bernard Brussel-Smith (Johnson).</p>
        <p>''SUMMER SHOW,'' DFN, 560 Broadway, at Prince Street, (212) 334-3400 (through Aug. 18). Mixed in among the 53 works in this cheerfully uneven hodgepodge of a show are pictures of sunbathers by Joan Semmel; a large, darkly expressionistic beach scene in charcoal by Susan Grossman; small, woozily distorted suburban images by Steve Mumford; a gloomy, swampy landscape painted by William McCarthy; and a painting of a naked sunbather with a strategically placed book by Elyse Taylor (Johnson).</p>
        <p>Galleries: Chelsea</p>
        <p>''FAMILY TREE,'' Robert Mann, 210 11th Avenue, between 24th and 25th Streets, (212) 989-7600 (through Aug.t 25) Five photographers deal with relations between self and family. Leo Rubinfien's large, touching pictures portray his young, oddly beautiful, medically compromised daughter; Karl Baden's funny series of word and picture montages chronicle his endurance of his wife's pregnancy; Maria Meisenberger's photograms of her own nude body are seen through screens of genetic coding; Lois Guarino's self-portraits include hand-wrought symbolic elements; and Laurent Miller's pictures document a private performance using inherited bedsheets (Johnson).</p>
        <p>HYUN-MI YOO: ''BLANK PUZZLE,'' Cristinerose, 529 West 20th Street, (212) 206-0297 (through Aug. 4) Hyun-Mi Yoo makes clever sculptures using the grammar of the jigsaw puzzle. A window has its glass divided puzzle-wise, as does a standing, oval framed mirror. ''Well'' is a waist-high cylinder built of ceramic puzzle units, ''Pink Blank'' an oversized piece made of pink rubber, slumps lonesomely and comically in a corner (Johnson).</p>
        <p>''OPULENT,'' Cheim &amp; Read, 521 West 23rd Street, (212) 242-7727 (through Sept. 1) ''Opulent'' makes a good case for the visual pleasure principal. It includes Lynda Benglis's lustrous gold, intestinal hemisphere; an exotic bronze bell by St. Clair Cemin; paintings of lush profusion by Chris Ofili, Beatriz Milhazes and Richmond Burton; and more orderly stripe or grid-based paintings by Juan Usle and Philip Taaffe. The prize for interesting materials goes to Jeff Perrone's funky stripe paintings made of richly colored sand and buttons (Johnson).</p>
        <p>Other Galleries</p>
        <p>''THE MORRIS MUSEUM: A COLLECTED CENTURY,'' PaineWebber, 1285 Avenue of the Americas, at 51st Stret, (212) 713-2885 (through Sept. 8) This miscellaneous sampler from New Jersey's third largest museum includes selections from all its departments, from paintings to fashion to natural science. The selection includes a bronze statue of Pan by the American Renaissance sculptor Frederick William MacMonnies, beaded Victorian handbags, Navajo rugs, a mechanical Popeye the Sailor toy and a contemporary painting by Wolf Kahn. While almost everything is interesting, nothing in the show is really amazing (Johnson).</p>
        <p>''SIX ABSTRACT PAINTERS,'' Karen McCready, 425 West 13th Street, (212) 243-0439 (through Sept. 1) Emphasis on process is the link in this show. Carleen Sheehan paints lush, trippy postcard-size fields of dots, nets and stripes; Margaret Lanzetta layers grid patterns in black, gray and white; Garry Mitchell's loosely gridded pictures are elegantly blurred and richly colored; Beth Miller and Janis Provisor produce drippy, scrawly compositions; and Nicole Parcher mixes gestural drawing and collage (Johnson).</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>JOHN AHEARN: ''SCULPTURE FROM EAST 100TH STREET, PART 2,'' Alexander and Bonin, 132 10th Avenue, at 18th Street, Chelsea, (212) 367-7474 (through today). Mr. Ahearn's cast of plaster characters, impressions of his neighborhood friends taken from life, has changed slightly since his 1995 move from the South Bronx to the barrio of East 100th Street. Mostly wall sculptures in half-length or head-and-shoulder presentations, these painted likenesses range from whimsical self-portraits to frolicking teenagers at a New Year's Eve party. The revelers include ''Chris and Starr,'' a couple wearing New Year's Eve hats, linked by Chris's arm as he toots on a toy trumpet; ''KP,'' a boy and girl locked in a kiss, and ''Terrell With Top Pop,'' a well-fed boy who swigs from a soda bottle. Mr. Ahearn, who is very good at conveying in paint the subtle range of flesh tones, portrays himself twice: as a hand-wringing clown with red nose and turned-down mouth, and more introspectively with a pensive face turned toward the wall. New in this work are several unpainted plaster casts of many hands joined together, cast from subjects seated around a table. Suggesting the sculptural reliefs on medieval cathedrals, they add a spiritual dimension to this very human show (Glueck).</p>
        <p>* ''ART AND ORACLE: SPIRIT VOICES OF AFRICA,'' Metropolitan Museum of Art (through Sunday). This is the first big international loan exhibition of African art to appear at the Met outside the Michael C. Rockefeller wing, and it is gorgeous. The subject is divination, the practice of channeling superhuman knowledge to predict the future, diagnose illness and promote social harmony. Nearly every object here has a role in that process or reflects its effects, from a ''power figure'' that looks as explosive as a stick of dynamite to a Yoruba divination tray believed to be the oldest African wood sculpture in the West, to the portrait of a king who was warned by diviners to beware of water and had himself depicted as half-fish. (He ended up in exile far across the Atlantic in Martinique.) (Cotter).</p>
        <p>* ''THE ART OF PUBLISHERS' BOOKBINDINGS: 1815-1915,'' Grolier Club, 47 East 60th Street, (212) 838-6690 (through tomorrow). This sumptuous display of more than 250 books offers a fascinating window onto the history of book production and cover design. Many volumes are more interesting for historical than aesthetic reasons, but the show is studded with visual gems, like a haunting gilded design centered on the image of scissors and a lock of hair by Aubrey Beardsley for Alexander Pope's ''Rape of the Lock'' (Johnson).</p>
        <p>''STUART DAVIS IN GLOUCESTER,'' National Academy of Design, 1083 Fifth Avenue, at 89th Street, (212) 369-4880 (through Sunday). The quaint fishing port of Gloucester, Mass., seemed an unlikely hangout for the jazzy city painter Davis (1894-1964). But he actually loved the place, and in the summers he spent there, from 1915 to 1934, he used motifs drawn from the rocky coast, the townscape and the maritime activity as he worked toward a more progressive style of painting. This show, with some 45 oils, watercolors and drawings, gives a good account of his struggles in assimilating Modernist ideas to arrive at the innovative American Cubist style for which he is celebrated. But Davis's art had more to do with his own genius: his gift for paring line and shape to essences and uniting them with scintillating color. Hours: tomorrow and Sunday, noon to 5 p.m.; today to 6 p.m. Admission: $8; $4.50, children 6 to 16, students and the elderly (Glueck).</p>
        <p>''GAME ON!,'' Sara Meltzer, 516 West 20th Street, Chelsea, (212) 727-9330 (through today). Fourteen artists have fun with sports in this smart and playful show. The two members of Type A wrestle on video; Sylvan Lionni's simulation of a Ping-Pong table and Michael Scott's baseball field on canvas both elegantly parody 1960's-style formalism; Jason Dodge offers a sleek conflation of sports and commodity fetishism; and Christopher Chiappa presents a concrete crash helmet (Johnson).</p>
        <p>ROBERTO JUAREZ: PAINTINGS, Robert Miller Gallery, 524 West 26th Street, (212) 366-4774 (through tomorrow). Gone are the lush blooms and biotica that used to flourish in Roberto Juarez's richly wrought paintings. His current works are New York-based abstractions that play on the garish mix of buildings in the new Times Square, along with elements from his recent paintings of Rome, now pared down to linear essences. True, the mosaics of loops, mazes, convoluted whorls and calligraphic writhings that characterize some paintings don't always make direct allusions. The biggest canvas, ''Times Square Tiles,'' suggests a huge, relaxed coil of beadwork, made up of tiny black and white modules. It evokes strands of genetic material swimming in a primal soup more than it does Times Square. The liquescent effect comes from the pale grounds of pink, green and other less distinguishable tonalities skillfully laid down by Mr. Juarez. These are strong paintings, a nice change of pace for this artist (Glueck).</p>
        <p>''HUMAN/NATURE,'' Caren Golden, 526 West 26th Street, (212) 727-8304, (through today). The old nature-culture duality gets a diversified workout in this entertaining show. Marguerite Kahrl ensconces a little talking model of the Unabomber's cabin in a papier-mache tree. Roxy Paine creates magically realistic cow pies that sprout psychedelic mushrooms. Austin Thomas photographs or paints pictures of special stones and adds odd, typewritten diaristic stories about them. And Robert Beck presents a haunting, multimedia installation that may memorialize a teenager's death in a hunting accident (Johnson).</p>
        <p>''PET SHOW 2000,'' Cynthia Broan, 423 West 14th Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 633-6525, (through tomorrow). Animals are considered, as pets and otherwise, and mostly with tongue in cheek, by 15 artists. On view are Mark Dion's mock Victorian posters advertising the vivisection of a goat; knitted walking outfits for dogs and other animals by Petra Schoenewald; a collapsed, inflatable bunny cast in concrete and painted pink by Tim Thyzel, the show's curator; and, by Rebecca Major, a sweet, straight photograph of a pet rabbit stretched out on a blue rug (Johnson).</p>
        <p>''SENTIMENTAL EDUCATION,'' Deitch Projects, 76 Grand Street, SoHo, (212) 343-7300 (through tomorrow). There are always a few hot summertime group shows that don't make the living feel easy, and this is one. Organized by the art critic David Rimanelli, it is titled after Flaubert's notably unsentimental 1870 novel about a good-looking ninny who heads to Paris for the artist's life. And it gathers together a group of interesting young New York and Los Angeles artists. Although the work isn't uniformly strong, it makes an intense cumulative read, like a page of entries from an archskeptic's personal notebook (Cotter).</p>
        <p>''TAIGONG FISHING, WILLING TO BITE THE BAIT,'' Jack Tilton Gallery, 49 Greene Street, SoHo, (212) 941-1775 (through Monday). Chinese-born and Paris-based, Huang Yong Ping has made previous appearances in New York, notably as a Hugo Boss Prize short-lister, but this is his best work here so far. It's an elegantly made installation based on a Chinese legend, though the story seems to matter less than the atmosphere of mystery generated by the evocative objects: a fish net hung with lures, copper pans suspended like scales, a world globe that opens like a chest and holds live poisonous insects (Cotter).</p>
        <p>''TOMORROW,'' Rare, 435 West 14th Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 645-5591 (through today). This noisy, invigorating exhibition is supposed to be about things to come, but it does not really make much sense as a theme show. It includes Beth Campbell's funny, handmade flow chart ''My Potential Future Based on Present Circumstances;'' Tony Matelli's anxious prehistoric men in hyperreal three dimensions; Ryan McGinness's field of plastic toy soldiers called ''Saving Ryan's Privates;'' and a Pop-Minimalist stack of empty fish tanks by Michael Phelan (Johnson).</p>
        <p>JOAQUIN TORRES-GARCIA, CDS, 76 East 79th Street, (212) 772-9555 (through tomorrow). This pioneering, peripatetic Uruguayan Modernist is represented in a modest exhibition of small works on paper and several easel-size oil paintings. The show includes early, brusquely painted city and harbor scenes but is devoted mainly to the artist's distinctive combination of grid-based abstraction and cosmic, pictographic symbolism (Johnson).</p>
        <p>* ''WEEGEE: DISTORTIONS,'' Matthew Marks Gallery, 523 West 23rd Street, Chelsea, (212) 243-0200 (through today). This fantastic show presents the little-seen, underappreciated late work of Arthur Fellig (1899-1968), or Weegee, whose gritty, implicitly Expressionistic camera work both invented and surpassed tabloid photojournalism in the 1930's and 40's. The early 50's found Weegee in Hollywood, inventing mostly in his darkroom and bringing the Expressionistic, often malicious edge of his art into the open. He subjected photographs, both old and new, to a range of abuses: melting negatives, doubling exposures and adding curved or variously textured glass to the enlarger. What he found was, in effect, a ready-made form of caricature. The victims of his distortions include movie starlets and politicians, artists and artworks whose images are bent and twisted, multiplied and divided to optically amusing, psychologically penetrating and sometimes frightening effect. The images are historically polymorphous as well, belonging equally to the history of Surrealism, political caricature, animation and photo appropriation (Smith).</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
