<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Jets' Ward Is Growing Into Role as Receiver</title>
    <meta content="28JETS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218204"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Jets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Battista, Judy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ward, Dedric</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000728T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE5D6163DF93BA15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="845" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Jets' Ward Is Growing Into Role as Receiver</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JUDY BATTISTA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Battista, Judy</byline>
      <dateline>HEMPSTEAD, N.Y., July 27</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Scene at New York Jets training camp described; receiver Dedric Ward discusses his preparations for season (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Even in this quietest of training camps, Keyshawn Johnson still hovers over the Jets, every view of the wide receivers infused with a comparison to the exiled star who seems to have grown mythically tall since his departure.</p>
        <p>If the corps of receivers charged with replacing Johnson seem Lilliputian when lined up on the height chart, then Dedric Ward -- without the renown of the starter Wayne Chrebet or the hype of the rookie class -- seems small enough, at 5 feet 9 inches, to fit into Johnson's pocket. Until he is on the field during training camp.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Even in this quietest of training camps, Keyshawn Johnson still hovers over the Jets, every view of the wide receivers infused with a comparison to the exiled star who seems to have grown mythically tall since his departure.</p>
        <p>If the corps of receivers charged with replacing Johnson seem Lilliputian when lined up on the height chart, then Dedric Ward -- without the renown of the starter Wayne Chrebet or the hype of the rookie class -- seems small enough, at 5 feet 9 inches, to fit into Johnson's pocket. Until he is on the field during training camp.</p>
        <p>Ward, penciled in as Johnson's replacement, had made a series of impressive receptions in the first two weeks of camp in an effort to fend off the rookie challengers and solidify his spot as the other starter. Today, he made a leaning, contorted catch, and during last Saturday's scrimmage, he repeatedly pulled down sideline passes. After starting the first five games of last season while Chrebet nursed an injured foot, then moving back to the third-receiver role when Chrebet returned, Ward seems ready to settle into the life of a starter.</p>
        <p>''I considered that a stepping stone,'' Ward said. ''That was an opportunity to get a feel for it on an every-down basis. When you're in on a consistent basis, you can stay loose, stay in the game. It's more of a challenge as a situational player coming in and out.''</p>
        <p>In his five games as a starter last season, Ward caught 15 passes for 143 yards and 2 touchdowns, unspectacular numbers. For the season, he had 22 catches for 325 yards and was disappointing as a punt returner, averaging just 7.6 yards per return. But Ward spent much of the off-season working out in Las Vegas with other pros, including Detroit quarterback Charlie Batch. The excruciating heat helped Ward hone his conditioning while he worked on sprinting drills. But defensive back Otis Smith has also noticed that Ward spent time in the weight room.</p>
        <p>''He has gotten a lot stronger,'' Smith said. ''He's not getting jammed on the line as much. He's a lot stronger at the line of scrimmage.''</p>
        <p>Ward will need whatever size -- and he thinks speed is a more critical factor than size -- he has added. With Johnson gone, the Jets do not have a designated receiver who regularly goes over the middle with Johnson's fearlessness.</p>
        <p>Ward has been known largely as a deep threat, but that role may be amended. With the Jets passing for now on the chance to sign a big, veteran receiver like Sean Dawkins or Carl Pickens, the group of receivers they have in camp will be charged with making up for Johnson's 89 receptions.</p>
        <p>''We're going to be versatile,'' Ward said. ''We don't have a guy who stands out at 6-4. We have guys who can get downfield. In certain situations, you'll see a lot of guys doing a lot of different things. I want to be a productive receiver, whether that's 20 catches or 50 catches.''</p>
        <p>Ward, as much as any receiver, has gone largely unnoticed in camp, lost in the talk about Laveranues Coles's speed, Windrell Hayes's hands and Yatil Green's knees. Chrebet, of course, is locked in for his starting role, but Ward seems to have benefited from the challenge he has received.</p>
        <p>''I like the way he's practiced,'' Coach Al Groh said. ''His consistency has improved and that's a key issue for Dedric. The change in Dedric's role is that he's seeing more people behind him, chasing him. Some people run a little faster when they're being chased than when they're chasing. Early indications are that he's responding.''</p>
        <p>EXTRA POINTS</p>
        <p>Linebacker MO LEWIS has a strain in his left leg and is day to day. It is possible he could miss Saturday night's game against New Orleans at Giants Stadium. . . . Cornerback RAY MICKENS (hamstring) should return to practice next week, ending a frustrating period of inactivity. ''It's tough for me to be on the sideline after working hard this summer,'' Mickens said. ''I was playing pretty well the first four days of camp. I'm anxious to get back.'' Mickens's injury has given the rookie TONY SCOTT more practice time with the starting unit as the slot cornerback and Mickens has been helping Scott learn the position. . . . Defensive end ERIC OGBOGU (shoulder) and defensive tackle JASON WILTZ (elbow) missed practice. . . . Rookie receivers LAVERANUES COLES and WINDRELL HAYES will get rotations during Saturday's game returning kicks.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
