<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mad Scientist's Weight Loss Formula for Disaster</title>
    <meta content="28NUTT$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218183"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Murphy, Eddie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mitchell, Elvis</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Nutty Professor II: The Klumps (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews/By Elvis Mitchell</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000728T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE1D9163DF93BA15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1442" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mad Scientist's Weight Loss Formula for Disaster</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELVIS MITCHELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mitchell, Elvis</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Elvis Mitchell reviews movie Nutty Professor II: The Klumps, directed by Peter Segal and starring Eddie Murphy as seven different characters; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Poor Eddie Murphy. He gave the performance of a lifetime in ''The Nutty Professor,'' with the kind of professional breakthrough that showed he had become an actor with serious chops, and yet Jim Carrey gets all the reviews. In ''Nutty Professor II: The Klumps,'' Mr. Murphy again displays enough agility to show that he deserves to be taken seriously. We probably shouldn't feel too bad for his being overlooked; after all, the first ''Professor'' was a big hit. And this one will be, too.</p>
        <p>Parts of the film are tremendously funny. Every single scene in which Mr. Murphy, hidden away under millions of dollars' worth of transformative makeup, plays all the members of the Klump family -- all of them together in some scenes -- will knock the blues right out of you. But some of the cheap laughs to which the picture stoops will give you the blues. This makes ''Nutty Professor II'' half a movie at best. The broad humor at times derails Mr. Murphy's performances, but the movie provides a vehicle for him to display his reach.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Poor Eddie Murphy. He gave the performance of a lifetime in ''The Nutty Professor,'' with the kind of professional breakthrough that showed he had become an actor with serious chops, and yet Jim Carrey gets all the reviews. In ''Nutty Professor II: The Klumps,'' Mr. Murphy again displays enough agility to show that he deserves to be taken seriously. We probably shouldn't feel too bad for his being overlooked; after all, the first ''Professor'' was a big hit. And this one will be, too.</p>
        <p>Parts of the film are tremendously funny. Every single scene in which Mr. Murphy, hidden away under millions of dollars' worth of transformative makeup, plays all the members of the Klump family -- all of them together in some scenes -- will knock the blues right out of you. But some of the cheap laughs to which the picture stoops will give you the blues. This makes ''Nutty Professor II'' half a movie at best. The broad humor at times derails Mr. Murphy's performances, but the movie provides a vehicle for him to display his reach.</p>
        <p>The original ''Nutty Professor,'' made in 1963, was an update of ''Dr. Jekyll and Mr. Hyde'' starring Jerry Lewis as Dr. Julius Kelp, a mega-nerd college professor crippled by  shyness. Kelp invents a formula to unleash his inner hipster, Buddy Love. The 1996 remake starring Mr. Murphy did the same thing, with the actor playing an overweight professor, Sherman Klump, who spent time with his family -- mother, father, elder brother and grandmother, all played by Mr. Murphy.</p>
        <p>In portraying Buddy Love, Mr. Lewis was shockingly good. He burrowed deep to come up with a dexterous, shaped performance that was both sublime and a murderously hostile star turn: a full-blooded parody of his former partner, Dean Martin. Mr. Lewis's impersonation came complete with a satyr's cosmic boredom and an ability to read people that functioned as a dry Vegas version of Sherlock Holmesian ratiocination. For Mr. Murphy, Buddy Love is a sketch character, with condescension for this loud-mouthed player manque built-in. Mr. Murphy can't play this guy straight; he's too busy scoring off Love's loutishness.</p>
        <p>The main crisis is that Buddy Love still exists inside Sherman, and he erupts from Sherman's subconscious with awful frequency. Buddy finds a way out when Sherman withdraws the aberrant gene that created his slim but ravenous Id; the extracted gene looks like irradiated Windex. In another subplot, Sherman discovers a Fountain of Youth formula, and his father, Cletus, drinks some of it to recapture his potency.</p>
        <p>It is in his depictions of the Klumps that Mr. Murphy exhibits perceptiveness and depth. He doesn't condescend to any of the people for an instant, and his affection for the characters -- the kind of people he might have made fun of as a younger man -- is contagious. They're funny because he has so thoroughly worked out the deportment, which is what makes them real. The Klumps are people he knows and loves, especially Sherman's mother, whose vanity is part of the characterization. He has a character actor's reflexes now; he can submerge himself into a role without telegraphing to an audience what he thinks of the character.</p>
        <p>Generally, performers wearing layers of makeup strain to show off. Mr. Murphy uses the prosthetics as a tool, as they should be used; he has worked out all of the emotional details from the inside. (Method actors study for years to achieve this kind of understanding.) His Sherman Klump has reserves of modesty and charm, with a mellow bass chuckle that radiates contentment. Mr. Murphy could play the character for cheap pathos -- the sad, heavy-set clown who demands sympathy -- but he doesn't. Instead, Sherman is a man who has settled into his place in the world; he has a jaunty, graceful gait for such a big man. It's his infatuations that get him into trouble.</p>
        <p>In the first ''Professor,'' Jada Pinkett got his pheromones going. This time it's Janet Jackson, and the biggest special effect in the movie is her playing a genetics scientist. The names of the chemical compounds don't come trippingly off her tongue; it's as if they trip off her tongue. She is not the only person given to monologues better suited to the creaky exposition scenes of an austere Hammer Studios horror film of the 1950's and 60's; ''The Klumps'' screeches to a halt a number of times as we get lengthy scientific explanations, leaving skid marks and unintended comedy. And there's a lot to explain.</p>
        <p>There's also enough toilet humor  to show that Mr. Murphy can compete with Mr. Carrey and the Farrelly brothers. There are flatulence flambe and projectile pellets from a giant hamster, among other touches. ''The Klumps'' features parodies within parodies as well; one is a dream sequence that takes on ''Star Wars'' and ''Deep Impact,'' while another uses ''Cape Fear'' as a launching pad. (The rhythm-and-blues singer Freda Payne, who still looks like a hood ornament carved out of chocolate, shows up to cruise Cletus.)</p>
        <p>There's also straight-talking, libidinous Grandma, who brings down the house; some of her material is unbelievably crude and shocks a laugh out of you. She's clearly based on the gruff, dirty comedian Moms Mabley, and her behavior shows where Buddy Love comes from, especially when the two meet and she sizes him up like a prime cut. Even he is put off by her audacity. ''You look just like Ken Norton in that movie 'Mandingo,' '' she says, running her tongue across her gums.</p>
        <p>It's tough for ''The Klumps'' to work as well as its predecessor because there is no novelty left in Mr. Murphy's prodigious multiple performances. (In addition, some of the characters sound similar to Mr. Murphy's voice-over as the gruff super on the Claymation series ''The PJ's'' on Fox.) Still, he shows the discordant nimbleness of Thelonious Monk, the brilliant jazz pianist whose hands found chord voicings so distinctive it was as if each had a mind of its own. How else could Mr. Murphy keep all these characters straight and still riff in the way he does? The essentials are all worked out, and a scene in which the Klumps gather around the television set to watch Sherman at a news conference is a classic.</p>
        <p>Tribute should be paid, too, to the makeup artist, Rick Baker, who won an Oscar for the first Murphy ''Professor.'' Care has been taken to make all the Klump men look like family; their heads are the same shape and the plain-spoken father, Cletus, and Sherman's brother, Ernie, are balding. Sherman has all his hair, perhaps because he is closer in looks and temperament to his big-hearted mother. But each of the characters has an individual and well-defined mouth. The differentiations in Mr. Baker's workmanship almost deserve their own movie.</p>
        <p>The Farrellys have been applauded for the genius African-American triplets in ''Me, Myself and Irene,'' hip-hop gunslingers who have filtered the chaos theory through Chris Rock and Richard Pryor. But it's Mr. Murphy who has made the daring move: the large, courtly Sherman Klump, with his countrified enunciation -- the kind of black man who would probably be taken for a preacher, like many other African-Americans in suits -- is a prodigy, a man who takes pride and refuge in his understanding of science. It's subversive on a level that many African-Americans will know, and love.</p>
        <p>''Nutty Professor II'' is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). It includes plentiful toilet humor and broad sexual jokes.</p>
        <p>NUTTY PROFESSOR II  The Klumps</p>
        <p>Directed by Peter Segal; written by Barry W. Blaustein, David Sheffield, Paul Weitz and Chris Weitz, based on a story by Steve Oedekerk, Mr. Blaustein and Mr. Sheffield; director of photography, Dean Semler; edited by William Kerr; music by David Newman; production designer, William Elliott; produced by Brian Grazer; released by Universal Pictures. Running time: 105 minutes. This film is rated PG-13.</p>
        <p>WITH: Eddie Murphy (Sherman Klump, Buddy Love, Granny Klump, Mama Klump, Papa Klump, Young Papa Klump and Ernie Klump), Janet Jackson (Denise Gaines), Larry Miller (Dean Richmond) and John Ales (Jason).</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
