<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Westchester Correction Officers Reach Deal on Labor Contract</title>
    <meta content="28WEST$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218310"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Guards</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Westchester Correction Officers Benevolent Assn</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Baker, Al</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Guards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000728T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE5D8173DF93BA15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="411" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Westchester Correction Officers Reach Deal on Labor Contract</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AL BAKER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Baker, Al</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Westchester Correction Officers Benevolent Association reaches tentative contract accord with Westchester County, NY, that will raise pay of 770 correction officers and modify costly disability rule; at heart of dispute was rule allowing officers to go on disability without first proving injury; county says over 100 officers a day call in injured, forcing others to work mandatory extra shifts in volatile environment (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The union that represents 770 correction officers in Westchester County has reached a tentative agreement on a new labor contract that would raise the pay of employees and modify a costly disability rule, officials said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The settlement came late Wednesday after more than four years of negotiations with two county administrations. The tentative deal was greeted with relief by both sides, who in recent weeks said that the dispute had ratcheted up tensions inside the county jail, which holds 1,300.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The union that represents 770 correction officers in Westchester County has reached a tentative agreement on a new labor contract that would raise the pay of employees and modify a costly disability rule, officials said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The settlement came late Wednesday after more than four years of negotiations with two county administrations. The tentative deal was greeted with relief by both sides, who in recent weeks said that the dispute had ratcheted up tensions inside the county jail, which holds 1,300.</p>
        <p>''My members have waited a really long time,'' said Joseph K. Spano, the president of the Westchester Correction Officers Benevolent Association, ''and I want them to get this thing and review this proposal in its entirety.''</p>
        <p>Larry S. Schwartz, an adviser to County Executive Andrew J. Spano, a Democrat, said no details on the deal would be released until it was ratified by the union members. But he said, ''We believe it is fair to the correction officers and it is fair to the taxpayers of Westchester County.''</p>
        <p>At the heart of the labor dispute was a perquisite, negotiated in 1989 by a former Republican administration, that allows officers to go on disability without first proving that they are injured. Currently, more than 100 officers a day report that they are injured and cannot come to work, forcing others to work mandatory extra shifts in a volatile environment, according to the county.</p>
        <p>The union has been without a contract since December 1995. The annual base salary for officers with four years on the job is $47,050. The new contract would extend through the end of 2001.</p>
        <p>Mr. Spano, the union chief, said that he would immediately provide copies of the agreement to his board of directors and that on Aug. 8 union members would meet before the vote among the rank and file, on Aug. 17.</p>
        <p>If the proposal passes by a simple majority, it will then go to the county Legislature, and will require a 9-to-8 majority vote to pass, Mr. Schwartz said.</p>
        <p>Lois T. Bronz, the board's vice chairwoman, said she had not seen the contract but lawmakers would like it finalized in September.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
