<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>AUTOS ON FRIDAY/Safety; When Losing a License Is No Curb on Driving</title>
    <meta content="28CARS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218169"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drivers Licenses</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wald, Matthew L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drivers Licenses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000728T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE0DB163DF93BA15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="904" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>AUTOS ON FRIDAY/Safety; When Losing a License Is No Curb on Driving</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wald, Matthew L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Autos on Friday column on dangers posed by people who continue to drive with suspended or invalid licenses and cause havoc on the road (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>REVOKING or suspending a driver's license is one of the most severe punishments for moving violations. But the police and some safety advocates suspect that often it is no punishment at all, and no protection for other people on the road, because in many cases it does not stop the violator from driving.</p>
        <p>A new study agrees, finding that at one of the few points for which data is collected on license status -- when someone is killed -- at least one of the drivers involved does not have a valid license in about one accident in five.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>REVOKING or suspending a driver's license is one of the most severe punishments for moving violations. But the police and some safety advocates suspect that often it is no punishment at all, and no protection for other people on the road, because in many cases it does not stop the violator from driving.</p>
        <p>A new study agrees, finding that at one of the few points for which data is collected on license status -- when someone is killed -- at least one of the drivers involved does not have a valid license in about one accident in five.</p>
        <p>In a study sponsored by the AAA Foundation for Traffic Safety, researchers analyzed 184,000 fatal crashes over five years, involving more than 206,000 fatalities. Nearly 37,000 of the crashes involved a driver who did not appear to be properly licensed. Of the 278,000 drivers involved in the crashes, regardless of who was at fault, 13.8 percent had a license that was not valid for one reason or another. Some had never been licensed, and others had been denied licenses. Fifty-four percent had licenses that had been revoked or suspended.</p>
        <p>The finding impressed the president of the AAA foundation, David K. Willis. The roughly 42,000 who died in crashes involving an improperly licensed driver was the equivalent of dozens of ''Boeing 737's falling out of the sky each year,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Usually, he said, his foundation issues reports and makes recommendations, but in this case it had none. ''I wish I knew the answer,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Many fatal crashes are single-car wrecks, and the unlicensed driver is the only driver involved, but often there are passengers or drivers of other vehicles. And sometimes, according to the survey data, there were even collisions involving two or three cars that were all driven by people who were not licensed.</p>
        <p>By focusing on a single point with reliable data -- fatal crashes -- the study underscored how little is known about everyday driving.</p>
        <p>The authors, Lindsay I. Griffin III and Sandra DeLaZerda, both with the Texas Transportation Institute at Texas A &amp; M University, did not make their own estimate of the prevalence of driving without a proper license, but cited the work of others. A 1994 study predicted that 30 to 70 percent of drivers whose licenses were suspended or revoked might continue to drive. That study showed a sharp regional divergence in the extent of the problem, which was far worse in the West.</p>
        <p>Those driving with an invalid license, no license, or ''unknown license status'' at the time of a fatal crash made up more than 20 percent of total fatalities in Alaska, Hawaii, California, Arizona, the District of Columbia and New Mexico. They were less than 10 percent in Maine, New Hampshire, Minnesota, Kentucky, Massachusetts, Nebraska, Ohio, Maryland and Iowa.</p>
        <p>There was also a big demographic difference. Men, who are nearly 3 times as likely as women to be drivers in fatal crashes, were more than 6 times as likely to be driving with a suspended license and almost 10 times as likely to be driving with a revoked license.</p>
        <p>Compared with all drivers, those without proper licenses were also likely to be young. And accidents involving unlicensed drivers were clustered at night.</p>
        <p>The profile of the unlicensed driver thus resembles that of the drunken driver -- and, in fact, the unlicensed drivers were far more likely to have had one or more suspensions for driving under the influence of alcohol, suggesting that the license problem is an extension of the drunken-driving issue.</p>
        <p>Mothers Against Drunk Driving and other safety advocates have been successful in persuading some states to invoke ''administrative license revocation,'' known as A.L.R., a process under which a person stopped for driving under the influence loses his or her license promptly, with court proceedings later. But Karolyn Nunnallee, the immediate past president of MADD, said that while the procedure was sound, ''we don't want A.L.R. to be a stand-alone law.'' She added, ''We want fines assessed, community service hours ordered and jail time for second-time offenders.</p>
        <p>In a surprising twist, Ms. Nunnallee and others agree that people who drive with suspended or revoked licenses tend to speed less, run fewer red lights and commit fewer other infractions, for fear of drawing attention to themselves. ''They oddly continue to drive a little safer than they did before,'' she said. They also drive fewer miles, some experts believe.</p>
        <p>But to make them stop driving altogether is much harder. California has experimented with ''arresting'' the vehicle when someone's license is revoked or suspended, so to speak, and holding it for 30 days; North Carolina and some other states will confiscate and auction off a vehicle for certain driving offenses. Neither tactic is foolproof, though.</p>
        <p>Dr. Griffin, the study's co-author, said the long-term solution might be technological, a license that is a ''smart card,'' like an automated-teller card or a key card, that would be required to start the engine. But even this would not be perfect, he said, because someone without a valid license could steal one, or borrow one from someone else. And Mr. Willis said such cards would pose ''a Big Brother issue.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
