<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>D.H. Blair and Executives Indicted in Fraud Case</title>
    <meta content="Y28BLAI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218208"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Brokers and Brokerage Firms</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Industrial Espionage</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Blair, D H, &amp; Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Morgenson, Gretchen</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Brokers and Brokerage Firms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Espionage</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Futures and Options Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000728T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04EFD6163DF93BA15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="565" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>D.H. Blair and Executives Indicted in Fraud Case</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GRETCHEN MORGENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Morgenson, Gretchen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>D H Blair &amp; Co, defunct Manhattan brokerage firm, and 15 of its officers and employees are indicted on securities fraud charges by grand jury; prosecutors say firm's executives reaped illegal profit by manipulating stock prices, engaged in high-pressure sales tactics to generate excessive commissions and stole investor data from other firms to increase their customer base; 173-count indictment charges that from 1989 to 1998 executives and stockbrokers at D H Blair ran firm as criminal enterprise (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>D.H. Blair &amp; Company, a defunct Manhattan brokerage firm, and 15 of its officers and employees were indicted yesterday on securities fraud charges by a grand jury in Manhattan. The firm's executives, prosecutors said, reaped illegal profit by manipulating stock prices, engaged in high-pressure sales tactics to generate excessive commissions and stole investor data from other firms to increase their customer base.</p>
        <p>The 173-count indictment, announced by District Attorney Robert M. Morgenthau, charged that from 1989 to 1998 executives and stockbrokers at D. H. Blair ran the firm as a criminal enterprise. Mr. Morgenthau said that Kenton Wood, Blair's chairman, supervised the fraud, as did Alan Stahler and Kalman Renov, the vice chairmen. D. H. Blair ceased operation in 1998.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>D.H. Blair &amp; Company, a defunct Manhattan brokerage firm, and 15 of its officers and employees were indicted yesterday on securities fraud charges by a grand jury in Manhattan. The firm's executives, prosecutors said, reaped illegal profit by manipulating stock prices, engaged in high-pressure sales tactics to generate excessive commissions and stole investor data from other firms to increase their customer base.</p>
        <p>The 173-count indictment, announced by District Attorney Robert M. Morgenthau, charged that from 1989 to 1998 executives and stockbrokers at D. H. Blair ran the firm as a criminal enterprise. Mr. Morgenthau said that Kenton Wood, Blair's chairman, supervised the fraud, as did Alan Stahler and Kalman Renov, the vice chairmen. D. H. Blair ceased operation in 1998.</p>
        <p>The investigation began in the fall of 1997 and grew out of Mr. Morgenthau's prosecution of A. R. Baron, a fraudulent brokerage firm that bilked investors out of $75 million. When Baron closed in 1996, most of its brokers moved to D. H. Blair.</p>
        <p>More than 50,000 customers invested with Blair in the period covered by the indictment, prosecutors said. One victim, a 56-year-old disabled man from Colorado, lost $150,000 from a disability settlement that he had allocated for medical bills and living expenses. A 70-year-old Florida man lost $250,000 from his retirement accounts.</p>
        <p>''D. H. Blair's was a sophisticated fraud,'' said Daniel J. Castleman, chief of the investigation division in the district attorney's office. ''They were dealing with real companies, but manipulating prices of stock by illegal means in order for favored customers to make money.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Castleman said Blair officials falsified business records, suppressed clients' complaints and misled securities regulators to evade detection. The firm's chief stock trader and 11 of its registered representatives were also named in the indictment. Three former brokers have admitted securities fraud.</p>
        <p>Lawyers for Mr. Stahler and Mr. Wood called the charges baseless and said their clients would contest them vigorously. Mr. Renov's lawyer did not return a phone call.</p>
        <p>Prosecutors could not specify how much was stolen from investors. They said Blair manipulated shares of 10 companies taken public by an associated firm, D. H. Blair Investment Banking. The investment bank was not named in the indictment.</p>
        <p>Earlier this year, the National Association of Securities Dealers took action against D. H. Blair, which resulted in a $2.4 million restitution fund.</p>
        <p>D. H. Blair Investment Banking, which was spun off from the brokerage firm in 1992, is now run by J. Morton Davis, who presided over D. H. Blair &amp; Company for more than 20 years. Eight years ago, he turned the brokerage operation over to family members. Mr. Stahler and Mr. Renov, the vice chairmen indicted yesterday, are sons-in-law of Mr. Davis.</p>
        <p>Two years ago, Mr. Davis wrote a book entitled ''From Hard Knocks to Hot Stocks: How I Made A Fortune Through Smart Investing and How You Can, Too.''</p>
        <p>Prosecutors say the investigation of D. H. Blair &amp; Company is continuing.</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
