<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Big City; Absolutely, Positively Unrealistic</title>
    <meta content="28BIG" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218250"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Outdoor Advertising</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Absolut</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tierney, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/John Tierney</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Outdoor Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000728T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E3DB173DF93BA15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="833" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Big City; Absolutely, Positively Unrealistic</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN TIERNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tierney, John</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>John Tierney column on Manhattan studio apartment depicted in life-size, three-dimentional Absolut vodka billboard; holds apartment, while far larger than most New York City studios, conforms to popular image of such apartments in films and television (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ABSOLUT New York, as defined on a new billboard at Lafayette and Bond Streets, is a studio apartment in the shape of a vodka bottle. The three-dimensional apartment is fully equipped with real furniture, rugs, kitchen appliances and a bathtub that are all affixed to the billboard.</p>
        <p>It's described as a life-size apartment, which is indeed the scale of the 49-foot-wide billboard, but anyone who has been hunting for real-life apartments in NoHo could quibble with the dimensions. This studio apartment has a total of 900 square feet of space, which is absolutely not New York in today's real-estate ads. That's more like the size of a two-bedroom.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ABSOLUT New York, as defined on a new billboard at Lafayette and Bond Streets, is a studio apartment in the shape of a vodka bottle. The three-dimensional apartment is fully equipped with real furniture, rugs, kitchen appliances and a bathtub that are all affixed to the billboard.</p>
        <p>It's described as a life-size apartment, which is indeed the scale of the 49-foot-wide billboard, but anyone who has been hunting for real-life apartments in NoHo could quibble with the dimensions. This studio apartment has a total of 900 square feet of space, which is absolutely not New York in today's real-estate ads. That's more like the size of a two-bedroom.</p>
        <p>But while the apartment may not conform to reality, it does conform to the popular image of a Manhattan apartment. Over-size homes are the norm on film and television. When New Yorkers see their alleged apartments on the screen, their reaction is often Robert Redford's in ''Legal Eagles'' upon entering the SoHo loft of Darryl Hannah, a performance artist who has just told him she inherited no money from her father.</p>
        <p>''Lot of room,'' he says, looking in surprise around a space big enough to be a basketball court.</p>
        <p>In ''Desk Set,'' Katherine Hepburn lives in an Upper East Side apartment that seems grandiose for a magazine researcher, although it's nothing compared with the digs of a newspaper reporter, Lois Lane. In the movie ''Superman,'' Christopher Reeve finds Margot Kidder waiting on a rooftop terrace fit for a wedding reception. It looks like the Peninsula Hotel's rooftop bar, but with a better garden.</p>
        <p>Even before John Cassavetes and Mia Farrow get to know their strange new neighbors in ''Rosemary's Baby,'' it's clear that supernatural forces are at work. How else could an unsuccessful young actor get an apartment in the Dakota?</p>
        <p>How does Sigourney Weaver, playing a classical musician in ''Ghostbusters,'' afford a co-op on Central Park West with a huge kitchen and a park view? How does Deborah Kerr, playing a school teacher in ''An Affair to Remember'' who says she's ''on a budget,'' manage a one-bedroom apartment with a large sunken living room, marble fireplace and balcony?</p>
        <p>There's been some realism on TV, as on ''The Honeymooners'' and ''Seinfeld.'' The huge apartment of a waitress and an unemployed chef on ''Friends' is explained away as a rent-regulated legacy. But the huge rooms on ''Mad About You'' remain a mystery to most New Yorkers, including Chuck Katz, the author of ''Manhattan on Film: Walking Tours of Hollywood's Fabled Front Lot.''</p>
        <p>''The bathroom in 'Mad About You' looks bigger than most Manhattan apartments,'' Mr. Katz said. ''It's not realistic for that young couple to be living in a place like that, but you can see the practical reasons for it. In one episode they get locked in the bathroom. If two people got locked in my bathroom, there'd be no room for a film crew.''</p>
        <p>LOCATION scouts for films are accustomed to suspending disbelief. ''I've told directors dozens of times that an apartment is a little upscale for the character,'' said Dana Robin, who has 15 years of experience scouting locations. ''But the directors need high ceilings and big rooms for light and cameras.'' They also have to consider the audience in the rest of the country.</p>
        <p>''People in the rest of the country would be shocked to see how New Yorkers really live,'' Mr. Robin said. ''Your hero, unless he's a down-and-outer, should live in what looks to the audience at least like a respectable place, if not better. The entertainment business likes to perpetuate a bigger and grander picture of life.''</p>
        <p>So does the advertising industry, which is why the studio on the billboard is so big. ''We didn't set out to create an apartment for the New York Everyman,'' said Richard Lewis, worldwide account director for Absolut at the TBWA/Chiat/Day agency. ''It's a place where the Absolut New Yorker would live.''</p>
        <p>These fantasy apartments can be disillusioning for the natives, because they must make our places look even more cramped by comparison. But in some ways we also benefit from the false images.</p>
        <p>''These big apartments are a P.R. campaign for New Yorkers,'' Mr. Katz said. ''We don't want the rest of the country to know how we live. We'd rather show a young actor in the Dakota instead of in a fifth-floor walk-up in Brooklyn. We don't want our friends back in Tucson or Chicago to know the real bargain with the devil here: you can get a great job, but you have to live in a shoe box.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
