<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Babies' Pain Has Long Effect, Study Hints</title>
    <meta content="Y28PAI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218234"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pain</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Rats</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Science (Journal)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Grady, Denise</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ruda, Maryann (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Pediatrics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Pain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000728T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E6DC173DF93BA15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="743" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Babies' Pain Has Long Effect, Study Hints</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DENISE GRADY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Grady, Denise</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Study showing that pain administered in infancy can create permanent hypersensitivity in rats may have implications for human infants who undergo painful medical procedures; research led by Dr Maryann Ruda is published in journal Science (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A study showing that pain administered in infancy can permanently rewire the nervous system in rats may have implications for human infants undergoing painful medical procedures, researchers are reporting today.</p>
        <p>Rats whose feet were made sore  for a few days when they were infants ended up hypersensitive to pain as adults, the researchers found. The finding, they said, could be worrisome in the case of babies and premature infants in intensive care units who are repeatedly stuck with needles and subjected to other painful tests and treatments.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A study showing that pain administered in infancy can permanently rewire the nervous system in rats may have implications for human infants undergoing painful medical procedures, researchers are reporting today.</p>
        <p>Rats whose feet were made sore  for a few days when they were infants ended up hypersensitive to pain as adults, the researchers found. The finding, they said, could be worrisome in the case of babies and premature infants in intensive care units who are repeatedly stuck with needles and subjected to other painful tests and treatments.</p>
        <p>If the finding in animals is confirmed in people, it will provide strong evidence that even the smallest premature babies need careful treatment for pain. In the past, it was thought that newborns and premature infants had little pain sensitivity, and circumcisions and even major operations were often performed on them without anesthesia.</p>
        <p>It is now known that infants are quite sensitive to pain, and they are no longer subjected to surgery without anesthesia. But they do still undergo painful procedures, like blood tests without the use of painkilling creams that numb the skin.</p>
        <p>In the rats, hypersensitivity apparently occurred because their nervous systems were still developing and reacted to the foot irritation by sprouting extra pain nerves in the spinal cord, according to the new report, by Dr. Maryann Ruda and other researchers from the National Institute of Dental and Craniofacial Research, whose work is being reported today in the journal Science.</p>
        <p>But it is not clear how much bearing the findings have on people, even though baby rats and human infants behave similarly in response to pain, and the pain pathways in their nervous systems develop in much the same way.</p>
        <p>Dr. Charles Berde, a professor of pediatrics and anesthesiology at Harvard Medical School, who did not take part in the new study, said some research in human infants had also suggested that lasting hypersensitivity could result from pain during infancy. But, he said, the findings are highly controversial.</p>
        <p>At one extreme, he said, are researchers who argue that babies are highly resilient and recover from all manner of unpleasant experiences. At the other extreme are those who take the view that injury and pain will damage a child for life. The truth may fall somewhere in between, he said, but good data about long-term effects is scarce.</p>
        <p>''It is certainly true that injury in early life causes changes in the pattern of connections and nerve organization,'' Dr. Berde said. ''That has good and bad aspects. There may be persistent oversensitivity to pain, but there may also be more capacity to recover from it.''</p>
        <p>He said that premature babies in intensive care units often did become hypersensitive to pain, but that it was not known how long the condition lasted. Paradoxically, in some cases where children might be expected to become hypersensitive, they do not, he said. For example, he said, babies with shoulder injuries resulting from difficult births rarely show signs of pain, even during physical therapy; adults with similar injuries from motorcycle accidents frequently have long-term pain.</p>
        <p>Dr. Ruda and her colleagues injected a substance to create a sore and swollen hind foot for five to seven days in newborn rats.</p>
        <p>''We let them mature like normal rats would, and when they were adults we looked at the anatomical organization of the nerves innervating the hind paw, going from the foot to the spinal cord,'' she said. The researchers found that extra nerve endings had sprouted and had also branched into new areas of the spinal cord where they would not normally be found. The adult animals also showed a greater than normal response to pain, Dr. Ruda said.</p>
        <p>She said that rats were generally considered a good model for studying pain in humans, but that a study in people would be needed to determine whether they suffered similar long-term consequences.</p>
        <p>''What's needed now,'' she said, ''is to get a population of individuals that did have treatments that caused significant pain and tissue injury as neonates and do careful pain measures on them now and see if there are differences and to what extent they occur.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
