<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tea With a Twist</title>
    <meta content="28EATI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="39" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218156"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="EATING OUT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tea</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000728T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEFDD163DF93BA15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1501" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tea With a Twist</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Eating Out reviews of interesting places to enjoy afternoon tea in Manhattan; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Afternoon tea is a charming and relaxing way to escape the bustle of the city for an hour or two. Here are several of the most interesting tea places in Manhattan. (These summaries are taken from dining reviews, columns and articles in The Times by William Grimes, Eric Asimov and others.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Afternoon tea is a charming and relaxing way to escape the bustle of the city for an hour or two. Here are several of the most interesting tea places in Manhattan. (These summaries are taken from dining reviews, columns and articles in The Times by William Grimes, Eric Asimov and others.)</p>
        <p>1. Anglers and Writers  +++  (212) 675-0810  420 Hudson Street,</p>
        <p>at St. Lukes Place  West Village  $$ Cash only</p>
        <p>This family-run institution is eclectic and charming, decorated with antique tables and china, fishing gear and lace doilies. The menu offers homey American fare, from tasty soups and sandwiches to salads and family-style dinners, the likes of chicken pot pie filled with fresh vegetables and aromatic herbs, turkey casserole, bourbon-glazed baked ham and lamb stew. There is a popular afternoon tea, served in antique pots with beautiful English china and Danish open-face sandwiches like seafood salad, salmon salad and chicken salad, homemade fruit scones and petits fours. Tea is served 3 to 7 p.m. weekdays and 4 to 7 p.m. on weekends.</p>
        <p>2. C3  +  (212) 254-1200  103 Waverly Place, at Macdougal Street  Greenwich Village  $ All major cards</p>
        <p>This pleasant restaurant in the Washington Square Hotel has been through several chefs, several menus and several renovations in recent years. It always seems to be able to offer enticing food at attractive prices. With John McGrath as the chef, C3's menu includes internationally accented dishes like crisp calamari with chipotle aioli, grilled Thai shrimp, and plantain-crusted snapper. The afternoon tea menu -- 3:30 to 5 p.m. Monday through Saturday -- offers finger sandwiches and assorted sweets with a pot of tea at $8.25 for one or $14.95 for two. The tea selection includes about 10 varieties of black, green and herbal teas.</p>
        <p>3. The Felissimo Tea Room  +++  (212) 956-0082  10 West 56th Street  $ All major cards</p>
        <p>This town house department store has given tea a New Age twist, imbuing the traditional ceremony with a mystical healthfulness that is as restfully pleasant as it is contrived. In the top-floor tea room, tranquil music forms a backdrop for the sleek wood tables, high-back chairs and modern semi-industrial interior softened by sheaves of dried wheat. Delicious sandwiches include roasted vegetables and hummus, smoked salmon, and brie and sliced apple. Tiny scones are studded with bits of chocolate, almost a dessert prelude to the platter of cookies and chocolates that complete the meal. A wide selection of teas is served in small black earthenware pots and cups from 3 to 5:30 p.m. daily.</p>
        <p>4. The Gotham Lounge  +++  (212) 903-3918  Peninsula Hotel  700 Fifth Avenue, at 55th Street  $$ All major cards</p>
        <p>The Gotham Lounge in the lobby of the Peninsula Hotel is an intimate setting for afternoon tea from 2:30 to 5 p.m. daily for $35 a person. The menu includes tea sandwiches like smoked salmon; cucumber and crab meat; and smoked chicken and asparagus; scones with Devonshire clotted cream and fruit preserves; lemon poppyseed, banana walnut and chocolate macadamia tea breads; little fruit tartlets; and chocolate pastries. There are seven varieties of tea from Taylors of Harrogate.</p>
        <p>5. Lady Mendl's Tea Salon  +++  (212) 533-4600  56 Irving Place, near 17th Street  $ All major cards</p>
        <p>Some people find nothing more romantic than afternoon tea, especially at a place like Lady Mendl's. Aside from the painstaking service, the lovingly assembled collection of antique upholstered chairs, couches and tables, the period French and English china, and the Persian and Russian rugs, the five-course tea is deliciously enticing. It may start with a mild sweet, like sorbet or ground walnuts with chopped dates and a splash of Grand Marnier, then move on to tea sandwiches, scones with clotted cream and jam, petits fours and finally luscious tarts and cakes, all washed down with the carefully chosen and unusual teas. Tea is served Wednesdays through Fridays at 3 p.m. and Saturdays and Sundays, with seatings at 2 and 4:30 p.m. at $30 a person.</p>
        <p>6. The Mark  +++  (212) 879-1864  25 East 77th Street  $ All major cards</p>
        <p>Tea is served in an attractive sitting area full of flowers and plants just outside the entrance to Mark's, the hotel restaurant. With lots of dark green and wood, the room looks like a handsome library in an English hunting lodge, with comfortable chairs and side tables and just the right light for reading. The $21 Mark tea -- from 2:30 to 5:30 p.m. -- includes three delicate, delicious sandwiches like smoked salmon; cucumber and watercress with dill butter; and egg salad with mango chutney. Large raisin scones are served with mascarpone, and there is a welcome choice between some attractive pastries and a dish of fruit. The tea, Harney's &amp; Sons from Britain, is excellent, served with a small pot of hot water to dilute the tea if it has steeped too long.</p>
        <p>7. Payard Patisserie And Bistro  **  [Rating: Two stars]  (212) 717-5252  1032 Lexington Avenue, at 73rd Street  $$ All major cards</p>
        <p>For four years, Francois Payard created the remarkable desserts at Daniel. A few years ago he and Daniel Boulud joined forces to open this bakery and bistro, and the crowds have been ogling the gorgeous display of pastries ever since. The bakery selection is encyclopedic, ranging from classic French desserts like eclairs and mille-feuilles to Viennese confections to tarts and cakes. Afternoon tea, served 3:30 to 5 p.m. Monday through Saturday, includes a selection of Payard teas; minisandwiches like radish and cucumber with fresh dill, and smoked salmon; scones; madeleines with creme fraiche; and miniature pastries.</p>
        <p>8. Tea and Sympathy  ++  (212) 807-8329</p>
        <p>108 Greenwich Avenue, near 13th Street  West Village  $ Visa and Mastercard</p>
        <p>This charming, eccentric and comforting little English restaurant has an edge that stops it from ever being merely cute. It's the perfect atmosphere for the old-fashioned but delicious food, like shepherd's pie, Sussex chicken, bangers and mash, and the full English breakfast (served on Saturdays and Sundays). Afternoon tea with finger sandwiches and delicate scones, cake, jam and real clotted cream is wonderful, and the service is always charming. Tea is served 11:30 a.m. to 6 p.m. weekdays, 2 to 7 p.m. Saturdays and Sundays.</p>
        <p>9. The Tea Box  +++  (212) 350-0100  Takashimaya  693 Fifth Avenue, near 54th Street  $ All major cards</p>
        <p>The exquisite East-West tea served in the basement of this Japanese department store is a wonderful way to while away an afternoon on Fifth Avenue. The Zen-like dining room attracts a shopping crowd as stylish as the minimalist serving trays. Tea -- served 3 to 6 p.m. Mondays through Saturdays -- includes three open-face ''sandwiches,'' like marinated cucumber on pressed rice, chicken and wasabi on Japanese bread, and a delicate vegetarian spring roll, all arranged on a tray, garnished with fresh fruit. For dessert, several slender cookies and two of the richest, most luxurious chocolates imaginable. Almost 40 teas are available.</p>
        <p>10. T Salon And T Emporium  +++  (212) 358-0506  11 East 20th Street  Flatiron district  $ All major cards</p>
        <p>The T Salon is a combination restaurant, salon and store. For a modern take on the traditional afternoon tea, few places are more pleasant or offer a better variety of teas. The selection is huge, about 250 different kinds, with an unusual mixture of herbal and black teas as well as fragrant pots of classic blends. Sandwiches include delicious smoked chicken with avocado mayonnaise citrus dressing; a triple decker of smoked salmon with sprouts and peppered cream cheese on pumpernickel and rye; and radish and thin-sliced cucumber with goat cheese. Then an assortment of light scones is served with Devonshire cream and organic raspberry preserves. Finally, more pastries than one person can eat, including a light tea cake made with chocolate and Earl Grey tea, dusted with sugar. Tea is not confined to the afternoon here; it's served daily from 10 a.m. to 8 p.m.</p>
        <p>11. Yaffa's T-Room  +  (212) 274-9403  353 Greenwich Street  TriBeCa  $ All major cards</p>
        <p>This casually extroverted, quirky restaurant shares its quarters with a bar and draws a predictably motley crew. People smoke, and the room is full of the owner's artwork. Best are sandwiches, Middle Eastern dishes and breakfast like omelets, plump waffles and sweet crepes. Tea is served in the quieter back room from 2 to 6 p.m. daily if you call the day before and make a reservation. Thirty teas are available, as well as traditional minisandwiches, like egg salad, and smoked turkey; scones; and a plate of dessert samplings.</p>
        <p>Summaries taken from reviews use the star ratings. Others are taken from the $25 and Under column (+) and articles (++), and capsule revies from New York Today: www.nytoday.com (+++).</p>
        <p>What the Stars Mean</p>
        <p>**** -- Extraordinary  *** -- Excellent  ** -- Very Good  * -- Good  None Poor to Satisfactory</p>
        <p>Price Range  Based on the cost of a three-course dinner, per person, tax, tip and drinks not included.</p>
        <p>$ -- $25 and under  $$ -- $25 to $40  $$$ -- $40 to $55  $$$$ -- $55 and over</p>
        <p>Past Reviews -- Good Eating columns back to June 1998, along with reviews from The Times and capsule reviews by Times critics of additional restaurants not reviewed in the newspaper, are available on New York Today.</p>
        <p>EATING OUT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
