<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tensions Build for Inauguration in Peru</title>
    <meta content="Y28PER$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218199"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Inaugurations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Peru</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Krauss, Clifford</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fujimori, Alberto K (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Toledo, Alejandro</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Peru</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Peru</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000728T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500EFD7163DF93BA15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="867" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tensions Build for Inauguration in Peru</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFFORD KRAUSS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Krauss, Clifford</byline>
      <dateline>LIMA, Peru, July 27</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Inauguration of Peruvian Pres Alberto K Fujimori, who recently won a third five-year term despite having resisted pressures for democratic reforms, promises to be raucous; more than 100,000 protesters across the country have been organized by opposition led by Alejandro Toledo to march in attempt to discredit inauguration; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In this capital today women were washing Peruvian flags they say have been sullied by President Alberto K. Fujimori, vendors were selling crude gas masks and riot police were taking up positions.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fujimori is to begin his third five-year term on Friday, having resisted pressures for democratic reforms. It promises to be a raucous inauguration.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In this capital today women were washing Peruvian flags they say have been sullied by President Alberto K. Fujimori, vendors were selling crude gas masks and riot police were taking up positions.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fujimori is to begin his third five-year term on Friday, having resisted pressures for democratic reforms. It promises to be a raucous inauguration.</p>
        <p>Through a mix of economic populism, political repression and deal making in Congress, he has tightened his grip on power since his re-election eight weeks ago, which was roundly criticized for vote tampering and campaign dirty tricks.</p>
        <p>After the voting, Mr. Fujimori promised to work with the Organization of American States to strengthen the independence of the judiciary, to revamp electoral agencies and to expand freedom of the press. He has, however, reduced the influence of officials in his government who have most advocated reform.</p>
        <p>The opposition, led by Alejandro Toledo, the business professor who dropped out of the presidential race a week before the May 28 runoff, has organized more than 100,000 people across the country to march in an attempt to discredit the inauguration. But efforts to block the ceremony have been dropped.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fujimori has appeared oblivious to criticism from the United States and many Latin American and European governments. ''The opinions of other countries are not important to us,'' he said recently.</p>
        <p>In the lame-duck Congress, Mr. Fujimori pushed through legislation that gives the agency regulating telecommunications more power to monitor private phone conversations and to obtain access to computer and telephone records without court order. He also has broken with his usual free-market policies, through a new law that removes tax benefits for foreign mining companies that reinvest profits in the country. He has blocked several privatizations in order to maintain control over gas and water prices as well as to shore up a government pension fund.</p>
        <p>The moves have upset businessmen and Wall Street analysts, who express concerns that Mr. Fujimori will use populist economic policies to buttress his political position.</p>
        <p>In addition, Congress acted not only to clear high-level Fujimori campaign officials of charges that they led an effort to forge a million signatures to put the president on the ballot, but also voted to make four whistle-blowers who exposed the forgery criminally liable. The charges of forged signatures, substantiated by the newspaper El Comercio, were a large factor in Mr. Fujimori's failure to win a first-round victory.</p>
        <p>The Organization of American States is continuing to press for a democratic opening, but Mr. Fujimori has refused to follow a demand that he fire his intelligence chief, Vladimiro Montesinos, for campaign abuses.</p>
        <p>So far, Mr. Fujimori has not faced international sanctions aside from a few mostly symbolic actions by the United States Congress, which delayed delivery of $42 million in foreign aid and excluded Peru from a recent $1.3 billion antinarcotics package that primarily helps Colombia, but also Ecuador and Bolivia.</p>
        <p>The Clinton administration has signaled that it will continue to work with Mr. Fujimori, particularly on antinarcotics programs. Still, it expressed strong comments about Mr. Fujimori when Ambassador John Hamilton told a July 4 gathering here that ''cosmetic or superficial changes will not resolve the crisis of credibility.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hamilton will lead a spare United States delegation to the inauguration. The only foreign presidents to attend will be Hugo Banzer of Bolivia and Gustavo Noboa of Ecuador. Nine Latin American presidents attended Mr. Fujimori's last inauguration in 1995.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fujimori has tried to head off a chilling of relations with Washington by ordering the air force to deploy 18 Sukhoi-25 tactical fighter jets, formerly used as a deterrent against Ecuador, to fight the drug trade.</p>
        <p>The opposition had placed its hopes on international influence, believing that the United States and the Organization of American States might even prevail on Peru to hold new elections. But now Mr. Toledo and other opposition leaders are expressing bitter disappointment, going so far as to accuse the regional group of complicity in Mr. Fujimori's election victory.</p>
        <p>A dozen or so opposition legislators have changed sides in the last two months, so Mr. Toledo's ability to pressure Mr. Fujimori has decreased. In one case, a former Toledo ally in the new Congress changed his allegiances after judges friendly to Mr. Fujimori reversed an embezzlement conviction against him.</p>
        <p>In one gesture today, the Fujimori government pardoned and freed eight people who, according to a government-appointed commission, had been falsely prosecuted on terrorism charges. But 46 other pardon requests presented to Mr. Fujimori last December remained unanswered.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
