<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Toyota Tells British Suppliers to Use Euros Instead of Pounds</title>
    <meta content="Y11EUR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/11/business/11EURO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221642"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Currency</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">European Union</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bayerische Motoren Werke Ag</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ford Motor Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nissan Motor Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Matsushita Electric Industrial Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blair, Tony (Prime Min)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Currency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000811T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E0D8173FF932A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="588" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Toyota Tells British Suppliers to Use Euros Instead of Pounds</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN COWELL</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, Aug. 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Toyota Motor Corp instructs British components suppliers to do business in euros instead of pounds; move reflects distress among automakers and other manufacturers in Britain because of pound's high value relative to euro--situation that has made British exports to Europe expensive; similar efforts by BMW, Ford and Nissan and Matsushita to cope with high value pound noted; move adds pressure to government of Prime Min Tony Blair to adopt less ambiguous policy about joining single currency; rekindles Britain's debate about euro and its fluctuations, with some arguing that it is euro's weakness, not pound's strength, that is problem (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Toyota Motor Corporation said today that it had instructed British components suppliers to do business in euros instead of pounds. The move reflected the distress among automakers and other manufacturers here over the pound's high value relative to the euro, a situation that has made British exports to Europe expensive.</p>
        <p>This year, BMW of Germany pulled out of a six-year investment in the Rover Group of Britain, complaining that the pound's high value against the euro had hurt profits. The Ford Motor Company also cited the pound's strength against the euro in a decision to close a major assembly plant. The Nissan Motor Company of Japan has threatened to transfer production of a new subcompact from its plant in northeastern England. And Matsushita Electric Works of Japan has also warned it may close British plants.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Toyota Motor Corporation said today that it had instructed British components suppliers to do business in euros instead of pounds. The move reflected the distress among automakers and other manufacturers here over the pound's high value relative to the euro, a situation that has made British exports to Europe expensive.</p>
        <p>This year, BMW of Germany pulled out of a six-year investment in the Rover Group of Britain, complaining that the pound's high value against the euro had hurt profits. The Ford Motor Company also cited the pound's strength against the euro in a decision to close a major assembly plant. The Nissan Motor Company of Japan has threatened to transfer production of a new subcompact from its plant in northeastern England. And Matsushita Electric Works of Japan has also warned it may close British plants.</p>
        <p>Essentially, the move today by Toyota passed on the uncertainties and costs of currency fluctuations to the many components makers who supply 80 percent of the parts for the 180,000 cars that Toyota produces in Britain from two plants. Toyota's British subsidiary, Toyota Motor Manufacturing UK, exports about 70 percent of its cars to the zone of 11 nations in Europe that adopted the euro last year.</p>
        <p>''This will have a huge impact on the motor components sector, who will have to bear the brunt of currency fluctuations,'' said Sir Ken Jackson, an auto labor leader who would like Britain to adopt the euro.</p>
        <p>Moreover, Toyota's decision, said Edward Roberts, chief executive of the component maker Peterson Springs in the British Midlands, would leave British manufacturers with payments in euros while all their costs were in pounds. ''If we get paid in euros, what do we do with them? Our employees don't want to be paid in them, and our small suppliers don't want them either.''</p>
        <p>Many foreign companies have invested in Britain as a springboard for exports to the Continent, seeking advantage from Britain's relatively low costs and more flexible labor laws. But, since the euro was introduced in January 1999, the single currency has fallen 25 percent against the yen and 16 percent against the pound.</p>
        <p>Some British-based car producers, particularly in the luxury market, seem untroubled by the slide in the euro. Ford announced today that it would build a new factory in Britain to expand its high-end Aston Martin sports cars division. The factory, with 400 new jobs, would produce a relatively low-priced Aston Martin -- retailing at $90,000 to $135,000.</p>
        <p>Toyota said through a spokesman that not all suppliers had been told to do business in euros and said existing contracts in pounds would continue to be honored.</p>
        <p>The move added to the pressure on Prime Minister Tony Blair's government to adopt a less ambiguous policy about joining the single currency. While Britain says it sees economic benefit in the single currency, it insists that it will not join without holding a referendum and assessing the euro's performance against its own economic yardstick. There was no indication today that Toyota's move had shifted British policy.</p>
        <p>But it rekindled Britain's debate about the euro and its fluctuations, with some arguing that it is the euro's weakness -- not the pound's strength -- that is the problem.</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
