<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Birth of a Candidate: Al Gore Goes Into the Family Business</title>
    <meta content="11GORE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000812T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <meta content="AL GORE'S JOURNEY: Headlong Into Politics" name="series_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221704"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE FIRST RACE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Tennessee</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">House of Representatives (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Henneberger, Melinda</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Albert Sr (1907-98)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Tennessee</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Tennessee</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Tennessee</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000811T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E6DC143FF932A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="4464" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Birth of a Candidate: Al Gore Goes Into the Family Business</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MELINDA HENNEBERGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Henneberger, Melinda</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>When Al Gore first ran for House of Representatives from Tennessee in 1976, his prospects were seen as slim, but Gore pulled off victory by a narrow margin, winning seat held by his father and creating in process the basis of his own campaign style, strategy, and ideology; 1976 campaign described in detail; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For years -- since college, anyway -- Al Gore had been telling friends that the very last thing he would ever do with his life was go into politics. That was fine for his father, he would say, but not for him.</p>
        <p>When he changed his mind, though, while he was in his second year of law school and working evenings at The Nashville Tennesseean, he kept it to himself.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For years -- since college, anyway -- Al Gore had been telling friends that the very last thing he would ever do with his life was go into politics. That was fine for his father, he would say, but not for him.</p>
        <p>When he changed his mind, though, while he was in his second year of law school and working evenings at The Nashville Tennesseean, he kept it to himself.</p>
        <p>''I had a vague, unarticulated game plan,'' Mr. Gore said in a recent interview. ''I'd get my law degree, continue in newspapers'' -- by buying The Carthage Courier, in the little Tennessee town where he had spent summers growing up -- ''move to the farm, spend 10 or 12 years establishing myself in the community and run for Congress at 40.''</p>
        <p>Not so vague. But unarticulated, definitely.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore's friends remember being kept out of the loop, as usual, until after the fact. ''He didn't ask anybody whether he should run,'' said his closest Tennessee friend, Steve Armistead.</p>
        <p>In fact, Mr. Gore kept his own counsel right up until the very moment he heard that his local congressman, Joe L. Evins, was retiring unexpectedly -- years ahead of Mr. Gore's own plan. His boss at the paper, the publisher, John Seigenthaler, who had been encouraging Mr. Gore to consider public life, called him at home one evening in February of 1976 to tell him the news.</p>
        <p>And after less than a minute, he hung up and told his wife, Tipper, ''I think I'm going to run.'' Then, as they both have described the scene, he dropped to the floor and started doing pushups, to keep from drowning in adrenaline.</p>
        <p>''I had not articulated the extent to which my thinking had evolved'' to anyone until then, Mr. Gore said. Surely he had dropped a hint to his wife, who has always been his closest confidante and adviser?</p>
        <p>''We had talked about buying The Carthage Courier,'' he said, a plan that had only recently fallen through when the paper was sold to a higher bidder. ''But the idea of 12 years out I never emphasized in the plan, because it was so speculative.''</p>
        <p>But had he even mentioned the possibility to his wife? Well, no, Mr. Gore said finally, after some hemming and hawing. ''I don't think she's over it yet,'' he sighed.</p>
        <p>His wife's memory of that evening is that she had just put a tuna noodle casserole on the table when the phone rang and their lives changed. ''It was unsettling to me,'' Mrs. Gore said in a separate interview in their home. ''I had a new baby, a couple of part-time jobs and a husband who'd just quit law school to run a race he wasn't supposed to win. Nobody's ever thought about it that way, have they?''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore did take a risk in 1976, pouring a huge chunk of his own money into a campaign that was short on other people's cash because he was not favored to win.</p>
        <p>And from his earliest days on the stump, he showed both the best and the worst of himself as a candidate. In 1976, he won because he outworked the competition and had his facts down cold. Yet in the process he also turned off even some old friends by presenting himself as more conservative than he was. He cut his shoulder-length hair, moved to the right on gun control and called homosexuality ''abnormal.''</p>
        <p>In that race, Mr. Gore's first job was to differentiate himself from his father, former Senator Albert Gore, who had suffered a bitter defeat six years earlier. In the same way, the vice president must in this campaign separate himself from another political force of nature, Bill Clinton.</p>
        <p>The question for Al Gore was then and is now: Is he his own man? And the answer has stayed the same also.</p>
        <p>In one sense, he has yet to prove that he is, partly because he has changed positions on some issues, leaving unclear just where he stands. But it is also because he is so complicated, with a million moving parts behind the shut-down exterior, that there is no perfect soundbite of an answer to the larger question of who he is.</p>
        <p>He may well be trying to hide some parts of himself from a public that does not seem particularly enchanted by complexity. Yet even his efforts to tell all can seem like attempts to obscure. He often answers a question by saying, ''On one level . . .'' and then plowing through many levels more. His thinking is often so subtle that the harder he tries to download the entire mental file, the more he sounds like he's hedging.</p>
        <p>And though Mr. Gore has certainly been a dutiful senator's son and loyal vice president, he is so self-contained, making even important decisions in a surprisingly solitary way, that it is possible to conclude that, if anything, he is probably too much his own man.</p>
        <p>From a young age, there were whole areas of his life he kept to himself. On the farm in Tennessee, where he has said he had his closest friends and most relaxed times, the nine months of the year he spent in Washington were never mentioned.</p>
        <p>Throughout his career, he has stubbornly resisted advice to a degree that has driven generations of aides crazy. One longtime aide said Mr. Gore really listens only to his family, who tend to encourage him to follow his own instincts.</p>
        <p>So for Mr. Gore, being his own man has often meant going it alone.</p>
        <p>The Newspaperman's Life</p>
        <p>First, he found his own way back to politics.</p>
        <p>He said he wanted nothing to do with his father's line of work after watching the Vietnam fiasco. And had all the legislation in the world kept the Rev. Dr. Martin Luther King Jr. from getting shot? When his father was turned out of office in what historians regard as a particularly dirty race in 1970, Al Gore not only walked away, he walked away mad.</p>
        <p>After he got back from Vietnam, he turned down all the invitations to political functions that poured in from his dad's old friends, who were eager to adopt him. He showed next to no interest in discussing politics. Even on the night President Richard M. Nixon resigned, Mr. Gore stayed home, instead of joining friends at a party.</p>
        <p>He had been a journalist in the Army in Vietnam, and after his discharge took a job writing obituaries and police stories for The Tennesseean. At night, he attended divinity school for about a year, though he never felt a call to the ministry. For him, it was mostly an effort to puzzle through the morality of the war through a structured, intellectual exercise.</p>
        <p>But he hoped to make a life in newspapers, or at least a rarefied version of that life. ''I was expecting that my path would take me to writing either journalism of a different level,'' he said, ''or books of the sort our family friend David Halberstam was writing.'' Mr. Halberstam is the Pulitzer prize-winning reporter and author of ''The Best and the Brightest.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Seigenthaler had made a habit of hiring celebrity offspring like Mr. Gore, including Robert F. Kennedy's son David and Hank Aaron's daughter Gaile. The paper's longtime city editor, Frank Ritter, edited them all.</p>
        <p>''I'll never forget the lead David Kennedy put on a story about the locusts who come out and mate every 13 years,'' Mr. Ritter said, laughing. The lead, or opening paragraph, of the story -- which never ran -- began, ''If you had not had sex in 13 years, you'd be screaming, too.''</p>
        <p>''But Al was all serious,'' Mr. Ritter said.</p>
        <p>He approached the lowliest assignments with great industry. ''Even when he was asked to cover the Christmas parade,'' said one former colleague, Alan Carmichael, who now owns a public relations firm in Knoxville, ''it was a very serious project for him.'' (The byline on that one was ''Ebenezer Scrooge, as told to Albert Gore, Jr.'')</p>
        <p>Yet Mr. Gore did not fail to notice that he was no competition for Mr. Halberstam. ''I saw a lot of others who did better stories,'' he said, ''day after day after day.''</p>
        <p>Co-workers saw that he was in journalism mostly to influence public policy. And in that, too, he was ultimately disappointed. After graduating to investigative pieces, he became convinced that some members of the local Metro Council were demanding bribes from developers in return for scheduling their zoning cases.</p>
        <p>With Mr. Seigenthaler's blessing, Mr. Gore worked with law enforcement officials on a sting operation -- a relationship that many journalists these days would consider too cozy. A source of Mr. Gore's wore a wire as he met with a council member. Mr. Gore later helped transcribe the tapes, and the cash that the authorities said had exchanged hands during the sting was provided by The Tennessean.</p>
        <p>But when the case against the council member went to trial, the defense accused the paper of going after the official because he was black. The jury deadlocked along racial lines, a mistrial was declared and the man was acquitted at a second trial. Colleagues remember that Mr. Gore was devastated.</p>
        <p>And it was that experience, he says, that ultimately led him to explore a career in the law, and then circle back to politics. ''It was a kind of call to arms,'' said Mr. Gore, who often speaks about his work in moral and even religious terms. ''This process held nearly sacred is being defiled, and good people need to jump in and help the forces of good prevail.''</p>
        <p>Quietly, though -- and without ever committing himself -- Mr. Gore had already prepared himself to take advantage of the ''once-in-a-lifetime opportunity'' that presented itself when Mr. Evins, who was considered congressman-for-life, decided to retire. Though he says he did not have a political run in mind at the time, while still in college he took a summer course in Tennessee history and bought into a real estate venture in Tennessee's fourth district that, in addition to making him some money, provided him with business credentials there.</p>
        <p>As he says, ''Even though I really had closed the door'' as a young man, ''I had left a trail of bread crumbs.''</p>
        <p>A Campaign Style Is Born</p>
        <p>One of the first decisions the 27-year-old congressional candidate made was to tell his father, the former senator, to stay out of the race.</p>
        <p>Two hours after hearing from Mr. Seigenthaler, Al and Tipper had already packed a bag and were driving from their apartment in Nashville to their farm in Carthage, which soon became campaign headquarters.</p>
        <p>Later that same night, Mr. Gore called his parents to tell them he was running for his father's old congressional seat. As Mr. Gore remembers it, the senator was initially unenthusiastic.</p>
        <p>''He had begun to see how much of life he had been missing,'' Mr. Gore said. ''There was no 'Yippee!' He said, 'Al, it's such a hard life, I hate for you to put yourself through this.' ''</p>
        <p>Before long, though, Mr. Gore said, his father's ''zest for battle came bubbling up and he was raring to go.'' And at that point, Mr. Gore told the senator point blank that he would have to sit out the campaign -- much as Gov. George W. Bush seems to have sidelined his father during his first political race, also for a freshly vacant Congressional seat, in 1978.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore was adamant that the senator would have to refrain from making a single speech or statement on his behalf. ''He didn't understand it or like it, but I insisted,'' the vice president said.</p>
        <p>Was that a hard conversation to have? ''Not really,'' he said coolly. ''It was hard for him to hear it. But I didn't want to be elected as his son.''</p>
        <p>Yet this distancing strategy was as tricky in 1976 as it is today. Though Senator Gore had lost statewide in 1970, he was still well regarded in his old district, even if the district was more conservative than the senator.</p>
        <p>There were no burning issues in the race. And among the nine candidates, all Democrats, the favorite was the majority leader of the Tennessee House, Stanley Rogers, who had the party's support sewn up.</p>
        <p>Even Mr. Gore's campaign press secretary, Ken Jost, a colleague at The Tennesseean, said it had never really occurred to him that Mr. Gore might actually win. And plenty of people thought the only way Mr. Gore could even hope to prevail was by exploiting the familial connection he was busy running away from.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore, though, balked at this, and thought the key was to outwork the competition. And that's what he did, starting the morning he announced his candidacy -- right after he threw up in a public restroom inside the Smith County courthouse. Day after day, he drove the back roads of middle Tennessee, and ran across fields to ask farmers for their support. On one occasion, he even climbed a telephone pole to shake hands with the lineman.</p>
        <p>Certainly, Mr. Gore was not anyone's idea of a natural on the stump, and he stuck with the same two tired jokes throughout the campaign, though they almost never got a laugh. He told one of them, about the Republican kittens that became Democrats -- ''They have their eyes open now'' -- on the trail again only recently.</p>
        <p>After one of his more rousing efforts at speechifying, at a cattle auction in Murfreesboro, ''there was not one ounce of applause,'' recalled Mr. Carmichael, who wrote about the campaign for The Tennesseean.</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Gore kept going back, asking for support time and time again, and in many cases wore people down.</p>
        <p>Several longtime supporters in Tennessee said in recent interviews that they had taken his lack of God-given talent for backslapping and baby-kissing as proof that he was getting into politics for the right reasons. When they saw him breaking a sweat, they approved.</p>
        <p>Recently, Mr. Gore's jam-packed campaign schedule and hours-long town hall meetings have been seen as a sign of desperation in his race against Mr. Bush, whose pace is more leisurely. But even after Mr. Gore won his Congressional seat, he held something like 1,200 town meetings. The exact number of meetings, like the number of burgers sold by McDonald's, was always the last line in Representative Gore's news releases.</p>
        <p>And right or wrong, it is Mr. Gore's enduring belief that the winner is usually the guy who works the hardest. Last fall, at the peak of the Bill Bradley boomlet, Mr. Armistead had lunch with his old friend and told Mr. Gore he was a little worried that Mr. Bradley might take the nomination away from him.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore, though, seemed perfectly serene. There had already been a turning point in the race, he declared -- one somehow overlooked by all the pundits. ''He told me he thought the turning point was that Bradley had to leave a debate in New Hampshire'' soon after it was over, leaving Mr. Gore alone to work the crowd for hours more.</p>
        <p>''He said he knew he would win after that, and he tied it back to '76,'' Mr. Armistead recalled. ''He said, 'It was just like when Stan Rogers had to walk off and leave that crowd of people at the Alexander County Fair and I got to stay and answer all their questions.' ''</p>
        <p>When Ideology Meets Strategy</p>
        <p>In those days, Mr. Gore not only made all the major decisions in his campaign, but financed it, too, like some independent film project, with loans and maxed-out credit cards. He took out a $50,000 loan and kicked in a total of $125,000 of his own money.</p>
        <p>Though his father was not a wealthy man while Mr. Gore was growing up, he did make a lot of money after losing office in 1970. And at age 27, Mr. Gore already had a substantial bank account, owing mostly to the homebuilding business and another real estate venture his family had brought him in on. His donations to his own campaign accounted for more than two-thirds of the $188,560 he raised in the race, at a time when his financial statements showed a net worth of $273,841.</p>
        <p>He wrote some of his own campaign releases and drove himself around, too, speeding to hit the maximum number of events and using a C.B. radio -- his handle was ''Carthage Campaigner'' -- to avoid getting caught.</p>
        <p>Though aides insist that he has long since gotten over the inclination to run his own campaign, Mr. Gore still does not seem able to resist involving himself in the details. He reads his clips closely enough to be able to spar over word choice, and is remarkably well-versed on the gossip from his campaign plane.</p>
        <p>On the 4th of July, a rare day off for the vice president, he called a reporter several times to talk about some photos he had agreed to provide The New York Times. Once, he called to get directions for the assistant who was to drop off the packet, and later he called back to make sure it had arrived.</p>
        <p>In his first race, though, he could serve as his own driver without getting accused of micromanaging. One day, as he was ferrying his wife, his press secretary, Mr. Jost, and a reporter, Mr. Carmichael, between campaign stops, Mr. Carmichael unexpectedly asked whether Mr. Gore had ever smoked marijuana.</p>
        <p>Mr. Carmichael said Mr. Gore immediately stopped the car, got out and walked around for a few minutes -- a technique the vice president still uses in interviews. Recently, after being asked a delicate question over the phone, he repeated a couple of times that he was losing the connection: ''What? I'm losing you.'' Then he went on and answered.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Gore came back to the car where Mr. Carmichael was waiting, he said he would not answer the question because it had not been put to the other candidates. Eventually, the question was withdrawn and the news that the candidate had smoked marijuana was put off for 11 more years, when he revealed it during his first presidential campaign.</p>
        <p>What everyone covering the race did write about, though, was the surprisingly conservative ground staked out by Mr. Gore, who felt he had to distance himself from the senator's liberalism.</p>
        <p>It paid off, too. He surprised everyone by snagging an endorsement from the right-leaning Nashville Banner, a paper that had always been a harsh critic of his father. The Banner had been sold to the Gannett Company several years earlier, and still retained its conservative voice.</p>
        <p>''It was very important in establishing credibility to have gotten The Banner's endorsement,'' said Mr. Jost. ''The editorial board of a decidedly Republican, conservative newspaper thought he'd be a good Congressman, too.''</p>
        <p>His strongest competition in the race, Stan Rogers, now says that both he and Mr. Gore, whom he supports, pandered in that race. ''No doubt about it, Al postured himself in a more conservative image,'' Mr. Rogers said. ''But we both did, so I can't blame him. I attempted to paint him as the liberal even though that's what I was. I just tried to paint the senior brush on him'' -- as in Albert Gore, Senior -- ''but the senator was not photographed, not seen in the campaign, until election night when it was all over. And that was smart.''</p>
        <p>In the campaign, Mr. Gore also spoke against gun control, and a week before the primary told a crowd, ''I don't believe a woman's freedom to live her own life, in all cases, outweighs the fetus's right to life.'' Both of these positions were news to his former colleagues at The Tennesseean, where he had written an editorial expressing outrage over the proliferation of cheap handguns.</p>
        <p>''On the political spectrum, I would have put him as a liberal Democrat,'' said Lloyd Armour, who ran the paper's editorial page for many years. And he didn't run as that? ''Oh, no, he wouldn't have dared,'' his former boss said. ''Middle Tennessee is conservative.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore turned in his last editorial just a few hours before he quit the paper to run for Congress. And already in campaign mode, the words he'd written were more colorful than usual. The piece never ran, but Mr. Armour still remembers how it began: ''Education in Tennessee is a damned disgrace.''</p>
        <p>After Mr. Gore was elected, he would often stop back in at The Tennesseean at the end of a full day of town hall meetings. Then he'd plop down at a desk, and write his own story -- rather than just issuing a press release. His old editor, Mr. Ritter, was usually running the desk.</p>
        <p>''And you didn't have any staff on the weekend so he saved you a lot of trouble,'' Mr. Ritter said. ''He'd go set the hot type, read the proof and make the corrections, too,'' if you'd let him, he laughed. ''Then we'd put our feet up on the desk late and have coffee.''</p>
        <p>It was in one such late-night session that Mr. Ritter finally asked his friend about his surprisingly conservative campaign positions on abortion and gun control.</p>
        <p>''I said, 'Al, how in the world can you not support gun control? The Tennesseean has always been for strict gun control,' '' Mr. Ritter recalled. ''He said, 'Frank, they all hunt in my district, and there's no way in the world I could win if I came out against guns.' ''</p>
        <p>On abortion, Mr. Ritter said, ''He said: 'Here's my position. I don't believe government funds should ever be used to finance abortions.' Of course, he's really changed that now.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Ritter, an enthusiastic mid-life convert to Catholicism, is fond of Mr. Gore and has a signed photo of the vice president and his wife meeting the Pope in his office at The Tennessean. But when asked where he thinks Mr. Gore really stands, he said: ''On those two issues, I have no idea. If I was a one-issue man and that was my one issue, either gun control or abortion, I'd be leery.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore has remained consistent on some relatively conservative views he expressed back then -- on national defense and criminal justice, for example. But of course, he now categorically supports gay rights, strong gun-control legislation and abortion rights.</p>
        <p>When he called homosexuality ''abnormal,'' was he pandering, or did he really think that? ''That was a view, a statement I long since retracted,'' he said. ''I don't think that way'' anymore, he added, ''because I've long since learned better. But I was encumbered with a stereotype, and the bad news is that statement was an accurate reflection of my belief at the time. It wasn't a pose.''</p>
        <p>On gun control, he pleads guilty to changing his position to suit his constituents, but also said: ''If I had had a strong belief that it was really important, I would have said so. I did not see it as a compelling issue at that time. I really didn't.''</p>
        <p>On other issues, including abortion, he said, ''I've grown in the last 24 years, seriously.'' But over all, he insists he listed only a little to the right to win the race.</p>
        <p>''I don't think it's unfair to say I probably leaned more conservative,'' he said, ''but they still were all positions I was comfortable with at the time. Even at Harvard, I was more moderate than all my friends. I don't think you can say that was a pose.''</p>
        <p>A Winner, and His Family</p>
        <p>Late into the night of the August 5th primary that would decide the race, it was still too close to call, and as Steve Armistead drove Mr. Gore to his victory party at the Holiday Inn in Lebanon, half an hour away, they still didn't know if he had won or lost.</p>
        <p>Mr. Armistead had also driven his friend to a party at Nashville's Hermitage Hotel the night his father lost his Senate seat in 1970. In the car that night, Mr. Gore had quietly told Mr. Armistead that his father had come to him and asked him to write his victory speech.</p>
        <p>''He knew there was not going to be any victory speech,'' Mr. Armistead said. ''But he went in and made an effort to write it rather than say, 'Dad, this race has been over for a long time.' ''</p>
        <p>When they arrived at the party in Lebanon, Mr. Gore sensed that his friends were steeling themselves for another Gore loss.</p>
        <p>The tally went back and forth. But Mr. Gore's home base in Smith County was one of the last to be counted, around 11 p.m., and Mr. Gore ended up winning by just a few thousand votes, receiving 32 percent of the vote to Mr. Rogers' 29 percent.</p>
        <p>Then, at last, the senator was allowed up on stage to speak, though he was by some accounts nearly delirious with feeling.</p>
        <p>''He was never one to express himself a whole lot, but that was explosion night for him,'' said Mr. Armistead. ''He was hollering, shaking the hands. Senator Gore was just overly excited.''</p>
        <p>The papers the next day reported that the senior Gore told the crowd: ''You elected me to Congress when I was 29 years old, and you elected Al at the age of 28. He's starting out one year earlier than I did, so maybe that means he'll go one step farther.'' In fact, the senator had gone to Washington at 30, but this was not a night for quibbles.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore himself was so excited he just kept on thanking people.</p>
        <p>And for the first time in the race, he emphasized his family ties. ''I have a family that teaches you what public service is all about,'' he said in his speech. ''That is what my family has taught me.''</p>
        <p>Al Gore's Journey</p>
        <p>This is the 10th article of a series about the lives of the presidential candidates. Future articles will look at George W. Bush's work in his father's White House and Al Gore's mid-life crisis.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE FIRST RACE  Correction:  August 12, 2000, Saturday  A front-page article yesterday about Al Gore's earliest political campaign gave a misspelled name at several points for the newspaper on which he worked before deciding to seek office. It is The Tennessean, in Nashville, not Tennesseean.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: August 12, 2000, Saturday</p>
        <p>A front-page article yesterday about Al Gore's earliest political campaign gave a misspelled name at several points for the newspaper on which he worked before deciding to seek office. It is The Tennessean, in Nashville, not Tennesseean.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
