<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Testing the Durability of Welding as a Creative Form</title>
    <meta content="11JOHN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="32" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221592"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ART REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Neuberger Museum of Art</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnson, Ken</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000811T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402EED6163FF932A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1221" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Testing the Durability of Welding as a Creative Form</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEN JOHNSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Johnson, Ken</byline>
      <dateline>PURCHASE, N.Y.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ken Johnson reviews Neuberger Museum's exhibit of welded sculpture of twentieth century; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rumors of the death of painting circulated widely during the 1970's, only to be disproved by subsequent decades. But it seems that a less publicized but possibly better founded rumor of death has been in play recently: that of welded sculpture.</p>
        <p>In an essay accompanying ''Welded! Sculpture of the 20th Century'' at the Neuberger Museum of Art here, the exhibition's curator, Judy Collischan, raises the issue only to deny it. ''Welding continues to be a viable means of expression for many artists,'' she writes. But this show -- a broad but unfocused, mostly mediocre selection of more than 90 metal sculptures from the early 30's to the late 90's -- does little to discourage the thought that welded sculpture as a genre may belong more to the past than to the future.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Rumors of the death of painting circulated widely during the 1970's, only to be disproved by subsequent decades. But it seems that a less publicized but possibly better founded rumor of death has been in play recently: that of welded sculpture.</p>
        <p>In an essay accompanying ''Welded! Sculpture of the 20th Century'' at the Neuberger Museum of Art here, the exhibition's curator, Judy Collischan, raises the issue only to deny it. ''Welding continues to be a viable means of expression for many artists,'' she writes. But this show -- a broad but unfocused, mostly mediocre selection of more than 90 metal sculptures from the early 30's to the late 90's -- does little to discourage the thought that welded sculpture as a genre may belong more to the past than to the future.</p>
        <p>The tradition of 20th-century welded sculpture began in the 1920's with the Spanish metalsmith Julio Gonzalez, who learned welding in a Renault factory. His Cubist assemblages inspired his friend Picasso, who made some of his own. And the works of Gonzalez and Picasso, in turn, inspired David Smith, an American who might be called the Picasso of welding, so inventive and prolific was his output from the 1930's into the 1960's. Finally, the English sculptor Anthony Caro, inspired by Smith, brought welded sculpture to a climax of formalist daring and elegance.</p>
        <p>It can be argued, then, that the core tradition of welded sculpture coincides with the rise and fall of Modernist abstraction. But this may be too narrow a view. Artists used welding to branch off in any number of directions, including Abstract Expressionist, Minimalist, Pop and other representational and abstract modes.</p>
        <p>It is this broader view that the Neuberger exhibition favors: anything in which heat was used to join metal parts qualifies. Unfortunately, this inclusive philosophy has led to a confusing lack of discrimination in the selection and representation of artists, and in distinguishing among different kinds of welded sculpture. This show could use an editor.</p>
        <p>It appears that the project was too ambitious for the resources of the Neuberger, the museum on the Purchase College campus of the State University of New York. Major works by major figures are not easy to procure on a college museum's budget. Gonzalez and Picasso are represented, by just three small works. The Gonzalez, an eight-inch Cubist figure in silver, is a lovely little classic from 1932. But the two Picassos -- a small, Gumby-like figure made from cut and folded sheet metal and a man's head painted on folded sheet steel -- are from the early 1960's and have little to do with his innovative, Cubism-based metal assemblages of the late 20's and early 30's.</p>
        <p>None of the three works by David Smith show him to best advantage: a fanciful 1945 billiard player assembled from Picassoid and Miroesque parts; ''Steel Drawing I,'' also from 1945, a flat plate of steel with diagrammatic lines cut through it; and a comparatively small ''Voltri XVI'' (1962), a steel-working bench with industrial parts attached. With works by comparatively minor artists like Theodore Roszak, Herbert Ferber and Seymour Lipton taking up as much or more space nearby, Smith's towering significance is obscured.</p>
        <p>There are good pieces by Richard Stankiewicz, who made formally exacting yet quirkily animated assemblages of rusted found junk in the 1950's, and a couple of fine, vintage crushed auto-body sculptures by John Chamberlain. But two of the most important sculptors of the 60's, Caro and Mark di Suvero, present minor pedestal sculptures, while the far less significant Jason Seley is represented by a sizable and conspicuously hideous piece made of chrome car bumpers.</p>
        <p>Ms. Collischan gets closer to the right balance in her useful, extensively illustrated catalog (published by the museum and Hudson Hills Press). Here one finds longer entries with multiple reproductions of other, more important works by the most influential artists (including some, like Naum Gabo and Jean Tinguely, not in the show) and briefer entries on less important artists like David Hare and Harold Cousins. If the show were more like the book, especially in representing the first three or four decades, it could have been a terrific exhibition.</p>
        <p>Besides the quality problem, there are conceptual issues. A large piece by Donald Judd, for example, a row of four galvanized cubes joined by a single blue bar, may have welding in it, but unlike David Smith's work, which is unimaginable without it, welding was not essential for Judd. His box works are, as often as not, joined together by screws. Welding seems incidental to the kinetic work of George Rickey, too, who is more interested in the choreography of mechanical movement than in the kind of compositional freedom that welding offers.</p>
        <p>And one of the more interesting new sculptures in the show, Jonathan Kirk's ''Burning Chamber,'' a funky, neatly made sheet metal construction representing some kind of fantastic industrial structure, could as easily have been riveted or screwed together as welded. Framed in the right way, such works might deserve a place in this kind of exhibition, but mixed in randomly they are distracting and puzzling.</p>
        <p>That there is a more narrowly definable welded sculpture tradition continuing into the 1990's is affirmed by many works in the show. Well-composed assemblages by Peter Reginato, Lee Tribe, Fletcher Benton and David Annesley reflect the core Gonzalez-Picasso-Smith tradition. The most impressive piece in this vein is a big, open sculpture that looks like a giant bear trap, by William Tucker.</p>
        <p>While artists like Mr. Reginato, Mr. Tribe or Mr. Annesley have a reverent, custodial relationship to the tradition, others relate to it in a more witty way. The effect of Nancy Graves's Dr. Seuss-style assemblage of festively painted, cast bronze plant forms; Deborah Butterfield's remarkably lifelike horse made from found pieces of rusted metal; and Judy Pfaff's expansive, rickety cloud of bedsprings, wire and tin cans -- all depend in significant measure on their clever play with Early Modernist modes.</p>
        <p>But whether they approach the tradition earnestly or mischievously, what is notable about all these artists is their retrospective stance. For them, welded sculpture does not have the shock of the new that it had for Picasso and Smith. Now it is a solidly established tradition, to be honored or spoofed. In some cases, like the small, neatly made bowl-shaped works by Ann Sperry and Jenny Lee or a basketlike object of woven wire by Kendall Buster, it begins to look as much like craft as art.</p>
        <p>Conceivably, a different selection of contemporary artists might have made a case for something more urgent happening in contemporary welding. This show makes it hard to avoid concluding that welding by itself is too limiting for today's most adventurous artists.</p>
        <p>''Welded! Sculpture of the 20th Century'' is at the Neuberger Museum of Art, Purchase College, 735 Anderson Hill Road, Purchase, N.Y., (914) 251-6100, through Aug. 27.</p>
        <p>ART REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
