<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Summer School Attendance Disappointing, Levy Says</title>
    <meta content="11SUMM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221689"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Truancy</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holloway, Lynette</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Levy, Harold O (Chancellor)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000811T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05EEDE143FF932A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="758" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Summer School Attendance Disappointing, Levy Says</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYNETTE HOLLOWAY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Holloway, Lynette</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>NYC Schools Chancellor Harold O Levy releases what he calls disappointing attendance figures for last day of summer school classes; blames some parents, saying that thousands withdrew their children forcing them to be held back a grade; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Schools Chancellor Harold O. Levy yesterday released what he called disappointing attendance figures for the last day of summer school classes. He blamed some parents, saying thousands withdrew their children, forcing them to be held back a grade.</p>
        <p>''The fact that there were parents who would sign out their children from what I think is an educationally necessary program is very disturbing,'' Mr. Levy said. ''That means that we've done a very poor job explaining to parents that being left back is critical. I thought the message was clear. Obviously, we need to do a lot more homework with parents.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Schools Chancellor Harold O. Levy yesterday released what he called disappointing attendance figures for the last day of summer school classes. He blamed some parents, saying thousands withdrew their children, forcing them to be held back a grade.</p>
        <p>''The fact that there were parents who would sign out their children from what I think is an educationally necessary program is very disturbing,'' Mr. Levy said. ''That means that we've done a very poor job explaining to parents that being left back is critical. I thought the message was clear. Obviously, we need to do a lot more homework with parents.''</p>
        <p>When summer school began on July 5, enrollment was about 319,000, he said. When classes ended last week, enrollment was about 303,000. Of those, about 200,000 had been told that if they did not attend, they would automatically be held back.</p>
        <p>Enrollment among those students in third through eighth grade for whom summer school was required fell by 4,350, after parents withdrew them, Mr. Levy said. Among high school students and those who were strongly urged to attend, there were 46,924 withdrawals, he said.</p>
        <p>The numbers are fluid because some students enrolled at the last minute, while some who were registered never showed up. At the end, the final tallies decreased significantly when thousands of parents withdrew their children from the register.</p>
        <p>Summer school classes for elementary and middle schools ended last week, with students spending this week taking tests to determine if they will move to the next grade. High school students are taking Regents makeup exams this week and next.</p>
        <p>Seventy-nine percent of students enrolled in the summer program in elementary and middle schools attended on Aug. 3, the last day of classes. That was the same as on July 17, the last date for which citywide figures were released. Among students who chose to attend -- those who were urged to go but were to be promoted if they did not -- 74.6 percent attended on Aug. 3, up from 71 percent two weeks earlier.</p>
        <p>Attendance among high school students, which was consistently low, shot up to 60.8 percent, from 50 percent on July 17. But the percentage rise is attributed to a drop in the number of students on the rolls.</p>
        <p>Mr. Levy said he was unsure what he could do beyond what the system had done to bring in truants. The Board of Education hired 144 attendance teachers to go door to door and call students' homes to encourage them to go to summer school. When it became apparent in the first days of the program that truancy was a problem, Mr. Levy led a telephone campaign to call parents.</p>
        <p>About 60 percent -- 155,000 out of 260,000 -- of the city's high school students were registered for the summer program, most of them because they failed one or more courses or failed a Regents examination required for graduation.</p>
        <p>The high school students who failed to show up for classes, officials said, knew that they would not necessarily be held back if they skipped summer school. High school students can be promoted to the next grade if they fail a course or a Regents exam, as long as they make it up later.</p>
        <p>For the most part, Mr. Levy said he was pleased with the summer program. He said there were sufficient books and teachers, and good curriculums and instructional programs. He kicked off the day at Wadleigh Secondary School in Harlem, whose eighth graders had excellent summer school attendance.</p>
        <p>But Borough President Fernando Ferrer of the Bronx, who met with 25 parents this week, said that many were not notified in time to send their children to summer school. Others, who sent their children, said that the curriculum did not adequately address the children's needs and that the classrooms were not properly air-conditioned.</p>
        <p>''I don't want to scapegoat parents,'' Mr. Ferrer said. ''I want to understand their challenges so that we can improve the summer school program next year.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
