<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Kick Off Shoes, Kick Up Heels</title>
    <meta content="11FAMI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="39" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221593"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FAMILY FARE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Entertainment and Amusements</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Graeber, Laurel</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Entertainment and Amusements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000811T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E7DF173FF932A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="990" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Kick Off Shoes, Kick Up Heels</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Laurel Graeber</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Graeber, Laurel</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Family Fare column on events of interest to families in New York; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Children often find the adult world sober and dull. Imagine, then, their pleasure at discovering a profession in which grown-ups not only go barefoot and wear funny clothes, but also run, twirl and leap with abandon.</p>
        <p>That profession is modern dance, to which Daniel Gwirtzman and his company provide a delightful introduction. ''Welcome to the World of Dance,'' a Saturday children's matinee that complements the company's run at the Flea Theater in Manhattan, explains what contemporary choreography is all about. The dancers then take the lesson several thrilling steps further by inviting the young audience members to join in.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Children often find the adult world sober and dull. Imagine, then, their pleasure at discovering a profession in which grown-ups not only go barefoot and wear funny clothes, but also run, twirl and leap with abandon.</p>
        <p>That profession is modern dance, to which Daniel Gwirtzman and his company provide a delightful introduction. ''Welcome to the World of Dance,'' a Saturday children's matinee that complements the company's run at the Flea Theater in Manhattan, explains what contemporary choreography is all about. The dancers then take the lesson several thrilling steps further by inviting the young audience members to join in.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gwirtzman first leads the children through some simple warm-up exercises in their seats. Bare feet can feel the floor better, he explains, adding, ''Imagine trying to play the piano with mittens.'' The troupe then performs a program of music that is lively and fun, like ragtime and big band, and dances that are, too, like the Charleston and the can-can.</p>
        <p>As Matthew, my 5-year-old, demonstrated, an hourlong performance is bound to elicit questions, from the expected (''Whoa, how'd they do that?'') to the unexpected (''Mom, do both of them have underwear on?'').</p>
        <p>For him and his fellows, the high point was going onstage to learn the hora, an Israeli folk dance, and the bus stop, a 70's disco creation that includes the pose that John Travolta immortalized: index finger pointing to the sky. By the time the last strains of the score from ''Saturday Night Fever''were heard, most of the adults were on their feet, too.</p>
        <p>''Welcome to the World of Dance,'' tomorrow and Aug. 19 at 3 p.m. at the Flea Theater, 41 White Street (between Church Street and Broadway), Lower Manhattan, (212) 226-2407. Tickets: $15. Reservations advised.</p>
        <p>Early Sisterhood</p>
        <p>Even if you don't have strong feelings about this year's elections, there's a political rally this weekend that your family will be proud to join.</p>
        <p>The rally, on the Lower East Side, supports voting yes in a 1915 referendum on women's suffrage. It takes up the first few minutes of ''Forward Into Light: The Story of the First Women Voters of 97 Orchard Street,'' a historical play in which the audience can also cheer the cause.</p>
        <p>''Forward Into Light'' is this year's Origins Project, an annual collaboration between the Lower East Side Tenement Museum and the City Lights Youth Theater. Each summer, with the help of Carmen Rivera, a playwright, the theater's 12- to 16-year-olds write a script about the lives chronicled by the Tenement Museum: in this case, they include those of Sarah Burinescu, Bessie Rubinsky and Ida Breuner, the first neighborhood women to vote.</p>
        <p>''We focused on Sarah because we had the most information on her,'' said Susan Sterman-Jones, the production's director. ''Her youngest daughter is still alive.''</p>
        <p>The play also features Lillian Wald, who was actually a visiting nurse at the Henry Street Settlement, and several interesting fictional creations, like Lavinia Dock, who threatens to have throngs of women ''showing our ankles in the streets,'' and Everett P. Wheeler, a composite character who is president of the Man Suffrage Association Opposed to Political Suffrage for Woman. His group warns that women voting will result in ''anarchy,'' ''apocalypse'' and ''damaged fetuses.''</p>
        <p>As a recent rehearsal showed, the young cast is adept at portraying the passions the issue provoked. With period songs, the play is a vivid, timely reminder that the political process is still something to take pride in.</p>
        <p>''Forward Into Light,'' at the Lower East Side Tenement Museum's theater, 97 Orchard Street (meet at the museum, 90 Orchard Street, at Broome Street), (212) 431-0233, extension 223. Today and Sunday at 2; tomorrow at 2 and 4:30 p.m. Tickets: $7; students and the elderly, $6; under 6, $3. Reservations required.</p>
        <p>Stepping Into Art</p>
        <p>On Sunday Queens will offer a children's dream: a building in which they are not only allowed to track sand, splash water, paint on the walls and draw on the floor, but also strongly encouraged to do so.</p>
        <p>It is P.S. 1 Contemporary Art Center, the Museum of Modern Art affiliate in Long Island City. At ''A Day at the Beach, a Day for Families,'' patrons of all ages will dig their hands -- and feet -- into various mediums, working with contemporary artists.</p>
        <p>In a space called FlyBy, young visitors will take part in ''Splat,'' a work in progress that is as much fun as it sounds. Devised by Carola Dertnig, the project includes a huge swing. Children immerse their feet in paint, hop on the swing and -- splat! -- smack their soles on the wall. You might say that it is visual and performance art at the same time.</p>
        <p>In ''Dunescape,'' an indoor-outdoor series of galleries that includes wading pools and sand, children can enjoy workshops like book-making with Heather Malin, designing paper dolls with Layla Lozano and creating a tower with Jennifer Kim, using a Sol LeWitt sculpture as inspiration.</p>
        <p>High-tech art will visit in the form of RoboSapien 2000, a robot designed by the artist Pixelfaces. Using a computer, visitors can make Robosapiens speak and move. If you want to hear Elvis belting out ''Hound Dog,'' ''the music will come out of his costume and he'll dance to it,'' said Erin Sircy, coordinator of the event.</p>
        <p>''A Day at the Beach, a Day for Families,'' Sunday from noon to 6 p.m. at P.S. 1 Contemporary Art Center, 2225 Jackson Avenue, Long Island City, (718) 784-2084. Free with suggested donation: $5; the elderly and students, $2; free for members and Long Island City residents.</p>
        <p>FAMILY FARE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
