<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NASA Sending 2 Rovers to Mars In Twin Trips Landing in 2004</title>
    <meta content="Y11MAR$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221649"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Robots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mars (Planet)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Aeronautics and Space Administration</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wilford, John Noble</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mars (Planet)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Robots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000811T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E2D7173FF932A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="532" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NASA Sending 2 Rovers to Mars In Twin Trips Landing in 2004</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN NOBLE WILFORD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wilford, John Noble</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>NASA officials, wanting to make the most of an especially favorable launching opportunity in 2003-2004, decide to send not one but two large robotic roving vehicles to Mars on separate missions; say cost for two missions would probably not exceed $600 million (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Wanting to make the most of an especially favorable launching opportunity in three years, NASA officials have decided to send not one but two large roving vehicles to the surface of Mars on separate missions.</p>
        <p>NASA officials said yesterday that they were confident that the spacecraft and roving vehicles could be built and tested in time for launchings in 2003, on May 22 and June 4. The Mars landings are scheduled for 2004, on Jan. 2 and 20.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Wanting to make the most of an especially favorable launching opportunity in three years, NASA officials have decided to send not one but two large roving vehicles to the surface of Mars on separate missions.</p>
        <p>NASA officials said yesterday that they were confident that the spacecraft and roving vehicles could be built and tested in time for launchings in 2003, on May 22 and June 4. The Mars landings are scheduled for 2004, on Jan. 2 and 20.</p>
        <p>In announcing the decision, Dr. Edward J. Weiler, NASA's associate administrator for space science, said the agency would not require an increase in its budget to pay the estimated $200 million cost of the additional landing mission. The White House is reported to have approved the expanded Mars effort on the condition that the money for it come from other National Aeronautics and Space Administration programs.</p>
        <p>''We hope this won't cause cancellation of any programs in other parts of NASA,'' Dr. Weiler said at a news conference at NASA headquarters in Washington.</p>
        <p>Space officials said the cost for the two missions would probably not exceed $600 million. The plans, they said, included money to support more rigorous testing ordered after two Mars spacecraft failed last year.</p>
        <p>The orbits of Earth and Mars are such that favorable flight opportunities occur once every 25 months. And some are better than others, requiring less rocket energy to make the journey. Dr. Weiler noted that the 2003-2004 ''launch window'' would be the last especially favorable opportunity for an additional six years.</p>
        <p>Two weeks ago, when the decision to send one rover to Mars was announced, officials said they were studying the scheduling and budget implications of going for two landings. Scott Hubbard, NASA's Mars program director, who recommended the expanded mission, said yesterday, ''This is a chance to double our science, and do it for far less than twice the cost.''</p>
        <p>The rovers will be identical 300-pound wheeled robots designed to travel more than 300 feet each day over the Martian surface, taking pictures and analyzing rocks.</p>
        <p>The exact landing sites do not have to be chosen until launching time. Scientists said they were looking at shallow basins, some 60 miles or more in diameter, where surface water might have collected in the past and left chemical fingerprints. The search for evidence of Martian water, past or present, is the main scientific objective of current exploration of the planet.</p>
        <p>Dr. Weiler said that with two spacecraft, it might be possible to send one to a relatively smooth and safe landing place, then send the second to a somewhat riskier but scientifically enticing site.</p>
        <p>Excited by the assignment to develop the science instruments for the rovers, Dr. Steven Squyres, a planetary geologist at Cornell University, said, ''This mission will be humanity's first great voyage of exploration of this new millennium.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
