<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Accord Is Seen On Key Issue In Phone Strike</title>
    <meta content="Y11PHON" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221673"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TECHNOLOGY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Organized Labor</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Verizon Communications</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Communications Workers of America</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Romero, Simon</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barnes, Julian E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Organized Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000811T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEED6173FF932A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="864" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Accord Is Seen On Key Issue In Phone Strike</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SIMON ROMERO and JULIAN E. BARNES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barnes, Julian E; Romero, Simon</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Verizon Communications and striking employees reportedly reach agreement on issue at heart of dispute; company reportedly will make it easier for unions to organize some of employees currently in nonunion jobs in wireless division (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a development that could hasten the end of the strike by more than 86,000 employees of Verizon Communications, the company and its unions resolved an issue at the heart of their dispute yesterday, people close to the talks said.</p>
        <p>Verizon will make it easier for the unions to organize some of the employees currently in nonunion jobs in the company's wireless division, those close to the talks said. The unit, Verizon Wireless, is the nation's largest wireless operator, and its employees are not striking. The wireless operation is managed and majority owned by Verizon, the nation's largest telecommunications employer, in a venture with Vodafone AirTouch of Britain.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a development that could hasten the end of the strike by more than 86,000 employees of Verizon Communications, the company and its unions resolved an issue at the heart of their dispute yesterday, people close to the talks said.</p>
        <p>Verizon will make it easier for the unions to organize some of the employees currently in nonunion jobs in the company's wireless division, those close to the talks said. The unit, Verizon Wireless, is the nation's largest wireless operator, and its employees are not striking. The wireless operation is managed and majority owned by Verizon, the nation's largest telecommunications employer, in a venture with Vodafone AirTouch of Britain.</p>
        <p>Although there are other issues still to be resolved, and labor experts said it remained unclear whether the wireless workers would want to join a union, the strike's key sticking point has been settled.</p>
        <p>''I think we're at a situation where the rest of the issues could come together pretty quickly,'' said Eric Rabe, a spokesman for Verizon.</p>
        <p>The agreement reached yesterday would allow workers at Verizon Wireless within the former Bell Atlantic territory to use an expedited organization process called a card check, in which workers are allowed to join a union if a majority of employees at a work site sign cards saying they want to join. The card check is considered quicker and easier than holding elections.</p>
        <p>This concession by Verizon could have far-reaching industry implications, coming from the company that is both the nation's largest wireless carrier and the largest local telephone company. Altogether, Verizon, formed by Bell Atlantic's recently completed acquisition of the GTE Corporation, has 260,000 employees. Verizon provides wireless telephone service in 31 states and wireless service in 50 states. For the most part, the fast-growing wireless industry is not unionized.</p>
        <p>Still, the union did not win an all-out victory on the wireless issue, because the card check will be allowed only in the strike region -- the 12 Eastern states, from Maine to Virginia, and the District of Columbia, that made up the former Bell Atlantic territory.</p>
        <p>It remains to be seen how this issue might play out in other parts of the country as other parts of Verizon's union work force come up for contract renewal in coming years. And for that matter, it is not certain whether workers in Verizon Wireless, who are relatively well paid, will want to become union members.</p>
        <p>So far, fewer than 50 of Verizon Wireless's 32,000 employees are union members. And only about 8,000 of those are in the region covered by the contract negotiations.</p>
        <p>''It's not a slam dunk,'' said Paul Osterman, professor of management at M.I.T. ''The unions will have to articulate very well what they can offer to the wireless people.''</p>
        <p>In any case, negotiators for Verizon and the unions representing the striking workers -- the Communications Workers of America and the International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers -- now plan to turn their attention to other issues.</p>
        <p>As the strike enters its sixth day, talks will address union concerns that include the subcontracting of work to nonunion workers in areas like the installation of high-speed Internet lines. Other issues include job stress, mandatory overtime and a new contract for the handful of employees at Verizon Wireless who are already union members.</p>
        <p>The strike has made it difficult for the company to respond to repair calls from customers, to install new lines or answer many directory assistance requests. Moreover, acts of vandalism during the strike have taken thousands of phone lines out of service.</p>
        <p>The strike has also strained relations between Verizon's management and its striking rank-and-file technicians and customer service representatives.</p>
        <p>In the largest display of this tension so far, some 8,000 striking workers protested yesterday outside Verizon's headquarters on Avenue of the Americas at 42nd Street in Midtown Manhattan. As the ranks of demonstrators swelled, thousands of workers spilled into Bryant Park, which is across the avenue from the headquarters building.</p>
        <p>Addressing the rally, John J. Sweeney, president of the A.F.L.-C.I.O., said the strike was important to workers across the nation.</p>
        <p>''There will be no peace for this renegade corporation until it stops outsourcing good union jobs,'' Mr. Sweeney said, prompting cheers from the crowd.</p>
        <p>The crowd was generally peaceful, but some strikers screamed and blew whistles at managers walking into the Verizon headquarters building.</p>
        <p>''It's our future; wireless is a growth industry,'' said James Nicholson, 29, a striking employee from the Bronx. ''We built this company, and we should have a chance to grow with it.''</p>
        <p>Sgt. Andrew McInnis, a spokesman for the New York Police Department, said the strikers had a permit to demonstrate along the Avenue of the Americas. As for the spillover into Bryant Park, ''it's a public park,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''Anybody is allowed to demonstrate in a public park. That's the basis of the American way.''</p>
        <p>TECHNOLOGY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
