<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Child Poverty Rate Fell as Economy Grew, But Is Above 1979 Level</title>
    <meta content="Y11POV$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221722"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Income</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cost of Living</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Center for Children in Poverty</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Columbia University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Terry, Don</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Income</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000811T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E3DB143FF932A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1281" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Child Poverty Rate Fell as Economy Grew, But Is Above 1979 Level</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DON TERRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Terry, Don</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, Aug. 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Study released by National Center for Children in Poverty, Columbia University, says despite current economic boom, child poverty in all but a handful of states is still higher than it was 20 years ago; more than 13 million American children, 3 million more than in 1979, live in poverty; advocates for children cite low income and high living costs as primary factors; photo; chart (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Child poverty rates fell significantly in many states in the current economic boom, but nationwide, and in all but a handful of states, child poverty is still higher than it was 20 years ago, according to a study released today by the National Center for Children in Poverty at Columbia University.</p>
        <p>More than 13 million American children, 3 million more than in 1979, live in poverty.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Child poverty rates fell significantly in many states in the current economic boom, but nationwide, and in all but a handful of states, child poverty is still higher than it was 20 years ago, according to a study released today by the National Center for Children in Poverty at Columbia University.</p>
        <p>More than 13 million American children, 3 million more than in 1979, live in poverty.</p>
        <p>Here in California, where 1 out of 6 of the nation's poor children live, child poverty has been particularly stubborn. According to the study, the child poverty rate soared by 90 percent from 1979 to 1993 as the Golden State was badly tarnished by recession, and declined only 14.9 percent in the next five years of economic growth.</p>
        <p>The recent decline in California was encouraging but still lagged behind the rest of the nation, which saw a 17.1 percent decline after a 38.8 percent increase from 1979 to 1993.</p>
        <p>Nationally, according to census data, the child poverty rate rose to 18.7 percent in 1998, the most current information available, from 16.2 percent in 1979. In New York, the rate is 24.2 percent, or nearly 1 in 4 children living in poverty, up from 18.9 percent in 1979.</p>
        <p>Elected officials and advocates for children across the country cited low wages and high living costs as primary factors in the persistence of child poverty.</p>
        <p>Deborah Leff, president and chief executive officer of America's Second Harvest, the nation's largest domestic hunger relief organization, said a family earning the minimum wage was ''literally earning thousands of dollars under the poverty line,'' which in 1998 was $16,666 for a family of four and today is $17,050.</p>
        <p>''You can get off welfare, work hard, play by the rules and still not be able to feed your family,'' Ms. Leff said.</p>
        <p>Elie Ward, the executive director of Statewide Youth Advocacy, said poverty rates in New York had often been worse than the national ones because of the high cost of living that low-income workers face in New York City.</p>
        <p>Gail Nayowith, executive director of the Citizens' Committee for Children of New York, said the level of child poverty in New York was affected by the city's many immigrants, who often work for very low wages and have large families.</p>
        <p>The report does not say why some states, like Illinois and New Jersey, have seen significant reductions in child poverty rates since 1979, and others have seen increases or relatively minor declines.</p>
        <p>Whether welfare reform has had any effect on child poverty rates is also unclear, said Julian Palmer, a spokesman for the children's poverty center.</p>
        <p>But Robert Goerge, assistant director of the Chapin Center for Children at the University of Chicago, said Illinois' early welfare overhaul, with generous benefits, which began in 1993, helped explain why the state's children had risen out of poverty.</p>
        <p>That program, for instance, allowed welfare recipients to continue receiving health benefits and food stamps while easing into full-time employment, long before other states allowed such a benefit.</p>
        <p>''You can make more money and not get penalized,'' Mr. Goerge said.</p>
        <p>Jacqueline Tencza, a spokeswoman for the New Jersey Department of Human Services, said her state had  used savings from cuts in welfare payments to help people who get off welfare.</p>
        <p>For instance, Ms. Tencza said, $100 million that had previously been spent on welfare checks was shifted to subsidies for child care.</p>
        <p>At $125 to $150 a week, child care often accounts for at least 40 percent of the take-home pay of a former welfare mother who has just joined the work force, Ms. Tencza said.</p>
        <p>But in Georgia, where welfare caseloads have been reduced by more than half since 1997, the number of children in poverty rose more than 29 percent from 1993 to 1998, according to the study.</p>
        <p>''I don't think anyone ever believed that the immediate result of welfare reform would be the reduction of poverty,'' said Michael L. Thurmond, commissioner of the Georgia Department of Labor and the architect of the state's welfare reform plan.</p>
        <p>Poverty can take generations to overcome, Mr. Thurmond said.</p>
        <p>In Los Angeles, poverty has dogged Zena Garcia and her children for years. But this year was going to be different. This year Mrs. Garcia was going to do something special for her son James's 12th birthday next Thursday. Maybe she would take him to the zoo or buy him one of those foldable scooters every child seems to zip by on. This year was going to be different because her husband, Manuel, 36, had a job.</p>
        <p>''My husband is working as hard as he can, but it's still not enough to pay the bills,'' Mrs. Garcia, 43, said here the other day. ''I haven't been able to pay the phone bill in two months, and they're about to cut it off. And on Friday, I have to make a choice: pay the gas bill or buy shoes for my daughter.''</p>
        <p>Her daughter, Virginia, is 6 and will start first grade in the fall. Mrs. Garcia knows what her choice will be. She is going to buy her daughter a pair of shoes. If the gas is shut off as a result, she said, ''we'll deal with it.''</p>
        <p>''I want the same thing for my kids that every parent wants,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Garcia works as a cook's assistant in a hospital, but has no steady hours and no benefits. He  brings home $399 to $500 every two weeks. He has repeatedly applied for part-time or full-time status, which would provide crucial benefits.</p>
        <p>''We're waiting and praying that it happens,'' Mrs. Garcia said.</p>
        <p>Both Garcias, who were born in this country, completed a job training program in nearby Santa Monica at the St. Joseph Center, an organization that helps poor families. But so far Mrs. Garcia has not been able to find work and has returned to school to earn a high school equivalency diploma. As their case worker, Lupe Rojo, said, the Garcias are doing all they can to make it.</p>
        <p>''It gets depressing,'' Mrs. Garcia said.</p>
        <p>Her son lives in a home for troubled children. Mrs. Garcia talks to him every other day on the telephone, and that is why her phone bill is so high. She has not had the heart to tell him that he cannot go to the zoo or have a scooter.</p>
        <p>''It's going to hurt,'' she said. ''It's going to hurt me.''</p>
        <p>Her daughter has been pestering her about a scooter of her own. But seeing her mother near tears the other day, Virginia put a hand on Mrs. Garcia's shoulder and said, ''Only get one, because I'll share mine with James.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
