<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>PUBLIC LIVES</title>
    <meta content="11PUBL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221693"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Rowing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ocean Voyages</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Atlantic Ocean</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barron, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cronin, Colleen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Finlay, Roy</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sex and the City (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Public Lives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ocean Voyages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rowing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boats and Boating</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000811T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E6DD143FF932A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="765" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>PUBLIC LIVES</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BARRON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barron, James</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>public lives column; shooting of scene of television program Sex and the City described; attempt by Colleen Cronin and Roy Finlay to become first man-and woman team to cross Atlantic Ocean in rowboat discussed; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tossing Out Wings and a Ring</p>
        <p>The ''Sex and the City'' cameras were rolling one night last week. The script called for SARAH JESSICA PARKER to throw chicken wings off the terrace of a Fifth Avenue penthouse. But something else went flying: the $2,000 Bulgari ring that she has worn on her little finger since the show's first season.</p>
        <p>''They were doing a scene where she and the guy were stoned,'' said MICHAEL PATRICK KING, the show's executive producer, ''so stoned they were throwing chicken wings out of a bucket to see them fly. She threw a chicken wing and watched the ring go with it. She remained in character until they yelled 'cut.' Then she screamed, 'My ring!' ''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Tossing Out Wings and a Ring</p>
        <p>The ''Sex and the City'' cameras were rolling one night last week. The script called for SARAH JESSICA PARKER to throw chicken wings off the terrace of a Fifth Avenue penthouse. But something else went flying: the $2,000 Bulgari ring that she has worn on her little finger since the show's first season.</p>
        <p>''They were doing a scene where she and the guy were stoned,'' said MICHAEL PATRICK KING, the show's executive producer, ''so stoned they were throwing chicken wings out of a bucket to see them fly. She threw a chicken wing and watched the ring go with it. She remained in character until they yelled 'cut.' Then she screamed, 'My ring!' ''</p>
        <p>The crew checked the sidewalk, on Fifth Avenue in the East 80's. Mr. King said they held up traffic and scoured the avenue itself. ''Sarah Jessica Parker was going, 'I need it, I have to find it,' '' he said.</p>
        <p>Eventually, the search party gave up and returned to the penthouse to shoot another scene -- everyone except JIMMY GILLIAR, who is in charge of props for the show. He decided that it was time for a hot dog, Mr. King said. ''He took a step out into the crosswalk and saw this shiny thing in the crosswalk,'' Mr. King said. ''He bent down and picked it up, and yet he still went to get the hot dog. He got what he wanted, and she got what she wanted.''</p>
        <p>The ring had tried to escape a few weeks earlier, when Ms. Parker was throwing rose petals at a wedding. It landed in a bush on the Upper East Side. ''We found it immediately,'' Mr. King said.</p>
        <p>Sailing the Seas The Wireless Way</p>
        <p>The modern world: two people in a 26-foot-long rowboat that they built by hand, somewhere in the Atlantic, with laptop computer, cell phone, digital camera, modem and a Global Positioning System navigation system.</p>
        <p>The two people in the boat -- COLLEEN CRONIN, a long-distance cyclist from Bayside, Queens, and ROY FINLAY, 38, a former diver in the British Royal Navy -- are the first man-and-woman team to try to cross the Atlantic in this way.</p>
        <p>Rowing around the clock -- sometimes together, sometimes not -- they are also trying to set a record for a west-to-east crossing. Going in that direction is considered more difficult than going from east to west because west-to-east sailors cannot count on help from trade winds. They left St. John's harbor, Newfoundland, on July 28. To beat the current record of 55 days, set in 1987 by TOM McCLEAN, a British oarsman, they will have to arrive in Ireland by Sept. 21. They have financial backing from Great Spirits, a liquor importer.</p>
        <p>There has been more to the voyage than fighting bad weather and trying to stay on course: on Sunday, Ms. Cronin celebrated her 30th birthday on the boat, the Celtic Crossing. ''Roy did most of the rowing'' that day, she wrote in an e-mail message, and she spent the time sitting in the sun. ''We saw about 15 dolphins swim around the boat, performing flips in the air. I think they new it was my b'day.''</p>
        <p>She said that they had sailed through rough weather last week -- they covered 70 miles on Friday before a nighttime storm surrounded them. ''We knew something was brewing,'' she said. ''By about 10 o'clock, with no moonlight, no stars and the thick fog rolling in, there was virtually no visibility. We shifted rowing by the hour. For about four hours as we rowed, waves crashed on the deck in every direction.'' Yesterday, they were heading into an easterly wind, which slowed them down.</p>
        <p>Ms. Cronin, who competed in five New York Marathons in the 1990's and the Dublin Marathon last year, met Mr. Finlay on a visit to Ireland. ''I loved Ireland so much I haven't changed the time on my watch,'' she said. ''But this wasn't the way I expected to be going back. I'd never built a boat before, I'd never seen the process of a boat being built. Day 1, pieces of plywood and plans on the floor. I look at it now and say, this is a strong, stable boat.''</p>
        <p>JAMES BARRON</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
