<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Battle of the Bandwidths; Space Is Coveted as Wireless Expands</title>
    <meta content="Y11SPE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221687"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cellular Telephones</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Paging Systems</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Labaton, Stephen</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cellular Telephones</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Paging Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000811T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800EFDE143FF932A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1649" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Battle of the Bandwidths; Space Is Coveted as Wireless Expands</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN LABATON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Labaton, Stephen</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Aug. 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bottleneck has developed in broadcast spectrum controlled by broadcasters which was once viewed as virtually worthless but is now probably one of most valuable assets in new information age; spectrum space is in extremely short supply, with volume of Internet traffic doubling every 100 days and traffic rapidly migrating from personal computers to wireless devices like cell phones and hand-held computers; telephone companies, Internet businesses and broadcasters are battling to determine which companies will control spectrum that makes new wireless technology work, and at what cost; fight is alarming both regulators and industry executives; photos; chart (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Traveling recently through Morocco, Lowell W. Paxson marveled when he used his cell phone to view a street map enabling his driver to find an obscure restaurant there.</p>
        <p>But to his critics in the telephone and regulatory worlds, Mr. Paxson, the chairman of Paxson Communications, which owns a string of mostly small television stations, now seems to be one of the biggest impediments to the proliferation of such technology in the United States.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Traveling recently through Morocco, Lowell W. Paxson marveled when he used his cell phone to view a street map enabling his driver to find an obscure restaurant there.</p>
        <p>But to his critics in the telephone and regulatory worlds, Mr. Paxson, the chairman of Paxson Communications, which owns a string of mostly small television stations, now seems to be one of the biggest impediments to the proliferation of such technology in the United States.</p>
        <p>With the volume of Internet traffic doubling every 100 days and with that traffic rapidly migrating from personal computers to wireless devices like cell phones and hand-held computers, the airwaves are running out of free space. And much of the airspace coveted by the makers of wireless devices is in the hands of Mr. Paxson and a small group of other broadcasters, including Barry Diller of USA Networks and the Sinclair Broadcast Group, a major broadcaster based in Baltimore.</p>
        <p>The spectrum space controlled by the broadcasters was once viewed as virtually worthless, but it is now perhaps one of the most valuable assets in the new information age, as important as oil and coal were in the industrial revolution. Cell phones, hand-held personal digital assistants, laptop computers and other wireless devices need spectrum space to function.</p>
        <p>The broadcasters' sliver of spectrum space, occupying channels 60 to 69 in many major markets, was given to them free by Congress four years ago. In exchange, the broadcasters promised to make digital television widely available by 2006 and return the spectrum when they had done so.</p>
        <p>But the development of digital television has stalled. And since the stations do not have to give up their spectrum licenses until 85 percent of all television viewers have switched to digital TV -- a milestone that may be decades off -- a bottleneck has developed, with spectrum space in extremely short supply.</p>
        <p>As a result, telephone companies, Internet businesses, and the broadcasters  are battling to determine which companies will control the spectrum that makes the new wireless technology work, and at what cost. In Britain, five licenses sold for a total of $35.5 billion in April. And government officials estimate that the space now occupied by Mr. Paxson and the other broadcasters could be worth billions.</p>
        <p>The fight is alarming both regulators and industry executives.</p>
        <p>''The big story is that our spectrum policy in the United States is totally messed up,'' said Reed Hundt, a former chairman of the Federal Communications Commission who is now on the boards of eight Internet companies (none of which is seeking a spectrum license). ''And right now the F.C.C. is really holding a handful of hot coals.''</p>
        <p>The broadcasters say they cannot give up their spectrum licenses until the regulators issue rules to help accelerate the transition to digital television. They want the F.C.C. to force cable television companies to carry signals for both traditional TV and the new digital TV, expanding the so-called must-carry rules. They also want the agency to move faster to impose technical standards allowing easier coordination between digital broadcasters and cable companies.</p>
        <p>Regulators say they are moving rapidly on some of the rules the broadcasters want but say others are unfair and, in at least one instance, probably unconstitutional.</p>
        <p>William E. Kennard, chairman of the F.C.C., said this week that the broadcasters had made unreasonable demands on his agency, trying to use their leverage as holders of valuable spectrum licenses.</p>
        <p>''The law put the broadcasters completely in the driver's seat,'' he said. ''The broadcasters made a deal with the United States Congress. They promised a lot of key people in Congress that if you give us this spectrum, we will give the public high-definition television. But nobody really said that the American public wanted it or what the business plan was. There were a lot of promises made, but none has been fulfilled.''</p>
        <p>For their part, the telephone and Internet companies say they cannot make plans to buy the available spectrum -- or even draw up business plans that include the use of the spectrum -- until they know how and when the broadcasters will make it available and at what price. The telephone companies interested in acquiring frequencies include Verizon Communications, Voicestream, BellSouth, Nextel, Sprint and a joint venture of BellSouth and SBC Communications.</p>
        <p>The dispute has raised significant concerns that venture capitalists and investors in wireless technology will shift their attention to Europe and Asia. Officials there, unencumbered by the kinds of laws that have restricted the F.C.C., have been moving swiftly this year to liberate the airwaves for newer uses. The effect of this would be to shift technology investment overseas, and, as a result, technology innovation and development as well.</p>
        <p>Congress had ordered the F.C.C. to auction the pieces of the channel 60 to 69 spectrum that are not in the hands of the broadcasters -- chiefly pieces outside urban areas -- sometime this year. But many telephone and Internet companies have been unwilling to put together significant business plans or bids, preferring to wait until spectrum in major markets is available.</p>
        <p>As a result, the F.C.C. has rescheduled the auction three times this year, and this month the agency announced it would not sell the available spectrum until next spring. Broadcasters and Internet executives say that even that new date may be overly optimistic because the agency is likely to be undergoing a transition to new leadership after the presidential election. As a consequence, they say it is probable that these issues may not be resolved for more than a year.</p>
        <p>Some regulators have blamed Congress for giving away such a valuable asset, while others fault the broadcasters for failing to live up to their promise to rapidly roll out digital television. Had the broadcasters managed to do so, they would have then vacated the extra spectrum they were given for the transition, averting the current situation.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Paxson, who was in Washington this week pressing Congressional aides to prod the F.C.C. to adopt must-carry and other rules favorable to the broadcasters, blamed in large part what he called the incompetence of the F.C.C. and its inability to move quickly for the failure of digital television.</p>
        <p>''On this subject, digital television, Kennard gets at F,'' Mr. Paxson said. ''Other than that, he has done a great job.''</p>
        <p>For months, Mr. Kennard has been warning of a spectrum drought caused by demand outstripping supply just as the Internet migrates from the wire to wireless devices like cell phones and hand-held computers.</p>
        <p>As consumers increasingly reach the Internet through wireless connections, experts fear that the heavy use of the airwaves will begin to create colliding signals and other problems that could greatly frustrate the further development of the technology.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hundt estimates that at the current rate of growth, the government must nearly triple the amount of spectrum available for wireless Internet the next five years.</p>
        <p>Signals transmitted on the space occupied by channels 60 to 69 possess highly desirable characteristics: they can pass through walls and other structures with great clarity and little interference.</p>
        <p>When Congress decided to give away the spectrum to the broadcasters rather than sell it, there were some, most notably Senators John McCain and Bob Dole, who called it a terrible government giveaway. In his book about his term as chairman, Mr. Hundt has called it the ''largest grant of government largess since the 19th century donation of 10 percent of the public land in the West to three dozen railroad companies in order to persuade them to build transcontinental railroads.''</p>
        <p>But government officials and industry lawyers now say that the giveaway -- valued at the time as high as $70 billion -- will never be undone because of the enormous political strength of the broadcasters. As a result, they say, the only solution to the current shortage of available spectrum space is a negotiated settlement between the telephone companies and the broadcasters.</p>
        <p>For Mr. Paxson and the other owners of the stations broadcasting from channels 60 to 69, the increasing value of the spectrum presents huge opportunities. He is in the process of developing ways to use digital technology for multiple channels that will enable him to begin new networks in partnership with NBC, and the money he could get for his spectrum space would significantly increase the resources he has at hand.</p>
        <p>Paxson Communications, which has a market value of about $630 million, owns 19 stations in the coveted spectrum, more than any other company. By many estimates, those frequencies are worth billions of dollars to the telephone companies.</p>
        <p>Mr. Paxson, the inventor of interactive home shopping on television more than two decades ago, bristles at any suggestion that he has been hoarding the airwaves. He brushes off complaints by rivals that he is holding back as he watches European auctions for spectrum.</p>
        <p>''I've been doing this since 1954 and have been involved in developing more of these stations than anyone else,'' he said. ''Am I greedy? Of course not. I've got four million shareholders who say, 'What are you doing with digital? What are you doing with spectrum?' ''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
