<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Where Hindenburg Fell, Midair Crash Revives Talk of Curse</title>
    <meta content="11VICT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221696"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lakehurst Naval Air Center (NJ)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Burlington County (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jacobs, Andrew</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Military Bases and Installations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000811T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E1DD143FF932A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1285" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Where Hindenburg Fell, Midair Crash Revives Talk of Curse</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW JACOBS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jacobs, Andrew</byline>
      <dateline>LAKEHURST, N.J., Aug. 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses reaction at Lakehurst, NJ, Naval Air Engineering Station to midair plane crash in which 6 civilian Navy employees were among 11 people killed; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A grim hush fell over the Airship Tavern this afternoon as the enlisted men and naval engineers put down their beers and glanced at the overhead television, its screen showing the wreckage of a shattered aircraft that took the lives of six of their co-workers.</p>
        <p>A day after the midair collision of two small planes near here killed 11 people, those who work at this military base were trying to grapple with the loss of so many colleagues at once -- and with an unsettling history of air disasters.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A grim hush fell over the Airship Tavern this afternoon as the enlisted men and naval engineers put down their beers and glanced at the overhead television, its screen showing the wreckage of a shattered aircraft that took the lives of six of their co-workers.</p>
        <p>A day after the midair collision of two small planes near here killed 11 people, those who work at this military base were trying to grapple with the loss of so many colleagues at once -- and with an unsettling history of air disasters.</p>
        <p>''Everyone is just so devastated,'' said Ellie Cameron, a bartender at the tavern, which is filled with pictures of the Hindenburg, the dirigible that burned and fell here in 1937, killing 36 people. ''It's too much to bear.''</p>
        <p>For those who work and live in this township of scrub pines and new subdivisions about 70 miles southwest of Manhattan, aviation disasters have always been closely associated with the Lakehurst Naval Air Engineering Station, which these days specializes in technology for aircraft carriers.</p>
        <p>At the base entrance, a Blue Angel F-4 jet stands as a memorial to three naval stunt pilots who died here in 1973 when two of the fighter jets collided during a training exercise. In 1933, the crash of the Navy airship U.S.S. Akron, which was based at Lakehurst, took 73 lives. Only three crewmen survived.</p>
        <p>More than ever, it is a legacy that feels like a curse.</p>
        <p>''When I got assigned here, people told me, 'That's the place where bad things happen,' '' said Petty Officer Second Class Louis Lemos, 25, an accountant at the base, as he stood at the front gate. ''I guess they were right.''</p>
        <p>Except for the flag flying at half staff, there were few outward signs of trauma. Of the 11 people killed, six worked here as civilian engineers, managers or logisticians. The seventh naval employee worked from a base near Philadelphia. The other four victims were pilots, including one who was in training.</p>
        <p>''This has affected everyone on the base,'' said Pamela Schott, who is coordinating a team of 20 crisis intervention counselors. ''Many people knew the victims for 20 or more years, so the loss has had a real ripple effect.''</p>
        <p>The plane that took off from Lakehurst was a Piper Navajo, a commuter plane that seats 10, making its usual morning run from the base to Patuxent River Naval Air Station in Maryland. All the passengers had meetings at the air station and were to have returned Wednesday evening.</p>
        <p>George DiBiase, the chief engineer at Lakehurst, said all the employees making the trip were involved in the design and production of mechanisms that catapult fighter jets from the decks of aircraft carriers and then help them to land. In contrast to many military bases, with their frequently shifting staffs, most of those  working at the Lakehurst base are civilians who live in the community.</p>
        <p>''People tend to stay here and they and their families become close to one another,'' said Mr. DiBiase, 66, who has worked at Lakehurst since the 1950's.</p>
        <p>One of those killed, Michael Simodejka, 52, a logistics management specialist from Toms River, made the trip almost every week, said his wife, Patricia. Like the other victims, Mr. Simodejka left his home before dawn on Wednesday so he could make the 7:15 a.m. flight from an airstrip at the base.</p>
        <p>Friends and co-workers of Mr. Simodejka, the father of two grown children, said he was an avid hunter and often swam in his backyard pool.</p>
        <p>It was the first shuttle trip for John A. Zukow, who usually took commercial flights to Maryland. An engineering technician and former paratrooper, Mr. Zukow, 56, lived in a retirement community in Berkeley Township with his wife, Kathleen. The Zukows had moved from Toms River to the retirement community, the Silver Ridge Park Westerly, last December.</p>
        <p>To their neighbors, most of whom are over 70, the Zukows were considered ''the kids on the block,'' said a nearby resident, Stephen Timko, who described Mr. Zukow as outgoing and conscientious. ''He was always helping people and always asking to help,'' Mr. Timko said.</p>
        <p>The other workers from Lakehurst were Angelo George, 39, a program manager from Toms River with a wife and four young children; Robert G. Polo, 39, a logistics management specialist from Barnegat; John J. Vail Jr., 36, a program manager from Howell, and Cynthia Kovacs, 39, a mechanical engineer from Robbinsville whose husband, Wayne, also works at Lakehurst.</p>
        <p>A co-worker, Dennis Dusenshine, said Ms. Kovacs helped design systems to prevent midair collisions. ''It's kind of ironic,'' Mr. Dusenshine told The Associated Press.</p>
        <p>Ms. Kovacs also survived breast cancer, working the entire time she was undergoing treatment. She was declared free of cancer in February, said Pattie Odoardo, another co-worker. ''It's very heartbreaking,'' she said, ''to see someone survive such a terrible disease and then go like that.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Kovacs ran six miles a day, sometimes going to the base gym on her lunch hour or after work. A neighbor, Aurelia Youngken, said Ms. Kovacs was active with the P.T.A. and the local Little League. She had a 5-year-old son and a 9-year-old daughter. ''They were her life and joy, her children,'' Ms. Odoardo said.</p>
        <p>The seventh Navy employee, David Dahlen, 57, lived in Warminster, Pa., and worked as a contractor with the Naval Inventory Control Point in Philadelphia. Mr. Dahlen, who along with Ms. Kovacs boarded the plane at the Trenton-Mercer Airport, was involved in foreign military sales and logistics management. A family friend, Fran Poole, described Mr. Dahlen as a stock car racing enthusiast, a doting grandfather and a singer in a barbershop quartet.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dahlen, he said, took the shuttle three or four times a year and always called his wife, Gail, soon after his arrival in Maryland. ''When she did not get the call yesterday, she knew deep down that something had happened,'' Mr. Poole said.</p>
        <p>The pilots of the Piper Navajo were Joseph Peter Mari, 37, of Toms River and Daniel Groff, 38, of Forked River, who had a wife and young son. The two men, employees of Patuxent Airways of California, Md., often flew the shuttle together.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mari, who was single and lived with his parents, was planning to return to aviation school in the fall, his father, Frank, said. Although he enjoyed flying commuter planes, his goal, his father said, was to fly commercial jets. ''Since he was a little boy he wanted to fly,'' he said. ''It was his passion.''</p>
        <p>The other aircraft involved in the crash, a four-seat Piper Seminole, was being flown by Craig Robinson, 28, and a student pilot, Jason Wismer, 20, of Bensalem, Pa. Mr. Robinson, an officer with the Washington Township Police Department, was a flight instructor in his free time. ''Next to his wife and child, flying was his life,'' said Ted Kszcpka, his father-in-law. ''It's what he loved.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
