<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Starting Off With Sex, Ending Up With Love</title>
    <meta content="11AFFA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221603"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Scott, A O</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Affair of Love, An (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Pornographic Affair, A (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000811T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01EFDE173FF932A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="701" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Starting Off With Sex, Ending Up With Love</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Excerpts from A O Scott's March 24 review of French film An Affair of Love (formerly titled A Pornographic Affair), which was shown as part of New Directors/New Films series, and is now in commercial release; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''An Affair of Love'' was shown as part of this year's New Directors/ New Films series under the title ''A Pornographic Affair.'' Following are excerpts from A. O. Scott's review, which appeared in The New York Times on March 24. The film opens today in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>''A Pornographic Affair'' may shock you, but not necessarily for the expected reasons. It concerns the relationship of two anonymous, respectable people (Nathalie Baye and Sergi Lopez) who spend each Thursday afternoon in a Paris hotel room doing something that dare not speak its name. If you're anticipating the next ''Last Tango in Paris,'' think again. ''A Pornographic Affair'' is more like ''When Harry Met Sally'' remade as a panel discussion on the highfalutin French talk show ''Apostrophe.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''An Affair of Love'' was shown as part of this year's New Directors/ New Films series under the title ''A Pornographic Affair.'' Following are excerpts from A. O. Scott's review, which appeared in The New York Times on March 24. The film opens today in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>''A Pornographic Affair'' may shock you, but not necessarily for the expected reasons. It concerns the relationship of two anonymous, respectable people (Nathalie Baye and Sergi Lopez) who spend each Thursday afternoon in a Paris hotel room doing something that dare not speak its name. If you're anticipating the next ''Last Tango in Paris,'' think again. ''A Pornographic Affair'' is more like ''When Harry Met Sally'' remade as a panel discussion on the highfalutin French talk show ''Apostrophe.''</p>
        <p>Harry and Sally were best pals who discovered, almost too late, a sexual attraction. This made their story a romantic comedy. Elle and Lui (Her and Him), as our dutiful pornographers are known, start out as sex partners and then fall in love, which makes ''A Pornographic Affair'' -- well, what exactly? A movie that takes itself, and its subject, very seriously indeed. But for all its earnest intellectualism, this film tells you everything you already knew about sex but wouldn't have bothered to ask in the first place, including that, if presented in just the right way, it can be just as boring as anything else.</p>
        <p>Ms. Baye's character, finding herself single and at loose ends, places an advertisement in an adult magazine soliciting a man willing to fulfill a long-standing fantasy of hers. Mr. Lopez's character -- can't they at least have silly dirty-minded pseudonyms, like real porn stars? -- finds her request compatible with his tastes, so they meet at a cafe, have a drink and then repair to a hotel. We never see what happens behind the door.</p>
        <p>Nor will either one, in the otherwise candid postmortem interviews, identify the special practice that binds them together.</p>
        <p>Perhaps this reticence is supposed to make our imaginations run wild, or expose us for the crass voyeurs we are. Perhaps Elle and Lui are playing pinochle, or doing the crossword puzzle in Le Monde. Whatever it is, their esoteric hanky-panky never ruffles the air of pleasant, faintly melancholy sincerity that they display on the other side of the door. Only when they decide to get really crazy and have normal sexual intercourse (which we are allowed to see, and which is tastefully cinematic) do they discover any real, risky emotion.</p>
        <p>But not, in the end, all that much. ''A Pornographic Affair,'' directed by Frederic Fonteyne, posits an eroticism without heat and discovers a romantic passion without intensity. Lui and Elle present themselves to each other and to us entirely without context.</p>
        <p>They seem to chat quite amiably in their cafe (and, for all we know, in bed), but they never mention their jobs, their friends, their life histories or anything else that might make them recognizable as people. The film operates on the premise that to suppress such detail is to strip characters to their emotional essence. But with so little information, it's hard to see what would draw these people to each other.</p>
        <p>Worse, it's impossible to figure out why we should be interested in them. When the film reaches its, uh, climax, we don't feel the vicarious longing that would make us care whether they stayed together or not.</p>
        <p>''A Pornographic Affair'' is too busy congratulating itself for its restraint, good taste and edifying absence of prurience to bother with such mundane concerns. Ms. Baye and Mr. Lopez are good-humored and pleasant to watch, but their characters are unable to remember how long their dalliance lasted or how many times they did whatever it was they were doing. Do they even recall what it was? Clearly, this is an affair to forget.</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
