<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Jets Shuffling Quarterback Deck Against the Ravens</title>
    <meta content="11JETS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/11/sports/11JETS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221679"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Baltimore Ravens</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Jets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Battista, Judy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Baltimore Ravens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000811T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE7DE143FF932A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="924" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Jets Shuffling Quarterback Deck Against the Ravens</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JUDY BATTISTA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Battista, Judy</byline>
      <dateline>HEMPSTEAD, N.Y., Aug. 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on New York Jets preparing for preseason game against Baltimore Ravens; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Five series are all that separate Jets quarterback Vinny Testaverde from his lost season. Just 34 plays, 17 in each of the first two preseason games, to shake off the rust, work out the leg and feel out the new receivers. But Coach Al Groh is apparently comfortable enough with the first-team offense, which has scored on three of the five Testaverde-led possessions, and secure enough with the limited work Testaverde has had, to juggle the quarterback rotation for Saturday's game against Baltimore.</p>
        <p>Groh announced today that Ray Lucas, Testaverde's backup who performed admirably when Testaverde was injured last season, will start against the Ravens. Groh would not give a time frame for how long Lucas will remain in the game, but he wants Lucas, who had a difficult game against Green Bay while playing with the backup offense, to get considerable work with the first unit.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Five series are all that separate Jets quarterback Vinny Testaverde from his lost season. Just 34 plays, 17 in each of the first two preseason games, to shake off the rust, work out the leg and feel out the new receivers. But Coach Al Groh is apparently comfortable enough with the first-team offense, which has scored on three of the five Testaverde-led possessions, and secure enough with the limited work Testaverde has had, to juggle the quarterback rotation for Saturday's game against Baltimore.</p>
        <p>Groh announced today that Ray Lucas, Testaverde's backup who performed admirably when Testaverde was injured last season, will start against the Ravens. Groh would not give a time frame for how long Lucas will remain in the game, but he wants Lucas, who had a difficult game against Green Bay while playing with the backup offense, to get considerable work with the first unit.</p>
        <p>Testaverde will go in after Lucas and, Groh hopes, get a chance to run the two-minute offense with the first team near the end of the second quarter. The rookie Chad Pennington will play after Testaverde.</p>
        <p>''I only want Vinny to play with the first group, so I want to make sure that's not too short,'' Groh said. ''But I want to make sure it's a worthwhile stint for Ray, too. He started a number of games for us, and I want to get him back into that mode.''</p>
        <p>Testaverde is a perfectionist and would likely not feel he is where he wants to be even if he were playing every down in the preseason. But today, Testaverde said that he had hoped to get more time than he has so far this preseason.</p>
        <p>''Last week, I didn't express this to coach, but I would have liked to play more,'' Testaverde said. ''But that's a coach's decision. He has to do what he has to do to get the team ready. There's a fine line between being ready and putting yourself at risk for the opener.''</p>
        <p>Testaverde said he may lobby Groh for more time against the Giants next Friday, the Jets' final preseason game.</p>
        <p>''If I felt like I need it going into the last game, yeah,'' Testaverde said. ''Or maybe even this week, depending on how the game goes.''</p>
        <p>The shakeup in the quarterback rotation is nothing new in the Bill Parcells era with the Jets. In 1998, when Glenn Foley was the designated starter, Parcells started Testaverde in the second game of the preseason. Last season, Parcells started Lucas over Testaverde against the Giants in the third preseason game to bolster Lucas's confidence as a backup after a disastrous performance by Lucas earlier in the preseason.</p>
        <p>Today, Groh said that he had no concern about the amount of preparation Testaverde has gotten in his first action since the yearlong layoff caused by the injury to his Achilles' tendon. And for Lucas, this is a chance to ease the angst caused by a two-interception outing against Green Bay, after which Lucas said he singlehandedly lost the game for the Jets.</p>
        <p>''I'm looking forward to playing again after what happened last week,'' Lucas said.</p>
        <p>The switch means Testaverde will have to wait to hear how Baltimore fans react to the quarterback the Ravens released in 1998. Testaverde said this game, his first against Baltimore, has no special significance for him and that he is not out to show the Ravens, or their owner Art Modell, who once made unkind remarks about Testaverde's resurrection with the Jets, what they have missed since he left.</p>
        <p>''That really didn't mean a whole lot to me,'' Testaverde said. ''I have no bad feelings toward the Ravens.''</p>
        <p>If Testaverde is comfortable with his return to Baltimore, he seems less at ease with the group of young Jets receivers. He has a comfort level, he said, with the veterans Wayne Chrebet, Dedric Ward and Dwight Stone. But he has had limited opportunity to work in games with younger players such as Laveranues Coles and Windrell Hayes. While Testaverde said he feels good about how the first team offense has played so far, he is concerned about the development of the larger group.</p>
        <p>''The more we get together, the better we are,'' Testaverde said. ''These guys have to put themselves in a position to be able to get with the first team.''</p>
        <p>EXTRA POINTS</p>
        <p>The rookie SHAUN ELLIS will start at left defensive end for the second game in a row while RICK LYLE will start on the right side. . . . Defensive lineman JASON WILTZ (arm) and wide receiver YATIL GREEN (groin) will not play against Baltimore. This injury does not bode well for Green, who did not play in the first preseason game and did not have a reception in the second game. . . . Cornerback AARON GLENN had his left ankle wrapped and in a brace Thursday and did not practice, but Coach AL GROH was not sure if he would play Saturday. . . . DEDRIC WARD will start as the punt returner.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
