<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>It's Hard to Rear an Angel, Especially in Devil Town</title>
    <meta content="11BLES$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221615"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smits, Jimmy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Basinger, Kim</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Russell, Chuck</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mitchell, Elvis</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Bless the Child (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews/By Elvis Mitchell</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000811T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E2DC173FF932A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="956" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>It's Hard to Rear an Angel, Especially in Devil Town</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELVIS MITCHELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mitchell, Elvis</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Elvis Mitchell reviews movie Bless the Child, directed by Chuck Russell and starring Kim Basinger and Jimmy Smits; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The new thriller ''Bless the Child'' is runny with heartbreak; it's a supernatural soap opera. Maggie (Kim Basinger) is a dedicated psychiatric nurse who has a warm, flattering light on her even when she rides in the back of a Manhattan bus. When her angry younger sister, Jenna (Angela Bettis), shows up with a newborn daughter, old family conflicts flare. Maggie growls at Jenna for being a drug addict, and Jenna snaps back that at least she was able to give birth, leaving her barren sister speechless. Then Jenna leaves altogether, abandoning Cody, her little girl, at Maggie's apartment.</p>
        <p>''Bless the Child'' is an ecumenical suspense story, directed by Chuck Russell with an attempt at the hushed elegance of ''The Sixth Sense.'' Despite a few chills, the movie is more like ''The Exorcist'' or ''The Omen'' with a happy face drawn on its soul -- the first suspense film of the ''Touched by an Angel'' era. But just when you think that the movie is trying to show a little class, Mr. Russell does something like send a car off a bridge, and then have it explode as it hurtles toward the water.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The new thriller ''Bless the Child'' is runny with heartbreak; it's a supernatural soap opera. Maggie (Kim Basinger) is a dedicated psychiatric nurse who has a warm, flattering light on her even when she rides in the back of a Manhattan bus. When her angry younger sister, Jenna (Angela Bettis), shows up with a newborn daughter, old family conflicts flare. Maggie growls at Jenna for being a drug addict, and Jenna snaps back that at least she was able to give birth, leaving her barren sister speechless. Then Jenna leaves altogether, abandoning Cody, her little girl, at Maggie's apartment.</p>
        <p>''Bless the Child'' is an ecumenical suspense story, directed by Chuck Russell with an attempt at the hushed elegance of ''The Sixth Sense.'' Despite a few chills, the movie is more like ''The Exorcist'' or ''The Omen'' with a happy face drawn on its soul -- the first suspense film of the ''Touched by an Angel'' era. But just when you think that the movie is trying to show a little class, Mr. Russell does something like send a car off a bridge, and then have it explode as it hurtles toward the water.</p>
        <p>In one scene, Ian Holm appropriates Kevin Spacey's line from ''The Usual Suspects'' -- ''the Devil's greatest trick is convincing people he doesn't exist'' -- without bursting into laughter. Gothic stridors and ominous chanting issue from the soundtrack so often that you'd think ''Rosemary's Baby'' was playing on a television set in the other room. ''Bless the Child'' seems derivative of so many other movies that you're surprised that it doesn't have to credit its sources the way hip-hop artists do when they sample songs.</p>
        <p>Maggie rears Cody on her own, and though the girl at age 6 is labeled autistic, Maggie believes that it's something else. ''She's special,'' she says, doting on Cody's otherworldliness. When a cleaned-up Jenna -- now married to Eric (Rufus Sewell), a rich, creepy and powerful cult leader who seems to be trying to repress a British accent -- returns for Cody, Maggie smells that something wicked this way comes. There is a brief touch of wit: as Maggie fears that Cody is going to be taken away by Jenna and Eric, a television cartoon shows a small animal being scooped up by a giant talon.</p>
        <p>The screenwriters, Tom Rickman, Clifford Green and Ellen Green, have carved away all the surplus plot of Cathy Cash Spellman's novel, a potboiler crammed with incident: a custody battle from beyond the grave, with trips to Egypt and great, musty tombs.</p>
        <p>Mr. Russell and the writers have also pared away the doom patrol Maggie assembled in the novel to fight the forces of evil for Cody. Her ally in the film is an F.B.I. agent, John Travis (Jimmy Smits), a former seminary student who is also an expert in santeria (to whose forces Mr. Smits succumbed in ''The Believers,'' another mediocre picture about Satan in New York).</p>
        <p>Holliston Coleman, the young actress playing Cody, has a forehead that furrows with concern and an adult cleft in her little chin. With her faraway look, she's enormously compelling, a real find. And Ms. Bettis, all red-rimmed eyes and shaky grip on stability, does well, too.</p>
        <p>Christina Ricci turns up to deliver some important exposition, and disappears; she might as well be one of the mysterious strangers who step in to help Maggie with her quest, including a construction worker who has the languid dark-blond looks of a Renaissance Jesus. In the end, though, Maggie has to do battle herself, since this is also a test of faith for her; she's a lapsed Catholic.</p>
        <p>Ms. Basinger speaks very slowly and intently, as if she is self-medicated, until Maggie learns that Cody will be sacrificed on Easter and shakes off her well-meaning stupor, bolting into action. Eventually, ''Bless the Child'' is tiresome, though you have to have a soft spot for a movie in which the commercialized self-help movement -- Eric's motto is ''Do what you will, will what you do'' -- is equated with Satanism.</p>
        <p>''Bless the Child'' is off kilter enough to be unsettling. It features a string of offscreen child murders, a scene in which Eric has an epistemological conversation with Cody as he threatens to shove her off a roof (Ms. Coleman is so good that she almost makes it work) and a confrontation between Maggie and Jenna in which  Maggie gasps, ''Drugs!,'' as if heroin were a brand name she was afraid to utter. The scares may be only intermittent, but the oddities remain.</p>
        <p>''Bless the Child'' is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It includes violence, profanity, child endangerment and scenes of ghastly special effects, including armies of rats.</p>
        <p>BLESS THE CHILD</p>
        <p>Directed by Chuck Russell; written by Tom Rickman, Clifford Green and Ellen Green, based on the novel by Cathy Cash Spellman; director of photography, Peter Menzies; edited by Alan Heim; music by Christopher Young; production designer, Carol Spier; produced by Mace Neufeld; released by Paramount Pictures. Running time: 115 minutes. This film is rated R.</p>
        <p>WITH: Kim Basinger (Maggie O'Connor), Jimmy Smits (John Travis), Holliston Coleman (Cody), Rufus Sewell (Eric Stark), Angela Bettis (Jenna), Christina Ricci (Sheri) and Ian Holm (Reverend Grissom).</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
