<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>When Tires Start Blowing Apart</title>
    <meta content="11FRI2" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221668"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tires</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobile Safety Features and Defects</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recalls and Bans of Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bridgestone Tire &amp; Rubber Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Firestone Tire &amp; Rubber Co</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Safety Features and Defects</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recalls and Bans of Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tires</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000811T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E0D6173FF932A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="605" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>When Tires Start Blowing Apart</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial says Bridgestone/Firestone's recall of 6.5 million defective tires is deeply troubling and that companies need to provide reassuring answers to some critical questions before they can re-establish credibility with public (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There are too few public facts to know for sure whether Bridgestone/Firestone or Ford Motor Company waited too long to recall tires that may have caused hundreds of accidents, 80 injuries and 46 deaths in the United States alone. But what is known is deeply troubling.</p>
        <p>Bridgestone/Firestone recalled about 6.5 million tires this week because they are prone to shedding their treads. The company says it does not know why the specific models of tires in question are plagued by problems. But it decided to recall the tires anyway in the wake of mounting complaints, a federal investigation and dozens of lawsuits. The recall is expected to cost more than $300 million, and that does not count the potentially huge liability costs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There are too few public facts to know for sure whether Bridgestone/Firestone or Ford Motor Company waited too long to recall tires that may have caused hundreds of accidents, 80 injuries and 46 deaths in the United States alone. But what is known is deeply troubling.</p>
        <p>Bridgestone/Firestone recalled about 6.5 million tires this week because they are prone to shedding their treads. The company says it does not know why the specific models of tires in question are plagued by problems. But it decided to recall the tires anyway in the wake of mounting complaints, a federal investigation and dozens of lawsuits. The recall is expected to cost more than $300 million, and that does not count the potentially huge liability costs.</p>
        <p>The complaints, however, are hardly news to either company. Both have settled lawsuits over tire problems, imposing a gag rule on plaintiffs as a condition for cash rewards, so that word of the cases never reached the public or federal safety officials. In the past year Ford has recalled tires in Saudi Arabia, Venezuela and several other countries in hot-climate zones, yet continued to install them on vehicles in the United States. Bridgestone/Firestone has provided replacement tires for customers whose tires failed during the warranty period, yet the company did nothing to protect its other customers until this week.</p>
        <p>Of course, any time that a product is recalled as defective it gives rise to the question ''why not earlier?'' Ford says that the tire failures abroad appeared to reflect unusual driving conditions -- high-speed travel in very hot climates in overloaded vehicles on underinflated tires -- unlike those in the United States. Bridgestone/Firestone says its complaint records did not reveal a disturbing pattern. The National Highway Traffic Safety Administration launched an investigation only in May of this year because it received too few consumer complaints to establish an unusual trend of accidents.</p>
        <p>But before Bridgestone/Firestone or Ford can re-establish credibility with the public, they must provide reassuring answers to some critical questions. Was Ford's dismissal of the relevance of crashes abroad cavalier given that most of the accidents in this country seem to have occurred under hot driving conditions in the South that may have mirrored some of the conditions abroad? As for regulatory responsibilities, manufacturers are required to report defective products to the safety administration. Did Bridgestone/Firestone comb its warranty data and other records carefully for an unusually high incidence of defects?</p>
        <p>At least one consumer safety advocate does not think so. Clarence Ditlow of the Center for Auto Safety says data that his organization has collected suggests that the number of complaints and the failure rate on the suspect tires far exceed levels that should trigger a recall.</p>
        <p>Some lessons emerge even without a final accounting of the facts. Ford says that in the future it will inspect warranty data on the tires it installs on its vehicles, a sensible practice that might have cut short this problem. By the same logic, the safety administration, and Congress, should examine whether manufacturers should be required to submit summaries of warranty information to federal regulators.</p>
        <p>The safety administration appears understaffed and underfinanced, hampering its ability to react to such crises. The agency collects reports on fatalities and accidents, but they are not nearly exhaustive enough to reveal disturbing patterns before outsiders bring complaints to their attention. That too deserves serious review. Had it not been for a Houston television report on the problem that triggered a spate of complaints to the agency earlier this year, most drivers would still be unaware of their danger.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
