<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Recreating Last Moments Before a Midair Collision</title>
    <meta content="11CRAS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221692"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Burlington County (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hanley, Robert</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000811T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E6DD143FF932A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="873" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Recreating Last Moments Before a Midair Collision</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT HANLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hanley, Robert</byline>
      <dateline>BURLINGTON TOWNSHIP, N.J., Aug. 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>National Transportation Safety Board continues investigation into mid-air crash of two planes in southern New Jersey; they attempt to recreate last moments before collision; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A federal investigator today described the last few moments before a midair collision of two small planes that killed 11 people on Wednesday morning: The smaller plane was flying east, almost directly toward the sun, and beginning a left turn toward the northeast. The other plane was heading south, at the same altitude.</p>
        <p>The scenario, recreated through the analysis of radar data, does not provide any conclusions about the early-morning crash, said George W. Black, a member of the National Transportation Safety Board and head of the federal inquiry. But it does provide clues.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A federal investigator today described the last few moments before a midair collision of two small planes that killed 11 people on Wednesday morning: The smaller plane was flying east, almost directly toward the sun, and beginning a left turn toward the northeast. The other plane was heading south, at the same altitude.</p>
        <p>The scenario, recreated through the analysis of radar data, does not provide any conclusions about the early-morning crash, said George W. Black, a member of the National Transportation Safety Board and head of the federal inquiry. But it does provide clues.</p>
        <p>''We're looking into sun angles to determine if the sun was at a point where it might have been a problem,'' Mr. Black said.</p>
        <p>Aboard the smaller plane, a twin-engine Piper Seminole, were a flight instructor and a student.</p>
        <p>The other plane, a twin-engine Piper Navajo, carrying a pilot, co-pilot and nine civilian employees of the Navy, had the sun directly to the pilot's left, Mr. Black said.</p>
        <p>''It will be another interesting point in our investigation that the Seminole was looking at the sun,'' Mr. Black said.</p>
        <p>Both planes were flying at 3,000 feet; neither plane was climbing or descending when the collision occurred, he said.</p>
        <p>A preliminary examination of the wreckage from both planes revealed that a propeller blade on the Navajo, the larger aircraft, had struck the vertical part of the Seminole's tail, Mr. Black said. But it was not clear whether the strike was evidence of the first point of contact or whether it occurred after the planes collided.</p>
        <p>Four people aboard the crippled Navajo were thrown from the plane as it plunged, skimmed rooftops and struck an attached garage at a two-story house at 1 Philly Court. There, it exploded and set off a fire that destroyed the house. The other passengers were recovered from the wreckage Wednesday afternoon.</p>
        <p>The Seminole crashed into a soybean field about a mile away. The bodies of the flight instructor, Craig Robinson, 28, of Hamilton Township, N.J.,and a teenage flying student, Jason Wismer of Bensalem, Pa., were found near the wreckage.</p>
        <p>There was no evidence that either pilot saw the other plane before the crash, Mr. Black said. Both pilots were flying under flight rules that required them to scan the skies for nearby planes.</p>
        <p>''It is incumbent on both of them to keep a lookout under visual flight rules,'' Mr. Black said. ''Their regulatory obligation is to keep a look-out.''</p>
        <p>He added that the skies were clear at the time of the crash.</p>
        <p>Drew Stecketee, a spokesman for the Aircraft Owners and Pilots Association, said there were several reasons why pilots failed to spot approaching aircraft: distraction from  conversation or other activity in the cockpit; talking on the radio; a view obstructed by a windshield post or even the co-pilot's head.</p>
        <p>In the investigation, he said, the National Transportation Safety Board will use the headings, altitudes, speed and other information about both aircraft, even the exact eye level of the pilot and the height of the co-pilot's head, to find out exactly where the two planes would have appeared in each other's windshields. Neither pilot was in radio communication with an air traffic controller or an airport tower before the crash, and neither pilot made a distress call, Mr. Black said.</p>
        <p>The Navajo had been airborne only about six minutes, he said. It had taken off from the Trenton-Mercer Airport at 7:45 a.m. after making a stop to pick up other passengers, Mr. Black said. The flight originated at the Naval Air Engineering Center at Lakehurst, N.J.</p>
        <p>The Seminole was on an instructional flight out of Northeast Philadelphia Airport, about 15 miles west of the housing development, which is known as Steeplechase. Mr. Black said the investigation had not yet learned the Seminole's precise takeoff time. The training flight was in a federally designated practice area for student pilots.</p>
        <p>Initially, Mr. Black said, the Navajo's pilot had planned to fly directly from Lakehurst to the Patuxent River Naval Air Station in Maryland. But shortly before or just after the plane left Lakehurst, the pilot radioed controllers that he was heading to Trenton-Mercer to pick up more passengers, Mr. Black said.</p>
        <p>Officials at Lakehurst said the pilot switched plans because he had learned that two passengers had driven to Trenton-Mercer Airport, which was closer to their homes. Originally, Mr. Black said, the Navajo's pilot had filed a flight plan to fly to Patuxent under instrument flight rules. That would have required air traffic controllers in the area to watch radar scopes for data on the Navajo's flight and to provide the pilot with periodic flight advisories. Such advisories would have included a controller's warning that the Seminole was very near.</p>
        <p>When the Navajo's pilot abandoned his original direct flight, he began operating under the visual flight rules, without the supervision of an air traffic controller, Mr. Black said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
