<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Russians Say Anti-Mine Group Aids Rebels</title>
    <meta content="Y11RUS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/11/world/11RUSS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221677"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bail</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Egypt</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sachs, Susan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ibrahim, Saad Eddin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Egypt</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Egypt</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000811T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506EEDF143FF932A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="832" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Russians Say Anti-Mine Group Aids Rebels</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICK E. TYLER</byline>
      <dateline>MOSCOW, Aug. 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Saad Eddin Ibrahim, Egyptian human rights activist who has been under investigation, is released on bail after being held in prison for 45 days without being charged; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With Russian casualties mounting from land mine attacks in Chechnya, the Federal Security Service today accused a London-based mine-clearing organization of providing military training and assistance to rebel forces still engaged in attacks and ambushes against Russian security forces.</p>
        <p>Guy Willoughby, the president of the organization, Halo Trust, which is financed in part by the United States and the trust of Diana, the late Princess of Wales, acknowledged tonight that some of the 100 or more Chechens his organization trained between 1997 and 1999 might have ''joined the fighters'' and transferred their skills to rebel formations laying mines and staging ambushes against Russian troops.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With Russian casualties mounting from land mine attacks in Chechnya, the Federal Security Service today accused a London-based mine-clearing organization of providing military training and assistance to rebel forces still engaged in attacks and ambushes against Russian security forces.</p>
        <p>Guy Willoughby, the president of the organization, Halo Trust, which is financed in part by the United States and the trust of Diana, the late Princess of Wales, acknowledged tonight that some of the 100 or more Chechens his organization trained between 1997 and 1999 might have ''joined the fighters'' and transferred their skills to rebel formations laying mines and staging ambushes against Russian troops.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Willoughby, who spoke by telephone from Scotland, denied that his organization of former military officers who have risked their lives to clear mines and to train others to do the same in places like Angola, Kosovo and Cambodia has strayed beyond its mandate to locate and clear more than 270 minefields in Chechnya left over from the 1994-96 war. Those mines and cluster bombs, he said, many of them dropped from Russian helicopters on schools and other civilian targets, represented a serious risk to kill and maim Chechen civilians.</p>
        <p>''We were doing what we do in every other country,'' Mr. Willoughby said. ''If people want to state that mine-clearers around the world are potential terrorists, they'll have a hell of a job convincing anyone of that.''</p>
        <p>The organization's $20 million budget receives about $3 million in support from the State Department, he said. The memorial fund of Diana, who took a special interest in the issue, contributed more than $375,000 to the group last year, according to published reports.</p>
        <p>A statement issued today by the Federal Security Service, the domestic intelligence agency, said it had ''reliable information on training of specialists in mines and explosions for the armed formations of international terrorists fighting on the territory of the Russian republic.'' It said ''one of the structures covertly carrying out such activities'' was Halo Trust, a nongovernmental organization.</p>
        <p>The statement from the agency also charged that Halo Trust officials had collected intelligence on Russian tactics, weapons and munitions being used in the war zone and passed this information back to their headquarters. It said the group also ''carried out full-scale topographic surveillance of all the territory of the Chechen Republic fixing the Chechen villages to the NATO system of coordinates.''</p>
        <p>''Halo Trust smuggled special equipment, communication facilities and combat equipment for the illegal militants,'' the statement said, adding that one commander of the Halo Trust contingent, Matthew Middlemis, was a ''career military intelligence officer.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Willoughby characterized those allegations as ''completely absurd'' and ''rubbish.''</p>
        <p>He said Halo Trust entered Chechnya openly in 1997, after the first Chechen war ended and before the current conflict began. Its teams mapped 276 minefields in the devastated republic and then shared its report with the Russian military mission based at Grozny airport in Chechnya.</p>
        <p>To map the minefields, Mr. Willoughby said, the Halo Trust teams conducted topographical surveys using equipment that measured standard latitude and longitude measurements. During this period, he said, the organization worked under the sponsorship of the legitimately elected Chechen administration of President Aslan Maskhadov.</p>
        <p>Halo Trust ceased its mine-clearing operations in Chechnya last fall after four of its Chechen mine-clearers were killed in a Russian rocket-artillery barrage on the town of Stari Achkhoi, where Halo Trust was engaged in clearing mines that had been dropped on the town's primary school by Russian forces in 1995.</p>
        <p>''That's when we stopped de-mining and the de-miners all went home and we switched our work to humanitarian medical programs,'' Mr. Willoughby said. ''I can't say that one of them did not join the fighters -- they may have -- but as far as we were concerned, they were civilians.''</p>
        <p>There was no explanation for the timing of today's charges by the Federal Security Service, many months after Halo Trust abandoned its mine-clearing operation in Chechnya. The service made one of its spokesmen available for interviews on Russia's state television news channels tonight, which gave prominent display to the charges. One television report showed video captured from Chechen rebels of a man identified as a Halo Trust trainer examining a Russian bomb in a field.</p>
        <p>Since late spring, the Chechen rebels have adopted new tactics, relying more extensively on mine warfare, Russian military commanders have warned. This summer, military dispatches from Chechnya have reported almost daily incidents in which Russian armored personnel carriers and other troop transports and vehicles struck mines. As many as 14 Russian servicemen were wounded in mine blasts on Aug. 1 and 2, and 18 mines were defused by federal troops.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
