<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>9 Subway Agents Made Cash On Spent Cards, Police Say</title>
    <meta content="11CLER$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221732"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Subways</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Murphy, Dean E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Subways</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000811T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02EFDB143FF932A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="802" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>9 Subway Agents Made Cash On Spent Cards, Police Say</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DEAN E. MURPHY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Murphy, Dean E</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>NYC police arrest 9 subway ticket booth agents on charges of stealing $98,678 by selling new MetroCards containing falsified fares they had transferred from discarded cards; police say that more arrests are pending (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With a certain twist of the wrist and some underhanded salesmanship, it is possible to make a lot of money from discarded MetroCards, the reusable electronic tickets that have pushed the New York City subway token into near-obsolescence.</p>
        <p>The city's transit agency had wanted to keep that a closely guarded secret for the better part of the six years the cards have been in existence. It seems a MetroCard with no remaining value can be tampered with to obtain an additional $1.50 fare. With some knowledge of computers, moreover, it is possible for a transit employee to transfer the falsified $1.50 value to a new card.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With a certain twist of the wrist and some underhanded salesmanship, it is possible to make a lot of money from discarded MetroCards, the reusable electronic tickets that have pushed the New York City subway token into near-obsolescence.</p>
        <p>The city's transit agency had wanted to keep that a closely guarded secret for the better part of the six years the cards have been in existence. It seems a MetroCard with no remaining value can be tampered with to obtain an additional $1.50 fare. With some knowledge of computers, moreover, it is possible for a transit employee to transfer the falsified $1.50 value to a new card.</p>
        <p>''We are not going to give anybody a handbook on how to beat the system, but there is a way to bend the card that tricks the system into thinking there is one ride left,'' said Albert W. O'Leary, a spokesman for New York City Transit, the Metropolitan Transportation Authority unit that runs city subways and buses. The secret has been an open one among many employees of the transit agency, but for nine of them working in Manhattan, the idea of exploiting it apparently was too tempting to resist.</p>
        <p>Nine ticket booth agents were charged yesterday with stealing  $98,678 by selling new MetroCards containing falsified fares they had transferred from discarded cards. Police said more arrests, involving a half-dozen or so ticket agents in other boroughs, were expected.</p>
        <p>''They are bending and manipulating the MetroCards,'' Anne Milgram, an assistant district attorney, said at  the arraignment of four agents in  State Supreme Court in Manhattan. All nine agents pleaded not guilty.</p>
        <p>The employees, who worked independently of one another, collected  $1,470 to $34,947 each over the last seven months, prosecutors said. Some of the money apparently went to runners who were hired to collect thousands of otherwise worthless fare cards tossed on the ground or in garbage cans. Most of the accused employees have worked for the transit agency for more than five years.</p>
        <p>''The message here to anybody who is ever tempted is you will be caught and you will pay a price,'' Mr. O'Leary said in a telephone conversation from the transit agency's headquarters. ''We watched them walk eight of these station agents in handcuffs out of this building yesterday to central booking.''</p>
        <p>Since they first went on sale at two subway stations in Manhattan on Jan. 4, 1994, MetroCards have been a sensation with riders. The transit agency sold 600 of them the first day. Now, about 85 percent of the seven million daily subway and bus riders  use the cards instead of cash or tokens. The tokens have become such an anachronism that the transit agency has changed the name of its 3,361 ticket handlers from token booth clerks to station agents.</p>
        <p>But authorities acknowledge that the potential for abuse is a bit nerve-racking. So far this year, 748 people have been arrested for selling illegal rides, known by police as a swipe, often by means of a carefully bent no-value MetroCard.</p>
        <p>Even so, losses from fare beating are down sharply since the cards were introduced. Last year, the transit agency lost $13 million to fare theft, compared with more than $70 million a year in the late 1980's, according to the agency. The agency collects $2 billion annually in fares.</p>
        <p>Mr. O'Leary said that the machines that read fare cards could be altered to make it impossible to cheat the system but that the transit agency had resisted such a change because it would also cause the machine to mistakenly reject more legitimate cards.</p>
        <p>Police Sgt. Jack Cassidy, who heads the transit bureau's special investigations unit, said the scheme involving the nine station agents had its origins in a police crackdown in the last few years on so-called swipers, the people who illegally sell individual rides to boarding passengers.</p>
        <p>When it became increasingly difficult to evade police, the swipers began colluding with station agents, who transferred the falsified fares to new MetroCards and sold them over the counter.</p>
        <p>The station agents charged with grand larceny yesterday by the Manhattan district attorney are Anthony Waller, 29, of Brooklyn; Robert Moody, 35, of Manhattan; Bindu Aranakkal, 26, of Queens; Kim Melville, 34, of the Bronx; Floyd London, 39, of Brooklyn; Dhaniram Gopal, 45, of Queens; Rodney C. Ashby, 35, of the Bronx; Gary L. Campbell, 35, of Manhattan; and Eugene H. Stovall, 36, of the Bronx.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
