<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fulfilling the Job Description: Thin, Catty and Self-Obsessed</title>
    <meta content="11INTE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221609"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Swain, Dominique</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lange, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holden, Stephen</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Intern (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews/By Stephen Holden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000811T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E0DD173FF932A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="797" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fulfilling the Job Description: Thin, Catty and Self-Obsessed</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN HOLDEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Holden, Stephen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Stephen Holden reviews movie Intern, directed by Michael Lange and starring Dominique Swain; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''Intern'' takes such relentless glee in skewering the pretensions of the fashion industry that it's difficult to choose the nastiest bit in a movie crammed with mean-spirited caricatures and catty bons mots. My favorite happens to be the moment when Jocelyn Bennett (Dominique Swain), a sleek young intern at Skirt magazine, takes a cup of iced cappuccino to Antoinette De la Paix (Anna Thompson), a grim, bony-faced editor.</p>
        <p>After taking one sip, Antoinette realizes something is terribly wrong, and Jocelyn meekly confesses that the coffee shop ran out of skim milk and she had to make do with low-fat (2 percent) milk. Turning ashen, Antoinette begins shaking with rage and screams, ''Oh, God!'' Grabbing a handy wastebasket she promptly vomits.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''Intern'' takes such relentless glee in skewering the pretensions of the fashion industry that it's difficult to choose the nastiest bit in a movie crammed with mean-spirited caricatures and catty bons mots. My favorite happens to be the moment when Jocelyn Bennett (Dominique Swain), a sleek young intern at Skirt magazine, takes a cup of iced cappuccino to Antoinette De la Paix (Anna Thompson), a grim, bony-faced editor.</p>
        <p>After taking one sip, Antoinette realizes something is terribly wrong, and Jocelyn meekly confesses that the coffee shop ran out of skim milk and she had to make do with low-fat (2 percent) milk. Turning ashen, Antoinette begins shaking with rage and screams, ''Oh, God!'' Grabbing a handy wastebasket she promptly vomits.</p>
        <p>One suspects that bulimia is epidemic in this wasp's nest of gaunt, overdressed women and their conniving gay male colleagues, of which Sebastian Niederfarb (Billy Porter) is a typical example. Affecting an air of the grand inquisitor, Sebastian imperiously  orders Jocelyn to ''send this fax to Galliano's buttonist's boyfriend's stylist in Monaco,'' as if he were directing a secret bombing mission over the Middle East. Paranoia is rampant at Skirt because someone has been faxing all the magazine's editorial ideas to its archrival, Vogue.</p>
        <p>As for the viability of those ideas, you be the judge. At Skirt, the editors get worked  up over concepts like ''wheelchair chic'' and the fantasy that next year every woman in America will be wearing a helmet.</p>
        <p>With acidic dialogue by the screenwriters Jill Kopelman and Caroline Doyle, both of whom served time at fashion magazines (and who have claimed in interviews that every nutty tidbit is based on an overheard conversation), ''Intern'' has the ingredients of a nifty satire. But the movie's technical aspects are so shoddy that it often looks and sounds like a crudely edited home movie. Much of the acting is amateurish, and the sound is so poor that some of the dialogue is unintelligible.</p>
        <p>The story follows the ascent of poor, persecuted Jocelyn from despised intern to  revered staff member, as she plays sleuth to uncover the traitor in the magazine's ranks.  Ms. Swain, who made such a great screen Lolita, has matured into a bland, cool cookie  who fails to make her character sympathetic or even engaging.</p>
        <p>While plotting her climb, Jocelyn also makes romantic headway with the magazine's art director and ''token heterosexual male,'' Paul Rochester (Ben Pullen), a suave young Englishmen who is described as being ''as straight as a Marc Jacobs pleat'' and is rumored to be related to Prince Charles. Before befriending Jocelyn, Paul allows himself to be the plaything of Resin (Leilani Bishop), the rudest and most selfish and narcissistic cover girl ever to sulk down a runaway.</p>
        <p>'Intern'' is ultimately as sycophantic as it is needling. Every few minutes the movie  stops dead in its tracks for useless cameo appearances by the likes of Gwyneth Paltrow, Diane von Furstenberg and Tommy Hilfiger, among many others. Joan Rivers also appears as a Skirt editor and fashion fanatic who rants on woodenly about living for the day when terms like ''leisure suit'' and ''housedress'' are stricken from the language.</p>
        <p>The biggest mystery about ''Intern'' is how a film about people who are obsessed  with appearances could wind up looking so hopelessly drab and tacky.</p>
        <p>INTERN</p>
        <p>Directed by Michael Lange; written by Caroline Doyle and Jill Kopelman; director of photography, Rodney Charters; edited by Anita Brandt-Burgoyne; music by Jimmy Harry; production designer, Jody Asnes; produced by Galt Neiderhoffer, Etchie Stroh and Daniela Soto-Taplin; released by Moonstone Entertainment. At  the Screening Room, 54 Varick Street, at Laight Street, TriBeCa. Running time: 90 minutes. This film is not rated.</p>
        <p>WITH: Dominique Swain (Jocelyn Bennett), Ben Pullen (Paul Rochester), Peggy Lipton (Roxanne Rochet), Joan Rivers (Dolly Bellows), David Deblinger (Richard Sinn), Dwight Ewell (Gustave), Billy Porter (Sebastian Niederfarb), Leilani Bishop (Resin), Anna Thompson (Antoinette De la Paix) and Paulina Porizkova (Chi Chi Chemise), and cameos by Kevin Aucoin, John Bartlett, Philip Bloch, Kenneth Cole, Simon Doonan, Frederic Fekkai, Donna Hanover, Tommy Hilfiger, Gwyneth Paltrow, Cynthia Rowley, Elizabeth Saltzman, Richard Sinnott, Andre Leon Talley and Diane von Furstenberg as themselves.</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
