<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Behind the Enduring Cliches of Asia and the West</title>
    <meta content="11BOOK$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="43" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221602"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Buruma, Ian</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bernstein, Richard</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Missionary and the Libertine, The (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000811T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907E3DE173FF932A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1097" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Behind the Enduring Cliches of Asia and the West</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD BERNSTEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bernstein, Richard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Richard Bernstein reviews book The Missionary and the Libertine: Love and War in East and West by Ian Buruma; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE MISSIONARY AND THE LIBERTINE</p>
        <p>Love and War in East and West</p>
        <p>By Ian Buruma</p>
        <p>323 pages. Random House. $25.95.</p>
        <p>For years, now, Ian Buruma, the British journalist, has been writing some of the most trenchant and sophisticated commentary around on that very large portion of the cultural-political world known as Asia. In his new book, ''The Missionary and the Libertine,'' he reproduces essays that have appeared elsewhere -- most often in The New York Review of Books -- and adds a thematic introduction to explain his intriguing title.</p>
        <p>''There has been a sensual, even erotic, element in encounters -- imaginary or real -- between East and West since the ancient Greeks,''  Mr. Buruma writes, setting out the libertine aspect of his theme. This is complicated, but westerners have often dreamed of Asia as a zone of hedonism, he says, of guiltless liberation from the ''cold, pinched and dreary climate of the Christian, especially Protestant, West'' -- in other words, from the missionaries.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE MISSIONARY AND THE LIBERTINE</p>
        <p>Love and War in East and West</p>
        <p>By Ian Buruma</p>
        <p>323 pages. Random House. $25.95.</p>
        <p>For years, now, Ian Buruma, the British journalist, has been writing some of the most trenchant and sophisticated commentary around on that very large portion of the cultural-political world known as Asia. In his new book, ''The Missionary and the Libertine,'' he reproduces essays that have appeared elsewhere -- most often in The New York Review of Books -- and adds a thematic introduction to explain his intriguing title.</p>
        <p>''There has been a sensual, even erotic, element in encounters -- imaginary or real -- between East and West since the ancient Greeks,''  Mr. Buruma writes, setting out the libertine aspect of his theme. This is complicated, but westerners have often dreamed of Asia as a zone of hedonism, he says, of guiltless liberation from the ''cold, pinched and dreary climate of the Christian, especially Protestant, West'' -- in other words, from the missionaries.</p>
        <p>Asia, at times, he writes further, has bought into these contrasting images -- the West as the masculine master of discipline, the East as supine and passive -- with interestingly paradoxical results. Authoritarian Asian governments like Singapore's or China's, criticized for human rights abuses, have replied that they embody ''Asian values'' and therefore repudiate the moral laxness that comes with too much individual freedom. Mr. Buruma argues that ''Asian values'' are readaptations of the missionary idea, that Asia was complacent and soft while the West represented hard work and moral propriety.</p>
        <p>''The missionaries, then, have taken post in Kuala Lumpur, and the whores of Babylon have moved to London and New York,'' Mr. Buruma writes.</p>
        <p>The essays that he has included in this collection bear in one way or another on this theme, though often rather loosely, and that fact illustrates both the virtues and the shortcomings of this new book. As always, Mr. Buruma is a pleasure to read. He displays a remarkable breadth and he writes with a kind of unassuming authority about matters that he has thought deeply about. One essay, wittily entitled ''Samurai of Swat,'' delves into Japanese baseball and what it tells us of the Japanese self-conception: a great deal as it turns out. This essay is one of the most directly relevant to the sexualized images of Mr. Buruma's main theme, beginning with the shock that rocked Japan in 1964 when a huge Dutchman named Anton Geesink beat the Japanese judo champion for the gold medal at the Tokyo Olympics.</p>
        <p>''Judo was not just a national sport,'' Mr. Baruma writes,''it symbolized the Japanese way -- spiritual, disciplined, infinitely subtle; a way in which crude Western brawn would inevitably lose to superior Oriental spirit. And here, in Tokyo, a big, blond foreigner had humiliated Japan in front of the entire world. It was as though the ancestral Sun Goddess had been raped in public by a gang of alien demons.''</p>
        <p>A book of essays is almost by definition thematically diffuse, and not all of Mr. Buruma's essays are focused clearly to a central concept, much less advance one. Some of the selections, informed and perceptive as they are, are dated: Mr. Buruma's essay on the fallen Pakistani leader Benazir Bhutto, written before she fell, for example. They illustrate the limitations inherent in putting previously published work under a single cover, rather than developing ideas into a book from scratch. (Actually, Mr. Buruma has written several books from scratch, including ''Anglomania: A European Love Affair'' and ''God's Dust: A Modern Asian Journey.'') Still, the essays are remarkably varied and of consistent high quality, and demonstrate that, talent aside, it's useful when reflecting on the world to do so from a solid base of knowledge.</p>
        <p>Among Mr. Buruma's topics are several Indian figures, or Westerners who were captivated by India. He writes brilliantly about the filmmaker Satyajit Ray and the writers  Nirad C. Chaudhuri and V. S. Naipaul. But perhaps the most absorbing of his India essays is one on the poignant and bitter love affair between the Romanian mythologist Mircea Eliade and the Indian writer Maitreyi Devi. This chapter, like ''Samurai of Swat,'' relates closely to the erotic history of East and West, having at its core a near cliche: ''Young, romantic Westerner falls in love with mysterious Oriental girl and, through her, with the mysterous Orient, only to bang his head on the prison wall of exclusive Oriental customs.''</p>
        <p>But as Mr. Buruma teases out the Rashomonesque nature of the story -- the love affair was seen very differently by the parties to it -- he evokes a rich panorama of East and West, and of the conflict between the rationalism that is supposedly Western and the fascination for the irrational that is supposedly of the East.</p>
        <p>Japan is the other principal subject for Mr. Buruma, and he takes several different bearings on that country, treating topics as varied as sadomasochism among early 20th-century writers, the sexual fantasies of the filmmaker Nagisa Oshima and Michael Crichton's anti-Japanese novel ''Rising Sun'' (which Mr. Buruma compares to German works of the 1930's showing the supposed menace of the Jews).</p>
        <p>He also includes a marvelously pithy, probing review of a novel by the Japanese writer Banana Yoshimoto, who, when she was still in her 20's, had sold six million copies of her first two novels. He links that astonishing commercial success to another literary-commercial phenomenon in Japan, the fascination with a kind of innocent androgyny among teenage girls, finding that both are related to the sense among the Japanese that once they have passed a certain age, the options for women become seriously limited.</p>
        <p>''Since family duties are (or at any rate were) particularly onerous in Japan and sex roles so rigidly defined,'' he writes, ''it is no wonder that young girls so often long to stop time and to retreat into a fantasy world of purity, androgyny and prepubescence.''</p>
        <p>That sentence perfectly illustrates Mr. Buruma's knack for holding some cultural artifact up to the light and perceiving something otherwise obscure, erotic and plausible glimmering within it.</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
