<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>It's a Small World</title>
    <meta content="29FRANKT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="37" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242584"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Frank, Thomas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zachary, G Pascal</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Global Me, The: New Cosmopolitans and the Competitive Edge (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001029T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE0D9123EF93AA15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1088" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>It's a Small World</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Thomas Frank</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Frank, Thomas</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Thomas Frank reviews book The Global Me: New Cosmopolitans and the Competitive Edge: Picking Globalism's Winners and Losers by G Pascal Zachary (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE GLOBAL ME</p>
        <p>New Cosmopolitans and the Competitive Edge:  Picking Globalism's Winners and Losers.</p>
        <p>By G. Pascal Zachary.</p>
        <p>313 pp. New York: PublicAffairs. $26.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE GLOBAL ME</p>
        <p>New Cosmopolitans and the Competitive Edge:  Picking Globalism's Winners and Losers.</p>
        <p>By G. Pascal Zachary.</p>
        <p>313 pp. New York: PublicAffairs. $26.</p>
        <p>Of the many forms of ecstatic millennialism that accompanied the dawn of the new economy, few have proved more alluring or durable than the belief that market economies have some special relationship with the downtrodden of the earth. The market's dynamic inclusiveness is hailed in op-ed defenses of the World Trade Organization, hymned in those gorgeous-mosaic Cisco commercials, saluted by berguru Tom Peters in one of his sorties against the all-white managerial staffs of the past.</p>
        <p>The logic behind this particular bit of corporate idealism goes like this: ethnic diversity gives rise in some reliable way to ''creativity,'' therefore ethnically diverse companies will outperform ethnically uniform companies. Taken a little farther, the idea leads to a whole range of liberationist claims: markets militate against national boundaries; markets smash racism; markets want us to be free to wander and to sell our labor to whomever we choose.</p>
        <p>Greater diversity in the workplace is obviously a welcome development. At the same time, the instances of business rewarding racism or profiting from racism -- from slavery and colonialism to redlining and ghetto pricing -- are so plentiful and familiar that the idea of markets as an inexorable antiracist force has never really been taken seriously by the public.</p>
        <p>Stepping forward to defend this crucial free-market faith, G. Pascal Zachary, a senior writer at The Wall Street Journal, announces in ''The Global Me'' that he has discovered ''a new gold standard for human development'': ''Hybridity,'' a sort of ultradiversity, is the factor determining the fates of industrialized nations, the thing that makes these countries ''vital or stagnant, winners or losers.'' The model citizen of this new order is a figure he calls ''the mongrel'' and to whom he attributes all manner of virtues: ''mongrels are heroic''; they are ''the source of innovation, daring and toleration''; they are ''more creative'' than others, they have ''more perspective,'' they ''are more willing to rebel against tradition,'' and they feel a kinship with ''the shunned, the neglected, the overlooked, the underdog.''</p>
        <p>As it turns out, the natural home of this ultracreative, mixed-race rebel is the multinational corporation. Always looking for better ways of doing things, these giant concerns have become ''hybrid hothouses,'' ''champions of diversity.'' Zachary reels off example after example of prominent non-WASP executives and recounts scenes in which white-collar people from many different countries clash and cooperate for the greater good of profit. The heroism of the mongrel underdog, ironically, also helps affirm the power of the world's most powerful country. As the United States is the only land where such ''hybridity'' is found in great abundance, it has triumphed naturally over countries like Japan and Germany that have failed to fully embrace the ''new gold standard.'' Rather than being a source of shame, race relations emerge here as America's single greatest virtue, the rationale for our domination of the world. As in much of the euphoric literature on the new economy, the American way is also said to be the inevitable way, with other nations warned to ''Mongrelize or Die!''</p>
        <p>Whatever one may think of such arguments, ''The Global Me'' is a book that deserves to be taken seriously. While management gurus rely on simple assertion to make their claims about corporate fondness for the little guy, Zachary approaches the subject with an enormous amount of research and firsthand reporting. He shows an impressive familiarity with academic postcolonial studies. He visits with members of forgotten ethnic groups in the former Soviet Union. He watches television with people in deepest Borneo. And the book has lofty implications, tacitly claiming for the new market world all of the glory and the righteousness associated with multiculturalism. The cosmopolitan corporation here becomes the rightful heir of the civil rights movement, the heir of the fight against imperialism, the final flower of the human search for justice.</p>
        <p>But in order to make the picture turn out so nicely Zachary must make some rather curious moves. While it is refreshing to see a business journalist take an interest in the big theorists of postcolonial studies, the pro-market, pro-corporate, pro-American conclusions that Zachary draws from their work is perverse in the extreme. To put it mildly, postcolonial studies -- a field concerned with the subjugation of third-world peoples by the West -- does not generally regard capitalism as a benign force. Even more telling is Zachary's failure to discuss frankly the subject of social class, a topic that is omnipresent in most postcolonial studies. Certainly the first and most obvious way in which markets shape human identity is by dividing us into classes: management and labor, bosses and bossed. But while Zachary distinguishes between ''rich nations'' and ''poor nations'' and includes all sorts of anecdotes about plucky third-world migrants, his book is written almost exclusively from the perspective of management. Working-class people, even a Central American labor leader whose story Zachary tells, are described as bearers of this or that national consciousness, not a class-based one. Only ethnic differences go to make up ''creativity''; other sorts of ''divergent thinking'' need not apply. So while Chineseness bounces off Irishness to yield dot-com magic, working classness evidently has no contribution to make at all.</p>
        <p>As in most such books, though, class eventually finds its way back in. When discussing the working class of our own country, for example, Zachary sometimes falls back on the old ''hard hat'' stereotype: Whether black or white, workers are said to be cranky, backward doubters of management's newfound cosmopolitanism. And their rebellions are to be managed, not celebrated. Zachary even recounts a cautionary tale about a ''monocultural'' work force that got upset about something and walked out. Their employers then hired a replacement work force with a ''diversity of views,'' which prevented them from getting together enough to act in such a disruptive manner.</p>
        <p>Zachary has a lively style, and the appeal of his ideas to the market's true believers should be obvious in the context of recent controversies over free trade and the World Trade Organization. But is a maquiladora really an expression of compassion for the people who work in it? Or is all this corporate multiculturalism just an effort to pull a skein of rainbow legitimacy over a typically brutal episode of financial history?</p>
        <p>Thomas Frank is author of ''One Market Under God'' and editor of The Baffler.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Thomas Frank is author of ''One Market Under God'' and editor of The Baffler.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
