<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Peony: A Regal Tree That's Really a Shrub</title>
    <meta content="CNGARDEN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242739"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="IN THE GARDEN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GARDENS AND GARDENING</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001029T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E6D71031F93AA15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="872" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Peony: A Regal Tree That's Really a Shrub</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOAN LEE FAUST</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE first time I saw a tree peony, I was overwhelmed, thunderstruck, just plain awed. The flowers were pure magnificence, easily a foot across. They looked like polished satin in the most vivid shade of red. The plants themselves assumed an almost regal position with handsome foliage as the flowers' foil.</p>
        <p>That encounter took place many years ago, but since that time I have been one of this flower's biggest fans. Not every garden and not every gardener has been successful in growing these plants. They are not all that difficult, but this is a peony that needs and deserves just the right situation to thrive. I know well, I tried and failed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE first time I saw a tree peony, I was overwhelmed, thunderstruck, just plain awed. The flowers were pure magnificence, easily a foot across. They looked like polished satin in the most vivid shade of red. The plants themselves assumed an almost regal position with handsome foliage as the flowers' foil.</p>
        <p>That encounter took place many years ago, but since that time I have been one of this flower's biggest fans. Not every garden and not every gardener has been successful in growing these plants. They are not all that difficult, but this is a peony that needs and deserves just the right situation to thrive. I know well, I tried and failed.</p>
        <p>To begin with a tree peony is not truly a tree. It is more a shrub peony. Its stems are woody and botanically it is derived from the species, Paeonia suffruticosa, which means ''somewhat like a shrub.''</p>
        <p>Further, this particular peony is a native of the mountainous regions of China, which indicates its culture should be somewhat shady (partial shade), well-drained soil and, of course, as with all peonies, fertilizer used generously because peonies are hungry plants.</p>
        <p>The tree peony is quite hardy in this region. However, in regions where the winters are severe and there is deep soil freezing, a protective mulch may be helpful, placed on the plants in late fall. The plants are long lived so they deserve a position of prominence in a well-designed garden. The tree peonies can be placed either as single specimen features, as a shrub might be, or they can be incorporated to show off in a handsome border. As with any peonies, fall planting is important because the plants need the long late fall season to settle down and start to make root growth. For this reason, nurseries usually do not list peonies in their spring catalogs.</p>
        <p>The tree peony flowers bloom a bit earlier than those of the herbaceous peony hybrids, although with the plethora of hybrids in all forms available these days it is hard to be too definite about when they bloom.</p>
        <p>As to the peony's long life, there is proof in the pudding. In the bible of peony culture, ''The Peonies'' by John C. Wister, there is a picture of Dr. Wister standing by a magnificent tree peony in the now well-known Tyler Arboretum in Lima, Pa. The tree peony is said to be a century old and to have well over a hundred flowers every spring.</p>
        <p>Tree peonies have a fascinating history that dates back to the Tang Dynasty (618-906). The flower was known then as the King of Flowers and its culture was exclusive to the leading families of the day. The flower became a motif in art, fabrics and interior design.</p>
        <p>Not until the sixth or seventh centuries did the tree peony reach Japan. It is said to have been introduced there by Buddist monks. Although the Chinese revered the tree peony, it was the Japanese hybridists who brought the flower to perfection and strengthened stems through hybridization.</p>
        <p>The magnificent flower finally reached European gardens. For a brief time there was a tree peony mania in France, similar to the tulipmania in the Netherlands, as the plants were excruciatingly expensive to buy at first. Then the market settled down.</p>
        <p>Finally in 1846 the noted plant explorer, Robert Fortune, who traveled to China at least four times for the Royal Horticulture Society, made a saner culture of the tree peony possible.</p>
        <p>Robert Fortune brought back to England 25 of the finest tree peonies. This magnificent collection is attributed to the modern hybrids that exist today. Many of them are grafted plants using the rootstock of herbaceous peonies. For this reason, nurserymen now recommend that tree peonies should be planted deeply to insure good root development.</p>
        <p>By contrast, planting of herbaceous peonies is entirely different. These peonies must be planted just under the surface of the soil. This can be as shallow as one to two inches deep. Failure to heed this important rule is probably the main reason for bloom failure on the herbaceous peonies. But the timing of planting for both kinds remains the same, late fall.</p>
        <p>Credit for much of the successful work with the early tree peony hybrids goes to A. P. Saunders who was a professor at Hamilton College. His devotion to the peony and its beauty led to the development of many superb hybrids. Since that time, many excellent plants have been made available. Their flower color range is wide and handsome. The best way to choose a particular variety is to observe them in bloom, study catalogs or ask professionals who know them.</p>
        <p>Tree peonies are not carried by many nurseries, since they have become somewhat a specialty and are still in the expensive category. However Song Sparrow Perennial Farm (formerly Klehm Nursery), 13101 East Rye Road, Avalon, Wis. 53505 (608-883-2221) lists an extensive selection of these plants in their free catalog.</p>
        <p>IN THE GARDEN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
