<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Music, Please, but Not in a Ghetto</title>
    <meta content="29TONY" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/29/arts/29TONY.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242647"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tommasini, Anthony</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001029T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE3DB1531F93AA15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="984" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Music, Please, but Not in a Ghetto</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY TOMMASINI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tommasini, Anthony</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anthony Tommasini column holds new music performances should not be relegated to lower rungs of concert halls and should not be segregated from older, classical works; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>RECENTLY, while speaking to students in the ''Writing About Music'' class at the Manhattan School of Music, I offered some thoughts on the role critics could play in encouraging performances of new music. After emphasizing the positive, I got into my standard rap about the dismaying timidity of programming by many major American orchestras and ensembles.</p>
        <p>It's an abrogation of responsibility toward the future of the art form for music directors of symphony orchestras to give only scant performances of new works, I said. Besides, how could thinking musicians not be naturally curious about the music of living composers? It would be quite odd for a repertory theater company or a dance troupe to present only works by creators long dead. But the concert hall is in danger of becoming a museum.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>RECENTLY, while speaking to students in the ''Writing About Music'' class at the Manhattan School of Music, I offered some thoughts on the role critics could play in encouraging performances of new music. After emphasizing the positive, I got into my standard rap about the dismaying timidity of programming by many major American orchestras and ensembles.</p>
        <p>It's an abrogation of responsibility toward the future of the art form for music directors of symphony orchestras to give only scant performances of new works, I said. Besides, how could thinking musicians not be naturally curious about the music of living composers? It would be quite odd for a repertory theater company or a dance troupe to present only works by creators long dead. But the concert hall is in danger of becoming a museum.</p>
        <p>One student, a clarinetist from Ireland, challenged me. She asked why orchestras shouldn't play programs of standard works if those are what their audiences want to hear? Isn't it possible that the orchestra is a relic of the 19th century and composers are no longer interested? Besides, she added, there are special places for new music. She described some concerts of new music by Pierre Boulez's Ensemble Intercontempo rain that she attended in Paris. The concerts were great, and the hall was always packed. With all that going on, why shouldn't the mainstream orchestras in Paris, and elsewhere, be allowed to stick to the standard repertory?</p>
        <p>The problem, I answered, is that new music gets relegated to a new-music ghetto, treated like some specialized subcategory of the classical-music repertory. True, there are now a few centuries of important repertory works that musicians must maintain. But the best way for audiences to experience older works freshly is to hear them along with new or recent ones. When mixed programs are interestingly put together, a wonderful reciprocity can occur between the old and the new: you hear the sense of innovation in the old works and the sense of history in the new works.</p>
        <p>I'm not sure that my answer satisfied the student. But her question stayed with me the next night during a concert at the Miller Theater of Columbia University. The excellent Ensemble Sospeso, a contemporary-music group, devoted an entire program to the Dutch composer Louis Andriessen, whose cutting-edge works are steeped in jazz and rock as well the brainiest styles of contemporary composition.</p>
        <p>During his short tenure, George Steel, the director of the Miller Theater, has turned the place into a hotbed of contemporary music and proved adept at reaching new listeners. His success suggests that if the setting is right, the players are enthusiastic and the program is bracing, rock fans who listen to Radiohead and the Beastie Boys might also groove to works like Gyorgy Ligeti's mesmerizing Piano Etudes or Mr. Andriessen's giddy ''Hout'' (''Wood''), for amplified saxophone, marimba, guitar and piano.</p>
        <p>On the night of the Andriessen concert the hall was filled with young people, lots of them in jeans, lugging backpacks of books. Everyone seemed engaged by the music. Aspects of the concert that might have unsettled traditionalists -- the mix of electronic and acoustic instruments, the amplification of the audacious piece ''Disco,'' for piano and violin -- were accepted by these hip listeners as nothing unusual. More such events are coming up at the Miller Theater, including an enticing series called Piano Revolution and programs by ensembles like Scratchband, which plays works that obliterate stylistic divisions in contemporary music.</p>
        <p>So what's the problem? Only that, once again, some exciting new-music activities wind up segregated from the rest of classical music. The mainstream orchestras and chamber ensembles badly need the jolt of energy that the Miller's younger, open-minded patrons could provide. But it's unlikely that these newcomers will be drawn down Broadway to Lincoln Center, which must seem to them rarefied and stuffy.</p>
        <p>It's too bad; some lively contemporary works are being presented this season, especially by the Chamber Music Society of Lincoln Center. For years the society had an ambivalent relationship with new music. Among its players were heroes of contemporary music, like the cellist Fred Sherry, a former artistic director; but its subscribers tended to be highly traditional in their tastes. This year Mr. Sherry has organized a nine-concert festival of some 50 living New York composers, ranging from Milton Babbitt to Stephen Sondheim. Yet it might have been more beneficial (though surely more risky) to mix these works into the regular offerings and enliven the repertory for the whole season.</p>
        <p>Critics should keep urging major orchestras and ensembles to program contemporary music. Of course, no one wants to hear conservative musicians performing new works out of a weighty sense of obligation (though you can hear plenty of automatic-pilot performances of Brahms quintets and Mozart symphonies). And it's no fun to be at a mostly traditional orchestra program when the audience turns resentful during the one modern piece.</p>
        <p>But I've seen the opposite happen many times: people at the weekly symphony concert mutter among themselves as the conductor walks out to present a premiere; as the piece begins, you see listeners responding almost despite themselves; the music is strangely intriguing, colorful, jerky, kind of wild, never dull; the audience senses the alert involvement of the players; before long there are surprised smiles all over the hall.</p>
        <p>I have great admiration for what Mr. Steel is trying to do and for the adventurous patrons who are attracted to the Miller's concerts. I just wish that some of that excitement would spread around town. And I especially hope that the young clarinetist from the Manhattan School, who clearly loves contemporary music, will not accept the status quo at the symphony. We're counting on musicians like her to change things from within.</p>
        <p>MUSIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
