<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ideas &amp; Trends: The Car Is King; Mass Transit Riders Are Pawns</title>
    <meta content="29PURD$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/29/weekinreview/29PURD.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242934"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Buses</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Subways</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Los Angeles County (Calif)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Purdum, Todd S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/Los Angeles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Buses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Subways</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001029T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E7D81F31F93AA15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1031" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ideas &amp; Trends: The Car Is King; Mass Transit Riders Are Pawns</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TODD S. PURDUM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Purdum, Todd S</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Most of Los Angeles seemed to hardly notice recently ended monthlong bus and subway strike against county's sprawling Metropolitan Transportation Authority; more than 8 in 10 Los Angeles households have at least one car, and buses and subways serve only about 450,000 people a day, out of population of 5.9 million; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT lasted 32 days and left half a million people stranded without their usual means of transportation. Maids and nannies struggled to find new ways from East Los Angeles to Beverly Hills, office workers carpooled and were chronically late and the notoriously bad traffic on freeways and surface streets was, if anything, worse.</p>
        <p>Yet, somehow, most of Los Angeles hardly seemed to notice the monthlong bus and subway strike against the county's sprawling Metropolitan Transportation Authority that finally ended 10 days ago. For most of its duration, the strike rarely made the local television news. Politicians and union members faced little public pressure to reach a settlement. Only the intercession of a famous outside mediator, the Rev. Jesse Jackson, finally ended the walkout.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT lasted 32 days and left half a million people stranded without their usual means of transportation. Maids and nannies struggled to find new ways from East Los Angeles to Beverly Hills, office workers carpooled and were chronically late and the notoriously bad traffic on freeways and surface streets was, if anything, worse.</p>
        <p>Yet, somehow, most of Los Angeles hardly seemed to notice the monthlong bus and subway strike against the county's sprawling Metropolitan Transportation Authority that finally ended 10 days ago. For most of its duration, the strike rarely made the local television news. Politicians and union members faced little public pressure to reach a settlement. Only the intercession of a famous outside mediator, the Rev. Jesse Jackson, finally ended the walkout.</p>
        <p>After all, this is the place where you are your car. It's not unusual for commuters to drive 100 miles round trip each day, or 45 minutes to eat dinner with friends. More than 8 in 10 Los Angeles area households have at least one car, and even the poorest residents tend to know somebody who knows somebody who has one in which they can share a ride. In a county with a population of 9.4 million, buses and subways move about 450,000 people any given day; there are 5.9 million registered cars and trucks.</p>
        <p>But here's the paradox: greater Los Angeles grew up in the sprawling pattern the world knows today not because of the automobile but because of mass transit, the streetcars and rail lines of a century ago, that allowed a collection of interconnected communities and garden suburbs to flourish in contrast to the denser, traditional cities of the East and Midwest. The explosion of car culture only accelerated that trend -- as did the subsequent decline of mass transit.</p>
        <p>Now, with more freeways more crowded than ever and literally no room left to build many new ones, Los Angeles County (an area three-fifths the size of Connecticut) is more dependent than ever on mass transit for the survival of its service economy. Two-career middle-class couples can go off to work in no small measure because of an interconnected system (mostly bus lines) that deposits cheap and reliable household help near their doors each day.</p>
        <p>What's more, current projections call for the region to grow by six million people, or two Chicagos, over the next 20 to 25 years. That means even affluent Angelenos will have to look for new ways to avoid the daily agonies of driving clogged freeways, or make their peace with living in denser neighborhoods closer to their jobs -- or both.</p>
        <p>''This strike shouldn't have happened and we should have been able to avoid it through negotiation,'' said Zev Yaroslavsky, a Los Angeles County Supervisor and M.T.A. board member, who like his colleagues took a hard line in the standoff with the agency's 4,300 drivers. ''But we have to position this agency for the long term, to expand the quality and quantity of service to this increasingly transit dependent region.''</p>
        <p>The transit agency was under intense pressure to cut costs because of the huge price tag of its last big idea: a subway serving a relatively small part of the central city that wound up costing $4.5 billion for just over 17 miles of track. Plans for a grander system fell victim to construction delays, cost overruns and political infighting. Meanwhile, with so much money going to the subway, bus service declined and fares rose, so ridership fell overall. Now, the focus is on expanding the overcrowded bus system with new express routes and technology that keeps traffic lights green to speed the buses down major arteries.</p>
        <p>To be sure, the challenges of building a workable system are enormous in a region where, in the words of Peter Gordon, a professor of urban and regional planning at the University of Southern California, ''origins and destinations are ubiquitous.'' That means commuters are just as likely to be traveling from one suburb to another as from the suburbs to an urban core, so models like New York or Boston make little sense. Which is why it may be tempting to draw the wrong lesson from the strike -- that since the city did not grind to a halt, mass transit does not matter here.</p>
        <p>''It may be that some of the seeming non-impact is that the impacts are diffuse and hard to quantify,'' said Eric H. Monkkonen, a professor of urban history and policy studies at the University of California at Los Angeles. It's one thing to measure the lost income of people who couldn't get to work. But what about the lost services for people whose workers didn't show up? Or whose secretaries were late because they were driving their sisters to work? Is a missed doctor's appointment for someone with a chronic illness a minor inconvenience?</p>
        <p>''Just as Los Angeles is a spread-out city, it doesn't depend on any one network,'' Professor Monkkonen added. In the Northridge earthquake, for example, when the Santa Monica Freeway was closed because a bridge collapsed, affluent workers still managed to find ways to drive into downtown Los Angeles on surface streets. In fact,  Los Angeles has a certain resilience precisely because it has no one center of action, but is instead a sprawling collection of ''edge cities.''</p>
        <p>INDEED, the municipal bus systems of cities-within-the-city, like Santa Monica, kept operating and, in some cases, expanded service to relieve the strain of the M.T.A. strike. And Angelenos mostly managed to limp along, in car pools, gypsy cabs, on bicycles and on foot.</p>
        <p>In this city, owning a car remains the most reliable mark of upward mobility, and immigrants aspire to own a used Toyota here the way they might learn the subway map in New York. But in a place where it's getting harder and harder for everyone to drive, there's reason to think the fire next time could be worse.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
