<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For the Adventurous, New Possibilities in Latin America</title>
    <meta content="29PORT$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/29/business/29PORT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242927"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PORTFOLIOS, ETC."/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Latin America</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Morgan, J P, Securities Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fuerbringer, Jonathan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Asilis, Carlos</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Portfolios Etc</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001029T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E4DA1F31F93AA15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="857" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For the Adventurous, New Possibilities in Latin America</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN FUERBRINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fuerbringer, Jonathan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jonathan Fuerbringer column notes J P Morgan Securities emerging-markets equity strategist Carlos Asilis believes Latin American stocks have fallen enough in recent months to make them appear to be bargains, though he warns they could fall further before rebounding next year (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CARLOS ASILIS, emerging-markets equity strategist at J. P. Morgan Securities, is seeing the kind of small changes in the correlations between markets that help analysts change their minds.</p>
        <p>In the last quarter of 1999, as the Nasdaq composite climbed 48.2 percent, Morgan Stanley Capital International's Latin America Free index climbed 32.8 percent, following the indexes' relatively close correlation of the previous three quarters. Because Mr. Asilis expected that correlation to continue, and because he worried that the Nasdaq rally had gone too far, too fast, in February he advised institutional clients to sell.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CARLOS ASILIS, emerging-markets equity strategist at J. P. Morgan Securities, is seeing the kind of small changes in the correlations between markets that help analysts change their minds.</p>
        <p>In the last quarter of 1999, as the Nasdaq composite climbed 48.2 percent, Morgan Stanley Capital International's Latin America Free index climbed 32.8 percent, following the indexes' relatively close correlation of the previous three quarters. Because Mr. Asilis expected that correlation to continue, and because he worried that the Nasdaq rally had gone too far, too fast, in February he advised institutional clients to sell.</p>
        <p>But in the second and third quarters of this year, he said his monitors began to sense that the correlation was breaking down in a favorable way. He found, for example, that the Latin America index fell only 12.2 percent in May, while the Nasdaq tumbled 20 percent. And by mid-October, when the Nasdaq had fallen 27.4 percent over 30 trading days, the Latin America index was off just 12.3 percent. So he advised his clients to get back into Latin America.</p>
        <p>Well, Latin American indexes have certainly fallen enough recently to make one wonder if it is time to buy. The Morgan Stanley Latin America index is down 18.7 percent for the year and 26.2 percent from its March high. Brazil's Bovespa index is down 14.0 percent for the year and 22.5 percent from its March high, while Mexico's Bolsa index is off 13.0 percent for the year and 25.4 percent from its March high.</p>
        <p>But get this caveat that comes with the recommendation: There is still a risk that the Latin America index could drop an additional 20 percent before rebounding next year. What would make someone take this risk? Mr. Asilis thinks that the economic and political fundamentals are strong in Mexico and Brazil and that the Latin America index could surge 30 percent in dollar terms over the next 12 months.</p>
        <p>Another reason for getting in now, he said, is that Latin American stocks are not that liquid, and that means that a surge in buying would push prices up sharply. For example, Telefonos de Mexico, or Telmex, Mexico's phone company, has an average daily trading volume of $165 million, which is nothing if an institution has a half-billion dollars to move into the Latin American markets. So buying the stocks you want, Mr. Asilis said, can take 20 to 30 days.</p>
        <p>Ian Laming, the Latin American strategist for Morgan Stanley Dean Witter, also is feeling good about the region. He is also well aware of the risks.</p>
        <p>He recommended in July that dedicated institutional investors -- who run funds that invest only in Latin America -- add to positions in Brazil. Since then, the Brazilian market has fallen 15.5 percent. (He wryly noted in his July analysis that he should have varied the Beatles song title for that recommendation to ''All You Need Is Luck.'')</p>
        <p>BUT Mr. Laming is not deterred. For his dedicated investors, he still thinks that Brazil is the best place to be. And as far as international institutional investors are concerned, he said it is getting close to the point where they should be getting back in again. ''When sentiment gets this bad, it is better to be a buyer than a seller,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But ''you do need a benign global market to make emerging markets work,'' he added.</p>
        <p>In an Oct. 9 analysis, when Mr. Laming reaffirmed his July choice of Brazil, the price of oil was about $30 a barrel, down from a peak of $37. The euro was at 86 cents to the dollar, up from a then-record low of 84 cents. Those developments allowed Mr. Laming to conclude that the euro had stabilized and that oil prices had fallen enough to diminish the chances of a hard landing for the American economy.</p>
        <p>But the situation has changed. Oil prices are higher. The euro, despite a rescue effort by the world's leading central banks, has resumed its decline. The Middle East is still explosive. The American stock market has not yet seemed to find its feet. And many investors are worried the economy will slow much more sharply than expected. The one big risk, Mr. Asilis said, is ''of a shock coming out of the United States.''</p>
        <p>In an interview last week, Mr. Laming said he was still convinced that the trend is not getting any worse. But the recent volatility in the stock market shows that many investors are still uncertain.</p>
        <p>This all adds up to a reminder about emerging markets: Even if the big guys are toying with the idea of jumping back in, and even if emerging markets have had a nice decline, you still have to be nerveless. And you have to have a long-term view. Mr. Asilis is addressing his advice to institutional investors with a 12-  to 18-month horizon. Mr. Laming thinks longer term. He advises  a three-year horizon. And you are either in, working hard on your choices. Or you are out. No dabbling.</p>
        <p>PORTFOLIOS, ETC.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
