<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Turning to the Former Chief For Help in Troubled Times</title>
    <meta content="29BOSS$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/29/business/29BOSS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242912"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001029T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E6DC1F31F93AA15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1465" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Turning to the Former Chief For Help in Troubled Times</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By REED ABELSON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>RETIREMENT was the chance to get away: After leaving Campbell Soup, David W. Johnson had been enjoying life by climbing Mount Kilimanjaro. Thomas L. Gossage, who had left Hercules Inc., was living in Atlanta and serving on a few corporate boards. And Henry B. Schacht had traded his responsibilities as chief executive of the gigantic Lucent Technologies for a post as chairman of a much smaller maker of office communications equipment spun off from Lucent.</p>
        <p>But recently, these men have all been summoned back to the companies they once headed. Other returnees include Paul A. Allaire at Xerox and John E. Pepper, who came back to Procter &amp; Gamble as chairman. While they are expected to hold the top jobs only temporarily, they all face serious challenges: strategies gone badly wrong, bitter earnings disappointments and impatient and angry investors.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>RETIREMENT was the chance to get away: After leaving Campbell Soup, David W. Johnson had been enjoying life by climbing Mount Kilimanjaro. Thomas L. Gossage, who had left Hercules Inc., was living in Atlanta and serving on a few corporate boards. And Henry B. Schacht had traded his responsibilities as chief executive of the gigantic Lucent Technologies for a post as chairman of a much smaller maker of office communications equipment spun off from Lucent.</p>
        <p>But recently, these men have all been summoned back to the companies they once headed. Other returnees include Paul A. Allaire at Xerox and John E. Pepper, who came back to Procter &amp; Gamble as chairman. While they are expected to hold the top jobs only temporarily, they all face serious challenges: strategies gone badly wrong, bitter earnings disappointments and impatient and angry investors.</p>
        <p>The recent spate of corporate decisions to bring back these executives points to the intense pressure on boards to get rid of struggling leaders quickly, even if there are no clear successors in place. When companies stumble these days, by missing Wall Street's earnings estimates or in some other way, investors rush for the exits, severely punishing their stocks. Lucent and Xerox lost about two-thirds of their market value in a matter of months; Hercules, a chemical producer, had traded near its decade lows.</p>
        <p>''From the board's perspective, it is a no-brainer,'' said Patrick McGurn, the director of corporate programs for Institutional Shareholder Services, a Rockville, Md., group that advises large investors on shareholder issues. ''It buys them time; it buys them breathing space.''</p>
        <p>The anxiety that has affected investors in general in recent months appears to be spreading to boardrooms, said James M. Citrin, an executive recruiter for Spencer Stuart, and boards are inclined to reach back to solve their current problems. Directors, Mr. Citrin said, ''are betting more on past proven track records than on the promise of the future.''</p>
        <p>Not everyone thinks that rehiring the chief executive is a good idea. The choice has ''very troublesome repercussions,'' Mr. McGurn said. In fact, many regard the trend as a board failure -- an indication that directors may not have done the proper planning to have permanent successors identified and ready to step in. At Xerox, for example, Anne M. Mulcahy, the company's president, was viewed as not being ready to assume the role of chief executive when G. Richard Thoman was dismissed in May, but  no one was ahead of her in line.</p>
        <p>''These companies run into a management-succession crisis,'' said Gerald Meyers, the former American Motors chief executive who is now a business professor at the University of Michigan.</p>
        <p>Companies generally defend the encores for their former chiefs, calling them the best choices for the jobs, particularly in difficult times. The executives are intimately familiar with the company and have already proved to be capable leaders, they said.</p>
        <p>Although most of these companies are  seeking permanent chief executives, the  searches may take several months because they are starting from scratch. ''This arises from the fact that there is a dearth of seasoned, readily available executives who can step in in a crisis,'' said Ralph Whitworth, an activist shareholder who has been board chairman for two companies in which he has invested, Waste Management and the Apria Healthcare Group.</p>
        <p>In bringing back highly regarded former chiefs, companies want to comfort investors. The stock of Hercules, for example, rose 8 percent on the news this month that the company was bringing back Mr. Gossage, who had been in charge for about five years until 1996. He is now considering an outright sale of Hercules, which is struggling under a heavy load of debt.</p>
        <p>Investors also seemed pleased by the prospect of Mr. Johnson's return to Campbell Soup, where he was responsible for a nearly sixfold increase in the stock price in about eight years. Mr. Schacht is credited with the success of the Lucent spinoff from AT&amp;T in the mid-1990's before he stepped down as Lucent's chief executive in 1997 and as chairman in early 1998.</p>
        <p>''The boards recognize that the stakes are so high, the markets so unforgiving and the competition so fierce, they cannot leave a vacuum,'' Mr. Citrin of Spencer Stuart said.</p>
        <p>But analysts and investors are also wary of bringing back an executive who may be at least partly responsible for troubles that became apparent only later. ''Nothing happens in the short term at a large organization,'' said Roderick Hills, a former chairman of the Securities and Exchange Commission and a longtime corporate director.</p>
        <p>Mr. Johnson's critics say he did not invest wisely in brands and was wrong to raise Campbell Soup's prices so sharply, causing losses of market share. At Xerox, Mr. Allaire has been criticized for his own reorganization attempts and as being too slow to recognize competitive threats.</p>
        <p>And in plenty of companies, new management cannot overcome earlier mistakes.  Michael Useem, a management professor at the Wharton School of the University of Pennsylvania, pointed to the huge losses incurred by General Motors in the early 90's during the brief tenure of Robert C. Stempel as chief executive. ''Many of the problems went back to Roger Smith, his predecessor,'' Mr. Useem said.</p>
        <p>Most returning executives remained on the boards of the companies as their successors struggled. Mr. Allaire was said to have really never left Xerox; he was chairman during Mr. Thoman's 13-month reign. Mr. Schacht, who groomed his successor, stayed on the board. Mr. Johnson and Mr. Pepper were on their companies' boards until months before their successors' ousters.</p>
        <p>While companies say their executives offer valuable insights and support to their successors, investors tend to frown on the practice of having former chief executives stay on the board. In general, ''I think former C.E.O.'s should not come back and haunt the company,'' Mr. Whitworth said.</p>
        <p>It is unclear, of course, how these returning executives will perform, although Steve Jobs has had notable success at Apple Computer since coming back in 1997 as chief executive of the company he helped found. Still, Apple has hardly been immune to the downdraft in technology stocks.</p>
        <p>Former executives may be unable to provide a fresh perspective, Mr. Hills said. ''He is almost never the person to turn it around,'' he said in general of a returning chief executive. ''He can be the right person to hold it together.''</p>
        <p>AT Xerox, investors may not be significantly more patient with Mr. Allaire than they were with Mr. Thoman, said David Giroux, an analyst at T. Rowe Price, the mutual fund company in Baltimore. Once the company has sold off enough operations to buy it more time, shareholders may demand new management.</p>
        <p>''You will see a groundswell after those asset sales are made,'' Mr. Giroux predicted. Although Mr. Thoman could not make the changes needed at Xerox, Mr. Giroux said, ''I think the right outsider could do it.''</p>
        <p>And no one claims that fixing these companies is easy. Many have been blind-sided by changes in their industries, or as consumers turned away from once-invincible brands, whether of canned soups or copiers.  In some companies, there have been failed strategies: overly large acquisitions, unsuccessful mergers or bungled reorganizations.  ''This is hard work,'' Mr. Whitworth said. ''It can end up being a swamp.''</p>
        <p>At risk are the reputations of some of these executives, many of whom spent most of their careers building them at the companies they are now trying to rescue. Like Casey Stengel, the manager who led the New York Yankees to seven world championships, they may find the second act much more challenging, said John M. McMillin, an analyst who follows Campbell Soup for Prudential Securities. When Mr. Stengel went on to manage the New York Mets, his record was forever diminished: the team finished last in each of his four seasons.</p>
        <p>Mr. Johnson, who expects to leave Campbell by year-end, has so far been unable to come up with the plays that would mark his return as a success, Mr. McMillin said. ''If  David Johnson had to do it all over, he might not do it again,'' he said.</p>
        <p>BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
