<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>INVESTING WITH: Michael J. Donnelly and Mark S. Kopiniski; American Century Emerging Markets Fund</title>
    <meta content="29INVO$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/29/business/29INVO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242907"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gould, Carole</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Donnelly, Michael J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kopinski, Mark S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Investing With</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001029T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E6DD1F31F93AA15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="984" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>INVESTING WITH: Michael J. Donnelly and Mark S. Kopiniski; American Century Emerging Markets Fund</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAROLE GOULD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gould, Carole</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Carole Gould Investing column profiles Michael J Donnelly and Mark S Kopinski, co-managers of $110 million American Century Emerging Markets Fund, which has returned average 2.5 percent over three years, versus average 8.0 percent loss among its peers; photo; graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MICHAEL J. DONNELLY, a manager of the $110 million American Century Emerging Markets fund, speaks Spanish, French and a smattering of Russian. Mark S. Kopinski, the other manager, speaks fluent Japanese. Collectively, the 14 American Century international analysts speak 13 languages, including Ukrainian, Cantonese and Afrikaans.</p>
        <p>But the fund speaks to its investors in a different language: It returned 3.9 percent in the 12 months ended Oct. 26, compared with a loss of 2.6 percent for its peers in the diversified emerging markets category, according to Morningstar Inc. Over three years, a generally rough period for the emerging markets, the fund returned 2.5 percent a year, on average, versus a loss of 8.0 percent for the average fund in the category.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MICHAEL J. DONNELLY, a manager of the $110 million American Century Emerging Markets fund, speaks Spanish, French and a smattering of Russian. Mark S. Kopinski, the other manager, speaks fluent Japanese. Collectively, the 14 American Century international analysts speak 13 languages, including Ukrainian, Cantonese and Afrikaans.</p>
        <p>But the fund speaks to its investors in a different language: It returned 3.9 percent in the 12 months ended Oct. 26, compared with a loss of 2.6 percent for its peers in the diversified emerging markets category, according to Morningstar Inc. Over three years, a generally rough period for the emerging markets, the fund returned 2.5 percent a year, on average, versus a loss of 8.0 percent for the average fund in the category.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kopinski, 44, and Mr. Donnelly, 35, called the market sell-off of  September and October overdone.</p>
        <p>''The emerging markets have been beaten up past a point that's reasonable,'' Mr. Donnelly said. ''I think they're due for a considerable rally soon.''</p>
        <p>In picking stocks, the managers study 1,500 companies in 35 countries around the world. They use computer screens in their research -- though such filtering can be difficult for companies in some markets. ''Our database is built around quarterly reporting, which isn't available in many emerging-markets countries,'' Mr. Kopinski said.</p>
        <p>They look for companies with annual earnings growth of at least 20 percent, but they may raise or lower that bar depending on the industry and the countries where they operate. For example, earnings in countries that have devalued their currency may not be sustainable, Mr. Kopinski explained.</p>
        <p>The portfolio's earnings growth rate averages 27 percent, versus 17 percent for the Morgan Stanley Capital International Emerging Markets Free Index.</p>
        <p>The earnings test pares down their universe to about 300 companies, from which they eventually choose 100 to 125 stocks for the fund.</p>
        <p>When working in their New York offices, the two men meet at 9 a.m. daily with the international analysts for the American Century fund family, sharing information about earnings announcements as well as global, country and industry trends.</p>
        <p>''The global perspective gives us context for our investment decisions,'' Mr. Donnelly said. In the cellular phone industry, he added, ''we were scratching around early in the emerging markets because we saw the trend developing in Europe.''</p>
        <p>Their work also requires an understanding of both corporate and national cultures, the managers said.</p>
        <p>The managers often sell shares after one disappointing earnings report. ''If a good company stumbles, it tends to take time to get back on its feet again,'' Mr. Kopinski said.</p>
        <p>One favorite is Tubos de Acero de Mexico, a maker of pipes used for oil and gas transportation and drilling; the company trades as American depository receipts on the New York Stock Exchange.</p>
        <p>''The company operates in a quasi-oligopolistic market around the world,'' Mr. Kopinski said. ''Now that the price of oil is increasing, it will be a direct beneficiary of equipment purchasing by the major international oil companies.''</p>
        <p>Sales volume is on the rise despite quarterly price increases of 4 to 5 percent. Most sales are priced in American dollars, providing a hedge against weakness in the Mexican peso, Mr. Kopinski added.</p>
        <p>The fund bought shares in September 1999 at $14.80. On Friday, they closed at $13.95, or 6.31 times the consensus earnings estimate of $2.21 a share for this year.</p>
        <p>THEY also like Folli-Follie, a Greek retailer of midpriced fashion jewelry sold in rented space in department stores in about a dozen countries worldwide.</p>
        <p>A visit to the company in May confirmed that operations were strong, Mr. Donnelly said. He expects annual earnings growth of 40 percent through 2002. ''They're gaining market share in Japan,'' he said, ''and moving into shops in the larger department stores, even though the Japanese economy is slow.''</p>
        <p>Growth in same-store sales, those at stores open at least a year, has doubled in the last three years. The company has opened stores in the United States and France and plans to expand into duty-free shops in Asia, Mr. Donnelly added.</p>
        <p>The managers bought shares in May 1998 at 7,390 drachmas. The stock closed on Friday at 7,610 drachmas, or 59 times analysts' earnings estimates of 129 drachmas a share for this year.</p>
        <p>Another holding is China Mobile (Hong Kong). The company is the largest cellular provider in China, Mr. Kopinski said; its acquisitions of regional mobile phone operators have resulted in a network running the length of China's eastern seaboard. The company has modernized the billing systems of its acquired companies, improved networks and pursued business users aggressively, he said, resulting in ''a lot of upside in the subscriber base and earnings of the acquired companies.''</p>
        <p>Vodofone recently acquired a small stake in the company, Mr. Kopinski said, a move that will help it become part of a global network.</p>
        <p>The managers bought the stock in June 1999 at $52 (Hong Kong); it now trades at $52.75, or 41.5 times consensus 2000 earnings estimates of $1.27 a share.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
