<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Way We Live Now: 10-29-00: The Ethicist; Pushing the E-Envelope</title>
    <meta content="WLN103118" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Education; Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242672"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electronic Mail</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Privacy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parties (Social)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cohen, Randy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine/Columns/The Ethicist</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Privacy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parties (Social)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electronic Mail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001029T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E6D81231F93AA15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="614" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Way We Live Now: 10-29-00: The Ethicist; Pushing the E-Envelope</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Randy Cohen</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cohen, Randy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Randy Cohen The Ethicist column answers questions on supervisor who routinely reads employee e-mail, using one self-written paper for more than one college class and whether to accept invitation to 'Pimp and Ho' party (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I discovered that my supervisor routinely reads employee e-mail. Legal issues aside, is this ethical? I can understand doing so if a crime is suspected, but not as a matter of routine. It feels like a violation of my privacy. What do you think? -- Anonymous, New York</p>
        <p>While it is indeed legal, I agree with you: your supervisor should not routinely read employee e-mail. The right to privacy does not vanish at your office door. That the employer owns the computer system is not germane. The company presumably owns the restrooms, but the boss doesn't get to spy there.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I discovered that my supervisor routinely reads employee e-mail. Legal issues aside, is this ethical? I can understand doing so if a crime is suspected, but not as a matter of routine. It feels like a violation of my privacy. What do you think? -- Anonymous, New York</p>
        <p>While it is indeed legal, I agree with you: your supervisor should not routinely read employee e-mail. The right to privacy does not vanish at your office door. That the employer owns the computer system is not germane. The company presumably owns the restrooms, but the boss doesn't get to spy there.</p>
        <p>Absent suspicions of specific wrongdoing, one justification for this practice is to ensure that employees use work time for work. This argument is not enough. Every worker every day has passing thoughts unrelated to the job. We all need to make a doctor's appointment or contact a child's school. While your supervisor has a valid interest in learning if an employee is a habitual slacker, there are less intrusive ways to do so. Surely the dismal quality of a layabout's work -- or lack of it -- will be apparent (as will the gentle snoring sounds emanating from his cubicle).</p>
        <p>Also, many e-mail messages that are work-related -- an early draft of a report, comments about a co-worker -- are not something you necessarily want scrutinized. A desire for privacy is not an admission of wrongdoing, and to assume otherwise is to rupture the bonds of trust between employee and employer. If every legitimate activity were subject to constant monitoring, we'd all be flossing our teeth on prime-time TV. Naked. On CBS.</p>
        <p>Assigning a term paper for a history class, my professor said we were not to use any papers we had written for other classes; he said this was plagiarism. But is it plagiarism if the paper is my own work? Beyond the legal dimension, is it ethical to hand in one paper for two classes? -- Anonymous, St. Louis</p>
        <p>You should not hand in a prewritten paper. Your professor's ban is reason enough, but even without it, you should still forswear the practice. As unlikely as it may seem, a paper is not merely a dreary obligation to be discharged; it is a chance to learn, and that's what your prof is trying to get you to do. Submitting a prewritten paper may not be plagiarism -- it is no crime to copy from yourself -- but it isn't a boon to pedagogy either. And it certainly violates the spirit -- and in this case, the letter -- of university life.</p>
        <p>Similarly, even if your own lab work eventually makes it possible, you ought not let a superintelligent bioengineered dog take your exams for you.</p>
        <p>Friends invited my wife and me to a ''Pimp and Ho'' party, asking us to wear outrageous attire inspired by 70's blaxploitation movies. The prospect of being in a room full of white people dressed as stereotypes of black street criminals makes me squeamish. Should I confront my friends about their racist party? Simply not go? Or just get over my white liberal guilt and shop for a zebra-print fedora? -- Anonymous, New York</p>
        <p>I share your discomfort and agree that this event is creepily racist.</p>
        <p>(Similar qualms will keep me from attending that ''Come as a Big Jew'' square dance.) It also manages to insult women. You should decline the invitation and explain why, gently and tactfully -- make it not a confrontation but a quiet conversation, or even just add a line or two to your R.S.V.P.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
