<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Justice Is Better Than Revenge</title>
    <meta content="29SUDETIT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242596"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sudetic, Chuck</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bass, Gary Jonathan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goldstone, Richard J</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Stay the Hand of Vengeance (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">For Humanity: Reflections of a War Crimes Investigator (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001029T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06EED9123EF93AA15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1433" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Justice Is Better Than Revenge</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Chuck Sudetic</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sudetic, Chuck</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Chuck Sudetic reviews books Stay the Hand of Vengeance: The Politics of War Crimes Tribunals by Gary Jonathan Bass and For Humanity: Reflections of a War Crimes Investigator by Richard J Goldstone (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Stay the Hand of Vengeance</p>
        <p>The Politics of War Crimes Tribunals.</p>
        <p>By Gary Jonathan Bass.</p>
        <p>402 pp. Princeton, N.J.:</p>
        <p>Princeton University Press. $29.95.</p>
        <p>For Humanity</p>
        <p>Reflections of a War Crimes Investigator.</p>
        <p>By Richard J. Goldstone.</p>
        <p>152 pp. New Haven:</p>
        <p>Yale University Press. $18.50.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Stay the Hand of Vengeance</p>
        <p>The Politics of War Crimes Tribunals.</p>
        <p>By Gary Jonathan Bass.</p>
        <p>402 pp. Princeton, N.J.:</p>
        <p>Princeton University Press. $29.95.</p>
        <p>For Humanity</p>
        <p>Reflections of a War Crimes Investigator.</p>
        <p>By Richard J. Goldstone.</p>
        <p>152 pp. New Haven:</p>
        <p>Yale University Press. $18.50.</p>
        <p>Polite discourse has a weak arsenal of adjectives to describe crimes of war. These words -- inhuman, unspeakable, heinous, and a few others -- fail to evoke the personal and societal fury that such crimes provoke. And comprehending this fury is a prerequisite to understanding the importance of war crimes tribunals. So imagine a gang of soldiers shooting a young woman in the head, nailing her hand and foot to a four-by-eight, and setting her adrift on a river. Picture bullets puncturing the chests of bound prisoners, and listen for the gurgle of their last breaths. Smell the corpses of chemical-weapons and gas-chamber victims. Hear the bleating of a skinned man whose tongue has been cut out. See the ooze from the bodies of children run over by tanks. Now multiply these horrors a thousandfold and a thousandfold again.</p>
        <p>What should be done with people who commit such acts? And what is to be done with the political and military leaders who launch wars of aggression that lead to these crimes? Both Gary Jonathan Bass and Richard J. Goldstone argue compellingly that they should be tried before a court that has the authority to find them not guilty.</p>
        <p>Bass's book, ''Stay the Hand of Vengeance,'' is a timely and exhaustive survey of how political leaders have wrestled with the problem of war criminals since 1815, when Napoleon was banished from Europe without a trial. The subsequent record contains more failures than successes. The Weimar Republic's trials of German war criminals after World War I produced one acquittal after another but still triggered a nationalist reaction that Hitler was only too happy to exploit. Britain imprisoned dozens of Turks implicated in the Armenian genocide; but it exchanged them for a few captured British soldiers, and to this day Armenians have taken revenge while the Turkish government continues to deny that Armenians were ever slaughtered. Next came Nuremberg, which afforded Nazi leaders fair trials; but for obvious reasons the justice it administered had blind spots, and the bombing of Dresden and other crimes against humanity were ignored. Now we have the current trials of mostly minor war criminals from the former Yugoslavia and Rwanda while the major culprits -- Radovan Karadzic, Ratko Mladic, and Slobodan Milosevic -- remain at large because the political will to arrest them is lacking.</p>
        <p>Despite this grim inventory, Bass, an assistant professor of politics and international affairs at Princeton, argues convincingly that trying war criminals is a better option than its alternative: vengeance. His adversaries in the debate are the so-called realists in the field of international relations: diplomats, political leaders, and philosophers who oppose using moral standards to restrict the behavior of states outside their borders, not to mention applying the principle of due process to war crimes. Serious talk about war crimes trials, they argue, can prolong wars and thwart postwar efforts to build peace. ''To realists,'' Bass writes, ''a war crimes tribunal is simply something that the countries that decisively win a war inflict on the helpless country that loses it. It is punishment, revenge, spectacle -- anything but justice.'' He cites the patriarch of American realism, Hans Morgenthau, discussing the prospects for Nuremberg: ''I am doubtful of the whole setup under which these trials will be conducted. What, in my opinion, they should have done is to set up summary courts-martial. Then they should have placed these criminals on trial before them within 24 hours after they were caught, sentenced them to death, and shot them in the morning.''</p>
        <p>Bass relates how realists in the administration of Franklin D. Roosevelt, led by the secretary of the treasury, Henry Morgenthau Jr., almost prevailed after World War II. Their plan included a spate of summary executions and the reduction of Germany to a country of peasants and herders. It was thwarted by Henry Stimson, the secretary of war, and other American leaders, who persuaded President Roosevelt that even the worst Nazi criminals should be afforded due process because to do anything less would cheapen the liberal set of values for which the country fought. ''Liberal states,'' Bass observes, ''are unlikely to shoot war criminals, although they can be tempted by that prospect. Rather, even when liberal decision makers are painfully aware of the risks of acquittal, delay, and embarrassment posed by a war crimes tribunal, domestic norms push them to apply due process beyond their own borders.'' A young colonel, Murray Bernays, drew up the plan for the Nuremberg trials. In it, he argued that not providing the defendants due process ''would do violence to the very principles for which the United Nations have taken up arms, and furnish apparent justification for what the Nazis themselves have taught and done.''</p>
        <p>Bass is careful not to buy some of the arguments cited by supporters of war crimes tribunals. These advocates say tribunals can fortify peace, rehabilitate former enemy countries, purge threatening enemy leaders, and strip them of their charisma and strength. In fact, trials can also spark a nationalist backlash in a defeated country, especially if the victors delay the legal process and cut and run in the way they did from Turkey after World War I. Tribunal advocates also argue that trials can deter war criminals, place the blame for atrocities on individuals rather than on whole ethnic groups, and establish the truth about wartime atrocities. But there is, for now anyway, insufficient evidence to prove that they can.</p>
        <p>''At a minimum,'' Bass concludes, ''long-run deterrence of war crimes would require a relatively credible threat of prosecution: that is, a series of successful war crimes tribunals that became so much an expected part of international affairs that no potential mass murderer could confidently say that he would avoid punishment.'' These tribunals, he adds, would have to be more robust than the courts set up for Yugoslavia and Rwanda.</p>
        <p>As the first prosecutor at the United Nations criminal tribunal for the former Yugoslavia and Rwanda, Richard J. Goldstone saw how little the international community was willing to do to bring war criminals to the dock and how reluctant liberal governments are to put their own soldiers at risk in order to arrest war criminals. Goldstone's book, ''For Humanity,'' is a brief memoir that begins with his experiences leading the investigations into criminal attempts to stymie the transition from apartheid in his native South Africa. In the end, however, his book is a plea for the United States to support the creation of an international criminal justice system ''sufficiently empowered to cause would-be war criminals to reconsider their ambitions, knowing that they might otherwise be hunted for the rest of their days and eventually be brought to justice.''</p>
        <p>Goldstone says the Clinton administration's deference to the Pentagon lies behind its decision to oppose a treaty, drafted in Rome in July 1998, that would create an international criminal court. ''The stated fear of the United States was that some renegade or malicious prosecutor might some day initiate unfounded political prosecutions against United States citizens,'' Goldstone writes. ''The prospect of such conduct was made virtually impossible by the terms of the draft treaty. . . . These protective devices were sufficient to satisfy 120 members of the international community, including three permanent members of the Security Council, the United Kingdom, Russia, and France.''</p>
        <p>Since the extralegal exile of Napoleon, we have witnessed the world wars, the gassings, the Holocaust and the shame of Bosnia and Rwanda as well as the invention of the World Wide Web, the creation of the European Union, the lifting of trade barriers and other developments that are erasing borders and redefining international relations. Watchdog organizations and advocates like Human Rights Watch, Amnesty International, George Soros's Open Society Institute and others have come up with facts and funds to goad governments to do justice in situations in which revenge was once the only ''remedy'' available. These two books present important reminders that if our world is to become more globalized and humane, governments, including our own, must keep step by prosecuting war criminals. Vengeance cannot remain the only outlet for the fury of the kith and kin and countrymen of their victims.</p>
        <p>Chuck Sudetic, the author of ''Blood and Vengeance: One Family's Story of the War in Bosnia,'' is a contributing editor at Rolling Stone.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Chuck Sudetic, the author of ''Blood and Vengeance: One Family's Story of the War in Bosnia,'' is a contributing editor at Rolling Stone.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
