<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>These Political Button Men Are Relic Makers Now</title>
    <meta content="29YORK$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242920"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEW YORKERS &amp; CO."/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Campaign Buttons and Posters</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Slater, N G, Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Slater, Robert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Slater, Alan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Crow, Kelly</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Buttons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Posters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001029T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E6DB1F31F93AA15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1349" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>These Political Button Men Are Relic Makers Now</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KELLY CROW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Crow, Kelly</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on brothers Robert and Alan Slater, owners of N G Slater Corp, New York City's only political campaign button factory; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE button brothers are busy. That should come as no surprise, since the elections are only a few days away. One day last week Alan and Robert Slater tried to talk buttons between  the calls and orders pouring into their sunny, wood-paneled offices in the city's only button factory, the N. G. Slater Corporation on West 19th Street at Seventh Avenue.</p>
        <p>''We just got a call from Nader's people,'' said Robert, 54, the younger and more talkative Slater, as he eagerly showed off the 17 variations of ''Hillary for Senate 2000'' buttons they have made for this campaign so far. (Some have Ms. Clinton's name in a pink triangle or written in Hebrew. Others show her face beneath slogans like ''I Love New York.'')</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE button brothers are busy. That should come as no surprise, since the elections are only a few days away. One day last week Alan and Robert Slater tried to talk buttons between  the calls and orders pouring into their sunny, wood-paneled offices in the city's only button factory, the N. G. Slater Corporation on West 19th Street at Seventh Avenue.</p>
        <p>''We just got a call from Nader's people,'' said Robert, 54, the younger and more talkative Slater, as he eagerly showed off the 17 variations of ''Hillary for Senate 2000'' buttons they have made for this campaign so far. (Some have Ms. Clinton's name in a pink triangle or written in Hebrew. Others show her face beneath slogans like ''I Love New York.'')</p>
        <p>''We make a Lazio button, too,'' said Alan, 58, ''though he's not as big of a client. But we make buttons for everybody.''</p>
        <p>If only everybody wore campaign buttons. More buttons are on costumes in ''Gore Vidal's 'The Best Man' '' than on city streets these days, it seems. Jim McManus at the McManus Democratic Club said only a dozen of his 1,500 members wore buttons to club events. Activists, he calls them. He suspects few New Yorkers today even own one.</p>
        <p>The button brothers have similar suspicions. They know campaign buttons are relics of an age before television and technology, when candidates relied on stump speeches and whistle stops rather than prime-time face time. They know campaign buttons are more popular on eBay than on lapels. And they know buttons are bad political barometers: the candidate who distributes the most does not necessarily win.</p>
        <p>But Alan and Robert Slater are content to run the only button-making factory in the Northeast. This week, they will churn out thousands of Gore and Bush buttons, including one with Mr. Gore kissing his wife, Tipper, because they think a few people still believe in the symbolic, if not persuasive, power of the campaign button. For now, it keeps them busy.</p>
        <p>''For us, the campaign button is the symbol of a campaign,'' Robert said. ''Not the American flag, not the bunting. It's the button.''</p>
        <p>Despite shifts in political climate, the mechanics of making a button have changed little since Nathaniel George Slater of  Brooklyn began his business 64 years ago. He set up at West 29th Street, first with 50 workers, then 100. His sons have 12 workers.</p>
        <p>The modern Slater factory is cluttered with packing boxes and reams of paper. A radio plays Michael Jackson, and everything from printing to laminating to punching to pinning is performed mostly by a chatty group of Latino women. There is a haunting grace in the rows of punching machines that line the factory's wooden floor. Tall as parking meters, these punchers once shook the walls with their pounding. Only a handful are needed these days. The rest stand silent.</p>
        <p>In the 1930's and 40's, though, the button business boomed. One of Nathaniel Slater's first major clients was the federal government, which ordered buttons supporting the National Recovery Act and war bonds. The 1950's and 1960's brought space race buttons and civil rights buttons, with the company supplying both the Rev. Martin Luther King Jr. and the Black Panthers. In 1972, Nathaniel slapped a yellow smiley face on a button, wished the world a happy day, and helped create an icon for a generation.</p>
        <p>While the Smiley Face is the Slater legacy, Nathaniel and his sons have created  buttons for every presidential and significant New York candidate since 1936, including candidates from the Communist and Socialist Workers Parties. (Several Slater buttons are in the Smithsonian.) Demand was especially high during the glory days of campaign buttons, ''I Like Ike'' in the 50's and Kennedy versus Nixon in 1960.</p>
        <p>But buttons were popular campaign trinkets well before Eisenhower. Abraham Lincoln handed out brass buttons when he sought re-election in 1864, and campaigns have long valued buttons as small but visible ways to inspire voters.  BUT in the 1960's, television took over. Presidential candidates  could reach voters in their living rooms with advertisements and  debates. Buttons lasted mainly because candidates knew people liked mementos.</p>
        <p>''Anything people can put on to show their support, they want,'' said John Wingate, head of materials for the Lazio campaign. He estimated they had given out 200,000  buttons, including one saying ''Viva Lazio.''</p>
        <p>The Slater Corporation presses 25 million buttons a year, and in an election year, about half are for campaigns. But Robert and Alan Slater admit that the bulk of their business belongs to big business, to the Revlon ad campaigns and McDonald's special sauce promotions. While 100,000 buttons is a sizable order for a campaign -- and Slater can produce it in three days -- Burger King routinely orders 1,000 buttons to give away at each of their 3,500 stores, or 3.5 million. Slater also makes T-shirts, magnets, stickers and other custom products.</p>
        <p>''We're still campaigning,'' Robert said. ''It's just we're campaigning for products now, instead of politics.''</p>
        <p>Yet the collectibles market for buttons has never been bigger. People who would never wear a Gore or Bush button will spend hundreds of dollars for a Goldwater or Eleanor Roosevelt button. On Friday, 1,132  presidential campaign buttons were up for bid on eBay, including one that promoted an Al Gore-Dianne Feinstein ticket (for $1,000).</p>
        <p>''Everybody seems to want a piece of history, to know where they came from,'' said George Darrow of Fun Antiques, a collectibles store on First Avenue with more than 2,000 campaign buttons. ''Some people even collect losers, the guys who ran and you never heard from again.''</p>
        <p>The Slaters admit they were slow to smell the resale opportunity. In 1972, when the George McGovern-Thomas Eagleton presidential ticket fell apart, the brothers felt foolish for pressing 100,000 buttons. ''We thought they were garbage,'' Alan said, ''but the next day, we got calls from all over. Everyone wanted that button.''</p>
        <p>The Slaters no longer sell old buttons for pennies, but otherwise their business is much the same as the one their father started. They still sell new buttons for a quarter, and they don't copyright their designs. Not surprisingly, they don't think buttons alone can sway an election. They refuse to collect buttons themselves, and they don't want their children to follow them into the button business.</p>
        <p>''We are truly one of the dinosaurs,'' Robert said. Yet standing in their boneyard of a factory, buttons on the walls, the brothers are still optimistic about the survival of their symbol. For now, they have enough orders to prove it.</p>
        <p>''Campaigns may have become high-tech, and buttons, to some extent, have lost their appeal,'' Robert said. ''But maybe people don't want everything to be high-tech. Maybe they want something old-fashioned, something they can hang onto.''</p>
        <p>NEW YORKERS &amp; CO.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
