<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Great Depression</title>
    <meta content="29DERESCT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242582"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Deresiewicz, William</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fischer, Tibor</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">I Like Being Killed: Stories (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001029T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E0D9123EF93AA15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1522" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Great Depression</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By William Deresiewicz</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Deresiewicz, William</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William Deresiewicz reviews book I Like Being Killed: Stories by Tibor Fischer (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I LIKE BEING KILLED</p>
        <p>Stories.</p>
        <p>By Tibor Fischer.</p>
        <p>261 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Metropolitan Books/</p>
        <p>Henry Holt &amp; Company. $24.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I LIKE BEING KILLED</p>
        <p>Stories.</p>
        <p>By Tibor Fischer.</p>
        <p>261 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Metropolitan Books/</p>
        <p>Henry Holt &amp; Company. $24.</p>
        <p>With this, Tibor Fischer's first collection of stories after three decreasingly worthwhile novels, a career that began just eight years ago with a good deal of promise -- and even greater praise -- appears to have hit bottom. So devoid are these pieces of any literary merit, it's a tribute to Fischer's lingering reputation that they got published at all. At the same time, the sheer dreariness that pervades them, as well as the demoralized quality of their execution, gives the volume a morbid psychological interest. The tough-guy persona that Fischer projects in his novels, an image that has established him as one of the voguish young rogues of British fiction, collapses here like a leaky balloon. After three volumes of frenetic hilarity and brittle swagger, we seem to see the real man for the first time. It's not a pretty sight.</p>
        <p>Fischer's career began with a fairly impressive act of historical imagination. ''Under the Frog'' tells the story of a young Hungarian basketball player in the years leading up to the 1956 revolution. The choice is less audacious than it seems; Gyuri Fischer, the protagonist, is modeled on the author's father. But to conclude that Tibor initiated his literary career by recycling his old man's stories would be an exaggeration. Both Gyuri's lonely, horny, sardonic consciousness and his stultifying and murderous Stalinist milieu are rendered with the richness of a fully imagined world. Still, Fischer's use of nonautobiographical material, which must have seemed admirably mature, looks in retrospect like a sign of problems to come. As it has turned out, he can't bring himself to confront his own experience.</p>
        <p>''Under the Frog'' won instant acclaim. The novel was short-listed for the Booker Prize in 1993, the same year Fischer was anointed as one of Granta magazine's ''Best Young British Novelists.'' Those are relative honors, and perhaps deserved, but as good as the novel sometimes is, it has much to be forgiven. Its black humor, designed to come off as stoic and heavy with Mitteleuropean irony, is flippant and sophomoric as only a secondhand account could be. Other than Gyuri, the characters are flat and belong to recognizable types: the all-knowing teacher, the almost magically invulnerable friend, the doomed, heroic lover. The narrative lacks an overarching structure, consisting of a dozen vignettes spread out over as many years, and the ending is sentimental and too neat. Then there's Fischer's sense of literary style, his cutesy, lazy habit of enlivening his prose by the use or archly deliberate misuse of needlessly fancy locutions: ''bailed out of the womb,'' ''a tough [predicament] to mendacity out.'' At the time, all these must have seemed like problems Fischer would grow out of. Instead, he embraced them.</p>
        <p>From borrowed experience Fischer turned to outright fantasy. ''The Thought Gang'' follows the exploits of Eddie Coffin, an aging Cambridge philosophy don on the lam in France after embezzling his foundation grant. Coffin hooks up with Hubert, a petty thief with several missing body parts, and the Thought Gang, as they call themselves, embark on a series of absurdly easy bank robberies and other violent pranks. They're soon joined by a sexy teller from their first job, who, despite our hero's baldness, beer gut and utter lack of charm, can't stop throwing herself at him. Coffin is meant to be endearingly loutish, spending his time between heists sifting through the history of philosophical speculation in search of the meaning of life, or at least of his own failed version of it.</p>
        <p>But Coffin's act, equal parts glibness and self-pity, gets old fast. He doesn't engage philosophical ideas so much as fold them up into little slogans. One British reviewer saw the novel as ''really a sexual interpretation of the history of Western thought.'' I see it as low-calorie slapstick spray-coated with a glaze of intellectual pretense. It's the kind of thing that flatters readers into a cheap feeling of sophistication, as if merely to read names like Thales and Epictetus were equivalent to understanding what those thinkers wrote.</p>
        <p>If ''Under the Frog'' is nave, in other words, ''The Thought Gang'' is cynical. The novel, for instance, makes a great show of experimentalism. The text presents itself as a series of entries in Coffin's notebook, each sporting a clever title. Larger sections are marked off with little reefs of question marks. The verbal style is ''Under the Frog'' on coke: nerve-jangling mannerisms, compulsive punning and a baroque vocabulary that's long on initial z's: ''zacaton,'' ''zaibatsu,'' ''zalambdodont.'' Fischer wields his thesaurus here like a blunt instrument. But none of this gimmickry really means anything; the technical display derives not from Paris in the 1920's but from Madison Avenue in the 90's. It's the literary equivalent of the kind of packaging and marketing designed to make you think that a Big Mac is really a hamburger.</p>
        <p>About ''The Collector Collector'' not much need be said. It's like ''The Thought Gang,'' only less so: less energy, less point. Even Fischer doesn't seem very interested in the ridiculous premise he sets up. Our narrator this time is a ceramic pot. Yes, a thinking pot -- one, moreover, that's been around since the beginning of human history, has total recall, can read the thoughts of anyone who lays hands on it and can change shape at will. With all that, you'd think we were gearing up for something really spectacular. In fact, the novel barely gets off the ground, largely degenerating into a series of vaguely folkloristic vignettes recollected by the pot to soothe the sexual loneliness of the telepathic (or at least, ceramico-telepathic) young art expert in whose safekeeping it happens to find itself. In the end, as in ''The Thought Gang,'' the people we like get what they want, and the novel closes on a note of spurious emotional wisdom.</p>
        <p>Fischer's novels are books to deplore, denounce, even, for a certain kind of reader, delight in. ''I Like Being Killed'' is a book to diagnose. The protagonists of its seven stories nearly all share the same psychological profile: lonely, bitter, sexually apathetic, self-pitying, stuck. One runs a failing Web site company; another holds down a cruddy job at a law firm; still another holes up in libraries and bookstores, devoting his life to reading and shutting out human contact. Their hatred of everyone around them is surpassed only by their loathing of themselves. The grayness of these stories is numbing, their sameness even more so.</p>
        <p>The book itself has more trouble coping with its obligations than its characters do. Nothing ever gets going. Most of the stories peter out after a few pages, having failed to sustain a single scene or even adequately sketch a setting. The two longer pieces drift from event to event, initiating plot lines that dry out like streams in the desert. Some of the protagonists don't even have names, and no one has significant relationships; the book avoids human contact as assiduously as they do. Even Fischer's characteristic verbal energy is gone. It never amounted to more than a kind of rapid twitching, but without it, the corpse lies flat.</p>
        <p>It is difficult to avoid the conclusion that this depressed book about depressed people -- most of whom, as youngish white male Londoners, bear a family resemblance to their author, and none of whom are treated by him with the slightest ironic distance -- is the work of a depressed man. As such, it forms a logical complement to, and casts a retrospective light on, the manic glee of his previous books, especially the second and third. What appeared to be exuberance now looks like avoidance. Whatever psychic structure enabled -- or required -- Fischer to joke about dead Russian soldiers or chortle over the idea of a man being forced to nail his comrades' lips to a bar has apparently collapsed.</p>
        <p>A clue to what might lie behind both the ghoulishness and the despair may be found in Fischer's intermittent efforts here to endow depression with philosophical significance. We have nothing to live for, the argument implicitly runs, because we're all going to die. The collection's one decent piece -- a brief account from Fischer's stint as a reporter in Budapest, before he began publishing fiction -- records his horror at the sight of corpses in Timisoara during the early days of the Romanian revolution. Relevant, too, is the book's title, a last echo of the false, fragile bravado by which he had heretofore signified what he could not otherwise say.</p>
        <p>Author's Query</p>
        <p>For a book on Kate Douglas Wiggin, nee Smith (1856-1923), author of ''Rebecca of Sunnybrook Farm'' (1903), who married George Christopher Riggs (1861-1925), I would like to hear from anyone with information on Riggs, his family and the years they spent in New York City.</p>
        <p>Susan M. Wickham  11 Bure Homage Gardens,  Christchurch  Dorset BH23 4DR  England</p>
        <p>William Deresiewicz teaches English at Yale University. He is working on a study of Jane Austen.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">William Deresiewicz teaches English at Yale University. He is working on a study of Jane Austen.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
