<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Much for the Imagination In G.E.-Honeywell Deal</title>
    <meta content="29GEGE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/29/business/29GEGE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242924"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="INVESTING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">General Electric Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Honeywell International Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sorkin, Andrew Ross</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Welch, John F Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001029T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503EFDB1F31F93AA15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="674" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Much for the Imagination In G.E.-Honeywell Deal</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW ROSS SORKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sorkin, Andrew Ross</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>General Electric's planned $45 billion acquisition of Honeywell International may pose greatest challenge yet to GE chief executive John F Welch Jr, who is perhaps the most admired manager in the world; he has promised huge value to investors, but there is skepticism over whether GE will be able to integrate such a large company into its business; graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IS John F. Welch Jr. in over his head? The chairman of General Electric may be the most admired manager in the world, but his encore -- the planned $45 billion acquisition of Honeywell International -- could be his hardest job yet. For an executive who usually cares about the dowdiest of details, he has not figured out exactly how combining G.E. and Honeywell will work.</p>
        <p>''Use your imagination: this thing is going to be huge,'' he said, refusing to provide concrete details last week about his shotgun acquisition of Honeywell. ''We start out where a blind man could get, because of the arithmetic, double-digit accretion,'' he said, referring to earnings growth. ''That double-digit accretion just keeps going and going and going.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IS John F. Welch Jr. in over his head? The chairman of General Electric may be the most admired manager in the world, but his encore -- the planned $45 billion acquisition of Honeywell International -- could be his hardest job yet. For an executive who usually cares about the dowdiest of details, he has not figured out exactly how combining G.E. and Honeywell will work.</p>
        <p>''Use your imagination: this thing is going to be huge,'' he said, refusing to provide concrete details last week about his shotgun acquisition of Honeywell. ''We start out where a blind man could get, because of the arithmetic, double-digit accretion,'' he said, referring to earnings growth. ''That double-digit accretion just keeps going and going and going.''</p>
        <p>But exactly how Mr. Welch will create such value remains unclear to most investors. More important, there is skepticism over whether G.E. will be able to integrate such a large company into its business.</p>
        <p>Although G.E. has integrated hundreds of businesses into its corporate grid, Honeywell is the largest industrial acquisition ever: double the size of G.E.'s addition of RCA in 1986.</p>
        <p>''Integrating an acquisition is a mammoth task,'' said E. Ralph Biggadike, a management professor at Columbia Business School. ''Usually leaders of companies underestimate how long it takes and how important it is.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Welch boasts he has overseen 1,700 acquisitions and ''lives execution.''</p>
        <p>''I've seen before the same type of thing you've seen in G.E.: rapidly expanding operating margins every year, expanding top-line growth,'' he said. Of the savings he hopes to create, he said: ''A billion and a half is right in the gun sights in 48 hours.''</p>
        <p>Most analysts have had to rely on their best guesses about the synergies and cost savings that the deal might produce. Nicholas Heymann, an analyst at Prudential Securities, who is bullish on both G.E. and the deal, estimates that the combined company could save $12 billion to $15 billion by the end of 2002.</p>
        <p>G.E.'s shares, which closed on Friday at $52.50, have remained relatively steady since the deal was announced on Monday. Mr. Heymann expects the shares to reach $70 by the end of the year, $80 within 6 to 12 months and $100 in the next 12 to 15 months.</p>
        <p>The real question may be whether the market will hold up G.E.'s shares after Mr. Welch retires, not whether he will pull off the acquisition. As part of the acquisition agreement, he delayed his retirement from this April to the end of 2001.</p>
        <p>''Sure, there'll be disruption integrating it and sure, there'll be disruption changing C.E.O.'s,'' said Morton Pierce, chairman of the mergers and acquisitions practice at Dewey Ballantine, a law firm. ''But the two aren't cumulative; it won't result in geometric progression of disruption. It simply becomes the guy who succeeded Babe Ruth: Can he play right field and hit as well as his predecessor?''</p>
        <p>G.E. plans to announce Mr. Welch's successor before the end of the year. But some onlookers question if Mr. Welch's decision to defer his retirement will actually hamper the integration of Honeywell and the management transition.</p>
        <p>''How would you like to be kind of No. 1 in Jack's shadow?'' said Richard A. Bettis, a professor at the University of North Carolina's Kenan-Flagler Business School. ''It'll cause huge problems for the guy who is his successor. People will still be looking to Jack for every major decision. Everything we know about Jack is that he just can't not be involved.''</p>
        <p>As for Mr. Welch, G.E.'s largest individual shareholder, he is the biggest supporter of his final deal. ''I don't own anything else,'' he said. ''G.E. stock going up is all my kids and I got. So if you think I'm running out on that, you're wacky.''</p>
        <p>INVESTING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
