<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Footnotes</title>
    <meta content="29FOOTNOT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="82" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242617"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Home Furnishings</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wolf, Vicente</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Viladas, Pilar</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Home Furnishings</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001029T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE2DD1731F93AA15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1044" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Footnotes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Pilar Viladas</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Viladas, Pilar</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Footnotes on Park Avenue luxury apartment designed by Vicente Wolf; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>1. The dialogue between traditional and modern that characterizes the apartment's interior reflects a similar sensibility in its owners, according to the designer, Vicente Wolf. So it's no surprise that the owners were drawn to artists whose work reveals the same tension. Eric Fischl is known for art that addresses the psychological issues of modern life by figurative means, as in ''The Tire Store'' (a). Ross Bleckner, on the other hand, is known for his richly colored, densely patterned canvases in which the decorative and the abstract combine to evoke various moods, as in ''Covered Slide'' (b).</p>
        <p>2. It isn't every day that an interior designer is also a photographer, but Wolf has been taking photographs for the last 5 years -- after having collected other people's photography for 20. For a designer like Wolf, who must always keep his clients' needs uppermost in his mind, being able to see things his way was liberating. ''For the first time, it was about what I felt and what I liked,'' he explains. Wolf became interested in taking pictures because he needed a new creative outlet: ''I wanted to do something that made me scared -- it's what keeps me young.'' In addition to his fine-art photography (like ''La Romana,'' shown here) and to shooting his own projects, Wolf does the advertising photographs for his own furniture line.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>1. The dialogue between traditional and modern that characterizes the apartment's interior reflects a similar sensibility in its owners, according to the designer, Vicente Wolf. So it's no surprise that the owners were drawn to artists whose work reveals the same tension. Eric Fischl is known for art that addresses the psychological issues of modern life by figurative means, as in ''The Tire Store'' (a). Ross Bleckner, on the other hand, is known for his richly colored, densely patterned canvases in which the decorative and the abstract combine to evoke various moods, as in ''Covered Slide'' (b).</p>
        <p>2. It isn't every day that an interior designer is also a photographer, but Wolf has been taking photographs for the last 5 years -- after having collected other people's photography for 20. For a designer like Wolf, who must always keep his clients' needs uppermost in his mind, being able to see things his way was liberating. ''For the first time, it was about what I felt and what I liked,'' he explains. Wolf became interested in taking pictures because he needed a new creative outlet: ''I wanted to do something that made me scared -- it's what keeps me young.'' In addition to his fine-art photography (like ''La Romana,'' shown here) and to shooting his own projects, Wolf does the advertising photographs for his own furniture line.</p>
        <p>3. Although all the new furniture in this apartment was custom-made, Wolf, like an increasing number of interior designers today, designs home furnishings for production; indeed, he has had licensing arrangements with various manufacturers for the last 15 years, among them Henredon and Niedermaier. His own line, VW Home, (212) 244-5008, makes the Window Table (a), a $3,300 wood, bronze and nickel cocktail table that Wolf designed at tea-table height, ''so you don't have to bend down to pick up a drink,'' and the Night Tray Table (b). This combination bedside table and storage cube ($4,716) -- inspired by the one Wolf designed for the apartment -- has mahogany cabinetry and an inlaid mother-of-pearl tray top. Wolf's newest products include sterling silver flatware for VW Home, stainless-steel flatware for Sasaki and a line of rugs for Tufenkian, which will be available soon.</p>
        <p>4. Victorian-era furniture was last in vogue when Wolf started out, in the 1970's. Then, it was fashionable to mix Victorian and 20th-century pieces in a colorful, funky brand of eclecticism, but Wolf, who was into high tech at the time, wasn't interested. Now, with the benefit of 20-odd years of experience, he is ''not afraid to think of something old next to something new, and to understand the contemporary lines in an antique piece.'' But Wolf prefers 19th-century Italian and Russian pieces to English Victorian, because they aren't as strait-laced. Indeed, what Wolf loves about this Italian chair, which he used in the apartment, is that ''it's very architectural, and it has sex appeal.'' Antiques, the designer says, add that certain ''splash'' to interiors, ''like spices in cooking, or a piece of jewelry.''</p>
        <p>5. Wolf was inspired to hang silk curtains all around the dining room, as a backdrop for the paintings, after seeing them used this way in a Parisian art gallery. (Both the art and the curtains hang from a custom-designed bronze rod.) The art, Wolf says, looked as if it was ''floating on water.'' He drove that metaphor home by using a specially woven Indian silk in an iridescent blue-gray-green that looks to him ''like stormy water.'' The curtains, which were made by Monte Coleman, (212) 463-0085, have a practical advantage too: all that fabric dampens noise, which -- at a dinner party for 30 -- can be considerable.</p>
        <p>-- Pilar Viladas</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
