<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Other Legend of Sleepy Hollow</title>
    <meta content="29LADY$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20001105T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242710"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="GHOST STORIES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cemeteries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sleepy Hollow Cemetery (Ny)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Myths</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sleepy Hollow (Ny)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Thomas, Samuel M (Gen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leary, Robyn</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cemeteries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001029T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E2DB1331F93AA15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1025" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Other Legend of Sleepy Hollow</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBYN LEARY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Leary, Robyn</byline>
      <dateline>SLEEPY HOLLOW</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on mythology surrounding twice-life-size bronze statue of seated woman at Sleepy Hollow Cemetery in Sleepy Hollow, NY; some residents claim to have heard statue weeping and others felt tears on statue, which adorns tomb of Civil War Gen Samuel M Thomas; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE year is 1916. A little girl, 6 or 7, wanders into Sleepy Hollow Cemetery at night on a Halloween dare. She creeps among tombstones and mausoleums until she is stopped by an unsettling sound. It is a woman crying, softly, bitterly.</p>
        <p>Frightened yet determined, the girl makes her way toward the sound and arrives at the statue of a seated woman, twice-life-size. The weeping has stopped but when the girl climbs into the statue's lap and reaches up to touch the face, there are tears under the eyes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE year is 1916. A little girl, 6 or 7, wanders into Sleepy Hollow Cemetery at night on a Halloween dare. She creeps among tombstones and mausoleums until she is stopped by an unsettling sound. It is a woman crying, softly, bitterly.</p>
        <p>Frightened yet determined, the girl makes her way toward the sound and arrives at the statue of a seated woman, twice-life-size. The weeping has stopped but when the girl climbs into the statue's lap and reaches up to touch the face, there are tears under the eyes.</p>
        <p>The little girl was the grandmother of Emily Storms Arminio, a 10th-generation native of Sleepy Hollow, who recalls hearing the tale often.</p>
        <p>Over the years, succeeding generations of Sleepy Hollow residents, the people who Washington Irving described as subject to ''trances and visions,'' have created a ghostly mythology about the statue.</p>
        <p>Some claim to have heard the weeping, others to have felt the tears of this sculpture, which gazes sadly at the tomb of the Civil War general Samuel M. Thomas.</p>
        <p>They call her the Bronze Lady. She might also be called the Other Legend of Sleepy Hollow.</p>
        <p>Anthony J. Marmo, a village native, recalled his experiences with the statue in the early 1970's.</p>
        <p>''She was someone you learned about from the older kids,'' he said. ''Someone who knew the way would take you there. At one time you could hardly find it -- it was hidden by tall rhododendrons.</p>
        <p>Mr. Marmo recalled these Bronze Lady superstitions: ''If you knocked on the door of the general's tomb and looked through the keyhole, you would have a bad dream that night. Of course, that always worked. There was another one where, if you slapped her in the face, sat in her lap and spit in her eye, she would haunt you for the rest of your life. There was always one brave kid who did it.</p>
        <p>''When we got older, we'd be the ones bringing new kids up. One of us would hide behind the statue and come out screaming if a kid had the nerve to sit in her lap -- terrorize him, you know.''</p>
        <p>Sara Mascia, curator of the Tarrytown and Sleepy Hollow Historical Society, said: ''I've heard about her crying.</p>
        <p>''People have told me that she weeps because of some tragedy in her life. Of course, you can find scientific explanations for the tears -- the sculpture interacting with the environment and all that. What I used to hear when I was a kid was that if you're nice to the statue, she'll take care of you.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Mascia's memories include trips to the site at night with her friend who lived across the road from the cemetery, armed with flashlights or candles. ''We never really stayed too long on Halloween,'' she said.</p>
        <p>''If you were really brave you would sit on her lap and be taken care of for life,'' she said. She and her friend never got up the nerve to do that, she added, but they did touch the Lady on a few occasions.</p>
        <p>The sculpture sits between two stately pines in the north central section of the fabled graveyard, the burial place of Washington Irving, Andrew Carnegie, Elizabeth Arden, Thomas J. Watson and many members of the Rockefeller family.</p>
        <p>A shroud covers her wavy bronze locks and a Greco-Roman tunic the rest of her Amazon form. Her forearms are muscled and her hands large and sinewy. There is a forlorn sadness in the slumped shoulders and in the mouth and eyes. Her face is streaked.</p>
        <p>The work, by Andrew O'Connor Jr., a noted sculptor of his day, was commissioned by General Thomas's widow shortly after his death on Jan. 14, 1903. It's called Recuillement, or Grief, and was intended as a memorial figure to be placed in front of the general's tomb.</p>
        <p>The model for the sculpture, Jesse Phoebe Brown, posed frequently for O'Connor's works.</p>
        <p>As told in ''The Sculptors O'Connor'' by Doris Flodin Soderman (Gundi Publishers, 1995), the story goes that O'Connor was pleased with the sculpture but when Mrs. Thomas saw the finished product in his Paris studio, she expressed disappointment that the Lady wasn't gay enough. He told her to return in a week and he would show her another head. She returned and was happy with the results, whereupon O'Connor smashed the new head on the floor.</p>
        <p>''I just made this to show you that I could do it,'' he said, ''but I should never let such a monstrosity out of my studio.''</p>
        <p>Jeannie Galgano, a daughter of a former Sleepy Hollow mayor, remembers her encounters with the legend in the early 1960's.</p>
        <p>''When we were kids, the deal was that you were brave if you went up to the Bronze Lady and you sat in her lap and slapped her across the face and kicked her in the shins. Then you had to go across to the door of the mausoleum and knock on it three times -- and if you did all that, she would come and haunt you. We did it a couple of times but she never came to haunt us.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Arminio, the granddaughter of the little girl of the 1916 ghost story, said her grandmother warned her to be careful when approaching the statue.</p>
        <p>''She said if you went up to the Bronze Lady and touched her face and said a prayer, within 48 hours something would happen,'' she said. ''It would either be very good or very bad. I scoffed at the tale. But two days after I touched the Bronze Lady's face, a storm brought down a tree limb that crushed my Camaro.''</p>
        <p>GHOST STORIES  Correction:  November 5, 2000, Sunday  An article last Sunday about legends surrounding a statue of a woman in the Sleepy Hollow Cemetery misattributed an anecdote about a little girl's visit to the cemetery on a Halloween dare in 1916. It was a fictional ''ghost story,'' not one involving Emily Storms Arminio's grandmother or told by her.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: November 5, 2000, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article last Sunday about legends surrounding a statue of a woman in the Sleepy Hollow Cemetery misattributed an anecdote about a little girl's visit to the cemetery on a Halloween dare in 1916. It was a fictional ''ghost story,'' not one involving Emily Storms Arminio's grandmother or told by her.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
