<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Everyone's Landmark Finally Joins the Landmark Club</title>
    <meta content="29LAND$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20001105T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242904"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: MADISON SQUARE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Life Insurance Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Landmarks Preservation Commission (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kirby, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001029T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E7DD1F31F93AA15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="406" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Everyone's Landmark Finally Joins the Landmark Club</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID KIRBY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kirby, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York City Landmarks Preservation Commission confers landmark status on New York Life Building, neo-Gothic building built in 1928 on Madison Avenue between 26th and 27th Streets; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>More than 70 years after it was built, one of New York's most familiar landmarks has become an official landmark. Last Tuesday, the Landmarks Preservation Commission voted to confer the status on the New York Life Building, the 40-story structure famous for a golden pinnacle that glimmers at sunset and dawn.</p>
        <p>''The New York Life Insurance Company Building has a special character and special historical and aesthetic interest and value as part of the development, heritage and cultural characteristics of New York City,'' the commission report concluded.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>More than 70 years after it was built, one of New York's most familiar landmarks has become an official landmark. Last Tuesday, the Landmarks Preservation Commission voted to confer the status on the New York Life Building, the 40-story structure famous for a golden pinnacle that glimmers at sunset and dawn.</p>
        <p>''The New York Life Insurance Company Building has a special character and special historical and aesthetic interest and value as part of the development, heritage and cultural characteristics of New York City,'' the commission report concluded.</p>
        <p>''It's well-deserving of landmark status, a first-rate building that the company is extremely proud of,'' said Sandra Levine, acting director of the Historic Districts Council, a preservationist group. She said the building is one of the city's ''unprotected gems'' -- structures New Yorkers may think are landmarked but are not.</p>
        <p>The Neo-Gothic building, at 51 Madison Avenue between 26th and 27th Streets, was built on the site of the former Madison Square Garden and completed in 1928. It was designed by Cass Gilbert, the architect of the Woolworth Building, who was inspired by the Gothic towers of Europe.</p>
        <p>The building's most prominent feature, that deep-golden, eight-sided pinnacle, rises six stories. Originally it was made of gold leaf over a copper base, but pollution corroded most of the gold and much of the copper. In 1967, new gold-toned ceramic tiles were installed and part of the stonework on the 34th floor was removed to allow for the bigger, simpler structure (it was refurbished again in 1995). The pinnacle was first lighted on April 12, 1985, to commemorate the 140th anniversary of New York Life.</p>
        <p>So why was the building not designated sooner? ''It was never on anyone's list -- it was never proposed to us,'' said Terri Rosen Deutsch, spokeswoman for the landmarks commission.</p>
        <p>DAVID KIRBY</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: MADISON SQUARE  Correction:  November 5, 2000, Sunday  A chart last Sunday listing facts and figures about the New York Life Building, completed in 1928, misstated the historical importance of its elevators. They were not the first in an office tower; the Equitable Building had elevators when it opened in 1870 at 120 Broadway.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: November 5, 2000, Sunday</p>
        <p>A chart last Sunday listing facts and figures about the New York Life Building, completed in 1928, misstated the historical importance of its elevators. They were not the first in an office tower; the Equitable Building had elevators when it opened in 1870 at 120 Broadway.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
