<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Wag the Human</title>
    <meta content="29GORMANT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242586"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gorman, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Budiansky, Stephen</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Truth About Dogs, The (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001029T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504EFD9123EF93AA15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="744" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Wag the Human</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By James Gorman</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gorman, James</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>James Gorman reviews book The Truth About Dogs: An Inquiry Into the Ancestry, Social Conventions, Mental Habits, and Moral Fiber of Canis Familiaris by Stephen Budiansky (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Truth</p>
        <p>About Dogs</p>
        <p>An Inquiry Into the Ancestry, Social Conventions, Mental Habits, and Moral Fiber</p>
        <p>of Canis Familiaris.</p>
        <p>By Stephen Budiansky.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 263 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Viking. $24.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Truth</p>
        <p>About Dogs</p>
        <p>An Inquiry Into the Ancestry, Social Conventions, Mental Habits, and Moral Fiber</p>
        <p>of Canis Familiaris.</p>
        <p>By Stephen Budiansky.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 263 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Viking. $24.95.</p>
        <p>And what is the truth about dogs? According to Stephen Budiansky, they're parasites. Lovable, yes. Irresistible, absolutely. But con artists of the first degree, molded by evolution to appear loyal, devoted and true, but in fact driven by the desperate desire for chicken skin, half-chewed bones and, in today's world, lots of those incredibly expensive freeze-dried liver treats.</p>
        <p>He's got a point. If you've ever walked a dog on a cold night with a plastic bag for a glove, pleading with your so-called pet to hurry up, you have surely asked yourself just who is whose best friend.</p>
        <p>Budiansky has the answer. ''If biologists weren't victim to the same blindness that afflicts us all, they probably wouldn't hesitate to classify dogs as social parasites.'' They are superbly suited by the shameless fawning behavior common to both dogs and people trying to fit into the human world, mimicking children, friends or lovers and benefiting enormously. What do we get? A few Seeing Eye dogs, some help in finding disaster victims and a lot of ruined rugs.</p>
        <p>The best thing about this claim is that it turns the old-fashioned idea of domestication on its head. Did human beings somehow cleverly snare dogs into miserable bondage? Not a chance, Budiansky says, pointing out failed attempts at domestication of other creatures and arguing that people are just not that smart. ''We didn't choose dogs, after all,'' he writes. ''They chose us, and we're stuck with them.''</p>
        <p>Not that Budiansky doesn't love being the victim of this evolutionary con. He loves dogs, his own and others, helplessly, like millions of other people. He is willing to carry an aging collie up the stairs to his bedroom every night. Why? He can't help it.</p>
        <p>He doesn't want to change the situation, but he'd like to understand it, and he prefers science to sentiment. To that end, in ''The Truth About Dogs'' he has marshaled a whole range of studies, from the genetic to the behavioral, to answer questions, debunk myths and provide interesting anecdotes. The book has its share of hard-nosed biology (in the sections about mitochondrial DNA you really need to pay attention), but it's extraordinarily entertaining -- at least if you're the sort of person who has always wondered whether dogs evolved from wolves or jackals, or whether they really do feel guilt.</p>
        <p>They evolved from wolves, splitting off about 135,000 years ago, and they don't feel guilt, Budiansky says. His reasoning is impeccable. If a dog tucks its tail between its legs and looks abashed when the mess on the floor was actually made by another dog, the dog is not thinking, ''I'm so bad,'' it's thinking, ''He's going to yell, he's going to yell, I better act submissive.''</p>
        <p>I can't say that Budiansky, who has written a number of books about animals, has the last word on all these questions, but every answer he offers is backed up with well-described scientific evidence. When you find yourself disagreeing with him, it only makes reading the book more fun, and there are lots of good stories.</p>
        <p>Here's my favorite: in a test to see if dog breeds really were different, Budiansky reports, ''Border collies would stare at a remote-control toy car for the entire 120 seconds during the test that the car was moving, while Newfoundlands would pay attention to the car only if it ran directly into them.'' If this story makes you laugh, if you know the difference between a Border collie and a Newfoundland (or would like to know), you'll like this book. If you couldn't care less, you should probably stick to political biographies.</p>
        <p>My one complaint is that when Budiansky deconstructs the so-called love and loyalty that dogs have for their owners, he reduces it all to selfish biology. Well, maybe so. But this raises a question: Are there forms of ''love'' and ''loyalty'' in other species (say, human beings) that are not all biology? Are people, in fact, noble, true and loyal while dogs are faking it? I have my doubts, but I look forward to Budiansky writing ''The Truth About Humans'' for the answer.</p>
        <p>James Gorman is editor of the Circuits section of The Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">James Gorman is editor of the Circuits section of The Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
