<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>POSTINGS: $4,800 to $18,000 a Month; In Village, Living Above The Store</title>
    <meta content="29APOS$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242717"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001029T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E6DA1331F93AA15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="468" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>POSTINGS: $4,800 to $18,000 a Month; In Village, Living Above The Store</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Six loft-style luxury apartments are being constructed in two nondescript low-rise buildings atop D'Agostino supermarket in heart of Manhattan's Greenwich Village that are expected to fetch monthly rents of $4,800 to $18,000; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A walkup over a grocery for $216,000 a year?</p>
        <p>From the outside, there is no hint that the two nondescript low-rise buildings that sit atop portions of a D'Agostino supermarket in the heart of Greenwich Village contain luxury apartments being offered for rent for as much as $18,000 a month.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A walkup over a grocery for $216,000 a year?</p>
        <p>From the outside, there is no hint that the two nondescript low-rise buildings that sit atop portions of a D'Agostino supermarket in the heart of Greenwich Village contain luxury apartments being offered for rent for as much as $18,000 a month.</p>
        <p>Indeed even the interior entrances of the two connected buildings that sit next to each other in an L-shaped configuration at Greenwich and Bethune Streets represent understatement carried to great lengths. There are no lobbies, no doormen, not even elevators.</p>
        <p>But inside, there is little stinting on luxury in the six loft-style apartments being carved out of what was once a steel fabricating plant (Greenwich Street) and a coal yard (Bethune).</p>
        <p>Among the amenities in the units, which range from a studio to a four-bedroom, 2,300-square-foot penthouse, are outdoor decks that run as much as 2,500 square feet, 10-foot ceilings, in one case a 65-foot living room, and double-sided fireplaces.</p>
        <p>Even the one studio in the project has a large kitchen and balcony and, with 1,000 square feet, has sufficient space to create a separate bedroom. It will rent for $4,800 a month.</p>
        <p>To conform with requirements of the Landmarks Preservation Commission, the windows are modern interpretations of the old industrial sash style.</p>
        <p>''Because the buildings are in the Greenwich Village Historic District, it took quite a bit to design and get it accepted by the landmarks commission,'' said Mark Scott, the architect on the project. ''It had to be in context of the existing fabric.''</p>
        <p>The developer is Greenwich Associates, a partnership of members of the D'Agostino family that also operates the ground-floor supermarket. ''We had owned the building for a number of years and realized we had the opportunity to do something better there,'' said Nicholas D'Agostino 3rd, vice president for corporate administration of the supermarket chain.</p>
        <p>It is the family's first foray into residential real estate, but probably not its last.</p>
        <p>''It depends on what opportunities come around,'' Mr. D'Agostino said. ''It is important to have commercial property downstairs because that is our market.''</p>
        <p>Is he considering living above the store himself?  ''It might be nice to retire there,'' Mr. D'Agostino said, ''but I can't consider it seriously now. I have four young children.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
