<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BENEFITS</title>
    <meta content="29BENE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Society Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242883"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001029T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E6DF1F31F93AA15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="3548" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BENEFITS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Prince and the Academy  MONDAY -- The annual black-tie dinner-dance of the American Associates of the Royal Academy Trust will be held at the Rainbow Room, raising money to catalog the permanent collection at the Royal Academy of Art in London. Prince Andrew, the Duke of York, will briefly speak. The evening will begin with cocktails at 7:30 followed by dinner at 8:30 and dancing to the music of Bob Hardwick Sound. Tickets, $600, from (212) 980-8404.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A Prince and the Academy  MONDAY -- The annual black-tie dinner-dance of the American Associates of the Royal Academy Trust will be held at the Rainbow Room, raising money to catalog the permanent collection at the Royal Academy of Art in London. Prince Andrew, the Duke of York, will briefly speak. The evening will begin with cocktails at 7:30 followed by dinner at 8:30 and dancing to the music of Bob Hardwick Sound. Tickets, $600, from (212) 980-8404.</p>
        <p>Scholarship Support  MONDAY -- The Thurgood Marshall Scholarship Fund, which provides financial aid to students attending black public colleges and universities, will hold a fund-raising dinner at the Sheraton New York. Lynn Whitfield, an actress, will be a host, and Dr. Eddie N. Moore Jr., the president of Virginia State University, and Tommy Mottola, the chairman of Sony Music Entertainment, will be among those honored. The evening begins with a reception and silent auction at 6, followed by dinner and the awards. Black tie. Tickets, $500, from (212) 888-7003.</p>
        <p>Bette Midler Goes Hawaiian  MONDAY -- Bette Midler's Aloha Ball will raise money for the New York Restoration Project, an organization she founded to create, restore and maintain parks and community gardens in the five boroughs of New York. The event, at the Manhattan Center, 311 West 34th Street (Eighth Avenue) will have Ms. Midler as its host and begin at 6:30 with mai tais and pu pu platters. A Hawaiian-theme dinner will follow, with performances by Hawaiian singers and dancers. Rosie O'Donnell will then lead a live auction, with chances to bid on a dinner for 10 with Ms. Midler at Balthazar, the SoHo restaurant, and opportunities to appear in films and television shows. The comedians Jackie Mason and Dom Irrera will perform. Hawaiian attire or Halloween costumes suggested. Tickets, $500, (212) 627-1000.</p>
        <p>One for the Road  MONDAY -- Barbara Cook, the cabaret singer, will perform at a fund-raiser for the Acting Company, a nonprofit touring group that presents classic and contemporary plays and musicals in communities where live theater is rare. The organization also works with schoolchildren across the country, teaching theater, poetry writing and literary appreciation. The evening, at the Copacabana, 617 West 57th (11th Avenue), begins with cocktails at 6:15, followed by dinner and dancing at 7:30. The actor Kevin Kline, a board member, will present an award to the philanthropist Joan Warburg for her contributions to live American theater. Costumes or black tie. Tickets, $450, from (212) 944-5517.</p>
        <p>A Party for the Dia Arts Center  WEDNESDAY -- The Dia Center for the Arts will benefit from a party at its museum, at 548 West 22nd Street (10th Avenue). The event will begin at 7 with drinks and a viewing of artworks currently being exhibited, including an installation by Jorge Pardo and paintings by Bridget Riley. Dinner will follow. Proceeds will support the museum's exhibitions and its community outreach programs, which include classes for  public school teachers and students on contemporary art and poetry, along with museum visits, lectures and studio workshops. Tickets, $1,000, from (212) 293-5504.</p>
        <p>For Visiting Nurses  WEDNESDAY -- A dinner-dance at the Rainbow Room will raise money for the Visiting Nurse Service of New York's programs for elderly people, which include mental health counseling, post-hospital care and low-cost care for those needing it. Richard S. Braddock, the chairman of Priceline.com, will be honored. Cocktails at 6:30 will be followed by dinner and dancing to the music of the Alex Donner Orchestra. Black tie. Tickets, $750, from (212) 794-6341.</p>
        <p>Stepping Up to the Plate  WEDNESDAY -- The Boys Club of New York will hold its annual All Sports Hall of Fame Dinner at the Waldorf-Astoria. Among the athletes scheduled to attend are Jack Nicklaus, Yogi Berra, Larry Doby, George Blanda, Oscar Robertson, Ed Giacomin and Rosie Casals. The black-tie event, which will support the organization's camps, scholarships, and athletic and educational programs, will begin with cocktails at 6:30. Len Berman, a sports anchor on WNBC-TV, will be the master of ceremonies. Tickets, $1,000, from (212) 997-0100</p>
        <p>Living Landmarks  WEDNESDAY -- Arie L. Kopelman, Louis S. Auchincloss, Jerry Orbach, Sam Waterston, Betty Allen, Paul Binder, Michael Christensen and Joseph F. Cullman III are this year's crop of ''living landmarks,'' to be designated at the annual dinner-dance of the New York Landmarks Conservancy at the Plaza. The event raises money for the organization's preservation and restoration and rehabilitation programs, which have included creating affordable housing in landmark buildings. Two living landmarks from previous years will be there: Liz Smith, the host, and Peter Duchin, who will perform with his orchestra. The black-tie evening begins with drinks at 7. Tickets, $500, from (212) 995-5260.</p>
        <p>Doing Good by Eating Well  THURSDAY -- Daniel Boulud will cook an appetizer and receive an award at a black-tie dinner at the University Club. The event will raise money for the community service, advocacy, research and education  programs of the Greater New York Chapter of the March of Dimes. French chefs from Provence and restaurants in New York will prepare the rest of the meal. David Rosengarten, host of a cooking program on the Food Network, will be the master of ceremonies. Cocktails at 7. Tickets, $500, from (212) 353-8365.</p>
        <p>Preserving the Past  THURSDAY -- The Metropolitan Historic Structures Association, representing 85 historic sites in New York and New Jersey, will hold a reception to raise money for its lecture program on conservation of historic sites and to support distribution of its guidebook ''Glimpses of Old New York: House Museums and Historic Sites.'' Arthur Rosenblatt and Page Ayres Cowley, architects, will be honored for their efforts in historic preservation. The event will begin at 5:30 at one of the sites, the Museum House of the Colonial Dames in the State of New York, 215 East 71st Street. Tickets, $50, from (212) 685-9723.</p>
        <p>Fostering Education  THURSDAY -- Mary J. Blige, the singer, Russell Simmons, the impresario, and Howard Dodson, the director of the Schomburg Center for Research in Black Culture, will be honored at a black-tie dinner and dance at the New York Hilton. The event will raise money for the education programs of One Hundred Black Men Inc., which include mentoring, tutoring and college scholarships. Cocktails at 7:30. Tickets, $275, from (212) 777-7070.</p>
        <p>An All-Star Line-Up  THURSDAY -- WNYC, the public radio station, will honor Sarah Jessica Parker, the actress; Joan Weill, the chairwoman of the Alvin Ailey American Dance Theater; and her husband, Sanford I. Weill, the chairman of Citigroup, at a black-tie dinner at Cipriani, 110 East 42nd Street. The proceeds will help the station buy its broadcast licenses from New York City. The writer Calvin Trillin will be host, and the Eroica Trio will perform. Cocktails at 6:30 will be followed by dinner and the program at 7:30. Tickets, $500, from (212) 614-0400.</p>
        <p>Fun With, and for, Kids  FRIDAY -- The Big Apple Circus will hold its annual gala under the big tent at Lincoln Center's Damrosch Park. The evening will benefit the circus's community outreach programs, which include the Clown Care Unit for hospitalized children, the Circus for the Senses for children with difficulties hearing or seeing, free and low-cost tickets to the circus, and Beyond the Ring, which teaches circus skills to children 8 to 18. The event begins at 6 with cocktails, hors d'oeuvres and a boxed dinner, followed by the show at 7. Dessert and dancing will follow in the ring. Tickets, $200, or $100 for children 12 and under, from (212) 268-2500, ext. 129.</p>
        <p>Taking Bets  FRIDAY -- The annual Gamboling Gala, held by United Cerebral Palsy of New York City, will be at the New York Hilton and feature casino-style games of chance. Guests will have an opportunity to spend their ''winnings'' on jewels, furs, luggage and electronic equipment. The black-tie event raises money for the organization's services in New York, which include clinics, preschools and adult day care programs. A cocktail reception at 7 will be followed by a buffet dinner and dancing. Tickets, $750, from (212) 683-6700, ext. 205.</p>
        <p>Pilgrims' Progress  FRIDAY -- The Society of Mayflower Descendants in the State of New York will hold its annual ball at the St. Regis. Frances Daly Fergusson, the president of Vassar College, will be honored. The evening will benefit the society's education programs, which include visits to New York area schools by costumed guides from Plimouth Plantation, a ''living history'' museum in Plymouth, Mass., and awards to graduating high school seniors. Cocktails at 7:30 will be followed by dinner, dancing and the presentation of debutantes. Black or white tie. Tickets, $250, or $175 for those under 35, from (212) 759-1620.</p>
        <p>Hebrew Home Honors  NEXT SUNDAY -- The Hebrew Home for the Aged in Riverdale, the Bronx,  will honor Richard A. Grasso, the chairman of the New York Stock Exchange, at a dinner at the Waldorf-Astoria. Cocktails begin at 6, followed by dinner and dancing. Black tie. Tickets, $1,000, from (718) 581-1234.</p>
        <p>Whitney Gala  NOV. 6 -- The Whitney Museum of American Art will hold its annual gala at the museum. Guests will view its retrospective of Edward Steichen's photographs and other works, and the cabaret artist Andrea Marcovicci will perform. The black-tie event will raise money for the museum's collection, exhibitions and educational programs. Drinks at 7 will be followed by dinner and dancing in the Emily Fisher Landau Gallery at 8. From 9 to 1 a.m., guests will move to the Robert J. Hurst Gallery for dessert and dancing. Tickets, $1,000, or $150 for entry at 9 for dancing and dessert, from (212) 935-1033.</p>
        <p>Fighting Cancer  NOV. 6 -- The American-Italian Cancer Foundation will hold its annual gala at Cipriani, 110 East 42nd Street. The evening will raise money for the organization's research and fellowships in Italy and the United States, and for free mammograms and prostate cancer screenings in the New York area. Cocktails and a silent auction at 6 will be followed by a live auction, dinner and an awards ceremony. Tickets, $800, or $250 for those 35 and younger, from (212) 628-9090.</p>
        <p>Indigo Girls at the Pierre  NOV. 7 -- The Indigo Girls will perform at a benefit at the Pierre for the American Indian College Fund. Sherman Alexie, a Native American writer and poet, will be the master of ceremonies, and the event will raise money for scholarships and programs at the organization's 31 member institutions. Cocktails at 6:30 will be followed by dinner an hour later, and the performance will begin at 9:15. Black tie or native dress. Tickets, $500, or $85 for the show alone, from (212) 787-6312.</p>
        <p>Harvest Ball  NOV. 8 -- The Federation of Protestant Welfare Agencies will hold its annual Harvest Ball at the Lighthouse at the Chelsea Piers Sports Complex. The event raises money for the organization and its member agencies, which provide a variety of social services. John C. Whitehead, a former co-chairman of Goldman, Sachs &amp; Company, will be among the honorees. Cocktails and a silent auction at 6, with dinner and dancing to follow at 7; black tie. Tickets, $500, from (212) 838-2660.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
