<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Way We Live Now: 10-29-00; Pro Pharma</title>
    <meta content="WLN103152" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242674"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sullivan, Andrew</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Pharmaceutical, Biotechnology and Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001029T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E6D81231F93AA15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1032" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Way We Live Now: 10-29-00; Pro Pharma</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Andrew Sullivan</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sullivan, Andrew</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Andrew Sullivan article lauds America's pharmaceutical companies for discoveries over past decade that treat wide variety of ailments and illnesses; photo; table (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Here's an unfashionable romance: I love America's pharmaceutical companies. As a slogan, ''Better Living Through Pharmaceuticals'' still has a campy, futuristic ring to it, but for me, at least, there's nothing sci-fi about it. Because I have H.I.V., I swallow around 800 pills of prescription drugs a month and around 400 extra pills -- vitamins, antidiarrheic, antinausea pills and the like -- to contain the side effects of the first 800. That's close to 15,000 pills a year. When I first tested positive, I had a dream that I was walking down the street shaking like a baby's rattle because there were so many pills inside me. Eight years later, that shaking has become white noise. I asked my pharmacist the other day to tote up the annual bill (which my insurance mercifully pays): $15,600, easily more than I pay separately for housing, food, travel or clothes.</p>
        <p>I'm an extreme case -- along with many others now living relatively normally with chronic illnesses -- but I'm not completely atypical. Over the last decade, as new and better prescription drugs have become our primary form of health care, our common spending on them has soared. In 1999 alone, according to a study conducted by an independent consulting group, overall expenditure on prescription drugs in America rose by 19 percent -- but only 4 percent of that was because of increased prices. We're simply taking advantage of living in the 21st century and medicating ourselves to the gills.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Here's an unfashionable romance: I love America's pharmaceutical companies. As a slogan, ''Better Living Through Pharmaceuticals'' still has a campy, futuristic ring to it, but for me, at least, there's nothing sci-fi about it. Because I have H.I.V., I swallow around 800 pills of prescription drugs a month and around 400 extra pills -- vitamins, antidiarrheic, antinausea pills and the like -- to contain the side effects of the first 800. That's close to 15,000 pills a year. When I first tested positive, I had a dream that I was walking down the street shaking like a baby's rattle because there were so many pills inside me. Eight years later, that shaking has become white noise. I asked my pharmacist the other day to tote up the annual bill (which my insurance mercifully pays): $15,600, easily more than I pay separately for housing, food, travel or clothes.</p>
        <p>I'm an extreme case -- along with many others now living relatively normally with chronic illnesses -- but I'm not completely atypical. Over the last decade, as new and better prescription drugs have become our primary form of health care, our common spending on them has soared. In 1999 alone, according to a study conducted by an independent consulting group, overall expenditure on prescription drugs in America rose by 19 percent -- but only 4 percent of that was because of increased prices. We're simply taking advantage of living in the 21st century and medicating ourselves to the gills.</p>
        <p>This is our country on drugs. You can bash the ''big pharmaceutical companies'' all you want, but their products are among the most popular around. We can now treat arthritis, balding, impotence, depression, obesity, not to speak of cancer, heart disease, diabetes, in ways that were, only recently, a matter of science fiction. In the last 10 years, with the possible exception of information technology, no industry has more thoroughly transformed our lives. Calculating the economic benefits of this is impossible -- but think of the new antidepressants alone. If you know one person whose life has been overhauled by a stabler supply of serotonin, the ''happy'' chemical in our brain, then imagine the impact multiplied by millions. Or consider protease inhibitors. Thousands of H.I.V.-positive people are now contributing to the economy who might, without the drugs, be dead, sick or draining resources in hospital care. Perhaps it takes seeing the transformation in your own life to fully appreciate what drugs can do for the society as a whole.</p>
        <p>But what is our response to this? We complain about the price. According to polls, the cost of medicine is one of the hottest issues in this election. Vice President Al Gore has warned of price gouging by ''powerful forces.'' In a move intended to lower drug costs at home, Congress has passed a bill that will let anyone reimport American prescription drugs sold more cheaply overseas. Both major candidates have pledged to do something to subsidize or pay for medicines under Medicare. Whoever wins the election, the federal government's bargaining power with major drug companies is almost certainly going to be ratcheted up, forcing prices -- and profits -- down.</p>
        <p>What's not to like? Well, as with many other debates in this election, no one wants to point out that there's a trade-off. It would be wonderful if we could make the newest drugs affordable for anyone who needs them and keep the lifesaving research going. But cut prices and you cut profits. Cut profits and you cut research and development. Cut research and you slow new drug innovation. You may get cheaper and more widely available drugs in the short term, but you'll also get worse drugs in the long term, and risk ending the greatest era in research in memory. Don't big pharmaceuticals make enough money to take a hit? Sure, their profitability is slightly higher than some other industries -- but that barely offsets the unique risks the drug industry has to take. Of more than 5,000 potential medicines tested at some point in the lab, on average only 3 get into clinical trials, and only 1 is approved for patient use. In all, only 30 percent of drugs make enough money to recoup the cost of their own research, and the average time it took to bring a new drug to market in the 1990's was close to 15 years, at an average cost, according to Boston Consulting Group, of $500 million.</p>
        <p>The only way these risks will be run is if the payoff is big enough. Slap on de facto price controls, squeeze profits to get more short-term access for more people -- and you'll have one sure result. Investment for research will dry up, innovation will slow down and the great gains of the last decade will recede into history. Those gains are not just for the wealthy. Once patents run out and generics compete, the pricey innovations we now encourage lead to cheaper, better drugs for everyone. This is particularly true for the small, high-risk bio-tech companies that have pioneered some of the most substantial breakthroughs of the last few years.</p>
        <p>The private sector is now responsible for more than 70 percent of all the pharmaceutical research in this country -- and that share is growing. Whether we like it or not, these private entities have our lives in their hands. And we can either be grown-ups and acknowledge this or be infantile and scapegoat them. They're not ''powerful forces,'' penalizing America's ''working families.'' They're entrepreneurs trying to make money by saving lives. By and large, they succeed in both. Every morning I wake up and feel fine, I'm thankful that they do.</p>
        <p>Andrew Sullivan, a contributing writer to the magazine, has a new Web site, www.andrewsullivan.com.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Andrew Sullivan, a contributing writer to the magazine, has a new Web site, www.andrewsullivan.com.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
