<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Clueless in Virginia</title>
    <meta content="29CAREYT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242580"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carey, Jacqueline</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pearson, T R</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Blue Ridge (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001029T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E0D9123EF93AA15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1374" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Clueless in Virginia</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jacqueline Carey</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Carey, Jacqueline</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jacqueline Carey reviews novel Blue Ridge by T R Pearson; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BLUE RIDGE</p>
        <p>By T. R. Pearson.</p>
        <p>243 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Viking. $24.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BLUE RIDGE</p>
        <p>By T. R. Pearson.</p>
        <p>243 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Viking. $24.95.</p>
        <p>I wish more mainstream writers turned out the occasional mystery. There are notable exceptions, but most American detective novels are composed with all the verve and originality of the instruction manual that came with your food processor. And thanks to the iron grip of Raymond Chandler, that mystery-cum-manual is probably littered with preposterous metaphors that are better read with your eyes half shut, for your own protection. (English whodunits, on the other hand, are generally worse.)</p>
        <p>I can say all this because I am an indefatigable fan of the mystery genre. As such, I was curious to see what T. R. Pearson would do with it in his new book, ''Blue Ridge.'' Pearson is best known for ''A Short History of a Small Place,'' a deceptively folksy, highly ornate exploration of a suicide in a small Southern town. Every long-winded writer who ever set foot south of the Mason-Dixon line has been compared to Faulkner, but there's no getting around it -- A Short History of a Small Place'' is definitely Faulknerian. In mystery circles, Faulkner is best known for remaining indisputably himself when he wrote the detective stories in ''Knight's Gambit.'' Pearson, too, remains his neo-Faulknerian self in ''Blue Ridge,'' and the results are delightful.</p>
        <p>The book alternates between two crime stories, and -- on the surface, at least -- the conventions are followed. Ray Tatum, a new deputy sheriff in Hogarth, Va., is directed by a couple of hikers to a pile of bare bones just off the Appalachian Trail. The skull is caved in. For the investigation, he is teamed up, buddy-movie style, with a tough black Park Service employee who could be played by Pam Grier. (''Well, well,'' she says to one man they're questioning, ''if it isn't Superfly.'')</p>
        <p>The other story concerns Ray's cousin Paul, an actuary in Roanoke, who is asked to come to New York to identify the body of his son. Paul has never really been acquainted with the young man (more on that later), but he dutifully goes north and winds up being escorted around Manhattan by various colorful cops and criminals, all of whom are very interested in what exactly happened to this ne'er-do-well.</p>
        <p>The two puzzles end in real solutions, with none of the life-will-always-be-unknowable evasions found in many literary expositions of the genre. The solutions are simple and believable, not surprising -- but that isn't the point. Pearson is up to a lot more here.</p>
        <p>''Blue Ridge'' is much funnier than most mysteries: not too broad, not too dry, effortlessly finding the right tone, time after time. Paul, who can be devastatingly honest about his own haplessness, finds himself in especially ludicrous situations. (On an earlier trip to New York for an actuarial conference, he and a colleague decided to save money and stay in Weehawken, N. J., near the Lincoln Tunnel, in a motel that advertised rooms by the hour. As he recalls the story, the motel manager and a customer abandoned a heated argument and stood in stunned silence when confronted by the two men's request, ''helplessly constrained, I have to think now, to imagine me and Lowell engaged together in some manner of middle-aged white-boy sexual congress, 72 prepaid hours of swampy actuarial love.'')</p>
        <p>The splicing together of the two different plots puzzled me at first. The investigations start off unrelated and remain so throughout the book. (I think I can give that much away.) But gradually it became clear how very shrewd this decision was. Paul's story confounds expectations at every turn, from the moment a local policeman shows up at his insurance firm, obviously bearing bad news. Paul casts his mind over his family tree, trying to figure out which relative has died. When he is told it is his son, he pauses, then says, ''Who?'' It's a funny line, and quickly explained by the circumstances: the boy was conceived after a casual fling in the early 1970's and his now-deceased mother opted for single parenthood; Paul has seen his offspring only once or twice in over 20 years. But that ''Who?'' is also indicative of the poison in Paul's personality. He has no feel at all for human ties. His cousin Ray is the more usual solitary detective type: he's divorced; he wanders from job to job. But it's all because of a horrible loss in Ray's past for which he feels responsible. His presence is an implicit criticism of Paul, a character it would be hard to read a whole book about.</p>
        <p>After consulting an advice column in the newspaper about ways to ease up on his compulsive tidiness, Paul picks out a dog at the pound. But the dog annoys him, and one night he neglects to let his new pet back in the house. Later, when a neighbor with two kids asks if the dog is his, Paul says, ''Never seen him before'' and suggests that she keep him. This is the sort of thing heroes of detective novels do before they inexplicably go off and risk death to save the lives of strangers. The idea is that the dog would be better off with the neighbor, so the hero sacrifices his own comfort. You are never supposed to believe the crusty excuses he makes. But in ''Blue Ridge,'' even though you may be laughing at the way Paul tells the story, abandoning a dog turns out to be nothing more than abandoning a dog.</p>
        <p>In a comic novel, you'd barely notice Paul's fecklessness. In a detective novel, which depends on an exaggerated sense of responsibility in the hero, Paul's failings are always sneaking up on you. He sees people being threatened, injured and killed, and he doesn't seem to care. The real suspense here is whether this man will ever be roused from his almost sociopathic numbness.</p>
        <p>A whole series of parallel situations between Ray's story and Paul's reinforces the contrast between the two men: children lost, sexual favors offered, household furnishings inventoried. Ray even has a neighbor who has obsessively searched for his missing dog for 25 years. If all this sounds too schematic, it is -- a little. (It's also hard to forgive Pearson's use of the word ''closure,'' ironic or not.) But a mystery is defined by its artifice.</p>
        <p>Pearson has never been timid about pushing form to its limits, and his splendid prose is also artificial, stunningly so -- high-pitched, evocative, decorative and closer to the human heart than the rictus-grinned pseudorealism of many modern mysteries. For Pearson, aesthetics are the stuff of life. In the beginning of ''Blue Ridge,'' Ray gets thrown out of a motel because his dog barks at the cheesy furnishings. On the other hand, Paul's admiration of the impeccable taste of the criminal who first has him beaten up and then wines and dines him is a failing we cannot forgive.</p>
        <p>At one point, a New York detective asks for Paul's help in going through the stuff in his son's apartment and Paul comes across a photograph of the young man's mother:</p>
        <p>''She'd grown jowly, and her hair was cropped close and highlighted. She was standing in front of a run of board fencing, alongside a spruce the color of bread mold, was grinning slightly and looked tired to me, looked a trifle disappointed.</p>
        <p>'' 'How about her?' Doogan had emerged from the closet with a glossy 8 by 10 in hand, a photo of an arrestingly shapely woman in a bikini who cradled a spear gun in her arms.</p>
        <p>'' 'Ursula Andress,' I told him.</p>
        <p>''Doogan flipped the thing over for a closer look. 'Oh.' ''</p>
        <p>This moment of deflation seems so obvious that I can't believe I haven't come across something similar in the thousands of scenes I've read in which a victim's belongings are examined. Or maybe I have, but it wasn't as beautifully handled. Maybe it didn't demonstrate so pointedly the sad gap between pop-culture crime and real-life crime.</p>
        <p>Practitioners and fans of the mystery genre have long used Faulkner to shore up its sometimes shaky reputation. Sooner or later, they'll be doing the same with T. R. Pearson.</p>
        <p>Jacqueline Carey is the author of ''The Other Family,'' a novel, and ''Good Gossip,'' a collection of stories.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Jacqueline Carey is the author of ''The Other Family,'' a novel, and ''Good Gossip,'' a collection of stories.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
