<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Leaving His Home of 45 Years, An 89-Year-Old Starts Anew</title>
    <meta content="29MILE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242714"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MILESTONES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Retirement Communities and Assisted Living</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stevens, Larry</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ames, Lynne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retirement Communities and Assisted Living</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retirement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001029T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01EFDB1331F93AA15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="938" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Leaving His Home of 45 Years, An 89-Year-Old Starts Anew</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYNNE AMES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ames, Lynne</byline>
      <dateline>MOUNT VERNON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Larry Stevens, 89, describes his transition from living in independent apartment to becoming resident of Meadowview, assisted-living complex in Mount Vernon, NY; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LARRY STEVENS just made a major move, and Ralphie came with him. Ralphie is an affectionate brown tabby cat; Mr. Stevens is an 89-year-old retired accountant who last week left his New Rochelle home of 45 years and moved to a one-bedroom unit in Meadowview, an assisted-living complex that is part of the Wartburg Adult Care Community here.</p>
        <p>On a recent afternoon, golden autumn sunlight streamed through the windows of Mr. Stevens's new living room. Ralphie investigated a well-cushioned chair and began to doze. His owner talked about his personal journey, the move from the spacious five-room apartment where he lived with his wife, Elsie, to a situation where meals are taken in a communal dining room, residents congregate in lobbies and lounges, and a nurse is always on call.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LARRY STEVENS just made a major move, and Ralphie came with him. Ralphie is an affectionate brown tabby cat; Mr. Stevens is an 89-year-old retired accountant who last week left his New Rochelle home of 45 years and moved to a one-bedroom unit in Meadowview, an assisted-living complex that is part of the Wartburg Adult Care Community here.</p>
        <p>On a recent afternoon, golden autumn sunlight streamed through the windows of Mr. Stevens's new living room. Ralphie investigated a well-cushioned chair and began to doze. His owner talked about his personal journey, the move from the spacious five-room apartment where he lived with his wife, Elsie, to a situation where meals are taken in a communal dining room, residents congregate in lobbies and lounges, and a nurse is always on call.</p>
        <p>''I didn't cry when I left my old place,'' he said. ''I didn't turn around and say, 'So long, apartment.' I just left.</p>
        <p>''In April, I saw a video about Meadowview. It didn't give me any big sales pitch, they didn't have to lay it on me. I had the feeling that this was the time, it just felt right.''</p>
        <p>Events leading up to the move were like those that countless others have faced. In a sense, the transition began 15 years ago when Mrs. Stevens died, although at the time Mr. Stevens never thought about leaving the apartment. Mrs. Stevens had been in bad health, with cancer and other illnesses, and her husband was accustomed to taking care not only of her but of himself as well. He cooked, cleaned, went to work, did everything necessary for daily living.</p>
        <p>But when he suffered two bouts of congestive heart failure last year, even mundane tasks became overwhelming. When he came home from his most recent hospitalization, his son, Bruce, who lives in Manhattan, arranged for a home health aide to be in the apartment.</p>
        <p>''Sophie stayed with me; all she had to do was be there,'' Mr. Stevens recalled. ''She didn't have to bathe me or anything. I just needed to know someone was there. It scares you when you wake up in the middle of the night and feel you can't breathe.''</p>
        <p>Life, however, was becoming more restrictive. Mr. Stevens's son read about the new assisted living building at the Wartburg, which also has on its campus independent living cottages and a skilled nursing home. He suggested that his father investigate, even though the building was still under construction.</p>
        <p>''I came here in the spring, before it was finished,'' Mr. Stevens said. ''I liked the campus. They showed me a video of what the apartments would look like. But I didn't see an actual model apartment until Sept. 28.''</p>
        <p>The quarters are smaller than what Mr. Stevens was used to, but once he made up his mind, he would not be deterred. There is, for example, a small refrigerator and microwave, but no actual kitchen. ''I knew I'd have room for snacks, but no actual cooking facilities, so I reconciled myself to what was going to be.''</p>
        <p>Some of his furniture made the trip; certain larger pieces did not.</p>
        <p>''I did some purging in my apartment.'' He offered to donate his piano to Meadowview and they accepted. Now it is in one of the public rooms and, although he has not yet had time to play, he plans to entertain other residents with tunes like his favorites, ''As Time Goes By'' and ''If I Loved You.''</p>
        <p>''When I get to playing again it'll make a lot of people happy,'' he said. ''The songs I play will be songs they recognize. I'm like a barroom pianist -- put a list of songs in front of me and I'll improvise.''</p>
        <p>Although he never played piano professionally, Mr. Stevens was in a form of show business: from 1947 to 1950, he owned rides at carnivals. His biggest money-maker, he said, was the Roll-O-Plane, which he renamed the dive bomber ''for flair,'' which churned and turned riders upside down. So successful was he at his short stint in the amusement business, he was once offered the chance to manage Playland. ''I turned it down -- I didn't want to be king for a day. I've got no regrets.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, he seems to have few regrets about anything, including his move. An optimist who manages to be upbeat without being saccharine, his voice took on a wistful tone only once, as he was describing a favorite piece of furniture that could not make the trip.</p>
        <p>''It was something called a cellarette,'' he said. ''There's a liquor cabinet on the bottom, and when you open it up, the top becomes a bar with a Bakelite finish. The center part held highball glasses, ice bucket, decanters and cocktail shakers. That was one of my favorite pieces because it reminded me of good times.</p>
        <p>''When my wife and I entertained, we would work off of it. My son is taking it, so at least it stays in the family.'' He paused. ''Like I said, I liked it because it reminded me of good times that we had, fun we had all those years ago.''</p>
        <p>MILESTONES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
