<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fishing Maven Adopts an Artificial Reef</title>
    <meta content="29JOUR$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242702"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="LONG ISLAND JOURNAL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fishing, Sport</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reefs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Barges and Scows</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tugboats</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Legal Profession</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnson, Rich</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Burton, William C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fischler, Marcelle S</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Fishing, Line, The (Tv Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Fishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legal Profession</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fishing, Sport</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boats and Boating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001029T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E4DC1331F93AA15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1676" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fishing Maven Adopts an Artificial Reef</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARCELLE S. FISCHLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fischler, Marcelle S</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Long Island Journal column: fishing philanthropist Rich Johnson, host of Fishing Line radio and television shows, pays to have two barges and old tugboat sunk to augment artificial reef 3 miles off Jones Inlet; William C Burton, insurance lobbyist and lawyer from East Hills who advocates clear, cogent writing, founds Burton Award for Legal Achievement; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LANDLUBBERS might adopt a highway or a park. But Rich Johnson is a fishing philanthropist. He spends his days plying the waters around Long Island, searching for the best spots to cast a line. To create a habitat for sea bass, fluke, blackfish and porgies, fish that like rocks and the bottom of the ocean, he recently adopted an artificial reef.</p>
        <p>Not that paying for the sinking of two barges and an old tugboat was entirely altruistic. Mr. Johnson, 46, of East Atlantic Beach, is host of ''The Fishing Line'' radio and television shows, and he earns his living telling others where and when the fish are running. So what better place to send his fans than to the Fishing Line Reef, his personal fishing trove?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LANDLUBBERS might adopt a highway or a park. But Rich Johnson is a fishing philanthropist. He spends his days plying the waters around Long Island, searching for the best spots to cast a line. To create a habitat for sea bass, fluke, blackfish and porgies, fish that like rocks and the bottom of the ocean, he recently adopted an artificial reef.</p>
        <p>Not that paying for the sinking of two barges and an old tugboat was entirely altruistic. Mr. Johnson, 46, of East Atlantic Beach, is host of ''The Fishing Line'' radio and television shows, and he earns his living telling others where and when the fish are running. So what better place to send his fans than to the Fishing Line Reef, his personal fishing trove?</p>
        <p>While it wasn't quite the sinking of the Titanic, the making of an environmentally friendly artificial reef provides solid film footage. Mr. Johnson's half-hour television fishing show is broadcast 26 Saturday mornings a year at 9 a.m. on Channel 55. His audio program, also called ''The Fishing Line,'' is chock full of fishing tips and runs from 4 to 6:30 p.m. every Saturday on WGBB.</p>
        <p>Early on a recent morning, as Mike Mirabella, a cameraman, videotaped, and Corey Arnold, Mr. Johnson's editor and fellow fishing aficionado, gave instructions, Mr. Johnson marked the reef's location -- 3 miles out from Jones Inlet, with the Long Beach skyline visible in the distance -- by tossing two plastic jugs off Capt. Nick Montello's boat, Bottom Line, to use as temporary markers</p>
        <p>Then, doing what he called ''research and development,'' Mr. Johnson pulled out a fishing rod, attached a bit of banana peel to the hook and cast his line. Seconds later he reeled in a bunker fish to use as bait.</p>
        <p>''I give the viewers a good place to fish in close to shore to say thanks for watching and supporting us all this year,'' Mr. Johnson said as two tugboats from the Town of Hempstead chugged into view, pushing two discarded payload barges and a stripped tugboat toward the reef.</p>
        <p>''I also do it as a gift to my advertisers who are party boats and charter boats like Captain Nick who can use it as a place to take people fishing,'' Mr. Johnson said.</p>
        <p>While he did a segment for his television show, workers on the tugboats anchored the 40-foot barges, torched holes in their steel hulls and then used hoses to flood the hulks until they listed and slipped soundlessly into the sea.</p>
        <p>''It puts back into the environment,'' Mr. Johnson said, proud as a new papa when the barges sank. ''It sounds corny but I'm making my living fishing on the water. The more fish that are around, the better off I'll be because I can catch something.''</p>
        <p>An artificial reef program has been in place since 1962, said Steve Heins, a biologist with the Bureau of Marine Resources at the state Department of Environmental Conservation, who orchestrated the sinking.  There are 11 artificial reef sites around the Island and a plan was drafted in 1993 for an additional 15. Each can hold several hundred thousand yards of material.</p>
        <p>''This is basically a public-private partnership,'' said Mr. Heins, who oversees four to six reef projects a year. ''We just don't have the resources to do this type of construction work. It's really critical to have that kind of support.''</p>
        <p>The Town of Hempstead, Mr. Heins said, contributed the barges and the towing. Mr. Johnson picked up the costs of this sinking (he wouldn't say what they were) and that of a 60-foot steel trawler in 1998. Last June, Mr. Johnson arranged for 1,800 cubic yards of concrete rubble from a Wantagh bridge project to be added to the reef. The site had a permit from the years it was known as the McAllister Grounds, a reef area started by the Department of Environmental Conservation in the 1950's. The site's wooden components deteriorated long ago.</p>
        <p>Describing the ocean bottom, Mr. Johnson said: ''It's like a dining-room floor. Now you have to put furniture on there so you can sit down and have something to eat. We're actually setting the table for a bunch of different fish species to live and cohabitate.</p>
        <p>''It will take a year or two for barnacles or mussels to firmly establish a good all-around ecosystem, but when you put a piece of structure down there, the fish gravitate to it right away,'' he said. ''It's a hiding place, it's structure and it attracts fish. It's like an oasis in a desert.''</p>
        <p>The primary objective in building artificial reefs within a short distance of the inlet is to provide easier fishing opportunities, Mr. Heins said.</p>
        <p>''A lot of the wrecks and rocky areas that people need to go to catch fish are farther away, a distance from the shore,'' he said.</p>
        <p>While there are many old shipwrecks out in the ocean, Mr. Heins said, over time wood gets attacked by marine organisms and is eaten away. Though they eventually rust away, the steel barges will provide an undersea haven for 30 to 40 years. As the rust pulverizes and dissolves, the iron oxide it emits is utilized by marine plants as a fertilizer.</p>
        <p>Because of fishery management, size limits, bag limits and seasonal restrictions on commercial fishing, Mr. Heins added, the numbers of fish are increasing.</p>
        <p>Perhaps that's also because much of the fishing Mr. Johnson does is on land. A licensed New York State fishing guide, he gives an indoor course twice a year on surf fishing -- fishing off the beach -- through an adult education program in Long Beach. And using videotape from his shows, he provides inshore fishing lessons on how to catch fluke, flounder and striped bass. He also gives fishing seminars at the Freeport Recreation Center and produces a seminar series for the National Fishing and Outdoor Expo scheduled at the Nassau Coliseum at the end of January.</p>
        <p>Additionally, Mr. Johnson leads trout fishing expeditions in Connetquot and Nissequogue River state parks and does surf-fishing charters from Montauk to Breezy Point. He writes about his exploits in a fishing column in Long Island Boating World, a Copiague-based publication, and several weekly newspapers.</p>
        <p>Growing up in Rockville Centre, Mr. Johnson fished in the Hempstead Lake area and watched shows like ''Gadabout Gaddis'' and ''American Sportsman.'' Hunkered in front of freshwater shows, he'd noticed that the fishermen were always broadcasting from places like Alabama and Florida.</p>
        <p>''I said, 'Nobody's doing it in the Northeast,' '' recalled Mr. Johnson, who started a not-for-profit fishing club, Let's Go Fishing, in 1989 while working as a park ranger in his hometown. ''There's not a single show on TV that comes from the Northeast and shows people how to fish, how we do it up here. I figured it couldn't be that hard.''</p>
        <p>He began gathering advertisers and went on the air in 1995, first with the radio show and a month later on television. ''The Fishing Line'' has 100 advertisers.</p>
        <p>What's the secret to catching a fish? ''You have to know your quarry,'' Mr. Johnson said. ''You have to know what they prefer and what they like to eat and where they like to live.''</p>
        <p>In the Fishing Line Reef, perhaps? ''Fish will take up residence and never leave it until the water temperature dictates it's time to go to deeper water,'' Mr. Johnson said. ''Everything that swims in the ocean in this area will live on this reef at one time or another.''</p>
        <p>The Letters of the Law</p>
        <p>Lawyers are hardly known for their crisp, clean prose. They tend to long rambling sentences rampant with legalese and stuffed with words like herein, heretofore and aforementioned.</p>
        <p>Not William C. Burton, an insurance lobbyist and lawyer from East Hills. Mr. Burton, 52, is an advocate for clear, cogent writing. To clean up the gobbledygook, he founded the Burton Awards for Legal Achievement, rewarding legal scribes for using plain English.</p>
        <p>''It's time for lawyers to modernize legal writing, to eliminate archaic writing and stilted writing,'' said Mr. Burton, a partner in a law firm in Manhattan. ''It's complex writing, writing with sentences that never end. Once they sprinkle this type of writing in, I think they think it will pass muster in a court more easily.''</p>
        <p>Even as a student at Hofstra Law School years ago, Mr. Burton was frustrated by the convoluted sentences lawyers use. When he couldn't find a legal thesaurus to replace antiquated words, he decided to write one. First published in 1980 and updated in three subsequent editions, Burton's Legal Thesaurus (MacMillan) is considered an authoritative reference tool and the only freestanding thesaurus in the industry.</p>
        <p>A year and a half ago, Mr. Burton invited managing partners from the top 100 law firms in the nation to nominate the best articles written by members of their firms during 1999. He also asked the deans of 181 law schools to submit the best of their students' writings. Then he had a Harvard Law School lecturer, a California state judge and a descendent of Noah Webster evaluate the entries. Ten lawyers and 12 law school student received awards last summer at the first Burton Awards ceremony. He is now collecting submissions for the 2001 awards, which will be held next summer at Carnegie Hall.</p>
        <p>''My hope is that this will encourage more emphasis on legal writing and the profession will focus more on the quality and style of writing,'' Mr. Burton said.</p>
        <p>LONG ISLAND JOURNAL E-mail: lijournal@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: lijournal@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
