<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Out of the Loop, Art From Chicago</title>
    <meta content="29ART" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242631"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ART"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Chicago (Ill)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Whitney Museum of American Art (Stamford, Conn)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zimmer, William</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Illinois/Chicago</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Illinois</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001029T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02E2D71431F93AA15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="948" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Out of the Loop, Art From Chicago</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM ZIMMER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zimmer, William</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William Zimmer reviews Chicago Loop: Imagist Art 1949-1979, at Whitney Museum of American Art branch in Stamford, Conn; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ALTHOUGH it's now really the third city, Chicago has long been called the second city. But the sometimes coarse yet imaginative art that has  been produced there hardly makes the charts, in terms of its general familiarity. As a corrective and introduction, the Whitney Museum of American Art's branch in Stamford is presenting ''Chicago Loop: Imagist Art 1949-1979.''</p>
        <p>One may read ''loop'' as in ''loopy.'' The period covered by the show (when the New York art world was immersed in the abstract) saw groups of artists who gave themselves names such as ''Monster Roster'' and ''Hairy Who.'' These artists took as their example Ivan Albright who, as the show's curator, Cynthia Roznoy, says in her text for the brochure, is ''known primarily for his horrific images of human decay.'' A couple of his self-portraits, from 1947 and 1948, are included in the show to establish a genealogy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ALTHOUGH it's now really the third city, Chicago has long been called the second city. But the sometimes coarse yet imaginative art that has  been produced there hardly makes the charts, in terms of its general familiarity. As a corrective and introduction, the Whitney Museum of American Art's branch in Stamford is presenting ''Chicago Loop: Imagist Art 1949-1979.''</p>
        <p>One may read ''loop'' as in ''loopy.'' The period covered by the show (when the New York art world was immersed in the abstract) saw groups of artists who gave themselves names such as ''Monster Roster'' and ''Hairy Who.'' These artists took as their example Ivan Albright who, as the show's curator, Cynthia Roznoy, says in her text for the brochure, is ''known primarily for his horrific images of human decay.'' A couple of his self-portraits, from 1947 and 1948, are included in the show to establish a genealogy.</p>
        <p>Some of the earliest pieces chosen for the exhibit are by Leon Golub and Nancy Spero, an artist couple still at work. It's interesting to note how their work from the 1950's echoes their more recent images. Mr. Golub is known for his paintings of the horrors of war, especially torture, but also for figures with tough, bulbous heads. Here an expressionistic head and a relief sculpture in plaster, ''Tomb Figure,'' presage the later work. Ms. Spero has, evidently, always combined animated figures and writing.</p>
        <p>Many of the artists seem to move easily between painting and sculpture. Don Baum, for instance, is represented by ''The Abandoned Head'' on canvas and ''The Shovel'' put together of found objects including a scythe and a shovel. The two images are remarkably similar and it's not hard to find something of a ghoulish narrative in their coupling. An interest in sculpture might have originated with H. C. Westermann, one of the handful of artists with a national reputation. Westermann was enigmatic and surreal as evidenced by the somewhat winsome ''The Evil New War God,'' and the conundrum of an oil can with a thick rope emerging from its spout.</p>
        <p>An unfamiliar sculptor, Cosmo Campoli, is represented by two sculptures -- ''Jonah and the Whale,'' primarily in bronze, and ''Birth of Death'' in lead -- that are elegiac and embody profound concerns. Ellen Lanyon, too, is more reflective than offbeat in paintings such as ''One Way to Quarter a Pear'' and ''The Housekeeper's Terror.'' The deep reddish tonality of ''Vacationer,'' Seymour Rosofsky's painting of a man rowing a boat through city streets, establishes an apocalyptic tone, although his black and white lithograph ''The Family'' is somewhat more comical.</p>
        <p>The members of the Hairy Who explained that they were so named because ''the name and the group sprung fully grown, or in this case, fully hairy.'' Two of the ringleaders are Karl Wirsum and the fortunately named Jim Nutt. Mr. Wirsum contributes what might be his group's mascot, ''Hairy Armpits''; the collage painting shows a woman fluffing her abundant, painted red hair but tufts of real hair mark her upraised arms. The image is too ebullient to be gross.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nutt specializes in cartoonish characters with especially sharp edges. But the sharpness is somewhat mollified by the inherent slickness of his plexiglass surfaces. His works reflect the Hairy Who's penchant for literalness. ''Cotton Mouth'' features a head in profile with a wide grin revealing a host of cotton balls stuffed behind the plexiglass. A drawing bears the confessional title, ''Hi -- I'm So Happy (If a Bit Silly).''</p>
        <p>Christina Ramberg, a sleeker counterpart of Mr. Nutt, specialized in parts of figures, especially hair styles. In contrast to Mr. Nutt and others who traffic in gaudy color, Ramberg's work is primarily gray and black. Ray Yoshida, who was the teacher of many of the Hairy Who at the Art Institute of Chicago, also deals in expressive parts of the body. In ''Comic Specimen #6,'' Mr. Yoshida evidently cut out myriad hands from comic books and arranged them in rows to produce a lively sort of semaphore.</p>
        <p>Two artists known outside of Chicago contribute panoramic works that vividly portray unease in different ways. Ed Paschke's ''Violencia,'' done in lurid greens and blues depicts a man with his hand at a woman's throat. But it's just the specter of a head distinguished by a glamorous mouth, the kind associated with Marilyn Monroe. In fact two such mouths are side by side. The man's action is unmistakable, but everything else is indefinite. A series of parallel lines, like the flat lines on a cardiograph, run through the painting.</p>
        <p>Roger Brown made a name for himself with paintings featuring silhouettes of people in the lighted windows of buildings. Several towers filled with these figures, in animated poses, would be enough to portend the apocalypse, but in ''The Entry of Christ into Chicago,'' (the title refers to the Belgian James Ensor's expressionistic painting, ''The Entry of Christ into Brussels'') Brown added at ground level, a platform decked with bunting, on which are a dignitaries but also a rock band. Down the street, Jesus approaches on a flatbed truck. A small crowd of silhouetted figures is gathered, but a viewer's eye might be drawn to a woman having trouble opening her umbrella.</p>
        <p>''Chicago Loop'' is at the Whitney Museum of American Art's branch in Stamford through Dec. 6.</p>
        <p>ART</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
