<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Queen of Dish</title>
    <meta content="29STERNT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242595"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stern, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stern, Jane</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, Liz</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Natural Blonde (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001029T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807EED9123EF93AA15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1164" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Queen of Dish</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jane and Michael Stern</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stern, Michael; Stern, Jane</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jane and Michael Stern review autobiography Natural Blonde: A Memoir by Liz Smith (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NATURAL BLONDE</p>
        <p>A Memoir.</p>
        <p>By Liz Smith.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 460 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Hyperion. $25.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NATURAL BLONDE</p>
        <p>A Memoir.</p>
        <p>By Liz Smith.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 460 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Hyperion. $25.95.</p>
        <p>ONCE upon a time in the West, a girl was born named Mary Elizabeth Smith. She was loved by her family, especially by her fastidious father, Sloan, who regularly shaved his armpits with a safety razor and enlisted his young daughter to ''come and tweeze this hair out of my ear.'' Daddy Sloan would praise her for valor (like the time she stayed aboard a runaway pony) by cradling her between his legs and calling her his ''best boy.''</p>
        <p>There was much Mary Elizabeth Smith liked about growing up in Fort Worth. She liked watching her old granny, ''Big Mama,'' wring off the heads of live chickens, and she liked attending the Baptist church to hear testimony to Jesus by the visiting evangelist ''Hyman Appelman, the Converted Jew.'' But most of all, she liked Hollywood movies. Before the Great Depression, when the Smith family was still financially comfortable, young ''MES'' (nicknamed for her initials) was regularly taken to picture shows at the Tivoli by Dott, the family maid, who resembled Lena Horne.</p>
        <p>In the sultry darkness of the movie palace Mary Elizabeth Smith found the inspiration eventually to become Liz Smith, who today at 77 reigns as the Queen of Celebrity Journalists, America's Grande Dame of Dish.</p>
        <p>Smith's memoir is called ''Natural Blonde.'' It is a title itching to be challenged, but the author ingenuously pushes to the head of the line to be the first to tell us that being a ''natural blonde'' has nothing to do with genes or birthright and everything to do with the clever hands of her hairdresser, Vincent Roppatte. In Smith's world, becoming a bottled blonde is nature's way.</p>
        <p>It is hard not to like this candid Lone Star refugee who arrived in Penn Station with two suitcases in September 1949. Despite a career spent in the company of names like Trump, Forbes, Onassis, Hepburn and Madonna, Liz Smith remains a good ol' girl in custom cowboy boots. She writes of herself as everywoman -- insecure, oddly dressed, a little goofy -- ever the small-town gal bedazzled by celebrities and amazed that they seem to like her company. Thankfully, she does not confuse herself with the entertainment icons she writes about, although her name is arguably as well known as theirs, and in many cases more enduring.</p>
        <p>Smith knows that when a gossip columnist writes a memoir, readers expect gossip. We want the stories behind the stories, and although Smith may be a social force in her own right, she is well aware that her place in the firmament of superstardom is as a jolly conduit through whom decades of tabloid readers and TV viewers have gotten the scoop on what life is like on the other side of the velvet rope. So in this book her own adult life is woven into a half-century</p>
        <p>of who did what, when, to whom, and why. Although she stakes a claim for gossip as a centuries-old form of important social catharsis (apparently Greeks wrote nasty graffiti about one another on the rocks at Mount Hymettus), Smith never takes herself too seriously. She says that she does what she does because it is fun. That's apparent, because the pleasure she gets, she gives.</p>
        <p>Her brand of gossip is the old-fashioned kind, not the embarrassing or repulsive stuff dug up by so many of her journalistic colleagues. When she escorts us into the private lives of popular culture's gods and monsters, it's with a spirit of wonder, not meanness. Still, there is plenty of scandal. We are privy to one toe-curling occasion after Bette Davis accepted and reciprocated a dinner invitation with two male fans who had graciously given her their long-term space in a parking garage. At the end of the second dinner, Smith writes, ''Miss Davis herself showed them to the door. As they stepped outside, she said firmly, 'O.K. You've had me to dinner. I've had you to dinner. That's it; that's the end of it -- now we are even.' She shut the door firmly.'' Ouch!</p>
        <p>We learn that Truman Capote once brought out a fishbowl with about $35,000 worth of cocaine in it for a shocked Smith and the writer John Berendt to enjoy, then suddenly ''snatched it up and marched away with it, saying, 'No, it's too good for the likes of you.' ''We are told that the actress Maureen Stapleton ''drinks a bit. She used to prop her feet up on the table, and . . . she never wore underwear.'' Smith reveals that the novelist Philip Roth put the moves on the widowed Jackie Kennedy, only to be rebuffed by Jackie, who ''drew back, looked sternly at him and said, chidingly, 'Aw -- what did you have to go and do that for?' End of romance!'' The Natural Blonde tells us that attending the late Malcolm Forbes's colossal birthday bash in Morocco was about as glamorous as ''accompanying 700 people on an un-air-conditioned bus trip to Ardmore, Okla. -- during the dog days,'' and that Liz Taylor arrived in Leningrad for the filming of ''The Bluebird'' with 2,800 pounds of luggage and a load of Fortnum &amp; Mason food for herself, demanding to bathe daily in ''bottled distilled water because Leningrad's product often ran bright green and smelled of sulfur.'' Four hundred-plus pages of ''Natural Blonde'' are filled with such tidbits, which even hard-core hearsay hounds are sure to have missed over the years.</p>
        <p>''Natural Blonde'' has caused a bit of scandal itself because Smith does not address her own sexuality as squarely as some observers consider de rigueur in a memoir, especially a memoir by a professional snitch. She has been chastised for not sharing intimate details of her relationships with various women, including the archaeologist Iris Love. But Smith has never been one to report from under the covers, hers or anybody else's. As we breezed through ''Natural Blonde,'' we felt quite satisfied knowing the cheerful highlights of her passion for untouchable celebrities -- tales of swoonfulness around Rock Hudson, Warren Beatty, Robert Redford and Frank Sinatra that read like entries in a bobby-soxer's diary. As for what she personally has done in bed, more information would not have been welcome. Liz Smith gives a rosy buildup to her love life and then, like the camera in the melodramas she loved so much as a Texas girl, she discreetly pans away. As a lifelong movie buff, this Natural Blonde knows that imagination can fill in the details.</p>
        <p>Jane and Michael Stern have written more than 20 books about American culture on subjects that include Elvis Presley, Roy Rogers, good food and bad taste.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Jane and Michael Stern have written more than 20 books about American culture on subjects that include Elvis Presley, Roy Rogers, good food and bad taste.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
