<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In the Region/Westchester; White Plains Getting Retail Stores Near Big Mall</title>
    <meta content="29WCZO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242755"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Supermarkets</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shopping Centers</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">White Plains (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Container Store</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Stop &amp; Shop Cos</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Westchester (White Plains, Ny, Shopping Mall)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vizard, Mary Mcaleer</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/In the Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shopping Centers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Supermarkets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001029T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E6D61031F93AA15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1305" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In the Region/Westchester; White Plains Getting Retail Stores Near Big Mall</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARY McALEER VIZARD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Vizard, Mary Mcaleer</byline>
      <dateline>WHITE PLAINS</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Container Store opens and new Stop &amp; Shop supermarket is set to open near The Westchester mall in White Plains, NY; photo; maps (In the Region/Westchester) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN The Westchester, a million-square-foot mall, opened in 1995,  expectations were high that complementary retail would soon spring up around it.</p>
        <p>It has taken five years for the first new nearby store to arrive -- a 23,000-square-foot Container Store that opened last weekend at the corner of Bloomingdale Road and Westchester Avenue, directly across from Nordstrom's, one of the mall's two anchors. The other anchor is Neiman Marcus.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN The Westchester, a million-square-foot mall, opened in 1995,  expectations were high that complementary retail would soon spring up around it.</p>
        <p>It has taken five years for the first new nearby store to arrive -- a 23,000-square-foot Container Store that opened last weekend at the corner of Bloomingdale Road and Westchester Avenue, directly across from Nordstrom's, one of the mall's two anchors. The other anchor is Neiman Marcus.</p>
        <p>The Container Store, which sells household storage products, will soon be followed by the expected start of construction on a long-awaited new supermarket for the city, a 60,000-square-foot Stop &amp; Shop, to be built on a nearby site. ''We've been trying to get a new supermarket for 12 years,'' said George Gretsas, the city's executive officer. ''But we had trouble finding the right site.''</p>
        <p>All of White Plains has only one other supermarket, an old 20,000-square-foot Food Emporium on Mamaroneck Avenue about four blocks away, Mr. Gretsas said. ''This is the first modern supermarket in the city,'' he said of the Stop &amp; Shop.</p>
        <p>The Stop &amp; Shop is to be built on a nearly seven-acre site at the corner of Westchester Avenue and South Kensico Avenue, about a block from The Westchester. Construction is to start next month, Mr. Gretsas said, and the store is expected to open in early 2002.</p>
        <p>Over the years, there have been several other proposals to add more retail near the mall, most notably a plan to build a 250,000-square-foot shopping center around a stand-alone Saks Fifth Avenue store on Maple Avenue, across from Neiman Marcus. But none have come to fruition.</p>
        <p>''We consider the area around the mall as the gateway to the city,'' Mr. Gretsas said, ''and it's important to get the right stores in there and take our time to make sure we do it right. Both of these new stores are right for the city. We have no other store in the city like the Container Store, and the supermarket is something the city's needed for many years.''</p>
        <p>Since the mall is now the dominant player in the area, Mr. Gretsas said, all new stores must mirror its style as a visual element. For instance, the Container Store has the same light-brown brick facade and classical lines as the mall. ''Standing on Westchester Avenue,'' he said, ''the Container Store seems to be a part of the mall.''</p>
        <p>The exterior of the supermarket will also be designed to look like The Westchester, he said. ''We think it's important that all the new stores link with the mall in overall look,'' he said.</p>
        <p>THIS is the Container Store's first foray into the Northeast. ''We've been looking at the area for a while now but couldn't find the ideal site that had all the ingredients we look for,'' said John Mullen, a vice president of real estate for the Dallas-based chain. ''We look for best market, best site and best co-tenancy, and with The Westchester across the street, we have now met all our objectives.''</p>
        <p>The chain plans to open its second store in the area in Paramus, N.J., in 2001 or 2002, Mr. Mullen said.</p>
        <p>''We're also very interested in being in Manhattan, but we're in no hurry,'' he said. ''We consider Westchester as a spine reaching down to the city, and White Plains is ground zero. We'll wait and see how things go here.''</p>
        <p>The White Plains store is the 22nd Container Store to open nationwide in 22 years. Since its founding in 1978, the chain has grown around 25 percent every year, and projects sales to reach $237 million this year and $272 million in 2001, Mr. Mullen said.</p>
        <p>There is no prototype design for a Container Store, said Garrett Boone, the chief executive officer. ''We don't believe in one look because the environment around our store in Houston doesn't have anything in common with White Plains,'' he said. ''So why should they look the same?''</p>
        <p>The White Plains store was designed by a Westchester architect, Kenneth R. Nadler, who said he wanted it to look like the ''1930's style architecture of Westchester retail.'' Mr. Nadler's consulting business is based in Mount Kisco. ''We wanted to avoid the typical big box and create something more elegant and classical,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The store's brick facade has a green ornamental metal pattern that is ''meant to bring the eye down,'' Mr. Nadler said, ''so that the store appears smaller in scale than it is.''</p>
        <p>In contrast, he said, the interior is ''open, light and cheerful.''</p>
        <p>''Done in white and blue,'' he said, ''it's meant to evoke the sky and happiness.'' It also has a modern industrial feel with exposed piping, Mr. Mullen said, that ''represents functional solutions to problems, which is the store's philosophy.''</p>
        <p>The Container Store leased the property, which at one time was owned by New York Hospital, from Orix TMK White Plains Venture, a real estate investment company, for 15 years. The Container Store would not disclose its annual rent.</p>
        <p>Stop &amp; Shop's design will emulate The Westchester and the Container Store, said Anthony Colavolpe, a vice president of real estate. ''We've asked our architect to look at both, and incorporate some of the same elements into our store's design.''</p>
        <p>MR. COLAVOLPE said that being near a mall wasn't necessarily an  advantage for a supermarket. ''It's still a great location for us because of its access and the amount of traffic,'' he said. ''But we don't expect that people will be shopping at the mall and then decide to do grocery shopping afterward. That's usually done in a separate trip.''</p>
        <p>The city took so long to attract a major supermarket because it had difficulty finding a site large enough to accommodate a modern one and its needed parking area,  Mr. Gretsas said. The Stop &amp; Shop and its parking area will actually occupy two separate parcels.</p>
        <p>One part of the site is occupied by several city departments, including its Department of Public Works. Another part, privately owned, holds a former bowling alley, now vacant, and a branch of the Bank of New York, which is to close soon. Both buildings are to be razed.</p>
        <p>Stop &amp; Shop has signed a 75-year lease for the privately owned parcel, where the supermarket will be built.</p>
        <p>To make the plan work, the city needed to find another site for its Department of Public Works, Mr. Gretsas said. A solution presented itself when Nick Pepe, owner of an office building at 44 South Broadway, about a block from The Westchester, offered to construct and pay for a new 55,000-square-foot building for the department on property he owns near his building, at Brockway Place and South Kensico Avenue. The other departments are to be relocated elsewhere.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pepe is also going to build a garage above the Stop &amp; Shop parking area -- there will a total of 750 spaces -- and in exchange he asked that employees in his building at 44 South Broadway be allowed to park there for free.</p>
        <p>''With the more open office layouts, buildings now can hold more people than before, and we didn't have enough parking onsite,'' Mr. Pepe said. '' I think this is one of those rare instances where a solution presented itself that works well for everyone concerned. And that's very unusual.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
