<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'The Witch of Staten Island'</title>
    <meta content="29LORE$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242901"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="CITY LORE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rasenberger, Jim</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bodine, Polly</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001029T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE3DE1F31F93AA15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1518" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'The Witch of Staten Island'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JIM RASENBERGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rasenberger, Jim</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jim Rasenberger article recounts Halloween tale of Witch of Staten Island, about Polly Bodine who, in 1844, faced three trials and was convicted of murdering her sister-in-law and young niece and setting fire to their house; photos; drawings (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AT first glance, there is nothing remarkable about the house on Richmond Avenue. Encased in gray vinyl siding and surrounded by the kind of suburban sprawl that covers much of Staten Island these days -- a Perkins restaurant and a Wendy's across the street, the Dr. Martin Luther King Jr. Expressway a stone's throw away -- it could easily pass as just another 20th-century addition to this north shore neighborhood.</p>
        <p>But under the vinyl siding is a very old house with a haunting past: it was here, over 150 years ago, that Polly Bodine lived with her parents.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AT first glance, there is nothing remarkable about the house on Richmond Avenue. Encased in gray vinyl siding and surrounded by the kind of suburban sprawl that covers much of Staten Island these days -- a Perkins restaurant and a Wendy's across the street, the Dr. Martin Luther King Jr. Expressway a stone's throw away -- it could easily pass as just another 20th-century addition to this north shore neighborhood.</p>
        <p>But under the vinyl siding is a very old house with a haunting past: it was here, over 150 years ago, that Polly Bodine lived with her parents.</p>
        <p>Polly who?</p>
        <p>''The other day I asked my students to write down who they thought Polly Bodine was,'' said Marguerite Rivas, a local poet and an adjunct professor at the College of Staten Island. ''Nobody had any idea. One student thought it was Marilyn Monroe's real name.''</p>
        <p>The name may not ring many bells these days, but in her time, Polly Bodine was as infamous as Lizzie Borden, as reviled as O. J. Simpson. She was, in the words of P. T. Barnum, ''the Witch of Staten Island.''</p>
        <p>Her story begins on Christmas night in 1843. But this is no Christmas story.</p>
        <p>Staten Island in 1843 was a rural seafaring community of 10,000 residents living in hamlets. The night of Dec. 25, two boys returning home from a skating party saw smoke billowing from a house on Richmond Road. The house stood adjacent to Polly's, about where the Perkins parking lot is today, and belonged to her brother, a schooner captain named George Houseman. The captain was out at sea. His young wife, Emeline, and their 20-month-old daughter, Ann Eliza, were home alone.</p>
        <p>As neighbors rushed to the burning house, though, Emeline and the baby were nowhere to be seen. At first, rescuers assumed they had gone away for the holidays. Then one rescuer saw something in the kitchen near a charred basket of pumpkins and onions. It was Emeline's body.</p>
        <p>Nineteenth-century court papers document the body's condition in grisly detail: ''The back part of the head was very much burned, part of the skull wanting, and the brain baked by the action of the heat.'' Furthermore, ''on the left arm, both bones of the forearm were broken, and one of the bones was white and clear, the other blackened by the heat. . . .'' The body of the baby girl, discovered close by, was in even worse shape.</p>
        <p>Investigators quickly put together a chilling chain of events. Somebody had murdered mother and child -- so violently as to break their bones and shatter their skulls -- then set the house on fire to cover up the deed. Within a few days, investigators had their suspect: Polly Bodine.</p>
        <p>It is not clear why suspicion fell on her so readily. She was close to her sister-in-law, often spending the night with her to help with the baby. Nor did the apparent motive for the murders -- theft -- make much sense. Polly had money of her own and the amount stolen was trivial.</p>
        <p>This much is certain: Polly led a life that invited suspicion in 19th-century New York. She had separated from her husband and was sleeping with a New York apothecary named George Waite. She had undergone abortions at a time when public sentiment was turning against this previously accepted form of birth control -- and just two years before New York would criminalize it.</p>
        <p>''Abortion was a hot topic in 1843,'' said Amy Gilman Srebnick, a history professor at Montclair State University and the author of a book about the Mary Rogers case of 1841 (another murder that had recently shocked the city). ''It certainly would have affected how she was perceived. She was a fallen woman. And fallen women were fair game for all sorts of speculation.''</p>
        <p>Polly's behavior around the time of the murders did little to dampen such speculation. Early in the morning of Dec. 26, when Polly later claimed to be in Manhattan visiting Waite, a chambermaid saw her aboard a ferryboat departing Staten Island. She was drinking gin and eating a slice of pie, looking weary and wary. Polly was later spotted in a pawnshop on lower Broadway wearing a hooded cape and a green veil and hawking items from the victims' house. Other witnesses recalled seeing her wandering the streets of Manhattan in a daze.</p>
        <p>Polly was arrested on New Year's Eve. Three days later, she gave premature birth to a stillborn boy, another ''illicit offspring,'' as The New York Herald put it. In June, she came before the Richmond County Court for the first in a string of trials nearly as extraordinary as the murders themselves.</p>
        <p>The Richmond trial gripped New York, every word recounted in special editions of the new penny press newspapers like The Herald, The Sun and The Evening Post. With its spicy brew of sex, greed and gore, the Bodine case was tailor-made for their brand of sensationalism and outrage -- presumption of innocence be damned. ''There cannot be a doubt as to the guilt of the wretched woman,'' The Post proclaimed.</p>
        <p>Edgar Allan Poe threw in his two cents, filing a dispatch on the eve of the trial for a Pennsylvania newspaper. ''This woman may, possibly, escape,'' wrote Poe. ''For they manage these matters wretchedly in New York.''</p>
        <p>Poe was right. The first trial ended in a hung jury when one of the jurors refused to convict on the grounds that he lacked ''circumstantial evidence in the fourth degree.'' (What this meant was anybody's guess.)</p>
        <p>In an attempt to find an unbiased jury, the second trial was held in Manhattan. This became an even more spectacular event than the first. Women, particularly, seemed fascinated by Polly. The Herald remarked on the crowds ''of highly fashionable female spectators, giving the courtroom all the appearance of some of our fashionable theaters.'' P. T. Barnum added to the excitement with a wax tableau of Polly in his museum a few blocks from the courtroom. He portrayed her as a toothless ''witch'' of 70 -- though she was half that age -- savagely hacking away at her victims. Barnum's witch apparently had some magic on her side: Polly was convicted but the verdict was overturned.</p>
        <p>Her third and final trial took place in Newburgh. Polly's lawyers skillfully refuted the testimony of several crucial witnesses. This time, after more than two years in jail, Polly was acquitted. Her first words to her lawyer were: ''Can't I sue Barnum now?''</p>
        <p>The popular press was not quite done with Polly Bodine. In 1846, a New York publisher distributed a fantastically overheated pamphlet damning Polly as a vampirish slattern ''possessing an undying enmity to the human race, an insatiable thirst for blood, following murder as a calling.''</p>
        <p>It was a calling Polly apparently abandoned. She moved back to Staten Island and there lived in increasing anonymity until the age of 82. She left behind two grown children and a bundle of unanswered questions. If it really was Polly who killed Emeline and Ann Eliza, why did she do it? What would have possessed her to murder them so violently? And if she did not do it, who did?</p>
        <p>''I go back and forth,'' said Ms. Rivas, who spent the last year writing about Polly Bodine, among other Staten Island notables, in her poetry. ''I think she probably did it, or at least had something to do with it. That's what my gut tells me.''</p>
        <p>For inspiration, Ms. Rivas frequently visits the small cemetery where Emeline and Ann Eliza lie buried together. Their headstone stands at the edge of a busy four-lane road, in the shadow of a large shopping center -- a suitably forlorn place to wind up an old and mostly forgotten story. ''You know what really gets me?'' Ms. Rivas said. ''That they have to spend their eternal rest staring out at a ShopRite.''</p>
        <p>But this is a Halloween story, so it ends, finally, with a ghost. A small wood grows across the street from Polly's old house, a ragged bit of greenery used mostly to dump mowed grass and old liquor bottles. Recently, neighbors spotted a vaporous man in gray prowling those woods at night. Maybe he knows who committed those horrible murders 157 years ago. Or maybe he just wandered into the wrong Halloween story.</p>
        <p>CITY LORE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
