<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>October 22-28; Nasty Habit or Creative Boost? A Nail-Biting Issue</title>
    <meta content="29BOXA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/29/weekinreview/29BOXA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242937"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001029T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E4D71F31F93AA15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="407" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>October 22-28; Nasty Habit or Creative Boost? A Nail-Biting Issue</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jane Fritsch</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There is much information about the presidential candidates available to American voters, if they choose to use it. For instance, last week came news that Vice President Al Gore has a habit of chewing his fingernails to the quick. This was reported in an article in The New York Times about the vice president's health, which is quite good, except for some concern about his cholesterol level.</p>
        <p>So now the fingernail issue is out there, and as surely as night follows the day, the analysis must come.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There is much information about the presidential candidates available to American voters, if they choose to use it. For instance, last week came news that Vice President Al Gore has a habit of chewing his fingernails to the quick. This was reported in an article in The New York Times about the vice president's health, which is quite good, except for some concern about his cholesterol level.</p>
        <p>So now the fingernail issue is out there, and as surely as night follows the day, the analysis must come.</p>
        <p>''People who are more high-strung or high-energy benefit the most from a habit like nail-biting,'' said Dr. Susan Heitler, a clinical psychologist and the author of ''David Decides About Thumb Sucking'' (Reading Matters, 1996). ''One of Gore's assets is that he is a fairly high-energy, high-potency  person.''</p>
        <p>Nail-biting, like thumb-sucking and rocking in a rocking chair, is a habit prompted by certain situations or emotional states, Dr. Heitler said. ''Some nail-biters bite when they're thinking, others bite when they're upset, and others bite when they watch movies.''</p>
        <p>Such rhythmic activities affect the body's physiological state, she said, optimizing heart rate and blood pressure. In such a state, people can think through problems more effectively, she added. ''It would be interesting to know when he does the nail-biting,'' she said of Mr. Gore. ''It could be that his nail-biting correlates to his most creative thinking.'' (He said he did it ''every once in a while'' and did not link it to nervousness.)</p>
        <p>But there is a cost. ''Your fingers begin to hurt,'' Dr. Heitler said. ''It's socially off-putting, and people who are biting their nails look less confident, less mature.'' As a deterrent, she suggests rubbing one's fingers on hot chili peppers in the morning.</p>
        <p>Whether voters should be concerned is another question. ''You really have to step back and say, 'Is this particular behavior important in the larger context of what their life is about?' '' said Dr. John H. Greist, a psychiatrist and senior scientist at the Madison Institute of Medicine in Wisconsin. ''I think it's irrelevant. We're not asking him to model hands, we're asking him to serve as president.''</p>
        <p>Jane Fritsch</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
