<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>When 'Just Sit Tight' Is the Wrong Advice</title>
    <meta content="29SHAR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/29/weekinreview/29SHAR.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20001105T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242909"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blood</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sharkey, Joe</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Blood</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blood</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001029T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E3DD1F31F93AA15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="839" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>When 'Just Sit Tight' Is the Wrong Advice</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE SHARKEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sharkey, Joe</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Airlines dispute whether 'economy-class syndrome,' in fact a circulatory problem known as deep-vein thrombosis, is widespread consequence of long airplane trips, in wake of death last week of 28-year-old British woman following 20-hour 10,000-mile flight from Australia to London; reports linking blood clots to air travel have increased in recent years as airlines have crammed more seats into their planes; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AT first it sounds like a grimly humorous way to describe what you suffered on your last airline flight, when you were wedged for hours in a tight seat and the tray table slammed into your belly like a karate chop after the passenger in front of you decided to recline for a snooze.</p>
        <p>But ''economy-class syndrome'' is a real term given to what some medical experts claim is a more serious consequence of long airplane trips: a circulatory problem known as deep-vein thrombosis, which is essentially a blood clot. Economy-class syndrome turned up in headlines last week after a 28-year-old British woman collapsed and died at London's Heathrow Airport following a 20-hour, 10,000-mile flight from Australia (with a single stop in Singapore). An autopsy attributed her death to a deep-vein thrombosis.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AT first it sounds like a grimly humorous way to describe what you suffered on your last airline flight, when you were wedged for hours in a tight seat and the tray table slammed into your belly like a karate chop after the passenger in front of you decided to recline for a snooze.</p>
        <p>But ''economy-class syndrome'' is a real term given to what some medical experts claim is a more serious consequence of long airplane trips: a circulatory problem known as deep-vein thrombosis, which is essentially a blood clot. Economy-class syndrome turned up in headlines last week after a 28-year-old British woman collapsed and died at London's Heathrow Airport following a 20-hour, 10,000-mile flight from Australia (with a single stop in Singapore). An autopsy attributed her death to a deep-vein thrombosis.</p>
        <p>Deep-vein thromboses caused by immobility, a condition first widely diagnosed among Londoners jammed into air-raid shelters during World War II, has been increasingly reported among air travelers in recent years as airplane seating became more cramped on ever-longer domestic and international flights.</p>
        <p>How serious a threat is it? While there are disputes about the numbers of documented cases, the potential for circulatory problems caused by immobility is serious enough that airlines ''have given extensive attention to this issue in the United States and will continue to do so,'' said Michael Wascom, a spokesman for the Air Transport Association, which represents the domestic airline industry.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wascom said that his group, in affiliation with the Aerospace Medical Association, publishes a booklet for passengers called ''Useful Tips for Air Travelers,'' which he said ''covers a variety of cabin-environment issues, including recommended practices to prevent leg compression and blood pooling'' on long flights.</p>
        <p>British advocates of strengthened governmental oversight on issues like cramped airline seating and the possible transmission of infectious diseases in poorly ventilated cabins made widely reported claims last week that in Britain alone, 30,000 air travelers experienced deep-vein thromboses after flying last year. But aviation-medicine experts in the United States say these numbers are wildly exaggerated.</p>
        <p>''If there was that kind of an epidemic, the aerospace medical world would be very active'' in sounding an alarm, said Russell B. Rayman, a physician who is executive director of the Aerospace Medical Association, a group that represents professionals involved in clinical and research work in the aviation industry.</p>
        <p>Reports tying the blood clots to air travel have intensified in recent years, after airlines began cramming more seats into their planes. A decade ago, the space between seats in a typical airline economy-class cabin was about 35 inches. Now it is 31 inches on most planes (American Airlines gives a little more), and among frequent fliers complaints about cramped space rank second only to those about delays.</p>
        <p>While there are disputes about the numbers of cases, airlines are supporting medical studies of deep-vein thrombosis, and some are defending themselves against lawsuits filed by passengers who claim cramped seating caused deep-vein thrombosis conditions.</p>
        <p>On its Web site, British Airways has a health advisory that addresses deep-vein thrombosis. ''It has also been referred to as 'economy class syndrome,' '' the site says, adding: ''This is misleading, because individuals seated in theaters, cars, trucks, buses etc. may all be at risk.'' And the blood clots ''have been reported in travelers in premium cabins as well as economy,'' the site says. ''It seems to be the immobility rather than the environment which is a factor.''</p>
        <p>Over all, about five million Americans a year suffer from the condition, which accounts for about 800,000 hospitalizations annually, according to the DuPont Pharmaceuticals Company, which sells a blood-thinning drug, Innopehn, used to treat the condition. Most susceptible to the ailment are people who have recently had surgery, people with cancer, heart disease or diabetes, and ''those who are immobile for a prolonged period,'' DuPont said.</p>
        <p>''Certainly crowding and especially immobility increase the risk'' of deep-vein thrombosis in air travel and in any other situation where physical motion is constricted, said Dr. Rayman. He added that when he took an 18-hour flight home from Asia last week, in business class, he made sure to leave his seat regularly.</p>
        <p>''I get up and wander around every hour or so,'' on a long flight, he said. Even if it means disturbing other passengers to climb out across a row of seats, passengers should force themselves to stretch their legs, he suggested.</p>
        <p>The disputed claim that air travel accounted for 30,000 deep-vein thrombosis cases in Britain was made by a group in Oxford, England, called the Aviation Health Institute.</p>
        <p>''The shock to us is we've found it can happen to anyone,'' said Farrol Kahn, the director of the organization. 'We'd done research on people over age 50 because that's where you tend to find pre-existing circulatory problems, but we're now seeing it in fit people in their 30's and younger.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  November 5, 2000, Sunday  An article last Sunday about a circulatory problem that can afflict airline passengers and others who remain immobile for extended periods misidentified a blood-thinning drug that is used to treat it. The drug, manufactured by the DuPont Pharmaceuticals Company, is Innohep, not Innopehn.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: November 5, 2000, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article last Sunday about a circulatory problem that can afflict airline passengers and others who remain immobile for extended periods misidentified a blood-thinning drug that is used to treat it. The drug, manufactured by the DuPont Pharmaceuticals Company, is Innohep, not Innopehn.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
