<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Minivan Rentals: Roomy, Pricey</title>
    <meta content="29PRAC$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/29/travel/29PRAC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242626"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRACTICAL TRAVELER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Adelson, Andrea</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Columns/Practical Traveler</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001029T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07EEDB1731F93AA15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1150" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Minivan Rentals: Roomy, Pricey</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREA ADELSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Adelson, Andrea</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Andrea Adelson Practical Traveler column describes pros and cons of renting minivans; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN Mike and Pam Hilburn of Laguna Beach, Calif., arrived in Hawaii with their two sons, 11 and 7, in January for a 10-day vacation, the midsize Alamo rental car reserved for them looked uncomfortably small.</p>
        <p>''I wanted to be able to put all our stuff in it and be able to take recreation equipment to the beach,'' Ms. Hilburn said. ''All our luggage wouldn't fit in.'' So they rejected the four-door sedan, she said, and instead agreed to pay $30 more a day to rent a minivan, an Oldsmobile Silhouette, which the family liked more than they anticipated.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN Mike and Pam Hilburn of Laguna Beach, Calif., arrived in Hawaii with their two sons, 11 and 7, in January for a 10-day vacation, the midsize Alamo rental car reserved for them looked uncomfortably small.</p>
        <p>''I wanted to be able to put all our stuff in it and be able to take recreation equipment to the beach,'' Ms. Hilburn said. ''All our luggage wouldn't fit in.'' So they rejected the four-door sedan, she said, and instead agreed to pay $30 more a day to rent a minivan, an Oldsmobile Silhouette, which the family liked more than they anticipated.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hilburn's advice for traveling families renting cars is this: ''Definitely budget in an upgrade. You have to. The cars are so small.''</p>
        <p>These days a minivan rental is a popular upgrade among families, especially those accustomed to driving them at home, as well as among small groups taking a road trip for business. Compared with the trunk of the average car, the rear cargo area in some minivans is twice as big (up to 41 cubic feet in Chevrolet's Astro) and can take up to eight suitcases. They generally seat seven people.</p>
        <p>For parents, they are a godsend on a road trip since even with a crammed cargo area, a minivan is roomy enough to permit the middle bench or bucket seats to recline and allow a child to nap comfortably.</p>
        <p>Every national car rental company includes minivans in its inventory at most locations. The Dodge Caravan, Ford Windstar and Chevrolet Astro were among the most popular minivans registered to rental companies last year, according to Automotive Fleet Magazine, a trade publication. Notably absent is the Honda Odyssey, a popular minivan among buyers; Honda does not sell to fleets, said David Stepner, managing editor of Auto Rental News, an industry magazine in Torrance, Calif.</p>
        <p>Since only about half the minivan models are equipped with internal child safety seats, for ages 1 year and up (these include the Chevy Venture, Dodge Caravan, Chrysler Town and Country and Pontiac Montana), rental companies still offer strap-in seats, typically at $5 a day.</p>
        <p>Migratory Minivans</p>
        <p>Since minivans are not considered standard vehicles, guaranteeing that one is available -- especially equipped with a child seat -- should  not be left to chance, particularly outside major cities or in off-peak  travel periods. To accommodate peak seasonal demand, rental companies shift inventory around, bringing in minivans during Colorado's ski season, for example, and Orlando's summertime traffic.</p>
        <p>A reservation will generally ensure a better rate than a last-minute call, according to spokesmen for the car-rental companies, and will hold a vehicle by type, but not by model. The rental companies charge the same rate whatever model is available at the rental counter.</p>
        <p>Avis, (800) 331-1212, www.avis .com, offers Chevrolet Ventures and Astros, Oldsmobile Silhouettes Dodge Caravans and Chrysler's Town and Country. New in 2001 will be Ford Windstars and Pontiac Montanas. Besides built-in child seats, their differences are slight. The Astro, for example, seats an eighth person. The Silhouette features a push-button power sliding door. Windstar has two sliding doors and was the first minivan to receive a five-star rating (the highest) in front crash testing by the National Highway Traffic Safety Administration.</p>
        <p>The minivan inventory at Alamo, (800) 462-5266, www.alamo.com, includes Chevy Ventures and Astros.</p>
        <p>Budget, (800) 527-0700, at www .budget.com, features Windstar and a variety of Chrysler models..</p>
        <p>Dollar, (800) 800-5252, www.dollar .com, offers Chrysler minivans, as does Thrifty, (800) 847-4389, www.thrifty.com.</p>
        <p>Hertz, (800) 654-3131, www.hertz .com, carries Windstars. National, (800) 227-7368, www.nationalcar .com, offers Astros.</p>
        <p>Companies generally require a major credit card at the time of the  reservation to determine the credit-worthiness of a potential customer.  Providing one is cheap insurance,  though, given some companies' ''hold'' policies on promised vehicles.</p>
        <p>Holding a Reservation</p>
        <p>Unlike airline or hotel reservations, where customers are typically charged in advance, a rental car reservation is just that. If a customer fails to claim a reserved car within a few hours of the expected arrival, it goes to someone else.</p>
        <p>At Thrifty, for example, a car secured by a credit card is held for six hours beyond a customer's scheduled arrival time, and the reservation can be canceled anytime before arrival without penalty (but customers can be billed for a day's rental if they don't cancel). Without a card, the hold lapses in two hours, said Jason T. Logan, a Thrifty spokesman in Tulsa, Okla.</p>
        <p>Travelers who are thinking of renting a minivan but have never driven one should try to familiarize themselves with the vehicle first, says Jerry Cheske, an AAA spokesman.  He suggests going to an auto dealer for a test drive, though this advice only goes so far since renters cannot know what model minivan they will end up with. Among models made by the same automaker, though, handling will differ little because they share the same chassis.</p>
        <p>Another way to size up a minivan would be to study a new-car guide, in a bookstore or at a newsstand, which typically includes a vehicle's dimensions, including its cargo area. (Dollar's and Thrifty's Web sites suggest how many people and how much baggage will fit into their vehicles.)</p>
        <p>A minivan presents added driving costs compared with the nation's most popular rental car, the full-size Ford Taurus. At Hertz, for instance, the weekly rate for a minivan in Los Angeles during the Dec. 21-Jan. 9 period is $427, compared with $198 for a Taurus and $390 for a Ford Explorer. At Dollar, during the same period, a minivan would cost $300, a full-size car $190 and an S.U.V. $343. (Tax is extra.)</p>
        <p>Refueling costs differ, too. About 400 miles can be covered on one tankful in either a minivan or a full-size car, but the minivan's capacity is 20 gallons versus 16 gallons in the Taurus. That works out to $36.40 a tank compared with $29.12, based on  $1.82 a gallon, the average price for unleaded regular early this month.</p>
        <p>Car-rental prices are nearly as volatile as air fares and can vary between cities as seasonal demand fluctuates. While rate shopping is convenient at online travel portals like Expedia, Travelocity and CarWiz, better bargains await on rental companies' home pages, said Andrew Hastings, a travel-industry analyst for Gomez, a company in Lincoln, Mass., that rates Internet sites.</p>
        <p>As an example, Avis currently offers online a $339 weekly minivan rental with one free single-day ski pass for certain Western resorts Nov. 1 through April 30. That is about $48 a day plus the value of a lift ticket, around $45.</p>
        <p>However, on the Avis Web site, a minivan rental in Los Angeles around the December holidays was listed at $326 a week; on Travelocity,  $300, with National. It pays to cover all the bases.</p>
        <p>PRACTICAL TRAVELER ANDREA ADELSON is a business writer and minivan owner.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">ANDREA ADELSON is a business writer and minivan owner.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
