<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Korean War, Both Personal and Political</title>
    <meta content="29ART.$09" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242711"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ART REVIEWS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Korean War</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Guild Hall Museum (East Hampton, Ny)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Braff, Phyllis</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stubbing, Newton Haydn (1921-83)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Korean War</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001029T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E2DB1331F93AA15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="969" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Korean War, Both Personal and Political</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Phyllis Braff</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Braff, Phyllis</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Phyllis Braff reviews multipart exhibition on Korean War at Guild Hall Museum, East Hampton, Long Island, works by artist Newton Haydn Stubbing at Nabi Gallery in Sag Harbor and works by six New York and New Jersey artists at Flecker Memorial Gallery in Selden; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>'The Korean War'  Guild Hall Museum, 158 Main Street East Hampton. To Jan. 7. (631) 324-0806.</p>
        <p>Emotions associated with the Korean War are revisited in this absorbing multipart exhibition that looks at the conflict's manifestations in art and culture 50 years after hostilities began. Touching many bases, the show is a reminder of how potent artists' expressions can be when they blend the personal and the political. Messages are quite direct in the sections devoted to war art on loan from the military services, and to photojournalism, illustrations and newspaper cartoons all dating from  1950 through 1953; they are more metaphorical in the area showing recent pieces by younger, Korean-born artists who reflect on the war from their studios in the United States.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>'The Korean War'  Guild Hall Museum, 158 Main Street East Hampton. To Jan. 7. (631) 324-0806.</p>
        <p>Emotions associated with the Korean War are revisited in this absorbing multipart exhibition that looks at the conflict's manifestations in art and culture 50 years after hostilities began. Touching many bases, the show is a reminder of how potent artists' expressions can be when they blend the personal and the political. Messages are quite direct in the sections devoted to war art on loan from the military services, and to photojournalism, illustrations and newspaper cartoons all dating from  1950 through 1953; they are more metaphorical in the area showing recent pieces by younger, Korean-born artists who reflect on the war from their studios in the United States.</p>
        <p>It is especially valuable to be able to see a fine survey of work by the photojournalists and to speculate about the impact that this work had on the public psyche in the pre-television era. Using equipment that would produce telling, sharply detailed closeups, David Douglas Duncan personalizes the pain and conveys the immediacy of fear. A gripping photo essay by Margaret Bourke-White on the effects of war on civilians is psychologically demanding and emphasizes how human factors outweigh the distant battlefield images in achieving a sense of involvement.</p>
        <p>Coming to terms with changing perceptions, the young Korean-American artists often try to make art that demonstrates the dualities they find troublesome. Ik-Joong Kang's super-scale, chocolate-covered statue of General MacArthur deals with the paradox between the American savior handing out candy to hungry children and the overbearing foreign power. In photo montages that cover her body with symbols of war, Yong Soon Min gives a sense of her difficulties handling the role of expatriate.</p>
        <p>With their ability to use varied images, to toy with sequence and to create a specific pace and mood, videos can be particularly effective tools for artists. Soon-Mi Yoo manipulates the inherent fluidity of memories in her 13-minute ''Faith,'' while Y. David Chung juxtaposes the role of a contemporary convenience store clerk with references to ancient traditions and to combat destruction in the eight-minute video component of his installation, ''Turtle Boat Head.''</p>
        <p>Newton Haydn Stubbing  Nabi Gallery, Route 114, Sag Harbor. To Nov. 19. (631) 725 2629.</p>
        <p>Initially conceived as a survey of watercolors and drawings that would touch on four decades of work in England, Scotland, France, Spain and Long Island and that would present many pieces for the first time, this Newton Haydn Stubbing (1921-1983) exhibition broadened its scope by adding paintings from his last years.</p>
        <p>The expansion inevitably focuses a good deal of the attention on the artist's experiments with pigment and calls to mind the international reputation he built in the 50's when he applied paint with his fingers and palms, thus linking physicality and image in a haunting, edgy way. Selections here, from the 70's and early 80's, were executed after Stubbing abandoned these practices for health reasons.</p>
        <p>Landscape configurations and nuanced light appear to be inspirations for this late group. ''Valley Smoke,'' with its evocative pale sky and water and its purple hills is a good example of how Stubbing sought to achieve a powerful perceptual effect with a minimum of description. Dedicated color research seems primary, but a supernatural glow lends an engaging ambiguity.</p>
        <p>Some of the soft, transitory qualities in the paintings are effectively explored in a large number of appealing, ephemeral watercolors that continue to test the play between description, on the one hand, and passages of pure, light-saturated color on the other.</p>
        <p>The inclusion of small works on paper from the 60's based on Stubbing's handprint approach contributes to the show's insights. Highlights among the drawings include several that bracket the exhibition's range: swift studies of ducks done in 1953, during his Madrid residency, and a delicate rendering of a seashell that dates from 1982, a period when he spent much of his time in Sagaponack.</p>
        <p>'Exploring Heritage'  Flecker Memorial Gallery, Suffolk County Community College, Selden. To Nov. 10. (631) 451-4351.</p>
        <p>This powerful show concentrates on six New York and New Jersey artists who make the cultural practices of their heritage a central component in their creative work. The paintings, assemblages and sculpture filling this modest space are  assertive and seem loaded with social and psychological meanings.</p>
        <p>Wennie Huang's installations hint at the multiple meanings possible in interpretations of Chinese traditions.  In ''Summoning the Ghosts,'' scores of paired, regimentally positioned white papier-mache feet march without bodies, implying deprivation and suffering. The impact is almost as unnerving in ''Paper Daughter,'' a gridlike composition of foot images that refers to escaping with false identity documents and also to escaping from the practice of binding the feet of girls.</p>
        <p>Ivan Erickson, who makes bold masks, believes that retaining the art conventions of the Dominican Republic is vital to preserving cultural distinctions. Irene Gennaro, whose vividly colored wood carvings are particularly strong, considers her forms and materials to be influenced by a subconscious awareness of her Sicilian background.</p>
        <p>Kelynn Z. Adler's paintings pay homage to corn in the Mayan culture, especially the grain's life-sustaining properties and spiritually sustaining deities. A nostalgia for ancestral ways is present, and there is the implication that basic qualities are being lost to assimilation.</p>
        <p>Color, organic shapes and diverse materials are important in many of the approaches, particularly in the resonant assemblages by Yolanda Diaz and Michelle Santacross.</p>
        <p>ART REVIEWS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
