<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ideas &amp; Trends; There'll Be a Quiz On This Tomorrow</title>
    <meta content="29ZERN$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/29/weekinreview/29ZERN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242943"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Homework</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zernike, Kate</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Homework</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001029T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E3DC1630F93AA15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="862" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ideas &amp; Trends; There'll Be a Quiz On This Tomorrow</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATE ZERNIKE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zernike, Kate</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Debate over homework has swung back and forth between extremes over last 150 years; homework has been banned at one time and laid on heavy at other times; at present, homework has become a sort of icon of our culture, which admires long hours as the way to the American dream, but some parents are once again voicing concerns about heavy load and skepticism about value of homework (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Using materials found in your home, design assignments that will allow schools in the United States to keep up with those in other countries, allow parents to keep up with the Joneses, but will not keep students up at night. In your answer, you should consider the influence of the Horatio Alger narratives on American society and the impact of longer working hours on the average American family. Parents should be involved, but not too involved. Remember to factor in time for soccer, piano lessons, family togetherness, and a healthy dose of childhood exploration and fun (your answer should define healthy). Those who do not ultimately secure a good job will receive a failing mark. Extra credit for those who gain admission to a college in the U.S. News and World Report Top 20.</p>
        <p>STUMPED? Don't feel bad. Homework isn't really about doing work. It's about what homework stands for.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Using materials found in your home, design assignments that will allow schools in the United States to keep up with those in other countries, allow parents to keep up with the Joneses, but will not keep students up at night. In your answer, you should consider the influence of the Horatio Alger narratives on American society and the impact of longer working hours on the average American family. Parents should be involved, but not too involved. Remember to factor in time for soccer, piano lessons, family togetherness, and a healthy dose of childhood exploration and fun (your answer should define healthy). Those who do not ultimately secure a good job will receive a failing mark. Extra credit for those who gain admission to a college in the U.S. News and World Report Top 20.</p>
        <p>STUMPED? Don't feel bad. Homework isn't really about doing work. It's about what homework stands for.</p>
        <p>Reviled and even banned as recently as 50 years ago, homework has become what one author calls a ''virtual icon of our culture,'' a culture that admires long hours as the way to the American dream. But that admiration has always been undercut by the question: Is all the work worth it?</p>
        <p>This conflict was on display earlier this year, when the school board in Piscataway, N.J., limited nightly assignments and prohibited teachers from grading homework. Parents across the country phoned the district's superintendent to applaud him for his sanity. Others, though, railed at the decline of standards in America.</p>
        <p>The homework pendulum has swung back and forth over the last 150 years. Public health advocates declared homework ''child labor'' in the 1930's, when it was banned in some cities and limited by state law in California.</p>
        <p>Then, in 1957, the Soviets launched Sputnik, creating fear that America would lose the ''space race'' because its kids weren't getting a good science education. Yet another shock hit in 1983, when ''A Nation at Risk,'' a report by the National Commission on Excellence in Education, warned that a ''rising tide of mediocrity'' was threatening the nation's preeminence in industry, business, and technology. In both cases, homework was seen as a way to improve schools and safeguard the nation.</p>
        <p>To this day, said Brian Gill, a researcher at the RAND Corporation and co-author of a 1996 article titled '' 'A Sin Against Childhood': Progressive Education and the Crusade to Abolish Homework, 1897-1941,'' there is a widespread feeling that the educational system is in crisis. One response has been to triple the average homework load of the youngest students since 1981.</p>
        <p>But although some studies suggest that homework improves student test scores, others don't. The broadest of transnational studies, the Third International Math and Science Study in 1995, found no link between homework and achievement. For example, Japanese eighth graders got less homework than their American counterparts, but far outperformed them.</p>
        <p>One reason Americans hold so tightly to  homework is that it is wedded to two cherished national myths. It is the cauldron in which immigrants melt into the melting pot. And it is the ladder that anyone who works hard can climb to the top.</p>
        <p>''For some parents homework is about 'You are in second grade and I want you on that Ivy League track, and one of the ways I can do that is to make sure that you are busy,' '' said Jeffrey M. Young, superintendent of schools in Newton, Mass.</p>
        <p>Homework becomes a status symbol, proof that a school and a child are of a certain caliber. Outlining the 10 purposes of homework, Joyce L. Epstein, director of the Center on School, Family and Community Partnerships at Johns Hopkins University, identifies one as public relations. Schools are judged, she said, by how much homework they give. Juliet B. Schor, a Harvard professor and author of ''The Overworked American,'' and ''The Overspent American,'' recently overheard one parent boast that her child attended the better of two schools in town because it assigned more homework in kindergarten.</p>
        <p>But what of those parents, in Piscataway and elsewhere, who complain of too much homework? Mr. Young and other superintendents say they are as numerous as the parents demanding more work.</p>
        <p>A recent by the Public Agenda Foundation, a nonprofit research group, showed that a mere 10 percent of parents think their children have too much homework, and 64 percent say they receive about the right amount. Last year, another of the group's surveys found that 50 percent of parents had had a serious argument over homework and 34 percent identified it as a ''source of struggle and stress.''</p>
        <p>The two findings are not inconsistent, said Deborah Wadsworth, president of Public Agenda. Rather they indicate the conflict most parents feel. They hate the stress and struggle of homework, but also  want their children to do well.</p>
        <p>Maybe that anxiety is what homework stands for.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
