<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mexico Ending Coziness For Press and Powerful</title>
    <meta content="Y29MEX$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/29/world/29MEXI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242967"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mexico</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mexico City (Mex)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weiner, Tim</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fox Quesada, Vicente</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico/Mexico City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001029T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E1D91630F93AA15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="803" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mexico Ending Coziness For Press and Powerful</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TIM WEINER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Weiner, Tim</byline>
      <dateline>MEXICO CITY, Oct. 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mexico's long-ruling Institutional Revolutionary Party, set to relinquish power to opposition leader Vicente Fox Quesada, may also abandon its dwindling underwriting of press; many of Mexico City's three dozen daily papers, dependent on secret government support in form of paid propaganda posing as news, are likely to collapse (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Fistfights broke out at a Friday night staff meeting at Excelsior, once Mexico's most prestigious daily newspaper, after its managers confessed that it is nearly bankrupt and for sale.</p>
        <p>The truth is, like many other institutions under Mexico's ruling party, it sold out long ago.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Fistfights broke out at a Friday night staff meeting at Excelsior, once Mexico's most prestigious daily newspaper, after its managers confessed that it is nearly bankrupt and for sale.</p>
        <p>The truth is, like many other institutions under Mexico's ruling party, it sold out long ago.</p>
        <p>For decades, many of this nation's newspaper editors, publishers and reporters were bribed with money, sex, promises of power and other pleasures by the leaders of the Institutional Revolutionary Party, which has run Mexico since 1929.</p>
        <p>In turn, the papers helped mold public opinion in ways that pleased the politicians. They received coverage so compliant that they did not have to resort to censorship to control ideas and information.</p>
        <p>''They made a hall of mirrors, to see their own reflections, to think that things were as they said they were,'' said a Mexico City newspaper columnist, Raul Trejo Delarbe.</p>
        <p>But now the mirror is cracking. The party so long in power is about to relinquish the presidency to an outsider, Vicente Fox Quesada, and its underwriting of the press, which has been dwindling for a decade, may be dying. As a result, many of this capital's three dozen daily papers, dependent on secret government support, are likely to collapse.</p>
        <p>The system depended on the party's ceaseless control of power, the president's unfettered access to the treasury and a pliant press taking the bribes. ''I don't pay them so that they can beat me up,'' President Jose Lopez Portillo noted in 1982.</p>
        <p>Many newspapers depended on the money they regularly received for publishing ''gacetillas,'' paid propaganda posing as news. Many reporters printed the party line in exchange for payoffs. Two-thirds or more of Mexico City's dailies worked this way, said several editors. But clear signs suggest that the game is ending.</p>
        <p>The clearest came this month with the news that Excelsior, born with the 1917 revolution, was broke.</p>
        <p>Raymundo Riva Palacio, the editor of the respected daily Milenio, said the collapse of Excelsior was the perfect case study to explain the change coming to Mexico, its former leading party and the press. ''It was the most important newspaper in the last century,'' he said. ''But now the demolition of the old regime is taking its toll, and the newspapers that rely on government financing are having second thoughts.''</p>
        <p>A former presidential press minister went further: ''The PRI's loss of the presidency will mean the disappearance of most of the newspapers in Mexico City,'' he said flatly, contending that some smaller papers had been ''100 percent financed by the government.''</p>
        <p>Under the old system, the government's handouts and the papers' complicity took many forms.</p>
        <p>The most common were the ''gacetillas,'' which continue today. But political reporters, almost all of whom made less than $10,000 a year in salary, also received bribes, called ''chayotes,'' after a small and tasty squash that fits in the palm of the hand. The typical chayote was ''along the lines of three times their monthly wage,'' said Agustin Barrios Gomez, a radio talk-show host and newspaper columnist.</p>
        <p>Bribes also took the form of free food, liquor, airline tickets, cars, prostitutes or concessions on gasoline. The price could be higher for editors: the former governor of Chiapas, Gen. Absalon Gonzales, once paid $40,000 to kill a story, Mr. Riva Palacio said.</p>
        <p>A more subtle form of government manipulation was the direct financing of a number of smaller papers not only to distort the news but also to fragment the market and guarantee that no voice could grow too strong. ''It was a legitimate strategy of the government,'' the former press minister said.</p>
        <p>But that system began falling apart in the mid-1990's, as President Carlos Salinas began to cut back on government spending on the press, preferring more modern systems of spin. His successor, President Ernesto Zedillo, arguably Mexico's least corrupt modern president, cut back further and ''the perception is that things will change radically with Fox,'' Mr. Riva Palacio said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fox has said that in his presidency, which begins Dec. 1, the press in Mexico ''is going to have to follow the rules of ethics and responsibility, in an open and transparent way.''</p>
        <p>Several journalists said the old system eventually began to work against the politicians, who started to actually believe the stories they had planted in the press.</p>
        <p>''The politicians read their clips -- a different reality than the reality in the streets,'' Mr. Riva Palacio said. ''They misread reality.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
