<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Art of Listening</title>
    <meta content="29FINKELT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242583"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Finkle, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, Anna Deavere</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Talk to Me: Listening Between the Lines (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001029T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E0D9123EF93AA15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="729" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Art of Listening</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By David Finkle</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Finkle, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>David Finkle reviews book Talk to Me: Listening Between the Lines by Anna Deavere Smith (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TALK TO ME</p>
        <p>Listening Between the Lines.</p>
        <p>By Anna Deavere Smith.</p>
        <p>300 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Random House. $24.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TALK TO ME</p>
        <p>Listening Between the Lines.</p>
        <p>By Anna Deavere Smith.</p>
        <p>300 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Random House. $24.95.</p>
        <p>In Anna Deavere Smith's ''Talk to Me: Listening Between the Lines'' -- which is something of a memoir, something of a treatise on American character(s), something of a record of her theater career -- she objects at one point to being labeled a ''performance artist.''</p>
        <p>She's right to complain, since the term has acquired pejorative connotations after years of abuse by dubious practitioners. Indeed, if her one-woman plays (perhaps the most successful being ''Fires in the Mirror'') don't establish her as the inventor of contemporary documentary theater, she is indisputably its foremost advocate.</p>
        <p>Smith's M.O. is to select a topic -- often a divisive national event -- and conduct hundreds of interviews with concerned parties. Then she analyzes her tapes, decides which can be most cogently acted out and proceeds to construct a script that's usually notable for its balanced reportage. In both ''Fires in the Mirror,'' her account of the Crown Heights riots between Jews and blacks in 1991, and ''Twilight: Los Angeles, 1992,'' which examined the riots following the first Rodney King trial verdict, her lack of bias is astonishing.</p>
        <p>With ''Talk to Me,'' she goes behind the scenes and explains what she's listening for in the process of compiling a work she calls ''On the Road: A Search for American Character.'' What delights her ears is surprising: a trochee. That's right, a two-syllable metrical rhythm in which an accented syllable is followed by an unaccented one. In the 1960's, her acting-school Shakespeare teacher said that ''if you got a trochee in the second beat, a character was really 'losing it' psychologically, and this 'loss' made it possible for you to really know something about that character.'' Smith adds: ''Character, then, seemed to me to be an improvisation on given rhythms. The more successful you were at improvising on language . . . the more likely you could be found in your language, that is, if you wanted to be found in your language.''</p>
        <p>Literal and figurative trochees and rhythms are what she reports in her patchwork book, which leaps back and forth from the Baltimore of her childhood to the 1996 Republican National Convention in San Diego to a revealing 1997 meeting with Bill Clinton in the Oval Office that she characterizes as ''jazz.'' (Apparently, the president isn't a saxophonist for nothing.) The ostensible occasion for her reminiscence is her play, ''House Arrest,'' a look at the presidency and the press. Ultimately, however, she's attempting to size up the nation at a time when, as the rhetoric professor Hayden White tells her, the triumph of Western capitalism has been ''to identify democracy with the free market.''</p>
        <p>Smith takes up her task at full throttle, occasionally letting a bias show as she holds forth -- or lets others hold forth. Set out on the page as if they're poetry -- and perhaps they do qualify -- are excerpts from her interviews with Studs Terkel, George Stephanopoulos, Peggy Noonan, Helen Thomas, Mike McCurry, Maxine Waters, Marlin Fitzwater, James Carville, Arianna Huffington, Barney Frank, Ben Bradlee, Mike Wallace and others. Her chat with Ed Bradley goes, in part, like this:</p>
        <p>''Um</p>
        <p>I think the press is</p>
        <p>individually and collectively a captive</p>
        <p>of the White House</p>
        <p>[He puts a spoonful of yogurt in his mouth, and scrapes the cup]</p>
        <p>In that</p>
        <p>you go there every day.</p>
        <p>And you stay there.''</p>
        <p>Not so incidentally, Bradley puts into words some of what Smith wants to say about the compromised status of the press. But while she may be chasing a theory, she never catches it cleanly. It's one of the drawbacks of the ''House Arrest'' journey. Also, Smith does something in ''Talk to Me'' that she never does on stage -- she pontificates. ''I suggest here that knowledge will not save the world. We have shrunken hearts.''</p>
        <p>Smith may well be right, but she certainly sounds overbearing. And yet, whatever the shortcomings of her sprawling new book, it succeeds in teaching one crucial lesson: those who truly listen, truly hear.</p>
        <p>David Finkle writes frequently about books and the theater.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">David Finkle writes frequently about books and the theater.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
