<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lorin Latarro, Howard Lev</title>
    <meta content="29LATA$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Society Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242895"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="WEDDINGS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEDDINGS AND ENGAGEMENTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">LATARRO, LORIN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEV, HOWARD SAMUEL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Weddings and Celebrations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001029T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03EEDF1F31F93AA15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="578" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lorin Latarro, Howard Lev</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lorin Latarro, a dancer in the Broadway musical ''Swing,'' and Howard Samuel Lev, a marketing executive, were married last night by Rabbi Stanley Asekoff at the Pleasantdale Chateau in West Orange, N.J.</p>
        <p>Ms. Latarro graduated from the Juilliard School, and later was a dancer with Momix, a modern dance company directed by Moses Pendleton. Born Lorin Carmela Campolattaro, the bride is a daughter of Eileen Campolattaro and Dr. John Campolattaro of Fairfield, N.J. The bride's father, a dentist, has a private practice in Fairfield.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Lorin Latarro, a dancer in the Broadway musical ''Swing,'' and Howard Samuel Lev, a marketing executive, were married last night by Rabbi Stanley Asekoff at the Pleasantdale Chateau in West Orange, N.J.</p>
        <p>Ms. Latarro graduated from the Juilliard School, and later was a dancer with Momix, a modern dance company directed by Moses Pendleton. Born Lorin Carmela Campolattaro, the bride is a daughter of Eileen Campolattaro and Dr. John Campolattaro of Fairfield, N.J. The bride's father, a dentist, has a private practice in Fairfield.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lev is the chief operating officer of Global Fashion Village, a marketing company specializing in the fashion and entertainment industries, in New York. He graduated from the University of Maryland and is a son of Aura and Melvin Lev of New York. The bridegroom's father is a vice president for business coordination in New York for M-WEB, a wireless Internet company based in Sao Paulo, Brazil.</p>
        <p>Ms. Latarro and Mr. Lev met in the fall of 1996, at the Krispy Kreme store on 23rd Street in Manhattan. Earlier that year, Mr. Lev, his father and other family members had bought the rights to establish New York and New Jersey franchises for Krispy Kreme, the Southern doughnut chain. On this October day, Mr. Lev was behind the counter, helping out.</p>
        <p>''In true dancer's fashion, I ordered a dozen doughnuts and skim milk -- to balance out the calories,'' Ms. Latarro remembered with a laugh. Mr. Lev, who didn't stock skim milk, said in a good-natured way, ''You just ordered a dozen doughnuts; maybe you can make do with low-fat milk.'' It was his standard response to the not uncommon request for skim milk by people who ordered lots of doughnuts. For her part, Ms. Latarro noted that the man in the uniform -- khaki pants, olive button-down shirt and ''goofy'' baseball cap that had ''Krispy Kreme'' on the front -- ''was cute.''</p>
        <p>About a year later, on Nov. 22, Mr. Lev was doing a Krispy Kreme promotion with Michelle Visage, a morning host on WKTU, an FM radio station in New York. On the air, Ms. Visage complimented Mr. Lev on his looks, and said she would like to set him up with a friend. Ms. Visage then called Ms. Latarro, who was sleeping at the time, and put her on the air.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lev recalled, ''I was stuck with having to strike up a conversation with a stranger in front of a couple of million people.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Lattaro didn't realize she was talking to the same person she thought was cute. ''All I cared about was when he was going to open a store on the Upper West Side,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lev called Ms. Latarro that afternoon and left a message. Ms. Latarro took two weeks to return the call. After a pleasant half-hour conversation, they made a date for a Saturday night dinner.</p>
        <p>''He picked me up at my place,'' she remembered. ''When I opened the door, I instantly recognized him. I was surprised and thrilled that the cute guy in the goofy Krispy Kreme hat was going to be my date.''</p>
        <p>WEDDINGS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
