<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Way We Live Now: 10-29-00: Expert Opinion; Duck and Cover</title>
    <meta content="WLN103044" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242670"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Romanko, J R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001029T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E6D81231F93AA15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="915" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Way We Live Now: 10-29-00: Expert Opinion; Duck and Cover</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By J.R. Romanko</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Romanko, J R</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Experts offer advice on how Americans traveling abroad can protect themselves from terrorists; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Col. Ed Badolato, retired, executive director of the Counterterrorism and Security Foundation.  ''No. 1, get as much information as you can. Get the post report off the State Department's Web site. On a bus tour, ask what type of security services are provided. In some countries, they will put a policeman on the bus. Don't show your American passport unless asked for. I survived a lot of spook work in the Middle East, and if someone asked me where I was from, I'd say Canada. And if you think you're under surveillance, go into a reputable shop and say: 'I'm nervous here. Would you call the police or a cab.' Just get out. Don't try to outthink them.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Col. Ed Badolato, retired, executive director of the Counterterrorism and Security Foundation.  ''No. 1, get as much information as you can. Get the post report off the State Department's Web site. On a bus tour, ask what type of security services are provided. In some countries, they will put a policeman on the bus. Don't show your American passport unless asked for. I survived a lot of spook work in the Middle East, and if someone asked me where I was from, I'd say Canada. And if you think you're under surveillance, go into a reputable shop and say: 'I'm nervous here. Would you call the police or a cab.' Just get out. Don't try to outthink them.''</p>
        <p>Neil Livingstone, chairman of GlobalOptions, an international risk-management firm, and author of ''How to Protect Yourself in an Uncertain World''  ''If you're checking in as part of a group, don't stand with all of the group at the counter. Never have your company or government affiliation on your suitcase. Stay in the hotels of the local gentry rather than in the Hyatt. Don't stay on the ground level, in case something bad happens on the street. But in places like Korea, don't stay above the seventh floor, because fire ladders don't go that high. If you want to see if someone's been in your room, you can leave a voice-activated tape recorder in a drawer slightly cracked. Move around on your own, not in groups. Window seats are much safer than aisle seats, because hijackers never say, 'Excuse me, sir, let me through so I can get that guy by the window.' But if you are hijacked, don't make eye contact. And if you're arrested and interrogated, agree with them.''</p>
        <p>P. Edward Haley, professor of international relations at Claremont McKenna College in California  ''Minimize your exposure to places that are difficult to monitor. I personally don't like to go in a bus. I'll go in a cab. Also, I don't know that there's anyone in Europe who wears khaki, other than American tourists.''</p>
        <p>Robert Young Pelton, author of ''Come Back Alive'' and ''The World's Most Dangerous Places''  ''Get beyond the typical government or travel-agent advice. Use the Internet, use local newspapers, talk to your cabdriver. As for saying you're from Canada, that doesn't work. The leader of FARC in Colombia called me 'Gringo' and tried to kidnap me. I kept saying, 'I'm Canadian,' but they don't care. They just see us as gringos.''</p>
        <p>Frank Cilluffo, director of the terrorism task force at the Center for Strategic and International Studies  ''Don't be paranoid. If you stop traveling, the terrorists win by default. But the simple fact is, you can't protect everything everywhere all the time. Embassies can harden their security all they can, but you're displacing risks and telling the terrorists to look for other targets, making it more likely to go to businessmen and tourists.''</p>
        <p>-- J.R. Romanko</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
