<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Nonbeliever's Plaint: Who Let the Fans Out?</title>
    <meta content="29BASE$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/29/living/29BASE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242860"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Martin, Rick</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001029T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE1D71E31F93AA15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1140" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Nonbeliever's Plaint: Who Let the Fans Out?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICK MARIN</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Rick Martin comment on worst time to be sports wimp--when New York is having a Subway Series; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN ''Bright Lights, Big City,'' Jay McInerney's narrator ducks into a New York bar where there's a basketball game on TV. A barfly offers some obscene commentary.</p>
        <p>''He seemed to expect a response, so you ask him what period it is,'' Mr. McInerney writes. ''He looks you up and down, as if you were carrying a volume of poetry or wearing funny shoes. 'Third quarter,' he answers. Then he turns away.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN ''Bright Lights, Big City,'' Jay McInerney's narrator ducks into a New York bar where there's a basketball game on TV. A barfly offers some obscene commentary.</p>
        <p>''He seemed to expect a response, so you ask him what period it is,'' Mr. McInerney writes. ''He looks you up and down, as if you were carrying a volume of poetry or wearing funny shoes. 'Third quarter,' he answers. Then he turns away.''</p>
        <p>Mr. McInerney's sorrowful young Werther goes on about how alienating it feels to be locked out of that great fraternity of male camaraderie: sports fandom. To be clueless about the one thing every man, blue-collar or banker, has in common: the game. To be, let's be honest, a sports wimp.</p>
        <p>Hey, at least there wasn't a Subway Series going on!</p>
        <p>Was there ever a worse time or place not to be into sports than last week in New York? The city was ransomed by face-painted yahoos who were granted unlimited media time to express complex prognostications like ''Yanks in five! No doubt!'' Restaurants installed giant screens so their clientele could indulge in the classy pastime of watching the games while eating.</p>
        <p>My own company cafeteria was festooned with Mets and Yankees pennants. At one point one of the cashiers, who ring people up on both sides of the register, doctored his Subway Series T-shirt with handmade signs indicating that employees should line up on one side of him if they were pro-Yankees, the other if they were pro-Mets. There was no wimp line.</p>
        <p>That day I happened to be having lunch with a young journalism student, who confessed that he, too, didn't know or care about sports. What does he do when his fellow students try to engage him in sports banter? ''I just try to tell them what they want to hear,'' he said, shrugging. ''Whatever is the shortest possible answer.''</p>
        <p>I do the same thing. The doormen in my building accosted me morning and night, demanding a reaction to their elation or  outrage over the outcome of the previous night's game. I smiled feebly and nodded, or lifted my hands and mimed a ''no-speakee-English'' gesture.</p>
        <p>Superbowls and N.B.A. championships go by. I don't watch, don't care. Golf? I'd rather have my eyes poked out with five irons. Tennis I follow, because I play. But let's face it, tennis is a wimpy sport.</p>
        <p>I wasn't always this indifferent. As a nipper, I consumed all sports ravenously. Hockey, of course. Growing up in Toronto, after all. (Go Leafs!). But also football: both the American version and the Canadian league with its three downs, 110-yard field and, briefly, Joe Theisman. I watched baseball, the Olympics and every ''Battle of the Network Stars.'' (Go Robert Conrad!)</p>
        <p>I played sports at school -- there are limits to my wimpiness -- but the baseball cards went in the closet with the stamps, coins and bottle cap collection. I struck the pose of a cerebral hipster with more important things on his mind than who was going to win the Conn Smythe trophy. Things like great literature and skinny ties. I thought this would prove advantageous with the ladies, that I would be a welcome change from the armchair all-Americans who sat around in their underwear all weekend grunting for beers. I was wrong. Turns out women like sports. What's more, they like guys who like them. The Neanderthal underwear guy is like a whiff of Aqua Velva: a primitive indulgence that reminds them of their fathers.</p>
        <p>I console myself by thinking about the hours I've saved, the years added to my life by not watching sports. Not that I'm doing anything constructive with that time, but it's there in case I need it.</p>
        <p>George Will and David Halberstam and Richard Ben Cramer can get all intellectual and deep about baseball. But come on, who are they kidding? Allow me to quote from the song that Wednesday's New York Daily News called the Mets' anthem, ''Who Let the Dogs Out?''</p>
        <p>Who let the dogs out?</p>
        <p>Woof, woof, woof, woof woof.</p>
        <p>Who let the dogs out?</p>
        <p>Woof, woof, woof, woof woof.</p>
        <p>There are more lyrics but they are all exactly the same.</p>
        <p>The only reason I know about this little ditty is because Pat Kiernan, the early morning anchor on New York 1, read it in its entirety in his ''In the Papers'' segment. Not without some sardonic intonation, I might add.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kiernan looks about 12 but seems wise beyond his years. After a bunch of fan-in-the-street interviews on the Subway Series, a New York 1 reporter asked Mr. Kiernan which team's chances he liked for that night's game. Mr. Kiernan improvised some blather about ''playoff experience'' and other cliches. I sensed a kindred spirit.</p>
        <p>''Because of my job, I'm forced to pay attention to some articles I wouldn't otherwise,'' he said, when I called him to ask if he considered himself a sports wimp. ''I freely confess that there are times between stories that I will turn around to my producers and ask the stupidest sports question.''</p>
        <p>This summer, the front page of The New York Times reported that researchers had found sports fans to be better adjusted mentally than nonfans. As James C. McKinley Jr., a Times reporter, wrote:</p>
        <p>''Psychologists have long suspected that many die-hard fans are lonely, alienated people searching for self-esteem by identifying with a sports team. But a study at the University of Kansas suggests just the opposite -- that sports fans suffer fewer bouts of depression and alienation than do people who are uninterested in sports.''</p>
        <p>The general idea is that fans get a sense of well-being by tapping into a primal instinct to cheer on warriors who are out there killing other warriors from a rival borough.</p>
        <p>Reading these findings made me wonder if my occasional bouts of malaise were due to the fact that for the longest time I thought the Mets logo was the Yankee symbol, because of its old-timey font.</p>
        <p>A hard-core baseball fan ranted at me the other night that this was really a suburb series between New Jersey and Long Island. That made me feel better, as a New Yorker: the idea that New York had very little to do with it.</p>
        <p>Back when I did follow sports, I always rooted for the underdog.</p>
        <p>Go Mets.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
