<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Q &amp; A</title>
    <meta content="29QNA.$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/29/travel/29QNA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242629"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Columns/Q and A</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001029T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E2DA1731F93AA15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1090" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Q &amp; A</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUZANNE MacNEILLE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Christmas in London</p>
        <p>Q.  I'm trying to find Christmas events in London in early December that would appeal to my daughters, ages 6 and 8. Can you help? -- M. W. S., Seattle</p>
        <p>A.  London goes all out for Christmas and you'll find no shortage of things to do, even if it's just looking at the holiday lights and windows or visiting the Christmas tree in Trafalgar Square.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Christmas in London</p>
        <p>Q.  I'm trying to find Christmas events in London in early December that would appeal to my daughters, ages 6 and 8. Can you help? -- M. W. S., Seattle</p>
        <p>A.  London goes all out for Christmas and you'll find no shortage of things to do, even if it's just looking at the holiday lights and windows or visiting the Christmas tree in Trafalgar Square.</p>
        <p>On Dec. 2, the 20th Great Christmas Pudding Race takes place at the Covent Garden Piazza. Street entertainment, including live music and magic shows, starts at 11:30 a.m., an hour before the race. The runners, who are in costume, carry Christmas puddings on a tray in a relay around the market. The object is to win the race with one's Christmas pudding intact. The contest is open to all. The entry fee is $86 (proceeds go to cancer research); viewing the race, however, is free. Information: (44 20) 7404 8760.</p>
        <p>The Millennium Dome at Greenwich will have an ice rink, carol singers, brass bands and a Christmas market. Details will be available next month at www.dome 2000.co.uk. Tickets: $29; $24 for children 5 to 15 (at 69 pence to the dollar). Information: (44-87) 0606 2000.</p>
        <p>The Dulwich Picture Gallery, on Gallery Road in southeast London, will feature an exhibition of 100 works by E. H. Shepard, who illustrated the Winnie-the-Pooh books. The show runs from Dec. 5 to Jan. 14. On Dec. 10 at 3 p.m., a narrator and a pianist will perform Prokofiev's ''Peter and the Wolf,'' to be followed by a tea party for children and their favorite teddy bears. Admission: $8.70, $5.80 for children. Information: call (44-20) 8693 5254 or visit www.dulwichpicturegallery.org.uk.</p>
        <p>From Nov. 18 to Jan. 7, Legoland in Windsor, 21 miles west of London, is planning several events, including ''Peter Pan's Christmas Adventure,'' a 25-minute show performed throughout the day in the Imagination Theater. Details on other activities will be on the park's Web site, www.legoland.co.uk, next month. Open daily, except Christmas Day and New Year's. Admission: $26, children $22. Information: (44-87) 0504 0404.</p>
        <p>Victoria B &amp; B's</p>
        <p>Q.  My daughter and I are planning a trip to Victoria, British Columbia, in December and we'd like to share a room in a reasonably priced bed-and-breakfast. We hope to spend no more than $100 a night. -- M. M., Phoenix</p>
        <p>A.  There are dozens of moderately priced bed-and-breakfasts in and around Victoria, many of them in lovely historic houses. Here are a few possibilities, gathered from several sources.</p>
        <p>Ryan's Bed and Breakfast, 224 Superior Street, has seven guest rooms in a rambling 1892 Victorian house, 10-minutes from downtown. Rooms are furnished with antiques and have private bathrooms. Prices vary throughout the year. During your visit, double rooms range from $50 to $90 a night. The rates go as low as $40 in January and as high as $130 in  the summer. Prices are figured at  $1.51 Canadian to the United States dollar. Information: (877) 389-0012, fax (250) 389-2857.</p>
        <p>Medana Grove, 162 Medana Street, also about a 10-minute walk from downtown, has three guest rooms with private baths in a two-story Edwardian house with stained glass windows and antique furnishings. Low season rates range from $56 to $73 a night for a double room; in the summer, rates are $73 to $90. Information: (800) 269-1188, fax (250) 389-0425, www.victoriabnb.com.</p>
        <p>Oak Bay Guest House, 1052 Newport Avenue, a 20-minute drive east of downtown, is in a quiet, leafy area called Oak Bay. There are 11 guest rooms in a Tudor-style house, many with four-poster beds and all with private baths. The rates range from  $53 in the winter to $120 in the summer. Information: (800) 575-3812, fax (250) 598-0369, www.oakbayguest house.com.</p>
        <p>Tourism Victoria has listings of all kinds of accommodations. Its office, at 812 Wharf Street, is open daily;  call (250) 953-2033 or visit www .tourismvictoria.com.</p>
        <p>Tea in Paris</p>
        <p>Q.  We'll be visiting Paris and thought it would be pleasant to take a break from museums and shopping by having tea in a salon de the. Any suggestions? -- Gilberto Rizzo, Redding, Conn.</p>
        <p>A.  Though Paris is famous for its cafes, it also has numerous salons de the, many of which opened in the 19th century. Reservations are not accepted at the places mentioned below, except for lunch. Unless otherwise noted, they are open daily and close early in the evening, around 7 or 8.</p>
        <p>Mariage Freres, a tea room and shop at 30-32, rue du Bourg-Tibourg, in the Fourth Arrondissement, opened in the Marais neighborhood on the Right Bank in 1854. The shop is  outfitted with the original tea canisters, scales and worn wood counters. In the tea room, large tropical plants shade a tightly packed sea of small tables. There are more than 450 teas from 32 countries, ranging from about $5 to $10.25 for a pot (at 7.81 francs to the dollar). Desserts include green tea cake served with tea gelee (about $5). Mariage Freres also has shops on the Left Bank, at 13, rue des Grands-Augustins, and at 260, rue du Faubourg St.-Honore. Information: (33-1) 42.72.28.11.</p>
        <p>Laduree also dates from the mid-19th century. Its original home at 16, rue Royale in the Eighth Arrondissement, near the Place de la Madeleine, is decorated with lots of mirrors, frescoes and marble-topped tables. There is also a newer branch at 75, avenue des Champs-Elysees. Laduree serves 11 varieties of teas, ranging from a Chinese smoked black tea at $4 to a pot of Darjeeling at $5.75. Laduree's macaroons are famous -- the large macaroons cost $2.80 while small ones cost about $1. Information: (33-1) 40.75.08.75.</p>
        <p>Angelina, a 100-year-old tea parlor at 226, rue de Rivoli in the First Arrondissement, is known as much for its thick hot chocolate ($4.75 for a pot) and Mont Blanc dessert -- a combination of meringue, chestnut cream and flavored whipped cream ($4.75) -- as its teas. Information: (33-1) 42.60.82.00.</p>
        <p>The Paris Mosque, 29 rue Geoffroy-St.-Hilaire, in the Fifth Arrondissement, has a richly decorated tea room, with ornate woodwork, marble floors and shiny copper platter tables. Sweetened mint tea and honey pastries are the specialties here. Tea and pastries cost about $2.50 The tea room is open from 9 a.m. to 11:30 p.m. Information:  (33-1) 43.31.38.20.</p>
        <p>SUZANNE MacNEILLE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
