<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Campaign Briefing</title>
    <meta content="29CAMP$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/29/politics/29CAMP.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1243000"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001029T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E2DC1730F93AA15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="662" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Campaign Briefing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by B. Drummond Ayres Jr.</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE HOUSE</p>
        <p>GUN CONTROL COATTAILS -- A ballot initiative in Colorado that would require a criminal background check on anyone who buys a gun from an unlicensed dealer is expected to pass with such ease that Ken Toltz, a Democrat running for the House of Representatives, is betting he can ride the measure's coattails to victory.</p>
        <p>Mr. Toltz, who is trying to unseat Representative Tom Tancredo, a Republican from the state's Sixth Congressional District, is a proponent of strong gun control measures and has won the endorsement of Handgun Control Inc. Mr. Tancredo, a conservative Republican, opposes any new controls.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE HOUSE</p>
        <p>GUN CONTROL COATTAILS -- A ballot initiative in Colorado that would require a criminal background check on anyone who buys a gun from an unlicensed dealer is expected to pass with such ease that Ken Toltz, a Democrat running for the House of Representatives, is betting he can ride the measure's coattails to victory.</p>
        <p>Mr. Toltz, who is trying to unseat Representative Tom Tancredo, a Republican from the state's Sixth Congressional District, is a proponent of strong gun control measures and has won the endorsement of Handgun Control Inc. Mr. Tancredo, a conservative Republican, opposes any new controls.</p>
        <p>Guns are a big issue in the Sixth District. Columbine High School, scene of the nation's worst school shootings, lies within its boundaries.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tancredo holds a slight lead in the polls going into the final week of the campaign. But Mr. Toltz, a businessman in his first political race, is betting the popular ballot initiative will swing enough support his way for him to overcome that lead on Nov. 7.</p>
        <p>''The initiative has galvanized the suburbs, and for some people in the cause, it's the first time they have ever been involved in a political campaign,'' he says. ''Understandably, that should help us.''</p>
        <p>Michael Janofsky (NYT)</p>
        <p>THE SENATE</p>
        <p>NO DEBATE FOR KENNEDY -- It seems Massachusetts political addicts will be deprived of what many had expected to be the next big show of the season, a debate between Edward M. Kennedy and the challengers for his Senate seat.</p>
        <p>Senator Kennedy says that because the legislative session in Washington continues to drag on, there is not enough time to schedule a debate and that he plans to devote what little campaigning time remains after the session to talking directly to the people of Massachusetts.</p>
        <p>One of the senator's long-shot opponents, Carla Howell, the Libertarian candidate, says the state's newspapers and broadcast stations should press him to debate. The Republican challenger, Jack E. Robinson,  has offered to donate $2,500 to the charity of the senator's choice if he will change his mind.</p>
        <p>Carey Goldberg (NYT)</p>
        <p>THE ADVERTISING</p>
        <p>ACCESS TO THE AIR -- A public radio station in Washington has surprised its listeners in recent days by broadcasting advertisements for several Congressional candidates from the area.</p>
        <p>Why, since the station, WAMU, is a listener-supported, noncommercial operation owned by American University?</p>
        <p>The answer is that since 1972, under a provision of the Federal Communications Act, broadcasters are required to provide candidates for federal office with ''reasonable access'' to air time.</p>
        <p>Two candidates -- Terry Lierman, a Democrat running in Maryland's Eighth Congressional District, and Marc Rossi, an independent running in Virginia's 10th Congressional District -- asked for that access.</p>
        <p>They got it, without charge.</p>
        <p>Other area candidates have also been inquiring about access, station officials report. And a number of listeners have called to complain about the highly partisan spots.</p>
        <p>(NYT)</p>
        <p>FORWARDING ADDRESS -- Chicago election officials say a Web site that advertised it was buying absentee votes in the presidential election and selling them in batches to the highest bidders may still be violating the law even though it has changed its address and sales language. ''It's still a wolf in sheep's clothing,'' a spokesman for the city's Board of Elections, Tom Leach, says.</p>
        <p>The board won a court order last week that resulted in the Web site's being shut down. But then the site, voteauction.com, changed its address to vote-auction.com and reopened for business, talking of dealing in votes through ''contributions.''</p>
        <p>The board plans to seek a contempt citation.</p>
        <p>The Web site operation, which also is being investigated by election officials in other states, is owned by Hans Bernhard of Vienna, Austria, who runs a marketing company.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
