<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At an Iowa Rally, Nader's Supporters Stand Their Ground</title>
    <meta content="29NADE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/29/politics/29NADE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1243001"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE GREEN PARTY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iowa City (Iowa)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iowa</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cooper, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nader, Ralph</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Iowa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/Ralph Nader</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Iowa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Iowa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001029T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E1DC1730F93AA15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="618" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At an Iowa Rally, Nader's Supporters Stand Their Ground</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL COOPER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cooper, Michael</byline>
      <dateline>CEDAR RAPIDS, Iowa, Oct. 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ralph Nader supporters crowd Iowa City, Iowa, hall to hear him speak; score charges that his candidacy aids Gov George W Bush; Nader scores Democrats, speech; holds he does not have to attack Bush because dangers of Bush presidency are more apparent, interview (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>At every mention of the word ''spoiler,'' the crowd groaned.</p>
        <p>The students and others who packed a hall at the University of Iowa on Friday night to hear Ralph Nader, the Green Party's presidential candidate, justify his campaign simply did not want to hear any more about the possibility that they would throw the election to Gov. George W. Bush. They were so upset at being confronted with the evil of two lesser candidates, they said, that they refused to vote again for the lesser of two evils.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>At every mention of the word ''spoiler,'' the crowd groaned.</p>
        <p>The students and others who packed a hall at the University of Iowa on Friday night to hear Ralph Nader, the Green Party's presidential candidate, justify his campaign simply did not want to hear any more about the possibility that they would throw the election to Gov. George W. Bush. They were so upset at being confronted with the evil of two lesser candidates, they said, that they refused to vote again for the lesser of two evils.</p>
        <p>''This year the choice is between George W. Bush and a Democrat who is to the right of Bill Clinton,'' complained Ed Fallon, a Democratic state representative who introduced Mr. Nader. ''I don't begrudge my friends and constituents who plan to vote for Al Gore. I understand their fear of George W. Bush. But voting against somebody isn't enough anymore. If I had three hands maybe I could hold my nose, my gut and my mouth and vote for Al Gore. But in good conscience, I can't, I won't, and you shouldn't either.''</p>
        <p>Democrats were certainly nervous about the possibility: the party dispatched the Rev. Jesse Jackson and the comedian Al Franken to address students at the university, which is in Iowa City, that same afternoon.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nader himself was unsparing in his criticism of the Democrats, attacking them more often and more harshly than he did the Republicans. In an interview after the speech, he explained that he did not feel the need to go after Mr. Bush because the problems of a Bush presidency were more readily apparent.</p>
        <p>''Bush is a corporation running for president disguised as a person,'' he said, ''Whereas Gore touts his environmental record, says he can match it against anyone, even me. And that's an invitation.''</p>
        <p>Others said that to wean national politics from its dependence on big business, and to give a voice to people against the death penalty, the war on drugs, genetically altered crops, economic sanctions in Iraq and a host of other causes that the people here felt deeply about, radical change was necessary.</p>
        <p>Simply put, they said, things may have to get  worse before they get better. One labor leader used the analogy of a strike: the workers would be willing to endure ''short-term pain'' to win long-term reforms and benefits.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nader used another analogy, pointing out President Reagan's appointment of James Watt as the Interior Secretary, which so infuriated environmentally minded Americans that the rolls of watchdog groups doubled. ''He was a provocateur,'' Mr. Nader said, explaining that a more palatable appointment might have been an ''anesthetizer'' that would have left those people complacent. ''Sometimes people need a provocateur,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Late in the evening, a woman asked Mr. Nader whether by voting for him she would be electing Mr. Bush and endangering the right to abortions. Mr. Nader told her that it would not necessarily happen, noting that conservative presidents have appointed liberal judges to the Supreme Court and vice versa.</p>
        <p>The evening showed why the Nader campaign has been a political phenomenon. Not only did he fill a hall with nearly a thousand students, but many who came donated $3.50 for the privilege.</p>
        <p>Unlike the major candidates, who speak about issues like Social Security and Medicare that are aimed at elderly voters, and issues like education that are aimed at parents, Mr. Nader tailored his message to the young.</p>
        <p>''If you don't 'turn on' to politics,'' he warned, ''politics will turn on you.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE GREEN PARTY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
