<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CONGRESS BACKING PROJECTS AT HOME AT A RECORD PACE</title>
    <meta content="29PORK$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/29/politics/29PORK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1243022"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">House of Representatives (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schmitt, Eric</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001029T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07EEDA1730F93AA15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1266" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CONGRESS BACKING PROJECTS AT HOME AT A RECORD PACE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC SCHMITT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schmitt, Eric</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>congress backing project</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A few years back, the people of Toledo, Ohio, began building a new four-lane boulevard linking the northern edge of town to Interstate 280. But the money ran out before they could put on the finishing touches.</p>
        <p>So earlier this month, Representative Marcy Kaptur, a nine-term Democrat from Toledo, set out to fix that. As a senior member of the House Appropriations Committee, she tucked $250,000 into a transportation spending bill to line the otherwise barren twin ribbons of asphalt with two miles of trees, shrubs and flower beds.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A few years back, the people of Toledo, Ohio, began building a new four-lane boulevard linking the northern edge of town to Interstate 280. But the money ran out before they could put on the finishing touches.</p>
        <p>So earlier this month, Representative Marcy Kaptur, a nine-term Democrat from Toledo, set out to fix that. As a senior member of the House Appropriations Committee, she tucked $250,000 into a transportation spending bill to line the otherwise barren twin ribbons of asphalt with two miles of trees, shrubs and flower beds.</p>
        <p>''It needed major landscaping,'' said Ms. Kaptur, a former city planner who justified the federal money because the spur, the Greenbelt Parkway, connects to a federal highway.</p>
        <p>Democrats may be in the minority in Congress and may be complaining about the death of many of their legislative priorities, but when it comes to securing pet projects back home, from the most senior and secure lawmakers, like Ms. Kaptur, to the most junior and insecure members, Democrats hold their own with Republican rivals.</p>
        <p>As lawmakers struggle to adjourn for the year, Democratic leaders are taking special care to funnel heaping helpings of pork to their most vulnerable incumbents, including Rush D. Holt of New Jersey and Joseph M. Hoeffel of Pennsylvania. ''From our point of view, most of them have been very well taken care of,'' one senior House Democratic aide said.</p>
        <p>Pork-barrel politics is nothing new and lawmakers from both parties engage in it. Fueled by a fat economy, budget surpluses and an election-year eagerness to shower favors on voters, Congress is on pace to set a record this year in steering taxpayer money to projects like sunflower research in North Dakota, reindeer herders in Alaska and mapping chicken genes in Michigan.</p>
        <p>There's so much pork that one Republican House candidate, Derek Smith of Utah, is not even in Congress, but Representative Dick Armey of Texas, the majority leader, had $5 million set aside for water and land-related projects in Mr. Smith's district.</p>
        <p>''It's an embarrassment of pork riches,'' said Tom Schatz, president of Citizens Against Government Waste, an organization dedicated to eliminating pork, or the billions of dollars steered to projects back home that are not requested by the White House or reviewed by a Congressional committee.</p>
        <p>It will be several weeks before the organization can tally all the pet projects included in final spending bills, but Mr. Schatz said Congress is likely to break the record, $17.7 billion, set last year.</p>
        <p>Take just one bill, for example. In a $107.3 billion measure to finance housing, veterans and environmental projects, lawmakers earmarked 1,183 research, water and economic development initiatives. The combined value of the pet projects was just under $1.1 billion, or slightly more than what the bill provides for helping the homeless.</p>
        <p>Of course, one man's pork is another man's prime cut. ''You can probably get a good column written once in a while about pork-barrel spending and all that kind of stuff, but when you go down these items, these items are important to the constituencies in those states,'' Senator Tom Harkin, Democrat of Iowa, said on the Senate floor last week.</p>
        <p>There is no definitive breakdown between Democratic and Republican pork, but each party has its master purveyors of pet projects. Senator Ted Stevens, an Alaska Republican who heads the Appropriations Committee, had included in an Interior Department spending bill $1.25 million to repair a church in the Aleutian Islands and $176,000 for the Reindeer Herders' Association.</p>
        <p>Democrats have their own earmarking legends, notably Senator Robert C. Byrd of West Virginia, his party's senior member on the Appropriations Committee. Among other projects, Mr. Byrd included $4.6 million in an Interior Department spending bill to help restore a downtown section of Wheeling, W. Va.</p>
        <p>''When you have Stevens and Byrd, very persuasive chairmen who take home so much for their states, there's no credence if they say no to anyone else,'' Mr. Schatz said.</p>
        <p>Endangered incumbents are typically first in line for help. Republican leaders ensured that $102 million in road and bridge projects were earmarked for Representative Jay Dickey's district in Arkansas.</p>
        <p>Top aides to Representative Richard A. Gephardt, of Missouri, the House Democratic leader, collected a wish list from their half-dozen most vulnerable incumbents and had Mr. Gephardt tell senior Democrats on the Appropriations Committee that ''there was no higher priority than theirs.''</p>
        <p>(Mr. Gephardt did not ignore his own district's needs, securing $950,000 for a local sewer project and $2 million for a traveling exhibition of documents and artifacts related to the Lewis and Clark expedition.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Holt, a New Jersey freshman who faces a stiff re-election fight, is one of the beneficiaries, securing more than $18 million in road, dredging and bike path projects in his district.</p>
        <p>''I try to ask for as much as I can without asking for too much,'' Mr. Holt said. ''It's age-old politics.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hoeffel gained $29 million in roads projects from party elders looking out for him and, like Mr. Holt, from working his own contacts among colleagues. But Mr. Hoeffel had another perhaps unlikely ally: Senator Arlen Specter, a Republican on the Appropriations Committee, but more important, a fellow Pennsylvanian.</p>
        <p>''Let's face it, he comes from a state with a Republican senator on Appropriations whom we've worked closely with,'' said Frank X. Custer, Mr. Hoeffel's spokesman. ''Unlike a lot of people in Washington, we've tried to work across party lines.''</p>
        <p>Perhaps the best way for Democrats or Republicans to guarantee a pet project is not just to know someone on the Appropriations Committee, but sit on the coveted panel itself.</p>
        <p>Representative Robert E. Cramer, an Alabama Democrat on the committee, proudly announced in a news release on his Web site that in an agriculture spending bill, he had secured $725,000 for red snapper research, $600,000 for catfish-disease research and $500,000 for peanut-allergy research.</p>
        <p>An article on pork-barrel spending would be incomplete without mentioning $500,000 that Representative David E. Price, a North Carolina Democrat on the panel, won for additional study at North Carolina State University on managing and using hog manure. ''It's a severe problem in North Carolina, and this program turns waste into fertilizer pellets that don't smell,'' said Thomas Bates, a spokesman for Mr. Price.</p>
        <p>Representative Maurice D. Hinchey, a New York Democrat on the committee, had $100,000 set aside to help an apple-packing plant in New Paltz, N.Y., ride out a bad year, marked by low apple prices, hail storms and tornadoes. ''No one has ever given us this kind of support,'' said Charles M. Andola, secretary of the Consolidated Fruit Packers, the plant operator.</p>
        <p>Lawmakers from small states band together to back favorite projects. North Dakota's three-man Congressional delegation -- all Democrats -- united behind a $300,000 grant to hire a geneticist to study sunflowers at a federal laboratory in Fargo, N.D. North Dakota grows 85 percent of the nation's sunflowers.</p>
        <p>''This is the kind of crop research we're proud of,'' said Laurie Boeder, spokeswoman for Senator Kent Conrad, Democrat of North Dakota.  ''Scientists are looking for ways to make sunflowers more drought-resistant, more disease-resistant and more productive to feed more people on less land.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
