<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Presidents Find They Must Share Limelight</title>
    <meta content="29VENE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/29/sports/29VENE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1243010"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL: SUBWAY SERIES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Venezuela</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Cuba</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rohter, Larry</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sojo, Luis</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Castro, Fidel (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Venezuela</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Cuba</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Venezuela</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Cuba</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001029T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E6DB1730F93AA15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="615" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Presidents Find They Must Share Limelight</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LARRY ROHTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rohter, Larry</byline>
      <dateline>CARACAS, Venezuela, Oct. 27</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Yankees infielder Luis Sojo steals front page headlines in Venezuelan newspapers from Fidel Castro, who is visiting from Cuba; discusses Venezuelan loyalties in American baseball (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Fidel Castro and Hugo Chavez, the charismatic president of Venezuela, are accustomed to the spotlight and gravitate toward it almost instinctively. But today they found themselves competing for attention with an unexpected interloper: the Yankees reserve infielder Luis Sojo.</p>
        <p>''Sojo: The Yankees' Magic Charm'' read the jubilant front-page headline in one newspaper here this morning, announcing the end of the Subway Series.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Fidel Castro and Hugo Chavez, the charismatic president of Venezuela, are accustomed to the spotlight and gravitate toward it almost instinctively. But today they found themselves competing for attention with an unexpected interloper: the Yankees reserve infielder Luis Sojo.</p>
        <p>''Sojo: The Yankees' Magic Charm'' read the jubilant front-page headline in one newspaper here this morning, announcing the end of the Subway Series.</p>
        <p>Referring to the Cuban leader's arrival here Thursday for his first state visit in more than 40 years, another daily proclaimed ''Fidel Si, and the Yankees too,'' neatly bringing together the two events that are captivating the 24 million people of this baseball-crazed nation.</p>
        <p>Over and over throughout the day, Venezuelan television and radio stations broadcast interviews in which Sojo, a native of the Petare neighborhood of Caracas, joyously confessed that his two-out single in the ninth inning Thursday night made this ''the happiest day of my life.'' It was a feeling that many here were delighted to acknowledge and eager to share.</p>
        <p>''This caps a great year and a great week for Venezuelan baseball players,'' Jesus Leal Garay, a street vendor selling Yankee caps, said this morning. ''Andres Galarraga wins the Comeback Player of the Year award, and now another one of our guys brings us honor by getting the winning hit in the World Series.''</p>
        <p>The World Series was broadcast live on three television channels here, and though nearly everyone seemed to be watching, loyalties were clearly divided. Venezuelans tend to root in the Series for whichever team has the most Venezuelan players, but this year the only locals involved were a pair of second basemen: Sojo and Edgardo Alfonzo of the Mets.</p>
        <p>''I would ordinarily have been supporting the Mets because they had three Venezuelans on their roster last year, Alfonzo, Roger Cedeno and Melvin Mora, but I am mad at them for trading Mora to the Orioles so late in the season,'' said Eduardo Mejia Morales, an accountant. ''So I went with the Yankees instead, and I am glad I did.''</p>
        <p>Any Venezuelan who reaches the major leagues automatically becomes a celebrity here, his performance tracked and analyzed daily in the sports sections of newspapers, and Sojo, 34, is no exception. The same easygoing, playful nature that makes him a vital presence in the Yankee clubhouse has contributed to his widespread popularity in his homeland.</p>
        <p>But even to Venezuelans who follow baseball closely, Sojo seemed an unlikely candidate for World Series hero. ''He's not a great player like Luis Aparicio, David Concepcion or Omar Vizquel,'' said Francisco Munoz Hernandez, 61, naming three Venezuelan shortstops. ''But he had the guts and the steadiness to be able to respond to a historic opportunity.''</p>
        <p>If President Castro and President Chavez, a 46-year-old former army paratrooper, were also watching the Series, they weren't saying. Even though both are renowned for their love of the game and are in fact scheduled to manage national teams that will play each other this weekend, embarrassing political reasons may have prevented them from publicly acknowledging their interest.</p>
        <p>''The president knows he has got to have a ceremony to honor Sojo for this tremendous achievement,'' said Daisy Guillen Arocha, a hairdresser and mother of three sons who all play baseball. ''After all, Fidel Castro can visit us any time he wants, but who knows how long it will be before a Venezuelan gets the winning hit in the World Series again?''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL: SUBWAY SERIES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
