<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Final Days, Rallying Supporters and Attempting to Sidestep a Volatile Issue</title>
    <meta content="29GORE$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/29/politics/29GORE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1243041"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE CANDIDATES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Minnesota</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Minneapolis (Minn)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wellstone, Paul (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perez-Pena, Richard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Seelye, Katharine Q</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nader, Ralph</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Minnesota</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/Ralph Nader</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Minnesota</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Minnesota</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Minnesota/Minneapolis and St. Paul</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001029T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5D81730F93AA15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1030" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Final Days, Rallying Supporters and Attempting to Sidestep a Volatile Issue</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD PEREZ-PENA and KATHARINE Q. SEELYE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Seelye, Katharine Q; Perez-Pena, Richard</byline>
      <dateline>MINNEAPOLIS, Oct. 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vice Pres Al Gore and Sen Paul Wellstone appeal to independents and Ralph Nader supporters not to throw traditionally Democratic Minnesota to Gov George W Bush, rally, Minneapolis; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>All but pleading, Vice President Al Gore and Senator Paul Wellstone appealed directly tonight to independents and Ralph Nader supporters not to throw this traditionally Democratic state to Gov. George W. Bush.</p>
        <p>''Reform Party members, Green Party members, you are all welcome,'' Mr. Gore told a crowd estimated by the police at more than 5,000 people, who braved a 40-degree night to attend an outdoor rally downtown. ''We want a majority to take this country in the right direction.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>All but pleading, Vice President Al Gore and Senator Paul Wellstone appealed directly tonight to independents and Ralph Nader supporters not to throw this traditionally Democratic state to Gov. George W. Bush.</p>
        <p>''Reform Party members, Green Party members, you are all welcome,'' Mr. Gore told a crowd estimated by the police at more than 5,000 people, who braved a 40-degree night to attend an outdoor rally downtown. ''We want a majority to take this country in the right direction.''</p>
        <p>That Minnesota is considered a tossup is evidence of the roiled nature of this campaign -- this is one of several states where Mr. Nader's candidacy is hurting Mr. Gore -- and the vice president seemed almost exasperated at having to make the case here. When his descriptions of Mr. Bush's proposals drew boos, he said: ''O.K., that is a logical and rational reaction. But, hey, you've got to spread the word.''</p>
        <p>''Minnesota,'' he said, ''is the heart and soul of the Democratic Party.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore did not mention Mr. Nader, the Green Party candidate, by name, but Mr. Wellstone did, in an impassioned speech that left him hoarse and red-faced. ''It would be a horrible, horrible irony if a vote for Ralph Nader meant that George W. Bush became president of the United States,'' he said. ''It is too dear a price to pay for our country.''</p>
        <p>The star of Minnesota politics, Gov. Jesse Ventura, elected as a Reform Party candidate and now an independent, has not endorsed a presidential candidate. But Lt. Gov. Mae Shunk, who was his Reform running mate, addressed the rally tonight and endorsed Mr. Gore, comparing him to Mr. Ventura. Like the governor, she said, the vice president is ''a man of integrity, a man of honesty, a man who is a man of his word.''</p>
        <p>Stripping off his dark suit coat in the chill, Mr. Gore, his voice roughened by a sore throat, tried to impart to his supporters his sense of urgency about persuading friends and getting out the vote. ''We have 10 days left and much is at stake,'' he said. The outcome, he said, will be determined by ''how much passion you have for the future of the United States of America. I need your hearts. I need you to mobilize.''</p>
        <p>Earlier, Mr. Gore sidestepped a fierce struggle between gun-control advocates and the National Rifle Association, saying he would neither promote nor oppose the trend by several of the nation's cities toward suing firearms manufacturers for health costs related to gun violence.</p>
        <p>''That's up to local communities,'' the vice president said in a television interview on Friday night when asked if he would advocate such lawsuits. About three dozen cities have filed such suits in the past two years. So far, courts across the country have issued disparate rulings on whether cities can hold gun manufacturers responsible.</p>
        <p>Many of Mr. Gore's strongest backers -- including Edward G. Rendell, the former mayor of Philadelphia and now the Democratic National Committee's general chairman, and Richard M. Daley, the mayor of Chicago -- have backed such suits.</p>
        <p>Last year, Gov. George W. Bush, Mr. Gore's Republican opponent, signed legislation that prohibits Texas municipalities from suing gun makers without approval of the State Legislature. Enacting such bills in all 50 states is a priority of the gun industry and the rifle association. Mr. Bush has suggested he would sign similar federal legislation.</p>
        <p>''You can get a feel for my position by looking at what I've done in office,'' Mr. Bush told reporters in May, ''and what I did in office was sign a bill that made it very difficult for local municipalities to sue manufacturers of a legal product.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore's comments, in an interview with WPVI, the ABC affiliate in Philadelphia, are in line with a general toning down of his previously aggressive antigun stance. During his third debate with Mr. Bush, in answer to a question about gun control, he emphasized his support for gun owners' rights.</p>
        <p>Last summer, Mr. Gore joined President Clinton and other Democrats who attacked House Republicans over the failure of a gun-control measure, and Mr. Bush for signing the Texas bill. And shortly after declaring his candidacy in June 1999, Mr. Gore began warning audiences that Governor Bush would sign a bill that would ''protect gun manufacturers'' and that he himself would not.</p>
        <p>This morning, Mr. Gore spoke in Wilkes-Barre, Pa., about health care, and in his speech responded to concerns by Congressional Democrats that he was not doing enough to tie Mr. Bush to Congressional Republicans.</p>
        <p>''This week, Governor Bush's allies on Capitol Hill passed a brand-new health care bill,'' Mr. Gore said in a low-key address to a couple hundred people in a room at Wilkes University. ''But instead of H.M.O. reform, it's an H.M.O. boondoggle. This so-called reform bill that they pushed through gives H.M.O.'s $34 billion more in taxpayer money, but it doesn't have a dime's worth of patient protections. And it lets the H.M.O.'s drop seniors and leave them without coverage.''</p>
        <p>The matter of gun control is particularly touchy in Pennsylvania, another state that remains too close to call. Two important groups of voters in the state -- moderate women in the Philadelphia suburbs who favor gun control, and conservative, blue-collar white men in the western and rural parts of the state who oppose it -- have essentially neutralized the subject for both Mr. Gore and Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush has been endorsed by the National Rifle Association, which gave his campaign nearly $1 million in September and has spent millions of dollars pounding Mr. Gore in television and radio commercials and direct mail. The message, that Mr. Gore poses a dire threat to the rights of gun owners, has been aimed at states like Pennsylvania, which has the largest membership in the gun lobby after Texas, and other big states like Michigan, Missouri and Wisconsin, where the election is too close to call.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE CANDIDATES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
