<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At a Diner, the Series is Food for Thought</title>
    <meta content="29NABE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/29/sports/29NABE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1243009"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL: SUBWAY SERIES -- ACROSS THE DIVIDE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ridgewood Diner (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Feuer, Alan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001029T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E6DB1730F93AA15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1128" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At a Diner, the Series is Food for Thought</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN FEUER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Feuer, Alan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Scene at Ridgewood Diner on border of Queens and Brooklyn described; patrons and counter staff discuss baseball allegiances and make small bets with each other about outcome of World Series between New York Mets and New York Yankees; photo, map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was lunch time again at the Ridgewood Diner.</p>
        <p>An old truck driver sat at a booth in back, stealing hungry glances at everyone's food. An older woman sat across from him, a napkin stuffed in her empty cup. The Egyptian counterman sauteed some onions on the skillet with a happy little smile. He was working hard, but he was pleased.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was lunch time again at the Ridgewood Diner.</p>
        <p>An old truck driver sat at a booth in back, stealing hungry glances at everyone's food. An older woman sat across from him, a napkin stuffed in her empty cup. The Egyptian counterman sauteed some onions on the skillet with a happy little smile. He was working hard, but he was pleased.</p>
        <p>''So I won a dollar from her,'' Mohammed Hosnay told one of his customers, nodding at the woman as he slid the onions, golden brown, onto a toasted bun. ''I said the Yankees. She said the Mets. And I don't even understand this game.''</p>
        <p>''Would you believe at first he wouldn't even take the money?'' the woman, Ann McMahon, whispered to the truck driver. ''And after I cried for the Mets? Oh well, all's fair in love and war.''</p>
        <p>That's when the truck driver, Tony Corrado, chipped in his two cents' worth.</p>
        <p>''I don't know,'' he said, just speaking his mind. ''The old-timers put more enthusiasm into the game and they were paid less, too. Today, the players all carry combs in their back pockets. They're actors -- that's what they are.''</p>
        <p>Both the new fan and the old fan, though, would have none of it.</p>
        <p>''It was good for the city,'' Hosnay insisted.</p>
        <p>''Of course, it was good for the city,'' McMahon chimed in. ''Almost everybody's happy now.''</p>
        <p>The civil war finally ended last Thursday night when the Yankees beat the Mets to wrap up the first Subway Series since 1956 to descend from the heavens to the streets of New York. The Yankees dreamed of yet one more championship ring, the Mets dreamed of opening day 2001, and, in the neighborhoods, fans of both teams dreamed of the next time the city would crackle again with October magic.</p>
        <p>This year's World Series touched the farthest corners of New York and the region. It traveled through the city and the towns surrounding it on the lips of mothers and mailmen. It was in the air for almost a week, rising and falling, like an ambient tune. It actually did something. It made people put aside their regular lives.</p>
        <p>In the Ridgewood Diner, a 24-hour sandwich joint that lies on Myrtle Avenue amid the racket of the elevated train, it made McMahon cry and it convinced Hosnay that soccer was not the only sport around. It made Tony Corrado joke about the present. It made him long for the past.</p>
        <p>The diner sits on the border of two adjacent but vastly different neighborhoods: Bushwick, in Brooklyn, and Ridgewood, an interborough area that lies partly in Brooklyn but mostly in Queens. For six days, the World Series games drifted through the neighborhoods, sometimes bringing folks together, sometimes driving them apart, but always acting as a kind of athletic lens that allowed people to see a bit more clearly who they really are.</p>
        <p>The First Base Inn is a tavern in Ridgewood that sits at the edge of Bushwick's Yankees turf. Though it attracts its share of Yankees fans, it is the first bar near the borough line where a Mets fanatic can safely cheer for Al Leiter, Mike Piazza and Bobby Jones.</p>
        <p>There were not many Mets fans in the First Base Inn on Friday afternoon. The regular barman, Ronnie Kessler, had gone upstate to mourn for Bobby Valentine and the rest of the boys. The guy on the day shift, Tommy Damato, was behind the oak, but in truth he did not look that good.</p>
        <p>''What am I gonna do?'' Damato, a Mets fan, asked. ''Kill myself? I can't die. I got work to do.''</p>
        <p>Bob the locksmith walked in, dressed from head to toe in Yankees gear. ''We're the champs!'' he crowed. ''We did it again!'' He took a seat and ordered a drink.</p>
        <p>''When Luis Sojo hit that single I just flew off the couch,'' Bob said of Thursday night's game-winning hit. ''The dog was all freaked out. He didn't know what to do.''</p>
        <p>''Well, at least your dog's a Mets fan,'' Damato's sister, Rosemarie, said. Her voice was low. She looked as if she had been crying.</p>
        <p>Rosemarie told the locksmith: ''Next year. Just you wait.''</p>
        <p>''Next year?'' Bob responded. ''Look at the hat.''</p>
        <p>He pointed to his head. A Yankees baseball cap was on it. It said ''NY Yankees 2001.''</p>
        <p>Around the corner and up the block from the bar sits the St. Matthias School. Sister Theresa Torsone is a nun and a Yankees fan who teaches there. She never prayed for the Bombers once, she said. The team did fine without her.</p>
        <p>''They never let me down,'' said Sister Theresa, who has loved her Yankees since the DiMaggio and Mantle days. ''If it was meant to be, it was meant to be. And I guess it was meant to be.''</p>
        <p>St. Matthias, a Roman Catholic school, is so traditional that its students are not allowed to speak in the hallways as they move from class to class. They tried to abide by that rule Friday, but a couple of whispered ''Let's go Yankees!'' could be heard.</p>
        <p>''It's just been a good week,'' Sister Theresa said when school let out. ''Unfortunately, not everyone could win.'' She was more or less trying to frown. ''That would've been nice, but, of course, that's not real life.''</p>
        <p>Back at the Ridgewood Diner, Hosnay was marveling at just how far the week had brought him. He started out a baseball naif and ended up a fan. He may not know the infield fly rule yet, but when his shift was over on Thursday afternoon he went straight home to watch the game.</p>
        <p>''Hey, Mohammed,'' McMahon called out when Corrado, the truck driver, got up to talk with another friend. ''Do they have the ballgames on the TV there in Egypt?''</p>
        <p>''Yes, they have,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''And you watched them?'' she asked.</p>
        <p>''Not really,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''Ah,'' said McMahon. ''That's very interesting.''</p>
        <p>Some moments went by. People ate their lunch. Hosnay set a burger on the skillet. Then he turned around.</p>
        <p>''I don't understand everything,'' he said, ''but when I'm perfect then I'll be a real baseball fan. And I'll be with the Yankees.</p>
        <p>''I just feel like they have a good groove,'' he went on as the diner listened. ''The Yankees do a good job and everyone in New York likes them.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL: SUBWAY SERIES -- ACROSS THE DIVIDE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
