<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>PlayStation 2: Game Console as Trojan Horse</title>
    <meta content="26PLAY" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Circuits" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/26/technology/26PLAY.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241911"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sony Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marriott, Michel</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Circuits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001026T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E2DF1331F935A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1690" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>PlayStation 2: Game Console as Trojan Horse</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHEL MARRIOTT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Marriott, Michel</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sony releases new version of its popular home video game console, PlayStation 2; device incorporates many functions of personal computers; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EVAN LEVINE and Oliver Barrett, both 14, buzzed around a video game store in their Upper West Side neighborhood earlier this week with the unmistakable ease bred by countless visits. On this afternoon stop, the boys, self-proclaimed gamers, kept finding themselves drawn to a wall display of shrink-wrapped video games and accessories designed for the PlayStation 2, Sony's new version of its popular game console that goes on sale today.</p>
        <p>Oliver, who is several inches taller than Evan, stretched his lanky frame to pluck an empty PlayStation 2 box from the display's top shelf. Turning it over in his hands, he pondered whether the sleek, black game console could live up to its audience's expectations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EVAN LEVINE and Oliver Barrett, both 14, buzzed around a video game store in their Upper West Side neighborhood earlier this week with the unmistakable ease bred by countless visits. On this afternoon stop, the boys, self-proclaimed gamers, kept finding themselves drawn to a wall display of shrink-wrapped video games and accessories designed for the PlayStation 2, Sony's new version of its popular game console that goes on sale today.</p>
        <p>Oliver, who is several inches taller than Evan, stretched his lanky frame to pluck an empty PlayStation 2 box from the display's top shelf. Turning it over in his hands, he pondered whether the sleek, black game console could live up to its audience's expectations.</p>
        <p>''I think it's pretty cool,'' said Evan, adding that his parents were planning to buy a high-definition television soon. ''HDTV and PS2 -- that would be great.''</p>
        <p>PS2, as the video gaming world calls it, is Sony's latest salvo in the home video game war. But the $299 console is not merely a plaything. It plays audio CD's and DVD movies flawlessly. It has an optical port that permits users to plug the device into high-end stereo receivers and home theater amplifiers for Dolby Digital or DTS sound. There is also a Universal Serial Bus expansion port and an i.Link port, more commonly known as Firewire or IEEE 1394, for very high-speed (400 megabits per second) connections to devices like digital video cameras and high-capacity external hard drives.</p>
        <p>If it sounds as though the new Playstation is closer to a personal computer than a game console, that might be because Sony is eager to make that association.</p>
        <p>The company likes to call PlayStation 2 games ''software'' and proudly points out that the console's central processing unit can handle 66 million polygons, the visual elements that make up practically all the objects in a video game.</p>
        <p>The game console, which is called a ''computer entertainment system'' on its opening screen, also bears deep in its guts components of printed circuits and silicon that await a future broadband connection. That could transform the device into a powerful Internet hub, merging entertainment capabilities like playing games online with the ability to pull movies from the Internet.</p>
        <p>''This is the beginning of a trend toward more living-room entertainment,'' said Mark T. Starrett, an application specialist for Saitek, a maker of game controllers in Torrance, Calif., that has developed a wireless DVD remote controller for the PlayStation 2. ''We've had traditional VCR's and a television and a game console, and then we went to the PC for the Internet. Now we are looking at the first device that incorporates all of that.''</p>
        <p>Sony is using the PlayStation 2 as a Trojan horse to pump a menu of digital entertainment into homes. But the console's success will initially depend on how well it can actually play games. If the latest bloody version of Quake loses something in the move from the PC to the television screen, Sony's bigger plans for PlayStation 2 could stall or evaporate, some critics have noted.</p>
        <p>Jeremy Schwartz, a senior analyst at Forrester Research in Boston, said, ''Certainly the arrrival of these new game consoles coming online represents a significant shift from what we have had in the past, being tied to the living room and crowding around a television set to playing friends and family across town and country.''</p>
        <p>J Allard, general manager for Xbox, a new console being developed by Microsoft, said all these multiple-function game machines might be missing the point: extraordinarily good game play.</p>
        <p>''I don't know if people want to balance their checkbook, edit their videos and write term papers on a game console,'' Mr. Allard said. ''We think video gaming is superimportant and a well-accepted form of entertainment, and we want to be part of it -- not word processing.''</p>
        <p>The same argument has been made against playing video games on PC's. Game play on expensive PC's can be very good -- better, some gamers say, than on a game console -- but a single component, like a 64-megabyte graphics card, can cost more than a PlayStation system.</p>
        <p>And PC's tend to be complex and temperamental. With game consoles, there are never compatibility problems like the sort that often plague gamers using PC's. And as many gamers are fond of saying, no one ever has to reboot a game console.</p>
        <p>Unlike a PC, PlayStation 2 does not offer a way to connect to the Internet, and Sony has yet to announce firm plans for when and how online gaming will become available.</p>
        <p>Last month, Sega upped the ante with its $149 Dreamcast game console, which first entered the market a year earlier and came with a built-in 56K modem, by offering its online gaming Internet service provider, called Sega Net. The $20-a-month service provides not only a gaming network but also full Internet browsing and e-mail.</p>
        <p>Sony spokesmen are not saying much about the company's Internet options for PlayStation 2, only that it will not resort to a dial-up Internet service like Sega's and will look only at a much richer broadband connection possibly as early as next year.</p>
        <p>In the meantime, game designers are busy dreaming up ways to use the considerable technologies offered by PlayStation 2.  Sony is exploring the idea of harnessing its i.Link to permit players to upload digital images of themselves into games, literally placing themselves in the action, said Craig Howe, brand manager for ESPN the Games, a line of virtual sports games made by Konami of America for PlayStation 2. And there is talk that perhaps the new game machine will add voice recognition.</p>
        <p>''I think it's going to be a revolutionary experience,'' said Mr. Howe, whose company is making some of the 270 games currently in development for PlayStation 2.</p>
        <p>Right now, said Molly Smith, a spokeswoman for Sony Computer Entertainment America, the emphasis is on what Play Station 2 can do today. Under its skin is off-the-shelf computer hardware and Sony's own design. A collaboration between Sony and the Toshiba Corporation produced Play Station 2's custom-built128-bit chip, which  Sony calls the ''emotion engine.'' It does much of the heavy lifting, along with a separate graphics processor, calculating game physics so when a musclebound virtual shot-putter heaves a shot, his muscle tension and the flow of contours on his body are convincing. The chip, which calls on 32 megabytes of dynamic random access memory (DRAM), ensures that the same is true for the flight of the shot as it twists and turns through a computer-generated sky.</p>
        <p>The technology is impressive, but so far the marketing is not. Sony announced earlier this fall that its goal of delivering a million PlayStation 2 consoles to the North American marketplace today had to be halved because of parts shortages. Besides the initial 500,000 PlayStation 2 units, Sony said it would ship another 100,000 units a week to North America through the holiday season. Sony officials say they are still committed to delivering three million units to North America by the end of March 2001, supplies of the console are expected to be tight when they start to arrive in stores today.</p>
        <p>John Woodson, president of the Internet division of Babbage's, a chain of 1,000 video game and computer software stores, said his stores had been taking reservations for the new console since December 1999. ''Our customer base is gamers and they came immediately to us,'' he said, ''telling us that they wanted to be the first to get one.''</p>
        <p>When PlayStation 2 went on sale last year in Japan, Sony sold almost one million consoles in the first weekend. All told, Ms. Smith said, more than three million machines have been sold in Japan. And by March, she added, Sony expects to have blanketed the earth with some 10 million PlayStation 2 consoles.</p>
        <p>Mr. Woodson said his stores had more than 200,000 reservations for PlayStation 2 machines. For those who signed up early, he said, the chances of buying a PlayStation 2 today are very good. For those who signed up in the middle of the year, a machine for Christmas is likely. But for anyone who waited until late summer to reserve the game console, the chances of getting one this year are not good. Sony announced is postponing online sales.</p>
        <p>''PlayStation 1 really delivered,'' Mr. Woodson said, ''so a large group of people are really anticipating this one. They want to upgrade. They want a better experience.''</p>
        <p>Ato Boldon, the sprinter who won a silver medal at the 2000 Summer Olympics, is also a video gamer and said he had a great experience running his event on a newly released PlayStation 2 game.</p>
        <p>Last week he and Maurice Greene, the gold-medal winner in the 100-meter dash, restaged their Sydney contest in a New York sports bar using the ESPN International Track &amp; Field game, which features the likenesses of both runners.</p>
        <p>''The problem in the past sometimes with track and field games is that you don't get the feeling,'' Mr. Boldon said after beating Mr. Greene's virtual clone. ''This thing, having just come from the Olympics, looks realistic.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
