<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bottoms Up, the Murphy's Back</title>
    <meta content="26MURP$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241922"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Beds and Bedding</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Furniture</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stevens, Kimberly</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beds and Bedding</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Furniture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001026T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507EEDD1331F935A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1283" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bottoms Up, the Murphy's Back</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KIMBERLY STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stevens, Kimberly</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Murphy bed of yesteryear is making a comeback, and not only among space-starved; cast iron clunker that tormented Abbott and Costello has been simplified and streamlined by designers to appeal to upscale clientele; now glides from brushed-steel cabinetry, cherrywood armoires and maple bookcases with help of air pistons instead of whomping down with comic twang; some can be converted into tables; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IVY FAHRER recently built a seven-bedroom Gothic-style home with her husband in Harrison, N.Y. A wing of their house includes a large suite for her sister, who visits occasionally from Texas. What's unusual about the suite is where sister will slumber: A Murphy bed, king-size and custom-designed, complete with a pillow-top mattress. ''Only the best for the princess and the pea,'' Ms. Fahrer, the president of Cebon Cosmetics, said, laughing. ''My sister is very particular about where she sleeps.''</p>
        <p>The brushed-aluminum concoction, which incorporates shelves, closets and a nifty retractable desk, cost $15,000 -- the price of several conventional beds. But they wouldn't have folded up out of sight. ''The novelty is wonderful,'' Ms. Fahrer said, ''and when she's not around, my husband and I have an artists' retreat where we can paint and sculpt.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IVY FAHRER recently built a seven-bedroom Gothic-style home with her husband in Harrison, N.Y. A wing of their house includes a large suite for her sister, who visits occasionally from Texas. What's unusual about the suite is where sister will slumber: A Murphy bed, king-size and custom-designed, complete with a pillow-top mattress. ''Only the best for the princess and the pea,'' Ms. Fahrer, the president of Cebon Cosmetics, said, laughing. ''My sister is very particular about where she sleeps.''</p>
        <p>The brushed-aluminum concoction, which incorporates shelves, closets and a nifty retractable desk, cost $15,000 -- the price of several conventional beds. But they wouldn't have folded up out of sight. ''The novelty is wonderful,'' Ms. Fahrer said, ''and when she's not around, my husband and I have an artists' retreat where we can paint and sculpt.''</p>
        <p>The century-old Murphy bed is experiencing a renaissance, and not just among the space-starved. No longer the wacky clunker that tormented Abbott and Costello, the Murphy bed (now a generic term for the presto-chango bed patented by William L. Murphy in 1908) has gone millennial, springing from brushed-steel cabinetry, cherrywood armoires, maple bookcases. It's upwardly mobile, as well,  with a clientele that ranges from Ashton Hawkins, the executive vice president of the Metropolitan Museum of Art, to Jimmy Smits, the former ''NYPD Blue'' heartthrob, to Ralph Acampora, the Wall Street forecaster.</p>
        <p>A remote-control Murphy was a big draw in a 525-square-foot beach home on the market for $3.95 million in Del Mar, Calif. ''The Murphy bed has become cool again,'' said Tom Pearson, the property's broker. ''All these young Internet moguls, with their surfboards in one hand and their computers in the other, get a real kick out of the bed.'' That's if they even know it is a bed.</p>
        <p>With his Murphy bed's cherrywood and steel cabinetry, ''friends think it's a really mod entertainment center,'' said Joe Hill, 35, a hair stylist, who recently moved into a converted 18th-century schoolhouse in Tarrytown, N.Y., with his partner. When the bed's not in use, the two use the room to work out, do business or entertain.</p>
        <p>Gene Kolakowski, the vice president of the Murphy Bed Company International in Farmingdale, N.Y., whose doors opened at the turn of the century, contends it is a trend that simply follows a lifestyle. ''Multifunction is the key,'' he said. ''People are savvy about the use of space these days. They want a room where they can sleep, work, play and entertain. And they don't care how much it costs.''</p>
        <p>Jessica Goldbogen, the managing editor of InFurniture magazine, which covers trends in the industry, says designers are testing the perimeters of a bed and its function. ''It's a hot concept,'' she said by phone from High Point, N.C., where designers and manufacturers have been experimenting with Murphy bed design. Some beds turned into tables; other beds tried a different turnaround: they opened from both sides.</p>
        <p>Born to be comic props, the original beds of cast iron were bolted into the floor, with coiled box springs that leapt from the wall -- bonking Charlie Chaplin in the head, trapping the Muppets and offering Vinnie Barbarino (John Travolta) a bachelor lair.</p>
        <p>In 1989, after a challenge to its patent, the founding family lost its exclusive right to use the name Murphy bed, and ever since, competing manufacturers have vied for consumer attention. Most of the systems have been simplified and streamlined; with the help of air pistons, beds now glide from cabinetry instead of whomping down with a comic twang.</p>
        <p>Perhaps that is why Mr. Kolakowski's sales have doubled over a decade. Robert Meyers, the owner of the Murphy Bed Center, with two showrooms in Manhattan and another soon to open in Staten Island, says his sales are up 40 percent in just the last year.</p>
        <p>''People are finally really taking the bed seriously,'' he said excitedly as he paced around his West 23rd Street showroom last week. The company installs from two to five beds a day.</p>
        <p>The sales boom goes against the trend in the Murphy bed business. ''Murphy beds have always done well when the economy is flat,'' Mr. Kolakowski said. ''And this is the first time that it has done well in a strong economy. I think a lot of empty nesters are purchasing the beds so they can make their kids' rooms into offices, dens, sewing rooms -- you name it.''</p>
        <p>The bed's image still needs some improvement, though. Recently, the definition of a Murphy bed stumped a contestant on ''Who Wants to Be a Millionaire.''</p>
        <p>Henry Smith Miller, an architect, considers himself a pioneer of sorts in the comeback of the Murphy bed. In 1989, he designed a model apartment in the Police Building, at 100 Centre Street, furnished entirely with mobile furniture, including a Murphy bed.</p>
        <p>''We call it cross-programming,'' he said. ''We realized people want to be given the ultimate choice in shaping their environment, and the Murphy bed fits perfectly into this concept.'' Mr. Miller used Murphy beds last year, when he designed a loft space for Arnold Lehman, the director of the Brooklyn Museum.</p>
        <p>''For some reason, the Murphy bed always gets lumped together with a pull-out sofa bed,'' said Marjorie Noto, the president of American Linguists, Interpreters and Translators Inc. and proud owner of four Murphy beds. ''It's a travesty. My husband, Stan, and I wouldn't lie down on a sleep sofa if you paid us.''</p>
        <p>They have two Murphy beds in their Manhattan apartment and two in a condominium they recently purchased at Brown's Hotel in the Catskills. During the condo renovation, Ms. Noto had two Murphy beds with old mechanisms ripped out and replaced with up-to-date versions. ''The beds went, bolts, springs and all, as well as a dancing platform and a disco ball,'' she said gleefully.</p>
        <p>Accurately speaking, the Murphy bed has not so much returned as evolved. What was once considered an economical sleeping solution has in many cases become a luxurious and pricey alternative. The Murphy bed mechanism alone costs around $500, and custom cabinetry, mirrors and special mattresses make the price soar.</p>
        <p>Recently, Mr. Meyers of the Murphy Bed Center built a $30,000 traditional white lacquer unit complete with molding in a three bedroom Fifth Avenue apartment for a young couple who needed extra space for visiting in-laws. ''Clearly, for this couple money was no object,'' he said. ''They just wanted to make better use of the space.''</p>
        <p>But potential renters weighing the difference between a one-bedroom for $1,800 a month and a two-bedroom for $2,400 -- $600 a month -- might find that it doesn't take that long to amortize a Murphy bed, even one that costs $6,000. For Lisa Valentino, 30, a lawyer who lives in a 600-square-foot apartment in Battery Park City, the bed has made it possible to have a life.</p>
        <p>''I always had visions of getting stuck in the bed,'' she said. ''But I got over it. It's really cool, and I'm actually adding shelves to the basic unit I got. It has given me the space to really live.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
