<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Playful and Painful Contrasts As China Meets Mississippi</title>
    <meta content="26LEMO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/26/arts/26LEMO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241932"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE REVIEWS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Next Wave Festival</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Brooklyn Academy of Music</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kisselgoff, Anna</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lemon, Ralph</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Next Wave Festival</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001026T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEEDC1331F935A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="962" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Playful and Painful Contrasts As China Meets Mississippi</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNA KISSELGOFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kisselgoff, Anna</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anna Kisselgoff reviews Tree, second work in dance trilogy by experimental choreographer Ralph Lemon, performed at Next Wave Festival at Brooklyn Academy of Music; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''Tree,'' the second work in a dance trilogy by the experimental choreographer Ralph Lemon, ends with a magical moment at the Brooklyn Academy of Music's Harvey Theater. Robert Johnson, a blues singer, is heard on an old recording as Li Wen Yi, a farmer and folk musician from China, sits on a bench and vocalizes the tune in his own way.</p>
        <p>''Tree'' is about contrast and convergence. In this image of a charming Chinese man, small-boned and isolated in a pool of light, the distance between the Mississippi Delta and his own fields in the Yunnan Province suddenly fades away.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''Tree,'' the second work in a dance trilogy by the experimental choreographer Ralph Lemon, ends with a magical moment at the Brooklyn Academy of Music's Harvey Theater. Robert Johnson, a blues singer, is heard on an old recording as Li Wen Yi, a farmer and folk musician from China, sits on a bench and vocalizes the tune in his own way.</p>
        <p>''Tree'' is about contrast and convergence. In this image of a charming Chinese man, small-boned and isolated in a pool of light, the distance between the Mississippi Delta and his own fields in the Yunnan Province suddenly fades away.</p>
        <p>At the Harvey Theater (651 Fulton Street, Fort Greene) where the academy's Next Wave festival is presenting ''Tree'' through Saturday night, this evocative blend looked natural rather than naive.</p>
        <p>In large part, the saving grace is Mr. Lemon's poetic gift for evoking a shared humanity. For all his stream-of-consciousness structure, with its occasional lapses, the piece also succeeds because it is a rich assemblage of events and images. Many are playful and some are painful: Mr. Li and Wang Liliang, another folk culture expert from Yunnan, appear at one point in minstrel-show blackface instead of the Beijing  opera makeup promised.</p>
        <p>In addition to the performers from China, the cast comes from Taiwan, India, Japan, Africa and the United States. Dance styles and traditions are recognizable onstage and incorporated occasionally into the choreography as a whole. But differences are not erased.</p>
        <p>Rather than a collage, this choreography offers an overlap of incidents. There is an assemblage of simultaneous planes, a modernist device. What could be your standard multicultural celebration thus becomes a disjointed and suspense-filled dream.</p>
        <p>''Tree'' sprawls less than ''Africa/ Race,'' which was called ''Geography'' when it was seen in 1997 as the first part of the trilogy. Now ''Geography'' refers in general to the spiritual and actual journeys that have inspired Mr. Lemon, once best known for terse plotless pieces and an inventive spiraling idiom.</p>
        <p>Commissioned by the Yale Repertory Theater and its director, Stan Wojewodski Jr., the work thus far suggests a journey of discovery. In the projected third part, ''Home,'' Mr. Lemon hopes to explore his roots in the American South.</p>
        <p>Part I, also seen in the Next Wave, included an all-male cast from Africa and the United States, touching upon themes of identity. ''Tree'' is less focused, suggesting that Mr. Lemon picked up various ideas on his visits to Asia.</p>
        <p>A recurrent motif deals with earthquakes. David Thomson, formerly with Trisha Brown's company, recites factual descriptions of a quake while Asako Takami, a Japanese dancer who also joins in the Indian classical dances of the Odissi style with a male Odissi dancer, Manoranjan Pradhan, recites a vivid account of a train wreck during a Japanese quake.</p>
        <p>Nari Ward, a Jamaican-born artist from New York who designed the spectacular set for Part I, has now created an imposing structure of wood and glass that suddenly tilts forward: earthquake in action. There is also an episode in which the dancers line up as Cheng-Chieh Yu, a modern dancer from Taiwan, refers to fault lines and the dancers' bodies slump and tilt accordingly.</p>
        <p>There is a great deal of dance movement, often for three pairs of dancers simultaneously moving in disparate styles or doing their own version of another pair's dance. But ''Tree,'' whose title has multiple evocations, is also studded with sharp incidents that come from a universal root.</p>
        <p>Humor turns into a heart-stopping moment when Mr. Thomson tells a banal tale of a marriage gone wrong. Then in perfect French he tells off Djedje Djedje Gervais, a male dancer from the Ivory Coast who is nothing if not dynamic.</p>
        <p>After the fracas and the noise, Mr. Gervais asks: ''What do you call life? I want silence.'' In the meantime, he has climbed a tower. Suddenly he drops down, saved by a harness that keeps him a few inches from the floor. In empathy, Mr. Thomson drops from a low platform.</p>
        <p>Risk is another motif. The dancers throw stones at each other's feet and scamper to avoid being hit. Mr. Lemon, in one of several ironic solos, throws stones at his own feet and his movement is more exaggerated, his legs flying backward into the air. His exaggeration suggests how movement and personality can be transformed.</p>
        <p>The Indian performers, who include the Odissi drummer and dancer Bijaya Barik, and the men from Yunnan tend to perform their own dances. To make the crops grow there, apparently, one does an exquisite foot-crossing prance. But all have a sense of humor. Mr. Li enters at one point encased in a shopping cart which is topped by a huge swanlike sculpture. A comment on China's new consumer society?</p>
        <p>Funnier and sharper is the duel between Mr. Gervais and Mr. Thomson, virtually the star of the show, as they challenge each other with increasing swagger in a walking duet.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lemon's more typical modern-dance movement, with its spiraling torso and geometric outlines, is left to the American-based performers. They include Mr. Thomson, Carlos Funn and Yeko Ladzekpo-Cole, an African-born woman of striking presence. Occasionally others join in, like Wen Hui, also from Yunnan and a contemporary dancer. There is no contradiction. Mr. Lemon has not probed deeply into aesthetic traditions from abroad, but his hands-across-the Gobi Desert idea is valid: artists do understand one another.</p>
        <p>DANCE REVIEWS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
