<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Corn Developer Appeals to E.P.A.</title>
    <meta content="Y26CORN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/26/business/26CORN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241978"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Grain</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Corn</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Food Contamination and Poisoning</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Aventis Cropscience</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Environmental Protection Agency</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Western Family Foods</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mission Foods</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pollack, Andrew</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Food Contamination and Poisoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corn</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Grain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food Contamination and Poisoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vegetables</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001026T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE0D61331F935A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="422" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Corn Developer Appeals to E.P.A.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW POLLACK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pollack, Andrew</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 25</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Aventis CropScience, developer of StarLink corn, asks Environmental Protection Agency to allow its use in food for four years, saying new studies demonstrate 'reasonable certainty' that consumers will not be harmed; request is made as coalition of environmental groups announces that it has discovered StarLink in taco shells marketed by Western Family Foods; Western Family says it told its wholesaler to stop selling product on Oct 12 after other brands of taco shells from its supplier, Mission Foods, were found to have been contaminated; petition to EPA is aimed at averting widespread disruptions in food and grain industries because StarLink corn from this year's and last year's harvests is starting to show up in products (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Aventis CropScience, the developer of StarLink corn, asked government regulators today to allow its use in food for four years, saying new studies demonstrated ''reasonable certainty'' that consumers would not be harmed.</p>
        <p>The request by the developer, a unit of Aventis, was made as a coalition of environmental groups announced that it had discovered StarLink in taco shells marketed by Western Family Foods of Tigard, Ore. The company said it had already told its wholesalers to stop selling the product on Oct. 12 after other brands of taco shells from its supplier, Mission Foods, were found to have been contaminated.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Aventis CropScience, the developer of StarLink corn, asked government regulators today to allow its use in food for four years, saying new studies demonstrated ''reasonable certainty'' that consumers would not be harmed.</p>
        <p>The request by the developer, a unit of Aventis, was made as a coalition of environmental groups announced that it had discovered StarLink in taco shells marketed by Western Family Foods of Tigard, Ore. The company said it had already told its wholesalers to stop selling the product on Oct. 12 after other brands of taco shells from its supplier, Mission Foods, were found to have been contaminated.</p>
        <p>The petition to the Environmental Protection Agency, backed by many food industry trade groups, is aimed at averting widespread disruptions in the food and grain industries because StarLink corn from this year's and last year's harvests is starting to show up in products.</p>
        <p>But Aventis said it would continue to try to remove this year's harvest of StarLink from the human food supply and would stick by its decision to stop selling StarLink seed, even for animal feed.</p>
        <p>Aventis said it would take four years for foods made with this year's crop to pass through supermarket shelves and consumer pantries.</p>
        <p>An E.P.A. official has said the agency will have to make an assessment based on science. It is expected the agency will allow public comment first. But opponents of genetically modified foods are already raising protests. A number of such groups sent a letter to President Clinton on Tuesday urging that he block approval.</p>
        <p>Today Aventis offered several new pieces of evidence for its case that the key protein in StarLink is not an allergen. It found that the protein, known as Cry9C, did not elicit reactions when tested on the blood of people particularly susceptible to food allergies, according to a person with knowledge of the petition. The company also presented data showing that the protein would be destroyed by stomach acids more quickly than had been thought.</p>
        <p>But even if the protein is a potential allergen, Aventis said, there is so little in the food supply that people would not be exposed to enough to cause reactions. About one-half of 1 percent of the American corn crop is StarLink, and Aventis estimated that at most 12 percent of this year's harvest would get into food because the rest had been tracked down.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
