<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Departure of Chief at ABB Pushes Shares Sharply Lower</title>
    <meta content="26ABBB$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="W" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/26/technology/26ABBB.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241928"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Abb Ltd</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lindahl, Goran</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Centerman, Jorgen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cowell, Alan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001026T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E3DC1331F935A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="466" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Departure of Chief at ABB Pushes Shares Sharply Lower</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN COWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cowell, Alan</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, Oct. 25</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Goran Lindahl will step down at end of year as chief executive of ABB Ltd; company's shares fall 7.1 percent in Zurich; Lindahl will be replaced by Jorgen Centerman, who heads ABB's automation business; company reports nine-month profit rose 13 percent, to $1.25 billion, despite 8 percent drop in revenue, to $15.98 billion; ABB postpones planned stock listing in New York until early next year because of volatility of technology markets (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Describing himself as ''a punch-card type of guy'' in the Internet era, Goran Lindahl, chief executive of Swiss-Swedish technology group ABB Ltd., said today he would step down at the end of the year after four years in which he steered the company into technology-based businesses and away from its 110-year traditions in power generation and heavy engineering.</p>
        <p>The announcement surprised investors and battered ABB stock. ABB said Mr. Lindahl, 55, would be replaced by Jorgen Centerman, 48, a longtime employee of ABB who heads its fast-growing automation business. The changeover came as ABB faced the likelihood of tough new competition from the General Electric Company's $45 billion acquisition of Honeywell International, which will create one of the world's biggest automation concerns.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Describing himself as ''a punch-card type of guy'' in the Internet era, Goran Lindahl, chief executive of Swiss-Swedish technology group ABB Ltd., said today he would step down at the end of the year after four years in which he steered the company into technology-based businesses and away from its 110-year traditions in power generation and heavy engineering.</p>
        <p>The announcement surprised investors and battered ABB stock. ABB said Mr. Lindahl, 55, would be replaced by Jorgen Centerman, 48, a longtime employee of ABB who heads its fast-growing automation business. The changeover came as ABB faced the likelihood of tough new competition from the General Electric Company's $45 billion acquisition of Honeywell International, which will create one of the world's biggest automation concerns.</p>
        <p>ABB, which employs 165,000 people in 100 countries, also said that it was postponing a planned stock listing in New York until early next year because of the volatility of the technology markets.</p>
        <p>The news of Mr. Lindahl's departure overwhelmed ABB's announcement today that nine-month net profit rose 13 percent, in line with analysts' forecasts, to $1.25 billion, despite an 8 percent fall in revenue, to $15.98 billion. In Zurich, its shares fell 7.1 percent, to 154.25 Swiss francs ($85.92), reflecting uncertainties over the management change and concerns about falling demand in the global automation business.</p>
        <p>During his tenure, Mr. Lindahl shed the company's power generation, nuclear and rail divisions and moved it toward technology-driven businesses, particularly with the 1998, $2.1 billion acqusition of Elsag Bayley Process Automation of Italy. ABB completed the $1.2 billion sale of its stake in ABB Alstom Power to Alstom of France earlier this year.</p>
        <p>In a telephone interview from Stockholm today, Mr Lindahl disputed suggestions that he had been forced out. ''I think it's the right time'' to leave the job, he said.</p>
        <p>''The information-technology revolution has come faster than anybody thought a short time ago, and I'm still a punch-card type of guy,'' he said, referring to the technology that once drove computers. ''There are no hard feelings whatsoever.''</p>
        <p>Percy Barnevik, ABB's chairman, said the announcement of Mr. Lindahl's departure had been timed to show that ''we really wanted to illustrate that there's no profit warning, no change of direction.</p>
        <p>''Goran has done a great job leading the company in a new strategic direction,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
