<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Economic Scene; Are Bush and Gore flip-flopping over how to manage the economy?</title>
    <meta content="Y26SCE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/26/business/26SCEN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20001027T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241950"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Madrick, Jeff</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Economic Scene (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Economic Scene</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001026T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04EED91331F935A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1114" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Economic Scene; Are Bush and Gore flip-flopping over how to manage the economy?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jeff Madrick</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Madrick, Jeff</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jeff Madrick Economic Scene column on whether Presidential candidates Gov George W Bush and Vice Pres Al Gore are flip-flopping over how to manage economy; says if Gore loses the election, it will be wrong to say he overemphasized social spending; holds, to the contrary, he doggedly tried to prove he was fiscal conservative, and confused his message in the process; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>JUST after the political conventions this summer, it looked as if America had a clear-cut choice about how the economy should be managed. About $2.7 trillion of the projected $4.6 trillion in surpluses over the next 10 years are estimated to be generated by Social Security and Medicare. Gov. George W. Bush of Texas favored giving most of the rest -- some $1.3 trillion -- back to Americans in the form of a tax cut.</p>
        <p>Vice President Al Gore wanted to spend roughly $350 billion of it on a Medicare-based prescription drug plan for the elderly, but much of the rest, he said, should be devoted to a litany of programs for America's ''working families.'' Mr. Gore bolted out of the Democratic convention with a ratings lead.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>JUST after the political conventions this summer, it looked as if America had a clear-cut choice about how the economy should be managed. About $2.7 trillion of the projected $4.6 trillion in surpluses over the next 10 years are estimated to be generated by Social Security and Medicare. Gov. George W. Bush of Texas favored giving most of the rest -- some $1.3 trillion -- back to Americans in the form of a tax cut.</p>
        <p>Vice President Al Gore wanted to spend roughly $350 billion of it on a Medicare-based prescription drug plan for the elderly, but much of the rest, he said, should be devoted to a litany of programs for America's ''working families.'' Mr. Gore bolted out of the Democratic convention with a ratings lead.</p>
        <p>Since then, however, the vice president has made a rhetorical course correction. He started emphasizing the fiscal discipline of his agenda and referred less to what he would do for working families. Today, it would be hard to find a man or woman on the street aware of Mr. Gore's most interesting social proposals, including his provocative program to provide up to $200 billion in a program to help middle-income people accumulate long-term savings.</p>
        <p>''He backed away from a full-throated emphasis on working families,'' says Ruy Texeira, co-author with Joel Rogers of ''America's Forgotten Majority'' (Basic Books, 2000). ''And in the process, he muddied his vision of how to make the new economy work for these families.''</p>
        <p>Now, of course, Mr. Bush and Mr. Gore are about dead even in many polls.</p>
        <p>In truth, once we had a closer look at Mr. Gore's budget proposal, it was clear that he had locked himself into a stingier program than his convention rhetoric suggested. He earmarked the Social Security and Medicare surpluses -- $2.7 trillion -- to pay down most of America's federal debt. He set aside another $300 billion as a cushion because the surpluses were no sure thing. Chalk up about $3 trillion, therefore, or 65 percent of the projected surplus, to demonstrate fiscal probity.</p>
        <p>Working with a smaller pie, Mr. Gore also gave precedence to the elderly over working families. The Social Security and Medicare surpluses would be placed in a ''lock box'' so they could not be spent. The prescription drug proposal was his largest social program by far, and some complained that even it was too restrictive. That left $1 trillion or so for other social programs, or $100 billion a year, including his own tax cut. He only proposed another $115 billion for education over 10 years, for example.</p>
        <p>Despite that, Mr. Gore came up with several enticing ideas. He proposed to spend $200 billion to match the savings of middle-  and lower-income Americans, which he called Retirement Savings Plus. A couple earning $25,000 a year, for example, could put away $500 and receive another $1,500 from the government. The federal match would decline as incomes rose.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore proposed universal schooling for preschoolers and tuition tax credits -- solid new economy ideas. He wanted a higher minimum wage and a more generous earned-income tax credit. His tax cuts in general were aimed more at middle-  and lower-income workers than Mr. Bush's.</p>
        <p>But once Mr. Bush started accusing Mr. Gore of being a big spender and stressing a few social programs of his own, the tone of the campaign changed. One of the first hints was that the Gore campaign started using the term ''middle-class families'' instead of ''working families.''</p>
        <p>In the 1980's and early 1990's, politicians made hay over the middle-class fear that social programs, especially for the poor, were eating into their standard of living. Apparently, Mr. Gore did not want to rekindle those fears, even though most American families, not just the poor, were still strained by stagnating incomes and more hours of work.</p>
        <p>As part of the new plan, he also spent a lot of time criticizing Mr. Bush's budget plans. And Mr. Bush certainly appeared vulnerable. His stimulative tax cuts were proposed at the height of the business cycle, when they might have been most inflationary. The governor also refused to be specific about how he would pay for his Social Security privatization plan -- estimated to cost $1 trillion. Mr. Gore must have thought that he would strike gold, but so far it is lead.</p>
        <p>How good are Mr. Gore's own fiscally conservative economics? A strong case can be made that paying down some of America's debt -- that is to say, not spending all of the projected surplus -- makes economic sense. It may raise scarce savings when the nation is overly dependent on borrowing from overseas to meet its capital needs.</p>
        <p>But the tax increases under former President George Bush and President Clinton, along with federal spending cuts of the early 1990's, were also intended to raise national savings. What happened instead was that, while the government reduced its deficit, individual Americans saved less and borrowed more. Over all, national saving has not risen appreciably to this day.</p>
        <p>The true benefit of the tax increases and spending cuts, it turned out, was that they calmed investors, who bought bonds and sent interest rates lower. Today, the nation simply does not have to pay off the entire national debt, as Mr. Gore wants to do, to retain investors' confidence.</p>
        <p>Do working families really want help from government? Daniel Cohen has little doubt. As executive director of New York's small Working Families Party, Mr. Cohen brings blue-collar white workers together with inner-city black and Hispanic workers to find common economic ground.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cohen says that issues like capital punishment and police brutality often divide his members, but on issues like investment in education, healthcare and a living wage, they rally together. The two-year-old party's organizational strength has been influential in local elections across the state.</p>
        <p>The new economy has new needs, including better education, more accessible child care, flexible work hours and higher wages for lower-income workers. If Mr. Gore loses the election, it will be wrong to say he overemphasized social spending. To the contrary, he doggedly tried to prove he was a fiscal conservative -- and confused his message in the process.</p>
        <p>This column appears here every Thursday. Jeff Madrick is the editor of Challenge Magazine and a new collection of essays, ''Unconventional Wisdom: Alternative Perspectives on the New Economy.'' Mr. Madrick, Virginia Postrel, Alan B. Krueger and Hal R. Varian rotate as contributors.</p>
        <p>Correction:  October 27, 2000, Friday  The Economic Scene column in Business Day yesterday, about Vice President Al Gore's proposals for the projected budget surplus, misstated the surname of the executive director of the Working Families Party. He is Daniel Cantor, not Cohen.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: October 27, 2000, Friday</p>
        <p>The Economic Scene column in Business Day yesterday, about Vice President Al Gore's proposals for the projected budget surplus, misstated the surname of the executive director of the Working Families Party. He is Daniel Cantor, not Cohen.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">This column appears here every Thursday. Jeff Madrick is the editor of Challenge Magazine and a new collection of essays, ''Unconventional Wisdom: Alternative Perspectives on the New Economy.'' Mr. Madrick, Virginia Postrel, Alan B. Krueger and Hal R. Varian rotate as contributors.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
