<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Judge Orders Tax Concern To Cease New Solicitations</title>
    <meta content="Y26TAXX" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/26/business/26TAXX.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241980"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pyramid Schemes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Assets, Frozen</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Search and Seizure</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Renaissance/The Tax People</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Internal Revenue Service</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Postal Service</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnston, David Cay</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Luenberger, Jan (Judge)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stovall, Carla J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cooper, Michael C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Plains</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Search and Seizure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001026T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E4DF1031F935A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="469" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Judge Orders Tax Concern To Cease New Solicitations</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID CAY JOHNSTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Johnston, David Cay</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Renaissance/The Tax People, which has been marketing system to reduce income taxes that authorities say is really pyramid scheme, is ordered by Judge Jan Luenberger in Kansas to stop soliciting new clients; Carla J Stovall, attorney general of Kansas, filed civil lawsuit on Oct 20 to shut down company; but her office agrees in negotiations with lawyers for company to allow business to operate in limited fashion; Stovall's investigators, along with criminal investigators from Internal Revenue Service and US Postal Service, raided company's two offices in Topeka on Oct 12 and seized its files and computers; Luenberger freezes company's bank accounts and allows it to pay only base salaries and routine bills to serve existing clients; owner Michael C Cooper says he has 50,000 clients paying total of $5 million a month (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Renaissance/The Tax People, which has been marketing a system to reduce income taxes that the authorities say is really a pyramid scheme, was ordered by a Kansas judge yesterday to stop soliciting new clients.</p>
        <p>Carla J. Stovall, the attorney general of Kansas, filed a civil lawsuit on Friday seeking to shut down the company. But her office agreed in negotiations with lawyers for the company to allow the business to operate in limited fashion.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Renaissance/The Tax People, which has been marketing a system to reduce income taxes that the authorities say is really a pyramid scheme, was ordered by a Kansas judge yesterday to stop soliciting new clients.</p>
        <p>Carla J. Stovall, the attorney general of Kansas, filed a civil lawsuit on Friday seeking to shut down the company. But her office agreed in negotiations with lawyers for the company to allow the business to operate in limited fashion.</p>
        <p>Ms. Stovall's investigators, along with criminal investigators from the Internal Revenue Service and United States Postal Service, raided the company's two offices in Topeka on Oct. 12 and seized its files and computers. A week later, Michael C. Cooper, the company's owner, announced that it was back in business, prompting the attorney general's lawsuit two days later.</p>
        <p>Under a temporary restraining order signed yesterday by Judge Jan Luenberger of Shawnee County District Court, Renaissance/The Tax People can accept $100 monthly fees from existing clients, but only after each has signed a statement that they are aware that the state attorney general considers the company a pyramid scheme and that the Internal Revenue Service and the Postal Service are investigating the company.</p>
        <p>The judge froze the bank accounts of Renaissance/The Tax People and allowed the company to pay only base salaries and routine bills to serve existing clients. Mr. Cooper says he has 50,000 clients paying a total of $5 million a month.</p>
        <p>The judge also allowed Mr. Cooper access to his personal bank accounts.</p>
        <p>Clifton Jolley, a publicist for the Tax People, said that ''it is a good agreement because it allows the company to service existing customers.''</p>
        <p>He noted that the order applies only to Kansas. Mr. Jolly said he was not aware of any plans to open a new office outside Kansas.</p>
        <p>Mr. Jolley said the company had changed the policies that concern Ms. Stovall but had done a poor job of communicating this to officials.</p>
        <p>In a related development, the North Dakota securities commissioner, Syver Vinje, said yesterday that he had issued an order to Renaissance/The Tax People to stop making offerings of unregistered stock in the company to his state's residents. Matthew Bahrenburg, the commissioner's enforcement lawyer, said he had been personally offered stock at a seminar conducted by one of the company's independent marketing agents.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
