<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Need a Cushion for Life's Blows? This Show House Delivers</title>
    <meta content="26SHOP$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/26/living/26SHOP.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20001102T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241901"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PERSONAL SHOPPER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Interior Design</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rohrlich, Marianne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden/Columns/Personal Shopper</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interior Design</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001026T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807EFD71231F935A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="766" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Need a Cushion for Life's Blows? This Show House Delivers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Marianne Rohrlich</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rohrlich, Marianne</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Traditional Home Built for Women Showhouse includes 11 suites of rooms designed with personal lives of 11 celebrities in mind; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LIKE many show houses, the Traditional Home Built for Women Showhouse, opening today, has good ideas for the do-it-yourselfer. It also has a celebrity factor, with 11 suites of rooms designed with the personal lives of 11 contemporary divas in mind: Elizabeth Taylor, Tina Turner, Bette Midler, Diane Sawyer, Candice Bergen, Donna Karan, Liz Smith, Jane Seymour, Evelyn Lauder, Barbara Walters and Karol DeWulf Nickell, the editor in chief of Traditional Home magazine, which is the event's sponsor.</p>
        <p>''When you go to a decorator show house, you always see something you imagine you could do,'' Ms. Sawyer said. The rooms are in a grand 19th-century residence at 18 East 80th Street. Admission, which benefits the Breast Cancer Foundation, is $25. The house is open until Nov. 12. Information: (212) 935-1033.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LIKE many show houses, the Traditional Home Built for Women Showhouse, opening today, has good ideas for the do-it-yourselfer. It also has a celebrity factor, with 11 suites of rooms designed with the personal lives of 11 contemporary divas in mind: Elizabeth Taylor, Tina Turner, Bette Midler, Diane Sawyer, Candice Bergen, Donna Karan, Liz Smith, Jane Seymour, Evelyn Lauder, Barbara Walters and Karol DeWulf Nickell, the editor in chief of Traditional Home magazine, which is the event's sponsor.</p>
        <p>''When you go to a decorator show house, you always see something you imagine you could do,'' Ms. Sawyer said. The rooms are in a grand 19th-century residence at 18 East 80th Street. Admission, which benefits the Breast Cancer Foundation, is $25. The house is open until Nov. 12. Information: (212) 935-1033.</p>
        <p>While none of the decorators took big risks or showed major innovations, there was a clear theme: restraint, calm and comfort. Rather than pure stage sets to strut the decorator's stuff, this show house reflects real women and their needs. Neutrals won out over color, yet where color was used it blazes. Roderick Shade, known for modern interiors, decorated a study for Ms. Seymour that is traditional except for the bright red silk saris that cover windows and hide a wall of bookcases. Mr. Shade found a shop in Jackson Heights, Queens, where saris cost $79 to $250. ''Anyone who can sew a hem can make these drapes,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mary Douglas Drysdale, a Washington decorator, did an enormous, traditional kitchen/family room for Bette Midler (there's a detail on the front page of this section). The room is all about color (saffron yellow, robin's-egg blue, deep chartreuse) and comfort. Add a Persian rug, and bam!</p>
        <p>Several pairings matched designers with former clients, like Mario Buatta and Barbara Walters. ''I hired Mario to decorate my apartment after seeing a show house room he did that I just loved,'' Ms. Walters said. ''When he decorated my apartment 10 years ago I wanted it to be cozy. I was looking for comfort and wanted to sink into every chair.'' Ten years later, she added, the apartment is still comfortable. At the show house, Mr. Buatta curtained all four walls of a small media room with green taffeta. ''The curtains create a cozy cocoon -- and hide any wall imperfections,'' Mr. Buatta said. (Prewar apartment dwellers take note.)</p>
        <p>Barry Dixon, who has worked with Ms. Sawyer, said she, too, was looking for a cocoon. Hence, the overstuffed sofa in her living room here. ''My husband says I only have two words in my vocabulary -- 'sensual' and 'squishy,' '' Ms. Sawyer said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Lauder's space, designed by Thad Hayes, was painted a soft gray-green that she says is flattering to a woman's skin. ''I love tranquil colors in a room,'' she said. ''Then the people become the important objects.''</p>
        <p>PERSONAL SHOPPER  Correction:  November 2, 2000, Thursday  Because of an editing error, the Personal Shopper column last Thursday, about a show house called the Traditional Home Built for Women, omitted part of the name of the organization that is to benefit. It is the Breast Cancer Research Foundation, not the Breast Cancer Foundation.</p>
        <p>A picture caption with the column also omitted the first six words of the final sentence. It should have read,  ''The chair was bought for $70 at Mazza Frame Company in Brooklyn, then painted white and given a cushion covered with a silk sari.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: November 2, 2000, Thursday</p>
        <p>Because of an editing error, the Personal Shopper column last Thursday, about a show house called the Traditional Home Built for Women, omitted part of the name of the organization that is to benefit. It is the Breast Cancer Research Foundation, not the Breast Cancer Foundation.</p>
        <p>A picture caption with the column also omitted the first six words of the final sentence. It should have read,  ''The chair was bought for $70 at Mazza Frame Company in Brooklyn, then painted white and given a cushion covered with a silk sari.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
