<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Players On No. 7? Triple Play Is Likelier</title>
    <meta content="Y26SUB$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/26/sports/26SUBW.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241992"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL: SUBWAY SERIES -- TUNNEL VISIONS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Subways</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kennedy, Randy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Subways</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001026T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E7DD1031F935A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="717" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Players On No. 7? Triple Play Is Likelier</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RANDY KENNEDY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kennedy, Randy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article describes scene on No. 7 subway train before Game 4 of World Series (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There were a couple of riders on the No. 7 train yesterday who looked very much like professional baseball players. There was the very tall man who got on at the 61st Street-Woodside Station decked out in what appeared to be a complete Mets uniform. But he did not in the least resemble Mike Piazza, whose name was stitched on the back of his jersey.</p>
        <p>There was also the tanned guy who was wearing a Mets cap, a black warm-up suit and a silvery Cartier watch. He would not say what he did for a living but stressed that it was not baseball. And he added that if he were a baseball player, ''no way would you be seeing me on the train -- way too many crazy fans.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There were a couple of riders on the No. 7 train yesterday who looked very much like professional baseball players. There was the very tall man who got on at the 61st Street-Woodside Station decked out in what appeared to be a complete Mets uniform. But he did not in the least resemble Mike Piazza, whose name was stitched on the back of his jersey.</p>
        <p>There was also the tanned guy who was wearing a Mets cap, a black warm-up suit and a silvery Cartier watch. He would not say what he did for a living but stressed that it was not baseball. And he added that if he were a baseball player, ''no way would you be seeing me on the train -- way too many crazy fans.''</p>
        <p>That could sum up the general feeling expressed by a lot of riders up and down the No. 7 line yesterday, during an informal poll conducted at all the Queens stations on the way to Shea Stadium.</p>
        <p>Not a single rider -- including ones who had ridden the No. 7 for decades -- said they had ever seen a player taking the train. And if they did, they said, they would be so shocked they would probably not know what to say. In this day and age, they said, one of the last places they would expect to find New York baseball players is on the subway, even during a Subway Series. Come to think of it, they said, especially during a Subway Series.</p>
        <p>''I'd probably just sit there if I saw one,'' said Bryan Sepulveda, a Hunter College High School student who has been riding the No. 7 for five years. ''Maybe I'd shout out something corny like, 'Go Mets!' But I probably wouldn't. Because I wouldn't believe it was actually a player.''</p>
        <p>Rudolfo Hernandez, who was finishing the last bite of a turkey sandwich at the 111th Street stop, elaborated on this theme: ''These guys are fancy guys, you know. Very fancy guys. They don't go nowhere without a bunch of bodyguards. They wouldn't want to take a bunch of bodyguards on the train.''</p>
        <p>Of course, there was a time when New York baseball players were a fairly common sight in the subways, especially in Brooklyn. There is a well-known picture of Jackie Robinson wearing a suit and sitting comfortably on a cane subway seat, apparently on his way to a game.</p>
        <p>And, whether as a novelty or a point of pride or a way to stay in touch with the common people, there are still a handful of players who like to catch a train now and then. Chuck Knoblauch of the Yankees said he had ridden. John Olerud, when he played for the Mets, apparently got to the ballpark by train quite often. (Often enough that a teenage Mets fan on the platform at the Roosevelt Avenue-82nd Street stop said yesterday that his grandmother had run into Olerud on the train. She pronounced him ''a really nice guy.'')</p>
        <p>Rich Levin, a spokesman for Major League Baseball, said yesterday that it was possible -- he could not confirm anything -- that David Justice of the Yankees made his way to Shea by subway Tuesday night, apparently unrecognized.</p>
        <p>But nearly everyone interviewed said they could not understand why anyone would want to take the subway -- as cheap and reliable as it is -- if they did not have to. The straphangers did not begrudge the players their money or their drivers, at least not much. And they said that while it was a kind of romantic notion, they did not expect to see a real professional baseball player sitting across from them anytime soon.</p>
        <p>Two Peruvian men were asked whether they had ever spotted any. They looked at each other and then back at a reporter. ''Algunos,'' meaning some, one responded. He was asked which ones. The two men looked at each other again and broke into peals of laughter.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL: SUBWAY SERIES -- TUNNEL VISIONS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
