<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'Face Time,' With a Twist</title>
    <meta content="26FACE$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Circuits" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/26/technology/26FACE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241940"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Richtel, Matt</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Circuits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001026T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE3DB1331F935A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="950" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'Face Time,' With a Twist</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATT RICHTEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Richtel, Matt</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article describes new Internet phenomenon, personal Web sites on which proprietors post self-portraits; masses of Net users then pass judgment on person's good looks; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WITHIN days of the debut of his new Web site three weeks ago, James C. Hong  managed to attract thousands of visitors. The response might have been  more gratifying if only they had found him to be better-looking.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hong, 27, and a friend started AmIHotorNot.com, the latest example of a phenomenon that couples the relative anonymity provided by cyberspace with good old-fashioned vanity and the drive to judge other people. That site and others like it let users post photos, then have their looks rated by the masses on the Net. The sites seem to have touched a nerve.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WITHIN days of the debut of his new Web site three weeks ago, James C. Hong  managed to attract thousands of visitors. The response might have been  more gratifying if only they had found him to be better-looking.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hong, 27, and a friend started AmIHotorNot.com, the latest example of a phenomenon that couples the relative anonymity provided by cyberspace with good old-fashioned vanity and the drive to judge other people. That site and others like it let users post photos, then have their looks rated by the masses on the Net. The sites seem to have touched a nerve.</p>
        <p>The popularity of these sites, none more than a few months old, is growing rapidly as thousands of users post their pictures and tens of thousands of others drop by to pass judgment.</p>
        <p>''I got a 3.2,'' Mr. Hong said with a laugh, referring to the average score he received, on a scale of 1 to 10, from people who ranked his photo. But he insists that while the site isn't meant to be taken too seriously, it does provide a service that is tough to get in a face-to-face world.</p>
        <p>''People want to know what they look like,'' he said. ''They want the honest, brutal truth.''</p>
        <p>Of course, sometimes they want the honest truth about somebody else entirely. Witness a photograph of Sean Connery from one of his less well-known movies, ''Zardoz.'' The picture is not labeled, and if you haven't seen the movie, it appears to be of a very odd middle-aged man in specially designed red underwear, posing with a gun.</p>
        <p>People also like to deliver the truth, or something like it, to others. Some raters confess that they get guilty thrills from meting out snap results. On AmIHotOrNot.com, each time a visitor rates a face, a new one arises in its place, creating a chance for rapid-fire assessments and a veritable drive-through window of voyeurism and judgment, users said.</p>
        <p>''People like to hide behind the shroud of the Internet and mock other people,'' said one AmIHotOrNot visitor, Dion Lisle, 38, director of marketing at Valicert, a security software company in Mountain View, Calif.</p>
        <p>That said, Mr. Lisle contended that his own ratings were usually more generous than the average scores people received, though he said he knew better than to put his own picture on the site -- and face the masses.</p>
        <p>''I'm a 38-year-old guy in O.K. shape,'' Mr. Lisle said. ''I feel pretty good about myself, and I don't need anybody judging me.''</p>
        <p>Certainly, though, there are plenty of others who are seeking feedback. The site, up since Oct. 9, now has 20,000 pictures, a figure increasing by more than 1,000 a day (some pictures are of animals, supermodels and the occasional cartoon character, though Mr. Hong said the site had a program to weed those out). The site is probably attracting 200,000 to 300,000 visitors a day, which means four million page views, said Mr. Hong, who created the site with a friend, Jim Young, 27.</p>
        <p>AmIHotOrNot is strictly anonymous and offers no chance for the users to communicate with one another. Some other sites let users send  messages to one another using screen names, and perhaps set up dates.</p>
        <p>For example, Michael Hussey, 22, a recent graduate of the University of Maine, helped found Infinite Medium, a company that has a similar site, except that his site has become something of a dating hub. It has had  roughly 7,000 pictures and gets 150,000 page views a day, and it is not restricted to adults. The site says it is open to anyone 13 or older. No pornography is allowed, but teenagers  can and do post seductive images with suggestive user names and self-descriptions.</p>
        <p>''We're putting the responsibility in the hands of the surfers,'' Mr. Hussey said, adding that parents needed to take care about where their children went online.</p>
        <p>Sometimes the sites are criticized for promoting superficiality. Mr. Hussey said his site drew a ''decent amount of nasty e-mails'' from people who found the idea degrading.</p>
        <p>At Votbot Picture Ratings, operating since July, the site's creator, 24-year-old David K. Taing, has taken steps to soften the blow of an unflattering rating. Unlike the other sites, which rate people from 1 to 10, Votbot lets visitors rate photographs on a scale of 7 to 10, in increments of two-tenths of a point.</p>
        <p>Mr. Taing, who limits his site to those who say they are at least 17,  said users would soon be able to send e-mail to one another. And his site, first advertised in a chat room set up for Asians, is designed so visitors can sort photographs according to age, eye and hair color, and ethnicity in choosing which ones to view.</p>
        <p>Technically, a score of 7 still represents the lowest possible score -- the equivalent of 1 on any other site, and the message that someone finds the photograph horrendously ugly -- but Mr. Taing said a 7 was easier to take than a 1. ''If someone gets a 5, they could feel really disappointed,'' he said. ''But if someone gets a 7, they could feel pretty good.''</p>
        <p>Creators of some of the picture-rating sites have begun contemplating business models to figure out how to make money from the traffic at their sites.</p>
        <p>Of course, in the end, what may matter most in Silicon Valley is not how a person appears to the masses, but how that person's business model looks to investors.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
