<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Exuberant And Focused On Every Bach Phrase</title>
    <meta content="26TULL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/26/arts/26TULL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20001027T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241914"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">McDermott, Anne-Marie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holland, Bernard</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001026T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE6DE1331F935A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="569" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Exuberant And Focused On Every Bach Phrase</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BERNARD HOLLAND</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Holland, Bernard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bernard Holland reviews piano recital by Anne-Marie McDermott at Alice Tully Hall; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Bach anniversary (he died 250 years ago) grinds on in high profile and low. Murray Perahia's concert on Sunday afternoon at Avery Fisher Hall was well promoted and, by all reports, of high quality. Less visible, certainly less well attended, but of considerable substance was Anne-Marie McDermott at Alice Tully Hall on Monday playing the C minor and B flat Partitas and the G minor English Suite before intermission and music by Brahms after it.</p>
        <p>Notably uncontroversial was the choice of instruments: in both cases, the modern piano. It is refreshing how bored listeners seem to have become by the debate over old instrument versus new. Bach, indeed, thrives on the gritty qualities of 18th-century double reeds and gut strings, but the extraordinary design of this music -- not just the density of the harmonic and contrapuntal thinking but the constant conflict between symmetry and anti-symmetry -- lifts it above and beyond instrumental sound. Given the proper attention, Bach's music will sound as effective on the kazoo as on the most authentic of clavichords.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Bach anniversary (he died 250 years ago) grinds on in high profile and low. Murray Perahia's concert on Sunday afternoon at Avery Fisher Hall was well promoted and, by all reports, of high quality. Less visible, certainly less well attended, but of considerable substance was Anne-Marie McDermott at Alice Tully Hall on Monday playing the C minor and B flat Partitas and the G minor English Suite before intermission and music by Brahms after it.</p>
        <p>Notably uncontroversial was the choice of instruments: in both cases, the modern piano. It is refreshing how bored listeners seem to have become by the debate over old instrument versus new. Bach, indeed, thrives on the gritty qualities of 18th-century double reeds and gut strings, but the extraordinary design of this music -- not just the density of the harmonic and contrapuntal thinking but the constant conflict between symmetry and anti-symmetry -- lifts it above and beyond instrumental sound. Given the proper attention, Bach's music will sound as effective on the kazoo as on the most authentic of clavichords.</p>
        <p>Attention is what Ms. McDermott has to give. Extraordinary exuberance is the first impression, but then one notices the careful thought that has gone into every moment of Bach's music. Through the varied weight of her fingers and the judicious alternation of staccato and legato, we hear not just that there are inner voices but precisely where these voices begin and end, where the narrative is passed from one line to the next and how all of this intricacy serves one all-governing flow of music. Ms. McDermott's choices are wise but not dry. The unthinking is served by thought. Above all she listens.</p>
        <p>This pianist's high spirits can get the better of her. The Gigue of the B flat Partita was an ill-considered muddle, a high-speed race run on a muddy track. Ms. McDermott has great dexterity, but here her hands seem to be punishing her for bad judgment. Bach's fast movements in all three pieces often flirted with the speed limit but largely held together.</p>
        <p>Applied to Brahms's difficult Handel Variations, this near-recklessness became something admirable. In the more peaceful moments, Ms. McDermott gave a harsh and obdurate piece a warmth that it is unaccustomed to. The fiercer variations showed moments of physical strain but hung on and survived. Ms. McDermott's virtuosity is considerable in every sense but is at its best when hidden. The Sarabande of the G minor English Suite, a slow dance, is music seemingly from outer space, so strange and powerful in its changes of key and melodic asymmetry that it could belong to any century. I doubt that most masters of scales, arpeggios and thundering octaves could bring us as close to this music as we were on Monday night.</p>
        <p>The other pieces were the three Intermezzos of Brahms's Opus 117, products of old age that are as yielding and private as the Handel Variations are intimidating. Ms. McDermott heard them as brisk and understated, gracefully melancholic but a little short of heartbreak.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW  Correction:  October 27, 2000, Friday  A contents entry in the Arts pages yesterday for a review of a performance of Bach and Brahms on Monday at Alice Tully Hall misstated the pianist's given name. As reported in the review, she is Anne-Marie McDermott, not Alice.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: October 27, 2000, Friday</p>
        <p>A contents entry in the Arts pages yesterday for a review of a performance of Bach and Brahms on Monday at Alice Tully Hall misstated the pianist's given name. As reported in the review, she is Anne-Marie McDermott, not Alice.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
