<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Viacom Net Falls but Not as Much as Feared</title>
    <meta content="Y26VIAC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/26/business/26VIAC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241947"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Viacom Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fabrikant, Geraldine</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001026T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E7D91331F935A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="524" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Viacom Net Falls but Not as Much as Feared</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GERALDINE FABRIKANT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fabrikant, Geraldine</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Viacom reports net income of $33.4 million in third quarter, down sharply from third quarter of 1999, when company reported profits of $96.7 million; says cash flow rose 22 percent, to $1.45 billion, and revenue grew 7 percent, to $5.97 billion, compared with year earlier (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Viacom said yesterday that it had net income of $33.4 million, or 2 cents a share, for the third quarter of 2000. Though the figure was down sharply from the third quarter of 1999, when the company reported profits of $96.7 million, or 16 cents a share, the latest results came as a positive surprise to analysts, who had expected a small loss for the quarter.</p>
        <p>The company attributed the income decline to higher expenses and taxes, especially amortization charges related to its acquisition of the CBS Corporation. The merger was completed in the second quarter.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Viacom said yesterday that it had net income of $33.4 million, or 2 cents a share, for the third quarter of 2000. Though the figure was down sharply from the third quarter of 1999, when the company reported profits of $96.7 million, or 16 cents a share, the latest results came as a positive surprise to analysts, who had expected a small loss for the quarter.</p>
        <p>The company attributed the income decline to higher expenses and taxes, especially amortization charges related to its acquisition of the CBS Corporation. The merger was completed in the second quarter.</p>
        <p>On a pro-forma basis, treating CBS as if it had been acquired a year ago, cash flow, or earnings before interest, taxes, depreciations and amortization, rose 22 percent, to $1.45 billion, and revenue grew 7 percent, to $5.97 billion, compared with the quarter a year earlier.</p>
        <p>Analysts were generally delighted at the figures because the performance at Viacom is now largely driven by advertiser revenue at the CBS network, the television and radio stations it acquired as part of CBS and the MTV and Nickelodeon networks. Bucking reports of a general slowing of advertiser spending, Viacom's results showed robust advertising revenue at all the company's outlets. ''Advertising, the lifeblood of the business, is up 10 percent to 12 percent,'' said Ed Hatch, who follows the media industry for SG Cowen. ''Viacom is swimming upstream in a tepid market by executing better.''</p>
        <p>The most obvious improvement was at the television network, where the success of the show ''Survivor'' has been a boon. ''On any metric they are outperforming the industry,'' said Jessica Reif Cohen, who follows the company for Merrill Lynch Global Securities. ''They have great brands, and you are just beginning to see the synergies from the merger. One of the reasons that 'Survivor' did so well is because they promoted it on the MTV network, which helped attract a younger viewer.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Cohen said that when Viacom won rights to popular programming like wrestling away from other cable networks, it held on to the programs' viewers by promoting the programs heavily.</p>
        <p>Cash flow from the television division jumped 39 percent, to $369.2 million, while the cable networks posted a 23 percent increase, to $425.8 million, and the radio stations an increase of 18 percent, to $473.2 million. All the figures are pro-forma comparisons with the comparable quarter a year ago.</p>
        <p>At the video division, which is primarily Blockbuster, the video store chain, cash flow fell 8 percent, to $119.1 million. The company attributed the decline to delayed release of new titles and weaker box office titles in current release.</p>
        <p>Despite analysts' enthusiasm about the results, Viacom's stock fell $2.44 yesterday to close at $53.94. Mr. Hatch and others said that investors were still nervous about the effect that a slowdown in the economy might ultimately have on advertiser spending, even though leading media companies, including Viacom and Time Warner, have said that in a slowdown, advertisers tend to concentrate their spending on the strongest media brands.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
