<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Every Game System Needs At Least One Great Game</title>
    <meta content="26SPLA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Circuits" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/26/technology/26SPLA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241923"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sony Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olafson, Peter</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Circuits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001026T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E7DC1331F935A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="648" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Every Game System Needs At Least One Great Game</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER OLAFSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olafson, Peter</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Superior computer game available for new Sony PlayStation 2 is Dynasty Warriors 2; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BEHIND every great new game system is at least one great game. On the Sega Saturn, it was Panzer Dragoon. On the Sony PlayStation, it was Ridge Racer. The Nintendo 64 had Super Mario World, and the Sega Dreamcast had NFL 2000.</p>
        <p>Based on the games I have seen for Sony's PlayStation 2, which goes on sale today, that system-selling game could be Dynasty Warriors 2. It's a lightning rod for the agreeable sense of freedom I often experienced playing the first wave of PlayStation 2 games.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BEHIND every great new game system is at least one great game. On the Sega Saturn, it was Panzer Dragoon. On the Sony PlayStation, it was Ridge Racer. The Nintendo 64 had Super Mario World, and the Sega Dreamcast had NFL 2000.</p>
        <p>Based on the games I have seen for Sony's PlayStation 2, which goes on sale today, that system-selling game could be Dynasty Warriors 2. It's a lightning rod for the agreeable sense of freedom I often experienced playing the first wave of PlayStation 2 games.</p>
        <p>The second-generation PlayStation, a hefty but compact black console, will feel familiar to anyone who has used the original. Although it has a front-loading DVD drive instead of the PSX's top-loading CD-ROM, the two are almost identical in how they are set up. Like the PlayStation, it is plug-and-play: Pop in a disk, hit the Start button on the controller (identical except for color) if you want to cut short a game introduction, and go. (It also ran my original PlayStation games without a hitch.)</p>
        <p>The performance, however, will not feel familiar. The PlayStation 2 runs rings around its predecessor. The high-resolution graphics are lustrous, with neither a plain polygon nor pop-up, the phenomenon in which scenery suddenly appears out of nowhere.</p>
        <p>The on-screen update can be blistering, and the loading speed is respectable. The PlayStation 2 did not make me wait for long, and that is a kind of freedom as well.</p>
        <p>So far, no game exploits the PlayStation 2's performance quite like Koei's Dynasty Warriors 2, which is a 3-D fighting game, but not simply a 3-D fighting game. While many games in that genre offer discrete match-ups with a fixed number of combatants, the battle in this release doesn't end when your enemy goes down. Someone else is always there to meet you. Not only does the game feel free of limits of the fighting genre, but it effectively christens a new one: a war game in which you are there.</p>
        <p>Sometimes freedom is intrinsic to the game itself. That's the case for SSX from Electronic Arts, a game in which you perform stunts while racing on a snowboard down slopes that might intimidate a bobsled team. And Electronic Arts' football game, Madden 2001, seems to have escaped the boundaries of the console to achieve an astonishing realism. A third-person action and role-playing game from Activision, Orphen: Scion of Sorcery, took me out of my skin. I felt as if I were a character in one of those odd Japanese cartoons I watched when I was growing up.</p>
        <p>Sometimes a game's sheer size and range of choices are enticing. For example, Namco's fighting game, Tekken Tag Tournament, offers 34 characters and 2,000 moves. That's not a game. That's a career.</p>
        <p>And sometimes a game draws you in simply through its ease of entry. Ignore the documentation, hit a few buttons, and drive like crazy. For instance, Midnight Club from Rock Star Games allows you to drive where you will through trimmed-down versions of Manhattan and central London. The game displays a happy obsession with landmarks (including the Guggenheim and the Met). If you want to drive the Franklin D. Roosevelt Drive like a maniac, you can do that, too. New Yorkers may wonder if anyone will notice.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
