<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Saudi to Direct U.N. Program Aimed at Controlling Population</title>
    <meta content="Y26NAT$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/26/world/26NATI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241968"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations Population Fund</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations High Commission for Refugees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Crossette, Barbara</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Annan, Kofi (Sec Gen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Obaid, Thoraya Ahmed</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lubbers, Ruud</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001026T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE2D71331F935A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="493" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Saudi to Direct U.N. Program Aimed at Controlling Population</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA CROSSETTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Crossette, Barbara</byline>
      <dateline>UNITED NATIONS, Oct. 25</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>United Nations Secretary General Kofi Annan announces two appointments; says Thoraya Ahmed Obaid, American-educated Saudi woman, has been chosen as executive director of United Nations Population Fund, and Ruud Lubbers of Netherlands is new United Nations high commissioner for refugees (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Thoraya Ahmed Obaid, an American-educated Saudi woman, was chosen today to be executive director of the United Nations Population Fund, which has made the expansion of women's rights central to its mission of cutting population growth worldwide.</p>
        <p>Secretary General Kofi Annan, who announced the appointment at a news conference, also nominated Ruud Lubbers, a former prime minister of the Netherlands, as the new United Nations high commissioner for refugees.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Thoraya Ahmed Obaid, an American-educated Saudi woman, was chosen today to be executive director of the United Nations Population Fund, which has made the expansion of women's rights central to its mission of cutting population growth worldwide.</p>
        <p>Secretary General Kofi Annan, who announced the appointment at a news conference, also nominated Ruud Lubbers, a former prime minister of the Netherlands, as the new United Nations high commissioner for refugees.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lubbers's appointment goes to the General Assembly for approval, usually a routine step. The appointment of Ms. Obaid, a United Nations insider with 25 years of experience in women's issues and development, does not require Assembly approval.</p>
        <p>Ms. Obaid, 55, will replace Nafis Sadik of Pakistan, who retires later this year after presiding over a revolutionary decade in thinking about population at the United Nations, which has moved from basic family-planning programs into broad areas of reproductive health and freedom of choice.</p>
        <p>Mr. Annan said he had sought a woman from the developing world for the job. Other officials and leaders of nongovernmental women's organizations have been saying there was always the assumption that the appointee would be a Muslim able to work in Islamic nations, where women's rights are often curtailed.</p>
        <p>Ms. Obaid, head of the population fund's division for the Arab nations and Europe since 1998, has been part of two high-level missions to Afghanistan under the Taliban, where restrictions on women are extremely severe.</p>
        <p>''Today, all the Saudi women are recognizing that you broke the ceiling one more time for Saudi women, and we thank you for that,'' Ms. Obaid said to Mr. Annan at the news conference. Asked about the poor record of Saudi Arabia on women's rights, she said the government there had recently recognized international agreements on the treatment of women and was always supportive of her work at the United Nations.</p>
        <p>Ms. Obaid, a Saudi who was born in Baghdad and went to an American school in Cairo as a child, has a B.A. from Mills College in California and an M.A. and Ph.D. in English literature and cultural anthropology from Wayne State University in Detroit.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lubbers, 61, prime minister of the Netherlands from 1982 to 1994, was recruited by Mr. Annan, who passed over a substantial body of candidates supported by various member nations. Among the leading names were Bernard Kouchner of France, the United Nations administrator in Kosovo, and Sergio Vieira de Mello, a Brazilian who is running East Timor during its transition to independence. Awkwardly for Mr. Lubbers, the Netherlands government was supporting another Dutch candidate, Jan Pronk, the environment minister.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
