<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An all-out effort is under way to market an artificial sweetener.</title>
    <meta content="Y26ADC$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/26/business/26ADCO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241955"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sweeteners, Artificial</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sucralose (Artificial Sweetener)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mcneil Consumer Products Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Lowe Lintas &amp; Partners</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hays, Constance L</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Advertising (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001026T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E6D81331F935A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1115" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An all-out effort is under way to market an artificial sweetener.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Constance L. Hays</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hays, Constance L</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>McNeil Specialty Products are making large-scale advertising campaign for Splenda, artificial sweetener generically known as sucralose; Lowe Lintas &amp; Partners developed campaign; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WORLD of home-baked coconut pie, made without sugar? That is among the promises that the marketers of Splenda, an artificial sweetener generically known as sucralose, are making through a large-scale campaign that began last month and will peak in January with a series of television commercials intended to create consumer interest in the product.</p>
        <p>Splenda is made by McNeil Specialty Products, a division of Johnson &amp; Johnson. While McNeil executives would not disclose spending for the campaign, one industry expert put the figure at about $40 million, citing publications that the company distributed at trade shows this summer to describe how it planned to support the product.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WORLD of home-baked coconut pie, made without sugar? That is among the promises that the marketers of Splenda, an artificial sweetener generically known as sucralose, are making through a large-scale campaign that began last month and will peak in January with a series of television commercials intended to create consumer interest in the product.</p>
        <p>Splenda is made by McNeil Specialty Products, a division of Johnson &amp; Johnson. While McNeil executives would not disclose spending for the campaign, one industry expert put the figure at about $40 million, citing publications that the company distributed at trade shows this summer to describe how it planned to support the product.</p>
        <p>While the market is crowded with artificial sweeteners -- Equal and Sweet 'n' Low, to name just two -- advertising has trailed off in recent years.</p>
        <p>''It's a category that from a marketing standpoint spends a third of what it spent 15 years ago,'' said Kieran Walsh, executive vice president and managing director at Lowe Lintas &amp; Partners in New York, part of the Lowe Group unit of the Interpublic Group, which produced the Splenda television ads. ''And that's without accounting for inflation.''</p>
        <p>Executives in charge of Nutrasweet, generically known as aspartame and sold to consumers as Equal, confirmed that ad spending is down. Part of the reason is that in 1992, the patent held by Monsanto expired, which opened the field to competing manufacturers, said Nick Rosa, the president and chief executive of Nutrasweet's sweetener ingredient division, which was sold earlier this year by Monsanto to J. W. Childs Equity Partners.</p>
        <p>No new advertising is planned in response to Splenda, he added, noting the lessons of the past. ''When we launched Equal's tabletop sweetener, instead of cannibalizing Sweet 'n' Low, both businesses grew,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Still, executives at Merisant, which owns the Equal consumer business, indicated they planned a campaign of their own. ''We have plans to address the opportunity that there will be increased consumer interest in the category with another competitor,'' said Dan Beck, general manager for North America. ''And we are confident they will choose Equal.''</p>
        <p>McNeil is betting that Splenda's distinguishing characteristics -- it is derived from sugar and can be used in cooking -- will turn out to be strong selling points. In sucralose, three of the hydrogen-oxygen groups in each sugar molecule are replaced with chlorine atoms. The effect is that the sweetener is not absorbed into the body, meaning there are no calories to burn off later.</p>
        <p>The process was discovered by researchers in Britain in 1976 and was approved for consumer use by the Food and Drug Administration two years ago. Since then, it has become an ingredient in an array of foods and beverages, including Diet Rite cola, Swiss Miss sugar-free cocoa mix and Diet V8 Splash. It can withstand heat, making it unusual among artificial sweeteners. Now its promoters want to build up its image with consumers and persuade them to buy it in stores. The target audience is mostly women 35 and older, with busy lives involving lots of demands on their time and yet an inclination to bake. Diabetics are also being singled out through the company's Web site and other efforts with doctors.</p>
        <p>''What we have found is, the proposition that resonates with consumers is the fact that Splenda is made from sugar and tastes like sugar,'' said Debra A. Sandler, McNeil's vice president for worldwide marketing. ''The ads will focus on the origins of the products as well as the versatility of the product.''</p>
        <p>That versatility, particularly the idea of using Splenda in baking, will be a chief selling point. The product can be poured and measured in the same proportions as white sugar, Ms. Sandler said, although it weighs far less and looks more like powdered sugar than the granulated kind. Other artificial sweeteners have focused squarely and almost exclusively on the table top and the coffee wagon. Ms. Sandler sees the cooking realm as a big part of potential sales.</p>
        <p>''Upwards of 75 percent of the low-calorie sweetener category is the packet,'' she said. ''We feel there is an opportunity to grow the whole category, particularly the granular.''</p>
        <p>To do that, the company is distributing recipes, both on laminated cards and on its Web site at www.splenda.com. Predictably, many of the recipes are for pies and cakes, but others are for dishes like ''Sweet and Spicy Shrimp.'' Samples of Splenda are being handed out in stores and other public places.</p>
        <p>At the same time, McNeil also wants to be sure Splenda is a contender for use in coffee and tea. A partnership with 7-Eleven will feature Splenda in radio ads and put packets of it next to Equal and Sweet 'n' Low in the chain's 5,200 stores, beginning this month.</p>
        <p>''We saw it as a win-win-win proposition,'' said Alan Beach, 7-Eleven's category manager for hot beverages. ''We worked out a very extensive agreement that included a lot of different pieces.''</p>
        <p>While similar partnerships have been formed in the past, ''every product doesn't have the opportunities this one does,'' he added. ''It's new, it's unique and it has a lot of benefits.''</p>
        <p>McNeil is also distributing coupons for Splenda in newspapers. The sweetener is expensive compared with regular sugar but comparable to other artificial sweeteners. A 55-gram box of Splenda costs $2.50, a company spokeswoman said, and is the equivalent for cooking purposes of a pound of sugar.</p>
        <p>The company also signed Mia Hamm, the soccer player, to help promote the brand at an event earlier this month in New York. Ms. Hamm cited a story, commissioned by McNeil, that ranked United States cities by sugar consumption.</p>
        <p>Leading the pack was New Orleans, which could not have been a surprise, considering a propensity for pralines and an annual event called the Sugar Bowl. Ms. Hamm urged her audience to cut back on their calories by using Splenda and received a check from McNeil for her foundation, which promotes women's sports and finances research on bone-marrow disease.</p>
        <p>The television ads, scheduled to be broadcast in January, have been years in the conceptualizing, Mr. Walsh said. ''It's important for us to put a contemporary twist on this,'' he said, while declining to give any details, except that there will be no dancing molecules.</p>
        <p>''We have done a significant amount of research on this, and consumers are very excited about this,'' Mr. Walsh said. ''The demand for that silver bullet, food products that taste good and are also good for you, is eternal.''</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
