<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>AT&amp;T Realigns Its Planets</title>
    <meta content="Y26FON$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/26/business/26FONE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241974"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BREAKING UP AGAIN: NEWS ANALYSIS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">At&amp;t Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Armstrong, C Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Norris, Floyd</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001026T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E2D61331F935A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1832" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>AT&amp;T Realigns Its Planets</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FLOYD NORRIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Norris, Floyd</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Analysis of AT&amp;T Corp's decision to spin off its businesses into three or four or five companies; says breakup is desperate effort to make Wall Street happy, something company seems to think it can accomplish by dishing out lots of investment banking fees while reducing dividends paid to its shareholders; holds chairman-chief executive C Michael Armstrong did not discuss how having all these companies separate, or sort-of separate, will improve operations and business directly; says drop in AT&amp;T shares to $23.38 reflects mindnumbing complexity of deal, and how long it will take; reorganization will be completed in 2002; drawing; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If only AT&amp;T worked as hard at telecommunications engineering as it does at financial engineering, maybe investors would treat it with more respect. The newest breakup of AT&amp;T is a desperate effort to make Wall Street happy, something the company seems to think it can accomplish by dishing out lots of investment banking fees while reducing dividends paid to its shareholders.</p>
        <p>AT&amp;T plans to issue a blizzard of paper to confused shareholders as the company morphs into three or four or five companies, but who's counting? The number depends on how one counts tracking stocks in which the nominal parent company has no economic stake. Some of those companies will be sort-of independent, some will be more independent. Over time, they may grow apart, as did the companies that resulted from AT&amp;T's first breakup, in 1984.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If only AT&amp;T worked as hard at telecommunications engineering as it does at financial engineering, maybe investors would treat it with more respect. The newest breakup of AT&amp;T is a desperate effort to make Wall Street happy, something the company seems to think it can accomplish by dishing out lots of investment banking fees while reducing dividends paid to its shareholders.</p>
        <p>AT&amp;T plans to issue a blizzard of paper to confused shareholders as the company morphs into three or four or five companies, but who's counting? The number depends on how one counts tracking stocks in which the nominal parent company has no economic stake. Some of those companies will be sort-of independent, some will be more independent. Over time, they may grow apart, as did the companies that resulted from AT&amp;T's first breakup, in 1984.</p>
        <p>''I am personally convinced this will add tremendous value,'' said C. Michael Armstrong, the company's chairman and chief executive. That means he hopes the stock prices of the companies will be higher when they are separated than when they are together. At an analysts' meeting, he spoke of the incentives for executives and employees of the various operations that will come from having their own shares.</p>
        <p>What he didn't talk about was how having all these companies separate, or sort-of separate, will improve operations and business directly. There are some points to be made there. AT&amp;T's consumer operations will now be able to get into digital subscriber lines -- the phone company version of fast Internet connections -- while AT&amp;T's cable operations can continue to sell their own fast Internet connections and say they are better than D.S.L. But mostly this is a deal to make Wall Street happy.</p>
        <p>On one level, it clearly will do so. AT&amp;T and its various operations already are paying no fewer than four major investment banking firms -- Credit Suisse First Boston; Goldman, Sachs; Merrill Lynch; and Salomon Smith Barney -- for advice on aspects of this deal. More firms will probably be in before it is over. But the deal didn't do anything quickly for the shareholders. AT&amp;T shares fell $3.81, to $23.38, leaving the stock, adjusted for the last AT&amp;T split-up in 1996, barely above where it was in 1989.</p>
        <p>Part of that decline was because of the company's providing somewhat disappointing guidance on earnings for next year. The decline in the consumer long-distance business was clearly greater than AT&amp;T had expected, and there were problems in some other operations. But the fall also reflects the mind-numbing complexity of this deal, and how long it will take. Not until 2002 will it be completed. In the meantime, executives and employees will be vying to determine who goes where, with what is likely to be intense corporate infighting on the details of the split-up and the allocation of top jobs. That fighting is not likely to do a lot for operations.</p>
        <p>As for Mr. Armstrong's future, he promised to stay ''through 2000,'' then corrected himself to say he meant 2002. Whether he will be with one of the companies -- and which one -- after the break-up was not disclosed. Nor is it clear who will head any of the new companies, save for AT&amp;T Wireless.</p>
        <p>In brief form, here is what is going to happen. AT&amp;T now has its own common stock and two tracking stocks, Liberty Media and AT&amp;T Wireless. It has no real stake in Liberty Media, since the entire operating interest is owned by holders of the tracking stock. But it still has most of the economic stake in AT&amp;T Wireless; it sold a mere 16 percent stake to the public in an offering in April at $29.50 a share. Yesterday, those shares rose 94 cents, to $22.56.</p>
        <p>AT&amp;T is mum about what will happen to Liberty Media, but it will probably be turned into an independent company with few, if any, ties to AT&amp;T.</p>
        <p>As for AT&amp;T Wireless, shareholders of AT&amp;T will be offered a chance to exchange their shares in AT&amp;T for wireless tracking stock. AT&amp;T did not rule out selling more AT&amp;T Wireless shares, perhaps in a private placement. Whatever wireless shares are left will then be distributed to AT&amp;T shareholders, and AT&amp;T Wireless will become an independent company, with a license to use the AT&amp;T name and assorted contracts with other AT&amp;T operations.</p>
        <p>Similarly, AT&amp;T's cable operations -- to be called Broadband, because that name sounds a lot sexier -- will go away. First, a tracking stock will be sold, then the rest of the shares will be spun off to regular AT&amp;T shareholders. They will then be converted from tracking shares to regular shares, and AT&amp;T Broadband will be more or less independent. Liberty Media, if it stays as a tracking stock, will be part of that company, sort-of.</p>
        <p>What's left will be AT&amp;T Business, which has a variety of operations, and AT&amp;T Consumer, which will be a tracking stock for consumer long-distance, and whatever the company can put together in D.S.L., as well as its current Internet access business. That tracking stock will be completely distributed to AT&amp;T owners, leaving AT&amp;T Business with no economic interest in the consumer unit.</p>
        <p>The net effect will be at least three independent companies with the AT&amp;T label, plus one tracking stock with that label. Liberty Media may be a tracking stock or an independent company.</p>
        <p>Is all that clear? Of course not. Why create companies as tracking stocks, and then make them independent a few months later? Well, it will create more business for the lawyers and investment bankers, and more complexity for confused shareholders. Otherwise, the benefits are not clear. Mr. Armstrong, in the news conference yesterday, proclaimed that he and Charles H. Noski, AT&amp;T's chief financial officer, are the ''kings of trackers.'' It is a title that the architects of this plan richly deserve.</p>
        <p>When the dust settles, AT&amp;T will have saved a good portion -- it won't say how much -- of the $3.3 billion it now pays out in shareholder dividends. The consumer company will pay dividends -- Mr. Armstrong promised it would be ''a high-yield entity'' -- but the broadband and wireless companies will not pay dividends. It is not clear whether the AT&amp;T Business operation will pay dividends.</p>
        <p>It will be interesting to compare AT&amp;T's dividend savings to the fees it will spend for investment banking and legal services in connection with all these deals. Perhaps the amount spent helping confused shareholders figure out what is going on should be added to those fees. One hopes that the total won't eat up more than a year of the dividend savings.</p>
        <p>Mr. Armstrong was brought in to AT&amp;T in late 1997, after the failure of AT&amp;T's last strategy. It tried to get into computers by buying NCR, only to spin it off in 1996 after seeing the value erode. At the same time, it dumped its manufacturing operations, renamed Lucent Technologies, only to see that company become a Wall Street shooting star, which soared before tumbling this year.</p>
        <p>While AT&amp;T did not realize the value that Wall Street came to see in Lucent, some of that value was created by the spin off, which made it easier for Lucent to sell to AT&amp;T competitors. It is less clear how these spun-off companies will benefit from independence.</p>
        <p>The saddest part of all this is that Mr. Armstrong had a decent strategy to save the company and keep it from going the way of Western Union, the company it replaced as the dominant communications company. He bought up wireless and cable companies, seeking to put together national operations in two areas where technology is improving all the time. The consumer long-distance business provided cash to subsidize those investments.</p>
        <p>Mr. Armstrong's strategy still looks promising, and Mr. Armstrong says it is not being abandoned. But Wall Street lost faith in it, and sent the stock price down nearly two-thirds from its March peak of $61. Debt has risen sharply, which is one reason it is planning to sell some of the broadband operations -- and might sell more of the wireless company.  AT&amp;T concluded it had to do something. Raising more cash by selling AT&amp;T stock at these depressed levels did not seem like a good idea.</p>
        <p>The good news for investors is that the strategy may still work, although it is hard to see how the organizational chaos of the next couple of years will help. For one thing, the split-up will remove the long-distance cash-flow from the other operations that need it. If the strategy does work, the current AT&amp;T stock price will seem cheap. But it is more likely that the profits will come in spite of this strange deal, not because of it.</p>
        <p>BREAKING UP AGAIN: NEWS ANALYSIS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
