<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Clinton Almost Blames Arafat for Not Controlling Violence</title>
    <meta content="Y26DIP$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/26/world/26DIPL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20001030T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242027"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Israel-International Relations-US</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sanger, David E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barak, Ehud (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arafat, Yasir</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sharon, Ariel</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001026T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E7DA1031F935A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="674" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Clinton Almost Blames Arafat for Not Controlling Violence</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID E. SANGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sanger, David E</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 25</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Clinton comes close to blaming Yasir Arafat, Palestinian leader, for failing to rein in violence, and he offers some of his warmest praise of Israeli Prime Min Barak; Clinton is trying to have both men visit Washington for separate consultations on restarting peace effort; White House officials say privately that any chance of resuming peace talks would end if Barak forms emergency government with Ariel Sharon, hard-line opposition leader; American officials fear that any seeming meddling in internal affairs of Israel would weaken Barak (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Clinton walked to the edge of blaming Yasir Arafat today for failing to rein in violence and offered some of his warmest praise of Prime Minister Ehud Barak of Israel, who he said was ''getting the worst of both worlds'' as he struggled to remain in power.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton made his comments at an event this morning on the South Lawn as the president was trying to have Mr. Arafat and Mr. Barak visit Washington next week for separate consultations on restarting the peace effort.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Clinton walked to the edge of blaming Yasir Arafat today for failing to rein in violence and offered some of his warmest praise of Prime Minister Ehud Barak of Israel, who he said was ''getting the worst of both worlds'' as he struggled to remain in power.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton made his comments at an event this morning on the South Lawn as the president was trying to have Mr. Arafat and Mr. Barak visit Washington next week for separate consultations on restarting the peace effort.</p>
        <p>White House officials said the timing of the meetings was critical. They said they believed -- but would not say so publicly -- that any chance of resuming peace negotiations soon would end if Mr. Barak formed an emergency government with Ariel Sharon, the hard-line opposition leader. Those talks in Israel were under way.</p>
        <p>American officials are highly reluctant to talk about Mr. Sharon, for fear of seeming to meddle in the internal affairs of Israel, a move that could weaken Mr. Barak.</p>
        <p>''Talking points'' distributed to administration officials this week included the usual recitation of the need for Israel to determine the nature of its governing coalitions. One administration official acknowledged this week, ''We don't want to say or do anything that will ricochet and improve Sharon's chances.''</p>
        <p>Administration officials said their concern about Mr. Sharon was that his rise to power-sharing with Mr. Barak would be read by the Palestinians and other Arabs as a sign that Israel had given up on a negotiated peace. They would assume that Israel was pulling off the table concessions that Mr. Barak offered in August at Camp David that would permit joint sovereignty with the Palestians over parts of Jerusalem. Mr. Arafat rejected those proposals, saying they did not go far enough.</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Clinton stopped short of attacking Mr. Arafat -- with whom he had what one American diplomat called ''an inconclusive'' telephone conversation on Tuesday -- he pointedly omitted the Palestinian leader this morning from his short list of those who seek to end the violence.</p>
        <p>''We would like to see, and I think that the Israelis would like to see, a resumption of the peace process,'' Mr. Clinton said. ''But both parties have got to do what they said they'd do.''</p>
        <p>Senior administration officials said Mr. Clinton, despite omitting Mr. Arafat's name, believed that the Palestinian leader wanted to restart the peace effort. But there remains a significant gap on how to accomplish that, the officials said.</p>
        <p>''I do think Chairman Arafat can dramatically reduce the level of violence,'' Mr. Clinton said, and he made no criticism of how the Israeli military has responded with tank and helicopter fire to stonings, gunfire and other acts of violence from Palestinians.</p>
        <p>Hours after Mr. Clinton spoke, the House overwhelming passed a resolution to express support for Israel and condemn Palestinian leaders for the eruption of violence. The nonbinding measure passed, 365 to 30. It condemned Mr. Arafat and other Palestinian leaders for ''encouraging the violence and doing so little for so long to stop it, resulting in the senseless loss of life.''</p>
        <p>White House officials were clearly concerned that the strength of the language would make it more difficult for Mr. Clinton to walk the line between supporting Israel and acting as what the president calls an ''honest broker.'' Mr. Arafat and Mr. Barak could both show up here next week for separate talks, administration officials said. ''We're still trying to work it out,'' one official said.</p>
        <p>The talks take on an urgent note because Mr. Clinton fears that without progress at the negotiating table, the fractured cease-fire agreed to last week in Egypt will completely collapse.</p>
        <p>If the talks here fail to come together next week, the calendar suggests that they will be difficult to arrange for weeks to come, with the election ahead and Mr. Clinton then traveling to Asia.</p>
        <p>Correction:  October 30, 2000, Monday  An article on Thursday about comments by President Clinton on the violence between Israelis and Palestinians misstated the month in which peace talks were held at Camp David this summer. It was July, not August.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: October 30, 2000, Monday</p>
        <p>An article on Thursday about comments by President Clinton on the violence between Israelis and Palestinians misstated the month in which peace talks were held at Camp David this summer. It was July, not August.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
