<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Knicks Join Pack Trying to Recruit An Available Star</title>
    <meta content="26KNIC$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/26/sports/26KNIC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242038"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Minnesota Timberwolves</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, Joe</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Broussard, Chris</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New York Knicks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Minnesota Timberwolves</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001026T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E1DA1031F935A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="580" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Knicks Join Pack Trying to Recruit An Available Star</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRIS BROUSSARD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Broussard, Chris</byline>
      <dateline>UNIONDALE, N.Y., Oct. 25</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Knickerbockers have set their sights on forward Joe Smith, whose contract with Minnesota Timberwolves was voided by National Basketball Association, making him a free agent (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Knicks have set their sights on the 6-foot-10-inch forward Joe Smith, whose contract with the Minnesota Timberwolves was voided today by the National Basketball Association, making him a free agent.</p>
        <p>''He's certainly a great player and we certainly have interest in him,'' General Manager Scott Layden said tonight at halftime of the Washington Wizards' 87-86 exhibition victory over the Knicks. ''We'll certainly see if there's a chance to get him here.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Knicks have set their sights on the 6-foot-10-inch forward Joe Smith, whose contract with the Minnesota Timberwolves was voided today by the National Basketball Association, making him a free agent.</p>
        <p>''He's certainly a great player and we certainly have interest in him,'' General Manager Scott Layden said tonight at halftime of the Washington Wizards' 87-86 exhibition victory over the Knicks. ''We'll certainly see if there's a chance to get him here.''</p>
        <p>The Knicks are over the salary cap, so they can offer Smith only the midlevel exception, or $2.25 million a year. Layden said approximately half of the league's 29 clubs can make the same offer, while a couple of others can offer more.</p>
        <p>Dan Fegan, Smith's agent, said that the Knicks would be a good fit for his client.</p>
        <p>''He's still looking at his options with other teams, but New York is a situation that would suit him,'' Fegan said, adding that he had spoken to Layden tonight.</p>
        <p>Smith, 25, is entering his sixth season. He has averaged 14.5 points and 7.5 rebounds a game. The No. 1 pick in the 1995 draft, Smith averaged only 9.9 points and 6.2 rebounds a game last season as the Timberwolves' sixth man.</p>
        <p>Still, Smith has great potential and could help the Knicks in their area of greatest need -- rebounding. Though mainly a power forward, he can also play small forward and center, particularly in the small Eastern Conference.</p>
        <p>The Miami Heat, which lost Alonzo Mourning for the season because of a kidney disorder, could be able to offer Smith $3.9 million if the league awards the club a disabled-player exception. The Heat applied for it today. The Chicago Bulls, who reportedly have an interest in Smith, could offer him about $6 million.</p>
        <p>Fegan said if Smith retained his Larry Bird rights -- a provision that allows a team to re-sign its own free agent after three years, even if the new contract exceeds the salary cap -- the Timberwolves would be his first choice.</p>
        <p>Latrell Sprewell could play a role in helping the Knicks sign Smith. The two played together at Golden State in the 1995-97 seasons and were good friends.</p>
        <p>''If he knows we're interested, he's going to be willing to come,'' said Sprewell, who called Smith tonight.</p>
        <p>''I've seen him quite a bit at Minnesota and he's a very good player,'' Layden said of Smith. ''He's matured into a fine player. I think he's improved every year. He's highly skilled, yet he does things that help a team win. He looks like a guy who can play a number of positions.''</p>
        <p>REBOUNDS</p>
        <p>Coach JEFF VAN GUNDY was upset with the Knicks' performance Wednesday. ''We've got a lot of things to tighten the screws on,'' he said. ''Guys were more worried about the World Series than about tonight's game.'' . . . CHRIS WHITNEY's 3-pointer with 2.4 seconds left was the decisive shot for the Wizards. . . . LATRELL SPREWELL, who showed up 20 minutes before tip-off, led the Knicks (5-2) with 23 points.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
