<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Strangers in a Strange Land: Yankee Fans at Shea</title>
    <meta content="26YANK" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/26/sports/26YANK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242064"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL: SUBWAY SERIES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lapointe, Joe</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001026T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E0D91031F935A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="734" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Strangers in a Strange Land: Yankee Fans at Shea</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE LAPOINTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lapointe, Joe</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses apparent high number of New York Yankees fans attending World Series at Shea Stadium (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The difference is obvious, although the sample is unscientific. Just listen. With the Mets and the Yankees playing in the all-New York World Series, there is more cheering for the visiting team when the games are at Shea Stadium than there is when the games are at Yankee Stadium.</p>
        <p>''You hear actual Yankee chants here,'' Jay Payton of the Mets said last night before Game 4 at Shea, when the Yankee fans became really loud in the ninth inning, as Mariano Rivera closed out Game 4 and put the Yankees within one victory of their third straight World Series title. ''Over at their stadium, you didn't hear Met chants at all.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The difference is obvious, although the sample is unscientific. Just listen. With the Mets and the Yankees playing in the all-New York World Series, there is more cheering for the visiting team when the games are at Shea Stadium than there is when the games are at Yankee Stadium.</p>
        <p>''You hear actual Yankee chants here,'' Jay Payton of the Mets said last night before Game 4 at Shea, when the Yankee fans became really loud in the ninth inning, as Mariano Rivera closed out Game 4 and put the Yankees within one victory of their third straight World Series title. ''Over at their stadium, you didn't hear Met chants at all.''</p>
        <p>Payton may be a rookie, but he has picked up on a reality of team rivalries in the New York area. In hockey, it applies to the Rangers when they play the Devils in New Jersey or the Islanders on Long Island. In basketball, it happens when the Knicks play the Nets in New Jersey.</p>
        <p>The team with the longer history has the advantage, even if it is only a matter of percentages on the road. A rough estimate of the fan breakdown in Yankee Stadium for the first two games of this Subway Series, judging by the sound of the cheering and chanting and the team logo clothing on the spectators, might have been 90 percent for the Yankees, 10 percent for the Mets. In Tuesday's Game 3 at Shea, it seemed to be 75 percent for the Mets, 25 percent for the Yankees. Last night, those 25 percent sounded like 50 percent at the end of the game.</p>
        <p>''There's a lot more Yankee fans in the city,'' Payton said. ''Yankee fans have more connections. We've got more blue-collar, hard-working people here, and Yankee fans get all the rich celebrities you see sitting behind home plate. They've got all the connections to get all the tickets.''</p>
        <p>Also sitting behind home plate is Nelson Doubleday, the chairman of the Mets. When asked if he had noticed the support for the road team in Game 3, Doubleday widened his eyes with mock alarm.</p>
        <p>''Horrified!'' he said of his reaction. ''Somebody turncoated on us. Gave their kids the seats or gave their parents the seats. Or something.''</p>
        <p>When asked if this bothered him, Doubleday said: ''It's fun. It's fun. I'm not thin skinned.''</p>
        <p>Bobby Valentine, the manager of the Mets, echoed Payton when he said Yankee fans ''are better at getting tickets than our fans, huh?''</p>
        <p>If that is so, one of the reasons may have been the timing of the distribution process. The Mets sold their World Series tickets after it was clear that there would be a Subway Series. The Yankees put their World Series tickets on sale before a Subway Series was a certainty, making Mets fans less inclined to buy tickets for Yankee Stadium games.</p>
        <p>In addition, the Mets sold all their Series tickets by phone, making them more widely available. The Yanks sold some tickets at the Yankee Stadium box office, making it more likely that fans more familiar with the Yankees would buy them.</p>
        <p>Some of the tickets went to couples with divided loyalties. Two of them attending last night were Joe and JoJo Samples of Edison, N.J. They arrived early, working their way near the dugouts to watch batting practice. Joe Samples wore a Mets jersey with ''Piazza'' on the back. It honored Mike Piazza, the Mets' star catcher. JoJo Samples wore a Yankees shirt decorated with ''Jeter,'' honoring Derek Jeter, the Yankees' star shortstop.</p>
        <p>Payton said part of the reason for the balance of support might be that the Yankees have been bigger winners lately, with two consecutive championships and three in the last four seasons. The Mets last won the World Series in 1986.</p>
        <p>''It comes with winning,'' Payton said of fan support. ''You've got die-hard fans and you've got fair-weather fans. We wouldn't mind having some fair-weather fans.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL: SUBWAY SERIES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
