<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Mets, Lots of Faith, Few Runs</title>
    <meta content="26METS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/26/sports/26METS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242086"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL: SUBWAY SERIES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kepner, Tyler</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001026T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE3D81031F935A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="836" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Mets, Lots of Faith, Few Runs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kepner, Tyler</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Mets players and coaches discuss trailing World Series, 3-1, to New York Yankees (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There are two pieces of white paper taped above Edgardo Alfonzo's locker at Shea Stadium. Written on one are a few of the standard inspirational sports words: faith, passion, consistency, victory. On another is a passage from the Bible: ''Now faith is assurance of things hoped for, a conviction of things not seen.''</p>
        <p>The Mets are left with their faith now, left to believe they have lost their final game of the season and can come back to win this World Series despite falling behind three games to one last night.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There are two pieces of white paper taped above Edgardo Alfonzo's locker at Shea Stadium. Written on one are a few of the standard inspirational sports words: faith, passion, consistency, victory. On another is a passage from the Bible: ''Now faith is assurance of things hoped for, a conviction of things not seen.''</p>
        <p>The Mets are left with their faith now, left to believe they have lost their final game of the season and can come back to win this World Series despite falling behind three games to one last night.</p>
        <p>Alfonzo, the Mets' ignitor in the first two playoff rounds, went 0 for 3 in last night's 3-2 loss to the Yankeees. He is 2 for 16 in the Series. He led with his performance and his words in the playoffs, challenging the Mets after a sloppy loss to St. Louis in Game 3 of the National League Championship Series. Now, Alfonzo said, his teammates will know what to do.</p>
        <p>''Each guy has to know pretty much what they're doing,'' Alfonzo said. ''It's a situation where you have to just believe in your talent and think about what you have to do. Every guy has a job to do here, and it's not going to be one guy. We have to do it all together.''</p>
        <p>The Mets will attempt to become the first team since the 1985 Kansas City Royals to overcome a 3-1 deficit to win the World Series. This is the 41st time a World Series has stood at 3-1, and 34 times, the team that led 3-1 went on to capture the title.</p>
        <p>The last time the Mets trailed by 3-1 in a postseason series was in the N.L.C.S. last year, when Robin Ventura lifted the Mets to a 15-inning victory in Game 5 with his grand slam single. The Mets took the Braves to the 11th inning of a sixth game before finally succumbing.</p>
        <p>Ventura discounted that experience and said he knows his teammates have come back from all manner of adversity.</p>
        <p>''We've been in lower spots before,'' he said. ''You don't know if you're going to do it, but if there's any group that can do it, I want to go at it with this one.''</p>
        <p>Several Mets, including Ventura, noted that the Mets have lost three one-run games in this series, which makes the deficit tougher to take, in some respects. When you win, Ventura said, you don't reflect on how you did it. But when you lose a close game, there are moments to replay in your mind, points in the game that could have altered the outcome.</p>
        <p>The Mets took a 3-2 lead into the bottom of the ninth in Game 1, only to lose the game in the 12th. After falling behind 6-0 in Game 2, the Mets rallied for five runs before Kurt Abbott struck out to end the game.</p>
        <p>Now comes Game 4, when the Mets had base runners in seven innings but could score only on Mike Piazza's two-run homer in the third.</p>
        <p>''The first game, you were winning; the second game probably not as much,'' Ventura said. ''But tonight, you have an inning where you have some guys on and you just don't do anything with it. But any time you don't get any hits, you always think that way.''</p>
        <p>Ventura was 0 for 4 last night, stranding a runner in the sixth and eighth. He grounded to short for the first out of the second, and after the next two Mets reached base, Mike Bordick and Bobby J. Jones popped out to end the threat. After Piazza's third-inning homer, the Mets would get no runners past first base.</p>
        <p>The Yankees left more runners on base than the Mets, but they capitalized just enough to win again. Benny Agbayani, who failed to get a hit last night for the first time in 13 postseason games this year, said the thing that most impresses him about the Yankees is their relentless attack.</p>
        <p>When asked what will be the hardest thing to overcome about the Yankees, Agbayani did not hesitate. ''Holding them down, not letting them get on base, not letting them execute,'' Agbayani said.</p>
        <p>If coming up one run short can be frustrating to some players, it can embolden others. Center fielder Jay Payton, who said the Mets have ''nothing to lose'' at this point, felt that way.</p>
        <p>''If you get blown out in three out of four games, then guys are going, 'They're just flat-out better than we are and we might not have a chance,''' Payton said. ''But these games have been determined by one pitch or one hit. That gives us a lot of confidence that we can get that one hit or pitch and turn it around and win the next three games.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL: SUBWAY SERIES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
