<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="26DIGE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242001"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001026T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902EEDD1031F935A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1256" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AT&amp;T Outlines Its Plan To Split Into Four Parts  AT&amp;T pulled back from an expensive three-year effort to become the first one-stop shop selling long-distance, wireless, cable television and Internet services as a single package with a single bill. Instead, the company announced, it will break itself into four parts.</p>
        <p>The nation's eighth-largest company, which only two decades ago dominated the telephone business and ranked with General Motors and Mobil among the nation's very largest companies, will soon be four much smaller businesses competing against many formidable, and sometimes larger, rivals. [Page A1.]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AT&amp;T Outlines Its Plan To Split Into Four Parts  AT&amp;T pulled back from an expensive three-year effort to become the first one-stop shop selling long-distance, wireless, cable television and Internet services as a single package with a single bill. Instead, the company announced, it will break itself into four parts.</p>
        <p>The nation's eighth-largest company, which only two decades ago dominated the telephone business and ranked with General Motors and Mobil among the nation's very largest companies, will soon be four much smaller businesses competing against many formidable, and sometimes larger, rivals. [Page A1.]</p>
        <p>Northwest Airlines Trial Delayed  A federal judge agreed to postpone a court battle in which the Justice Department is trying to force Northwest Airlines to sell its controlling stake in Continental Airlines. The closely watched trial was set to begin in Detroit today. But the judge pushed back the start to Nov. 1 at the request of Northwest, which asked for time to try to settle the case. [C5.]</p>
        <p>Judge Puts Limits on Tax Company  Renaissance/The Tax People, which has been marketing a system to reduce income taxes that the authorities say is really a pyramid scheme, was ordered by a Kansas judge to stop soliciting new clients. Carla J. Stovall, the attorney general of Kansas, filed a civil lawsuit on Friday seeking to shut down the company, which is owned by Michael C. Cooper. But her office agreed in negotiations with lawyers for the company to allow the business to operate in limited fashion. [C6.]</p>
        <p>Bond Trader Files More Complaints  A bond trader at Morgan Stanley Dean Witter who has accused the firm of sexual discrimination filed additional complaints with the Equal Employment Opportunity Commission, accusing Morgan Stanley of firing her on Tuesday in retaliation for her complaints. A spokesman for the firm confirmed that the trader, Allison K. Schieffelin, had been dismissed. [C6.]</p>
        <p>CBS has agreed to pay $8 million to about 200 female technicians who said in a class-action lawsuit that they had been sexually harassed and discriminated against. [C14.]</p>
        <p>AOL Asks to File Microsoft Brief  America Online asked a federal appeals court for permission to file a supporting brief in the appeal of the Microsoft antitrust case, noting that the plaintiffs in the case -- the federal government and 19 states -- support the idea while Microsoft opposes it. The company did not say what its brief might discuss, though it is clear that the brief will support the government's argument and a federal judge's rulings against Microsoft. [C4.]</p>
        <p>For Team Owner, a Business Slump  For John W. Henry, who owns the Florida Marlins and has a minority stake in the New York Yankees, the World Series can help take his mind off his other business, an investment company. The Financial and Metals Portfolio, one of his largest and most aggressive funds, fell 18.7 percent last year and is down 17.4 percent this year. The assets of his investment group have been sliced to about $1 billion from $2.4 billion a year ago. [C9.]</p>
        <p>Viacom Profit Beats Expectations  Viacom reported higher revenue and cash flow for its third quarter, but net income fell sharply on higher taxes and costs associated with its acquisition of CBS. The company earned $33.4 million, or 2 cents a share, compared with $96.7 million, or 14 cents a share, in the quarter a year earlier. Analysts had been expecting a loss of 2 cents a share. Shares of Viacom fell $2.44, to $53.94. [C10.]</p>
        <p>September Home Resales Fell 2.7%  Sales of previously owned homes fell 2.7 percent in September to a pace that still shows a vigorous economy, a report showed. [C5.]</p>
        <p>Gore Muddles His Economic Ideas  Since the political conventions, Vice President Al Gore has emphasized the fiscal discipline of his agenda and referred less to programs for working families, confusing his message in the process. Jeff Madrick: Economic Scene. [C2.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
