<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Yemen Reports Arrests of Foreign-Born Arabs in Cole Attack</title>
    <meta content="Y26SHI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/26/world/26SHIP.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242034"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cole (USS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Yemen</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Egypt</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Algeria</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Bureau of Investigation</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Islamic Jihad</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Burns, John F</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Saleh, Ali Abdullah (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Yemen</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Algeria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Egypt</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Egypt</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Algeria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Yemen</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001026T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E4DA1031F935A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="877" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Yemen Reports Arrests of Foreign-Born Arabs in Cole Attack</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN F. BURNS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Burns, John F</byline>
      <dateline>ADEN, Yemen, Oct. 25</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Ali Abdullah Saleh of Yemen says 'preliminary investigations' indicate that at least one of two men who reportedly carried out suicide bombing attack on destroyer Cole was Egyptian and that unspecified number of foreign-born Arabs have been detained on suspicion of assisting in attack; Saleh says inquiry, involving FBI and Yemeni investigators, has led to tentative conclusion that suspects belong to Islamic militant group, Islamic Jihad; says they are from Yemen, Egypt, Algeria and other Arab states (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Ali Abdullah Saleh of Yemen said today that ''preliminary investigations'' indicated that at least one of the two men who reportedly carried out a suicide bombing attack on the destroyer Cole was an Egyptian and that an unspecified number of ''Yemenis, Egyptians, Algerians'' and other foreign-born Arabs had been detained on suspicion of assisting in the attack.</p>
        <p>Mr. Saleh said the inquiry, involving the United States Federal Bureau of Investigation and Yemeni investigators, had led to a tentative conclusion that the suspects belonged to an Islamic militant group that he named as the Islamic Jihad. His remarks echoed comments that he and American officials made last week.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Ali Abdullah Saleh of Yemen said today that ''preliminary investigations'' indicated that at least one of the two men who reportedly carried out a suicide bombing attack on the destroyer Cole was an Egyptian and that an unspecified number of ''Yemenis, Egyptians, Algerians'' and other foreign-born Arabs had been detained on suspicion of assisting in the attack.</p>
        <p>Mr. Saleh said the inquiry, involving the United States Federal Bureau of Investigation and Yemeni investigators, had led to a tentative conclusion that the suspects belonged to an Islamic militant group that he named as the Islamic Jihad. His remarks echoed comments that he and American officials made last week.</p>
        <p>He identified the group as Arabs who joined the American-backed Muslim guerrillas that drove Soviet forces from Afghanistan in the 1980's, many of whom later took refuge in Yemen and formed Islamic terrorist groups.</p>
        <p>''Those held are from the Islamic Jihad organization,'' Mr. Saleh said. ''They are Yemenis, Egyptians, Algerians or from other Arab states.''</p>
        <p>His reference to the Islamic Jihad offered no other details beyond the observation that Yemen, despite having deported members of the Islamic Jihad to their own countries, still had ''pockets remaining in hiding, dressed in Yemeni clothes.''</p>
        <p>''We don't know what the investigation will turn up in the coming days,'' Mr. Saleh said. ''But things look good, and the investigation results are promising.''</p>
        <p>American terrorism experts here said Mr. Saleh appeared to be referring to a group known as the Egyptian Islamic Jihad, one of the deadliest in a network of Islamic terrorist organizations in the Middle East, Europe and North America. It has been linked to the World Trade Center bombing in New York in 1993 and to Osama bin Laden, the Saudi exile accused of masterminding the bombings of two United States embassies in Africa in 1998.</p>
        <p>Mr. bin Laden, the son of a construction tycoon who is in his mid-40's, had been named by American officials here as one of the leading suspects in the Cole attack.</p>
        <p>But the officials said that was based less on any hard evidence and more on his past record, including a warning that he made on a videotape this year of fresh attacks on American forces. The tape was broadcast on an Arab satellite television network three weeks before the attack on the Cole.</p>
        <p>Standing beside Mr. bin Laden on the tape as he made the threat were two Egyptians who are widely believed to be among his closest associates, Ayman al-Zawahiri and Rifai Ahmed Taha. American intelligence has identified Mr. Taha as a leading figure in an armed Egyptian terrorist group, Jamaa Islamiya.</p>
        <p>In his interview today, Mr. Saleh said, ''The man who carried out the bombing was an Egyptian national, according to eyewitnesses and preliminary investigations.''</p>
        <p>The president appeared to be referring to one of the two men aboard a white motorized skiff that American officials say skirted the Cole's port side and detonated an explosive cargo as the destroyer was moored, refueling, at 11:18 a.m. on Oct. 12.</p>
        <p>Yemeni investigators said today that investigation included a 12-year-old's leading the police an abandoned vehicle and trailer next to a remote boat slip on the Bay of Aden, six miles from the attack on the Cole.  The boy told the police that he had been tipped $12.50 to watch the vehicle and trailer by two Arabic-speaking men, one heavily bearded and wearing glasses and the other clean shaven with darker skin, before they launched the boat on Oct. 12.</p>
        <p>Yemen reportedly has more than 60 people under arrest with direct or indirect links to the bombing, including 40 from outside Yemen. The people in custody apparently include three Yemenis seized today in a raid on a safe house known as Al Tawahi above the harbor.</p>
        <p>Yemeni investigators said they were holding three people believed to have played a role, wittingly or unwittingly, in helping the bombers. They included a welder and a carpenter in the suburb of Little Aden who were said to have visited another safe house that the bombers used. The carpenter was said to have confessed to having helped build a false wood floor to cover the explosives believed to have been concealed in the skiff.</p>
        <p>At least one Somali, and possibly as many as 10, were said to have been arrested last week in Taiz Province, 60 miles northwest of Aden, where registration papers in the name of a Somali were issued for an abandoned vehicle that is suspected of having been used in the attack.</p>
        <p>One account by Yemeni officials involved in the investigation said a Somali had confessed to having taken money from two men to buy the vehicle and register it in her name. Somalia, across the Gulf of Aden on the Horn of Africa, has been a source of a large influx of refugees to Aden in recent years, partly because of the civil war there.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
