<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Method Expected for Seeking Donations to Aid Parks</title>
    <meta content="26PARK$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242090"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lipton, Eric</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leisure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001026T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E2D81031F935A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="875" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Method Expected for Seeking Donations to Aid Parks</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC LIPTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lipton, Eric</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York City officials concede that informal system of soliciting donations from corporations and other private groups that hold events in public parks was flawed and vulnerable to abuse; say they plan to revamp it; approximately a dozen nonprofit groups that benefit city parks are given money each year that is donated to city by corporations or other organizations that hold events in park (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>City officials conceded yesterday that the informal system of soliciting donations from corporations and other private groups that hold events in public parks was flawed and vulnerable to abuse, and said they would revamp it.</p>
        <p>Without written guidelines or a fee schedule, donations are routinely solicited by staff members at the city's Department of Parks and Recreation and then given to one of about a dozen nonprofit groups that assist city parks, like the City Parks Foundation and the Central Park Conservancy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>City officials conceded yesterday that the informal system of soliciting donations from corporations and other private groups that hold events in public parks was flawed and vulnerable to abuse, and said they would revamp it.</p>
        <p>Without written guidelines or a fee schedule, donations are routinely solicited by staff members at the city's Department of Parks and Recreation and then given to one of about a dozen nonprofit groups that assist city parks, like the City Parks Foundation and the Central Park Conservancy.</p>
        <p>''There is a recognition that the way it was being done was simply wrong,'' Council Speaker Peter F. Vallone said yesterday. ''It may have been well intended. But you can't have well-meaning people collecting money on behalf of the city and then spending it in the dark.'' Members of Mr. Vallone's staff added that he and the Giuliani administration had an ''agreement in principle'' to revise the system.</p>
        <p>The process of requesting money for use of the parks first became the subject of intense criticism last month, after the dispute with the National Museum of Catholic Art and History, which wanted to hold a fund-raising event at an East Harlem Park. The event's organizers said that they had not been told about the donation requirement until the last minute.</p>
        <p>When the group refused to honor the request -- until an anonymous donor stepped in -- city officials including Mr. Vallone came to the museum's defense, calling the demand ''an absolute outrage'' that ''bordered on a shakedown.''</p>
        <p>Henry J. Stern, the city parks commissioner, ultimately apologized for the way the donation request had been handled.</p>
        <p>City officials said yesterday that they could not estimate how much the donations amounted to each year. But they did release a list of the 62 donations made so far this year, totaling $1.1 million, to one of the largest of the charities, the City Parks Foundation.</p>
        <p>They ranged from the $50,000 donated for use of the Passannante ball field on Houston Street for five days last month for a Marc Jacobs fashion show to the $20,000 paid to set up the Schick Shave Shack in July at Washington Square Park.</p>
        <p>Payments for some events have been as high as $1 million, which the promoters of the Sting concert in  Central Park contributed, officials said.</p>
        <p>No one has questioned making private groups, for the most part, pay the city for the privilege of using the parks, particularly if the use benefits a for-profit organization, or in cases when the public is prevented from using a park.</p>
        <p>What has come under fire is the ''arbitrary numbers at the 11th hour'' that determine the size of a contribution, one Council official said.</p>
        <p>The donations also compensate the city for any damage that has to be repaired, and City Council officials said that they had no documented knowledge of any misuse of donated funds.</p>
        <p>After the dispute with the museum, officials from the Giuliani administration and the City Council agreed to work on a revised system of handling the requests.</p>
        <p>''It will let people know, as early as possible, what is going to be involved in holding an event in a city park,'' said Robert Lawson, a parks spokesman. ''We want to avoid any misunderstandings or any last-minute issues that might come up.</p>
        <p>The new guidelines, which City Council officials said they soon expected to see, at least in draft form, would take into account displacement of the public, the extent of the commercial nature of an event, the physical impact it would have on a park and its duration, in deciding on  a requested donation or fee.</p>
        <p>City Council officials said they would also like better controls over how the money is spent. Now, the money is usually allocated to make improvements in parks in a neighborhood near where the event is held.</p>
        <p>DONATIONS TO NONPROFITS  Funds for Groups That Benefit Parks</p>
        <p>Approximately a dozen nonprofit groups that benefit city parks are given money each year that is donated to the city by corporations or other organizations that hold events at parks. The donations can be as much as $1 million for a single event. The City Parks Foundation  collected $1.1 million in donations this year from 62 events. Here is a list of the top 10 contributions.*</p>
        <p>1. Worldwide Senior Tennis Tour. Wollman Rink in Central Park, June 13 to 19.  $75,000</p>
        <p>2. Doctors Without Borders, Central Park, Van Cortlandt Park and Prospect Park, Sept. 16 to  Oct 2.  $50,000</p>
        <p>3. Marc Jacobs Fashion Show, Passannante Ballfield, Greenwich Village, Sept. 15 to 20.  $50,000</p>
        <p>4. Lands' End -- My Virtual Model Tour, Union Square Park, Oct. 17 to 19.  $50,000</p>
        <p>5. Toy Fair, Worth Square, Feb. 10 to 17.  $50,000</p>
        <p>6. General Motors, Central Park, April 17 to 18.  $45,000</p>
        <p>7. Discovery Channel's Crocodile Hunter, Madison Square Park, Feb 14.  $45,000</p>
        <p>8. AIDS Walk, Central Park, May 21.  $40,0000</p>
        <p>9. Alteon Web Systems, Battery Park, April 25.  $30,000</p>
        <p>10. Silicon Alley Street Fair, Union Square Park, May 21.  $30,000</p>
        <p>* There were three other $30,000 donations. City officials said yesterday that they could not provide a comprehensive list of all donations made to compensate for park use.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
