<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CALENDAR</title>
    <meta content="07CAL.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228499"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000907T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE2DD1439F934A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="710" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CALENDAR</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Glassmaker's Art  American Craft Museum, 40 West 53rd Street; (212) 956-3535.</p>
        <p>''Memories of Murano: American Glass Artists in Venice,'' an exhibition of works by 20 contemporary artists, starts on Wednesday and runs through Jan. 7. The show explores the influence that glassmaking techniques developed on Murano, the Venetian island, have had on American artists who have worked at Venetian glass factories since 1959. Artists in the exhibition include Dale Chihuly, James Carpenter, Micheal Nourot, Benjamin Moore and Tina Aufiero, all of whom learned techniques like making glass with a mosaic look, fusing hot glass sections to form vessels, cold and hot decorative techniques and methods of mixing custom colors.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Glassmaker's Art  American Craft Museum, 40 West 53rd Street; (212) 956-3535.</p>
        <p>''Memories of Murano: American Glass Artists in Venice,'' an exhibition of works by 20 contemporary artists, starts on Wednesday and runs through Jan. 7. The show explores the influence that glassmaking techniques developed on Murano, the Venetian island, have had on American artists who have worked at Venetian glass factories since 1959. Artists in the exhibition include Dale Chihuly, James Carpenter, Micheal Nourot, Benjamin Moore and Tina Aufiero, all of whom learned techniques like making glass with a mosaic look, fusing hot glass sections to form vessels, cold and hot decorative techniques and methods of mixing custom colors.</p>
        <p>Open Tuesday through Sunday, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m. (until 8 p.m. on Thursdays). Admission is $5; for students and those 65 and older, $2.50; members and children 12 and under, free.</p>
        <p>Lincoln Center Crafts  Plazas at Lincoln Center, Columbus Avenue at 64th Street; (973) 746-0091.</p>
        <p>More than 200 artisans will offer porcelain vases, wooden clocks, woven jackets, leather handbags, gold jewelry, glass bottles and other items in a craft show and sale on Saturday and Sunday, and again on Sept. 16 and 17. Open 11 a.m. to 7 p.m. Free.</p>
        <p>An Architect's Work  Max Protetch, 511 West 22nd Street; (212) 633-6999.</p>
        <p>The work of the architect Samuel Mockbee, who is based in Jackson, Miss., and Memphis, will be the subject of an exhibition of photographs, paintings and models from Saturday through Oct. 21. Mr. Mockbee, the recipient of a 2000 MacArthur Foundation grant, runs a program at Auburn University in Alabama, where he and his architecture students design and build homes for local residents, many of whom are poor. Several of these projects, which are undertaken pro bono, will be included in the exhibition. Open Tuesday through Saturday, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m. No charge.</p>
        <p>Tree Care Classes  Trees New York, 51 Chambers Street, Suite 1412A; (212) 227-1887.</p>
        <p>A 12-hour course on caring for New York's street trees, with lectures and a hands-on Saturday outing, will be offered in all five boroughs. The lectures, from 6 to 8 p.m., start Sept. 21 in Brooklyn; Sept. 25 in the Bronx; Oct. 3 and Oct. 12 in Manhattan, and Oct. 11 in Queens and Staten Island. The fee for the course is $80. Reservations are required.</p>
        <p>Trees New York, a nonprofit organization, will sponsor a lecture on the Asian long-horned beetle on Sept. 20 at 6 p.m., at the Arsenal in Central Park, Fifth Avenue and 64th Street. Reservations are required. No charge.</p>
        <p>One Man's Skyline  New-York Historical Society, Central Park West at 77th Street; (212) 873-3400.</p>
        <p>An exhibition of drawings and photographs about buildings designed by Cass Gilbert, including the Custom House (1899), the Woolworth Building (1913) and the United States Army Supply Base on the Brooklyn waterfront (1918), opens on Tuesday and runs through Jan. 21.</p>
        <p>Among the programs to be offered with the exhibition, which are free with museum admission, are a discussion on public architecture, Oct. 10 at 6:30 p.m.; a daylong symposium on Gilbert, Oct. 14, from 10 a.m. to 2 p.m.; and a discussion on the past and future of the New York skyline, Oct. 17, at 6:30 p.m. Reservations are required for programs. The museum is open Tuesday through Sunday, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. Suggested donation is $5; children and those 65 and older, $3.</p>
        <p>Antiques on Park  Seventh Regiment Armory, 643 Park Avenue (66th Street); (212) 472-1180.</p>
        <p>An antiques show and sale of furniture, lamps, rugs, maps, jewelry, china and clocks by 100 dealers starts on Wednesday, from 4 to 9 p.m., and continues Sept. 14 through 16, noon to 9 p.m., and on Sept. 17, noon to 6 p.m. Admission is $10.</p>
        <p>Not Just for Pandas  LongHouse Reserve, 133 Hands Creek Road, off Cedar Street, East Hampton, N.Y.; (631) 329-3568.</p>
        <p>On Saturday, from 10 a.m. to 4 p.m., a bamboo festival and a luncheon will offer talks on growing bamboo, a demonstration of bamboo in flower arrangements and a display of bamboo artwork and toys. Reservations are required. Fee, with lunch, $45; without lunch, $25.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
