<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>2 Cigarette Makers Are Said to Discuss Settling All Smokers' Suits</title>
    <meta content="Y07TOB$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/07/national/07TOBA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228569"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000907T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE2DE1539F934A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="444" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>2 Cigarette Makers Are Said to Discuss Settling All Smokers' Suits</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARRY MEIER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two of the nation's major cigarette companies have been engaged in preliminary talks with plaintiffs' lawyers as part of a bid to reach a nationwide settlement of all smokers' claims against the tobacco industry, lawyers involved with the talks said yesterday.</p>
        <p>Spokesmen for the two companies, Lorillard Tobacco and the Liggett Group, declined to comment,  Other cigarette makers said they had no intention of settling.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Two of the nation's major cigarette companies have been engaged in preliminary talks with plaintiffs' lawyers as part of a bid to reach a nationwide settlement of all smokers' claims against the tobacco industry, lawyers involved with the talks said yesterday.</p>
        <p>Spokesmen for the two companies, Lorillard Tobacco and the Liggett Group, declined to comment,  Other cigarette makers said they had no intention of settling.</p>
        <p>The disclosure was made as a federal judge in Brooklyn issued an order yesterday that could provide a mechanism for reaching a global settlement of claims by smokers.</p>
        <p>Judge Jack B. Weinstein of Federal District Court told the parties to come to court Monday prepared to consider a suggestion by plaintiffs' lawyers to spin off claims for punitive damages against cigarette makers into a nationwide class-action suit, with separate trials for claims for compensatory damages.</p>
        <p>Such a division would be unique. Plaintiffs' lawyers, in pressing for a separate punitive damages suit, are apparently seeking to play on the companies' biggest concern.</p>
        <p>Earlier this year, a state jury in Florida issued a $144.8 billion punitive award to members of a class-action lawsuit brought on behalf of all Florida residents who had been made sick by smoking. The companies have appealed that verdict.</p>
        <p>Months ago, Judge Weinstein made a bid to create a class action for all claims, but the companies rejected his suggestions. Spokesmen for the nation's three biggest cigarette makers -- the Philip Morris Companies, J. R. Reynolds Tobacco and the Brown &amp; Williamson Tobacco Company -- also criticized the latest plan.</p>
        <p>''We have no intention whatsoever of settling these lawsuits and we are not discussing settlement with plaintiffs' attorneys or anyone else,'' said Mark Smith, a spokesman for Brown &amp; Williamson, a unit of British American Tobacco P.L.C.</p>
        <p>William S. Ohlemeyer, associate general counsel for Philip Morris, rejected the proposal, saying ''we intend to vigorously oppose any attempts by this federal court to consolidate these cases.''</p>
        <p>In recent years, tobacco companies agreed to pay $246 billion to settle suits brought by state attorneys general. But that settlement did not foreclose claims by individual smokers, as in Florida.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for Liggett, a unit of the Vector Group that is the smallest of the major cigarette makers, declined to comment. Liggett has previously sought to settle litigation against it.</p>
        <p>But the apparent interest of Lorillard Tobacco, a unit of the Loews Corporation, in settlement talks comes as a surprise. A Lorillard spokesman said it was not company practice to comment on litigation or potential litigation.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
