<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>World Briefing</title>
    <meta content="Y07BRI$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/07/world/07BRIE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228601"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000907T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E0DC1539F934A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1040" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>World Briefing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled By Jeanne Moore</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>FRANCE: FUEL STALEMATE -- Prime Minister Lionel Jospin, left, ruled out any new concessions to trucking unions blockading fuel supplies that have caused gas stations around the country to run dry and disrupted air traffic. He spoke after France's largest trucking union rejected a government proposal to lower diesel taxes and reimburse truckers for fuel costs. The union said the government offer did not go far enough.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>FRANCE: FUEL STALEMATE -- Prime Minister Lionel Jospin, left, ruled out any new concessions to trucking unions blockading fuel supplies that have caused gas stations around the country to run dry and disrupted air traffic. He spoke after France's largest trucking union rejected a government proposal to lower diesel taxes and reimburse truckers for fuel costs. The union said the government offer did not go far enough.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>NORTHERN IRELAND: BOMBING INQUEST OPENS -- An inquest into the 1998 car bombing in Omagh that killed 29 people and injured more than 300 opened with witnesses calling on members of the Real I.R.A. -- the dissident Republican group that took responsibility for the act but said it was a mistake -- to come forward and ''clear their consciences.'' The police say they know who the bombers are but do not have enough evidence to bring them to trial. The inquest is expected to last four weeks.</p>
        <p>Warren Hoge (NYT)</p>
        <p>GERMANY: EASTERNERS PARDONED -- Two former members of the East German Politburo, Gunter Schabowski and Gunther Kleiber, who were jailed in December for their role in East Germany's shoot-to-kill policy at the Berlin Wall, were pardoned by Mayor Eberhard Diepgen of Berlin. Justice officials said they would be freed on Oct. 2, after serving less than a third of their three-year sentences. They said the pardon was a symbolic gesture to help rehabilite those who had apologized for their role in the East German state.</p>
        <p>Victor Homola (NYT)</p>
        <p>AFRICA</p>
        <p>CONGO: KILLINGS IN GORILLA HAVEN -- Hutu militiamen armed with machetes and guns attacked a gorilla sanctuary in southeastern Congo, killing at least 10 people, officials said. The attack came a day after militias killed six people nearby. The 1.5 million-acre park has been closed to tourists since 1998, when rebels backed by neighboring Rwanda and Uganda took up arms against Congo's president, Laurent Kabila. Park officials are able to patrol only 10 percent of the forests.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>ZIMBABWE: LEGAL CHALLENGE -- The Commercial Farmers Union said it would file a Supreme Court action challenging President Robert Mugabe's power to seize white-owned farms with no obligation to pay compensation. Since June, Mr. Mugabe has served notice of intentions to acquire 1,952 of 3,041 white-owned farms he has earmarked to resettle landless blacks. The government has also passed legislation absolving it of responsibility to pay compensation for the land if Britain, the former colonial power, does not provide the funds.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>THE AMERICAS</p>
        <p>ARGENTINA: HUNGER STRIKE -- Thirteen Marxist guerrillas who were convicted on terrorism charges related to the attack on an army barracks in 1989 went on their second hunger strike this year demanding a court appeal in their case. The attack by the tiny All for the Fatherland band on the La Tablada base outside Buenos Aires left 39 dead. The rebels say there were only trying to halt a coup, a claim disputed by most historians and political analysts.</p>
        <p>Clifford Krauss (NYT)</p>
        <p>CHILE: CONSCRIPTION TO END -- President Ricardo Lagos announced that the armed forces will phase out the draft and become a voluntary force by the year 2005, in a move that potentially will impact the lives of 27,000 young people every year. The high command supports the new policy as a way to modernize the military.</p>
        <p>Clifford Krauss (NYT)</p>
        <p>MIDDLE EAST</p>
        <p>GAZA: PALESTINIAN PROTEST -- Hamas, the leading Islamic fundamentalist group in the Palestinian entity, and Islamic Holy War, a smaller group, will boycott this weekend's meeting of the Palestinian Central Council. The two organizations' spokesmen said they expected the council to defer declaration of a Palestinian state and endorse a continuation of the peace effort, which they reject.</p>
        <p>Deborah Sontag (NYT)</p>
        <p>ASIA</p>
        <p>JAPAN: MARINE SENTENCED -- A United States marine was convicted in a military court and sentenced to a two-year jail term for molesting a Japanese schoolgirl on the island of Okinawa, a crime that led to local protests against American military bases. Lance Cpl. Kenny K. Titcomb, 19, was found guilty of molesting the 14-year girl on July 3 after entering her home as she slept, a military spokeswoman said. Corporal Titcomb was tried in a military court because he was expected to face a tougher sentence there than in a Japanese court, which could only have tried him as a juvenile.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>AFGHANISTAN: TALIBAN GAINS -- After fierce fighting, the ruling Taliban militia has captured the critical northeastern city of Taloqan, an opposition stronghold. Taloqan has changed hands several times during the long civil war. If the Taliban can hold on, they will have a significant victory over the forces of Ahmad Shah Massoud. The opposition now controls only a neighboring province and small pockets in a few other northern provinces.</p>
        <p>Barry Bearak (NYT)</p>
        <p>INDIA: HOSTAGE TALKS BREAK DOWN -- Talks with the criminal Veerappan, who has been holding the movie star Rajkumar captive for five weeks, have broken down. R. R. Gopal, an emissary between the two sides, said the bandit is sticking to his demands for the release of dozens of his jailed comrades -- something state authorities have been willing to do but the courts have forbidden.</p>
        <p>Barry Bearak (NYT)</p>
        <p>KASHMIR: LETHAL DECADE -- The latest official death toll in a decade of violence is 33,854, according to a police document reported by Agence France-Presse. This includes 19,781 civilians, 11,757 militants and 2,316 security forces. Separatists claim the numbers understate the carnage by at least half.</p>
        <p>Barry Bearak (NYT)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
