<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="07DIGE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228563"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000907T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507EEDF1539F934A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="652" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tire Hearings Scrutinize Firestone and Ford Motor  Newly released documents provided additional evidence that Bridgestone/Firestone and possibly Ford Motor knew about a pattern of tire failures long before a recall was announced in August.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Tire Hearings Scrutinize Firestone and Ford Motor  Newly released documents provided additional evidence that Bridgestone/Firestone and possibly Ford Motor knew about a pattern of tire failures long before a recall was announced in August.</p>
        <p>The disclosures came during a day of hearings on Capitol Hill at which lawmakers called for a larger budget for safety regulators and proposed federal criminal penalties for any future cases in which companies might be found to have knowingly sold products with lethal defects. [Page A1.]</p>
        <p>F.T.C. Investigates Drug Companies  The Federal Trade Commission said that it was investigating whether Bristol-Myers Squibb and American Bioscience colluded to keep the lower-cost generic version of Bristol's cancer drug, Taxol, off the market. The Food and Drug Administration gave Ivax, a generic drug maker, tentative approval last month to sell generic Taxol. But regulators said they could not let Ivax sell the drug because of a complex legal agreement between Bristol-Myers and American Bioscience. The F.T.C. said in court papers that the terms of the agreement ''raise potential competitive issues.'' Shares of Ivax rose $7.81, to $39. [C6.]</p>
        <p>Novell to Eliminate 900 Jobs  Novell said that it would eliminate 900 jobs, or about 16 percent of its worldwide work force, to reduce costs. The company said it would take a pretax charge of $40 million to $50 million in its fourth quarter. [C8.]</p>
        <p>Nasdaq Slides Again, but Dow Rises  A sell-off in semiconductor stocks drove the Nasdaq composite index down 129.84 points, or 3.1 percent, to 4,013.34. Other markets fared better, largely because of strength in a handful of financial stocks and in oil shares. The Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index fell 14.83 points, or 1 percent, to 1,492.25. The Dow Jones industrial average advanced 50.03 points, or 0.4 percent, to 11,310.64. [C10.]</p>
        <p>Book Agent Leaves William Morris  Robert Gottlieb, one of the most powerful agents in book publishing, resigned as head of the William Morris agency's New York literary group to start his own agency and multimedia management company. [C7.]</p>
        <p>Productivity Up 5.7% in Quarter  Productivity, a measure of how much a worker produces for each hour on the job, grew at a 5.7 percent annual rate from April through June, up from the 5.3 percent pace originally estimated, new data showed. [C2.]</p>
        <p>Time Warner Buys Africana.com  Facing an uncertain climate for Internet start-ups, the founders of Africana.com, the Harvard University professors Henry Louis Gates Jr., left, and Kwame Anthony Appiah, have sold their venture to Time Warner. Professor Gates said the deal would help keep the Web site, one of many seeking a worldwide audience of African descent, alive. ''The revenue model was slow to develop, let's put it that way,'' he said. ''I would have become worried about its future by next year unless there was some dramatic turnaround.'' Terms of the deal were not announced. [C2.]</p>
        <p>Heinz Issues a Profit Warning  H. J. Heinz said that its second-quarter profit would be lower than analysts expected, and its shares fell nearly 5 percent, to $35.44. [C2.]</p>
        <p>Europe and U.S. in Trade Standoff  The European Union and the United States are holding fast in several trade disputes, their continued standoff threatening a more punishing confrontation between the two trading blocs, the world's biggest. [C4.]</p>
        <p>Good Times May Fuel Regulation  In the past, bad times might be expected to lead to new regulations and protectionism as people turn to government as a source of security. That may no longer be true. In the United States, new regulations tend to come after prolonged periods of prosperity. When times are good, restrictions look relatively cheap. Virginia Postrel: Economic Scene. [C2.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
