<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>PUBLIC LIVES</title>
    <meta content="07PUBL$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/07/nyregion/07PUBL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228640"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Malpractice</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parties (Social)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Macfarquhar, Neil</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Andrews, Julie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barnes, Julian</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kessler, Scott M (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Public Lives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Malpractice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parties (Social)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000907T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04EEDB1539F934A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="659" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>PUBLIC LIVES</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NEIL MacFARQUHAR with Julian Barnes</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barnes, Julian; Macfarquhar, Neil</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Public Lives column discusses how UN meeting has resulted in overload on diplomatic party circuit; singer Julie Andrews settles her medical malpractice suit against throat specialist Dr Scott M Kessler; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>An Overload On a Party Circuit</p>
        <p>The powwow of presidents and other potentates at the United Nations is not just causing gridlock on the city's streets but also overloading the diplomatic party circuit.</p>
        <p>The American ambassador to the United Nations, RICHARD C. HOLBROOKE, had a dinner on Tuesday night honoring the president of Mali, ALPHA OUMAR KONARE, whose country also holds the presidency of the Security Council this month.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>An Overload On a Party Circuit</p>
        <p>The powwow of presidents and other potentates at the United Nations is not just causing gridlock on the city's streets but also overloading the diplomatic party circuit.</p>
        <p>The American ambassador to the United Nations, RICHARD C. HOLBROOKE, had a dinner on Tuesday night honoring the president of Mali, ALPHA OUMAR KONARE, whose country also holds the presidency of the Security Council this month.</p>
        <p>President Konare decided to deliver his after-dinner remarks, hailing renewed Unites States attention to Africa, in French. With no official translators on hand, Mr. Holbrooke's wife, the writer KATI MARTON, stepped up to provide the simultaneous English version for guests like the REV. JESSE JACKSON, ED BRADLEY from CBS News and several African-American congressmen, including DONALD M. PAYNE of New Jersey.</p>
        <p>The United States Secretary of State, MADELEINE K. ALBRIGHT, and one of her predecessors, HENRY A. KISSINGER, swept in late from another soiree to catch the end of the toast.</p>
        <p>Not everyone in New York City is participating in the festivities, especially its most renowned nondiplomat, MAYOR RUDOLPH W. GIULIANI. Asked yesterday if he was invited to a bash being thrown  by President Clinton, the mayor said he was too busy making sure that everyone's limousine arrived securely and on time to bother attending himself.</p>
        <p>''And given my political views and everything else, I'm not sure that it would have been the nicest evening,'' the mayor said, adding, ''And you got some people there who have murdered a lot of people.'' He did not elaborate.</p>
        <p>Another New York politician, GOV. GEORGE E. PATAKI, was one of the featured speakers at a fete for businessmen at the Jacob Javits Convention Center on Tuesday given by China's vice premier, QIAN QICHEN.</p>
        <p>Governor Pataki told the audience that he planned to go on a trade mission to China this year, noting that China is the state's sixth-largest trading partner, with $2 billion in trade annually. ''We intend to seize this opportunity, so economic opportunities between New York State and China grow stronger and stronger,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Asked about China's human rights record, Mr. Pataki responded: ''It is important we use these ties to reiterate our respect of the rule of law and respect for human rights. I think stronger ties will lead to greater political freedom.'' His aides seemed to think facing traffic might be a better bet than any more questions on that score and hustled him away.</p>
        <p>Singer Settles Malpractice Suit</p>
        <p>Lawyers for JULIE ANDREWS announced yesterday that the singer had settled her medical malpractice lawsuit against a Manhattan throat specialist, DR. SCOTT M. KESSLER.</p>
        <p>''I am delighted to have settled this case in a favorable manner and am glad to close this chapter on an event which was unfortunate for all concerned,'' Ms. Andrews, 63, said in a statement.</p>
        <p>Her lawyers, ORIN SNYDER and PETER PARCHER, said the settlement reached last month specified that the terms could not be disclosed. Dr. Kessler declined to comment.</p>
        <p>The case had been scheduled to go to trial Tuesday before JUDGE LEWIS A. KAPLAN in Federal District Court in Manhattan. The settlement was reached privately, without arbitration.</p>
        <p>''She is still having profound difficulties singing as a result of the surgery,'' Mr. Snyder said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Andrews was starring in ''Victor/Victoria'' on Broadway in 1997 when she underwent surgery at Mount Sinai Medical Center to remove noncancerous nodules in her throat. The lawsuit alleged that she was not told that the operation carried risks of permanent hoarseness and other complications that might leave her unable to sing.</p>
        <p>At the time, her husband, BLAKE EDWARDS, was widely quoted as saying that her voice had been all but ruined.</p>
        <p>Initially, Mount Sinai and DR. JEFFREY D. LIBIN, Dr. Kessler's partner, were named in the suit, but Ms. Andrews later agreed to drop them.</p>
        <p>NEIL MacFARQUHAR with Julian Barnes</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
