<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cone Hopes to Return Before the Season Ends</title>
    <meta content="07CONE$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/07/sports/07CONE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228595"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olney, Buster</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cone, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000907T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02E3DC1539F934A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="912" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cone Hopes to Return Before the Season Ends</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olney, Buster</byline>
      <dateline>KANSAS CITY, Mo., Sept. 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Status of injured New York Yankees pitcher David Cone discussed (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>His left shoulder throbbing, and tired from a night of trying to sleep in a chair, David Cone had an M.R.I. test today and, medically, the news was good. The test showed that his dislocated, nonthrowing shoulder, pushed back into place after being hurt in Tuesday's game, did not appear to have much damage beyond the injury itself.</p>
        <p>But Cone acknowledged that he was pushing himself to keep a professional demeanor and to focus on what he needs to do pitch again this season -- and at the same time, suppress thoughts of all the possibilities inherent when a 37-year-old athlete is seriously injured.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>His left shoulder throbbing, and tired from a night of trying to sleep in a chair, David Cone had an M.R.I. test today and, medically, the news was good. The test showed that his dislocated, nonthrowing shoulder, pushed back into place after being hurt in Tuesday's game, did not appear to have much damage beyond the injury itself.</p>
        <p>But Cone acknowledged that he was pushing himself to keep a professional demeanor and to focus on what he needs to do pitch again this season -- and at the same time, suppress thoughts of all the possibilities inherent when a 37-year-old athlete is seriously injured.</p>
        <p>Cone will return to New York on Friday for treatment, and he believes he will pitch again this year. But the chances that he will pitch to get enough of a look for a spot on the postseason roster seem remote, given what's left of the regular season.</p>
        <p>''We'll start a rehab program, and in seven days re-evaluate where we are,'' Cone said. ''I don't know how I'm going to feel, but I've got to try to get ready to pitch again. What happens after that, I don't know. Postseason roster? Who knows. I'm obviously in a backup position right now, but who knows what's going to happen.''</p>
        <p>Cone dislocated his left shoulder in the third inning of Tuesday's game against the Royals. Chasing a bunt that was popped into the air, Cone dived and landed on his left elbow, the force of his 200-pound body knocking his shoulder out of place.</p>
        <p>The seriousness of the injury was apparent right away to nearby teammates. A doctor struggled for 15 to 20 minutes to move Cone's shoulder back into place; some teammates in the trainer's room had to leave. ''It's just such a helpless feeling, knowing that he's in so much pain,'' Yankees Manager Joe Torre said.</p>
        <p>In practical terms, Cone's injury is not a major blow to the Yankees, as his aneurysm could have been in 1996, as his right shoulder trouble was in 1997.</p>
        <p>The Yankees will use four starters in the postseason, and even before Cone dislocated his shoulder, he probably had only a slim chance of being part of that rotation. Roger Clemens, Andy Pettitte, Orlando Hernandez and Denny Neagle will probably start.</p>
        <p>Cone's best chance to play might have been as a long reliever.</p>
        <p>But Cone is among the handful of players, along with Bernie Williams and Paul O'Neill and a few others, who have been the core of the Yankees' rebirth in the last six years. He is highly respected for his competitiveness, and for his ability to win big games. Torre would undoubtedly love any excuse to include Cone on his postseason roster.</p>
        <p>Even if Cone comes back quickly, however -- say he pitches again in two weeks or so -- he would have only one or two appearances to show he would be more useful than Dwight Gooden or Ramiro Mendoza or the left-hander Randy Choate. There is also the chance that another starter could get injured.</p>
        <p>''You need to have him out there,  and have him pitch,'' Torre said of his evaluation of Cone.</p>
        <p>Within a couple of hours after he was hurt, Cone began thinking about how his left shoulder affects his pitching. His advantage is that when he winds up, Cone does not draw his hands above his shoulders. But his left arm must function to the point that he can raise his glove and protect himself from a line drive, and more to the point, be effective.</p>
        <p>''How much do I need this left arm when I'm throwing a baseball? You need it a lot,'' Cone said, asking and answering his own question. ''Your left arm is your base. It's important. Obviously, it's not as important as your throwing arm, but you need everything in baseball -- your timing, your rhythm.''</p>
        <p>Cone paused and smiled. ''I don't know, maybe it'll help me,'' he said.</p>
        <p>George Steinbrenner, the Yankees' principal owner, called Cone today, relating how he separated his own shoulder playing football in high school. Teammates have been supportive, Cone said.</p>
        <p>But he seemed sad. He wants to pitch, something he has done most of his life, something he won't do for much longer.</p>
        <p>Having rebounded from three months without a victory to go 3-1 in his last five starts, Cone expects to pitch next year, although it may not be for the Yankees, with his one-year contract about to expire.</p>
        <p>''When the season is over, I've got to do some soul-searching,'' he said. ''It's also a question of finding a job. There's not a big market out there for 38-year-old, 4-11 pitchers.''</p>
        <p>He was talking about his age and his record.</p>
        <p>''I'm realistic, as well,'' he said. ''I also know that in my heart of hearts, I can still pitch.</p>
        <p>''I've still got to keep myself geared up for the chance to come back, and maybe even a long shot to pitch in the playoffs. First round, second round, who knows? The other part of me says, maybe this isn't going to win. Maybe this is it. You fight it, back and forth. I'm a professional, I've got to do everything I can to be ready.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
