<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Critics Urge Regents to Reject CUNY's Four-Year Master Plan</title>
    <meta content="07CUNY$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/07/nyregion/07CUNY.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228554"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">City University of New York</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arenson, Karen W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000907T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE6DF1539F934A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="711" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Critics Urge Regents to Reject CUNY's Four-Year Master Plan</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KAREN W. ARENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Arenson, Karen W</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Critics of City University of New York urged State Board of Regents to reject university's master plan for next four years, saying it would turn CUNY into an elite university and shut door on city's most educationally needed students (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Critics of the City University of New York yesterday urged the State Board of Regents to reject the university's master plan for the next four years, saying it would turn CUNY into an elite university and shut the door on the city's most educationally needy students.</p>
        <p>At a public hearing, CUNY officials and their supporters, however, said their plan was an effort to salvage the reputation of the university, which has come to be known as a remedial mill for poorly prepared students.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Critics of the City University of New York yesterday urged the State Board of Regents to reject the university's master plan for the next four years, saying it would turn CUNY into an elite university and shut the door on the city's most educationally needy students.</p>
        <p>At a public hearing, CUNY officials and their supporters, however, said their plan was an effort to salvage the reputation of the university, which has come to be known as a remedial mill for poorly prepared students.</p>
        <p>''We have gone in a very short period of time from being an institution adrift to a university on the move,'' said Herman Badillo, CUNY's chairman.</p>
        <p>The 133-page CUNY master plan, a four-year map of the university's direction required by state law, lays out a variety of new steps, including a gradual increase in the proportion of full-time faculty, fostering the development of core curriculums at all of CUNY's 17 undergraduate colleges, upgrading of the university's schools of teacher education, creating an honors program to attract the academically strongest students, and the building of areas of excellence in technical fields.</p>
        <p>The Regents, who were mostly silent during seven hours of testimony from about 80 speakers, said they expected to vote on the plan next week.</p>
        <p>By law, the City University of New York, like the state university, must file a master plan with the State Board of Regents every four years, and usually the plans stir little interest. But the plan CUNY filed in May, which was the subject of the Regents hearing yesterday in a spacious auditorium at the Fashion Institute of Technology, has become the centerpiece of the debate over CUNY's efforts to transform itself. The hearing drew political officials, union officials and civic leaders as well as students, professors and administrators from within CUNY.</p>
        <p>While speakers generally supported some plans, like improving teacher education, they picked apart many others. They said the CUNY plan focused too narrowly on high-tech areas to please business, that it did not call for enough hiring in the liberal arts, that it neglected the education of students to focus on research and that it would redirect money into the most selective colleges at the expense of the community colleges, which still take all students with a high school diploma.</p>
        <p>''This document represents a radical departure from the historic, customary and statutory mission of CUNY,'' said Sandi E. Cooper, a history professor at the College of Staten Island and the CUNY Graduate Center and the former chairwoman of the CUNY faculty. ''Its motivation is not rooted in respect for high standards, as its authors proclaim, but in a mix of business school management mantras married to the conviction that public higher education is primarily a gateway to corporate employment.''</p>
        <p>Strong support for the master plan and CUNY's chancellor, Matthew Goldstein, came from the schools chancellor, Harold O. Levy, who was on the Board of Regents before becoming schools chancellor this year. He noted that as a Regent last November, he had been torn over whether to support CUNY's plan to remove remedial classes from the senior colleges and to bar students who had not passed CUNY's placement tests in English and math. Yesterday he said he no longer had any doubts, and urged the Regents's strong support for the master plan and Chancellor Goldstein.</p>
        <p>''Our institutions share the same fundamental goal -- achieving higher standards for our students, for our faculty and staff, and for public education as a whole,'' he said. ''The university has taken large strides toward increasing standards and accountability.''</p>
        <p>Robert Dottin, a biology professor at Hunter College who runs a center for gene studies there, said the master plan's support for ''centers of academic excellence'' within the university and nationally was a ''sound approach'' and urged its approval.</p>
        <p>''We cannot wait until the entire university agrees with the plan,'' he said. ''It will never happen.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
