<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Feeding the 'Energy Eater'; Atlantic Canada's Oil Boom Helps the Northeastern U.S.</title>
    <meta content="Y07OIL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/07/business/07OIL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228525"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Production</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Production</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terra Nova (Oil Production Vessel)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Canada</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Northeastern States (US)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Newfoundland (Canada)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Nova Scotia (Canada)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Labrador (Canada)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Atlantic Ocean</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brooke, James</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada/Newfoundland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada/Nova Scotia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada/Labrador</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Production</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000907T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E1DA1439F934A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1612" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Feeding the 'Energy Eater'; Atlantic Canada's Oil Boom Helps the Northeastern U.S.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BROOKE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brooke, James</byline>
      <dateline>ST. JOHN'S, Newfoundland</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Atlantic coastal area of Canada is emerging as major source of oil and natural gas, with Northeastern US as its primary customer; Hibernia oil field and Sable gas field are already in production; Terra Nova, $200 million, 14-story oil production vessel will move 220 miles east of St John's, Newfoundland, next spring, lock into place over 400-million-barrel pool of oil, and start pumping 100,000 barrels a day, largely for Northeastern US; Nova Scotia has started sending gas south, and that flow could increase greatly in coming years; Atlantic Canada, from Nova Scotia to Labrador, could prove to be next-generation North Sea or Prudhoe Bay; Newfoundland, long Canada's poorest province, stands to reap biggest benefit; of the 11 oil fields larger than 100 million barrels discovered worldwide since 1979, 4 have been off coast of Newfoundland, on Grand Banks; Newfoundland is in midst of 15-year, $10 billion oil investment plan; by 2004, province will be pumping 400,000 barrels a day, same amount as small OPEC producer; map; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>From this unexpected corner of the North Atlantic, American consumers could soon see a ray of relief from shortages that have kept oil and natural gas prices stubbornly high. But even though the new energy supplies will be welcome, they are not expected to bring prices down soon.</p>
        <p>Next spring, Terra Nova, a $200 million, 14-story oil production vessel will move 220 miles east of here, lock into place over a 400-million-barrel pool of oil, and start pumping 100,000 barrels a day, largely for the Northeastern United States. In addition, Nova Scotia has started sending natural gas south, and that flow could increase greatly in coming years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>From this unexpected corner of the North Atlantic, American consumers could soon see a ray of relief from shortages that have kept oil and natural gas prices stubbornly high. But even though the new energy supplies will be welcome, they are not expected to bring prices down soon.</p>
        <p>Next spring, Terra Nova, a $200 million, 14-story oil production vessel will move 220 miles east of here, lock into place over a 400-million-barrel pool of oil, and start pumping 100,000 barrels a day, largely for the Northeastern United States. In addition, Nova Scotia has started sending natural gas south, and that flow could increase greatly in coming years.</p>
        <p>Atlantic Canada, from Nova Scotia to Labrador, could prove to be the next-generation North Sea or Prudhoe Bay. And Newfoundland, long Canada's poorest province, stands to reap the biggest benefit. Of the 11 oil fields larger than 100 million barrels discovered worldwide since 1979, 4 have been off the coast of Newfoundland, on the Grand Banks.</p>
        <p>Today, the cacophony from 1,300 workers hammering and welding the Terra Nova production vessel near here are drawing attention to two new trends: Americans' growing reliance on Canada for energy, and the future of Atlantic Canada as a major supplier of oil and natural gas to the Northeastern United States.</p>
        <p>While most oil fields outside the Persian Gulf are mature and declining in production, Atlantic Canada's oil industry is taking its baby steps. Of the four major fields offshore here, Hibernia started producing in 1997 and Terra Nova is to start producing early next summer.</p>
        <p>''We have barely touched the Grand Banks,'' said Gary Bruce, vice president for offshore development with Petro-Canada, Canada's second-largest integrated oil company and the lead operator at Terra Nova.</p>
        <p>Newfoundland is in the midst of a 15-year, $10 billion oil investment plan. By 2004, this long-overlooked province is to be pumping 400,000 barrels a day, the same amount as a small OPEC producer like Ecuador. That quantity, to be sure, would meet only a small portion of the average daily United States consumption of nearly 20 million barrels. But unlike Ecuador, Newfoundland is politically stable and no more than three days by tanker from New York.</p>
        <p>Already, Canada is the top supplier to the United States of natural gas and the No. 2 supplier of oil, after Saudi Arabia. During the first half of this year, a 44 percent jump in the value of Canada's oil and gas exports to the United States helped push Canada's June trade surplus with its neighbor to a monthly record of $5.2 billion. Responding to higher prices, Canada's oil production in June was up 7.5 percent from a year earlier, to 2.25 million barrels a day, according to the Canadian Association of Petroleum Producers.</p>
        <p>While Western states have long imported oil and gas from Alberta, Eastern states only started importing natural gas from Nova Scotia's massive gas field in January and oil from Newfoundland's Hibernia field three years ago. By 2005, 40 percent of Canada's conventional oil production is to come from Newfoundland. After half a century of production, wells in Alberta produce an average of 50 barrels a day. Off Newfoundland, the average is 20,000 a day.</p>
        <p>In a mirror-like reversal of Canada's traditional oil picture, Exxon Mobil now estimates the potential conventional offshore oil reserves of Eastern Canada to be 40 billion barrels, compared with 34 billion for Western Canada. Lured by estimates like these, the major oil players are pumping billions of dollars through this four-century-old harbor city.</p>
        <p>''Eastern Canada is becoming better and better known in the industry,'' said Kenneth J. Miller, a Scot, who shuttles between here and Calgary, Alberta, to run Mobil Oil Canada's eastern operations. Canada's largest oil producer, Exxon Mobil has a leading, 33 percent, share in Hibernia; a 22 percent interest in Terra Nova, and 60 percent of Nova Scotia's new gas development, the Sable Offshore Energy Project.</p>
        <p>In addition to Exxon Mobil and Petro-Canada leading developments here, there is Husky Oil, which leads in White Rose, a field that is to start production toward the end of 2003. Chevron Canada Resources leads in Hebron-Ben Nevis, tentatively scheduled for production around 2006. In late July, Canadian officials increased their estimates of Hibernia, White Rose and Hebron-Ben Nevis by a third, to 2.1 billion barrels.</p>
        <p>''When you see an iceberg, you only see 10 percent,'' said Brian Tobin, premier of Newfoundland and Labrador. ''Well, our oil and gas industry is an iceberg waiting to reveal itself.''</p>
        <p>While some oil goes to Eastern Canada, the big market is the Eastern seaboard of the United States.</p>
        <p>''All the oil is going down the North Atlantic, to New York, to Philadelphia,'' said David N. Willis, president of the consortium that operates Hibernia, which is producing 165,000 barrels a day.</p>
        <p>Mark Turner, a ship captain and maritime lawyer here, said, ''New York is the energy eater.''</p>
        <p>In addition to oil, Atlantic Canada offers natural gas, increasingly the  energy of choice for new American homes and power plants. While much of New York City's gas comes from Alberta, the reserves of Newfoundland and Labrador are 62 trillion cubic feet, estimated Mr. Turner, who recently completed his term as chairman of the Newfoundland Ocean Industries Association, the energy company group here. That would provide energy for more than 700 million homes for a year.</p>
        <p>In Nova Scotia, a new 653-mile pipeline is pumping natural gas from the 3.5-trillion-cubic-foot Sable reserve through New Brunswick, Maine and southern New Hampshire to link up with existing pipelines north of Boston. Near the Sable development, three other companies are drilling 15 test wells this year. Nova Scotia has granted 43 exploration licenses and has set an Oct. 30 deadline for bids on 2,875 square miles of ocean around Sable. As a measure of the gas industry's infancy, there are about 200 wells, largely for exploration, off Nova Scotia, compared with more than 6,000 in the Gulf of Mexico.</p>
        <p>''The U.S. is consuming gas like crazy,'' Mr. Bruce of Petro-Canada said. ''If current prices remain on a sustainable basis, it will be economical to run a gas pipeline to the U.S.''</p>
        <p>With natural gas prices running at almost double last year's levels, oil producers in Newfoundland are studying rival proposals to tap their mammoth gas reserves with a pipeline or with ships loaded with compressed or liquefied natural gas.</p>
        <p>Paul D. Dicks, Newfoundland's energy minister, estimated that within 10 years a gas pipeline would be built from the Grand Banks to Newfoundland to Boston, a $3 billion project.</p>
        <p>The investments in Atlantic Canada are part of a response to the stimulus of rising prices. In Western Canada, the number of wells drilled this year is expected to jump 50 percent, to 15,529. Over all, a government survey showed that oil companies planned to invest $13 billion in plants and equipment this year. Fueling investments are record second-quarter profits. Petro-Canada's profit jumped fourfold, to $174 million. Alberta Energy increased profit sixfold, to $78.5 million.</p>
        <p>The people of this island jutting into the North Atlantic, nicknamed the Rock, see the energy boom as welcome news. Newfoundland has Canada's highest unemployment rate, about 17 percent. In recent years, it has been the only province to lose population, shrinking by about 1 percent a year.</p>
        <p>Accustomed to bad news, and to making ends meet with federal revenue-sharing payments averaging about $3,400 a resident, Newfoundlanders are suddenly reading headlines in Toronto newspapers like ''Newfoundland, Alberta expected to lead growth.''</p>
        <p>In a startling turnaround, this province of 540,000 people had the highest growth rates of Canada's 10 provinces in 1998 and 1999. This year, it is expected to top the list again, matching the last two years' growth rates by expanding 5 percent.</p>
        <p>Offshore oil production is an extremely capital-intensive business, with the cost of a single well often being 100 times that of a land-based well. To lift employment, Newfoundlanders have set an ambitious goal of joining Scotland, Norway and South Korea as major fabricators of offshore drilling structures.</p>
        <p>Although initial royalties from Hibernia have been considered low by the provincial government, Mr. Tobin, the premier, said he believed that oil and gas would be Newfoundland's ticket to self-sufficiency.</p>
        <p>''When I look to oil and gas,'' said Mr. Tobin, a former federal fisheries minister, ''I see Newfoundland and Labrador in a decade shaking off a history of being the poor cousin, the have-not province of Canada.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
