<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Summit Watching: Who Was That Man in the Suit?</title>
    <meta content="Y07NOT$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/07/world/07NOTE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228573"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SUMMIT IN NEW YORK: REPORTER'S NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wong, Edward</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gootman, Elissa</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000907T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E0DE1539F934A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="727" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Summit Watching: Who Was That Man in the Suit?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWARD WONG and ELISSA GOOTMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gootman, Elissa; Wong, Edward</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Reporter's Notebook vignettes from behind the scenes during summit of world leaders at United Nations; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The television cameras and reporters raced across the marble lobby of the Waldorf-Astoria and swarmed around the Chinese man in a dark suit. Was he a high-ranking party official? Perhaps President Jiang Zemin himself?</p>
        <p>Hardly. It was William Chiu, chairman of the American Fujian Association of Commerce and Industry. He had just left a meeting with President Jiang. On Tuesday morning, more than 300 Chinese-American community leaders, businessmen and scholars gathered at the hotel to hobnob with the leader of the world's most populous country. About a third were from the New York area.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The television cameras and reporters raced across the marble lobby of the Waldorf-Astoria and swarmed around the Chinese man in a dark suit. Was he a high-ranking party official? Perhaps President Jiang Zemin himself?</p>
        <p>Hardly. It was William Chiu, chairman of the American Fujian Association of Commerce and Industry. He had just left a meeting with President Jiang. On Tuesday morning, more than 300 Chinese-American community leaders, businessmen and scholars gathered at the hotel to hobnob with the leader of the world's most populous country. About a third were from the New York area.</p>
        <p>''The meeting was just great,'' said Mr. Chiu, an insurance agent who lives in the Long Island community of Setauket. ''It's like we're in the same family.''</p>
        <p>There were even Taiwanese- Americans at the meeting, but they never raised the issue of Taiwan independence because the meeting was ''a family talk,'' Mr. Chiu said.</p>
        <p>The insurance agent was among a crowd that welcomed Mr. Jiang earlier this week when he flew in. But a cadre of pro-Tibet protestors had also shown up, something that Mr. Chiu would rather forget.</p>
        <p>''They want their freedom, but they should give us our freedom too,'' he said. ''Don't bother us, don't interrupt us.''</p>
        <p>Since Mr. Jiang was in town for the rest of the week, would Mr. Chiu be meeting with him again?</p>
        <p>''I think he's very busy,'' the insurance agent said. ''There are 1.2 billion people in China. He has a lot of work to do.''</p>
        <p>A Room-Service Stampede</p>
        <p>With more than 30 heads of state on the premises, the Waldorf-Astoria finds itself this week having to provide literally world-class service in ways it has never done before. Where gastronomic matters are concerned, such an undertaking would bring stomachaches to many a chef.</p>
        <p>Not so at the Waldorf, said Christophe Le Chatton, director of food and beverage operations. The hotel has doubled the number of cooks on duty, and quadrupled the number of room-service waiters.</p>
        <p>''To coordinate how to make them happy is important,'' Mr. Le Chatton said of the world leaders. ''They're all equally important in their own mind.''</p>
        <p>The requests are as varied as the languages heard these days in the hotel lobby. There is, for instance, the state leader who insists on drinking papaya juice. World affairs being what they are, Mr. Le Chatton remained discreet about that dignitary's identity. ''I never give out names,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Then there are the delegates who asked the hotel to fetch Thai food from a local restaurant, and those who brought their own chefs. (China and India, for instance.) Space in the kitchen was cleared away, woks were provided. But the chefs brought with them their own knives, strictly for use in the kitchen, not in plenary sessions or backroom conferences.</p>
        <p>In New York to Talk Trash</p>
        <p>Most dignitaries converged on the city to ponder things like world poverty and globalization, but a few arrived with humble concerns.</p>
        <p>Rwanda's health minister, Dr. Ezechias Rwabuhihi, found time to talk about garbage trucks, landfills and sewage treatment.</p>
        <p>''It seems like New Yorkers have a lot of expertise in these matters,'' said Isidore Munyiakazi, an official at the Rwandan mission to the United Nations, who accompanied Dr. Rwabuhihi on his visit Tuesday to the Sanitation Department's Worth Street headquarters.</p>
        <p>If New York can cope with its trash, Rwanda should be able to handle the waste generated by its growing population, Mr. Munyiakazi reasoned. ''People leave their garbage outside, then the city tries to collect it. But we don't have enough cars, we don't have enough personnel and we don't have enough landfills,'' Mr. Munyiakazi said.</p>
        <p>Chief William Jelley, who heads the agency's Bureau of Cleaning and Collection, briefed the minister, who seemed to have trouble finding the office, said Peter C. Fenty, a Sanitation Department spokesman. ''I guess they ran into Gramercy Park, which can be a surprise.''</p>
        <p>SUMMIT IN NEW YORK: REPORTER'S NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
