<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CRITIC'S CHOICE/Jazz CD's; Clarion Calls To Honor Armstrong's Centennial</title>
    <meta content="07CEED$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/07/arts/07CEED.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228498"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Armstrong, Louis (1900-71)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ratliff, Ben</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000907T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE3DD1439F934A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1075" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CRITIC'S CHOICE/Jazz CD's; Clarion Calls To Honor Armstrong's Centennial</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN RATLIFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ratliff, Ben</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ben Ratliff (Critic's Choice) reviews three new compact disc sets with major works of Louis Armstrong, commemorating his centennial year; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Louis Armstrong is receiving the treatment he deserves in his centennial year: a thorough sonic overhaul and repackaging of most of his major work. Here are three Armstrong sets that have emerged in recent months.</p>
        <p>Hot Fives and Sevens</p>
        <p>It's pointless to rememorialize some of the best-known jazz in the world, the recordings Armstrong made with his Chicago-based studio bands from 1925 to 1929. But some of the tracks on ''Louis Armstrong: The Complete Hot Fives and Hot Seven Recordings'' (Sony Legacy, four CD's) still leap out and ask new questions. They don't settle passively into a cliched conception of music from the late 20's.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Louis Armstrong is receiving the treatment he deserves in his centennial year: a thorough sonic overhaul and repackaging of most of his major work. Here are three Armstrong sets that have emerged in recent months.</p>
        <p>Hot Fives and Sevens</p>
        <p>It's pointless to rememorialize some of the best-known jazz in the world, the recordings Armstrong made with his Chicago-based studio bands from 1925 to 1929. But some of the tracks on ''Louis Armstrong: The Complete Hot Fives and Hot Seven Recordings'' (Sony Legacy, four CD's) still leap out and ask new questions. They don't settle passively into a cliched conception of music from the late 20's.</p>
        <p>The contrapuntal tangle of ''Muskrat Ramble'' is a two-and-a-half-minute force field of contained energy. Armstrong's improvisations (and those of Johnny Dodds on clarinet) in ''Potato Head Blues'' have no hesitation: they know exactly what they want to do. ''Skid-Dat-De-Dat,'' with its four-bar portions connected by short improvisations and then a scat-singing solo, is formally radical and can provide shocks of the same kind that Ornette Coleman's early work does.</p>
        <p>This collection makes the Hot Fives and Sevens catalog -- most of which has always been available separately -- unified and thoroughly manageable as a start-to-finish listening experience. As Sony has reorganized it, the set is not without strangenesses, which it makes no attempt to elide or push under the rug. The reissue has been produced by Phil Schaap, and he presumes your familiarity with the programming buttons on the CD player. You are given full information, presented with all tracks and alternate takes in chronological order, given a four-second pause track to program in between songs if you like, and the tacit suggestion is that if you want to canonize any further, you go right ahead.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schaap's drive to get things right has an interesting twist: it tends to respect the effect of the public imagination on culture. He's not trying to rewrite history so much as give you the commonly accepted version as well as his own. Some of the Armstrong tracks included here are not strictly recordings by the various groups he called Hot Five or Hot Seven but were released as such in the past. They've earned inclusion, if only by an error of history. And ''Cornet Chop Suey,'' released through the years in what's now thought to have been a slowed-down key of E flat, is also included in F.</p>
        <p>The sound here is bright and present, even more so than on the JSP reissues that were for a while the tolerable alternative to Columbia's muffled-sounding initial CD reissues of this material.</p>
        <p>'Hello, Dolly!'</p>
        <p>''The Ultimate Collection,'' three CD's, is Verve/Universal's generous version of the best moments from Armstrong's contract with Decca from 1935 to 1945, and again for most of the 1950's, as well as earlier sessions on Vocalion and later ones on ABC Paramount. It captures a lot of big-band material but also duets, small groups and collaborations with singers.</p>
        <p>I'm generally not taken by reissues that present an artist through radically different recording situations from track to track; the endless length of CD's presents work enough without the added burden of having to reconfigure your ears and brain every three minutes.</p>
        <p>But these discs are merely being true to its central character, as Armstrong contracted himself out so often.</p>
        <p>Half the interest of this motley set is seeing how the changing cast of musicians fell into line around him: they swung hard and enthusiastically, where they could. Most often there's a huge chasm between leader and band; basically he's an actor with bravado, throwing his beautiful voice forward at the crowd and not particularly interested in the mise-en-scene.</p>
        <p>This is a collection that has no particular agenda except that it's a good time to sell Armstrong. Every once in a while, as parent companies of record labels merge, a new retrospective of somebody like Armstrong gets dislodged, based on new holdings. (There won't be a true ultimate collection until Sony and Universal become part of the same entity.)</p>
        <p>But here is much music that Armstrong was famous for: the great 1939 Louis Armstrong and his Orchestra sessions, including ''West End Blues'' and ''You're a Lucky Guy,'' with Sid Catlett on drums forcefully slapping the band along; the touching ''Rockin' Chair'' vocal duet with Jack Teagarden, which was given a reprise at the Newport Jazz Festival in the late 50's and put into the concert film ''Jazz on a Summer's Day''; the recordings with Sidney Bechet of ''Perdido Street Blues''; records made with the Mills Brothers, Louis Jordan, Billie Holiday and Ella Fitzgerald; and the deathless ''Hello, Dolly!'' and ''What a Wonderful World'' of the mid-60's.</p>
        <p>Titans at Work</p>
        <p>When Armstrong and Duke Ellington, the two most influential figures in jazz history, met in a studio in 1961, they didn't make a composed, perfect record together. What they did make can be heard on the two-CD set ''The Great Summit: Complete Sessions'' (Roulette/Blue Note). In situations like this Ellington worked as if on a sketch pad; he didn't make composed, perfect records except with his own orchestra.</p>
        <p>He and Armstrong were in elder-statesman mode at the time, touring with their respective orchestras. It's not a famous record for obvious reasons; a few tracks suffer from underrehearsal. But it's magnificently laid back. Armstrong does an equal amount of singing and playing; though he hadn't performed most of these Ellington-associated pieces, he sounds close to them.</p>
        <p>A companion disc, ''The Making of the Great Summit,'' full of the same tunes, but with false starts and tiny discussions about arrangements, isn't a particular draw, unless you love hearing the sound of engineers' voices and Ellington's ''Aaanngh!'' as he occasionally heads into a wrong key. But it's an aid in understanding how in control Armstrong was: his singing is full-bodied and headlong even when the band stops cold and he feels like continuing just out of pride in workmanship.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
