<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Yanks Give Rivera a Rest and Pay the Price</title>
    <meta content="07YANK$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/07/sports/07YANK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228638"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Kansas City Royals</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olney, Buster</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Plains</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Kansas City Royals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000907T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05EFDB1539F934A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="830" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Yanks Give Rivera a Rest and Pay the Price</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olney, Buster</byline>
      <dateline>KANSAS CITY, Mo., Sept. 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Kansas City Royals defeat New York Yankees, 3-2; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Boston could sweep this weekend and the Yankees would still be in first place, so Manager Joe Torre can afford to be judicious and take advantage of the growing division lead. He began the process of reinstalling second baseman Chuck Knoblauch into his lineup tonight, and was intent on resting the closer Mariano Rivera.</p>
        <p>Knoblauch did O.K., making a couple of strong throws and going 0 for 4. But Rivera's temporary replacement bombed: Mike Stanton emerged from the bullpen for the bottom of the ninth entrusted with a 2-1 lead, and walked off the field disheartened minutes later, as Kansas City players celebrated a 3-2 victory around him.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Boston could sweep this weekend and the Yankees would still be in first place, so Manager Joe Torre can afford to be judicious and take advantage of the growing division lead. He began the process of reinstalling second baseman Chuck Knoblauch into his lineup tonight, and was intent on resting the closer Mariano Rivera.</p>
        <p>Knoblauch did O.K., making a couple of strong throws and going 0 for 4. But Rivera's temporary replacement bombed: Mike Stanton emerged from the bullpen for the bottom of the ninth entrusted with a 2-1 lead, and walked off the field disheartened minutes later, as Kansas City players celebrated a 3-2 victory around him.</p>
        <p>If Knoblauch was Torre's most significant reclamation project over the last week, he has been replaced by Stanton, whose problems have lasted the better part of a month. ESPN silently filled the face of a large-screen television after tonight's game, and just as Stanton was about to leave the clubhouse, he realized highlights of the Yankee game were forthcoming.</p>
        <p>Stanton pulled out a folding chair, sat with his forearms rested against the back, and watched the whole, horrible inning unfold again, sipping a bottle of water in his right hand.</p>
        <p>The Yankees had taken a 2-0 lead, on solo home runs by Jeter (in the fourth) and Paul O'Neill (in the sixth). Orlando Hernandez had thrown 122 pitches in eight brilliant innings, killing a Kansas City rally in his last inning by starting a double play.</p>
        <p>Rivera pitched two innings Sunday, another inning Monday, and Torre and the pitching coach Mel Stottlemyre were determined to give him two days off, back-to-back. There's nothing wrong with Rivera, Torre said, other than being a little tired, and he will be available to pitch here Thursday.</p>
        <p>Beyond that, Torre wanted to use Stanton again, to give him a chance to emerge from his funk; Stanton gave up home runs in four straight outings at the end of last month, then was not used for 10 days until pitching an inning Tuesday.</p>
        <p>Tonight, Stanton struck out the Royals' Carlos Beltran. Kansas City Manager Tony Muser inserted the right-handed-hitting David McCarty as a pinch-hitter, with a right-handed hitter on deck. Torre had the option of calling on the right-hander Jeff Nelson.</p>
        <p>But he stuck with the left-handed Stanton, who has been more effective against right-handers, anyway. ''Heck, he got Sweeney and Dye out last night,'' said Torre, referring to Mike Sweeney and Jermaine Dye, the Royals' best hitters.</p>
        <p>Stanton fell behind McCarty three balls and no strikes before McCarty singled. Nelson leaned against the bullpen wall, arms crossed. Febles ripped a doubled into the left-center-field gap, and the pinch-runner Luis Ordaz scored the tying run from first.</p>
        <p>With the left-handed-hitting Johnny Damon at the plate, Stanton remained in the game, and Damon singled through the middle, scoring Febles and setting off a Royals celebration.</p>
        <p>''It can't get a whole lot worse,'' Stanton said. ''Joe has the confidence to send me out there in the ninth, and I fail. There's no excuse for me going out there and doing that. I let the team down, I let Duque down.''</p>
        <p>Knoblauch played behind Hernandez for seven innings before being replaced for defense, and somewhere, the Yankees owner George Steinbrenner was smiling. Most of the owner's criticisms are calculated -- the ''fat toad'' reference to Hideki Irabu last year being an exception -- and when he inferred last week that Knoblauch's elbow pain was fake, his intent was to prod the second baseman back into the lineup.</p>
        <p>Knoblauch said he didn't need that motivation; he just wants to play again, and he felt good. ''It was good,'' he said. ''On the right track.''</p>
        <p>Knoblauch was the first position player in the Yankees' lineup to emerge from the clubhouse in the half-hour before tonight's game, stretching his legs and going through a series of sprints to warm up.</p>
        <p>Knoblauch's notorious throwing jitters, active in June, are mostly dormant in September, the fault line faded but still in place. With Johnny Damon running from first on a pitch in the first inning, Rey Sanchez chopped a grounder to second. Knoblauch fielded the ball cleanly, briefly considered a flip to second before setting himself, tapping the ball in his glove, stepping with his left foot and throwing, hard and straight, all in perfect rhythm. He had a couple of other chances, as well, attempting to finish two double plays, looking a little awkward but always throwing the ball straight.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
