<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Microsoft Device Shows Gamers Just Who's Talking the Talk</title>
    <meta content="07GEE3" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Circuits" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/07/technology/07GEE3.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228504"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEWS WATCH"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Microsoft Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Austen, Ian</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Circuits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000907T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E0DD1439F934A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="408" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Microsoft Device Shows Gamers Just Who's Talking the Talk</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By IAN AUSTEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Austen, Ian</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Microsoft offers hardware device to enables people playing computer games on Internet to talk with teammates, while preventing opponents from listening in; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For online gamers, the ability to speak through the Internet to other players while playing has obvious advantages. But it also has the potential for trouble. ''If you're in the middle of a combat game and you're strategizing with your team mate, it's important not to let your opponents hear that,'' said Isabella Carniato, Microsoft's Game Voice marketing manager.</p>
        <p>But making those Internet voice connections and then keeping track of who is hearing what can sometimes become as complicated as determining the next step in destroying the enemy in some cyberbattle.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For online gamers, the ability to speak through the Internet to other players while playing has obvious advantages. But it also has the potential for trouble. ''If you're in the middle of a combat game and you're strategizing with your team mate, it's important not to let your opponents hear that,'' said Isabella Carniato, Microsoft's Game Voice marketing manager.</p>
        <p>But making those Internet voice connections and then keeping track of who is hearing what can sometimes become as complicated as determining the next step in destroying the enemy in some cyberbattle.</p>
        <p>While studying architecture and political science at the University of Waterloo in Ontario, Ms. Carniato developed and marketed one of the earliest pieces of software that allowed gamers to speak as well as play over the Net. But now that Microsoft has taken over Ms. Carniato's company, which produced Battlefield Communicator and put her on its payroll, she is now proposing that the next big thing for gamers who chat is a piece of hardware.</p>
        <p>The main problem with software for managing voice connections is invisibility, Ms. Carniato said. Most games don't make it practical to show the on-screen displays of voice-management software during play. Given that, it quickly becomes easy for players to lose track of exactly who is listening at any given moment.</p>
        <p>The Microsoft SideWinder Game Voice is a chunk of black plastic that resembles an oversize hockey puck. When plugged in through a computer's U.S.B. port, it acts something like an old-fashioned telephone switchboard. Eight buttons on top of the device light up to show live connections and allow users to alter the pattern of the hookups quickly.</p>
        <p>In addition to several pieces of chat software, the device, which costs $54.95, comes packaged with a headset microphone. Because of that, Microsoft has also included voice-recognition software that allows users to operate most games with voice as well as keyboard commands.</p>
        <p>But Ms. Carniato acknowledged that there were many situations where pecking away at a keyboard would still be more convenient. ''You would never say 'shoot' or other commands that are right under your fingers,'' she said. ''If you're just shooting until you run out of rounds, it doesn't make sense.''</p>
        <p>IAN AUSTEN</p>
        <p>NEWS WATCH</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
