<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>One U.S. Team Eliminated; Second Reaches the Finals</title>
    <meta content="07CARD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228513"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BRIDGE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bridge (Card Game)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Truscott, Alan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Crossword and Games/Bridge</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bridge (Card Game)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000907T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E0DC1439F934A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="573" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>One U.S. Team Eliminated; Second Reaches the Finals</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Alan Truscott</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Truscott, Alan</byline>
      <dateline>MAASTRICHT, the Netherlands, Sept. 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Results of semifinals of World Championship bridge tournament noted; diagram (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>One United States team marched to victory here today in the semifinal of the World Championship, and the other was defeated.</p>
        <p>In the women's play, Joan Jackson, Robin Klar, Peggy Sutherlin, Petra Hamman, Shawn Quinn and Mildred Breed, all from Texas, led throughout against Norway and won by the considerable margin of 123 imps.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>One United States team marched to victory here today in the semifinal of the World Championship, and the other was defeated.</p>
        <p>In the women's play, Joan Jackson, Robin Klar, Peggy Sutherlin, Petra Hamman, Shawn Quinn and Mildred Breed, all from Texas, led throughout against Norway and won by the considerable margin of 123 imps.</p>
        <p>Whom they would face in the final beginning on Thursday was unclear until the end of the day's play. Canada led Germany by just 18 with 16 deals remaining to be played, but then pulled away and won by 49, setting up a North American final.</p>
        <p>The American open team, consisting of George Jacobs, Ralph Katz, Howard Weinstein, Steve Garner, David Berkowitz and Larry Cohen, played superbly in the early rounds but was crushed in the semifinal by a Polish team that performed with great efficiency. With 16 deals remaining, the Americans trailed by 104 and conceded defeat.</p>
        <p>The second session, on Tuesday night, was a disaster for the Americans. The score for 16 deals was 47 to minus 2 against them, perhaps unique on such an occasion. The negative score was the result of slow-play penalties against both sides.</p>
        <p>In the other semifinal, Italy defeated England by 85, setting up an Italy-Poland final on Thursday, and that is expected to be a close battle.</p>
        <p>The play of the final matches can be followed live on the Internet. The site is: www.canalweb.net/vers .asp?e=bridgeentv.</p>
        <p>On the diagramed deal from the quarterfinal stage, a deal that seemed likely to be a heavy loss proved to be a pleasant surprise. An American player was unhappy when he misguessed as South in defending against five diamonds. After he led a top spade and saw his partner play the seven and declarer the 10, there was no way to know who held the four because North would also have played the seven from a seven-four combination.</p>
        <p>With the actual layout, he should have played another top spade, for his partner would eventually have scored a heart trick to defeat the game. Instead he shifted to his singleton heart, which would have been right if his partner had held the heart ace and the missing spade. Unfortunately for South, East was able to win the heart lead, draw trumps and throw his spade loser on a club winner, making his game.</p>
        <p>But the potential disaster did not materialize. In the replay, as shown in the diagram, North-South bid a spade too far. David Berkowitz, the American West, doubled and led his top clubs. He then led the club two, and his partner, Larry Cohen, ruffed and read the message correctly. The two was a suit-preference signal asking for a low-ranking suit, and an underlead of the diamond ace permitted West to win and provide a second club ruff. The heart ace was the sixth trick for the defense, and the penalty was 1100; all South could score was his seven trump tricks. The Americans gained 11 imps, and the player who misguessed against five diamonds was distinctly relieved. If he had guessed the winning defense, he team would have been only 4 imps better off.</p>
        <p>BRIDGE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
