<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>La Scala Bids Addio to the Favorite Haunt of Catcalls</title>
    <meta content="07ARTS$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/07/arts/07ARTS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228490"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ARTS ABROAD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fires and Firemen</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Teatro alla Scala (Milan)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Povoledo, Elisabetta</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000907T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E4DE1439F934A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="994" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>La Scala Bids Addio to the Favorite Haunt of Catcalls</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Elisabetta Povoledo</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Povoledo, Elisabetta</byline>
      <dateline>ROME, Sept. 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>La Scala opera house in Milan eliminates 200 $5 standing-room places on first and second galleries, haunt of the fanatical opera lovers called 'loggionisti,' whose booing or applause has dictated failure or success of performers, conductors and even operas at theater; administrators say standing room space violated fire regulations and will be re-established as part of theater's general overhaul, which begins at the end of 2001; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>These days the real drama at La Scala in Milan is taking place in the auditorium and not onstage. When the season starts up again with Puccini's ''Boheme'' on Tuesday, the 200 standing-room places of the first and second galleries will no longer be occupied. This is tragic news for its habitual dwellers, the feared and respected ''loggionisti,'' the ardent opera buffs who sit or stand in the galleries and are said to dictate the failure or success of a performer, a conductor or even an opera at the theater.</p>
        <p>Last week administrators at La Scala announced that having people stand in the two galleries did not conform to fire regulations, and so  standing-room tickets, which only cost about $5, would no longer be sold. They had been so prized that people stood in line for hours for them. Administrators did promise that the galleries would be restructured to conform to fire regulations as part of the theater's general overhaul, which is expected to begin at the end of next year. Until then, opera lovers will have to pay $12 to $150 (what tickets usually sell for) and just sit tight.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>These days the real drama at La Scala in Milan is taking place in the auditorium and not onstage. When the season starts up again with Puccini's ''Boheme'' on Tuesday, the 200 standing-room places of the first and second galleries will no longer be occupied. This is tragic news for its habitual dwellers, the feared and respected ''loggionisti,'' the ardent opera buffs who sit or stand in the galleries and are said to dictate the failure or success of a performer, a conductor or even an opera at the theater.</p>
        <p>Last week administrators at La Scala announced that having people stand in the two galleries did not conform to fire regulations, and so  standing-room tickets, which only cost about $5, would no longer be sold. They had been so prized that people stood in line for hours for them. Administrators did promise that the galleries would be restructured to conform to fire regulations as part of the theater's general overhaul, which is expected to begin at the end of next year. Until then, opera lovers will have to pay $12 to $150 (what tickets usually sell for) and just sit tight.</p>
        <p>La Scala was built in 1776 by Empress Maria Theresa of Austria to replace an earlier building that had burned down. Nearly all of the world's greatest opera singers have performed there over the years, and many great operas have had their world premieres there, including Verdi's ''Nabucco,'' ''Falstaff'' and ''Otello'' and Bellini's ''Norma.''</p>
        <p>Unlike a flop on Broadway, failure at La Scala does not necessarily mean the disappearance of a work. The world premiere of Puccini's ''Madama Butterfly'' at La Scala in 1904, for example, was a disaster.</p>
        <p>Whatever the lapses in judgment, many agree that the power to make or break the reputation of performers, conductors and operas comes from the loggionisti, who greeted the decision to cut the standing-room places with dismay. ''This is very unpleasant because we will lose a traditionally passionate public that truly loves opera, lives for opera and will line up for tickets for hours, making huge sacrifices just to see a performance,'' said Giuseppe Castagnetti, president of Gli Amici del Loggione, a group of 2,000 opera aficionados who occupy most of the seats in the balconies. ''A theater is more than just its conductors and the works that are presented in it, but also its public.''</p>
        <p>At La Scala the public usually means the loggionisti. He said that the opera house's decision was even more serious coming just before the start of its millennium season, which will feature 11 works by Verdi, starting with ''Il Trovatore'' on Dec. 7 and for which tickets will be even more in demand than usual.</p>
        <p>The loggionisti, whose legendary fanaticism has more than once been compared to that of Italy's soccer fans, recoil at being considered a claque of people who for money or free tickets or simply out of passion band together to applaud or deride a performance.</p>
        <p>Rather, they pride themselves on their familiarity with libretti and scores, and part of the mandate of Gli Amici del Loggione is to hold regular conferences and two or three-day workshops before every new La Scala offering. Such intimate knowledge of the music tends to breed contempt of less-than-perfect performances. Some say that Luciano Pavarotti has refused to sing again at La Scala since he was booed in 1992 by the loggionisti during his first performance of Verdi's ''Don Carlo.''</p>
        <p>Two years ago the American soprano Renee Fleming was booed repeatedly when she sang the lead in a summer production of Donizetti's ''Lucrezia Borgia.'' Even emerging singers are not spared. ''For a young singer, performing in front of the loggionisti is like coming into hell,'' said a La Scala employee who asked not be named. ''Knowing there are people who can destroy you listening in the gallery -- well, for the singers it feels a lot like going to the front in the middle of a battle.'' The loggionisti defend their right to speak out (or make catcalls).</p>
        <p>One 30-year veteran of La Scala who was more than once the target of  the loggione's disapproval said she was nonetheless sorry to see the standing-room places go. ''I like the loggionisti because I have received the warmest demonstrations of approval from them,'' said the mezzo-soprano Fiorenza Cossotto, who made her singing debut at La Scala in Poulenc's ''Dialogues des Carmelites'' in 1957. ''At the same time no one wants to be reprimanded or reproved, it makes an artist very nervous,'' she said. Ms. Cossotti said she had been contested ''even when I didn't deserve it but I had to put up with it.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Castagnetti put it this way: ''You either have more amorphous theaters where the public does not participate, like the Met, where I have heard some horrible performances without the public saying anything, or you have La Scala, which prides itself in being competent.''</p>
        <p>Though today one is more likely to hear someone on the street singing  Janet Jackson's latest song than a Verdi aria (as was common in the second half of the 19th century), Italians are still proud of their rich opera heritage.</p>
        <p>The imminent demise of the standing-room clique made the front pages of many Italian newspapers and prompted earnest editorials. In the Rome-based paper Il Messaggero, the journalist Rita Sala made a passionate appeal to La Scala's music director, Riccardo Muti.</p>
        <p>''Maestro Muti, do something,'' she pleaded. ''The Mediterranean blood of Apulia and Naples that flows in your veins may have been tempered by northern discipline, but it will certainly not accept that the loggionisti be left outside the door. Protest, Maestro.''</p>
        <p>ARTS ABROAD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
