<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Words of Many Government Leaders, and Many Views of the World</title>
    <meta content="Y07LEA$12" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/07/world/07LEAD.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228594"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SUMMIT IN NEW YORK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Cuba</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iran</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Ireland</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Bangladesh</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">France</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Maldives</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blair, Tony (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Castro, Fidel (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Khatami, Mohammad (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ahern, Bertie (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barak, Ehud (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Putin, Vladimir V (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wazed, Hasina (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chirac, Jacques (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jiang Zemin (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gaymoom, Maumoon Abdul (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Text</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Bangladesh</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Maldives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Ireland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iran</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Cuba</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Bangladesh</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Maldives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iran</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Ireland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Cuba</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000907T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E3DC1539F934A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1853" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Words of Many Government Leaders, and Many Views of the World</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Excerpts from speeches of world leaders at UN, including Prime Min Tony Blair of Britain, Pres Fidel Castro of Cuba, Pres Mohammad Khatami of Iran, Prime Min Bertie Ahern of Ireland, Prime Min Ehud Barak of Israel, Pres Vladimir V Putin of Russia, Prime Min Hasina Wazed of Bangladesh, Pres Jacques Chirac of France, Pres Jiang Zemin of China and Pres Maumoon Abdul Gaymoom of Maldives; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>These are excerpts from speeches of world leaders yesterday at the United Nations, drawn from official transcripts:</p>
        <p>'There can be change. There can be hope for Africa.'  TONY BLAIR  Prime Minister, Britain</p>
        <p>There is a dismal record of failure in Africa on the part of the developed world that shocks and shames our civilization. Twenty-one of the 44 countries in sub-Saharan Africa are affected by conflict which undermines efforts at development. Even worse, 10 times as many people died of AIDS in Africa last year as were killed in all continent's wars combined.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>These are excerpts from speeches of world leaders yesterday at the United Nations, drawn from official transcripts:</p>
        <p>'There can be change. There can be hope for Africa.'  TONY BLAIR  Prime Minister, Britain</p>
        <p>There is a dismal record of failure in Africa on the part of the developed world that shocks and shames our civilization. Twenty-one of the 44 countries in sub-Saharan Africa are affected by conflict which undermines efforts at development. Even worse, 10 times as many people died of AIDS in Africa last year as were killed in all continent's wars combined.</p>
        <p>Nowhere are more people dying needlessly from starvation, from disease, from conflict. Deaths caused not by acts of fate, but by acts of man. By bad governance, factional rivalries, state-sponsored theft and corruption.</p>
        <p>Nowhere are more people being left behind on the wrong side of a growing digital and educational divide, children being denied the opportunities that will transform the lives of their contemporaries elsewhere in the world. Yet, 30 years ago, the same depressing analysis might have been made of parts of Asia or Latin America. There can be change. There can be hope for Africa.</p>
        <p>There is political leadership, business opportunity and above all the will on behalf of people for a better future in Africa. We must be partners in the search for change and hope.</p>
        <p>'Blind laws are offered like divine norms.'  FIDEL CASTRO  President, Cuba</p>
        <p>There is chaos in our world, both within the countries' borders and beyond. Blind laws are offered like divine norms that would bring peace, order, well-being and the security our planet so badly needs. That is what they would have us believe.</p>
        <p>Three dozen developed and wealthy nations that monopolize the economic, political and technological power have joined us in this gathering to offer more of the same recipes that have only served to make us poorer, more exploited and more dependent.</p>
        <p>There is not even discussion about a radical reform of this old institution -- born over a half-century ago when there were few independent nations -- to turn into a true representative body of the interests of all the peoples on Earth; an institution where no one would have the irritating and anti-democratic right of veto and where a transparent process could be undertaken to expand membership and representation in the Security Council, an executive body subordinated to the General Assembly, which should be the one making the decisions on such crucial issues as intervention and the use of force.</p>
        <p>It should be clearly stated that the principle of sovereignty cannot be sacrificed to an abusive and unfair order that a hegemonic superpower uses, together with its own might and strength, to try to decide everything by itself. That Cuba will never accept.</p>
        <p>'A moral and humane world with liberty and progress.'  MOHAMMAD KHATAMI  President, Iran</p>
        <p>Democratic principles have gradually become the criteria of good-governance domestically. They deserve to become the new norm governing global interactions.</p>
        <p>Therefore, the exigencies of a few power holders should not supersede the interest of humanity through familiar practices of endorsement of undemocratic governments, not responsive to the will and needs of their people, and application of double and multiple standards of response to incidents around the globe.</p>
        <p>Moreover, the structure of power in our contemporary world must be reformed. In a global society whose constituents, much like equal individuals within nation-states, are nations of equal right and dignity, diverse cultures and civilizations can and should work collectively to build a moral and humane world with liberty and progress for all.</p>
        <p>'We live in a society, not a marketplace.'  BERTIE AHERN  Prime Minister, Ireland</p>
        <p>The statistics of poverty and inequality in our world are shocking and shameful.</p>
        <p>Half the world's population struggling on less than $2 a day; over a billion on less than $1.</p>
        <p>A quarter of a billion children of 14 and under working, sometimes in terrible conditions.</p>
        <p>Death from preventable and treatable diseases; 10 people will die of malaria in the five minutes I take to address you. There was much talk some years ago of a ''new world order.''</p>
        <p>A new order is indeed dawning. The capacity of globalization to transform our economies and societies is enormous.</p>
        <p>But, unless shaped by a value system, globalization will mean an ever more lopsided world. The level playing field will remain an illusion as long as a majority of players are ill fed, ill trained and ill equipped.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the phrase ''fair world order'' better sums up what we should strive for. It recognizes that we live in a society, not a marketplace. It admits concepts of justice and human solidarity. It acknowledges that, while not everyone will live in the same way, we are all entitled to dignity and decency.</p>
        <p>'At the Rubicon, and neither of us can cross it alone.'  EHUD BARAK  Prime Minister, Israel</p>
        <p>The opportunity for peace in the Middle East is now at hand, and must not be missed.</p>
        <p>We envision a peace that will preserve the vital interests and the dignity of all sides. But no one side can achieve 100 percent of its dreams if we are to succeed.</p>
        <p>My own government has shown, in negotiations with Syria and the Palestinians, as in our full implementation of U.N. Security Council Resolution 425, that it can make painful decisions for the sake of peace.</p>
        <p>It remains to be seen whether our counterparts are also capable of rising to the magnitude of the hour.</p>
        <p>The member states of the United Nations can lend a pivotal hand by encouraging the difficult process of reconciliation, and by opposing any unilateral measures, which may well spark a renewed cycle of violence and obliterate the prospects of peace.</p>
        <p>I call out to Chairman Arafat to join me in this historic passage.</p>
        <p>We are at the Rubicon, and neither of us can cross it alone.</p>
        <p>'New horizons for secure life on the planet.'  VLADIMIR V. PUTIN  President, Russia</p>
        <p>The new century of the United Nations should prolong itself into a millennium of effective stability. It has to enter the annals of history as the period of real disarmament. . . .</p>
        <p>We should reliably block the ways for spreading of nuclear weapons. We can achieve this by, inter alia, excluding usage of enriched uranium and pure plutonium in the world atomic energy production.</p>
        <p>This is technically quite possible to implement. But more important is that incineration of plutonium and other radioactive elements creates prerequisites for the final solution of the radioactive residues problem. It opens fundamentally new horizons for secure life on the planet.</p>
        <p>In this connection Russia proposes to work out and put into practice a relevant mechanism with the participation of the I.A.E.A. Particularly alarming are the plans for militarization of the outer space. In spring of 2001 we shall celebrate the 40th anniversary of the first flight of man to the outer space.</p>
        <p>That man was our compatriot, and we suggest to organize on that date, under the umbrella of the U.N., an international conference on prevention of the outer space militarization. I think that the most proper place for it shall be Moscow.</p>
        <p>'As part of a global village, we should work together.'  HASINA WAZED  Prime Minister, Bangladesh</p>
        <p>Can we afford islands of prosperity in an ocean of suffering and darkness? Let us resolve that as part of a global village, we should work together so that all can benefit from the process of globalization and we can have a win-win at the end.</p>
        <p>Globalization and a borderless world are not a panacea for all social and economic ills. While they can reinforce the rich and the powerful, they can also impoverish the weak and the vulnerable.</p>
        <p>'We all know that the U.N. plays a major role.'  JACQUES CHIRAC  President, France</p>
        <p>Our world, which is still fraught with political, economic and financial crises, does not suffer from a surfeit of rules, but from the problems of keeping international law and practices abreast of change and progress.</p>
        <p>If we are to build a world order that meets the needs of our times, we must strengthen and improve the coexistence of great institutions such as I.M.F., the World Bank, the W.T.O. and, first of all, the U.N.</p>
        <p>We all know that the U.N. plays a major role. In its first half-century of existence, this universal, democratic institution has become irreplaceable.</p>
        <p>We must let it adapt to today's world.  By modernizing the methods of the General Assembly, which is the world's Parliament in a way. By supporting the reforms undertaken by our secretary general, Mr. Kofi Annan, whom I would like to salute here. By making the best use of the information revolution.</p>
        <p>And finally, by providing the necessary resources, as the European Union countries do, supplying more than one-third of the budget and half of the financing for U.N. funds and programs. This will enable the U.N. to fulfill its duties and influence the course of world history.</p>
        <p>'There should not be only one color in the universe.'  JIANG ZEMIN  President, China</p>
        <p>The world is diverse and colorful. Just as there should not be only one color in the universe, so there should not be only one civilization, one social system, one development model or one set of values in the world.</p>
        <p>Each and every country and nation has made its own contribution to the development of human civilization. It is essential to fully respect the diversity of different nations, religions and civilizations, whose co-existence is the very source of vigorous development in the world.</p>
        <p>We should promote the exchanges between different civilizations in a spirit of equality and democracy and encourage them to learn from one another in order to attain common progress.</p>
        <p>Dialogue and cooperation in the field of human rights must be conducted on the basis of respect for state sovereignty. This is the fundamental and most effective way to protect and promote human rights.</p>
        <p>So long as there are boundaries between states, and people live in their respective countries, to maintain national independence and safeguard sovereignty will be the supreme interests of each government and people. Without sovereignty, there will be no human rights to speak of.</p>
        <p>'Inaction speaks louder than words.'  MAUMOON ABDUL GAYMOOM  President, Maldives</p>
        <p>To those who learn from mistakes the past is a good guide for the future. But let us not go back a thousand years. Let us go forward to a hundred years hence.</p>
        <p>When the U.N. meets to usher in yet another century, will the Maldives and other low-lying island nations be represented here?</p>
        <p>Not only a sobering thought, but an alarming one.</p>
        <p>Now, I have only 30 seconds left. It would be a pity to disperse from this gathering without a final commitment to save the earth. I don't wish to be cynical, but, are we to believe that the world really cares? Are we to believe that all humanity is one?</p>
        <p>Inaction speaks louder than words.</p>
        <p>SUMMIT IN NEW YORK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
