<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Temptation, in Spike Heels And a Devilish Price Tag</title>
    <meta content="07SHOP$16" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Circuits" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/07/technology/07SHOP.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228477"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ONLINE SHOPPER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shoes and Boots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Neiman Marcus Stores</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Slatalla, Michelle</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blahnik, Manolo</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Columns/Online Shopper</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Circuits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shoes and Boots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000907T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E5D61739F934A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="975" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Temptation, in Spike Heels And a Devilish Price Tag</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Michelle Slatalla</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Slatalla, Michelle</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Michelle Slatalla column on shopping on Internet at Neiman Marcus site selling Manolo Blahnik shoes; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HERE is how I am used to shopping on the Internet. I arrive at an online store that reminds me of a file cabinet, with all the merchandise tucked away in tabbed folders. I click on the appropriate folder. Inside I find a brochure for each item, with a short description, a price and sometimes a simple image to confirm that yes, this is the specific thing I have been trying to track down.</p>
        <p>Here is how I shopped online last week. I walked down a narrow, hidden alleyway, following a yellow butterfly as it flew past shuttered townhouses. Then, as if I were wandering around in a version of Myst optimized for shoe addicts, I peered through the window of a discreet door set in the middle of a mysterious brick wall and caught a glimpse of beautiful, spiky-heeled footwear displayed on simple metal perches.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HERE is how I am used to shopping on the Internet. I arrive at an online store that reminds me of a file cabinet, with all the merchandise tucked away in tabbed folders. I click on the appropriate folder. Inside I find a brochure for each item, with a short description, a price and sometimes a simple image to confirm that yes, this is the specific thing I have been trying to track down.</p>
        <p>Here is how I shopped online last week. I walked down a narrow, hidden alleyway, following a yellow butterfly as it flew past shuttered townhouses. Then, as if I were wandering around in a version of Myst optimized for shoe addicts, I peered through the window of a discreet door set in the middle of a mysterious brick wall and caught a glimpse of beautiful, spiky-heeled footwear displayed on simple metal perches.</p>
        <p>Beyond the door lay the Manolo Blahnik boutique that Neiman Marcus's online store started last month to sell really (really) expensive shoes, using technology that compresses and streams computer-generated video content at a rate that enables even shoppers who connect over pokey dial-up modems to feel as if they are browsing in the ladies' department of the Matrix.</p>
        <p>The technology is from RichFX, a company based in New York that also licenses its technology to the jewelry Web site Kirabo.com and will announce more partnerships in the next few months, company officials said. The software creates an immersive setting that appears in a single window -- no annoying pop-up boxes clutter the screen -- and is as compelling as a video game.</p>
        <p>''The idea is to turn the Internet into a place that you can move around in, a place that feels real,'' said Tal Kerret, RichFX's chief executive. ''If you come in at different times of day or night, you get a different experience, for example. The lighting in the store will be completely different.''</p>
        <p>Plenty of other technologies have offered similar promises, of course.</p>
        <p>''Other three-dimensional environments exist,'' said Peter Ausnit, an equity analyst at Deutsche Banc Alex Brown in San Francisco, ''but they don't download and stream on demand to deliver what you want when you want, and others didn't create a formula for such an elegant user interface.''</p>
        <p>All I had to do to visit the shoe boutique was to click on Introducing Blahnik on the neimanmarcus.com  (www.neimanmarcus .com) home page and then download (it took a few seconds) an update to the Real Networks Real Player already installed on my computer. (The update includes the RichFX Player). To navigate, all I had to do was click on Right, Left or Pause. The site also has a zoom feature.</p>
        <p>Still, when the yellow butterfly paused at the boutique's doorway, so did I. Don't go in, I told myself: It's a trick. This is not just some harmless computer game where I can pump my enemies full of bullets and splatter their kidneys against the wall. No, this technology may have a harmful impact on my behavior. No one needs $500 shoes, especially not me, a person who works at home in shorts. Where would I wear them, to the next meeting of the nursery school board?</p>
        <p>The door opened, the butterfly flew inside and I saw a pair of pointy black suede mules with a two-inch heel. They looked as sleek and fast as a cigarette boat. I suddenly remembered that I am the nursery school board's recording secretary. A person entrusted with the responsibility of taking the minutes every month should look put together, no?</p>
        <p>I went in. I browsed. I found it so easy. ''It's a quicker way to convey more information and at the same time you ask the shopper to do less work,'' Mr. Ausnit said. Then he added, as if this were a good thing, ''This technology will be explosive because it's fun.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Ausnit, who does not have to pay the credit card bills in my household, would probably also be charmed by the fact that as I approached the suede mule, the shoe stayed in perspective, getting bigger. He might even be thrilled to know that after I clicked on it, the shoe floated in midair like some enchanted object in a Harry Potter novel, spinning so close to my face that I was afraid the pointy toe would nick my nose and draw blood. I was in the Seventh Circle of Shopping and these were the Suede Mules from Hell. From hell, I tell you.</p>
        <p>I phoned Gayle Tremblay, vice president of Neiman Marcus Online, to ask her how in good conscience she could tempt shoppers so cruelly.  She did not seem wracked by guilt. ''I can tell you, those shoes would look fabulous on you,'' Ms. Tremblay said.</p>
        <p>I looked once more at the very, very, very beautiful shoes. I pictured myself wearing them. Even in jeans, I would look very, very, very beautiful. I would float in midair.</p>
        <p>Then I noticed the price, displayed unobtrusively on screen to the right of the RichFX window: $445.</p>
        <p>That brought me back to reality. I went upstairs to my closet and unearthed a pair of black and witchy Manolo Blahnik pumps I bought at a triple-reduced-price-end-of-season sale a few years back (they still cost too much). Wearing them, I sat down in front of my husband's computer to play Doom, which suddenly seemed a lot safer.</p>
        <p>ONLINE SHOPPER E-mail address: Slatalla@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail address: Slatalla@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
