<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Right-Hand Man at U.N. Behind the Summit</title>
    <meta content="07PROF" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/07/nyregion/07PROF.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228555"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PUBLIC LIVES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Politics and Government (U.S.)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">John G. Ruggie</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Finn, Robin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ruggie, John (Asst Sec Gen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Public Lives</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000907T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E5DF1539F934A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="994" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Right-Hand Man at U.N. Behind the Summit</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBIN FINN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Finn, Robin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Public Lives column profiles career of John G Ruggie, assistant secretary general at United Nations and assistant host of Millennium Summit; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IMAGINE that you threw an unprecedented three-day party on the banks of the East River, invited the heads of a world's worth of nations -- 189 presidents, premiers, prime ministers, princes and kings -- and almost all of them showed up. With princely demands, agendas and motorcades. Some with protesters in tow. All of them protected by a multimillion-dollar blanket of security that makes exceptions for no man, not even the host.</p>
        <p>That's why John G. Ruggie, into his fourth season as assistant secretary general at the United Nations and the assistant host of the Millennium Summit that runs through Friday at the U.N., raced into work at 5:30 a.m. for yesterday's opening ceremonies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IMAGINE that you threw an unprecedented three-day party on the banks of the East River, invited the heads of a world's worth of nations -- 189 presidents, premiers, prime ministers, princes and kings -- and almost all of them showed up. With princely demands, agendas and motorcades. Some with protesters in tow. All of them protected by a multimillion-dollar blanket of security that makes exceptions for no man, not even the host.</p>
        <p>That's why John G. Ruggie, into his fourth season as assistant secretary general at the United Nations and the assistant host of the Millennium Summit that runs through Friday at the U.N., raced into work at 5:30 a.m. for yesterday's opening ceremonies.</p>
        <p>''I had to beat the motorcades; I couldn't afford to get caught on the wrong side of First Avenue,'' says Mr. Ruggie, hyperventilating a bit at the prospect of missing his own shindig. Well, it's actually his friend Kofi Annan's shindig, but he and Mr. Annan, the U.N's secretary general, have been planning this summit almost since Mr. Ruggie, a career academic, left his post at Columbia University to sign on as Mr. Annan's right-hand man in 1997.</p>
        <p>A major theory both men share about the role of the U.N. in the 21st century: ''It's change or die.'' And that includes enlisting the private sector -- as in (greedy, selfish) corporate conglomerates -- to advance the U.N.'s agenda on everything from peacekeeping to cleaning up the environment.</p>
        <p>Time for some rhetoric: ''We don't expect global corporations to become altruists, but how do you promote fair labor standards if you don't work with major employers? How do you promote the environment if you don't work with the people who are doing the promoting? People tell us we shouldn't do business with companies like Shell and Nike, but what's the point of working with companies that are already perfect?''</p>
        <p>Mr. Ruggie, 55 and ''shy'' about admitting to it, has news for any corporation that thinks it can con the U.N.: ''This place is a fishbowl; if I'm the head of a corporation and I want to con the world, I wouldn't do it through this vehicle.''</p>
        <p>So Mr. Ruggie, besides being gung-ho about globalization, what kind of diplomat are you? ''That part's been hard for me, but I've learned to keep smiling no matter what somebody says,'' he confesses. And everybody at this level has something to say.</p>
        <p>''We've never had 152 heads of state together in one place before,'' says Mr. Ruggie, taking a timeout, in his shirt sleeves, in his overheated 38th-floor office atop the U.N. while the leaders of the world give their obligatory five-minute speeches downstairs. Mr. Ruggie isn't offended that the leaders of 37 nations didn't make it; they sent surrogates. Even without all 189 titular heads, the day's program is running late; a few presidents overstayed their five-minute limit while touching on the summit's themes: poverty, the environment, education, ending AIDS.</p>
        <p>HOW do you tell a president to stop talking? Mr. Ruggie does it silently, colorfully. Four and a half minutes into a dignitary's spiel, the green light at his podium turns to orange, and at five minutes, it turns red: the lights are visible to everyone in the room, too.</p>
        <p>''We don't have a trap door,'' says Mr. Ruggie, who also considers it undiplomatic to deploy a hook to clear the stage. Better to let the caterers know lunch will start late.</p>
        <p>''It's quite a process to get 189 nations to agree to a common platform,'' he notes. Some of them aren't speaking to each other. Some refuse to sit on the same side of the room. But all of them want their five minutes at the microphone, and Mr. Ruggie means to oblige since it's Mr. Annan's initiatives they're tackling.</p>
        <p>''He's the most wonderful human being I've ever met,'' Mr. Ruggie says of his boss. ''I know that sounds corny, but it's true.'' Mr. Annan had no difficulty enticing Mr. Ruggie away from Columbia for what was originally to be a one-year term: ''He called me, took me to lunch, and said, 'John, I'd find it useful to have somebody around who's not going to get swallowed up by the in box,' and I said, 'When can I start?' ''</p>
        <p>Mr. Ruggie says he's been a foreign policy, global village wonk since his graduate school days at Berkeley (he wanted to go to medical school until ''hopelessness'' in science nudged him toward political science), but he insists his best qualification for serving as Mr. Annan's adviser is his outsider status: ''I don't owe the U.S. government anything, I'm not a regular U.N. bureaucrat so I don't have to worry about taking positions that may affect my career path. I can just serve one master.''</p>
        <p>Born in Austria, raised in Toronto (he says he was eventually asked to leave Canada because he never learned to skate backward, a prerequisite for hockey), Mr. Ruggie grew up in blue-collar circumstances: ''We were deep blue,'' he recalls. His father, a house painter, never got past the third grade, and his mother cleaned houses and worked in a butcher shop. ''I didn't come from a theoretical home,'' he says.</p>
        <p>He married his high-school sweetheart (''Corny again'') and received a Ph.D. in political science from Berkeley in 1974. He and his wife, Mary, a sociology professor, joined the faculty at Columbia in 1978, became United States citizens 20 years ago. Now he's helping shape the future of the citizens of the world: ''It's easy to be cynical, and I know this summit is an inconvenience to New Yorkers, but we believe it will make history and make a difference.''</p>
        <p>PUBLIC LIVES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
