<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On Some Corporate Internet Sites, It's Not All Business</title>
    <meta content="07ZAMB" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Circuits" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/07/technology/07ZAMB.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228471"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SCREEN GRAB"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pollak, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">REVIEW</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Circuits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000907T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E1DA1739F934A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="766" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On Some Corporate Internet Sites, It's Not All Business</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL POLLAK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pollak, Michael</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Some corporate Web sites include entertaining options reflecting product's special place in modern culture; sampling of such sites; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WORK and play have a wonderful way of merging on the Internet. Take the prosaic corporate site. There is probably not much you can do to liven up, say, North American Veeblefetzer: product pictures, locations, corporate staff, how to order, shareholder information, Our Founder, and so on.</p>
        <p>Then there are corporate sites that beg to be enjoyed, the cyberspace equivalent of the time-traveling DeLorean in ''Back to the Future.'' One essential element is a corporate history that goes beyond nuts and bolts and shows an appreciation, nay, respect, for the product's special place in modern culture, even if it wasn't exactly what the company intended. Here are several that meet that standard.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WORK and play have a wonderful way of merging on the Internet. Take the prosaic corporate site. There is probably not much you can do to liven up, say, North American Veeblefetzer: product pictures, locations, corporate staff, how to order, shareholder information, Our Founder, and so on.</p>
        <p>Then there are corporate sites that beg to be enjoyed, the cyberspace equivalent of the time-traveling DeLorean in ''Back to the Future.'' One essential element is a corporate history that goes beyond nuts and bolts and shows an appreciation, nay, respect, for the product's special place in modern culture, even if it wasn't exactly what the company intended. Here are several that meet that standard.</p>
        <p>Frank J. Zamboni &amp; Company of Paramount, Calif. (www.zamboni .com), now in its 51st year, acknowledges the skating fans who have grown to love its efficient, boxy ice-resurfacing machines, which have a top speed of nine miles an hour, according to the trivia page. Oh, yes, a trivia page. Also, an online Pro Shop offering shirts, jackets, coin banks and -- this is truly inspired -- a pewter Zamboni Monopoly token.</p>
        <p>The Zamboni Story takes the reader back to the Iceland skating rink in Paramount, built in 1939 by Mr. Zamboni and his brother, Lawrence. It is still operating, the site notes. ''In fact, it's not unusual to see Zambonis driving down the neighborhood streets on their way to be tested at Iceland,'' the site says, suggesting yet another Southern California tourist attraction. There are pictures of early machines and the immortal No. 1, the Model A of 1949, which has been restored. Zamboni No. 2 caught the eye of Sonja Henie, who bought it for her traveling ice show in 1950, and immortality was on its way.</p>
        <p>The Makin' Ice page has a schematic showing how a Zamboni works. There are snapshots showing Zambonis with Snoopy, at the Boston Garden, at the Winter Olympics, in Japan and elsewhere.</p>
        <p>If you had to pick a single site devoted to the American fad, it would be hard to top the Wham-O Inc. page (www.wham-o.com). Founded in California by Arthur Melin and Richard Knerr, the company was named for the sound made by its slingshot, and for a while in the 1950's and 60's, it was the Microsoft of novelty producers. Frisbees. Hula Hoops. Superballs. Do-It-Yourself $119 fallout shelters. Chubby Checker Limbo sets.</p>
        <p>Wham-O's history page is a hoot. When Mr. Melin traveled to Africa in the 1960's, it says, he encountered a fish that laid its eggs in the mud during the dry season; when the rains came, the eggs hatched. The Web site says: ''Ah-ha, thought Melin. Sell chunks of mud, add water, and voila, instant aquarium. Millions of dollars of orders for Instant Fish were taken.</p>
        <p>''Unfortunately,the fish brought back to America wouldn't mate, so no fish eggs, no mud and the end of a great idea.''</p>
        <p>Frisbee has its own historical time line, starting in the 1920's, when Yale students were throwing pie tins from the Frisbie Pie Company of Bridgeport, Conn. There is a link to an article in Scientific American magazine on the aerodynamics of the Frisbee.</p>
        <p>A private tribute site honoring the Superball, and not affiliated with Wham-O, is www.superballs.com. It includes an extensive history and even reprints the 1966 patent by the inventor, a chemist named Norman H. Stingley.</p>
        <p>Then there is the story of chewing gum, on the site of the William Wrigley Jr. Company of Chicago (www.wrigley.com). The history starts off with the ancient Greeks and the mastic tree; North American Indians and spruce gum; and chicle, from the latex juice of the sapodilla tree. There is some corporate back-patting involving the psychological satisfaction of chewing, but we do learn that Wrigley originally offered his gum as premiums for boxes of baking soda and that his first two gum brands were Lotta and Vassar. A page notes that the farmland required to grow mint for Wrigley totals 53 square miles.</p>
        <p>Moving from underneath the school desk to its top, Binney &amp; Smith's Crayola site (www.crayola .com) is user- , parent- and teacher-friendly. In addition to the usual corporate information and helpful hints (stain removal is one of them), there is an online tour of the Crayola Factory museum in Easton, Pa., and a wide array of craft and entertainment projects. An online feature lets children print out their own cards and posters to color.</p>
        <p>SCREEN GRAB</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
