<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Yankees' Payroll Reaches 9 Figures</title>
    <meta content="01PAYR$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211637"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trades (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cleveland Indians</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chass, Murray</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Justice, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Cleveland Indians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Los Angeles Dodgers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trades (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000701T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE7D71439F932A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="786" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Yankees' Payroll Reaches 9 Figures</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MURRAY CHASS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chass, Murray</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Yankees payroll is highest in major leagues, topping $100 million after acquisition of David Justice from Cleveland Indians along with his $7 million salary (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Yankees did not need Sammy Sosa or Juan Gonzalez to establish a historic payroll plateau. The acquisition of David Justice did the job just fine.</p>
        <p>In obtaining Justice from the Cleveland Indians, the Yankees inherited his $7 million salary, which catapulted their payroll beyond the $100 million mark, making them the first baseball team to wade in those expensive waters. George Steinbrenner, the Yankees' principal owner, does not like to establish such standards, but he cannot escape this one.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Yankees did not need Sammy Sosa or Juan Gonzalez to establish a historic payroll plateau. The acquisition of David Justice did the job just fine.</p>
        <p>In obtaining Justice from the Cleveland Indians, the Yankees inherited his $7 million salary, which catapulted their payroll beyond the $100 million mark, making them the first baseball team to wade in those expensive waters. George Steinbrenner, the Yankees' principal owner, does not like to establish such standards, but he cannot escape this one.</p>
        <p>Although baseball payrolls are computed in different ways for different purposes, the method used by both Major League Baseball and the players association to determine season payrolls puts the Yankees' adjusted payroll at nearly $103 million, or $102,724,260 if all of the players' salaries are added. That total is up from the record level of $92.5 million at which the Yankees began the season.</p>
        <p>The primary change resulted from two trades. In adding Justice, who joined the Yankees yesterday in St. Petersburg, Fla., and sending Ricky Ledee to the Indians, the Yankees exchanged Ledee's $240,000 salary for Justice's $7 million salary. The Indians were delighted with that exchange rate, but the Yankees were not going to let money stand between them and another shot at the World Series.</p>
        <p>Earlier this month, the Yankees got Jose Vizcaino from the Los Angeles Dodgers for Jim Leyritz. That trade added a net of $2.5 million to the Yankees' payroll because Vizcaino has a $3.5 million salary and Leyritz $1 million.</p>
        <p>To help offset the difference, the Dodgers included $500,000 in the deal, but even if that sum were subtracted from the total payroll, the Yankees would still be in the nine-figure payroll area.</p>
        <p>The Indians did not send any money with Justice.</p>
        <p>Historic though it may be, the Yankees' bulging payroll will not evoke any congratulatory notes. They generally see the arrival of the $100 million payroll as further evidence that something drastic has to be done to resolve the growing disparity in payrolls.</p>
        <p>The Dodgers, who began the season with the second-highest payroll, are now more than $15 million behind the Yankees. But at the other end of the salary scale, the four lowest payrolls -- belonging to Minnesota, Florida, Kansas City and Pittsburgh -- do not total the Yankees' figure.</p>
        <p>''We were inexorably marching toward a club being over $100 million,'' Commissioner Bud Selig said, ''so I guess no one will be surprised.''</p>
        <p>Surprisingly, the frugal head of a club somewhere in payroll between the Yankees and their poor cousins was not disgusted that the Yankees had established a landmark figure.</p>
        <p>''That's not a big deal for me,'' he said, speaking on condition of anonymity. ''This is a natural evolution of the game. I might not like it, but so what?''</p>
        <p>A lucrative television contract has enabled the Yankees to spend more than other teams. This is the last year of the Yankees' 12-year, $486 million deal with Cablevision. No other team has earned even half that $40.5 million annual average in that period.</p>
        <p>An even bleaker prospect is ahead for the Yankees' competition. Whether they sign a new contract with Cablevision or embark on their own cable network through YankeeNets, the Yankees will reap far more revenue in the years ahead.</p>
        <p>Analysts have estimated that if the Yankees and Cablevision negotiate another deal, it could be worth $100 million a year to the team that has won the World Series three times in the last four years. Should the Yankees decide to create their own network, they would generate even more revenue.</p>
        <p>Other teams could console themselves because the Yankees added Justice and not Sosa or Gonzalez. If they had succeeded in completing a deal with the Chicago Cubs for Sosa, the Yankees would have had to sign him to a contract extension to secure his needed approval for the trade. That extension would have been worth somewhere in the $16 million to $18 million range.</p>
        <p>The Yankees, whose payroll covers their 25-man roster and seven players on the disabled list, could argue that because Justice has spent nearly half the season with the Indians, the Yankees' share of his salary will actually be $3,615,384.</p>
        <p>But when Major League Baseball and the players association compute a season's payroll, the entire salary is charged to the acquiring team.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
