<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Deciding It's Time to Simplify, Moynihans to Sell Upstate Farm</title>
    <meta content="01FARM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000707T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211605"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Derrymore</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Moynihan, Daniel Patrick (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bumiller, Elisabeth</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Moynihan, Elizabeth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000701T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E5DB1439F932A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="988" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Deciding It's Time to Simplify, Moynihans to Sell Upstate Farm</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELISABETH BUMILLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bumiller, Elisabeth</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Elizabeth and Daniel Patrick Moynihan decide to sell Derrymore, beloved country estate in upstate New York, purchased in 1964; asking price is $1.1 million; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There it was, tucked quietly in between the ads for the $4.5 million Greek Revival and the $2.5 million Colonial, announcing the end of a political era: ''DeMulder Realty Better Homes and Gardens is pleased to offer for sale: Derrymore, beloved country estate of Elizabeth and Senator Daniel Patrick Moynihan.''</p>
        <p>The price, $1.1 million, included two houses, two barns, ''bucolic views,'' pastures, woods, fields, ponds, a stream and ''8,000 feet of road frontage!''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There it was, tucked quietly in between the ads for the $4.5 million Greek Revival and the $2.5 million Colonial, announcing the end of a political era: ''DeMulder Realty Better Homes and Gardens is pleased to offer for sale: Derrymore, beloved country estate of Elizabeth and Senator Daniel Patrick Moynihan.''</p>
        <p>The price, $1.1 million, included two houses, two barns, ''bucolic views,'' pastures, woods, fields, ponds, a stream and ''8,000 feet of road frontage!''</p>
        <p>A phone call to Derrymore in upstate New York took the cheery real estate language of yesterday's advertisement in The Wall Street Journal to a more human dimension. ''It's over 500 acres,'' sighed Elizabeth Moynihan, the retiring senator's wife, who was cleaning out the woodshed that serves as her office while she spoke. ''It's a lot of work to maintain it, for me. Pat doesn't drive, and everyone I know over 70 is doing the same thing. He's giving up the Senate, and I'm giving up the farm.''</p>
        <p>But there are farms, and then there is the Moynihan farm -- the four-term senator's spiritual home, the site of the 19th-century schoolhouse where he has written his 18 books, a political base that tied the man born in Hells Kitchen to the history and hills of upstate.</p>
        <p>Such is the political symbolism of the farm that Hillary Rodham Clinton asked the Moynihans last summer if she could use it to  open her ''listening tour'' of New York State. The unforgettable sight of that day was of Mr. Moynihan slowly walking the woman who was seeking to replace him down the verdant road from his schoolhouse, as if giving away a bride, to the gantlet of press assembled in his hayfield. There were at least 200 reporters, 30 television cameras and 8 satellite dishes.</p>
        <p>''When I woke up this morning and went out on the front step and saw the satellite trucks at the top of the hill,'' Mrs. Moynihan said at the time, ''I felt like a character in 'The Invasion of' -- you know, one of those space alien movies.''</p>
        <p>But that most photographed moment of the Moynihans' lives at the farm -- in the hamlet called Pindars Corners, about 70 miles west of Albany, near Oneonta -- was also an odd one. The couple bought the farm in 1964 (Mrs. Moynihan refused to say for how much) and over the next 36 years rarely if ever used it for political events. Occasionally reporters would interview Mr. Moynihan there, but mostly it was the place where the senator and his wife spent their summers and raised their three children, Tim, 44; Maura, 42; and John, 40.</p>
        <p>But those days are over. ''It's called simplifying your life,'' Mrs. Moynihan said yesterday. ''Life has different cycles. Listen, I've painted these walls, I've painted this woodwork, I've planted these gardens. Who's going to do it? Who's going to take care of it?''</p>
        <p>The senator, a scholar-farmer who never actually gardened, concurred. ''When I see her out there farming the gardens,'' he said yesterday from Washington, ''I think it's time to say, 'Liz, why don't we go over and look at the Botanical Garden in the Bronx?' ''</p>
        <p>The prospective sale, he added, ''breaks your heart a little, but it's time.'' The senator is 73 and still recovering from major back surgery last year. Mrs. Moynihan, who is 70, said her husband's ''insides are fine, the head is great, the infrastructure is a little rocky.''</p>
        <p>The Moynihans said the sale of the farm did not necessarily mean that the senator, whose fourth term is up at the end of this year, would no longer be a resident of New York. The plan, they said, was to buy a smaller country house. ''I don't need over 500 acres,'' Mrs. Moynihan said. ''I don't need two houses, I don't need three ponds.''</p>
        <p>The Moynihans, who also own a condominium on Pennsylvania Avenue in Washington, bought the farm in February 1964, three months after John F. Kennedy's assassination, while Mr. Moynihan was assistant secretary of labor. ''We always wanted a farm,'' Mr. Moynihan said. ''We'd put the dog and the children and so forth in the station wagon and zigzag across Pennsylvania and look around. When Kennedy was assassinated, we were pretty depleted. And one day Liz got in the car with our daughter and just made the trip, got to Oneonta, and went to a real estate agent, and they said, yeah, they had a farm for sale. She saw it first thing and said, 'That's it.' ''</p>
        <p>Mr. Moynihan, then, never actually saw the farm before he bought it? ''Nor did I ever do any of the gardening,'' he replied.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Moynihan said that her real estate agent had received a few calls, and that she was planning to show the farm to one prospective buyer on Monday. Now that the couple had reached the decision to sell -- only last week, she said -- she was eager to have it over with. She was also looking forward to her life post-gardening. ''People have been visiting me for 38 years,'' she said. ''And now I'm going to start visiting them.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  July 7, 2000, Friday  An article on Saturday about the decision by Senator Daniel Patrick Moynihan and his wife, Elizabeth, to sell their upstate farm misstated Mr. Moynihan's birthplace. He was born in Tulsa, Okla., not the Hell's Kitchen section of Manhattan. He moved to New York with his family when he was a child.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: July 7, 2000, Friday</p>
        <p>An article on Saturday about the decision by Senator Daniel Patrick Moynihan and his wife, Elizabeth, to sell their upstate farm misstated Mr. Moynihan's birthplace. He was born in Tulsa, Okla., not the Hell's Kitchen section of Manhattan. He moved to New York with his family when he was a child.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
