<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With Seconds to Spare and Little Grace, Liberty Pulls Out the Victory</title>
    <meta content="01LIBE$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211644"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="WOMEN'S BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Liberty</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Indiana Fever</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Popper, Steve</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000701T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E2D71439F932A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="431" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With Seconds to Spare and Little Grace, Liberty Pulls Out the Victory</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVE POPPER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Popper, Steve</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Liberty defeats Indiana Fever, 72-70 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As they stalked off the Madison Square Garden court at halftime last night, frustrated and a little bit embarrassed, the Liberty players knew that they had to change their strategy and their approach. And in the back of their minds they also knew that the Indiana Fever would eventually cool off.</p>
        <p>The Fever had hardly missed from the opening tip, scoring the game's first 8 points, shooting 54 percent and opening an 18-point lead in the first half. In the second half, the Liberty pressed the action and finally pulled even with 19.2 seconds left. The Liberty had not led the entire night, but the players never believed they would not win the game.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As they stalked off the Madison Square Garden court at halftime last night, frustrated and a little bit embarrassed, the Liberty players knew that they had to change their strategy and their approach. And in the back of their minds they also knew that the Indiana Fever would eventually cool off.</p>
        <p>The Fever had hardly missed from the opening tip, scoring the game's first 8 points, shooting 54 percent and opening an 18-point lead in the first half. In the second half, the Liberty pressed the action and finally pulled even with 19.2 seconds left. The Liberty had not led the entire night, but the players never believed they would not win the game.</p>
        <p>After a timeout with 13.7 seconds to play, the Fever tried to inbound the ball, but Stephanie McCarty's pass went across the floor untouched and out of bounds. The Liberty gave the ball to Crystal Robinson. As the defense converged on her, she drove the lane and passed the ball to Tari Phillips under the basket. Phillips dropped in a layup with 1.5 seconds left, giving the Liberty its first lead of the game. It led to a celebration when the Fever's last-second 3-point attempt missed, giving the Liberty a 72-70 victory.</p>
        <p>''I can't be more proud of the effort and energy that was exerted by this team,'' Liberty Coach Richie Adubato said. ''I told the team before the game, this is professional basketball and you have to respect everybody. On any given night, they are capable of making shots, and they came out and made them.''</p>
        <p>Said Phillips, who made 13 of 19 field-goal attempts and scored a career-high 30 points: ''I'm so happy and delighted that we showed character and determination. We never lost sight of it. It was a gift and a prayer.''</p>
        <p>But the Liberty (7-7) needed full-court pressure to wake itself from its first-half slumber against the Fever (3-10). The Liberty reduced the deficit to 9 early in the second half and, after seeing the deficit grow to 16 with 12:57 remaining, narrowed the margin to 60-50 on a drive by Becky Hammon with 9:04 to play. ''We knew they couldn't shoot like that forever,'' Hammon said. ''We always felt like we were in the game with the shooters we have.''</p>
        <p>The Liberty then made one more frantic push, beginning with a 3-point field goal by Robinson. Hammon converted another 3-pointer, and when Phillips blocked a drive by McCarty, Hammon finished with a layup on the other end, closing the gap to 66-63 and setting the stage for the Liberty's victory.  WOMEN'S BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
