<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>When Biographies Aren't Limited to the Famous and the Dead</title>
    <meta content="01TANK$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Ideas/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211550"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THINK TANK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fox, Margalit</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rose, Phyllis</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Thurman, Judith</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Middlebrook, Diane Wood</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Columns/Think Tank</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000701T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E4D81739F932A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="967" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>When Biographies Aren't Limited to the Famous and the Dead</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Margalit Fox</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fox, Margalit</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Web site, www.bioregistry.com, offers professionally written 2,000-word biography starting at $4,000 written by writers such as Judith Thurman or Diane Wood Middlebrook; site was created by Phyllis Rose, author of The Year of Reading Proust, after building memorial Web page for her mother (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Suppose you want a renowned author to write your life story, but you don't happen to be famous -- or dead.</p>
        <p>Don't despair. Now a new Internet service allows ordinary citizens with somewhat deeper than ordinary pockets to commission custom portraits from eminent biographers like Judith Thurman, Francine du Plessix Gray and Diane Wood Middlebrook.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Suppose you want a renowned author to write your life story, but you don't happen to be famous -- or dead.</p>
        <p>Don't despair. Now a new Internet service allows ordinary citizens with somewhat deeper than ordinary pockets to commission custom portraits from eminent biographers like Judith Thurman, Francine du Plessix Gray and Diane Wood Middlebrook.</p>
        <p>The Web site, called the BioRegistry (www .bioregistry.com), was created by Phyllis Rose, a biographer whose most recent book is ''The Year of Reading Proust.''</p>
        <p>''There has surfaced periodically in the history of biography an interest in what Virginia Woolf called 'the lives of the obscure,' '' Ms. Rose explained. ''Anybody who thinks seriously about biography wants to write about 'ordinary' people, but there's no market for it.''</p>
        <p>So, armed with her Rolodex, Ms. Rose, the author of lives of Woolf and Josephine Baker, set out to create one. She conceived of the site last spring after her mother died and a friend helped her build a memorial Web page. Ms. Rose, who said she had found the experience ''incredibly satisfying,'' realized she could offer a similar service to others. The BioRegistry, which offers memorial portraits as well as profiles of the living, made its debut last November.</p>
        <p>The price of a 2,000-word biography starts at $4,000. (Fees are lower for what the site calls ''well-trained but unpublished'' writers.) The finished pieces can be posted on the BioRegistry site or on the client's own Web site, or they can be privately printed.</p>
        <p>As yet, Ms. Rose said, there have been no takers, so the future success of the site is unclear. But the Bio Registry's real significance may be to expand traditional notions of biography, its authors and their subjects.</p>
        <p>Viewed historically, the site is a natural outgrowth of the time-honored tradition of biography for hire. ''In essence, it's a continuation of what was going on all through the 19th century, where you would have almost vanity-published books of notable citizens,'' said Justin Kaplan, who received a Pulitzer Prize in 1967 for ''Mr. Clemens and Mark Twain.'' (Mr. Kaplan is not in the BioRegistry's stable, though he confessed to fantasies of riding horses out West for months on end while faithfully taking down the life of his tycoon host.)</p>
        <p>In the early 1900's, for instance, Col. William d'Alton Mann, self-styled New York dandy and noted scoundrel, published ''Fads and Fancies of Representative Americans at the Beginning of the 20th Century, Being a Portrayal of Their Tastes, Diversions and Achievements.'' Expensively bound in gold-stamped leather, the book comprised glowing biographical sketches of scores of prominent people, including President Theodore Roosevelt. The cost of inclusion ranged from $1,500 to $9,000, princely sums at the time. (There was a reason Mann could command such prices: those who didn't shell out for a biography would see their peccadilloes reported in unsparing detail in Town Topics, a weekly scandal sheet he also published.)</p>
        <p>But where the BioRegistry breaks with tradition -- besides eschewing blackmail -- is in its ecumenicalism. Much as the advent of photography democratized artistic portraiture (oil paintings for Astors, Kodak moments for you and me), the new electronic technology, Ms. Rose hopes, will broaden the definition of who is considered a fit subject for a written portrait.</p>
        <p>It also broadens opportunities for the biographer. ''Biography is absolutely the worst-paid endeavor in the world per hour of work,'' said Ms. Thurman, who received a National Book Award in 1983 for a life of Isak Dinesen and whose biography of Colette, ''Secrets of the Flesh,'' was a National Book Award finalist last year. ''This is an idea also for letting very skilled biographers use their talents in a way that would not be arduous and make some money, to be honest.''</p>
        <p>For each prospective project that interests them, Ms. Rose explained, BioRegistry authors will submit fee requirements -- say, $2 or $5 a word. The client will be charged twice that amount, with half going to the writer and half to the BioRegistry.</p>
        <p>Ms. Gray, the author of ''At Home With the Marquis de Sade,'' said she had signed on because she saw the Internet as a refreshing alternative to the impersonal, conglomeratized world of book publishing. ''Many of us are just fed up by all the traditional channels,'' she explained. ''It seems to me that working in a small community like this, there might be a new release, a new way out.''</p>
        <p>For Ms. Middlebrook, the author of lives of the poet Anne Sexton and the cross-dressing jazz musician Billy Tipton, the site is an acknowledgment of the singular demands of her craft. ''I was quite fascinated that she had hit upon this idea for expressing the occupation of the biographer as an occupation,'' she said of Ms. Rose. ''It's not that I see it as a source of work so much as a source of professional identity.''</p>
        <p>On its face, however, writing a BioRegistry portrait might seem closer to the work of a press agent than to biography. Since background materials are furnished by the client (warts included at the client's discretion), the writers are freed from the burden of doing original research -- and of providing journalistic balance.</p>
        <p>Ms. Rose's authors say they're not troubled. ''I do lots of journalism, some of it serious and some of it not,'' Ms. Thurman said. ''I feel no shame or problem with navigating back and forth into deep and shallow waters.''</p>
        <p>But whether Ms. Thurman's next project will be the life story of a 21-year-old dot-com millionaire remains to be seen. ''This appeals to me abstractly,'' she said. ''I'm not sure, when it comes down to the crunch, that if I'm writing something else I'll be willing to tear myself away and go do a private commission.''</p>
        <p>THINK TANK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
