<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CAMPAIGN BRIEFING</title>
    <meta content="Y01CAM$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211609"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000701T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E2DB1439F932A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1817" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CAMPAIGN BRIEFING</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE REFORM PARTY</p>
        <p>PEROT WILL NOT RUN -- Ross Perot, a two-time presidential candidate, decided yesterday against putting his name on the Reform Party's primary ballot, removing a big potential roadblock for Patrick J. Buchanan's candidacy. A Perot spokesman, Russell Verney, said Mr. Perot decided against running because he had no intention of actually competing for the White House against Gov. George W. Bush of Texas, the Republican contender, and Vice President Al Gore, his Democratic rival. A daylong series of meetings at Mr. Perot's office in Dallas included ''intense pressure'' to put his name on the ballot in an effort to stop Mr. Buchanan, Mr. Verney said. But Mr. Perot felt it would be unethical to seek the nomination but not really run, he said. Another difficulty was that Mr. Perot would have appeared on only about half the states' ballots in November. His decision to forgo a place on the primary ballot leaves two candidates who say they have enough support to win spots there: Mr. Buchanan, a former Republican, and the Natural Law Party candidate, John Hagelin.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE REFORM PARTY</p>
        <p>PEROT WILL NOT RUN -- Ross Perot, a two-time presidential candidate, decided yesterday against putting his name on the Reform Party's primary ballot, removing a big potential roadblock for Patrick J. Buchanan's candidacy. A Perot spokesman, Russell Verney, said Mr. Perot decided against running because he had no intention of actually competing for the White House against Gov. George W. Bush of Texas, the Republican contender, and Vice President Al Gore, his Democratic rival. A daylong series of meetings at Mr. Perot's office in Dallas included ''intense pressure'' to put his name on the ballot in an effort to stop Mr. Buchanan, Mr. Verney said. But Mr. Perot felt it would be unethical to seek the nomination but not really run, he said. Another difficulty was that Mr. Perot would have appeared on only about half the states' ballots in November. His decision to forgo a place on the primary ballot leaves two candidates who say they have enough support to win spots there: Mr. Buchanan, a former Republican, and the Natural Law Party candidate, John Hagelin.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>THE REPUBLICANS</p>
        <p>PROMOTING A NEW NO. 2 -- With former Senator John Danforth of Missouri having taken himself out of the running, Gov. Frank Keating of Oklahoma has become the speculative name-of-the-moment as a potential running mate for George W. Bush. Mr. Keating's name surfaced at midweek on the Internet as the latest favorite of the Republican presidential contender, though with caveats that everything could change. The Bush campaign took the rumor in stride. ''It's not true,'' the campaign spokesman, Ari Fleischer, said. ''The governor has made no decision.'' Mr. Bush is to meet at his Texas ranch on Monday with Dick Cheney, the former defense secretary who is heading the vice-presidential search, but only for an update, Mr. Fleischer said.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>THE SENATE</p>
        <p>KENNEDY CHALLENGER OFF BALLOT -- Jack E. Robinson, the entreprenuer who had hoped to be the Republican challenger to Senator Edward M. Kennedy, did not have enough valid signatures to put his name on the ballot, leaving Massachusetts without a Republican contender for the Senate. The state ballot law commission ruled yesterday that 153 of the 10,139 signatures Mr. Robinson turned in on June 6 were invalid, leaving him 14 short of the 10,000 signatures he needed to secure a spot on the ballot. The commission, a panel of three Republicans, one Democrat and one independent appointed by the governor, found that 90 those invalid signatures were forgeries.  Mr. Robinson has five days to appeal the ruling. Without a Republican on the ballot, Mr. Kennedy will face only Carla Howell of the Libertarian Party on Election Day.</p>
        <p>(NYT)</p>
        <p>THE UNIONS</p>
        <p>CLINTON TWEAKS G.O.P. -- President Clinton said in Philadelphia yesterday that Republicans would talk a good game when they arrived for their convention in late July but were not eager to point out the serious differences that divide the two parties. ''You'll have the awfulest time trying to figure out what the differences are,'' Mr. Clinton told a group of union members. ''They're going to love everybody and help everybody.'' Speaking at a gathering of the American Federation of Federal, State, County and Municipal Employees, Mr. Clinton recited a litany of issues on which Democrats and Republicans diverge, from the patients' bill of rights to the minimum wage to gun control. Mr. Clinton also questioned Gov. George W. Bush's commitment to Hispanics, saying he had not urged Republican senators to confirm Enrique Moreno, a Texan whom Mr. Clinton nominated to be a federal judge. ''If he had asked them to give him a hearing, they would have done it,'' Mr. Clinton said of Mr. Bush. ''He didn't say a word.''</p>
        <p>Marc Lacey (NYT)</p>
        <p>CONTRADICTING BUSH -- A ''Texas Truth Squad'' made up of union members from George W. Bush's home state chose the city where he will be nominated for president to begin a national speaking tour intended to besmirch the governor's record. The squad, consisting of a teacher, a prison guard, a food worker and a social worker, made its debut on Thursday at a union luncheon in Philadelphia presided over by John J. Sweeney, the president of the A.F.L.-C.I.O., which has endorsed Vice President Al Gore. Squad members asserted in a series of short speeches that during Mr. Bush's two terms as governor,  Texas has consistently ranked near the bottom in providing health insurance for children, retirement pensions, environmental protection and pay for state workers. Taking special aim at Mr. Bush's claim to be an education reformer, the group said he had diverted money from public schools and tried to raid teacher retirement funds at a time when the state ranked 45th in the College Board test scores. The squad is scheduled to make at least a dozen appearances around the country before Election Day.</p>
        <p>(NYT)</p>
        <p>THE HOUSE</p>
        <p>CROSSING PARTY LINES -- Representative James A. Traficant Jr., Democrat of Ohio, has said he will break ranks and vote to keep a Republican, Representative J. Dennis Hastert, as speaker of the House next year, a pledge that complicates his own party's bid to gain control on the House in the fall elections. In an interview on the nationally syndicated ''Hannity &amp; Colmes'' radio program, Mr. Traficant, a maverick who is serving his eighth term in the House, said, ''Hastert's a good man, and I'm going to vote for for him for speaker, and I don't give a damn who knows it.'' The vote for speaker is the first major roll-call taken when a new Congress convenes. The party that wins that vote controls the flow of legislation to the floor for the next two years and appoints chairmen of all committees and subcommittees. If Mr. Traficant does as he says he will, Democrats will have to win seven seats in November to gain control.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
