<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Killings Drive Indonesians Into Risky Boats and Dangerous Seas</title>
    <meta content="Y01IND$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211564"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Indonesia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Maluku Islands (Indonesia)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mydans, Seth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Indonesia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Indonesia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000701T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E3DF1439F932A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="834" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Killings Drive Indonesians Into Risky Boats and Dangerous Seas</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SETH MYDANS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mydans, Seth</byline>
      <dateline>JAKARTA, Indonesia, June 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Fighting in Maluku islands, Indonesia, between Muslims and Christians spurs many islanders to flee, driving them into risky boats and dangerous seas; nearly 500 people are feared dead following sinking of their battered ferry; passengers were desperately fleeing Moslem gangs that were killing people, apparently in revenge for what they describe as wave of killings by Christians in December; photo; map (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>They pushed and jostled in a panic to board the battered ferry, witnesses said, fleeing a massacre in which up to 200 of their fellow villagers had been killed.</p>
        <p>They were the lucky ones, mostly women and children as well as more than 30 wounded survivors, cramming aboard the old, wood-hulled Cahaya Bahari, nearly doubling its licensed load to almost 500 passengers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>They pushed and jostled in a panic to board the battered ferry, witnesses said, fleeing a massacre in which up to 200 of their fellow villagers had been killed.</p>
        <p>They were the lucky ones, mostly women and children as well as more than 30 wounded survivors, cramming aboard the old, wood-hulled Cahaya Bahari, nearly doubling its licensed load to almost 500 passengers.</p>
        <p>But only hours into their journey from the far eastern Maluku islands of Indonesia to a haven on the island of Sulawesi, the ship's crew sent a distress signal, saying that the engines were dead and that the ship was taking on water in heavy seas.</p>
        <p>Nothing more was heard from the ship, and tonight, 30 hours later, rescuers said they had found no trace of the Cahaya Bahari or its passengers and crew.</p>
        <p>''It would be a miracle if we could find anyone still alive,'' Solaeman, the head of the search and rescue team, told the Reuters news agency.</p>
        <p>The state-run Antara news agency said a life buoy had been found, but it was not clear whether it came from the missing ship. Searchers pulled two men from the stormy waters, but Mr. Solaeman said they were fishermen from a separate capsized boat -- their lives saved, perhaps, because of the loss of the Cahaya Bahari.</p>
        <p>Officials said strong currents might have swept the foundering vessel or its passengers out toward the mouth of the Pacific Ocean in stormy seas where the waves reached nine feet in height. They said the waters were thick with sharks.</p>
        <p>The Associated Press reported that at the small port of Manado, the vessel's destination and the capital of the province of North Sulawesi, hundreds of relatives -- many of them also refugees from a long-running religious conflict in the Maluku islands -- clustered at the waterfront, sobbing and whispering.</p>
        <p>''All we can do is pray and hope,'' said Ferry Potoboda, who said he had 20 relatives on the missing vessel, including wounded victims and children.</p>
        <p>The massacre on May 19 at the village of Duma on Halmahera Island was one of the worst incidents in a conflict between Christians and Muslims that has taken the lives of more than 2,500 people since it erupted 18 months ago.</p>
        <p>It involved an attack by Muslim gangs -- apparently including fighters who had traveled to the region on interisland ferries -- in what they described as revenge for a wave of killings by Christians on the island last December.</p>
        <p>More than 90 percent of Indonesia's 210 million people are Muslim, but in the Maluku islands, Muslims and Christians are evenly divided. This has made the area fertile ground for agitators seeking to create unrest in the hope of weakening the central government in Jakarta.</p>
        <p>The fighting first erupted in January 1999, in a marketplace fight  in Ambon that witnesses said appeared to be part of a planned provocation to touch off a local war.</p>
        <p>Today in Ambon, the small, pretty city that is the capital of the Maluku islands, residents reported that there was some easing of violence four days after President Abdurrahman Wahid declared a state of emergency.</p>
        <p>But it was not clear why the violence might have lessened. The military is already in control of Ambon but has lost much of its peacekeeping function as soldiers have turned against each other according to their religions, arming, aiding and sometimes apparently leading the local fighters.</p>
        <p>''Soldiers have broken ranks and joined the fighting as partisans, and, as a result, Indonesian troops right now have virtually no credibility in areas where a neutral force is most desperately needed,'' said Human Rights Watch, the New York-based monitoring group.</p>
        <p>As the fighting has continued, ferries from Ambon and elsewhere in the Maluku islands have carried away thousands of refugees.</p>
        <p>Among other destinations, both Muslims and Christians have fled to separate religious enclaves on the island of Sulawesi, where the refugees aboard the Cahaya Bahari were headed.</p>
        <p>When the killings have flared, as they did last week in Halmahera, the islands' small ports have become scenes of panic and anguish. Crowds fight their way up narrow gangplanks, passing their belongings and their children over their heads. Some even shinny up the ropes that moor the vessels.</p>
        <p>They are exchanging one danger for another. Indonesia's ferries are badly maintained and overloaded, and the rough seas of the monsoon season can be deadly. Disasters at sea are a way of life in Indonesia's broad archipelago of thousands of islands.</p>
        <p>Hundreds of passengers have already died this year. Among them were more than 40 people aboard the Masnait, a small ferry that capsized and sank last month. They too were refugees fleeing the fighting in Ambon.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
