<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>F.B.I. Watched an American Who Was Killed in Chile Coup</title>
    <meta content="01CHIL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211642"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Chile</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Bureau of Investigation</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schemo, Diana Jean</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Teruggi, Frank</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pinochet, Augusto (Gen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Chile</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Chile</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000701T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E3D71439F932A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="746" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>F.B.I. Watched an American Who Was Killed in Chile Coup</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DIANA JEAN SCHEMO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schemo, Diana Jean</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Newly declassified documents show that US FBI collected intelligence on American student living in Chile who was killed soon after Gen Augusto Pinochet's takeover of Chile in 1973; student identified as Frank R Teruggi Jr; case reviwed (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Federal Bureau of Investigation collected intelligence on an American student living in Chile who was killed soon after Gen. Augusto Pinochet's takeover of Chile in 1973, according to newly declassified documents made public today.</p>
        <p>In a December 1972 report from one informant, the F.B.I. said that the student, Frank R. Teruggi Jr., had attended a ''Conference on Anti-Imperialist Strategy and Action'' held by former Peace Corps volunteers who, the F.B.I. said, ''espouse support of Cuba and all third world revolutionaries.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Federal Bureau of Investigation collected intelligence on an American student living in Chile who was killed soon after Gen. Augusto Pinochet's takeover of Chile in 1973, according to newly declassified documents made public today.</p>
        <p>In a December 1972 report from one informant, the F.B.I. said that the student, Frank R. Teruggi Jr., had attended a ''Conference on Anti-Imperialist Strategy and Action'' held by former Peace Corps volunteers who, the F.B.I. said, ''espouse support of Cuba and all third world revolutionaries.''</p>
        <p>Though Chilean authorities have never confirmed that Mr. Teruggi was executed, he was arrested at his apartment days after the coup and tortured at the National Stadium, witnesses said. His body was discovered in the morgue 10 days later, riddled with bullet holes.</p>
        <p>The document was one of several hundred released today as part of a major declassification project -- ordered by President Clinton last year -- on rights abuses under General Pinochet's 1973-90 dictatorship.</p>
        <p>But today's release, which represented the final government disclosures on three Americans killed in Chile during the dictatorship, disappointed family members and human rights activists. While the documents offered some details, they broke no new ground as to the circumstances under which the Americans died. In addition to Mr. Teruggi, they were Charles Horman, an American journalist whose plight was portrayed in the 1982 movie ''Missing,'' and Boris Weisfeiler, a mathematics professor who disappeared in 1985.</p>
        <p>The Central Intelligence Agency released only six documents concerning Mr. Horman's death. It released a dozen or so more on the death of Mr. Teruggi, all concerning the attempts of the dead man's father to see a document the agency refused to release 24 years ago. The intelligence agency continued to withhold that document today, arguing that its information was provided by a foreign intelligence service.</p>
        <p>Joyce Horman, whose husband was killed at age 31, held up documents no more than an inch thick, many with chunks of black lines keeping whole paragraphs secret. ''Either they're withholding documents,'' she said, ''or they really didn't do anything to protect an American citizen or to investigate his detention in Chile at that time.''</p>
        <p>The only new insight Ms. Horman gleaned came from an informant who approached the United States Embassy in 1987 to say that Mr. Horman had been killed in the National Stadium the night of Sept. 19, 1973, for being a ''foreign extremist.''  On learning that the man they had killed was an American citizen, stadium officials panicked and had his body dumped on the streets, he said. But American Embassy officials had doubts about the informant's credibility, and lost contact with him.</p>
        <p>About half of the documents released today involved Mr. Weisfeiler, 44, who apparently was picked up by the military while hitchhiking in Chile. His body was never recovered.</p>
        <p>At her home in Newton, Mass., Mr. Weisfeiler's sister, Olga, spent the day combing through the documents, and they confirmed what she had gradually come to suspect since a Chilean lawyer reopened her brother's case this year: that her brother had been tortured and killed at a secretive concentration camp.</p>
        <p>The F.B.I. report, though covering events in 1971, was written the following year, after Mr. Terruggi took up residence in Chile and before the 1973 coup. In addition to noting his attendance at the Peace Corps conference, the report said a Chicago-area group, whose goals it described as furthering the ''Socialist revolution,'' had sent Mr. Terruggi to Chile.</p>
        <p>Though the documents released today do not indicate that the F.B.I. shared its information with Chilean authorities, the insinuations reappeared in the Chilean military's references to him after he was killed.</p>
        <p>The F.B.I. report did not allege any illegality in Mr. Teruggi's actions, and he traveled to Chile to support the elected Socialist government of Salvador Allende. But after his killing, Chilean military officers portrayed him as a revolutionary in Chile to ''discredit the governing junta,'' an unfounded charge because the junta did not exist until a few days before his death.</p>
        <p>A spokeswoman, Tracy Silberling, said there would be no comment on the bureau's report on Mr. Teruggi.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
