<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Downturn in Underwriting As Markets Show Volatility</title>
    <meta content="Y01UNDE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211583"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Thomson Financial Securities Data</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcgeehan, Patrick</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000701T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E0DE1439F932A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="991" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Downturn in Underwriting As Markets Show Volatility</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICK McGEEHAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mcgeehan, Patrick</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sharp downturn in Nasdaq stock market in April doused market for new issues of stock that had been strong in first quarter; Thomson Financial Securities Data reports $451 billion raised in US by investment banks, declined 24 percent from second-quarter 1999; list ranking managing underwriters of corporate bonds by dollar amounts (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On Wall Street, the second quarter roared in like a wildfire then fizzled to a campfire.</p>
        <p>A sharp downturn in the Nasdaq stock market in April doused the market for new issues of stock that had been strong in the first quarter. By late June, dozens of companies had shelved plans to go public, and some that tested the market were sorely disappointed. And rising interest rates depressed the market for all sorts of new corporate bonds, especially junk bonds, which are issued by companies with poor credit ratings.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On Wall Street, the second quarter roared in like a wildfire then fizzled to a campfire.</p>
        <p>A sharp downturn in the Nasdaq stock market in April doused the market for new issues of stock that had been strong in the first quarter. By late June, dozens of companies had shelved plans to go public, and some that tested the market were sorely disappointed. And rising interest rates depressed the market for all sorts of new corporate bonds, especially junk bonds, which are issued by companies with poor credit ratings.</p>
        <p>All told, the amount of money raised in the United States by investment banks -- $451 billion -- was down 24 percent from the second quarter of 1999. The total of stock and bond offerings in American markets fell to 3,823 in the second quarter from 5,047 in the second quarter of 1999. Measured by money raised in the United States capital markets, last quarter ranked eighth, according to Thomson Financial Securities Data in Newark.</p>
        <p>The slump hit investment banks just as they were rushing to hire new bankers and were raising pay and improving benefits to keep their employees from leaving for Internet start-ups. Disclosed fees for underwriting new issues sank about 45 percent, to $2.64 billion, from $4.8 billion in the first quarter of 2000, and about 20 percent from $3.29 billion in the second quarter of 1999.</p>
        <p>''The first quarter was as heady a market as we'd ever seen,'' said Jeff Edwards, co-head of stock capital markets at Merrill Lynch &amp; Company. But after the stock market swooned in mid-April, he said, ''there was a general pullback of all investors, retail and institutional.''</p>
        <p>Despite the newfound reluctance of investors to buy shares of untested companies, underwriters managed to float some landmark new issues. Most notable was the $10.6 billion spinoff of shares in AT&amp;T Wireless, the biggest initial offering by an American company.</p>
        <p>The $9 billion of that total raised in the United States accounted for more than one-third of the $24.5 billion raised through first-time stock offerings in the quarter and it accounted for the bulk of the initial offering proceeds raised by two of the biggest investment banks, Merrill Lynch and the Salomon Smith Barney unit of Citigroup. Each of those firms was a lead manager, along with the Goldman Sachs Group, of the AT&amp;T Wireless offering, and received credit for one-third of the United States proceeds, or about $3 billion.</p>
        <p>Aside from that deal, Merrill raised about $900 million in initial offerings and Salomon raised about $750 million, according to Securities Data.</p>
        <p>An initial offering is the most lucrative type of underwriting, leaving investment banks with as much as 7 percent of the money raised from investors.</p>
        <p>Goldman Sachs again was the leading underwriter of initial offerings and all issues of common stock, commanding about 25 percent of the market so far this year.</p>
        <p>Goldman managed several huge offerings during the rockiest period of the quarter in April, including the $4.6 billion initial offering of the insurer MetLife and the $3 billion spinoff of the T-Online subsidiary of Deutsche Telekom of Germany.</p>
        <p>Looking back over the quarter, Mark Tercek, co-head of Goldman's stock underwriting business, said, ''While market conditions were more difficult, we were still able to get a lot of deals done for companies of all stripes.''</p>
        <p>But, he added, investors are taking a more disciplined approach than they were during the I.P.O. frenzy that ran through much of last year and into the first quarter. ''That was a very ebullient, extraordinary period of time and it largely is over,'' Mr. Tercek said.</p>
        <p>After a weak May, the market for new stock started to recover in June and companies rushed back in to sell stock. Still, the market for new stocks was significantly stronger than the market for debt issued by corporations. As the Federal Reserve continued to raise short-term interest rates, investors were wary of buying bonds, especially those that mature in 10 to 30 years.</p>
        <p>Investors showed a distinct aversion to risky bonds promising high yields. There were only 66 junk bond offerings in the quarter, down almost two-thirds from 178 in the second quarter of 1999. They raised just $7.5 billion, down from $32.2 billion a year earlier.</p>
        <p>The virtual shutdown of the junk bond market came at the worst time for many young Internet companies that found that they could not finance their growth plans either by issuing stock or by borrowing in the public bond markets. That situation left some Internet retailers and other electronic-commerce companies no choice but to be acquired or go out of business.</p>
        <p>For blue-chip companies, the borrowing was easier at the end of the quarter, after the Labor Department's report on employment in May eased fears of further rate increases by the Fed.</p>
        <p>After that report hinted that the economy might be cooling, investors showed more interest in high-grade corporate bonds that mature in 10 years or more, said Randy Snook, head of corporate bond underwriting at Goldman Sachs.</p>
        <p>''Much of the year has been unusual in that the amount of short-term issuance has been quite high,'' Mr. Snook said. ''You can count the number of 30-year bonds issued from corporations on two hands.''</p>
        <p>Underwriters were encouraged by the reception for a $9.5 billion sale of bonds in the United States by Deutsche Telekom, which was split almost evenly among 5-year, 10-year and 30-year securities.</p>
        <p>''We're not expecting an avalanche of activity,'' Mr. Snook said. But, he said, ''We feel we have entered a period of much better market conditions than we've had in much of the first and second quarters.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
