<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rescue of Retail Chain May Threaten Recovery in Japan</title>
    <meta content="Y01YEN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211584"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Japan</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sogo Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Strom, Stephanie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000701T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E0DE1439F932A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="810" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rescue of Retail Chain May Threaten Recovery in Japan</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHANIE STROM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Strom, Stephanie</byline>
      <dateline>TOKYO, June 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Japan's Financial Reconstruction Commission says government will spend 97 billion yen ($924 million) to help rescue Sogo Co, averting major retail chain bankruptcy but reigniting concerns about Japan's economic future; accord paves way for Sogo's other banks to forgive over 630 billion yen in loans; decision to rescue Sogo and ease pressure on banks to which Sogo owes $16 billion raises questions about where government will draw line on use of public money and its commitment to economic reform; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Japanese financial authorities bailed out a highly indebted department store company today, averting a major corporate bankruptcy but reigniting concerns about Japan's economic future just as it is showing signs of breaking out of a decade-long malaise.</p>
        <p>The Financial Reconstruction Commission, the agency charged with overseeing reform in the banking system, said the government would spend 97 billion yen, or $924 million at current exchange rates, of taxpayer money to help rescue the store chain, the Sogo Company.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Japanese financial authorities bailed out a highly indebted department store company today, averting a major corporate bankruptcy but reigniting concerns about Japan's economic future just as it is showing signs of breaking out of a decade-long malaise.</p>
        <p>The Financial Reconstruction Commission, the agency charged with overseeing reform in the banking system, said the government would spend 97 billion yen, or $924 million at current exchange rates, of taxpayer money to help rescue the store chain, the Sogo Company.</p>
        <p>The agreement paved the way for Sogo's other banks to forgive more than 630 billion yen in loans, or roughly $6 billion. The banks had wavered for weeks on whether to grant Sogo's request for the debt forgiveness, one of the largest loan write-offs in Japanese bank history.</p>
        <p>But the agreement may have created bigger problems for the government, which faces heightened scrutiny of its use of taxpayer money.</p>
        <p>The decision to rescue the company -- and ease pressure on the banks to which Sogo owes a total of $16 billion -- raises questions about where the government will draw the line on the use of public money. The precedent set today could mean that thousands of companies will press for debt forgiveness.</p>
        <p>More important, the government's decision casts doubt upon its commitment to a serious overhaul of the economy, which has yet to decisively rebound from a decade of decline. ''It suggests that every time the Japanese government looks over the precipice and sees what it means to clean up this economy, it's just too scary,'' said Ronald Bevacqua, senior economist at Commerz Securities in Tokyo.</p>
        <p>Japan is not the first country to aid a private company. The United States rescued the Chrysler Corporation 20 years ago, and South Korea used public money to prop up businesses during its economic crisis.</p>
        <p>But Japan has taken the concept further. The government has spent a minimum of 7.7 trillion yen, or more than $80 billion at current exchange rates, to restore the banking system. The government has offered small and midsize businesses 30 trillion yen in loan guarantees to keep them afloat -- only to see a large number of them fail anyway.</p>
        <p>At the height of the banking crisis in early 1998, the Bank of Japan bought corporate debt securities to keep companies from suffering a short-term cash crisis. The Japan Development Bank was permitted to extend emergency credit lines to struggling companies like the Nissan Motor Company.</p>
        <p>But Sogo is not Nissan, never mind Chrysler. ''I think it is sensible to forgive some debt as we go through the process of restructuring the economy here, but is this the right company?'' asked James P. Fiorillo, senior banking analyst at ING Barings in Tokyo. ''I think not.''</p>
        <p>Sogo's restructuring plan envisions a return to positive net worth more than a decade from now. And there is widespread doubt whether Sogo can entice shoppers back into its dowdy stores.</p>
        <p>The government had hoped to avoid a very public bailout of a private company. But it was pushed into that position by Shinsei Bank, the former Long-Term Credit Bank, which the government sold last year to a private group led by an American investment firm, Ripplewood Holdings L.L.C. Under the terms, the government must buy back for the next three years any loans made by Long-Term Credit Bank whose book value falls by 20 percent or more.</p>
        <p>Sogo's loans fell into that category, and on Wednesday, Shinsei asked the Deposit Insurance Corporation to buy back 97 billion yen of the 200 billion yen Sogo owes it. Shinsei had already set aside 103 billion yen in reserves against a potential default on the loans. Once it became clear that the government would be holding the loans, not Shinsei, Sogo's other large creditors threatened not to forgive Sogo debts unless the government did the same.</p>
        <p>While the government was worried about destroying Sogo and putting its 9,900 employees out of work, it was more concerned about the impact of Sogo's failure on the banking system, according to officials: Many of Sogo's creditors had not adequately reserved against potential default.</p>
        <p>The fact that the government must still worry about the stability and soundness of banks that have already received public assistance and are supposedly in the process of seriously revamping their business practices suggests that the financial crisis is not really over.</p>
        <p>''We're still in crisis management mode in Japan,'' Mr. Fiorillo said.</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
