<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Museum to Visit From an Armchair</title>
    <meta content="01BARN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211614"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Circuses</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Endowment for the Humanities</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">City University of New York (CUNY)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kelley, Tina</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barnum, Phineas Taylor (1810-91)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Circuses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000701T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE3DA1439F932A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="928" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Museum to Visit From an Armchair</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TINA KELLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kelley, Tina</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Center for Media and Learning and New Media Lab, both part of CUNY Graduate Center, rebuild PT Barnum's American Museum on World Wide Web; combination zoo, museum lecture hall, wax museum and freak show, museum burned down twice in late 1800's; supported in part by grant from National Endowment for the Humanities, Web site provides full archive of information about museum and relevant 19th century subjects; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was a combination zoo, museum, lecture hall, wax museum, theater and freak show, a Museum of Un-Natural History that according to one historian was ''a central site in the development of American popular culture.'' It burned in July 1865, was rebuilt a few blocks away, and burned again in 1868.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, P. T. Barnum's American Museum opened once again, on the World Wide Web, a medium perhaps well suited to the circus-meister's fantabulous claims.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was a combination zoo, museum, lecture hall, wax museum, theater and freak show, a Museum of Un-Natural History that according to one historian was ''a central site in the development of American popular culture.'' It burned in July 1865, was rebuilt a few blocks away, and burned again in 1868.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, P. T. Barnum's American Museum opened once again, on the World Wide Web, a medium perhaps well suited to the circus-meister's fantabulous claims.</p>
        <p>Scholars and producers at the Center for Media and Learning and the New Media Lab, both part of the CUNY Graduate Center, have rebuilt the five-story museum in virtual space on a Web site. The Web address is http://web.gc.cuny.edu/ashp/lostmuseum. Supported in part by a grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities, the site will provide students and history buffs with a full archive of information about the museum and relevant 19th-century subjects. It will eventually include a variety of investigative paths to take through the five-story building, for those wanting to play detective and figure out who set it on fire the first time.</p>
        <p>Barnum, who believed that every crowd had a silver lining and that a sucker was born every minute, reveled in the museum's claim of being the most visited spot in America. He reported that the museum, which was open 15 hours a day, 6 days a week, often had up to 15,000 visitors a day (that would be more than 16 suckers per minute), though an accurate count might have been beyond his capacities.</p>
        <p>Signs in the museum, which was at Broadway and Ann Street, reportedly pointed enthusiastically toward a magnificent, not-to-be-missed attraction, ''The Egress,'' which was actually an unmarked exit. Those rushing to see said egress would find themselves outside, needing to pay another 25-cent admission fee.</p>
        <p>Those two bits bought visitors the chance to see Tom Thumb, the midget; Anna Swan, the giantess from Nova Scotia, whom Barnum dressed in 100 yards of satin and 50 yards of lace; the Fejee Mermaid (supposedly a mummified maiden, but actually the desiccated head of a monkey and the body of an orangutan, attached to the back of a fish); and the wax museum figure of Jefferson Davis, the Confederate president, wearing a woman's dress, in accordance with rumors that he tried to escape from Union forces in drag.</p>
        <p>Only a few of the original attractions were saved from the fires.</p>
        <p>''A red-shined fireman seized with either hand Franklin Pierce and James Buchanan by their coat-collars, tucked the Prince Imperial of France under one arm and the Veiled Murderess under the other, and coolly departed for the street,'' according to an article in The New York Tribune. ''Some one had stuck a cigar in General Washington's mouth, and thus, with his chapeau crushed down over his eyes and his head leaning upon the ample lap of Moll Pitcher, the Father of his Country led the van of as sorry a band of patriots as not often comes within one's experience to see.''</p>
        <p>Most of the rest of the exhibits, however, left behind only their legends.</p>
        <p>''There's not a lot to work with,'' said Joshua Brown, director for the Center for Media and Learning/American Social History Project.</p>
        <p>''There's a lot of guessing,'' he said. ''Part of the problem is it's Barnum, so a lot of it is humbug.''</p>
        <p>Peter Buckley, an associate professor of history at Cooper Union and a Barnum scholar, worked as an independent reviewer of the project.</p>
        <p>''I'm amazed at the little things that they've had to do to reconstruct it,'' he said of the online museum. ''They had to try and get the right texture for the floorboards and walls, so they had to go down to an old building in the South Street Seaport and take photos of old pine boards, hoping that was close to the original texture, and then mapping those textures throughout the building.''</p>
        <p>Internet surfers are able to see a film about Barnum, visit the main salon in the museum, zoom in on pictures on the walls, open exhibit drawers to read archival documents, and read contemporary accounts of the fire and of Davis's escapades.</p>
        <p>Stephen Brier, a co-director of the New Media Lab, said, ''It's a way of imagining the past, and we practice it in an unconventional way, so instead of writing monographs, we produce films and CD-ROM's, and now we're working on the re-creation of a space that no longer exists.''</p>
        <p>Andrea Ades Vasquez, the lab's managing director, said, ''We'd like it to be a model, for solving different mysteries.''</p>
        <p>In some ways, the Internet, which provides free admission to a wide variety of curiosities of varying authenticity, is an apt home for Barnum. In any case, he provides a fine lens on the era in which he lived.</p>
        <p>''Maybe what's uniquely American about Barnum was this effort -- he called it democratic, but it might be something else -- to bring everybody together, regardless of class background,'' Dr. Buckley of Cooper Union said. ''It was the whole period of the 1840's when I believe it's possible to say that a distinct American popular culture was developed, and the museum is central, and Barnum is central, to that development.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
