<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Leading Candidates in Mexico As Close on Issues as in Polls</title>
    <meta content="01MEXI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211610"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mexico</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Preston, Julia</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Labastida Ochoa, Francisco</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fox Quesada, Vicente</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000701T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E2DB1439F932A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1240" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Leading Candidates in Mexico As Close on Issues as in Polls</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JULIA PRESTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Preston, Julia</byline>
      <dateline>MEXICO CITY, June 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Leading candidates in Mexican presidential election are seen close on major issues; Francsico Labastida Ochoa of governing party and Vicente Fox Quesada of right-of-center opposition, who have been running neck and neck, are so close on economic issues that they use same slogan: 'An economy with a human face'; both candidates play down nationalism that used to be a campaign mainstay and favor good relations with United States (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The race for the Mexican presidency has been a show such as Mexico has never seen. The leading candidates have slugged it out on television, calling each other names and wrangling fiercely over the merits of change in a country governed by the same party for 71 years.</p>
        <p>But as the dust settled in the final days before Sunday's election, it was hard to find much difference on the major issues between the leading candidates, Francisco Labastida Ochoa of the governing party and Vicente Fox Quesada of the right-of-center opposition, who have been running neck and neck.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The race for the Mexican presidency has been a show such as Mexico has never seen. The leading candidates have slugged it out on television, calling each other names and wrangling fiercely over the merits of change in a country governed by the same party for 71 years.</p>
        <p>But as the dust settled in the final days before Sunday's election, it was hard to find much difference on the major issues between the leading candidates, Francisco Labastida Ochoa of the governing party and Vicente Fox Quesada of the right-of-center opposition, who have been running neck and neck.</p>
        <p>On economic issues, the most deeply felt by Mexicans, the two were so close that they used the same slogan: ''An economy with a human face.''</p>
        <p>Both candidates played down the nationalism that used to be a campaign mainstay and favored good relations with the United States -- although they did not say it too loudly. They even agreed on what not to bring up, so the crucial national security issue of narcotics was largely absent.</p>
        <p>The candidates reflected a consensus among Mexican voters, who have embraced the global economy but want a fairer share of it, and seek better government through peaceful, orderly reform. And with Mexico linked to the United States more firmly than ever, the room in which its politicians can maneuver has been reduced considerably.</p>
        <p>A leftist contender, Cuauhtemoc Cardenas Solorzano, contrasted with his rivals, calling for a renegotiation of the North American Free Trade Agreement and more confrontation with the United States. But the latest polls show that although Mexicans admire his honest zeal, they will not elect Mr. Cardenas president.</p>
        <p>Both Mr. Labastida and Mr. Fox were strong supporters of Nafta, which has transformed Mexico into an export powerhouse, creating millions of jobs in sectors that supply the booming United States market. Both criticized government policies that catered to the markets but did little to close the widening rift between rich and poor and between northern Mexico, where the export industries are based, and the south, where unemployment is rampant.</p>
        <p>Mr. Labastida, the candidate of the governing Institutional Revolutionary Party, or PRI, distanced himself from President Ernesto Zedillo, even though the government's tight fiscal policies generated a recovery and growth surge without which the PRI campaign would have been doomed. He criticized his party's president for neglecting the purchasing power of working class Mexicans. He proposed to double or triple current subsidies to farmers in regions hurt by American competition through Nafta.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fox stood on his experience as a former Coca-Cola executive and his record of boosting Mexican entrepreneurs when he was governor of Guanajuato state. He said he would create a cabinet ministry, separate from the Finance Ministry, to create jobs through private investment, promote ''aggressive policies'' on behalf of small businesses and send ''massive resources'' to the poorest regions.</p>
        <p>''No one among the analysts can make out whose proposals are better,'' said Damian Fraser, the head of Latin American research for UBS Warburg. ''Labastida has more experience in government and represents continuity. Fox has a somewhat greater commitment to free market policies.''</p>
        <p>The final polls showed Mr. Labastida and Mr. Fox in a tie, with Mr. Cardenas well behind. Mr. Fox comes from the moderate conservative National Action Party, known as the PAN, but spearheaded a diverse group of Mexicans who want a change from the ruling system.</p>
        <p>Despite the similarities, Mr. Labastida did score one propaganda coup against Mr. Fox. In a much-discussed television commercial, he showed a video clip of Mr. Fox speaking in English during a visit to the United States, describing a program he set up in Guanajuato to train gardeners for skilled jobs in the United States. Mr. Labastida comes in at the end to say that he planned to create jobs for Mexicans in Mexico.</p>
        <p>Even though relations with the United States have never been closer, Mexicans retain a gut wariness of their neighbor. Nationalism was unusually dormant through much of the leading campaigns, but in the final days the PRI revived it with accusations that Mr. Fox received illegal donations from across the border.  Mr. Fox denied the allegations.</p>
        <p>The two candidates both promised a harder line in defense of Mexican immigrants. Mr. Fox stressed a proposal to make a free labor market in the hemisphere in the coming years to parallel the free trade market, opening the border to the millions of Mexican migrants who now risk their lives to cross it illegally.</p>
        <p>Education was another hot-button issue, where Mr. Fox and Mr. Labastida diverged. Mr. Fox made a risky pitch to Catholics, who make up more than 90 percent of the population, suggesting that he would make more room for the Roman Catholic Church in public education. The idea drew a furious response from the PRI, whose anti-clericalism and commitment to nonreligious public schools date back to its founding. It was not clear how the overture played among the voters.</p>
        <p>Mr. Labastida also gambled, with a nationally broadcast radio commercial saying he would bring English and computer courses to all public schools. The opposition ridiculed the proposal as impractical and elitist. But PRI media experts found that the advertisement was popular with working class voters, and they kept broadcasting it for an extra two weeks.</p>
        <p>One issue too explosive for either candidate to dwell on was Mexico's No. 1 national security concern: the narcotics trade. One PRI state governor, Mario Villanueva, is wanted by the Mexican authorities on charges of laundering drug money. But Mr. Fox's party also had a bleak record on combating traffickers in Baja California and Chihuahua, two border states it governed in recent years.</p>
        <p>Both candidates said they would fight crime and corruption by overhauling the justice system. Mr. Labastida said he would dissolve the attorney general's office, the central federal justice institution, and create a new justice system more like that of the United States, where the fight against drugs would be isolated in one agency, federal prosecutors in another and federal police in a third.</p>
        <p>Many sparks in the campaign flew from the friction between two very different men. Mr. Labastida is an institutional man who served 37 years in government without making a big wave or a big mistake. Mr. Fox handily outperformed him in both debates because Mr. Labastida seemed noncommittal.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fox's forcefulness and populist informality both helped and hurt him. In a survey by Consultores y Marketing Politico, a public opinion research company, more of those interviewed liked and trusted Mr. Fox, but thought Mr. Labastida had ''the personality to be president.''</p>
        <p>The split that has made the contest so intense is over the record of the PRI, tarnished by corruption and repeated economic crises. Mr. Fox appealed to voters to abandon their deep-set risk aversion and throw off a system of rule that has dominated their entire lives.</p>
        <p>From a podium high above a huge crowd in Mexico City's central square, Mr. Fox boomed out the slogan that summarized his crusade: ''Don't stop now, Mexico!''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
