<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Whitman Trims $21.4 Billion Budget Before Signing It</title>
    <meta content="01JERS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211617"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Health Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Smoking and Tobacco</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kocieniewski, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Whitman, Christine Todd (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Smoking and Tobacco</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000701T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E0DA1439F932A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="711" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Whitman Trims $21.4 Billion Budget Before Signing It</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID KOCIENIEWSKI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kocieniewski, David</byline>
      <dateline>TRENTON, June 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New Jersey Governor Christine Todd Whitman signs $21.4 billion state budget into law after using line-item veto to trim $50 million in spending proposed by Legislature; budget represents 10 percent increase over last year's spending and includes $45 million tax cut for 240,000 low-income families, and FamilyCare, Governor's plan to use portion of tobacco settlement to help provide health insurance; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. Christine Todd Whitman signed a $21.4 billion state budget into law today after using her line-item veto to carve $50 million in spending proposed by the Legislature.</p>
        <p>The budget, buoyed by windfall tax revenues generated by New Jersey's surging economy, represents a 10 percent increase over last year's spending, and includes a $45 million tax cut for 240,000 low-income families, and FamilyCare, the Governor's plan to use part of the tobacco settlement to help provide health insurance for 125,000 New Jerseyans.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gov. Christine Todd Whitman signed a $21.4 billion state budget into law today after using her line-item veto to carve $50 million in spending proposed by the Legislature.</p>
        <p>The budget, buoyed by windfall tax revenues generated by New Jersey's surging economy, represents a 10 percent increase over last year's spending, and includes a $45 million tax cut for 240,000 low-income families, and FamilyCare, the Governor's plan to use part of the tobacco settlement to help provide health insurance for 125,000 New Jerseyans.</p>
        <p>The budget also includes increased spending for towns, preschools, public schools, colleges, nursing homes and charity care for indigent residents unable to pay hospital bills.</p>
        <p>But the spending package still provides an $870 million surplus, the largest in state history.</p>
        <p>''There's a lot of new policy initiatives in this budget,'' said Assemblyman Richard Bagger, a Republican from Westfield. ''From health care and education to tax cuts. This is one of those years when there's something for almost everyone.''</p>
        <p>Governor Whitman and the State Senate have also agreed on two other huge spending programs not included in the budget: the $3.75 billion Transportation Trust Fund to finance road improvements and a $12 billion plan to rebuild the state's aging public schools. But both measures must still receive the approval of the Assembly, which is expected to pass them when it reconvenes for a special session on July 13.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Whitman said she was grateful that she had the good fortune to govern during comfortable economic times, but said she felt obligated to make the $50 million in line-item-veto reductions.</p>
        <p>''It's very difficult during flush times to say no,'' Mrs. Whitman said, ''but we have a responsibility to spend tax dollars as if they were our own.''</p>
        <p>Among Mrs. Whitman's vetoes were $300,000 in spending cuts intended to send a blunt message to one of the governor's political adversaries, State Senator John A. Lynch, a Democrat from Middlesex County. Mr. Lynch was the lone dissenter in the Senate's 38-to-1 vote in favor of the budget, because, he said, the state should use its prosperity to reduce New Jersey's debt and offer more aid to its struggling cities.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Whitman retaliated against Mr. Lynch by denying financing to three programs he had requested in his hometown, New Brunswick: a $100,000 community shuttle bus program, $100,000 for a housing rehabilitation program and $100,000 for street lighting. To make sure her reasoning for those vetoes was clear, the governor's written budget message, distributed to reporters, included this explanation: ''The sponsor of this appropriation has indicated his lack of support for the fiscal 2001 budget. Therefore it would be inconsistent with the sponsor's intent to approve this appropriation.''</p>
        <p>When asked about those cuts, the governor flashed a smile. ''He didn't think this budget was good,'' she said with a chuckle. ''So if the budget isn't good, it isn't good in a lot of ways.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lynch and Mrs. Whitman have clashed in the past, and Mr. Lynch was a prime political backer of a fellow Democrat, Jim McGreevey, who nearly defeated Mrs. Whitman, a Republican, for governor in 1997.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lynch did not return calls for comment after the cuts were announced.</p>
        <p>Other line-item cuts by the governor included spending reductions for several hospitals, a variety of road projects and $1.5 million intended to help New Jersey teachers pay for continuing education.</p>
        <p>But Leonard Lance, chairman of the Assembly Budget Committee, said most legislators were able to secure money for projects in their districts. ''The budget is 99.8 percent of what the Legislature delivered to the governor,'' said Mr. Lance, a Republican from Hunterdon. ''The governor and the Legislature cooperated extremely well.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
