<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BOOKS IN BRIEF: NONFICTION</title>
    <meta content="RV090852" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="34" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199175"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Van Dagens, Margaret</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Golden, Eve</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Anna Held and the Birth of Ziegfeld's Broadway (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E7DB1738F937A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="382" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BOOKS IN BRIEF: NONFICTION</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Margaret Van Dagens</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Van Dagens, Margaret</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Margaret Van Dagens reviews book Anna Held and the Birth of Ziegfeld's Broadway by Eve Golden (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ANNA HELD AND THE BIRTH</p>
        <p>OF ZIEGFELD'S BROADWAY</p>
        <p>By Eve Golden.</p>
        <p>University Press of Kentucky, $27.50.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ANNA HELD AND THE BIRTH</p>
        <p>OF ZIEGFELD'S BROADWAY</p>
        <p>By Eve Golden.</p>
        <p>University Press of Kentucky, $27.50.</p>
        <p>The lively opening of ''Anna Held and the Birth of Ziegfeld's Broadway'' describes a 1913 New Year's Eve party when Held watched Florenz Ziegfeld walk out of her life with the actress Billie Burke. Today, Burke is remembered as the good witch in ''The Wizard of Oz,'' Ziegfeld is still known for his Follies, but who remembers Anna Held? Yet that night, Held was the most famous of the three, Eve Golden writes, and personified ''everything that was glamorous about Broadway, everything that was naughty about Paris.'' Born about 1870, Held was singing in Parisian music halls by 1896, when Ziegfeld came to Europe looking for ''flashy new talent.'' He promptly brought her to New York for his first Broadway show, promoting her with stories that she bathed in milk and other catchy nonsense. She charmed audiences with suggestive songs and flirty ways, soon becoming Ziegfeld's first famous star. Golden likens Held and Ziegfeld to ''nitro meeting glycerin.'' Successful and in love, they were married in 1897. However, in time their differences began to grate -- she was frugal, he gambled. In 1910 there was a crisis when Ziegfeld moved a mistress into the hotel where he and Held lived. Held moved out, but continued working with Ziegfeld. All through 1913, they see-sawed from divorce to planned remarriage until Ziegfeld abruptly married Burke. Held finished touring in her last Ziegfeld show, went back to France and stayed to entertain troops during World War I. Returning to America in 1916, she began another tour, but soon died of cancer. Golden, who has also written books about Jean Harlow and Theda Bara, has examined theatrical archives, press clippings, costumes, even some Held film footage. Although her book sometimes comes close to becoming a cumbersome reference guide, Golden succeeds in communicating Held's charm.</p>
        <p>Margaret Van Dagens</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
