<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Ready Red Bullet Offers a New Test for Fusaichi Pegasus in the Preakness</title>
    <meta content="14RACI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199579"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HORSE RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Preakness Stakes</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Durso, Joseph</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Preakness Stakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE4DA133BF937A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="938" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Ready Red Bullet Offers a New Test for Fusaichi Pegasus in the Preakness</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSEPH DURSO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Durso, Joseph</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses Red Bullet's chances of challenging Fusaichi Pegasus in Preakness (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Can a red bullet shoot down a flying horse?</p>
        <p>Or, more to the point, can the speed horse Red Bullet ambush Fusaichi Pegasus and destroy his chances of sweeping the Triple Crown?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Can a red bullet shoot down a flying horse?</p>
        <p>Or, more to the point, can the speed horse Red Bullet ambush Fusaichi Pegasus and destroy his chances of sweeping the Triple Crown?</p>
        <p>He tried it once, in the Wood Memorial last month at Aqueduct, but the flying horse surged past Red Bullet to win by four and one-quarter lengths. Then, while Red Bullet stayed behind in New York, Fusaichi Pegasus flew past the field to win the Kentucky Derby by a length and a half at Churchill Downs.</p>
        <p>''Never once did I feel I could have won the Derby,'' the trainer Joe Orseno said before putting Red Bullet aboard a van and shipping him to Pimlico for next Saturday's Preakness. ''We felt he wasn't a horse on schedule for the Derby.''</p>
        <p>But Orseno and Red Bullet's owner, Frank Stronach, apparently feel that the extra five weeks has given their colt the time he needs to take another shot at Fusaichi Pegasus. Their hopes were strengthened when Red Bullet zipped five furlongs in 58 4/5  seconds in a workout at Pimlico this morning. And they have hired Jerry Bailey, the country's premier jockey, to ride him when he takes the next step.</p>
        <p>The next step: the 125th Preakness at a mile and three-sixteenths, which is a sixteenth of a mile shorter than the Derby on a narrower track with sharper turns. Only five horses may challenge Fusaichi Pegasus this time, including only two of the colts he outran in the Derby: High Yield, the D. Wayne Lukas star, who finished 15th, and Hal's Hope, 16th after leading for most of a mile.</p>
        <p>Three others are committed to the Preakness: Hugh Hefner, second in the Snow Chief in his last start; Snuck In, second in the Arkansas Derby; and Red Bullet, second in the Wood. Four other colts who were soundly beaten in the Derby may give it another whirl in the Preakness: Impeachment (third), More Than Ready (fourth), Wheelaway (fifth) and Captain Steve (eighth).</p>
        <p>But the fresh horse, the dangerous horse, figures to be Red Bullet. He is a chestnut son of Unbridled, winner of the 1990 Kentucky Derby, and he reeled off three victories in a row this year, his first at the races. On Jan. 8, he won by seven lengths at Aqueduct. On Feb. 5, he won by two and one-half at Gulfstream Park. On March 19, he returned to New York and won the Gotham Stakes by half a length over Aptitude, who then ran second to Fusaichi Pegasus in the Derby. And on April 15, Red Bullet again outran Aptitude in the Wood, but both finished well behind the flying horse.</p>
        <p>Orseno said he believed that the Wood was decided when Red Bullet pressed the pace, only to save nothing for the critical stretch drive.</p>
        <p>Orseno stopped short of finding fault with Alex Solis, who rode Red Bullet in the Wood. But when Solis picked up Aptitude for the Derby, the die was cast. Orseno promptly signed up Bailey, and said, ''I don't want to have to scramble for a rider if we go on to the Belmont.''</p>
        <p>But standing in the path of all challengers is Fusaichi Pegasus, a son of Mr. Prospector and a grandson of Danzig, bought for $4 million as a yearling by the Japanese venture capitalist Fusao Sekiguchi. He did not race until last December, when he lost by a neck at Hollywood Park after a troubled trip. But since then, he has won five in a row.</p>
        <p>Fusaichi Pegasus became the Derby favorite when he won the Wood with a powerful drive through the homestretch that left Red Bullet and Aptitude in his trail. Three weeks later, he became the first Derby favorite to win the race in 21 years, since Spectacular Bid, and he did it with style and strength. He is a large animal with regal breeding and a smashing resume, and he has become the favorite to go on and become the 12th horse to sweep the Triple Crown.</p>
        <p>The last three horses who won the Kentucky Derby -- Silver Charm, Real Quiet and Charismatic -- also won the Preakness but fell short of winning the Belmont Stakes in the final strides. But none of them was the favorite in the Derby.</p>
        <p>Then along came Fusaichi Pegasus, a brilliant new star in the new century. You will hear no argument from Lukas, who has entered 38 horses in the Kentucky Derby over the last 20 years and won the race 4 times. ''Fusaichi Pegasus is a deserving favorite,'' Lukas said, ''but let's face it, he's not a wind-up toy. You're probably crazy to pick against him. So, we'll try to upset him.''</p>
        <p>The oddsmakers agreed. They expected to make Fusaichi Pegasus the heavy early favorite at perhaps 3-5 to win the Preakness.</p>
        <p>Bob Baffert, who won the Derby twice in the last four years, put it into perspective for his horse, Captain Steve, as well as the No. 1 challenger, Red Bullet.</p>
        <p>''Fusaichi Pegasus deserves to be the heavy favorite,'' Baffert said. ''He's got a lot going for him with his breeding, his record and the way he won the Derby.''</p>
        <p>HORSE RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
