<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Books in Brief: Children's Books</title>
    <meta content="RV085224" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199171"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">MacLeod, Anne Scott</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Osborne, Mary Pope</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Adaline Falling Star (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Columns/Children's Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DEEDC1738F937A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="440" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Books in Brief: Children's Books</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Anne Scott MacLeod</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MacLeod, Anne Scott</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anne Scott MacLeod reviews book Adaline Falling Star by Mary Pope Osborne (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ADALINE FALLING STAR</p>
        <p>By Mary Pope Osborne.</p>
        <p>Scholastic, $16.95.</p>
        <p>(Ages 10 and up)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ADALINE FALLING STAR</p>
        <p>By Mary Pope Osborne.</p>
        <p>Scholastic, $16.95.</p>
        <p>(Ages 10 and up)</p>
        <p>The author's note at the beginning of ''Adaline Falling Star'' says plainly, ''This story is fiction.'' Upfront and unambiguous, Mary Pope Osborne's words are an honorable exception in a publishing world increasingly apt to fudge the difference between historical truth and historical fiction in books for children.</p>
        <p>Adaline was real, the child of a marriage between an Arapaho woman and Kit Carson, the storied guide who accompanied John Fremont on his expeditions to the West in the 1840's. When his wife died in 1842, Carson took his daughter to relatives in St. Louis and provided for her education.</p>
        <p>Nothing more is known of Adaline's life; Osborne's story is the imagined experience of a lonely child, scorned for her Indian blood and fearful that her father has abandoned her, who sets out alone to find her way back to her mother's people.</p>
        <p>The voice is Adaline's, recounting her unhappy stay with her cousins and her perilous trek homeward through barely settled country. Osborne has tinkered a little with chronology. Though the Dictionary of American Biography says that Adaline was 5 when her father took her to Missouri, Osborne makes her 11 -- old enough to resist her relatives with cunning.</p>
        <p>Adaline refuses to speak after her father leaves her. No one knows that she can read; her guardians believe she is mute and see it as their duty to erase the taint of her Indian blood. Adaline never accepts her new life; her interior monologue alternates between yearning for her parents and rage toward nearly everyone else. In grief, she slashes her arms and legs, Arapaho fashion; in desperation, she runs away.</p>
        <p>The rest is a survival story. The elements are familiar: illness (an infection that nearly kills her), the animal companion (a dog that saves her life more than once), the happy ending (reunion with her father). Adaline's colloquial language fits the time, though I doubt anyone said ''way different'' in the 1840's.</p>
        <p>The weaknesses are the flashbacks in the early chapters, which may confuse a young reader, and the unsatisfyingly flat characterization of everyone but Adaline herself. On its own terms, however, ''Adaline Falling Star'' is a believable tale of grief, anger, determination and, finally, joy.</p>
        <p>Anne Scott MacLeod</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
