<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Reinvention Of Motherhood By Necessity</title>
    <meta content="14COLM$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199416"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="COPING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mother's Day</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lee, Felicia R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mother's Day</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE5D8143BF937A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="912" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Reinvention Of Motherhood By Necessity</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FELICIA R. LEE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lee, Felicia R</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Felicia R Lee Mother's Day Coping column on mothers who categorize and compartmentalize other mothers by wide range of options taken or not taken; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE transcendent joy and mind-bending fatigue are expected. But for some mothers, the unexpected bump on the journey is that women often set up a hierarchy of motherhood. They sort, they measure, they judge.</p>
        <p>Besides the divide between mothers who work in the home and those who work outside the home, women peck at one another about everything from child care to feeding decisions. In a time when women graze on more options than ever, many backward glances and pronouncements are made about the Other Mother.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE transcendent joy and mind-bending fatigue are expected. But for some mothers, the unexpected bump on the journey is that women often set up a hierarchy of motherhood. They sort, they measure, they judge.</p>
        <p>Besides the divide between mothers who work in the home and those who work outside the home, women peck at one another about everything from child care to feeding decisions. In a time when women graze on more options than ever, many backward glances and pronouncements are made about the Other Mother.</p>
        <p>A woman with college-age sons reminisced that on this  Mother's Day, the clashes are much the same as they were when her kids were young.</p>
        <p>''There were those who breast-fed and never gave the child a bottle,'' she recalled. ''There were those who always had a baby sitter and those who never did. There was a lot of gossip and envy and judgment.''</p>
        <p>Indeed. Mothers are seldom neutral about one another. We wonder why she put her career on hold to stay home; we ask why she flew off to Europe on assignment when the baby was 4 weeks old; we challenge her to work a four-day week because her current hectic pace means doing a so-so job at both home and office.</p>
        <p>The mother calculus locates women along a continuum that includes the soccer mom and the supermom, and career choices like the mommy track.</p>
        <p>Many women find those terms superficial and infuriating. The shorthand fails to capture the complexity of their lives and the loss each choice entails. Modern motherhood for many is a bring-your-own-pieces puzzle to fit together the need to support their families financially, meet their own needs for accomplishment and be there for Little League.</p>
        <p>And then answer questions about whether they have hurt their children or their careers.</p>
        <p>''Women aren't kind to each other,'' said an Upper West Side mother of two who left her job in television to stay home when she had her first son. ''I think it comes from being afraid of not having made the right choice and doing the right thing.''</p>
        <p>The woman said she found the gulf between mothering choices so deep that she avoids social situations in which people may try to make her feel bad. Often, when she says she stays at home, they ask, ''What do you do all day?'' with emphasis on the second ''do.''</p>
        <p>''New York is the kind of city where we're particularly driven,'' she said. ''You're as good as your last project, your last film, your last story. If you drop out of that, you lose your touchstones.''</p>
        <p>It cuts both ways. A working mother who dropped out of a play group on the Upper East Side said the mothers who stayed home just did not understand her. They questioned why she married a man who could not support her.</p>
        <p>In fairness, women pose questions not just in the service of status-sniffing. There is also real curiosity and empathy for one another as we negotiate family life in a time when the notion of family and what we owe children is up for grabs. New books trumpet the rights of the childless not to pay school taxes or work long hours while parents (read: mothers) avoid working weekends and overtime because of their family responsibilities.</p>
        <p>The ambivalence women feel about their choices and the harsh judgments that accompany those choices also reflect a deep social ambivalence. About the ''right'' roles for women. About how much we value children and the people who care for them.</p>
        <p>''You're going to feel guilty no matter what you do,'' said Mary Quigley, a journalism professor at New York University and the author of ''And What Do You Do? When Women Choose to Stay Home'' (Wildcat Canyon Press, 2000). Ms. Quigley, a mother of three, wrote the book with Loretta Kaufman, a writer who stayed home with her children for years.</p>
        <p>The title refers to the question many mothers dread, especially if they do not work for pay. Ms. Quigley and Ms. Kaufman found that, increasingly, mothers in their early 30's feel empowered by their decision to leave their careers and return to them when their children are older. Older women are more defensive.</p>
        <p>''I did not work for 12 years,'' Ms. Quigley recalled. ''Now, I go pick up my daughter at school and there are a lot of stay-home mothers and they say: 'Oh, you're so lucky. My mind is turning to mush.' The great thing is, we reinvent ourselves all the time, more than men.''</p>
        <p>So the brave mothers trudge on, trying to ignore those voices saying that what they do is never enough.</p>
        <p>''You can't just be a mother,'' said a musician with a 2-year-old girl. ''They want to put you in a category, to know what kind of mother you are. The choices say something about who you are financially and philosophically.</p>
        <p>''Look, the best gift we can give each other is the assumption that everyone out here is doing their best.''</p>
        <p>COPING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
