<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Elementary, My Dear Mr. Conan Doyle</title>
    <meta content="14SIGN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Television" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="63" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199615"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SPOTLIGHT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stasio, Marilyn</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holmes, Sherlock (Fictional Character)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Murder Rooms: The Dark Origins of Sherlock Holmes (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE0D9133BF937A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="803" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Elementary, My Dear Mr. Conan Doyle</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARILYN STASIO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stasio, Marilyn</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Marilyn Stasio reviews television movie Murder Rooms: The Dark Origins of Sherlock Holmes, two-part film that is joint production of WGBH Boston and BBC; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Well, it seems that Sherlock Holmes was a real person, after all. His name was Dr. Joseph Bell, a legendary medical diagnostician who taught at the Medical School of the University of Edinburgh when Sir Arthur Conan Doyle enrolled there in 1878 as a medical student. In fact, Dr. Bell chose the young Conan Doyle to be his clerk -- a devoted-slave position that entailed emptying the bloody buckets after an autopsy, trotting after the master on the forensic cases he handled for the Edinburgh police department, and writing down the brilliant principles of criminal deduction that would later issue from the lips of the immortal Sherlock Holmes.</p>
        <p>If it's proof you want, tune in to ''Murder Rooms: The Dark Beginnings of Sherlock Holmes,'' a two-part film , at 9 p.m. this Thursday and next on Channels 13 and 49. In this original drama, a joint production of WGBH Boston and the BBC, Ian Richardson plays Dr. Bell in a manner that brooks no misinterpretation about who the character is meant to be. The surgeon is standing in the amphitheater of the Royal Infirmary when he astonishes his class by deducing a patient's occupation, heritage, and physical complaint simply by looking at him. But he sounds just like the great Holmes, in his parlor at 221B Baker Street in ''The Adventure of the Dancing Men,'' explaining to Dr. Watson how he could tell from the chalk mark between his friend's fingers that he had decided not to invest in South African securities.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Well, it seems that Sherlock Holmes was a real person, after all. His name was Dr. Joseph Bell, a legendary medical diagnostician who taught at the Medical School of the University of Edinburgh when Sir Arthur Conan Doyle enrolled there in 1878 as a medical student. In fact, Dr. Bell chose the young Conan Doyle to be his clerk -- a devoted-slave position that entailed emptying the bloody buckets after an autopsy, trotting after the master on the forensic cases he handled for the Edinburgh police department, and writing down the brilliant principles of criminal deduction that would later issue from the lips of the immortal Sherlock Holmes.</p>
        <p>If it's proof you want, tune in to ''Murder Rooms: The Dark Beginnings of Sherlock Holmes,'' a two-part film , at 9 p.m. this Thursday and next on Channels 13 and 49. In this original drama, a joint production of WGBH Boston and the BBC, Ian Richardson plays Dr. Bell in a manner that brooks no misinterpretation about who the character is meant to be. The surgeon is standing in the amphitheater of the Royal Infirmary when he astonishes his class by deducing a patient's occupation, heritage, and physical complaint simply by looking at him. But he sounds just like the great Holmes, in his parlor at 221B Baker Street in ''The Adventure of the Dancing Men,'' explaining to Dr. Watson how he could tell from the chalk mark between his friend's fingers that he had decided not to invest in South African securities.</p>
        <p>''The charlatan is always the pioneer, the quack of yesterday is the professor of tomorrow,'' this eccentric genius thunders at the skeptical Conan Doyle (played by Robin Laing), who initially dismisses his teacher's amazing feats of deductive reasoning as ''tricks.'' Indeed, many of the ''tricks'' Dr. Bell flourishes here will eventually surface within the four novels and 56 short stories that constitute Conan Doyle's literary legacy.</p>
        <p>For his part in the drama, the young medical student puts aside his doubts and learns to apply the same methods of observation and analysis to several baffling cases under Dr. Bell's investigation, including a series of macabre murders that eerily anticipate the handiwork of Jack the Ripper. In this role of the pathologist's ''Dr. Watson,'' Conan Doyle begins to store up the impressions -- like the haunting notes of a street musician's lonely violin and the addictive allure of opium-- that will eventually coalesce in his characterization of ''the world's greatest consulting detective.''</p>
        <p>Although the fact is only suggested in ''Murder Rooms,'' Arthur Conan Doyle began writing his Sherlock Holmes stories within a year of meeting Dr. Bell. ''I thought I would try my hand at writing a story where the hero would treat crime just as Dr. Bell treated disease and where science would take the place of chance,'' he would later acknowledge. In fact, he dedicated his first story collection, ''The Adventures of Sherlock Holmes,'' to his mentor and went on to pay fuller homage to his penetrating analytic powers in the famous Science of Deduction chapter in ''A Study in Scarlet.''</p>
        <p>''It is fiction based on fact, a legend built on a legend,'' says the screenwriter, David Pirie, who was led to his interpretation of the teacher-pupil relationship through letters and papers only recently released by the author's estate. ''It has been known for a long time that Joseph Bell was a model for Sherlock Holmes,'' says Pirie, who goes on to point out that, ''what is not so well known is that Bell was carrying out secret investigations for the Crown'' at the time. During the year that Conan Doyle served as his clerk, Bell actually helped convict a man for murdering his wife.</p>
        <p>The father-son intimacy between Dr. Bell and his student clerk was the screenwriter's own contribution, based on knowledge of the young Conan Doyle's painful home life.</p>
        <p>''When he started as a student his father was about to be consigned to a lunatic asylum,'' Pirie explains. ''Suddenly he met this incredibly charismatic man.''</p>
        <p>''I am convinced,'' he continues, ''that 1878 was a huge turning point for Doyle, a white-heat moment psychologically, and that it had a huge influence on the creation of Sherlock Holmes.''</p>
        <p>SPOTLIGHT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
