<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>It's Not All Dazzle: MTV Has a Conscience, Too</title>
    <meta content="14HOOP$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="36" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000516T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199238"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION/RADIO"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mtv Networks</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hooper, Joseph</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lazin, Lauren</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">True Life (TV Program)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Real World (TV Program)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Tom Green Show, the (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E7D91138F937A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1747" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>It's Not All Dazzle: MTV Has a Conscience, Too</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSEPH HOOPER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hooper, Joseph</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Joseph Hooper's article on MTV's news and documentary division, which has produced series True Life, Real World and Tom Green Show; Lauren Lazin, vice president of division, comments; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SINCE its founding in 1981, MTV has gotten plenty of mileage out of young people's fantasies about sex, drugs and rock 'n' roll. But if the staple of the channel's programming, the music video, often conveys an unbridled hedonism, the channel's documentary programs can be regarded as the proverbial dropping of the other shoe.</p>
        <p>For instance, MTV's ''True Life'' documentary series takes its audience to some pretty rugged places, including two public restrooms. On ''I'm on Crystal Meth,'' which was first broadcast in February, the MTV reporter Serena Altschul keeps up a concerned patter as Amber, 19, shoots methamphetamine into a vein. Two years ago, on ''Fatal Dose,'' about a heroin epidemic in Plano, Tex., Ms. Altschul shared the facilities with two affluent addicts, Allen, 19, and Eric, 22, who was painfully struggling to find an injectable vein. ''If anybody still has any doubts,'' said Allen, taking over the narration of this cautionary tale about heroin, ''Eric is proof as to whether it's really glamorous.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SINCE its founding in 1981, MTV has gotten plenty of mileage out of young people's fantasies about sex, drugs and rock 'n' roll. But if the staple of the channel's programming, the music video, often conveys an unbridled hedonism, the channel's documentary programs can be regarded as the proverbial dropping of the other shoe.</p>
        <p>For instance, MTV's ''True Life'' documentary series takes its audience to some pretty rugged places, including two public restrooms. On ''I'm on Crystal Meth,'' which was first broadcast in February, the MTV reporter Serena Altschul keeps up a concerned patter as Amber, 19, shoots methamphetamine into a vein. Two years ago, on ''Fatal Dose,'' about a heroin epidemic in Plano, Tex., Ms. Altschul shared the facilities with two affluent addicts, Allen, 19, and Eric, 22, who was painfully struggling to find an injectable vein. ''If anybody still has any doubts,'' said Allen, taking over the narration of this cautionary tale about heroin, ''Eric is proof as to whether it's really glamorous.''</p>
        <p>This year, producers working mostly out of MTV's corporate offices in Times Square will make from 50 to 75 television documentaries. Many will be about music or the music business -- subjects that account for most of the channel's programming. But roughly a third of the documentaries tackle social problems that affect younger people: drug addiction, school violence, sexually transmitted disease. (Next on the schedule, on May 22, is ''Gun Fight,'' on the politics of gun control, part of the network's ''Choose or Lose'' documentary series about young people and political involvement.) But unless you happen to fall within the channel's 18-to-24 ''core demographic,'' this is probably news to you. In the minds of older television viewers, MTV's involvement in documentary filmmaking about nonmusicians begins and ends with ''Real World.''</p>
        <p>For the past eight years, that MTV series has offered its audience what amounts to a hugely popular lab experiment in which successive sets of seven college-age kids live together for a television season under the constant surveillance of a resident film crew. ''Every year we ask, 'When are we replacing it?' '' said Judy McGrath, president of the MTV network. ''But you can't beat it to death.''</p>
        <p>''Real World'' bills itself as ''a real-life soap opera'' and producers at MTV's News and Docs division are quick to point out that they have nothing to do with it.  ''Even in the documentary film world,'' said Lauren Lazin, the vice president for news and documentaries, ''I've had people discount our department because they think it's just 'Real World.' That's tough.''</p>
        <p>At MTV, reality is a concept that's parsed very fine. ''Real World'' and ''True Life'' both make their differing claims on it. Then there is Tom Green, of the outrageous ''Tom Green Show.'' A one-man lab experiment who regularly leaves the television studio to assault real-life bystanders with his own twisted Andy Kaufmanesque persona, Mr. Green won't be interviewing teenage drug addicts for a ''True Life'' documentary anytime soon. But he is currently working on an episode of his own show about his recent experiences with testicular cancer. ''It will definitely have a lot of the elements of 'True Life,' '' Ms. Lazin allowed.</p>
        <p>The average adult might lose his balance in such a slippery world. But according to Ms. Lazin, the younger generation, the most media-saturated in history, doesn't have a problem. ''They get the difference clearly,'' she said. For instance, the ''True Life'' episode first shown in August, ''I'm a Pro Wrestler,'' never bothers to state the obvious, that professional wrestling is a choreographed spectacle, not a competitive sport. Dave Sirulnick, 35, MTV's executive vice president of news and production, which oversees News and Docs, said: ''For our audience, it would be like saying, 'Well, you know, an episode of ''Felicity'' is not true.' It gets at the way young people watch it.'' Ms. McGrath, alluding to the mix-and-match aesthetic of hip-hop music, sums up her network's nonmusic programming this way: ''I look at it as the world remixed by MTV.''</p>
        <p>For the last 14 years, Ms. Lazin has had the job of figuring out the documentary portion of the mix. She came to the network with a Stanford master's in film and her own well-received documentary about young women in the 1920's, ''The Flapper Story,'' to her credit; and her film peers were more than a little puzzled. ''The attitude,'' Ms. Lazin said, ''was, 'If you want to be a documentarian, why aren't you at PBS?' '' And even she admits that when she first arrived at MTV, ''the word 'documentary' probably sounded like homework.''</p>
        <p>Her seemingly odd career choice paid off. In the intervening years, Ms. Lazin noted, relatively cheap-to-produce documentaries on cable channels like Discovery and Lifetime rushed in to fill the programming needs of the cable universe. ''That created an audience for reality filmmaking that I don't think was nearly there 20 years ago,'' she said. In the meantime, MTV was growing from a fairly small independent player in the television world into a crucial member of the Viacom corporate family. ''Sometimes I feel like I have my own independent film production company at this big multinational entertainment conglomerate,'' she said, though her personal style is more casual than corporate.</p>
        <p>Ms. Lazin does not completely disown the influence of ''Real World'' on her documentary division. ''On the pro side,'' she said, ''it has really groomed an audience to appreciate real-life drama. I think viewers get that real life can be as engrossing and engaging and challenging, as entertaining as actors and actresses and sets and make-up and costumes and all the artifices of narrative storytelling.''</p>
        <p>After the third season of ''Real World,'' in 1994, the H.I.V.-positive Pedro Zamora died, occasioning an outpouring of grief from the small televised circle of his San Francisco housemates and from the larger circle of 1.3 million young viewers. ''That to me was a wake-up call that our audience cared deeply about this disease,'' Ms. Lazin said.</p>
        <p>If the robust documentary culture at MTV has drawn a measure of inspiration from ''Real World,'' it is also attuned to the real real world. Mr. Sirulnick's news department aggressively covers stories that involve youth culture or the music industry or both. Coverage of the 1990 Florida obscenity trial of 2 Live Crew grew into the 1994 documentary ''Gangsta Rap,'' exploring censorship and rap. Coverage of the 1998 case of Matthew Shepard, murdered in Wyoming for being gay, led to the Emmy-nominated ''True Life: Matthew's Murder.''</p>
        <p>''The great moments have come back and forth,'' Mr. Sirulnick said, ''between the daily news organization covering something right now and the longer documentary analysis.'' In the case of the Columbine school shootings, MTV was, sadly, ahead of the curve, having just completed work on a documentary that addressed earlier high-profile school shootings. After the body count came in from Colorado, ''Warning Signs'' was rushed to air.</p>
        <p>''People were amazed,'' Ms. Lazin said. '' 'How did you know? How did you get this?' It was like, 'That's what we do.' We're in the business of taking that pulse.'' Last year, MTV's ''Fight For Your Rights'' campaign, which included ''Warning Signs,'' won a special Emmy.</p>
        <p>Ms. Lazin is pushing the channel to explore quieter, artier avenues in the documentary film world. This kind of film is represented by ''The Travelers,'' which was shown for the first time on April 19 (the channel regularly rebroadcasts its documentaries), concluding the current season of ''True Life.'' Shot in black-and-white with a cinema-verite sensibility, ''The Travelers'' tells the story of teenage hobos entirely in their own words. Only gradually, in accordance with the languid, folk rhythm of the film, does the desperate nature of the traveling enterprise become apparent. On the evidence presented, hard-core travelers either quit the life or, in travelers lingo, wind up as ''dead frogs.''  ''A lot of 'Travelers' is very traditional storytelling,'' Ms. Lazin said. ''Filmmakers don't have to come in with this bag of tricks of what they think MTV wants.''</p>
        <p>The Oscar-nominated filmmaker Liz Garbus made ''The Travelers.'' And if Ms. Lazin has her way, Ms. Garbus will be only one of many established artists to take advantage of MTV's documentarian safe haven. ''I would love to do a documentary with D. A. Pennebaker or Barbara Kopple,'' Ms. Lazin said, referring to two stars of nonfiction film. ''I don't think you have to be 24 to make a film about 24-year-olds.'' Ms. Lazin herself harbors ambitions of taking documentary films (including her own) into theaters, to be distributed by the MTV Films division responsible for ''Election'' and ''Varsity Blues.''</p>
        <p>If ''The Travelers'' represents one future for documentaries at MTV, the present seems to belong to Serena Altschul, the 29-year-old ''True Life'' reporter-producer who wades through the carnage of youth culture with the swagger of a seasoned war correspondent. On a recent ''True Life'' episode, ''I'm a Hacker,'' when Ms. Altschul is told that a particular teenage computer hacker has an attitude problem, she replies in her best Lauren Bacall voice: ''That's O.K. I have an attitude problem too.'' Mr. Sirulnick said, ''When you see our show, you know it's not the way ABC would do it.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, Ms. Altschul's aggressively hip persona and MTV's relentless focus on young people's stories can add up to unusual television. ''People are like, 'Come to our party, we're all going to be sniffing heroin here,' '' Ms. Lazin said. For the ''Fatal Dose'' documentary, Ms. Altschul left a teenage heroin party to get in a car driven by one of her obviously addled teenage subjects. ''Serena's up with every bit of it,'' Mr. Sirulnick said, ''whereas with Stone Phillips or whoever, it would be, 'How's school, junior?' ''</p>
        <p>For those not of the MTV generation, the whole notion of fearless MTV documentaries takes some getting used to. In the middle of ''I'm on Crystal Meth,'' Ms. Altschul asks Sheriff Joe Arpao for the lowdown on crystal meth use in Maricopa County, Arizona. He takes a close look at her and her punkishly short blond hair and wonders aloud: ''MTV, what is that, a music station? You want me to sing?''</p>
        <p>TELEVISION/RADIO Joseph Hooper's last article for Arts &amp; Leisure was about Ben Stein.</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 16, 2000, Tuesday  An article in Sunday Styles this week about the popularity of Commune, a new restaurant on East 22nd Street in Manhattan, misspelled the surname of an MTV news anchor who dined there recently. She is Serena Altschul, not Altshul.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 16, 2000, Tuesday</p>
        <p>An article in Sunday Styles this week about the popularity of Commune, a new restaurant on East 22nd Street in Manhattan, misspelled the surname of an MTV news anchor who dined there recently. She is Serena Altschul, not Altshul.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Joseph Hooper's last article for Arts &amp; Leisure was about Ben Stein.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
