<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lending Crackdown Said to Fall Short</title>
    <meta content="14DELT$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="36" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199568"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mortgages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Foreclosures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Delta Financial Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lambert, Bruce</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/Upstate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Subprime Lending</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreclosures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mortgages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05EFDB133BF937A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1273" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lending Crackdown Said to Fall Short</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRUCE LAMBERT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lambert, Bruce</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Consumer groups say crackdown by three federal agencies has failed to halt abuses by Delta Financial Corp, nationwide home lending company that makes high-cost loans to people with poor credit ratings; say settlement of suits by two New York State regulatory agencies has failed to help thousands of suffering borrowers, many of whom have been forced into foreclosure or bankruptcy; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When government regulators announced recently that they were protecting homeowners by cracking down on an abusive nationwide lending company, Margaret C. Roundtree hoped that they would intervene to save her home in Jamaica, Queens, from foreclosure.</p>
        <p>''I did expect to get some help,'' said Mrs. Roundtree, 68, a hospital technician. ''But nothing has been done.'' Now she faces the loss of the house, where she has lived since 1972.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When government regulators announced recently that they were protecting homeowners by cracking down on an abusive nationwide lending company, Margaret C. Roundtree hoped that they would intervene to save her home in Jamaica, Queens, from foreclosure.</p>
        <p>''I did expect to get some help,'' said Mrs. Roundtree, 68, a hospital technician. ''But nothing has been done.'' Now she faces the loss of the house, where she has lived since 1972.</p>
        <p>Three federal agencies settled their joint lawsuit against her lender, Delta Financial Corporation of Woodbury, N.Y., on March 30. They portrayed their decision as an industrywide warning to the booming but loosely regulated market in high-cost loans. But advocates for victims like Mrs. Roundtree say the officials let Delta off the hook. The critics also say the settlement did nothelp the thousands of suffering borrowers, many of whom have been forced into foreclosure or bankruptcy.</p>
        <p>And consumer groups are also attacking Delta's earlier settlement with two New York State regulatory agencies. While the state did extract some restitution for victims, critics say it is only a token amount of Delta's $1 billion-a-year operation. Only a few of the victims will be aided, and nothing will go to those who must lose their homes.</p>
        <p>Delta operates in 26 states, and in New York grew to become the largest subprime lender, a type that makes high-cost loans to people with poor credit ratings. But critics called Delta a predatory lender that focused on minority neighborhoods. Its victims, often elderly women, were targets of high-pressure pitches for loans with exorbitant fees and interest. Reacting to the complaints, regulators accused the company of violating lending and civil rights laws. But the settlements have frustrated Delta's critics.</p>
        <p>''Delta admits no wrongdoing and agrees to comply with the law -- which it's supposed to do anyway -- while many victims are stuck with horrendous loans for years to come, and people who already lost their homes and their life's savings are completely left out,'' said Sarah Ludwig, director of the Neighborhood Economic Development Advocacy Project, a nonprofit group in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Federal and state officials defend their decisions, saying they imposed heavy sanctions and stopped the abuses now, avoiding years of litigation and possibly keeping thousands more from being victimized. The restitution is the most ever won in the nation's banking industry, the regulators say. Delta also agreed to restrictions beyond statutory requirements and is subject to civil and criminal penalties for new violations.</p>
        <p>''This is not just a slap on the wrist,'' said David Medine, an associate director at the Federal Trade Commission, one of the agencies involved in the settlement of the federal lawsuit.</p>
        <p>Another agency, the Justice Department, said, ''This suit sends a clear message that the United States won't tolerate discrimination or illegal lending practices.'' The Department of Housing and Urban Development declined to reply to the critics. But earlier, Secretary Andrew M. Cuomo praised the deal, saying,  ''Lenders and mortgage brokers are put on notice by this settlement agreement that HUD and the federal government are prepared to fight for borrowers who are being victimized.''</p>
        <p>The first official to go after Delta was the state attorney general, Eliot L. Spitzer. At first, he tried to place Delta in receivership, but eventually his office settled. His civil rights chief, Andrew Celli, said: ''We started with one goal, to change the way the largest subprime lender in the state does business, and we met that goal. We made a conscious choice to reform this industry.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Spitzer's deputy, Mark Peters, added, ''Delta is now bound by a 265-page code of conduct, requiring a whole bunch of things the law doesn't require.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Spitzer pushed for $6 million in restitution, which the State Banking Department raised to $7.25 million, plus 525,000 shares of Delta stock it valued at nearly $5 million. ''The governor instructed us to obtain the maximum amount of restitution to the victims,'' said the acting banking superintendent, Elizabeth McCaul. ''We took the most from the company we possibly could.</p>
        <p>Under that settlement, 600 Delta borrowers were recently offered reductions of $50 to $400 in their monthly payments, or 5 percent to 40 percent, Ms. McCaul said. In addition, foreclosures were halted for 75 homeowners, who will also be offered reductions.</p>
        <p>Delta issued this statement: ''While Delta does not believe it has done anything wrong, it has acceded to these agreements in the best interests of our shareholders, customers and the communities we serve.''</p>
        <p>But the restitution pales in comparison to the victims' losses and Delta's billions of dollars in loans, critics say. The reduced-payment benefits end when borrowers die, sell their homes, refinance or are foreclosed upon. And the value of the Delta stock has shrunk below $1 million. ''It's funny money, all flash and no cash,'' said Patricia Sturdevant, director of the National Association of Consumer Advocates, a nonprofit group. ''This case sets a dangerous precedent for going soft on lenders who are cheating people out of house and home. The message is that crime pays.'' Since the federal agencies won no restitution, she said, there is no aid for victims outside New York.</p>
        <p>Because the settlements were court-approved, there is no apparent way to challenge them. Despite their long efforts against predatory lending, consumer groups say they were not consulted. The federal agencies filed their lawsuits against Delta, and that same day announced their settlements with the company.</p>
        <p>Most disturbing, the critics say, is a state requirement that victims who accept restitution must promise not to seek any other legal redress. They cannot sue Delta, and if they eventually face foreclosure, they will not be allowed to raise a defense in court that their loans were improper.</p>
        <p>''That's terrible,'' said Lee Squitieri, a Manhattan lawyer who is organizing a class-action suit for Delta borrowers. He is seeking to release them from bad loans, get compensation for excessive charges and impose punitive damages.</p>
        <p>Nearly all the restitution offers that the critics have heard about are for $50 a month. ''It's not nearly enough,'' said Nancy Slahetka, a lawyer who fights foreclosures for South Brooklyn Legal Services. Those offers are paltry, she said, and there are too few of them. ''There are thousands of victims, not hundreds.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Roundtree said she fell behind on her bills when she was out of work because of two car accidents and her resulting hip surgery. Her lawyer, Jeffrey Rosenberg, said she was talked into a loan of $92,000, ''far more than she needed,'' to pay her debts, plus $20,800 for home improvements, with cash supposedly left over for her. The interest rate was 12.15 percent.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Roundtree said she reluctantly signed blank papers when salespeople threatened that ''they were going to take my house away.'' Soon after, she said, she tried to invoke her right to cancel but was ignored. She never got the final papers, she said, and most of the promised renovations were never done.</p>
        <p>Although technically Delta did not originate the loan, the company was involved at the outset and took over the loan at the closing, the lawyer said. Inevitably, the payments fell into arrears, and now Delta is demanding $137,000 or the house.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
