<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fresh Air Fund Opens New World</title>
    <meta content="14FUND" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199268"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE FRESH AIR FUND"/>
      <identified-content>
        <org class="indexing_service">Fresh Air Fund</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nicholas, Raven</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Guida, Charles</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Guida, Diane</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Saslow, Linda</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507EFDF1F38F937A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1164" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fresh Air Fund Opens New World</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LINDA SASLOW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Saslow, Linda</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Raven Nicholas of Bronx, NY, one of about 140 children who will spend time this summer with Fresh Air Fund host families on Long Island; Raven will join Charles and Diane Guida and their children in Southampton for third summer; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR 11-year-old Raven Nicholas, the best things about spending part of her summer in Southampton are riding her bike and going to the beach. But there is also the cherished privacy of having her own room with a television set and a phone. Not to mention riding in a Porsche, sailing on a yacht and meeting Donna Karan and Puff Daddy at a private party.</p>
        <p>There is no time to miss her mother and older sister in the Bronx, Raven said, because her summer mom, Diane Guida, keeps her busy with continuous activities. If the family is not bike riding, visiting friends or off to the beach, Raven fills her time watching videos at home with the 4-year-old twins, Carley and Cassidy, or listening to music with Elizabeth, 17.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR 11-year-old Raven Nicholas, the best things about spending part of her summer in Southampton are riding her bike and going to the beach. But there is also the cherished privacy of having her own room with a television set and a phone. Not to mention riding in a Porsche, sailing on a yacht and meeting Donna Karan and Puff Daddy at a private party.</p>
        <p>There is no time to miss her mother and older sister in the Bronx, Raven said, because her summer mom, Diane Guida, keeps her busy with continuous activities. If the family is not bike riding, visiting friends or off to the beach, Raven fills her time watching videos at home with the 4-year-old twins, Carley and Cassidy, or listening to music with Elizabeth, 17.</p>
        <p>Raven is one of about 140 children between the ages of 6 and 18 who will spend two weeks in July with host families on Long Island through the Fresh Air Fund. Since 1877, the nonprofit fund has given free summer vacations to more than 1.7 million New York City children. This year, 6,000 children will visit volunteer host families in suburbs and small towns in 13 states. More than 65 percent of the children are invited back to stay with host families year after year.</p>
        <p>This is the third summer Raven has been at the Guidas' Southampton home.</p>
        <p>''After we saw a newspaper article about the Fresh Air Fund, we decided that this was something we wanted to do,'' said Charles Guida, an internist whose medical practice is in Southampton. ''I grew up in the city, and although we never went on vacations, my father used to take us in the car and just drive up to New England, stopping along the roadside for a picnic.</p>
        <p>''Those were the best times, and having recently moved from Queens out to the Island, I wanted to be able to provide an experience away from the city for someone whose folks couldn't do it for them.''</p>
        <p>With three daughters, the Guidas requested a girl. After an initial interview, when they learned that Raven, then 9, would be staying with them, they were excited but apprehensive, said Mrs. Guida, who was then a stay-at-home mother but has since returned to work as a biology teacher at Southampton High School.</p>
        <p>''Being that we live in a predominantly white neighborhood, and most of our friends are white, I worried whether she would feel comfortable in this environment,'' Mrs. Guida said. Raven is black.</p>
        <p>Dr. Guida had different concerns. ''I was only afraid that she would be bored,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But their worries were dispelled the moment they met Raven.</p>
        <p>''She came with a wonderful attitude,'' Mrs. Guida said. ''This was her vacation, and she was going to enjoy every minute of it.''</p>
        <p>Remembering how she felt before meeting the Guida family, Raven said: ''I was very nervous. I had gone away to Canada the summer before, but my older sister went with me, and even though we lived with different families, we saw each other all the time.''</p>
        <p>But Mrs. Guida remembered a bright-eyed 9-year-old who did not seem nervous at all.</p>
        <p>''When she saw her own room with a phone and TV, she told us she felt like the queen,'' she said. ''Within two days, she was holding our hands and hugging us.''</p>
        <p>For Raven's mother, Crystal Jenkins, a two-week break while her daughters were visiting other families allowed her to work overtime at her job as a customer service representative for Planned Parenthood.</p>
        <p>''Raven was particularly excited about going to the Hamptons because it was the same weekend that President Clinton was there,'' she said. ''When she called home, she talked nonstop about the family, her room and everything they were doing. She got to experience so many things she never would in the city.''</p>
        <p>Raven's two-week vacation included bike riding, boat rides, local theater, the circus, barbecues with family friends of the Guidas, being with the twins, walks to town with Elizabeth and almost daily trips to the beach.</p>
        <p>One of the best parts of going to the beach was riding in Dr. Guida's Porsche, said Raven. Another highlight was a Fresh Air Fund party whose guest list included Donna Karan and Puff Daddy.</p>
        <p>''It was at a mansion,'' Raven said. ''They had dinner and rides for us, and a pool.''</p>
        <p>But for Raven, not even that party could compare with the time she spent with Elizabeth, walking into town, going to a movie or just doing girl things.</p>
        <p>''For me, it's like having another sister,'' said Elizabeth, who was 15 during Raven's first summer. ''We hung out together at night, listened to music and taught each other dances. Last year when Raven came, she had corn braids and she braided my hair like hers.''</p>
        <p>The twins were in their ''terrible 2's'' during Raven's first summer and sometimes got on her nerves, Mrs. Guida said. ''But by the second year, they were older and loved to come into her room to watch TV, or asked her to push them on the swings,'' she said. ''There was more interaction and it was much easier for all of them. This summer they'll be turning 5, and I think it will be the best yet.''</p>
        <p>Throughout the year, Raven stayed in touch with the Guidas by phone, and at Christmas she received gifts from her host family.</p>
        <p>Last summer, they helped her start a photo journal of her summer experiences.</p>
        <p>''There were stories behind every picture,'' Raven said. ''When I came home, I had so much to tell all my friends.''</p>
        <p>Children are selected to participate in Fresh Air Fund programs based on financial need. They are from low-income families, with the majority receiving public assistance. There are no financial requirements for hosts of Fresh Air Fund children. Host families are not paid.</p>
        <p>As summer approaches, Raven is excited about returning to the Guida home, where her own bike is waiting for her. But she is less eager for a repeat of last summer's boat ride, despite the adventure on the boat she told her mother was a yacht.</p>
        <p>''It was really fun,'' Raven said. ''But when they parked the boat, we rocked back and forth, and I got a little seasick.''</p>
        <p>More information about the Fresh Air Fund, (800) 367-0003, is available via email at freshair@freshair.org or at the Web site at www.freshair.org. Tax-deductible contributions may be sent to the Fresh Air Fund, 1040 Avenue of the Americas, New York, N.Y. 10018.</p>
        <p>THE FRESH AIR FUND</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
