<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Trying to Keep the Sun From Setting on Britpop</title>
    <meta content="14ROSE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="34" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199227"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Oasis (Music Group)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Supergrass (Music Group)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rosen, Jody</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06EEDD1138F937A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1453" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Trying to Keep the Sun From Setting on Britpop</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JODY ROSEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rosen, Jody</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jody</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THOUGH England has long since come to terms with the political reality of its empire's demise, remembered glory still haunts the national imagination and reverberates in the country's popular culture: in the flag-fluttering pomp that greets royal weddings, in the blaring jingoism of the tabloid press, in the chants, to the tune of ''Rule Britannia,'' which rumble down from the terraces of soccer stadiums.</p>
        <p>Yearning for the grandeur of England's yesteryear exists even in the youth-obsessed realm of pop music. English pop has its own version of a venerated imperial heyday: the mid-1960's peak of the British Invasion. On the one hand, the era is a symbol of British cultural triumph: the moment when the Beatles, the Kinks, the Who and other seminal bands stampeded onto the American charts and established London as the home of the pop zeitgeist. But it is the music itself that resonates with modern Britain's fondest and most sentimental self-image. Its wonderfully rich mix of psychedelia and Victoriana, of fuzz-toned rock guitars and French horn fanfares, of visionary anthems and quaintly provincial evocations of village greens, conjures a fairytale England in which the boundlessly sunny present and the charmed past magically coexist.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THOUGH England has long since come to terms with the political reality of its empire's demise, remembered glory still haunts the national imagination and reverberates in the country's popular culture: in the flag-fluttering pomp that greets royal weddings, in the blaring jingoism of the tabloid press, in the chants, to the tune of ''Rule Britannia,'' which rumble down from the terraces of soccer stadiums.</p>
        <p>Yearning for the grandeur of England's yesteryear exists even in the youth-obsessed realm of pop music. English pop has its own version of a venerated imperial heyday: the mid-1960's peak of the British Invasion. On the one hand, the era is a symbol of British cultural triumph: the moment when the Beatles, the Kinks, the Who and other seminal bands stampeded onto the American charts and established London as the home of the pop zeitgeist. But it is the music itself that resonates with modern Britain's fondest and most sentimental self-image. Its wonderfully rich mix of psychedelia and Victoriana, of fuzz-toned rock guitars and French horn fanfares, of visionary anthems and quaintly provincial evocations of village greens, conjures a fairytale England in which the boundlessly sunny present and the charmed past magically coexist.</p>
        <p>For a few years in the mid-1990's, the English pop scene was consumed by the desire to relive that hallowed musical era. Guitarists sprouted mop-top hairdos, Union Jacks were hoisted above drum-risers and a wave of young bands flooded the airwaves with records whose jaunty, tuneful Anglicisms self-consciously invoked the legacy of the 60's greats. Flaunting classically English pop qualities -- wry lyrics, winsome melodies, exaggerated cockney-inflected vocals -- the trend was a defiantly Anglocentric rebuke to the grunts and macho poses of the American grunge bands that were dominating guitar pop: the chiming, cheery sound of the empire striking back.</p>
        <p>The movement, christened Britpop, swept up English pop culture in a whirl of music-inspired patriotism. When American bands resuscitate old styles, it is usually to make fashion statements. But the flag-toting fervor of the Britpop revival was something more serious. Against a backdrop of domestic uncertainty -- a floundering British economy, anxiety about joining the European Union, political weariness after nearly two decades under Conservative government -- Britpop offered an image of cultural renewal, promising not merely to resurrect the giddy cool of swinging London circa 1966 but to recapture some deeper lost essence of British greatness.</p>
        <p>Half a decade later, England has conspicuously abandoned the Britpop cause.</p>
        <p>The music press long ago declared the movement dead. Most of Britpop's upstarts have disappeared, dropping off the radar when their borrowed riffs and blokey histrionics fell out of fashion. Britain's latest guitar pop favorites strike different postures: quavering earnestness (Radiohead, Travis), Americana obsessed (Gomez), techno-savvy (Beta Band) or, in the case of the reformed ex-Britpop torchbearers Blur, a bit of all three.</p>
        <p>But traditionalist stalwarts remain. Two veteran Britpop bands, Oasis and Supergrass, are currently in the United States, touring behind new albums steeped in English pop classicism. Now several years removed from the peak moment of Britpop hysteria, the records provide insight into why the movement flared and fizzled, and are a study in Britpop's limitations and possibilities.</p>
        <p>Oasis was Britpop's marquee act. Led by the scowling, leering Gallagher brothers -- the lead singer Liam and the guitarist-songwriter Noel -- the band arrived on the British charts in 1994 with a bombastic sound and a grandiose aspiration: to be ''bigger than the Beatles.'' Where Britpop groups like Blur, Pulp and Gene embraced the literate, arty aspect of the English pop tradition, Oasis offered visceral pleasures: crunching guitars and the catharsis of soaring choruses. In Liam Gallagher, the band had a bona fide rock star, who put across his brother's often meaningless lyrics with gruff conviction.</p>
        <p>''(What's The Story) Morning Glory?,'' Oasis' second album, sold 15 million copies, but the band never managed a Beatles-like conquest of global pop. Its third record bombed, and the recently released fourth, ''Standing on the Shoulder of Giants'' (Epic EK63586), a collection of rhythmically turgid, mid-tempo retro-rock songs, finds Oasis slipping into wearisome self-parody.</p>
        <p>The root of Oasis's problem is the same misapprehension that vexed so many of its Britpop compatriots: a failure to comprehend the urbanity of classic English pop. The music of the British Invasion might sound quintessentially English to today's listeners, but its creators were cosmopolitan seekers, who assimilated a range of influences -- in particular black American music -- into their own very personal styles.</p>
        <p>Oasis professes devotion to the Beatles, but the band's gloss on its heroes is shallow. Though it endlessly cribs the Beatles' mannerisms -- announcing the gravity of its ballads with stately ''Hey Jude''-like piano chords, even co-opting famous Beatles lyrics -- Oasis has absorbed none of its idols' zeal for musical exploration. The Gallagher brothers traveled far on the momentum of their bluster, but with ''Standing on the Shoulder of Giants'' the band reaches the same dead end as a hundred Britpop lesser-lights: worshiping vapidly at the altar of the past, Oasis consigns itself to present-day irrelevance.</p>
        <p>Supergrass, a rugged trio from Oxford, never dared to dream Oasis-size dreams of rock glory. But its musical ambitions have always been vast. When the band first appeared in 1994, playing funny, taut songs that combined the stuttering tenacity of the Manchester punk legends the Buzzcocks with the wit of songwriters like Ray Davies of the Kinks, Supergrass quickly gained a reputation as Britpop's lovable clown princes. But even the band's most cartoonish songs, like its breakthrough single ''Caught by the Fuzz,'' were constructed with orchestral intelligence -- every burst of feedback, guitar overdub and background vocal was witty, telling and exact.</p>
        <p>On its third album, ''Supergrass'' (Island 314-542 388-2),  the band's promise is splendidly realized. Augmenting its power trio line-up with keyboards and a small string section, the singer-guitarist Gaz Coombes, the bassist Mick Quinn and the drummer Danny Goffey have made an almost epic album, integrating a riot of influences into an organic and highly eccentric contemporary variation on classic British guitar pop.  Avoiding the pratfalls of their peers, Supergrass treats Britpop not as an ideology or a kind of connoisseurship but as an approach to songcraft. The result is one of the best English pop records in many years.</p>
        <p>Supergrass has a command of a variety of pop styles, which it moves between with easy virtuosity. The band plays passages of Sly and the Family Stone-inspired funk, dreamy guitar arpeggios that sound like Pink Floyd, rave-ups in the style of glam-era David Bowie; it changes tempos and time signatures like a 70's progressive rock band and sings lonesome high-harmony parts that recall Brian Wilson's Beach Boys.</p>
        <p>But Supergrass has such a strong musical personality and such a lucid sense of purpose that the record never feels like pastiche: every arrangement and production flourish is made in the service of a song. The stunning album opener, ''Moving,'' is a case in point. The song starts out with Mr. Coombes crooning, accompanied only by guitar and strings, erupts into a churning, manic R-and-B chorus, then morphs into a lush Philadelphia soul-style ballad.</p>
        <p>But this stylistic hodgepodge feels just right: each musical passage gives its accompanying lyric the perfect coloration, and the listener feels the overarching mood of road-bound resignation in the loping bass line that nudges the song through its wistful fade.</p>
        <p>WHILE ''Supergrass'' is, unmistakably, a record in the Britpop tradition, it never indulges in genre cliches. When Oasis tries to spike its new album with psychedelia, the group trots out shopworn trippy motifs -- walls of echo and guitar reverb, sitar drones, woozy keyboards. Supergrass's psychedelia, like the Beatles', grades into the baroque; it is intrinsic, textural, symphonic -- an accumulation of sonic details, bristling beneath unusual melodies, that reward solitary listeners with sharp ears and a good set of headphones.</p>
        <p>''Supergrass'' is the album that the mid-90's Britpop movement promised but never delivered. Smart, inventive, melodically rich, rambunctious yet subtle, ambitious but totally unpretentious, it distills the best qualities of classic English pop and makes an emphatic argument for the idiom's continued vitality. Half a decade after the musical patriots packed up their flags, Supergrass has given England a reason to wave them. ''Britpop'' is dead; long live Britpop.</p>
        <p>MUSIC Jody Rosen's most recent article for Arts &amp; Leisure was about white rappers.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Jody Rosen's most recent article for Arts &amp; Leisure was about white rappers.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
