<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>They Come to the Dance Floor Bearing a Gift: Jazz</title>
    <meta content="14GLAD$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="46" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199247"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jazz</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Lincoln Center Jazz Orchestra</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Swing Dance Troupe</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gladstone, Valerie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marsalis, Wynton</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jazz</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E7D71138F937A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1624" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>They Come to the Dance Floor Bearing a Gift: Jazz</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VALERIE GLADSTONE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gladstone, Valerie</byline>
      <dateline>SANTA CRUZ, Calif.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Valerie Gladstone's article on Lincoln Center Jazz Orchestra's For Dancers Only tour, featuring musician Wynton Marsalis; orchestra, which will be appearing at New York's Roseland Ballroom, has added Swing Dance Troupe to the tour; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ON a sunny Tuesday in April, shortly after arriving in his seaside room at the West Coast Hotel here, the dapper trumpeter Marcus Printup removed his horn from its case, strode out on his balcony, leaned back on his heels and played Louis Armstrong's sultry ''West End Blues.'' On the beach below, a young man in jeans rose from the sand, threw his hands to the sky and began swaying his hips as if possessed. As Mr. Printup's lustrous notes filled the air, a couple of other members of the Lincoln Center Jazz Orchestra appeared on nearby balconies with their instruments and for the next 20 minutes a jubilant sound billowed out to meet the waves.</p>
        <p>By the time they stopped, other beachgoers who had joined the first lone dancer were clamoring for more. The musicians, beat after a flight from New York and a two-hour bus ride from San Francisco, retreated for a short break before sound check. Accustomed to touring's rigors, they were swinging hard only a few hours later at the venerable Cocoanut Grove Ballroom, led by the trumpeter Wynton Marsalis, the orchestra's musical director and a Pulitzer Prize-winning composer. It was the first stop on the West Coast leg of the orchestra's ''For Dancers Only'' tour, named for the 1937 Sy Oliver instrumental.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ON a sunny Tuesday in April, shortly after arriving in his seaside room at the West Coast Hotel here, the dapper trumpeter Marcus Printup removed his horn from its case, strode out on his balcony, leaned back on his heels and played Louis Armstrong's sultry ''West End Blues.'' On the beach below, a young man in jeans rose from the sand, threw his hands to the sky and began swaying his hips as if possessed. As Mr. Printup's lustrous notes filled the air, a couple of other members of the Lincoln Center Jazz Orchestra appeared on nearby balconies with their instruments and for the next 20 minutes a jubilant sound billowed out to meet the waves.</p>
        <p>By the time they stopped, other beachgoers who had joined the first lone dancer were clamoring for more. The musicians, beat after a flight from New York and a two-hour bus ride from San Francisco, retreated for a short break before sound check. Accustomed to touring's rigors, they were swinging hard only a few hours later at the venerable Cocoanut Grove Ballroom, led by the trumpeter Wynton Marsalis, the orchestra's musical director and a Pulitzer Prize-winning composer. It was the first stop on the West Coast leg of the orchestra's ''For Dancers Only'' tour, named for the 1937 Sy Oliver instrumental.</p>
        <p>On Friday night, when the band hits New York's Roseland Ballroom, where the jazz-loving Kofi Annan, the Secretary General of the United Nations, will do the introductions, Mr. Marsalis's 14 top-flight musicians, along with Milt Grayson, a vocalist to melt the coldest heart, and the competition-winning ballroom dancers Janice Wilson and Paulo Lanna will have encouraged audiences in 23 cities across the country to get up and dance. The BBC World Service will broadcast the concert on Sunday morning at 11. After the band's 10 years of giving concerts around the world, Mr. Marsalis and Rob Gibson, Jazz at Lincoln Center's executive producer and director, decided that audiences might like to do more than tap their toes. ''We kept being asked,'' says Mr. Marsalis in his warm New Orleans accent, ''why we don't have dances.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Marsalis, 38, first grabbed the public's attention in 1979. In addition to displaying unusual talent at the Juilliard School in New York and with Art Blakey's Jazz Messengers, he had a drive to spread the word of jazz's depth and breadth. In 1991, he established Jazz at Lincoln Center to do just that, with Gordon J. Davis as chairman of the board, giving jazz its first permanent home. It is to move to even more auspicious quarters in 2003 with the completion of new facilities on Columbus Circle. Mr. Gibson, 41, a producer of radio shows and jazz festivals in his native Georgia, joined Mr. Marsalis at the outset and became his equally zealous partner. They've been trying to put this dance tour on the road, costly at $850,000, for quite some time. Johnston &amp; Murphy, the maker of men's footwear, and the National Endowment for the Arts came up with the money.</p>
        <p>With this tour, Mr. Marsalis and Mr. Gibson hope that Jazz at Lincoln Center, already renowned for its concerts, education programs, workshops and television and radio broadcasts, will help revive the long-lost connection between jazz and dance, currently getting a boost from the Broadway hits ''Contact'' and ''Swing.''</p>
        <p>Jazz, a combination of minstrel songs, ragtime and blues, thrived in the New Orleans of the early 1900's, when dance halls jumped. By the 1920's, 2,000 dance bands were touring the country. A decade later, the fabled hoofers at Harlem's Savoy Ballroom captured the nation's attention with the Lindy Hop and generated a craze for new dance styles. But in the 50's, the public turned to rock 'n' roll and rhythm-and-blues for its dance music, and some jazz musicians, perhaps defensively, came to regard playing dances as demeaning. Mr. Marsalis's attitude is just the opposite. ''Great musicians inspire great dancers -- and vice versa,'' he says. ''Dance helps jazz evolve. Maybe we'll encourage new styles.''</p>
        <p>The orchestra's regular supporters didn't immediately go for the dance tour. ''We had to convince presenters to do what they're not used to doing,'' Mr. Gibson says. ''Plus, it's not always easy to find places with dance floors.'' They also had to figure out a danceable repertory. ''Our intention isn't to bring something back,'' he says. ''We're not into retro. We're building on what's gone before. Of course, we play Ellington, Basie and Goodman, but it's also a perfect opportunity for band members to write new music specifically for dance.''</p>
        <p>MS. WILSON and Mr. Lanna suggested that on the first dance tour the band should stick to swing numbers, saving Latin and Afro-Cuban grooves for future engagements. Rising to the occasion, the trombonists Wycliffe Gordon and Ron Westray, the saxophonist Ted Nash, the bassist Rodney Whitaker and Mr. Marsalis all wrote songs. Composing isn't new to them; every band member records independently and plays with small ensembles.</p>
        <p>Before opening in Santa Cruz, Mr. Gordon, who is built like a linebacker but writes like a poet, divulges the ingredients for a good dance number. ''The most important thing is the melody,'' he says. ''It's got to make you want to move. I keep in mind the tempo and the length of the song. It can't be too long. It needs good ground rhythm and space for the dancers to improvise.</p>
        <p>''Once the song begins, the dancer and the musicians do their thing -- it works a lot like call and response. An unexpected move by a dancer might inspire a musical phrase.'' Although he has started taking swing classes, tonight there's no time. Trombone in hand, he heads backstage to warm up.</p>
        <p>Until the 50's, the graceful Cocoanut Grove Ballroom, which was built in 1907, was a regular stop for dance bands. The manager, Gary Green, swears that ''the ghosts of Ellington, Calloway, Basie and Young still linger in its rooms.'' They certainly look very lively in their photos in the formal dining area, where their images are lined up alongside Stan Kenton, Benny Goodman, Lionel Hampton and Tommy Dorsey. Last year, the orchestra's concert at the University of California at Santa Cruz sold out its 2,000 tickets. This year, the Cocoanut Grove sold all of its 750 tickets, a harbinger of the orchestra's nearly sold-out dance tour.</p>
        <p>Just as the crowd spills through the door, the musicians sidle into their chairs on the bandstand, spruce in dark suits, white shirts, fancy ties and spats. In the crowd, older couples in velvet and silk are as common as college students in slacks and sweaters. The lights dim and a painted moon and silvery stars glitter on the ceiling. Mr. Marsalis gives the count for the rousing ''Big John Special,'' a Goodman signature tune. In no time, the dance floor is jammed. A few couples bound into the Lindy Hop, with its syncopated steps forward and back and requisite twirls, but far more devise a highly individualized hybrid of many styles. Two high school students, Jason Whittinghill, 17, and his friend Eric Callero, 18, observe from the sidelines, both nattily turned out in starched shirts, vests and striped pants.</p>
        <p>''I've been following Wynton since I was in seventh grade,'' says Mr. Whittinghill, jiving in place to ''Perdido.'' Mr. Callero says, ''It's very positive music.''</p>
        <p>Overhearing them, Melanie Johnson and Jordan Rager, both 20-year-old college students, chime in. ''This dancing is great because it's about the person you're with,'' Mr. Rager says. Yolanda Dybdahl, 75, and her 81-year-old husband, Chris, are here for another reason. ''It makes us feel 18,'' she says.</p>
        <p>At the end of the evening, the dancers aren't the only ones sweating. Nobody works harder in a dance band than the rhythm section. ''I knew in the back of my mind,'' says the drummer Herlin Riley, wearily putting away his equipment, ''that this was going to be a workout, but doing it is something else. Me and my man, Rodney, we have to keep driving to keep the tempo up.''</p>
        <p>Two days later, they're all up for the fervent audience of 2,000 that's set to go at Stanford University near Palo Alto. It's the 30th anniversary celebration for the presenter, Stanford's Lively Arts, and for the occasion an enormous tent has been erected on the university's pastoral grounds. Ms. Wilson and Mr. Lanna start off the proceedings with dance lessons. ''You have to become part of the music,'' Ms. Wilson says, her short skirt swinging out, her feet flying off the ground as Mr. Lanna takes her hand and spins her over his back. Their earnest students follow, leaving out the flip. Elegant in black tie, the famous Lindy Hopper Frankie Manning, who is 85 and who has been teaching in the area, watches approvingly. ''The music is bringing people together,'' he says.</p>
        <p>After the concert, heading back to the hotel on the bus, the band exchanges notes. ''It's wonderful seeing couples touching and holding each other,'' says Mr. Grayson, a true romantic. The much more pragmatic saxophonist, Joe Temperley, says, ''I think our sound's finally tight.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Nash sounds worried. ''It's hard to imagine what it's going to be like playing again for audiences that stay in their seats,'' he says. ''How will we know what they're feeling?''</p>
        <p>DANCE Valerie Gladstone's most recent article for Arts &amp; Leisure was about the choreographer Trisha Brown.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Valerie Gladstone's most recent article for Arts &amp; Leisure was about the choreographer Trisha Brown.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
