<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Type Casting</title>
    <meta content="14HELLERT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199148"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="CHILDREN'S BOOKS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Heller, Steven</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">de Cumptich, Roberto Vicq de</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Bembo's Zoo: An Animal A B C Book (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Columns/Children's Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E4D71F39F937A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="916" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Type Casting</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Steven Heller</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Heller, Steven</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Steven Heller reviews book Bembo's Zoo: An Animal A B C Book by Roberto de Vicq de Cumptich; drawings (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bembo's Zoo</p>
        <p>An Animal A B C Book.</p>
        <p>Written and illustrated</p>
        <p>by Roberto de Vicq de Cumptich.</p>
        <p>Unpaged. New York:</p>
        <p>Henry Holt &amp; Company. $17.95.</p>
        <p>(All ages)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Bembo's Zoo</p>
        <p>An Animal A B C Book.</p>
        <p>Written and illustrated</p>
        <p>by Roberto de Vicq de Cumptich.</p>
        <p>Unpaged. New York:</p>
        <p>Henry Holt &amp; Company. $17.95.</p>
        <p>(All ages)</p>
        <p>Every graphic designer has at least one favorite typeface that he or she uses ad nauseam. If I were not the art director of The New York Times Book Review (and thus restricted to Franklin Gothic, Imperial and Bookman), mine would be Bembo.</p>
        <p>This superb example of an Italian Renaissance letterform was originally derived from ''De Aetna,'' a book by Pietro Bembo about his visit to Mount Etna, made in 1495 by the Venetian printer Aldus Manutius. The typeface was revived in the 1920's by Stanley Morison and christened Bembo. Its weight, balance and color, the cut of its serifs (the little feet that cap and ground the letters) and the relationship of its capital to lowercase characters are sublime and work equally well for text and display settings. (Incidentally, typographers, like wine aficionados, frequently use the words ''sublime,'' ''balanced'' and ''robust'' to describe a fine cut of type. But I digress.)</p>
        <p>Bembo has long been one of the most popular typefaces for continuous reading. But never before in the history of typography (designers also love to invoke the history of typography as a pedigree) has its versatility been better displayed than in Roberto de Vicq de Cumptich's ''Bembo's Zoo.'' In his first book for children, de Cumptich, a Brazilian-born book jacket designer and an art director at HarperCollins, has created an abecedary of animals made entirely from Bembo letterforms and punctuation marks -- nothing else. And, you know, the conceit works.</p>
        <p>The original typeface was cut as metal punches by the master craftsman Francesco Griffo and meticulously composed by Aldus himself. Back in the 15th century, however, given the arduous mechanics involved in setting a page of text, the idea that this or any contemporary typeface could be transformed into pictographs was unthinkable. During most of the 20th century this kind of type-play required considerable cutting, pasting and photocopying to achieve the result. But in the 21st century, computer-aided digital typesetting has made it possible to do almost anything that the imagination conjures. Which is not to imply that de Cumptich's pictorial concoctions are at all facile. These are indeed original creations, designed to celebrate the typeface as it tickles perception.</p>
        <p>''Bembo's Zoo'' owes an inspirational debt to ''The Scarecrow,'' a 1925 children's book for adults by the avant-garde modernist designer-typographers Kurt Schwitters and Theo van Doesburg and the author Kate Steinitz, in which animated letterforms, used like stick figures, are both the characters and the props within a politically charged narrative. It is also influenced by a long tradition of abecedaries in which letterforms reveal the characteristics of other objects or things. The theory is that these books help children recognize letters in relation to the words they represent, as well as the physical nature of the things themselves.</p>
        <p>''Bembo's Zoo'' offers the same fundamental aides-memoire as other alphabet books, but it also provides another layer of visual experience. By using the letterforms as elements of the picture, the author invites the reader to decipher what form constitutes a particular creature, and the design reveals that the representation can be accomplished in many ways -- not only, for example, through realistic rendering.</p>
        <p>But even more important, the letters that are used as the shapes are only those found in the word itself. So the hippopotamus is constructed from these letters alone, with the license of using the letters more than once. The legs and neck of the giraffe are, predictably, multiple uppercase I's; for the ibis, B's are used, surprisingly, as feathers and lowercase i's as claws. Some of the designs, like those for the lion and the owl, are fairly easy to decode, while others, including those for the peacock and the flamingo, require a second and even a third glance.</p>
        <p>Graphic designers are not always accomplished as pictorial illustrators. Indeed, these days there is a curious professional caste distinction between those who just draw and paint and those who work only with type. With the advent of the computer, graphic designers are able to make ersatz (and often bad) illustrations with digital montage or collage programs. But de Cumptich has marshaled his expertise as a manipulator of shape, form and color so as not to infringe on the territory of traditional illustrators. He has used a limited palette -- forest green, orange and black, printed on a faint yellow background -- with great skill and sophistication. Thus, unlike most children's books, ''Bembo's Zoo'' is also a total design package, with each spread deliberately made to look as complete as a poster.</p>
        <p>You do not have to be a type maven to enjoy the conceit of ''Bembo's Zoo.'' But it would not be surprising if, after you spend some time with the book, Bembo becomes your favorite typeface.</p>
        <p>CHILDREN'S BOOKS Steven Heller is the art director of The New York Times Book Review and the author of ''Letterforms: Bawdy, Bad and Beautiful'' and ''The Swastika: A Symbol Beyond Redemption?''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Steven Heller is the art director of The New York Times Book Review and the author of ''Letterforms: Bawdy, Bad and Beautiful'' and ''The Swastika: A Symbol Beyond Redemption?''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
