<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sushi and Neighborliness in Harrison</title>
    <meta content="14DINE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199237"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DINING OUT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hajime (Harrison, Ny, Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reed, M H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CEEDA1138F937A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="754" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sushi and Neighborliness in Harrison</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By M. H. REED</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Reed, M H</byline>
      <dateline>HARRISON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>M H Reed reviews Hajime, sushi restaurant in Harrison, NY; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A FEW floral touches decorate Hajime, a neat, compact dining spot and clearly one of the favorites in the Harrison neighborhood. Most diners are greeted by name, and ''catch-up'' inquiries about events in private lives are not unusual. These regulars keep Osamu Takahashi -- sushi master and owner and known as Sam to his friends and customers -- and his staff bustling.</p>
        <p>Of the restaurant's two dining areas, the more pleasant is the first, which has a lovely long sushi counter with two carefully organized refrigerator cases well stocked with glistening fresh fish. A few tables for two line the wall of the narrow remaining space. Not only is this area bright and airy, but also the precise, almost orchestrated movements of cutting and assembling sushi and sashimi make an amazing show. The back room accommodates larger groups, sometimes with noisy young children who can make a small dining area seem even smaller.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A FEW floral touches decorate Hajime, a neat, compact dining spot and clearly one of the favorites in the Harrison neighborhood. Most diners are greeted by name, and ''catch-up'' inquiries about events in private lives are not unusual. These regulars keep Osamu Takahashi -- sushi master and owner and known as Sam to his friends and customers -- and his staff bustling.</p>
        <p>Of the restaurant's two dining areas, the more pleasant is the first, which has a lovely long sushi counter with two carefully organized refrigerator cases well stocked with glistening fresh fish. A few tables for two line the wall of the narrow remaining space. Not only is this area bright and airy, but also the precise, almost orchestrated movements of cutting and assembling sushi and sashimi make an amazing show. The back room accommodates larger groups, sometimes with noisy young children who can make a small dining area seem even smaller.</p>
        <p>A couple of specials are usually available, but no one will tell you about them unless, like the regular clientele, you know to ask. Having them listed on a blackboard would be extremely helpful. It wasn't until we heard a request for special chef's salad that we knew specials existed. It may be that this salad changes, but ours was a beauty. A perfectly ripe avocado half came piled high with chopped tuna, filaments of seaweed strewn atop, and the sauce, sprinkled with sweet, plump pine nuts, was zesty with hot wasabi. A menu item called toro taru taru seemed similar.</p>
        <p>Other appetizers also deserved note. Served warm, tiger's eye proved particularly delightful; tender broiled squid, prettily carved, wrapped a center of pink smoked salmon. And a small bowl of sunomono brought remarkably generous chunks of seafood in a vinegary dressing. Tangy nuta made good use of Hajime's many kinds of clams; this time the seafood was tossed with green onion, miso and sprouts.</p>
        <p>Showered with sesame seeds, seaweed salad was properly crunchy and satisfying. But we have had tissue-thin slices of fluke (usuzukuri) more artistically arranged, often into a rosette. Here the fish came simply piled in the center of the plate, and the complex ponzu dipping sauce that came with it was too strong and salty.</p>
        <p>Like the decor, most of Hajime's presentations were artistically modest, rather surprising for a cuisine that puts a great deal of emphasis on the appearance of a dish. But Hajime's draw is the fine variety of pristine raw fish kept on hand. Apart from three or four kinds of clam, familiar ingredients filled out the sushi menu, and assortments came in 7, 9 or 10 pieces. We enjoyed broiled eel, or anago (unage on the menu) brushed with a sweet thick sauce, squid (ika), yellow tail (hamachi), several cuts of tuna, tobiko (flying fish roe) and scallop (hotategai), among others. Except for slightly sinewy pieces of Spanish mackerel -- a delicious, delicate fish -- slicing was expert.</p>
        <p>Nuggets of rice forming the bed for pieces of sushi proved too thick for our taste. Better control of the fish-rice ratio could be had with combinations like chirashi or any of the ''don'' dishes, in which the chosen fish slices arrive atop a bowl of rice.</p>
        <p>With an eye to the coming warm weather, we skipped most of the cooked dishes, like hot noodle soups. Because of its popularity, we tried shrimps tempura. The shrimps were fresh but limp under a heavy batter.</p>
        <p>Dinner averages $24 without drinks, tax and tip, but the range is broad. Hajime is just south of Harrison Avenue.</p>
        <p>Hajime  267 Halstead Avenue,  Harrison. 777-1543.</p>
        <p>GOOD</p>
        <p>ATMOSPHERE -- Small, trim storefront restaurant with sushi counter and a few tables in the front area and an unprepossessing dining space in back. Warm welcome and prompt, friendly service.  SMOKING -- None.  RECOMMENDED DISHES -- Sunomono and nuta (vinegared seafood), tiger's eye, seaweed salad, all sushi and sashimi.  PRICES -- Lunch, main dishes, $8.75 to $13.75. Dinner, main dishes, $13 to $22.  CREDIT CARDS -- Major cards accepted.  HOURS -- Lunch, Tuesdays through Saturdays, noon to 2:30 P.M. Dinner, Tuesdays through Thursdays and Sundays, 5:30 to 10 P.M.; Fridays and Saturdays, 5:30 to 11 P.M.  RESERVATIONS -- Accepted.  WHEELCHAIR ACCESS -- Street level.</p>
        <p>THE RATINGS -- Excellent, Very good, Good, Satisfactory, Poor.  Ratings reflect the reviewer's reaction primarily to food, with ambience and service taken into consideration. Menu listings and prices are subject to change.</p>
        <p>DINING OUT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
