<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Plutocrats' Retreats; Boston</title>
    <meta content="PLUTO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sophisticated Traveler Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel; Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199134"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hotels and Motels</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Boston (Mass)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Fifteen Beacon (Boston Hotel)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reynolds, Catharine</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sophisticated Traveler Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts/Boston</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hotels and Motels</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E3D91F39F937A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1553" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Plutocrats' Retreats; Boston</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Catharine Reynolds</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Reynolds, Catharine</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Catharine Reynolds profiles Fifteen Beacon, luxury hotel on Beacon Street, Boston; notes Fifteen Beacon is a milestone in Boston's renaissance as financial and cybercenter; photos (Special section, The Sophisticated Traveler) (Part 2 of 2-part section) (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Who would have thought to recycle a 1903 office building occupied by the local school committee into a sumptuous boutique hotel? And in Boston, where, in spite of years of revolving-door management, clients remain sentimentally attached to the Ritz or are at best reluctant patrons of its upstart neighbor, the Four Seasons.</p>
        <p>Enter Paul G. Roiff, a seasoned real estate developer untainted by hotel experience. The 10-story Beaux-Arts building on the narrowest stretch of Beacon Street, with its cast-iron facade and limestone Corinthian columns under a copper cornice, struck him as a potential gem. And so 15 Beacon Street became Fifteen Beacon.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Who would have thought to recycle a 1903 office building occupied by the local school committee into a sumptuous boutique hotel? And in Boston, where, in spite of years of revolving-door management, clients remain sentimentally attached to the Ritz or are at best reluctant patrons of its upstart neighbor, the Four Seasons.</p>
        <p>Enter Paul G. Roiff, a seasoned real estate developer untainted by hotel experience. The 10-story Beaux-Arts building on the narrowest stretch of Beacon Street, with its cast-iron facade and limestone Corinthian columns under a copper cornice, struck him as a potential gem. And so 15 Beacon Street became Fifteen Beacon.</p>
        <p>Designed by William Gibbons Preston, one of the architects who shaped Boston's post-Civil War expansion into the Back Bay, today's Fifteen Beacon is a milestone in Boston's renaissance as a financial and cybercenter. The project has been undertaken in much the same perfectionistic spirit that animated merchants a century ago. For Mr. Roiff the cost overrun -- more than $11 million -- seems almost a point of honor, the price of doing things right. He made light of delays of more than a year, hoisting a banner from the cornice that proclaimed ''Opening Eventually.'' ''Eventually'' arrived last Jan. 3, and curiosity soon led my husband and me through Fifteen Beacon's doors.</p>
        <p>A plaster cast of Houdon's bust of Benjamin Franklin gazed on us as we signed the register. Mr. Roiff and Celeste Cooper, the hotel's designer, understand that whatever the announced purpose of their visit, people come to Boston expecting to touch the hem of American history, so they have placed busts of Washington, Jefferson, Franklin and John Adams throughout the hotel.</p>
        <p>Ms. Cooper's knowing hand is easy to trace, starting with the mahogany and stainless steel ''carpet'' leading across the small lobby toward the elevators. We followed it, taking in the Jules Olitski painting ''Green Dot'' and the handful of inviting chairs in front of the fireplace before the cage elevator sped us to the eighth floor.</p>
        <p>Our room had ''tryst'' writ large, with firelight blazing, the patchwork counterpane on the four-poster turned down and the lights dimmed. The bellman explained the bedside control panel for the fireplace, surround-sound and television with gee-whiz pride.</p>
        <p>Connectivity is omnipresent: there is a four-inch LCD television alongside the lighted shaving mirror to monitor markets, a desk-side color printer-fax-copier in every room, cordless as well as conventional telephones and a high-speed Internet outlet. Individual direct telephone and fax numbers are assigned to each of the 61 guest rooms and suites.</p>
        <p>The techie toys are subtly integrated into Fifteen Beacon's decor. Throughout the hotel, breakfast tones of espresso, oatmeal and cream are brightened with spots of light and gleaming metals: A pair of silver candlesticks here, a stainless steel chimney breast or table there. No two rooms are identical. Five are furnished with king-size beds; the rest are queen-size, though all are four-posters, and each room has a working fireplace.</p>
        <p>We ricocheted around our room, exclaiming at the plate of chocolate chip cookies, the small pot of miniature red roses, a still life of apples, the signed, limited-edition Joe Greene black-and-white architectural photographs, the basins set on Greek white marble counters and the Kiehl toiletries, including lip balm.</p>
        <p>In a world where a minibar's contents define the clientele the management seeks to wow, Fifteen Beacon offers the best: Ch2/3teau Lafite-Rothschild and Krug Grande Cuvee; Ketel One vodka, Dueno tequila, Knob Creek bourbon and Dallas Dhu single malt; three varieties of aromatherapy; an energy bar and shortbread; ginseng; chocolate sardines and oxygenated water.</p>
        <p>Nor have gracious domestic details been neglected: closets filled with we-trust-you wood and silk hangers, handsome luggage racks, an umbrella, current magazines set beside a chaise longue. Overnight shoeshine and 15-minute pressing services ensure that guests feel pampered.</p>
        <p>That evening we had dinner at The Federalist, the hotel's touted 80-seat restaurant. Set at the intersection of financial, legal and political Boston, the Fed is a natural rendezvous for a drink, a quick bite at the bar, courtship rites, or celebrations of major closings, which means that guests turn up in everything from raveled sweaters to sedate Savile Row, with sharp Italian tailoring predominating.</p>
        <p>After a brief wait in the bar beneath the gaze of a Ben Freeman painting of Thomas Jefferson peering from a two-dollar bill, we shifted to the airy dining room. Under Theodoros Stamos's mammoth Abstract Expressionist ''Corinthian,'' we sat at a table freighted with glittering European place settings. A square vase crammed with white camassias anchored the still life.</p>
        <p>Five breads from Cambridge's Hi-Rise Bread Company arrived as we read the menu. Each was admirable but deserved to have been warmed. The executive chef, Robert Fathman, aims to foster the clubby atmosphere by establishing a number of year-round house specials, withdrawing items only when worthy ingredients are not available. The pan-seared diver scallop with butternut squash and chanterelles confirmed the excellence of his suppliers. Subtle Windy Hamlet goat cheese sharpened the sweetness of a salad of red and golden beets. Although the cottony texture of my John Dory disappointed, I consoled myself filching forkfuls of my husband's fine lamb with baked dates and exemplary mashed potatoes -- and even sips of his 1998 Rasteau Ctes du Rhne ($15 a glass).</p>
        <p>High ceilings and upholstered banquettes circling the room mean that noise levels are tolerable. Overexcited behavior on the part of the diners occasionally punctuates the silken service. No sooner did a sneeze tickle me than our waitress appeared bearing a tissue box on a silver salver, seemingly having conjured it from the sleeve of her Alan Bilzerian-designed jacket.</p>
        <p>Desserts varied. The lemon cheesecake was more stodge than pucker. Tough pastry and apples stored past their prime spoiled an apple-Calvados tart. Still, the blueberry and the applejack sorbet and the banana chocolate chip ice cream were decidedly special.</p>
        <p>The hotel's 17,000-bottle wine list, created by the general manager, William J. Sander III, and the Russian-born sommelier, Christian Vassilev, reads like an oenophile's Almanach de Gotha, spotlighting cult wines like 1994 Screaming Eagle ($2,500) and Sassicaia, although there are others in the $40 and $50 range. The wines by the glass are no less carefully chosen. The best way to appreciate the cellar is to visit the stone-paved basement, where, if there isn't a private party, one can ogle the vintages themselves.</p>
        <p>And the oversize granite pillars at the end of the cellar recall the building's history -- this is Boston, after all. They are remnants of Edward Bromfield's 1722 three-story house, which was known for its terraced garden with flowers and fruit trees, and for its panoramic view of the harbor. This spring Fifteen Beacon is reviving local husbandry, installing greenhouses on the roof to cultivate herbs and heirloom tomatoes for its table.</p>
        <p>When we flung open our curtains in the morning, we were reminded that the hotel is largely hemmed in by neighboring office buildings as tall or taller. On the other hand, we could enjoy a treat unusual in modern hotels: Windows that open.</p>
        <p>My husband dodged what looked to be the last of the season's snowflakes for a run on nearby Boston Common, while I passed up the hotel's privileges at a health club a block away in favor of the bicycles, treadmill and weights of the small downstairs exercise room. All of which left us eager for a breakfast in our room of McCann's Irish oatmeal with lavender honey and a fruit plate, prettily presented if crowded onto a too-small tray. The only surprise was the small pitcher of what looked and tasted like cream for my morning tea.</p>
        <p>The glass shower screen was no match for the floods unleashed by an English shower head the size of a pizza pan, making the bundles of white towels monogrammed ''XV'' on the heated towel rail a necessity for a mopping-up operation. But at least there was no shortage of hot water.</p>
        <p>My husband left for his office while I dawdled. Late that morning I checked out, stepping out into Beacon Street -- a thoroughfare known in the 17th century as ''Poor House Lane'' -- my bank balance diminished but not annihilated. The doorman swept me into the Mercedes that Fifteen Beacon makes available to guests. Its driver betrayed only a flash of perplexity when I asked him to take me home, all of three blocks down Beacon Hill. And, like each of the dozen or so (out of 130) staff members who had helped us, he was quick to ask what had pleased me. Now that's attitude.</p>
        <p>At Home on Beacon Street</p>
        <p>FIFTEEN BEACON, 15 Beacon Street, Boston, Mass. 02108 (telephone: 617-670-1500; fax: 617-670-2525), has 61 rooms and suites, with rooms ranging from $395 to $895, suites from $1,200 to $1,800.  THE FEDERALIST (617-670-2515) is open for breakfast and lunch Monday through Friday, for brunch Saturday and Sunday, and for dinner daily. Lunch for two, with main course, dessert, glass of wine and coffee, is about $75; dinner for two, with appetizer, main course, dessert and coffee is about $120, exclusive of wine.</p>
        <p>Catharine Reynolds is a contributing editor at Gourmet.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Catharine Reynolds is a contributing editor at Gourmet.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
