<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mom's Personal Shopper</title>
    <meta content="14AGE.$09" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199413"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE AGE OF DISSONANCE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Morris, Bob</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE6D8143BF937A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="784" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mom's Personal Shopper</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BOB MORRIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Morris, Bob</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bob Morris describes his efforts to become personal clothes shopper for his aging, ailing mother (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Everyone knows it is a mother's right to make remarks on a son's appearance, from facial hair to slide sandals. But for years I've been on my mom's case, too. Like many daughters of the Depression, she is conflicted about spending money or time on fashion and hates shopping. When she was younger, she got away with this nonapproach because she was an obvious beauty. Now that she's living with a chronic illness, dressing herself to distract from her fragility seems especially crucial to me, and it is harder than ever to control my bossy inner stylist on my visits home.</p>
        <p>''When you're older,'' I tell her, ''busy is better, so get out the jewelry.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Everyone knows it is a mother's right to make remarks on a son's appearance, from facial hair to slide sandals. But for years I've been on my mom's case, too. Like many daughters of the Depression, she is conflicted about spending money or time on fashion and hates shopping. When she was younger, she got away with this nonapproach because she was an obvious beauty. Now that she's living with a chronic illness, dressing herself to distract from her fragility seems especially crucial to me, and it is harder than ever to control my bossy inner stylist on my visits home.</p>
        <p>''When you're older,'' I tell her, ''busy is better, so get out the jewelry.''</p>
        <p>On a recent visit, I found myself declaring that hairnets were only appropriate for bed and that T-shirts for summer were a bad idea with her thin neck and arms. I know I shouldn't have said anything, since she is trying to make peace with her physical condition, and is not, after all, an apartment one can just decorate to taste. But in some ways, a mom is a home too, isn't she? Besides, it was clear to me she'd be more attractive in half-sleeved button-down blouses. And by the way, why was she wearing such dowdy pants and bedroom slippers? Didn't she want to look her best?</p>
        <p>Eventually, my questions roused her from her torpor.</p>
        <p>''O.K. then,'' she said, ''take me to Macy's.'' And off we went.</p>
        <p>Having style issues with one's mom, it turns out, isn't so unusual among the fashion-conscious. Growing up, Simon Doonan, the creative director of Barneys New York, recalled asking his mom, ''Why can't you dress like that?'' while watching the plumed ladies on elephants at the circus. Lulu Johnson, a sleek young minimalist designer whose mother is the outrageous Betsey Johnson, remembers being mortified as a teenager at the remarks made by her classmates about her mother's wild style. Even Michael Kors, who credits his mother's subtle taste as inspirational, finds himself stridently art-directing her on occasion.</p>
        <p>''She makes mistakes, too, and I'm blunt,'' he said. ''I'll tell her she can't wear black loafers with the chamois pants suit, and she says, 'I didn't ask you, did I?' ''</p>
        <p>I know how he feels. Still, my mom's more like the designer Cynthia Rowley's mom.</p>
        <p>''She's lovely, but clueless about fashion,'' she said of her mom, who lives in Barrington, Ill. ''If I give her a beautiful coat from my collection, she'll ask if she can wear it for bowling. If I put her in heels, she'll walk around holding onto the furniture.''</p>
        <p>''If her taste were just a little worse,'' she continued, ''it might inspire me with some wacky design ideas. But that's where my dad comes in. He's got looks going on with plaids and earmuffs that would blow your mind.''</p>
        <p>Ultimately, Ms. Rowley advised me to let it go with my mom. Yet, as modest and mundane as it was, my trip with Mom to Macy's seemed to be lifting her spirits immensely.</p>
        <p>We found the half-sleeve style of shirt that I had envisioned for her, and it suited her so perfectly she bought three. I convinced her to buy solid-colored T-shirts for underneath,  and then found my inner stylist explaining the concept of color-blocking, even as shoppers and saleswomen looked on with raised eyebrows. We found the brand of elastic-waist pants she prefers, and on another floor, she tried on hats that would keep her hairdo from blowing in the wind. She isn't a hat person (who is, really?), and none of them worked. But as I carefully put each of them on her head and pointed her into the mirror, she looked at herself and laughed with a lightness I hadn't seen in years. Back home, she had the energy to try everything on again before bed.</p>
        <p>''Thank you, my little personal shopper,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Shakespeare wrote, ''Thou are thy mother's glass, and she in thee calls back the lovely April of her prime.'' He's right, of course. It's just that even at my age, when I should know better, I can't help being the mirror that calls it as it is right now.</p>
        <p>Weeks later, Mom is constantly wearing the shirts we bought together (sometimes with pearls, even) and getting compliments that have more of an effect on her than all the pills in her medicine basket. ''So you see, Mom, style does matter,'' I told her.</p>
        <p>''I don't know about style,'' she said. ''But those are very nice shirts.''</p>
        <p>THE AGE OF DISSONANCE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
