<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Word for Word/90-Second Philosophy; In Bite-Size Portions, The Wise Men Made Easy</title>
    <meta content="14WORD$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Books; Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199495"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Philosophy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Strathern, Paul</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Alexander, Daryl Royster</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Socrates in 90 Minutes (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E7D6153BF937A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1455" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Word for Word/90-Second Philosophy; In Bite-Size Portions, The Wise Men Made Easy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DARYL ROYSTER ALEXANDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Alexander, Daryl Royster</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Word for Word column of excerpts from Paul Strathern's books summarizing writings of famous philosophers, starting with Socrates in 90 Minutes; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>COLLEGE may be the last official stop for mulling over life's eternal questions. You know: Who am I? Where am I? And, of course, what is the meaning of life? Then again, maybe not.</p>
        <p>Philosophy, the discipline for students intent on becoming philosophers until their parents ask how much it pays, is now within reach and available without the deep pain of tuition. For the past few years, the writer Paul Strathern, who earned his own philosophy degree at Trinity College in Dublin, has been distilling most of the world's best-known philosophers to 90 minutes, which, he said, is the length of a soccer game. A godsend in this era of the short attention span, his series, published by Ivan R. Dee, begins with ''Socrates in 90 Minutes,'' wittily compressing his life and works, and proceeds to Locke, St. Augustine, Descartes and Sartre, among others. New books on George Berkeley and Paul-Michel Foucault are scheduled to be published next month.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>COLLEGE may be the last official stop for mulling over life's eternal questions. You know: Who am I? Where am I? And, of course, what is the meaning of life? Then again, maybe not.</p>
        <p>Philosophy, the discipline for students intent on becoming philosophers until their parents ask how much it pays, is now within reach and available without the deep pain of tuition. For the past few years, the writer Paul Strathern, who earned his own philosophy degree at Trinity College in Dublin, has been distilling most of the world's best-known philosophers to 90 minutes, which, he said, is the length of a soccer game. A godsend in this era of the short attention span, his series, published by Ivan R. Dee, begins with ''Socrates in 90 Minutes,'' wittily compressing his life and works, and proceeds to Locke, St. Augustine, Descartes and Sartre, among others. New books on George Berkeley and Paul-Michel Foucault are scheduled to be published next month.</p>
        <p>Mr. Strathern wanted to write about the philosophers' lives, he said, adding in a few of their ideas. ''If you fix it that way, people do get it,'' he said. ''It gets to them, like garlic: it sticks to them.'' Still, in this breathless age of day-trading, online banking, gym for lunch and the New York minute, who has 90 minutes? Let's whittle this philosophy thing down to 90 seconds. Excerpts from the books follow.</p>
        <p>DARYL ROYSTER ALEXANDER</p>
        <p>Bearing a Gift</p>
        <p>Socrates developed a method of negatively aggressive questioning called dialectic (the forerunner of logic). This he used in conversation to cut through the twaddle of his adversaries and arrive at the truth. . . .</p>
        <p>Socrates went on to study under the philosopher Archelaus, ''by whom he was beloved in the worse sense.'' . . . It wasn't long before Socrates had demonstrated to his own satisfaction that the so-called wise men of Athens in fact knew nothing -- just like him. So he concluded that the Delphic Oracle had been right: he was the wisest man -- because he knew that he knew nothing. . . . One of his best-remembered remarks is, ''The unexamined life is not worth living.''</p>
        <p>-- ''Socrates in 90 Minutes''</p>
        <p>The First Republican</p>
        <p>Plato explains that most human beings live as if in a dim cave . . . In more philosophical terms, Plato believed that everything we perceive around us -- the shoes and ships and sealing wax, and cabbages and kings, of everyday experience -- is merely appearance. . . .</p>
        <p>In Plato's ideal republic there would be no possessions or marriage (except among the lower orders, who were presumably the only people fit for such things). Children would be removed from their mothers soon after birth and educated communally. In this way they would come to regard the state as their parents. . . .</p>
        <p>In Plato, eros is regarded as the soul's impulse toward good. In its lowest form this is expressed in our passion for a beautiful person and our wish for immortality by producing offspring with that person. . . .</p>
        <p>-- ''Plato in 90 Minutes''</p>
        <p>The First Logician</p>
        <p>Where Plato's approach to the world was essentially religious, Aristotle's tended toward the scientific. This made him disinclined to dismiss the world around us as unreal. . . . Aristotle's most significant achievement was in the field of logic.  To all intents he invented this subject. Aristotle came to see logic as the foundation on which all learning was based. . . For example, if we make the following two statements: All humans are mortal. All Greeks are human. It can be inferred that: All Greeks are mortal. . . .</p>
        <p>Aristotle called his logic ''analytika,'' which means unraveling. Every science or field of knowledge had to start from a set of first principles, or axioms. From these its truths could be deduced by logic (or unraveled).</p>
        <p>-- ''Aristotle in 90 Minutes''</p>
        <p>That's Master Kung to You</p>
        <p>Confucius is the Latinized form of Kungfutzu (which means ''the master Kung''). . . . Late in life, Confucius was to remember: ''When I was 15 I was only interested in studying.'' This was the bedrock of his life, which he would later see as having been divided into distinct stages: ''When I was 30 I began my life; at 40 I was self-assured; at 50 I understood my place in the vast scheme of things; at 60 I learned to give up arguing; and now at 70 I can do whatever I like without disrupting my life.'' . . .</p>
        <p>Confucius was essentially a moral teacher. He was always sincere and distrusted eloquence. . . . The key element of Confucius's teachings was symbolized by the Chinese character jen. This stood for a conceptual blend of magnanimity, virtue, and love of humanity.</p>
        <p>-- ''Confucius in 90 Minutes''</p>
        <p>His Mother Loved Him</p>
        <p>Machiavelli was not an evil man. And . . . his political philosophy was not evil in itself. It was just extremely realistic. . . . [From the chapter, ''For Those Who Seize Power by Crime,'' from ''The Prince''] ''Cruelties inflicted immediately to secure one's position are well inflicted (if one may speak well of ill).'' Note this last proviso: Machiavelli still considered himself moral, even if his advice was not. . . Machiavelli's book is advice to a prince on how to run a state. It is not a guide to personal morality. It is aimed at a rare class of people in specific circumstances. . . Bertrand Russell was absolutely right when he called The Prince ''a handbook for gangsters.'' Mafia families do resemble Renaissance city-states -- in their primitive political methods, though alas not in their cultural sophistication or taste.</p>
        <p>-- ''Machiavelli in 90 Minutes''</p>
        <p>Man's a Piece of Work</p>
        <p>Descartes retained a deep ambivalence toward his education. It seemed to him to be largely rubbish: rehashed Aristotle encrusted with centuries of interpretations; the stifling theology of Aquinas which had answers for everything but answered nothing; a morass of metaphysics. . . . One day while sitting in his stove, Descartes had a vision. It's not clear precisely what he saw under these rather steamed-up circumstances, but it seems that this vision contained a mathematical picture of the world. . . . No matter how deluded I may be in my thoughts about myself and the world, there is just one thing that is undeniable: I am thinking. This alone proves to me my existence. In the most famous remark in philosophy, Descartes concludes: ''Cogito ergo sum'' (I think, therefore I am).</p>
        <p>-- ''Descartes in 90 Minutes''</p>
        <p>Too Dull for Words</p>
        <p>With John Locke philosophy enters its flat-earth period. Great ideas are often obvious. None more so than those of John Locke.  Much of his thought we would now regard as common sense. His philosophy was to lay the foundations of empiricism, with its belief that our knowledge of the world is based on experience. It also introduced the idea of liberal democracy, which has become the shibboleth of Western civilization. . . . This all makes Locke's philosophy rather uninteresting.</p>
        <p>-- ''Locke in 90 Minutes''</p>
        <p>A Terrible Thing to Waste</p>
        <p>''The height of audacity in serving up pure nonsense, in stringing together senseless and extravagant mazes of words, such as had previously only been known in madhouses, was finally reached in Hegel, and became the instrument of the most barefaced general mystification that has ever taken place, with a result which will appear fabulous to posterity, and will remain as a monument to German stupidity.'' So wrote Schopenhauer, who was Hegel's colleague at the University of Berlin. This remark is not intended to prejudice but merely to warn. With Hegel, philosophy becomes a matter of extreme seriousness, so we'd best get any jokes out of the way right at the start.</p>
        <p>-- ''Hegel in 90 Minutes''</p>
        <p>A Legend in His Own Mind</p>
        <p>With Nietzsche philosophy becomes dangerous again, this time with a difference. In previous centuries philosophy had been dangerous for philosophers; with Nietzsche it becomes dangerous for everyone. Nietzsche ended up by going mad. . . . Nietzsche's larger philosophical ideas are barely worthy of the name -- whether he's talking about supermen, eternal recurrence (the idea that we live our lives again and again throughout eternity), or the sole purpose of civilization (to produce ''great men'' such as Goethe, Napoleon and himself).</p>
        <p>-- ''Nietzsche in 90 Minutes''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
