<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Another Round of Questions Aimed at Pequots</title>
    <meta content="14PEQU" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Books; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199293"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gambling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Casinos</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mashantucket Pequot Indians</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Indians, American</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Ledyard (Conn)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">North Stonington (Conn)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Preston (Conn)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Interior Department</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bureau of Indian Affairs</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Benedict, Jeff</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hamilton, Robert A</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Without Reservation (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut/Mystic and the Southeastern Coast</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Casinos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Indians, American</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gambling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E7D91F38F937A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2542" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Another Round of Questions Aimed at Pequots</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT A. HAMILTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hamilton, Robert A</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Officials in Ledyard, North Stonington and Preston, Conn, armed with Jeff Benedict's book Without Reservation, have asked Congess to investigate whether Mashantucket Pequots, who have opened huge casino on tribal reservation, may be offshoot of Rhode Island tribe and that reservation was created illegally by Congress in 1983; also seek meeting with Pres Bill Clinton and want top Interior Department and Bureau of Indian Affairs officials to attend upcoming town meeting on subject; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SINCE 1984 the residents of Ledyard, North Stonington and Preston have watched gambling on the Mashantucket Pequot Tribal reservation grow from a bingo hall to a billion-dollar casino that attracts 40,000 people a day. Taxpayers in the three towns that border the casino have spent almost $1.3 million fighting the expansion of the reservation and the recognition of two other tribes in the region.</p>
        <p>Now a $26 book has given them ammunition in the battle, town officials said. The book, by Jeff Benedict, a Massachusetts author, contends that the Mashantucket Pequots might really be an offshoot of a Rhode Island tribe and that the reservation was created illegally in 1983 when Congress granted the tribe official recognition and unwittingly approved a map that contained two and a half times as much land as it was supposed to, and expanded even those boundaries, pulling land out of the reach of local towns' taxes and land-use regulation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SINCE 1984 the residents of Ledyard, North Stonington and Preston have watched gambling on the Mashantucket Pequot Tribal reservation grow from a bingo hall to a billion-dollar casino that attracts 40,000 people a day. Taxpayers in the three towns that border the casino have spent almost $1.3 million fighting the expansion of the reservation and the recognition of two other tribes in the region.</p>
        <p>Now a $26 book has given them ammunition in the battle, town officials said. The book, by Jeff Benedict, a Massachusetts author, contends that the Mashantucket Pequots might really be an offshoot of a Rhode Island tribe and that the reservation was created illegally in 1983 when Congress granted the tribe official recognition and unwittingly approved a map that contained two and a half times as much land as it was supposed to, and expanded even those boundaries, pulling land out of the reach of local towns' taxes and land-use regulation.</p>
        <p>Earlier this month, the towns called for a Congressional investigation and have asked for a meeting to discuss the matter with President Clinton when he attends the graduation ceremonies at the United States Coast Guard Academy in nearby New London this month.</p>
        <p>Officials of the three towns have also requested that top Department of the Interior and Bureau of Indian Affairs officials attend a public meeting this Thursday evening at North Stonington High School to discuss the recognition process and the findings in the book. Mr. Benedict has said he will also attend.</p>
        <p>Ledyard First Selectman Wesley J. Johnson Sr. said he expected the turnout at the meeting to be particularly heavy, given the nature of the information in the book, ''Without Reservation'' (Harper Collins, 2000).</p>
        <p>''At the least, there should be a Congressional investigation,'' Mr. Johnson said. ''I've said before, and it's even more relevant now, if they had the documentation to show that they were a tribe in 1983, they can show it again and settle everything very quickly. And if that land where the casino sits should not have been taken into trust, it would probably be very helpful to our economic development.''</p>
        <p>Officials at the Bureau of Indian Affairs, members of the region's Congressional delegation, and Richard Blumenthal, the state attorney general, all said they could not comment on the findings in the book because they have not read it.</p>
        <p>Marvin Fast, a spokesman for United States Senator Christopher J. Dodd, the senior member of the Connecticut delegation, said it was too early to decide on whether to act on the towns' request for a Congressional investigation.</p>
        <p>''We haven't read the book,'' Mr. Fast said. ''We obviously want to get a copy, read it, and talk to officials at the state level and within the delegation, before we decide what we should do.''</p>
        <p>Mashantucket tribal officials declined to be interviewed, but released a statement. ''The tribe has reviewed a copy of the book and feels there are many inaccuracies and distortions of history in it. These allegations are nothing new, and represent a continuation of an anti-Indian agenda. The tribe remains unified against anyone trying to define us, and declines to dignify the book with any further comment at this time.''</p>
        <p>The book contends that the Mashantucket Pequots only formed a tribe in 1975 when organizers were presented with the opportunity to file a lawsuit over reservation land claims. The book also says they had not acted as a tribe or lived together as one for decades, a requirement of federal recognition. Those requirements became moot when Congress, in an attempt to settle the lawsuit, passed a bill with the state's blessing that gave the tribe federal recognition. Along with that, the book says, the tribe also got the right to have the reservation exempt from regulatory oversight by Connecticut, which paved the way for gambling.</p>
        <p>Mr. Benedict says the state didn't realize what it was giving up and that lawyers for the tribe were surprised that Connecticut agreed to the regulatory request so easily. In 1992, about eight years after President Ronald Reagan signed the bill into law, the tribe opened the Foxwoods casino.</p>
        <p>Regardless of whether the book prompts any changes at the Mashantucket reservation, officials of the towns said they believed it will change the nature of the Native American recognition process for the four tribes seeking federal status: the Paucatuck Eastern Pequots and Eastern Pequots in North Stonington, the Golden Hill Paugussetts in Trumbull, and the Schaghticoke Tribal Nation in Kent.</p>
        <p>''It shows that it is prudent for the towns to look very closely at the recognition process, to make sure that all the procedures are followed, and to make sure we get to see all the documentation,'' Mr. Johnson said. ''It gives us some more issues to look at, and see where they lead us. I'm not a lawyer, but I think this raises some interesting questions.''</p>
        <p>Allegations that the Mashantuckets are not a real Indian tribe have been around for years. But town officials contend that the research and documentation by Mr. Benedict provide the argument with considerable credibility.</p>
        <p>Mr. Benedict, who grew up in Waterford, said he had just finished a book on the National Football League and was on a trip back from Florida in May 1998, and was thinking about the 600-member tribe that had started the Foxwoods casino. During all his time in the region, he never knew the tribe existed, yet in a matter of a few years it had sprung into national prominence.</p>
        <p>In early June of that year, he and his wife, Lydia, drove to his grandparents' house in the Niantic section of East Lyme. She went to the beach, while he made what he thought would be a quick trip to the library before joining her.</p>
        <p>''I never made it to the beach,'' Mr. Benedict said. ''I was at the library until it closed, and when I got home I had a huge pile of material. I told my wife, 'there's a book here. I don't know what the book is, but there is definitely a book here.'</p>
        <p>''For me the most important element was the statute passed in 1983 and its genesis,'' Mr. Benedict said. ''If there is a so-called smoking gun in this case, I figured it would have to be in that statute, so that's where I went to work, and I spent months and months investigating that statute.''</p>
        <p>In his book he details how, with the help of a lawyer from the Maine Indian Legal Services, Mashantucket Tribal Chairman Richard A. (Skip) Hayward filed aboriginal land claims against almost 800 acres in Ledyard. When residents realized they could not sell or borrow money against their property while the liens were in place, they appealed to their congressmen for help. United States Representative Sam Gejdenson and then-United States Senator Lowell P. Weicker Jr. got the bill passed that officially recognized the tribe and allocated money for it to purchase land for a reservation. The text of the bill refers to a reservation of up to 800 acres; the map submitted separately totals 2,000 acres.</p>
        <p>Later, as the tribe grew rich on casino profits, it began to add land beyond even those boundaries, which led to extensive court battles over whether it could annex nonreservation land and put it into ''trust status,'' where the federal government holds title to the property, which puts it beyond local rules.</p>
        <p>Mr. Benedict also contends that his research showed the last Native American living on the land, Mr. Hayward's grandmother, Elizabeth George, might not even have been a Mashantucket, but rather a Narragansett Indian. In the early years of this century there were few rules governing who could live on a reservation, he noted. He dismisses the tribe's criticism of his book as inaccurate.</p>
        <p>''I'm waiting for them to pull out the sources to prove that,'' he said. ''My sources are all listed in the back of the book for anyone to check. I couldn't have done that if I didn't have credible sources,'' Mr. Benedict said. He notes in his epilogue that Congress recognized the tribe, and Congress can in effect revoke that recognition.</p>
        <p>Mr. Benedict does not address in his book how the findings were overlooked by lawyers for the towns, by members of Congress, and by the media for so many years, but Mr. Johnson, the Ledyard first selectman, said he thinks it was just habit.</p>
        <p>''When I moved here in 1976, the tribe was never really an issue,'' he said. ''Everyone knew we had a reservation, and there were Indians living on it. Then, when the land claims were raised, the whole thing was resolved in Washington, so it never became a big issue here until afterwards.''</p>
        <p>Preston First Selectman Robert M. Congdon said for many years local people who questioned the genealogy of the Mashantucket tribe were called racists trying to deny Native Americans their heritage, so the towns have always been on the defensive.</p>
        <p>''I think the burden of proof is on the tribe to prove it's not factual, by either suing the author for making false claims, or at least coming out with information to refute what he has said,'' Mr. Congdon said.</p>
        <p>''Traffic in our town has gone from 6,000 cars a day along the roads leading to the casino, to 28,000 cars a day,'' he said. ''Property values have come down 25 or 30 percent in some cases. Emergency services have gone from 200 calls a year to 1,000 calls a year, and there is no increase in property taxes that you'd get with a normal business.''</p>
        <p>No matter what the outcome of an investigation, Mr. Johnson said he expects Foxwoods is here to stay.</p>
        <p>''Would you expect the state to close it down and throw 13,000 people out of work and give up a guaranteed $100 million a year in revenues?'' he asked. ''I would think they would have to give serious consideration to how it could be kept open. I'm sure the lawyers would be very busy for a long time figuring that out, as well as the legislators and the regulators.''</p>
        <p>For the town officials, the issue now is whether the book might provide a sort of blueprint for blocking the plans of two other tribes that have won preliminary approval for their recognition petition, the Paucatuck Eastern Pequots and the Eastern Pequots. Both groups have said they are looking for land to build casinos in southeastern Connecticut.</p>
        <p>Mr. Congdon said he was astonished to learn that rather than tracing history back to colonial times, the bureau has effectively said that members must only be able to trace their ancestry back to someone living on the reservation at the time of the 1900 census.</p>
        <p>The bureau said, in essence, ''if someone was living on a reservation in 1900, I don't care if they're Polish, they're Indian now,'' Mr. Congdon said. ''That could lead to hundreds of different tribes being recognized. Was that the intent of Congress? We certainly don't think so.''</p>
        <p>Town officials also said they have only received about 25 percent of the thousands of pages of documents that outline the genealogy and other factors that are considered when granting federal recognition to a tribe.</p>
        <p>''To start the 180-day review process before everyone has all the documentation is like telling people, 'O.K., I want you to all go out and play baseball, but I'm not going to give you a ball or bat,' '' said Nicholas H. Mullane, the first selectman of North Stonington. ''If they won't even show us how they reached this decision, it's surely not going to be a fair process.''</p>
        <p>Nedra Darling, a Bureau of Indian Affairs spokeswoman, said those two tribes appear to have met the seven criteria for recognition, which include a requirement that there be a continuous organization from first contact with Europeans, and a tribal government. She acknowledged that the bureau has a backlog that prevents it from getting much of the information out to the towns that they have requested, but it is a matter of clerical under staffing, not collusion.</p>
        <p>Schaghticoke Chief Richard L. Velkey said the key is not so much requiring the Bureau of Indian Affairs to go slower on its reviews, but rather providing it with the staff it needs to do the reviews properly. The Schaghticokes have been on a list of tribes ready for a final review for three years, and it has been told it will take another 10 to 12 years to get through it. Even if the bureau staff budget was quintupled, it would take more than a decade to clear out the backlog of 150 tribes seeking recognition, he said.</p>
        <p>''The pace that they've set, it'll take 115 years to get a decision in all those cases,'' Mr. Velkey said. ''I don't see how the process could slow down much more than it is, because it hasn't moved at all in four years.''</p>
        <p>But he agreed that town officials should demand that the bureau stick to its established requirements.</p>
        <p>''Ever since casino gambling started, everyone wants to be an Indian,'' Mr. Velkey said. ''You should have to meet all seven criteria, it shouldn't take so long that it becomes a prison sentence. We wholeheartedly agree with the towns.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Mullane said Mr. Benedict's book underscores how the Bureau of Indian Affairs wields tremendous power over the fate of local towns.</p>
        <p>''The recognition process was supposed to help poor Indian tribes win federal aid,'' Mr. Mullane said. ''But it's turning into a scheme for people to get a casino and make a lot of money. Jeff Benedict has shown that somebody has perpetuated a massive fraud.''</p>
        <p>The three towns had formed an association, the Coalition for Fair Tribal and Trust Acquisition Policies, that has just won the support of the Connecticut Council of Small Towns. Mr. Congdon said the book is making people aware of what is involved when a Native American tribe is recognized.</p>
        <p>''If they get recognition, they're going to make land claims somewhere in the region -- maybe Groton Long Point, maybe Waterford or Mystic, wherever. They're going to put liens on land titles and claim they are aboriginal lands, and people will not be able to sell their houses until the case is resolved,'' Mr. Congdon said. ''This is not a problem most towns have faced, but the book is waking a lot of people up to what can happen.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
