<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Jones Easily Wins Bout Against a Hapless Foe</title>
    <meta content="14FITE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199614"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BOXING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Freeman, Mike</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jones, Roy Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hall, Richard</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE1D9133BF937A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="799" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Jones Easily Wins Bout Against a Hapless Foe</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIKE FREEMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Freeman, Mike</byline>
      <dateline>INDIANAPOLIS, May 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Roy Jones Jr scores 11th-round TKO over Richard Hall in Indianapolis, Ind; retains International Boxing Federation, World Boxing Council and World Boxing Assn Light-Heavyweight championships; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Even before Roy Jones Jr. began to actually fight, the head games had started. Jones entered the ring with a rap artist and an entourage that seemed the size of the Chinese Army. Several seconds later, Jones walked up to his opponent, Richard Hall, got in his face, and gave him a stare that could melt lead. It looked as if a scuffle might break out right there.</p>
        <p>But it did not. Jones was not about to waste his good stuff then. And he has good stuff. Really good. Jones, while playing to the fans, put on the sort of boxing clinic that has come to be expected from him -- and maybe taken for granted. Jones completely dismantled Hall to retain his International Boxing Federation, World Boxing Council and World Boxing Association belts, as well as his status as probably the best fighter in the sport. Jones, 31, is now 42-1. Hall, 28, fell to 24-2.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Even before Roy Jones Jr. began to actually fight, the head games had started. Jones entered the ring with a rap artist and an entourage that seemed the size of the Chinese Army. Several seconds later, Jones walked up to his opponent, Richard Hall, got in his face, and gave him a stare that could melt lead. It looked as if a scuffle might break out right there.</p>
        <p>But it did not. Jones was not about to waste his good stuff then. And he has good stuff. Really good. Jones, while playing to the fans, put on the sort of boxing clinic that has come to be expected from him -- and maybe taken for granted. Jones completely dismantled Hall to retain his International Boxing Federation, World Boxing Council and World Boxing Association belts, as well as his status as probably the best fighter in the sport. Jones, 31, is now 42-1. Hall, 28, fell to 24-2.</p>
        <p>''I wanted to put on a beautiful performance,'' Jones said. ''The fans gave me that opportunity, and I was happy not to disappoint them.''</p>
        <p>Jones later added that Hall ''never came close to hurting me.''</p>
        <p>The light-heavyweight battle was stopped with 1 minute 41 seconds gone in the 11th round when Jones decided to cease toying with Hall. Jones pummeled him first with a vicious combination, then a straight left shot to Hall's face, followed by a right uppercut that snapped Hall's head backward.</p>
        <p>In some ways, the fight was a travesty. Jones could have easily finished Hall much earlier, but decided to play around with him, torturing him really.</p>
        <p>''Hall is a strong guy,'' Jones said. ''He took a lot of my punches. But I'm a fighting machine.''</p>
        <p>After that intimidating prefight stare from Jones came those frightening fists. Jones transforms them into what he wants. He blistered Hall with either a flurry of blows, or the kind of big rights that looked as if Hall were being given electric shocks each time they landed.</p>
        <p>Jones used his power early in the first round to stun Hall, dazing him with a series of right punches that led to two knockdowns. The fight continued, but was basically over at that point. Jones had established he was not taking the huge underdog lightly. The second round again saw Jones using that powerful right to punish Hall.</p>
        <p>Then came several strange rounds in which Jones seemed to pull back his aggression. There was no question Jones was by far the better boxer, but he slowed his attack, until the fifth round, when he began dancing around the ring, exciting the 13,215 people at the Conseco Fieldhouse. By the eighth round, Hall's face was bloodied.</p>
        <p>After the fight was stopped in the 11th round by the referee Wayne Kelly, Hall objected.</p>
        <p>But Kelly may have saved Hall from several nights in the hospital. These days it is not wise to spend too much time in the ring with Jones.</p>
        <p>The prefight publicity was unusual for a fight of this stature in that most of it focused on Jones's talking of subjects besides Hall. There was Jones speaking about his minor league basketball career. There was Jones daydreaming of moving up in weight to fight Lennox Lewis. There were a few times when Jones seemed to remember he had a title fight, but only a few.</p>
        <p>The Hall camp thought Jones was being cocky and looking past its fighter. Jones, though, is a multitasker. Boxing may be his profession, but there are other things he likes to do. There is even a part of Jones that needs other endeavors because in his weight class there are few legitimate challengers.</p>
        <p>That of course does not mean Jones fails to train hard. He did for Hall, and it showed in his physique. Jones was chiseled, weighing in at 173 pounds.</p>
        <p>Hall's best chance was thought to be his height advantage -- at 6 feet 31/2  inches, he is about 4 inches taller than Jones -- and power. Before his match with Jones, Hall had beaten his last five opponents in three or fewer rounds.</p>
        <p>In the other key match of the night, the I.B.F. middleweight champion, Bernard Hopkins, used his speed advantage to overwhelm the Canadian Syd Vanderpool (28-2) with inside punches. Hopkins (37-2-1) retained his title by unanimous decision.</p>
        <p>BOXING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
