<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Meta Schrenk, Michael Carr</title>
    <meta content="21CONTENT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199342"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="WEDDINGS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEDDINGS AND ENGAGEMENTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHRENK, META (META CARR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CARR, MICHAEL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Weddings and Celebrations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E5DE173BF937A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="554" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Meta Schrenk, Michael Carr</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Marguerite Kerr Screnk, a daughter of Katherine and William Schrenk of New York, was married yesterday to Michael Scott Carr, a son of Patricia and Paul Carr of Broomfield, Colo.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Marguerite Kerr Screnk, a daughter of Katherine and William Schrenk of New York, was married yesterday to Michael Scott Carr, a son of Patricia and Paul Carr of Broomfield, Colo.</p>
        <p>The Rev. Chris Wilburn, a Southern Baptist minister, officiated at the home of Trish McLeod, a friend of the bride, in Savannah, Ga. Robert Lamb, the deputy assistant secretary for policy management and budget in the Interior Department, and a friend of the couple, took part in the nondenominational ceremony.</p>
        <p>The bride, 33, is known as Meta. She paints and sells silk scarves and ties. She also helps organize environmental events, like an environmental film festival in Washington last month. She graduated from Middlebury College and received a master's degree from the Johns Hopkins School of Advanced International Studies.</p>
        <p>The bride's mother is a photographer, whose work has been shown at National Iron Bank, a gallery in Falls Village, Conn. Her father is a retired partner in Cravath, Swaine &amp; Moore, the New York law firm.</p>
        <p>The bridegroom, 29, is a lawyer specializing in water-rights cases for the Interior Department. He graduated from the University of Colorado at Boulder and received a law degree from Lewis and Clark College. His father, an engineer, tests the reliability of computer equipment for the Broomfield office of the Storage Technology Corporation, a maker of hard drives and other computer equipment.</p>
        <p>The couple met on a cross-country skiing trip in West Virginia on Valentine's Day weekend 1997. When they returned home to Washington, they began dating. Their first date began badly. Mr Carr was supposed to call Ms. Schrenk at 6 p.m., but he was stuck two hours away on an all-day hike. By the time he called, it was nearly 8. ''Isn't this typical?'' Ms. Schrenk recalls thinking. ''Why does this happen to me? I hate men.''</p>
        <p>Still, they rescued the evening with takeout pizza and rented movies. The next day, Ms. Schrenk had to baby-sit for a friend, and Mr. Carr volunteered to help. ''He won huge points,'' Ms. Schrenk said. ''He knew how to strap in a car seat and how to change diapers.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Carr proposed last year. Ms. Schrenk had expected a proposal when they vacationed in Paris on Valentine's Day, the anniversary of the ski trip when they met. But romantic occasion after romantic occasion came and went.</p>
        <p>They climbed to the top of the Arc de Triomphe and looked out at Paris at night. ''Can you imagine anything more romantic?'' Mr. Carr said. ''Well, yeah,'' Ms. Schrenk thought, disappointed again.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Carr proposed on a trip to Savannah, where Ms. Schrenk spent part of there childhood, it came as a surprise. She had packed his luggage, as she usually does, and found nothing resembling an engagement ring. But she noticed that he seemed distracted in Savannah.</p>
        <p>''I was annoyed because he wasn't paying attention to my guided tour,'' she said. At one point, they sat silently on a bench for 10 minutes. Finally, he asked her to marry him. Ms. Schrenk, remembering earlier false alarms, said, ''Do you really mean it?'' He then pulled out the ring. She cried and said yes.</p>
        <p>WEDDINGS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
