<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Team of Two Who by Now Think as One</title>
    <meta content="14GOLD$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199226"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FILM"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Allen, Woody</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Taylor, Juliet</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Small Time Crooks (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900EFDD1138F937A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="4160" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Team of Two Who by Now Think as One</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Excerpts from interview with Woody Allen and Juliet Taylor, Allen's casting director for 25 years, on opening of Allen's latest film Small Time Crooks and their 25-year association; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Juliet Taylor has helped Woody Allen cast 26 movies, including his latest, ''Small Time Crooks,'' opening on Friday. Since the actors Mr. Allen hires regularly receive Oscar nominations, The New York Times invited him and Ms. Taylor to discuss the process they use in casting his films. They met at the Park Avenue offices of his production company, and, in between compliments, talked about their 25-year association. Excerpts from the taped conversation follow.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Juliet Taylor has helped Woody Allen cast 26 movies, including his latest, ''Small Time Crooks,'' opening on Friday. Since the actors Mr. Allen hires regularly receive Oscar nominations, The New York Times invited him and Ms. Taylor to discuss the process they use in casting his films. They met at the Park Avenue offices of his production company, and, in between compliments, talked about their 25-year association. Excerpts from the taped conversation follow.</p>
        <p>JULIET TAYLOR. Often before Woody's written a script, he'll telephone me and talk about the idea with an eye to who might be cast.</p>
        <p>WOODY ALLEN. Usually I try not to write in anything to influence you -- so you read the script without any idea, for the most part, who I had in mind.</p>
        <p>TAYLOR. But you never alter the making of a film for an actor, which is unusual. Most directors will say, ''Oh gosh, if I can get so-and-so, I'll do it a year from this January.'' But you'll roll no matter what.</p>
        <p>ALLEN. Because the films are not based on an actor agreeing. I might wait if an actor said, ''Four weeks later I'll be available.'' But to wait for an actor who says, ''I can't do it this year'' -- I don't have any interest in that.</p>
        <p>TAYLOR. Except many directors do. And if you wanted the absolutely perfect cast, you could do that. But I always think it's kind of confident and interesting that you don't.</p>
        <p>ALLEN. If I can get the perfect person within reason, that's fine. If not, I make do. Because you can always ask yourself, you know, what if this actor or that actress gets hit by a truck? Are you not going to make the picture?</p>
        <p>TAYLOR. I also thought that you didn't want to get sucked into the whole ritual of centering your movie around an actor because then there are so many other people determining the future of your movie. I always think you're sort of resistant to someone else setting up your timetable.</p>
        <p>ALLEN. And it's just good luck that my films have always been financed completely irrespective of who was in them. So many directors I know, their whole film is predicated on getting such-and-such an actor or actress -- only then do they get the financing. But I've never had that problem. So I'm casting for the best person that I can cast. And if the best person is a complete unknown with no track record, that's fine. If the best person is a big star, that's also fine.</p>
        <p>TAYLOR. Don't you think we're thinking ahead a little bit more than we used to in the old days?</p>
        <p>ALLEN. I think I've gotten to a point with you of trying to alert you, because there have been times when you warned me, ''Look, you're going to shoot in the fall and there are a lot of films going.'' And so if I have an idea as I'm writing that would be great for a particular person, I don't mind telling you. And you can get some idea whether he or she is busy or leaving the country or would have any interest in working for no money. You know, there are a lot of restrictions working with me. There's not a lot of money to be made----</p>
        <p>TAYLOR. But actors love to work with you.</p>
        <p>ALLEN. Some do, but as you know, we've had our share of turndowns ----</p>
        <p>TAYLOR. Yeah, there are times when people have turned us down. But the track record is so great. Because they all look so wonderful in your movies.</p>
        <p>ALLEN. If they look good it's because the parts are often a good fit. Even if the movie stinks and I mess up in every way, their parts are good for them. I mean, they're not asked just to drive cars or do stunts or special effects or moronic, infantile jokes.</p>
        <p>TAYLOR. But not only do you write great characters, you always show everybody's best performance.</p>
        <p>ALLEN. Well, I let them have a lot to say about it. I have a lot of faith in the instinct of the actors. And if you encourage them to be creative, they do a lot of great things that I wind up getting credit for. It's really them making me look good in the end.</p>
        <p>TAYLOR. Another thing that's really worked out well -- although they'd love to be making billions of dollars -- is that our money is uniform. Everybody gets the same thing.</p>
        <p>ALLEN. Yes. They get practically nothing.</p>
        <p>TAYLOR. But at least everybody's getting nothing.</p>
        <p>ALLEN. Right. If people want to work with me, it's for reasons other than money. And I also have to be lucky, as you know. If they're coming off a $10 million payday and looking forward to another $10 million payday and they've got eight weeks free----</p>
        <p>TAYLOR. It's true -- catching them at the right moment. And also sometimes we try to work dates out so that they can then go make some blockbuster afterward.</p>
        <p>ALLEN. Right, whatever accommodations we can make for them, we try and make. With the exception of postponing the picture. We break our neck to accommodate them because they're accommodating us by working for a tiny fraction of what they're worth.</p>
        <p>TAYLOR. To get back to the process, Woody calls and says what he's thinking about. And we talk about possible actors. And then you go back and you write, and then we talk again. And I'll bring up names that I think might be what you're talking about----</p>
        <p>ALLEN. And more often than not I say, ''I never heard of that person.'' Because Juliet keeps abreast of everybody in television, everybody on Broadway and Off Broadway and Off Off Broadway, and I don't at all. So when I hand her a script and there are, let's say, 10 major parts, she'll give me a very substantial list of viable possibilities for each part. And some of the people I'll know because everybody knows them. And lots of the people I've never heard of.</p>
        <p>I can think of two times very vividly that I wrote a script and gave it to you -- one was ''Interiors,'' when you introduced me to Mary Beth Hurt, and she was just on the way up, and Juliet thought she'd be great. And the second she walked into the room, it was on the nose. I mean, she didn't have to speak. It was just absolutely perfect. And that was also true of Chazz Palminteri, with ''Bullets Over Broadway.'' ''A Bronx Tale'' hadn't come out, and I'd never heard of him. And the second he walked in this door, it was what I had written -- what I was thinking of without knowing he existed.</p>
        <p>And then there are times she will suggest very well-known people. When we were casting ''Hannah and Her Sisters,'' you mentioned Max von Sydow, you know, just speculating -- we throw names out for hours sometimes. And the second Juliet mentioned him, it stopped right there. It was just, ''Let's get him.''</p>
        <p>TAYLOR. It's not always that easy to get you to use new people.</p>
        <p>ALLEN. No, I know.</p>
        <p>TAYLOR. That's an ongoing battle. But you're getting better and better.</p>
        <p>ALLEN. Juliet's been pushing new people on me for years. I don't like any kind of change. So if I've worked with a person successfully, I like to work with that person again. And I don't like to meet people. I don't like casting at all. I don't like the process. I sit in this room and people come in here and we give them something to read, sometimes we'll just talk to them. And I find the whole thing nerve-racking and unpleasant.</p>
        <p>TAYLOR. When I first met Woody, I was the assistant to Marion Dougherty, who was casting ''Bananas.'' And back then, you didn't even conduct your own interviews. You sat in a chair in the corner of the room and your producer talked to the actors. Do you remember?</p>
        <p>ALLEN. Yes.</p>
        <p>TAYLOR. You were so uncomfortable.</p>
        <p>ALLEN. After years I had to give in. But I have nothing to say to them. When they come into the room, they often get the impression that it's not going well because it's so quick. But all I want to do is meet them briefly.</p>
        <p>TAYLOR. Woody thinks, ''They'll be thrilled that I'm only going to take a minute of their time.'' And they all want to sit down and really get to know him.</p>
        <p>ALLEN. And I don't like to do that. I don't learn anything by it. Juliet is always saying: ''This next person just won a Tony and she's a big deal. Please ask her to sit down for a minute.'' But usually I shake hands with them and the casting lasts 35 seconds, 40 seconds. I tell them we're doing a movie and Juliet thought they'd be right for something, and I just wanted to look at them. Every now and then we will read somebody.</p>
        <p>TAYLOR. More and more.</p>
        <p>ALLEN. Yeah, we never used to read anyone at all. And Juliet's prevailed on me. I always find that really uncomfortable, and I'm sure they hate it.</p>
        <p>TAYLOR. When we were in London working on ''Mighty Aphrodite,'' I would say to Woody, ''You have to let this next person have a little bit of a visit, because he's a knight.'' And he said, ''O.K., only the knights can sit down.''</p>
        <p>ALLEN. I mean, I just don't know what to say to them or do with them. It's awkward for me and I probably communicate that awkwardness to the actors. And that's the last thing in the world I want to communicate to them. All we're looking for is someone who strikes me as the right type for the part.</p>
        <p>TAYLOR. Woody, more than anyone I've ever worked with, works off an initial response to an actor. It's like what you said about Mary Beth a minute ago, when somebody walks in the room, before they've even opened their mouth, you distinctly know whether you feel they're right.</p>
        <p>ALLEN. Yes, because don't forget I'm the author of the script.</p>
        <p>TAYLOR. You go on that instinct more than most people I've worked with.</p>
        <p>ALLEN. Well, for me it's a wonderful thing, when you send in someone who's, you know, perfect. I find it's easier to get what I want from a guy who's 90 percent right as the character and can act a little than from a guy who's not as right and who's a great actor.</p>
        <p>TAYLOR. So as a result, sometimes we slip over into the other area, which is somebody who has a great quality for it, but really has very little acting experience. ''Stardust Memories'' was full of people who had either funny looks or interesting qualities, but really weren't very experienced actors.</p>
        <p>ALLEN. Yeah, movie acting is different from stage acting. Some of those people wouldn't last three minutes on a stage, because they have no craft and no authority. But if they've got to do a scene in a movie, they're absolutely great. Then they go back to their lives as lawyers or short-order cooks or whatever. And I've also met actors who have very impressive credentials -- and they're no good. I don't care how many Broadway plays they're in or how often they're nominated -- when I go to the movies, I and my friends don't buy them.</p>
        <p>TAYLOR. It's true. And I think you have good antennae. We usually agree, don't you think?</p>
        <p>ALLEN. I do..  TAYLOR. It's been over 25 years -- I really understand Woody's tastes, I guess. But you're definitely more scrutinizing about who you think is good than the rest of the film business.</p>
        <p>ALLEN. On who I think is good?</p>
        <p>TAYLOR. Who you're interested in. Often the stars everyone else is trying to get you'll have no interest in.</p>
        <p>ALLEN. But this is true in any job, whether actors or film directors or doctors or policemen. There are a few good ones, most are mediocre and there are a number of bad ones. There are a few really fine actors and actresses -- people you'll make a point of going to see every time they do a movie.</p>
        <p>TAYLOR. Do you want to say who?</p>
        <p>ALLEN. Well, I've never missed anything that Marlon Brando's done in my life, because the force of his acting was -- and is -- so special, so amazing. It reinvented acting. I mean, his contribution to my lifetime of theater and films is stupendous, beyond the contribution of most playwrights, most of the directors, and all of the actors.</p>
        <p>TAYLOR. But you have never tried to cast him.</p>
        <p>ALLEN. No, but only because there's never been anything he would be right for. I'm sure I would be intimidated. You know, I'm often very intimidated by many of the people I've cast over the years.</p>
        <p>TAYLOR. But you don't cast people you think will be difficult to work with. You like people who are going to be nice, and we go through a big ritual of checking people out.</p>
        <p>ALLEN. We do put time into it. But there again, I'm not a dedicated artist in the sense that I must have the right person if that right person is a pain in the neck.</p>
        <p>TAYLOR. Except that in other areas you are less reasonable -- like lighting. You don't like to shoot in the sun -- those things you don't let go.</p>
        <p>ALLEN. Some things bother me more. If I'm shooting in the sun, it's just so depressing when I look at the dailies -- they're so ugly if the weather's not right. But in the casting, you know, if I don't get the perfect actor, we still get somebody who's good. I don't want to hurt anybody's feelings, but there have been times when we've settled. It hasn't been often. But there will be somebody on Juliet's list and I'll say, ''No way.'' And eight weeks later, with no other prospects, I'm suddenly praying he or she is available. And sometimes someone is just all right, you know, and I don't have the patience to go any further.</p>
        <p>TAYLOR. Sometimes it's the other way around. I'll think we have it and he'll say, ''No.'' Not often.</p>
        <p>ALLEN. Right. But usually I don't have the patience you have with the whole process. I like to keep it moving, you know -- cast it, shoot it, edit it, get on to the next one.</p>
        <p>The single most outstanding thing that I notice when I'm casting is that actors or actresses will come in and be very charming and natural and speak just like we're speaking here. And then you give them something to read and they lapse into their acting mode. Suddenly they're not speaking like any human being you know. And of course, I never hire them.</p>
        <p>TAYLOR. But I think -- and this is true with every audition, not just auditioning for you -- they come in here and they want to impress you in a short amount of time; and people will often do too much, even though they're told by everyone: ''Just keep it natural. This is his style.'' Or sometimes because it's you, they push the humor too hard.</p>
        <p>ALLEN. It's interesting that doing too much is the universal ill of making a movie. So the actor will do too much. And a costume designer will have his equivalent or her equivalent. And the scenic designer. And the cameraman. Doing too much is a very common trap. They feel they're not doing enough if they just do a normal, graceful amount.</p>
        <p>TAYLOR. Don't you think, though, that actors who are really gifted have an ear for that, they can't hit a false note?</p>
        <p>ALLEN. I've seen many pictures with Michael Caine over the years -- great pictures, mediocre pictures. I've never seen him hit a false note. Liam Neeson is a guy who is pitch-perfect. He reads any line, whether he's Schindler or somebody else, and it sounds like a human being talking.</p>
        <p>TAYLOR. And that's really what the gift is. You have that or you don't, I think.</p>
        <p>ALLEN. Gene Hackman. Some of these people are just amazing. Now Geraldine Page, who was an enormous actress, didn't have that particular odd skill. She was a genius, but you had to watch her. You had to say ''do less'' or ''take it easy.'' And she was as great as they come.</p>
        <p>TAYLOR. There are people who said that about Olivier, too. Right? He had those moments where he got a little hammy.</p>
        <p>ALLEN. Very often. And he was a genius actor. But there are certain ones that just are real. And that's some kind of gift -- being natural on the screen.</p>
        <p>TAYLOR. It's amazing when you read actors and they do that. You just melt.</p>
        <p>ALLEN. Yeah. Do you remember how we felt, for instance, when Edward Norton came in for ''Everyone Says I Love You''?</p>
        <p>TAYLOR. Yes. Good example.</p>
        <p>ALLEN. Again, Juliet had heard of him, I never had. And we had heard the part read 15 times or something. And he came in, and -- there it is! All of a sudden it was alive. And it wasn't fancy. I almost always look for people that are real, unless we've decided at the beginning that we want to go for a clear-cut bravura-type performance. So we cast Mia [Farrow] to play in ''Broadway Danny Rose,'' to play a character that no way in the world is anything like her. And the pleasure for the audience, partially, comes from watching a good actress stretch herself, bring something off.</p>
        <p>''Small Time Crooks'' was no problem because it was a broad comedy----</p>
        <p>TAYLOR. And Woody was starring in it.</p>
        <p>ALLEN. And for me that was the easiest way to do it. So we had to find funny women. And I, of course, was intimidated because I was working with Elaine May and Tracey Ullman, these two comic genuises.</p>
        <p>TAYLOR. It gave us a chance to use people we like and have wanted to use. We've always wanted to use Elaine May.</p>
        <p>ALLEN. Right. Because the criterion is that they have to be, you know, funny people.</p>
        <p>TAYLOR. You know, one thing we didn't mention in terms of the process, which is pertinent in this case, is that because I've been working for Woody for so long, we spend a huge amount of time talking about actors before we even start seeing people. There are so many people Woody's used over the years that there's a whole pool -- and he likes the idea that we might cast a movie, literally, from the sofa in his apartment.</p>
        <p>ALLEN. Yeah, so I'd never have to meet anybody.</p>
        <p>FILM</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
