<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>It's a Dog's Life</title>
    <meta content="14LIPTAKT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199151"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="CHILDREN'S BOOKS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Liptak, Adam</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">George, Jean Craighead</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zimmerman, Andrea</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clemesha, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Seeber, Dorothea P</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Thompson, Colin</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">How to Talk to Your Dog (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">My Dog Toby (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Pup Just for Me, A/A Boy Just for Me (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Unknown (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Columns/Children's Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E3D71F39F937A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1077" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>It's a Dog's Life</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Adam Liptak</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Liptak, Adam</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Adam Liptak reviews following children's books: How to Talk to Your Dog by Jean Craighead George; My Dog Toby by Andrea Zimmerman and David Clemesha; A Pup Just for Me/A Boy Just for Me by Dorothea P Seeber; Unknown by Colin Thompson (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HOW TO TALK TO YOUR DOG</p>
        <p>By Jean Craighead George.</p>
        <p>Illustrated by Sue Truesdell.</p>
        <p>26 pp. New York: HarperCollins Publishers. $9.95. (Ages 5 to 9)</p>
        <p>MY DOG TOBY</p>
        <p>By Andrea Zimmerman and David Clemesha.</p>
        <p>Illustrated by True Kelley.</p>
        <p>Unpaged. San Diego: Silver Whistle/Harcourt. $15. (Ages 5 to 9)</p>
        <p>A PUP JUST FOR ME/</p>
        <p>A BOY JUST FOR ME</p>
        <p>By Dorothea P. Seeber.</p>
        <p>Illustrated by Ed Young.</p>
        <p>Unpaged. New York: Philomel Books. $16.99. (Ages 5 to 9)</p>
        <p>UNKNOWN</p>
        <p>By Colin Thompson.</p>
        <p>Illustrated by Anna Pignataro.</p>
        <p>31 pp. New York: Walker &amp; Company. $15.95.</p>
        <p>(Ages 5 to 8)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HOW TO TALK TO YOUR DOG</p>
        <p>By Jean Craighead George.</p>
        <p>Illustrated by Sue Truesdell.</p>
        <p>26 pp. New York: HarperCollins Publishers. $9.95. (Ages 5 to 9)</p>
        <p>MY DOG TOBY</p>
        <p>By Andrea Zimmerman and David Clemesha.</p>
        <p>Illustrated by True Kelley.</p>
        <p>Unpaged. San Diego: Silver Whistle/Harcourt. $15. (Ages 5 to 9)</p>
        <p>A PUP JUST FOR ME/</p>
        <p>A BOY JUST FOR ME</p>
        <p>By Dorothea P. Seeber.</p>
        <p>Illustrated by Ed Young.</p>
        <p>Unpaged. New York: Philomel Books. $16.99. (Ages 5 to 9)</p>
        <p>UNKNOWN</p>
        <p>By Colin Thompson.</p>
        <p>Illustrated by Anna Pignataro.</p>
        <p>31 pp. New York: Walker &amp; Company. $15.95.</p>
        <p>(Ages 5 to 8)</p>
        <p>IN ''How to Talk to Your Dog,'' Jean Craighead George writes, ''No one will ever love you as much as your dog does.'' The veteran nature writer puts it plainly: ''He will sleep by your bed, defend you from enemies and be your friend until he dies.'' Children know all this when they plead for puppies, and they have a lot in common with the dogs they adore: in their un-self-conscious playfulness, in their affinity for mischief and in their uncomplicated love.</p>
        <p>Books for children about dogs would seem, then, to be pretty much foolproof, a sure-fire subgenre. But with the exception of George's wise instruction manual and meditation on how our dogs understand us, none of these books are wholly satisfying.</p>
        <p>''How to Talk to Your Dog'' is plainly the pick of this litter, though it's really a dog owner's manual and not a children's book. Oh, young readers may well be drawn to Sue Truesdell's illustrations, which are pleasing in the easygoing style of the modern greeting card. They will not be much put off by the incongruous and ill-conceived photographs of the author interspersed throughout, in which she is made to seem to be cavorting with cartoon dogs. But there is rather too much text for really young children, and it is pitched at a fairly abstract level. (Incidentally, there's a companion title by the same author, ''How to Talk to Your Cat.'')</p>
        <p>Adults, though, will appreciate George's effortless colloquial prose and her insights. She explains why a dog's love is grounded in its clear understanding, reinforced by its owner's simple and affectionate signals, that the owner is the boss. She helps us see the world from the dog's perspective. A neighborhood's scents, she writes, ''are a dog's newspaper,'' containing ''all the neighborhood dog gossip.''</p>
        <p>George has a playful side. Her discussion of the meaning of various tail positions (''When he is feeling good, his tail is loose and down'') and facial expressions (''A wrinkled brow and ears held out to the side say he is confused'') is keyed with numbers that send the reader to an adjacent series of amusing illustrations.</p>
        <p>Each of the other books here revolves around a single device, and each will hold a child's attention at least until its conceit grows old. Only one, ''My Dog Toby,'' feels like an authentic story. It is a child's first-person account of her effort to teach a lovably dumb basset hound a trick: to sit. That is not much to build a narrative around, even for very young readers, but Andrea Zimmerman and David Clemesha infuse the story with some gentle lessons about appreciating dogs -- and people -- for what they are.</p>
        <p>The climax of the tale is a two-page spread of Toby looking confused and pleased at the same time, under the words ''Toby sat!'' (Apologies for giving away the ending.) That wonderful image, and the rest of the loose, appealing illustrations, are by True Kelley, who did similarly inviting work in ''Three Stories You Can Read to Your Dog.''</p>
        <p>''A Pup Just for Me'' and ''A Boy Just for Me'' are two stories in one book, with a second front cover where the back cover is supposed to be. The stories meet in a central illustration, as the boy and the pup meet. (More apologies.) Children may be taken by this unusual format, but it is contrived and does nothing to integrate what are basically two unrelated tales or, really, variations on two themes. In the boy's story, the boy rejects a series of pets until he gets a puppy. In the pup's story, the dog is mistreated by a series of masters before finding the boy. (Cruelty to animals is also not everyone's idea of a good bedtime read.)</p>
        <p>Ed Young, the distinguished illustrator who won the Caldecott Medal for ''Lon Po Po,'' gets top billing, and his stark, bold paper-collage illustrations -- the boy's set against black paper, the dog's against primary-color backgrounds -- are striking, if perhaps too stylized for most children. The surprise here is the pleasant light verse of the text by a 93-year-old newcomer to children's books named Dorothea P. Seeber. Her couplets don't really drive the story forward, but they are full of charm and sometimes approach Seussian rhythms. I particularly liked hearing about ''Miss Lydia B. Twitty (who lived in the city and kept twenty-two cats and one little kitty).''</p>
        <p>''Unknown'' is about a dog pound, and it is rather too pleased with its little trick: it names the dogs at the shelter after the signs over their cages, which explain how they came to be abandoned (''Owner Died,'' ''Unwanted Christmas Gift,'' ''Grown Too Large'' and so on).</p>
        <p>Unknown is the protagonist. He is adorable but shy and so is passed over as the dogs around him are adopted. He becomes a hero during a lightning storm, and this causes him to be chosen by a ''loving family.'' Colin Thompson's pedestrian writing is set in various type sizes in unlikely places on the book's pages, causing the whole enterprise to call to mind a ransom note. Anna Pignataro's sad-eyed watercolors are, unfortunately, fitting.</p>
        <p>The ''Pup/Boy'' book and ''Unknown'' end where they should have begun. Kids will keep asking for ''My Dog Toby'' because they will want to hear and think about that special rapport of children with dogs. They may be baffled by the text of ''How to Talk to Your Dog,'' for now at least, but that is what they will want to learn.</p>
        <p>CHILDREN'S BOOKS Adam Liptak is a senior counsel in the legal department of The New York Times Company.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Adam Liptak is a senior counsel in the legal department of The New York Times Company.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
