<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>AT A CONCERT WITH/Gretchen Pulvermann; The Force Behind a Series of Free Programs That Set Toes to Tapping</title>
    <meta content="14MUSI$12" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199294"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Rye (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pulvermann Foundation</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pulvermann, Gretchen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sherman, Robert</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E3D91F38F937A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="771" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>AT A CONCERT WITH/Gretchen Pulvermann; The Force Behind a Series of Free Programs That Set Toes to Tapping</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT SHERMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sherman, Robert</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with Gretchen Pulvermann of Rye, NY, guiding force behind Pulvermann Foundation's biennial concert series at Rye High School, who has been named city's Woman of the Year; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TWICE a year, Rye High School opens its doors to the free -- and increasingly popular -- Pulvermann Foundation concerts. Since 1992, the programs have featured such major artists as the bass-baritone Jerome Hines, the pianists Oxana Yablonskaya and Michael Boriskin, the violinist Chee-Yun, the folk singer Tom Chapin and the United States Military Academy Band from West Point, whose May visits have been a hallmark of the series.</p>
        <p>The West Pointers return for their ninth annual showcase next Sunday at 3 p.m.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TWICE a year, Rye High School opens its doors to the free -- and increasingly popular -- Pulvermann Foundation concerts. Since 1992, the programs have featured such major artists as the bass-baritone Jerome Hines, the pianists Oxana Yablonskaya and Michael Boriskin, the violinist Chee-Yun, the folk singer Tom Chapin and the United States Military Academy Band from West Point, whose May visits have been a hallmark of the series.</p>
        <p>The West Pointers return for their ninth annual showcase next Sunday at 3 p.m.</p>
        <p>In the audience will be Gretchen Pulvermann, who refuses to allow public acknowledgement of her presence but who is the longtime Rye resident who made it all happen. Last Memorial Day, however, Mrs. Pulvermann could no longer hide from public appreciation: she was named the city's Woman of the Year and was showered with congratulatory plaques and testimonials. ''They take up a whole wall,'' she said rather wonderingly. ''I have one from the mayor, another from the New York State Assembly, something from the county, even an Americanism Award from the American Legion. So much fuss, and all I did was try to bring music to our senior citizens.''</p>
        <p>In a recent interview, Mrs. Pulvermann reminisced about her music-loving husband, Heinz, who died in 1972, and how she organized the concerts to honor his memory.</p>
        <p>Q. When did you meet your husband?</p>
        <p>A. I was one of five American civilian women who volunteered to work overseas for the government during World War II. I knew French, so they sent me to Algiers as an interpreter, and that's where I met Heinz, who had been taken there as a prisoner. He was born in Germany, and as a Jew who spoke out against Hitler, he was considered especially dangerous by the Nazis. He had left Germany some years earlier, but he was in France as an engineering consultant when the invasion started and got trapped there. He made his way down to the southern part of the country, but then was arrested by the Vichy government and sent in chains to Algiers. Fortunately, he was released when the Americans came in, and that's when we met. We were married overseas as well.</p>
        <p>Q. How did your love of music fit in?</p>
        <p>A. Well, there was always music around the house when I was growing up, and it was even more pronounced after I married Heinz. He was innately musical, and between him and our dog, Jinx, who would get up on her hind legs and paw at me when she wanted me to put on a recording, we had music on almost 24 hours a day.</p>
        <p>Q. What prompted you to endow a concert series?</p>
        <p>A. I have no heirs. Absolutely none. So when I was reading about global graying, and wondering what I could do to help senior citizens who might be having money problems, I decided that Heinz would have loved the idea of free concerts. I wanted to have them right in town, and on Sunday afternoons so traveling wouldn't be a problem. I also felt that the performances had to be of top professional quality, yet entertaining enough to appeal to a wide audience. I'll never forget our first program. It was with Jerome Hines and the West Point Band, and, of course, I came down there early when they were still rehearsing. Well, I looked up at those 750 empty seats and was absolutely panic stricken, thinking we'll never fill this place. Then the audience started coming, and we actually wound up turning away over 300 people that day.</p>
        <p>Q. Have the audiences continued to come?</p>
        <p>A. We haven't had too many more of those standing-room-only crowds, but the auditorium is pretty full every time, and folks around here really look forward to the programs. A few years ago, the sanitation workers were on strike in Rye, and I was carrying a big poster under my arm to put up in a store, when one of the strikers saw me and said, ''Oh, Mrs. Pulvermann, we just love your concerts.'' And just recently, I was walking down Purchase Street when an elderly couple came along and asked me when the next program was. When I told her, the woman turned around to her husband and said: ''Make a note of that, dear. We don't want to leave on our vacation until after the concert.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
