<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Coaches Group Threatens to File Suit for Better Benefits</title>
    <meta content="Y14NFL$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199528"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL: NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fringe Benefits</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Football League Coaches Association</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Freeman, Mike</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fringe Benefits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E7D6123BF937A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1384" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Coaches Group Threatens to File Suit for Better Benefits</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIKE FREEMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Freeman, Mike</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Members of National Football League Coaches Assn, which represents 18 head coaches and more than 400 assistant coaches, prepares to file suit against National Football League seeking improved working conditions and benefits for assistant coaches; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The National Football League could soon face one of its most difficult challenges, as an association made up of dozens of head coaches and hundreds of assistants is preparing to file a lawsuit against the league early next month seeking improved working conditions and benefits.</p>
        <p>While there remains a solid chance the situation will soon be settled without court action, several owners and members of the association believe a legal battle may be imminent.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The National Football League could soon face one of its most difficult challenges, as an association made up of dozens of head coaches and hundreds of assistants is preparing to file a lawsuit against the league early next month seeking improved working conditions and benefits.</p>
        <p>While there remains a solid chance the situation will soon be settled without court action, several owners and members of the association believe a legal battle may be imminent.</p>
        <p>For the past few years, assistant coaches have been fighting for better benefits packages and an earlier retirement age. And while Commissioner Paul Tagliabue has been open-minded about the demands of the assistant coaches, ownership has been reluctant, and the slow pace of negotiations for an agreement has irked the assistant coaches.</p>
        <p>In fact, members of the National Football League Coaches Association, which represents 18 head coaches and more than 400 assistant coaches, said they recently informed the league that unless an agreement is reached by the beginning of next month, the association will file a lawsuit seeking improved retirement and benefit packages. The suit may also allege age discrimination.</p>
        <p>The N.F.L. maintains that it knows nothing of a possible lawsuit and is hopeful an agreement can be reached with the association. The issue will be revisited at the owners' meetings later this month in Baltimore.</p>
        <p>Coaches suing owners -- their employers -- would lead to a rather uncomfortable if not bitter situation. Action on the field would be unaffected, but it would be impossible for the chemistry among ownership, management and coaches not to be hurt.</p>
        <p>Officials of the coaches association say they have been all but forced to consider taking legal action because ownership has reacted slowly to their concerns. It is true, however, that the N.F.L. and the association have had amicable discussions, and the league respects Larry Kennan, the association's executive director. And, in fact, some progress has been made on several of the more minor issues.</p>
        <p>But on the larger differences, there remains a considerable gap. The association began as a way to address the concerns of assistant coaches, a group that does not have the same financial certainties as head coaches, who make more money and have long-term guaranteed contracts. Kennan, a former longtime assistant coach who used to be the offensive coordinator for the New England Patriots, was the catalyst who turned the organization from a squabbling group into a powerful, unified force.</p>
        <p>The association says that assistants are fired, on average, every one to three years, and fewer than 7 percent of the coaches in the league are age 60 or older. Since benefits begin at 65, most never see their full retirement package. The association wants a system in which a coach can collect benefits when his age and years of service add up to 75.</p>
        <p>The association also wants to establish health insurance for retired coaches and working contracts to run through March, as opposed to February, when they usually expire. Why? The association says that when assistant coaches are fired, it usually occurs in mid-January, immediately following the season, and most contracts end in February, so the fired assistants basically get a two-week paycheck. That money must last until another job opens up, which could be months away. The association wants its members to have a larger cushion.</p>
        <p>The coaches are also asking that independent arbitrators, as opposed to the league, settle contract disputes. They also want a $250,000 life insurance policy to carry over into retirement.</p>
        <p>Officials with the association maintain that making the changes they want would cost around $250,000 a team, about the same price to sign a low-round draft pick.</p>
        <p>Assistant coaches are certainly not crying that they are destitute. They know they make good money, even if their salaries have not risen in proportion to that of the athletes they coach. In 1982, the average player earned $150,000 a year, while the average coach made $50,000, a 3-to-1 ratio. Now the average player earns about a million dollars a season, to the $130,000 a year for the average coach, which is an 8-to-1 ratio.</p>
        <p>Quarterbacks Peyton Manning and Drew Bledsoe recently filmed an instructional football video, the proceeds of which would help former assistants facing financial difficulty and not eligible for pension and medical benefits. It seems remarkable in this age of skyrocketing franchise values and $10 million players that former coaches would need assistance.</p>
        <p>The main problem for owners, several said last week, was that if they give the assistant coaches what they want, then the trainers may be next in line, or the office secretaries.</p>
        <p>But few in football -- not even the players -- put the sort of hours into the job that assistant coaches do. Their work ethic places them in a special class. Most owners realize and appreciate this fact. The association hopes that the few owners who do not, soon will.</p>
        <p>The Best of the 90's</p>
        <p>The Hall of Fame Board of Selectors has been asked by the N.F.L. to pick the team of the 1990's. So far, about one-third of the votes are in and there are only a handful of unanimous choices. They are:</p>
        <p>Wide receiver, Cris Carter and Jerry Rice; guard, Bruce Matthews; running back, Barry Sanders; defensive end, Bruce Smith and Reggie White; defensive tackle, John Randle; linebacker, Junior Seau; cornerback, Deion Sanders; and safety, LeRoy Butler.</p>
        <p>Other voting leaders by position include quarterback Brett Favre, tight end Shannon Sharpe, offensive tackle Gary Zimmerman, center Dermontti Dawson, kickers Morten Andersen and Gary Anderson, punt returner Deion Sanders and kick returner Michael Bates.</p>
        <p>The coaching leaders are Marv Levy, Bill Parcells and Mike Shanahan.</p>
        <p>How Much for Fisher?</p>
        <p>One of the biggest blunders of the off-season is happening in Tennessee.</p>
        <p>Jeff Fisher, one of the game's brightest head coaches, has a year left on a contract that will pay him $1 million a season. That is a lot of money, but by N.F.L. standards, for the coach of the defending American Football Conference champions, it is the equivalent of earning minimum wage.</p>
        <p>Fisher had been in negotiations with the Titans' owner, Bud Adams, looking for a new contract that would pay him about $2 million to $2.5 million a year, a fair amount, but those talks recently broke down.</p>
        <p>Fisher wants a new deal from Adams before leaving for vacation in June, or he will not talk contract until after this season. Waiting that long would be a disaster for the Titans, who would have to sign him for even more as a free agent or risk losing him.</p>
        <p>There is one man who is probably watching the situation closely, and hoping Tennessee blows it with Fisher. His name is Charley Casserly, general manager of the Houston franchise, which does not play until 2002. Casserly would love to swoop in and steal Fisher from the Titans.</p>
        <p>Chances are the Titans will work something out with Fisher before his deadline. If not, and if Fisher does end up leaving, it will be Tennessee's loss.</p>
        <p>Monitoring Free Agency</p>
        <p>While, in some instances, free agency may be hurting some teams in the game -- see Keyshawn Johnson leaving the Jets for Tampa Bay -- it may not be hurting the sport as much as many think. Free agency started on March 2, and so far 105 unrestricted and restricted players have changed teams, which is only about three players a team. . . . Denver continues to monitor the Steve Young situation in San Francisco. If the 49ers release him, the Broncos will very likely try to gobble him up. Meanwhile, running back Terrell Davis has looked great in spring workouts as he attempts his comeback from reconstructive knee surgery. . . . New England recently contacted the Jets about hiring one of their scouts, Lionel Vital, but was denied permission by Bill Parcells to speak with him. The Patriots are expected to make a second attempt to get Vital soon.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL: NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
