<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Eating Just Like They Do in Portugal</title>
    <meta content="14CART" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199291"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="A LA CARTE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Heart of Portugal (Mineola, Ny, Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Scholem, Richard Jay</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DEFDA1F38F937A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="613" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Eating Just Like They Do in Portugal</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD JAY SCHOLEM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Scholem, Richard Jay</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Richard Jay Scholem reviews Heart of Portugal restaurant in Mineola, Long Island (A La Carte column) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT'S possible to whiz along Mineola Boulevard and not notice that the large stucco building with the wrought-iron gates, brick-trimmed entrance and circular windows that was Little Portugal is now Heart of Portugal. The Mineola spot has experienced an admirable resurgence under its new owners. Although it's not unpleasant cliched Portuguese decor (stone and rough-hewn walls, fireplace, lanterns, antique guns, boat models, Old Lisbon mural) remains largely in place, the nine-month-old Heart of Portugal, at 241 Mineola Boulevard (516-742-9797), has a revitalized menu, warmth and spirit that makes it one of the most outstanding restaurants in this ethnic enclave.</p>
        <p>Swift, informed Portuguese servers gladly describe the restaurant's Portuguese specialties, there is live entertainment Wednesday through Saturday nights, the bread basket's rolls and corn bread and a bowl full of delicious marinated black olives make a positive first impression and the difficult-to-resist Portuguese potatoes, which used to cost $2, are now (like the olives and bread) complimentary, and they keep coming.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT'S possible to whiz along Mineola Boulevard and not notice that the large stucco building with the wrought-iron gates, brick-trimmed entrance and circular windows that was Little Portugal is now Heart of Portugal. The Mineola spot has experienced an admirable resurgence under its new owners. Although it's not unpleasant cliched Portuguese decor (stone and rough-hewn walls, fireplace, lanterns, antique guns, boat models, Old Lisbon mural) remains largely in place, the nine-month-old Heart of Portugal, at 241 Mineola Boulevard (516-742-9797), has a revitalized menu, warmth and spirit that makes it one of the most outstanding restaurants in this ethnic enclave.</p>
        <p>Swift, informed Portuguese servers gladly describe the restaurant's Portuguese specialties, there is live entertainment Wednesday through Saturday nights, the bread basket's rolls and corn bread and a bowl full of delicious marinated black olives make a positive first impression and the difficult-to-resist Portuguese potatoes, which used to cost $2, are now (like the olives and bread) complimentary, and they keep coming.</p>
        <p>Those homemade potato chips, sprinkled with garlic and parsley, are but one sign of authenticity and generosity. (They're best when served warm as they were on a weekend, rather than at room temperature, as was the case on a slow weekday.) Another is the appearance of rarely encountered Portuguese ingredients among the nightly specials. A huge filet or two of goraz ($18.95), a tender, though substantial white-fleshed fish, was available one evening. It, like grilled shrimp, napped in a rich citrusy cognac and lemon sauce ($17.95), came on a plate rimmed by roasted red peppers, broccoli, zucchini, olives, eggplant, tomatoes, radishes and even an occasional slice of papaya.</p>
        <p>A meatloaf-shaped cylinder of gleaming white codfish ($17.95), lined with strips of onions, peppers and tomatoes, is typical of the most popular dishes found in Portugal's restaurants. Its chopped broccoli rape and cauliflower plate-mates also rang true, as did an iron crock of paelha marinheira ($17.95) with a melange of fresh clams, mussels, shrimp, scallops and half a lobster in moist, impeccably cooked saffron rice.</p>
        <p>Diners seeking authenticity should pick one of the weekend-only Portuguese specialties in the lower lefthand corner of the menu: baby goat ($15.95) and tripe, sausage and white beans ($14.95) will no doubt be chosen only by the most adventurous, but the barbecued chicken ($13.95) and rabbit stew ($15.95) are appropriate everyman selections. The moist-inside-crisp-outside chicken is cut into manageable chunks and served with nicely browned, roasted potatoes and strips of green pepper.  The rabbit stew is full of soft, fall-from-the-bone meat in a husky tomato based sauce that is especially enjoyable when it shares a fork with its mashed potato accompaniment.</p>
        <p>Soups, salads and starters are at least the equal of main events. A special of fresh, springtime asparagus ($6.95), under a blanket of melted Fontana cheese, isn't particularly Portuguese, but it is a fine choice.  Salad Portuguesa ($4.50), an agreeable, ambitious meld of lettuce, tomato, cucumber, onion, peppers, apple and asparagus, covered with the garlic vinaigrette house dressing, is a keeper, as is clams bulhao pato ($7.95), a dozen clams in a cilantro white wine sauce dense with garlic slivers, as well as a dozen snails ($6.95) in a white wine sauce of minced garlic and oregano that begs to be sopped up with one of those sponge-like Portuguese rolls.</p>
        <p>Another splendid selection is the velvety caldo verde ($3.75), or green cabbage soup, with feathery, thin, almost transparent slices of sausage.  A spicy sausage in another context is the show stopper of starters: chourica Portuguesa ($7.95), which looks like a fat, foot-long hot dog, is roasted tableside over flaming grappa until its skin is deeply charred and all its diverse flavors are fully realized.</p>
        <p>A LA CARTE E-mail address: licarte@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail address: licarte@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
