<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Only 2 Libraries Adopt Filters for the Internet</title>
    <meta content="14FILT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199306"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Libraries and Librarians</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Censorship</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Greenburgh (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">White Plains (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Callahan, Tom</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Censorship</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Libraries and Librarians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E2D8163BF937A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="748" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Only 2 Libraries Adopt Filters for the Internet</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TOM CALLAHAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Callahan, Tom</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Libraries across Westchester County, with exception of those in Greenburgh and White Plains, continue to resist adding Internet filtering software to computers in children's rooms; some librarians say issue is parental choice rather than censorship (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>GREENBURGH has joined White Plains as the only communities in the county using Internet filtering software in their libraries' children's rooms. The filter bars access to Web sites deemed inappropriate for children, including those that depict sex, violence or illegal drug use.</p>
        <p>But other libraries are resisting the move to filters.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>GREENBURGH has joined White Plains as the only communities in the county using Internet filtering software in their libraries' children's rooms. The filter bars access to Web sites deemed inappropriate for children, including those that depict sex, violence or illegal drug use.</p>
        <p>But other libraries are resisting the move to filters.</p>
        <p>''Right now, the filter is being put on one of 250 computer terminals in the Westlynx system,'' said Dr. Maurice J. Freedman, director of the Westchester Library System. ''I hope the filter will stay there and wither away. No other library is rushing to adopt these filters.''</p>
        <p>Westlynx is the automated system used by 37 of the 38 member libraries of the county system. White Plains has its own system.</p>
        <p>Steve Force, director of the Yonkers Public Library, said of the filters: ''I think it is kind of like baring the barn door after the horse has left. Ultimately, parents are responsible for how their child uses the Internet. Secondly, the best filter turns out to be the children's librarian.''</p>
        <p>For Demita Gerber, director of the Greenburgh Library, the issue is not censorship, but parental choice. ''Our primary commitment is to intellectual freedom,'' she said. ''This filter is to give parents the opportunity to choose. We are providing users with just another format, like having a book on tape or hard cover.''</p>
        <p>Greenburgh has 15 terminals with Internet access. Eleven are in the adult section; three are in the children's room, and one is reserved for teenagers. A sign will identify the filtered terminal.</p>
        <p>Last December the directors of the Westchester Library System voted 18 to 12 to allow the filter to be placed on Greenburgh's terminal. The vote was needed since Westlynx manages and maintains all the software on the computer terminals of each member library. Since it has its own automated system, White Plains did not need permission to put a filter on nine terminals in its children's room, which was done in February 1998.</p>
        <p>Greenburgh will use the same filtering software as the White Plains Library, a product called Cyber Patrol.</p>
        <p>Assemblyman Michael J. Spano, a Republican from Yonkers, is an advocate of filters. He introduced a bill in the State Assembly late last year that would cut off state aid to libraries that did ''not restrict access to minors by providing terminals that filter or block such computers from receiving obscene or pornographic materials.''</p>
        <p>The White Plains Library Board decided that filters would help librarians deal with the explosion of information on the Internet. Campbell Geeslin, president of the board, said, ''With all the stories in the media, we felt that if we did not face up to this issue early, it would be a problem eventually.''</p>
        <p>The filters only affect the nine computers in the children's section. The library has a total of 20 machines with Internet access. White Plains paid approximately $400 for the software and an annual $35 subscription fee. The filter blocks 12 categories of Web sites, and the list of blocked sites is updated daily.</p>
        <p>Of concern to many county librarians is the possibility that legitimate research topics may be inaccessible. ''Filters are more imperfect than people are willing to admit, and that creates a false sense of security,'' said Stephanie Sarnoff, director of the Scarsdale Library. ''The classic example is when you put in a query for Mars exploration, and it won't come up because the software reads the letters S-E-X and blocks it out.''</p>
        <p>But Sandy Miranda, director of the White Plains Library, said that this has not been an issue. ''There would be a problem if the software worked poorly and children couldn't do their homework assignments,'' she said. ''That hasn't been the case.''</p>
        <p>Last year, 10,000 children used the computer room in the White Plains children's department. Rosemary Rasmussen, manager of children's services for the library, said, ''We've had a few cases of children being blocked from wrestling sites, but there have not been any complaints from parents.''</p>
        <p>Library directors opposed to filters say that their computer terminals are in clear view of the librarians, who are quick to stop the viewing of pornographic Web sites.</p>
        <p>''The question is what is appropriate behavior in a library,'' said Sibyl Canaan, director of the Peekskill Library. ''We don't allow chess playing here or loud discussions. If somebody was sitting at a table, looking at pornography, it would not be appropriate behavior. Accessing porn sites in a library is not appropriate either.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
