<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sierra Leone Rebel Leader Reportedly Smuggled Gems</title>
    <meta content="14AFRI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199602"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Diamonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mines and Mining</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sierra Leone</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sankoh, Foday</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Crossette, Barbara</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Sierra Leone</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Sierra Leone</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mines and Mining</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diamonds</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E3D9133BF937A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="750" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sierra Leone Rebel Leader Reportedly Smuggled Gems</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA CROSSETTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Crossette, Barbara</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Documents collected in Sierra Leone and obtained by The New York Times show that warlord Foday Sankoh has systematically exploited diamonds to pay for his rebellion and enrich himself; papers were found in Sankoh's looted house (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the wake of fighting among rebel groups and government troops in the capital of Sierra Leone, officials loyal to President Ahman Tejan Kabbah are beginning to amass documents which they say show the extent to which the rebel leader Foday Sankoh was systematically exploiting the country's diamonds to pay for his rebellion and enrich himself.</p>
        <p>''Terrible people in history keep very good records,'' a high-ranking government official said in a telephone interview yesterday. And tomorrow, Sierra Leone's attorney general, Solomon Berewa, plans to begin making public a large number of documents found in the looted house of Mr. Sankoh, whose whereabouts are now unknown.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the wake of fighting among rebel groups and government troops in the capital of Sierra Leone, officials loyal to President Ahman Tejan Kabbah are beginning to amass documents which they say show the extent to which the rebel leader Foday Sankoh was systematically exploiting the country's diamonds to pay for his rebellion and enrich himself.</p>
        <p>''Terrible people in history keep very good records,'' a high-ranking government official said in a telephone interview yesterday. And tomorrow, Sierra Leone's attorney general, Solomon Berewa, plans to begin making public a large number of documents found in the looted house of Mr. Sankoh, whose whereabouts are now unknown.</p>
        <p>Copies of some of these papers dealing with the diamond trade were made available to The New York Times by other officials.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sankoh, whose forces are being held responsible for the abduction of about 500 United Nations peacekeepers -- some of whom had begun to be assigned to diamond-producing areas -- took over the mining ministry last year after a peace agreement brought him into government in return for ending his savage rebellion. Under Mr. Sankoh's soldiers, many of them brutalized children themselves, the limbs of civilians were hacked off and communities were destroyed to send a deliberate message of terror throughout the population.</p>
        <p>Because Mr. Sankoh, leader of the Revolutionary United Front, had been in government since last summer, some of his diamond deals would have presumably been legal. Foreign companies, including some from the United States, were known to have been negotiating with him, or at least exploring the possibility.</p>
        <p>But records that government officials say they are finding now appear to be meticulous accounts of personal deals recording the delivery to Mr. Sankoh of more than 2,000 stones of varying sizes from last August, soon after Mr. Sankoh came into government, until the beginning of this year.</p>
        <p>Based on the records they found -- along with letters from a business associate abroad, who was apparently trying to find a buyer for the diamonds in Antwerp, Belgium, the center of the rough diamond trade -- officials in Sierra Leone are convinced that the trouble with United Nations peacekeepers began when the force's Indian commander, Maj. Gen. Vijay Kumar Jetley, ordered some of his troops into the richest diamond mining area, around Kono, in eastern Sierra Leone.</p>
        <p>''As soon as Sankoh saw that the U.N. was serious about deploying in Kono, then he declared war on the U.N.,'' the senior official said.</p>
        <p>The documents involving diamonds -- including handwritten lists identifying every courier who brought stones to Mr. Sankoh, with notes about their color and size -- may answer other questions puzzling the government about the rebel leader's relations with President Charles Taylor of neighboring Liberia and with Mr. Sankoh's former field commander, Sam Bockarie.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bockarie, who personally delivered many of the stones to Mr. Sankoh, according to the records, opposed the peace agreement and fled to Liberia.</p>
        <p>At about that time, Mr. Sankoh's records no longer list diamond deliveries. Officials want to know why, as well as if and how, those events may have been related. In recent months, Mr. Sankoh, whose rebel movement was helped if not created by Mr. Taylor, appears to have been trying to circumvent the Liberians as he sought partners for diamond deals abroad.</p>
        <p>At the United Nations, the Security Council has produced a report on how the diamond trade fueled the rebellion in Angola of Jonas Savimbi and his organization, the Union for the Total Independence of Angola, or Unita. The council plans to act on that report in the fall after further investigations, possibly seeking punitive measures against countries or companies that have been trading with Unita in violation of United Nations sanctions.</p>
        <p>In Sierra Leone, officials say they are now looking at evidence of a similar gems-for-weapons system developed by Mr. Sankoh. Early reading of documents shows all the same hallmarks -- local mining operations, links to international traders and a marketing focus on Antwerp, which until recently has been lax in examining the origins of gems or the identities of sellers.</p>
        <p>Sierra Leone officials say that Mr. Sankoh may have been doing more than merely enriching himself and buying weapons for his rebel troops in the field. There is some evidence emerging, they say, that he may have been planning to accumulate enough resources to attempt to overthrow the government in Freetown.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
