<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Mysterious Human Sense of Smell: So Primitive and So Powerful</title>
    <meta content="14ODOR$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199446"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Smell</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Odors</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">New Models, Design and Products</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Moran, Tim</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Automobile Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Odors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Smell</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Models, Design and Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E7DF153BF937A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="455" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Mysterious Human Sense of Smell: So Primitive and So Powerful</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TIM MORAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Moran, Tim</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Scientists studying human sense of smell say that it sounds smart to control odor in cars by minimizing smell of what goes into them, but eliminating odors may cause more trouble than it solves; if a new-car smell is too weak, other, less-pleasant odors could seem overwhelming during honeymoon period when an owner is getting accustomed to new car (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT sounds smart to control the odor in cars by minimizing the smell of what goes into them. But eliminating odors may cause more trouble than it solves, say scientists studying the human sense of smell.</p>
        <p>''People judge a product based on the way it smells,'' said Dr. Alan Hirsch of the Smell and Taste Treatment and Research Foundation in Chicago. ''If it smells good, we perceive it as good.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT sounds smart to control the odor in cars by minimizing the smell of what goes into them. But eliminating odors may cause more trouble than it solves, say scientists studying the human sense of smell.</p>
        <p>''People judge a product based on the way it smells,'' said Dr. Alan Hirsch of the Smell and Taste Treatment and Research Foundation in Chicago. ''If it smells good, we perceive it as good.''</p>
        <p>Most people like the aroma of a new car for a variety of reasons, including smell-induced nostalgia.</p>
        <p>But if the new-car smell is too weak, other, less-pleasant odors could seem overwhelming during the honeymoon period when an owner is getting accustomed to a new car. These malodors, from air pollutants to naturally occurring body aromas, can do more than annoy. Dr. Hirsch said scientific studies of driving that he has reviewed, including a 1972 study of driving and air pollution near Los Angeles, proved that nasty smells can lead to hostility, bad driving and more accidents.</p>
        <p>Bad smells alone caused harsh behavior in a nondriving study. Men instructed to ''train'' others by using a variable jolt of electricity inflicted much tougher shocks when bad odors were piped to them.</p>
        <p>How does the sense of smell work? Some odors are so irritating that they cause a trigeminal stimulation -- the same kind that makes chili peppers ''hot'' or mints ''cool'' in the mouth. Trigeminal stimulation releases adrenaline, leading to a tense and angry state, Dr. Hirsch theorizes.</p>
        <p>''In the presence of bad odors, people tend to be more aggressive,'' he said. ''There are days when there's more bad odors in air pollution, people are driving more aggressively and they tend to get in more accidents.''</p>
        <p>There's no way to turn off the sense of smell, short of keeping odor-causing molecules from reaching the body's receptor cells. Smell is hard-wired deep into sensitive areas of the brain, ones that control emotion and memory, said Dr. Stuart Firestein, associate professor of biology at Columbia University.</p>
        <p>''One branch of the input goes directly to the hippocampus, and an area called the amygdela,'' Dr. Firestein said. ''The amygdela is interesting because it's known to be important in emotions, and the hippocampus is interesting because it's known to be important in memory.''</p>
        <p>Humans have not yet evolved a specific receptor for new-car smells. And even when a smell is specific, people can adapt situational responses to it, Dr. Firestein said.</p>
        <p>For instance, he said, ''the chemical that characterizes the smell of vomit, that very same chemical, if you think about it, is in Parmesan cheese.''</p>
        <p>TIM MORAN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
