<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="14FSUM$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199581"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E2DA133BF937A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="666" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>3-14</p>
        <p>U.S. Labor Lobbies Hard To Defeat China Trade Bill  The American labor movement is mounting its biggest lobbying campaign ever on trade matters in seeking to defeat the Clinton administration's drive to normalize commerce with China.</p>
        <p>1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>3-14</p>
        <p>U.S. Labor Lobbies Hard To Defeat China Trade Bill  The American labor movement is mounting its biggest lobbying campaign ever on trade matters in seeking to defeat the Clinton administration's drive to normalize commerce with China.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Vatican Reveals Fatima Secret  The Vatican disclosed the so-called third secret of Fatima, which for decades has kept the shrine of the Virgin Mary in Portugal at the center of conspiracy theories and doomsday cults. A Vatican official described the secret as a vision of the 1981 assassination attempt on the pope.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Sierra Leone Slides Back  With the apparent collapse of a nine-month-old peace accord in Sierra Leone, the country is on the verge of slipping back into warlordism, which for years had rendered Sierra Leone a state in name only.</p>
        <p>14</p>
        <p>Horn of Africa Fighting  Ethiopia and Eritrea fought along their border for a second day, ignoring appeals from the United Nations Security Council to end the battles.</p>
        <p>14</p>
        <p>Japan Embraces the Internet  The Internet is quietly transforming Japan, making celebrities of small farmers, empowering women, changing the way people apply for jobs and schools and generally chipping away at traditional patterns of behavior.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Dutch Explosions Kill 20  A blaze inside a fireworks warehouse set off multiple explosions that killed at least 20 people, wounded 175 more and sent balls of fire shooting over the center of the eastern Dutch town of Enschede.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>16-31</p>
        <p>California Governor Seeks Big Tax Break for Teachers  Gov. Gray Davis of California has proposed to exempt all public school teachers from the state's income tax, in what officials believe is the first such peacetime exemption for any occupation in American history.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Fears About Death Penalty  Texas has executed 127 people during the tenure of Gov. George W. Bush. The governor is certain they all were guilty, but some Texas officials who administer the death penalty say the state runs the risk of executing an innocent person.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Plants to Contain Drugs  Tobacco farmers are seeking to bolster their sagging business by growing plants genetically altered to contain pharmaceuticals.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>President Praises March  President Clinton praised the Million Mom March, saying the Washington event will send a message to the nation's gun lobby.</p>
        <p>16</p>
        <p>Fire Declared Disaster  President Clinton declared the area affected by the Los Alamos fires to be a ''major disaster.''</p>
        <p>16</p>
        <p>Dispute Over Cuban Doctors  A dispute in Florida over the licensing of Cuban doctors is testing the power of Cuban-Americans against the medical establishment.</p>
        <p>20</p>
        <p>Long-Awaited Medals of Honor  The Medal of Honor has been awarded to 21 servicemen of Asian descent who fought in World War II.</p>
        <p>21</p>
        <p>Interest Groups Attack  A trend is changing the face of political advertising: an increasing number of attack campaigns by special-interest groups.</p>
        <p>22</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>33-40</p>
        <p>Shifting Views of Giuliani As He Confronts Personal Crisis  Over a span of a few days Rudolph W. Giuliani became someone other than the mayor a city thought it knew.</p>
        <p>33</p>
        <p>Family Court in Disarray  A growing docket and a dwindling pool of lawyers available to represent the poor have so crippled the New York City Family Court system that judges are forced to adjourn cases repeatedly, according to a report to be released by the city's public advocate.</p>
        <p>35</p>
        <p>Fresh Air Fund</p>
        <p>38</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>41-42</p>
        <p>Chess</p>
        <p>41</p>
        <p>Weather</p>
        <p>43</p>
        <p>Cong. Vote</p>
        <p>39</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
