<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Markers Honor Parades Honoring Heroes</title>
    <meta content="14CANY" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199457"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: LOWER MANHATTAN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parades</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Monuments and Memorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Heroism and Heroes</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Alliance For Downtown New York</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fairfield, Hannah</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Heroism and Heroes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parades</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Monuments and Memorials</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE5DE153BF937A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="732" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Markers Honor Parades Honoring Heroes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HANNAH FAIRFIELD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fairfield, Hannah</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alliance for Downtown New York is replacing sidewalks of lower Broadway, from Battery Place to Murray Strees, with blue-tinted concrete embedded with granite plaques honoring all of city's 199 parades for heroes from 1886 to present; partial list; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Snaking between the skyscrapers of Lower Manhattan, Broadway is known as the Canyon of Heroes, the route of the city's signature ticker tape parades honoring athletes, astronauts, world leaders and the like. Now, the parades -- 199 in all, starting in 1886 -- are being honored themselves, with stone markers along the very path they traveled.</p>
        <p>The Alliance for Downtown New York is replacing the sidewalks of lower Broadway, from Battery Place to Murray Streets, with blue-tinted concrete. Imbedded along the 13 blocks, like bread crumbs for pedestrians to follow, will be black granite plaques placed 20 feet apart and bearing steel letters with the date and honoree of each parade. The first plaque, at Battery Place, will mark the first parade. It was an impromptu affair kicked off by brokers tossing stock ticker tape from their office windows to celebrate the dedication of the Statue of Liberty. The date was Oct. 28, 1886.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Snaking between the skyscrapers of Lower Manhattan, Broadway is known as the Canyon of Heroes, the route of the city's signature ticker tape parades honoring athletes, astronauts, world leaders and the like. Now, the parades -- 199 in all, starting in 1886 -- are being honored themselves, with stone markers along the very path they traveled.</p>
        <p>The Alliance for Downtown New York is replacing the sidewalks of lower Broadway, from Battery Place to Murray Streets, with blue-tinted concrete. Imbedded along the 13 blocks, like bread crumbs for pedestrians to follow, will be black granite plaques placed 20 feet apart and bearing steel letters with the date and honoree of each parade. The first plaque, at Battery Place, will mark the first parade. It was an impromptu affair kicked off by brokers tossing stock ticker tape from their office windows to celebrate the dedication of the Statue of Liberty. The date was Oct. 28, 1886.</p>
        <p>''The parades mirror what was important to the country, not just the city,'' said Bethany Rufener, design associate for the Alliance for Downtown New York. The sidewalk, she said, will ''provide a new, visible layer of knowledge and understanding to an area where so many people work.''</p>
        <p>In 1926, white clouds of confetti and ticker tape drifted down as the city celebrated the first explorers to fly over the North Pole. When Amelia Earhart became the first woman to fly solo across the Atlantic, she was wildly cheered at a parade on June 20, 1932.</p>
        <p>''Before television, the parades were a way for people to see history in the making,'' Ms. Rufener said.</p>
        <p>When computers replaced stock tickers, shredded printouts and rolls of toilet paper replaced ticker tape. Explorers, though, remained popular honorees, including the crew of the first nuclear submarine in 1958, and  astronauts Neil Armstrong, Buzz Aldrin and Michael Collins, who flew the first mission to land on the moon, in 1969. More than half of the 199 parades have honored visiting foreign leaders.</p>
        <p>''Young people may think we only have ticker tape parades when the Yankees win the World Series,'' said Paul Goldstein, district manager of Manhattan's Community Board 1, which includes the parade route. ''The new sidewalks will show a slice of the history of the oldest and most historic part of New York City.''</p>
        <p>The mayor decides who gets a ticker tape parade, and the city gets the bill. Private sponsors often help pay for the large parades, like the Yankees' victory lap, which can cost up to $800,000 for police and sanitation services.</p>
        <p>Mayor Robert F. Wagner held 69 parades during his administration from 1954-65, but Mayor Abraham D. Beame did not have any during his term from 1974-77, a time when New York was all but broke. Mayor Giuliani has held five since 1994, three of which celebrated Yankee victories in the World Series.</p>
        <p>Construction of the first phase of the parade walk, five blocks from Exchange Place to Liberty Street, is to start in May and end in September. Completion of the entire $50,000 project is scheduled for 2004, and designers are reserving 15 blank plaques for future parades.</p>
        <p>HANNAH FAIRFIELD</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: LOWER MANHATTAN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
