<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>M Is For . . .</title>
    <meta content="14SOAP$14" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199398"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FIRST PERSON"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mother's Day</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Contests and Prizes</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cbs Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Barnard College</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Feibusch, Daniela</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Frias, Jhosnayda</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Poon, June</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ward, Lindsey</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mother's Day</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Contests and Prizes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E6D9143BF937A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1001" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>M Is For . . .</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Excerpts from winning essays in annual contest sponsored by Barnard College and CBS Foundation in which New York City public school girls wrote about mothers and step-mothers; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN girls from around New York City, juniors in public schools, sat down to write about ''A Woman I Admire'' they chose subjects as celebrated as Princess Di, as memorable as Hester Prynne and as ancient as Eve. But many of the girls, in an annual essay contest sponsored by Barnard College and the CBS Foundation, wrote about mothers: mothers who struggled in a new country or changing circumstances, birth mothers who live in the imagination or heroic stepmothers who saved the day. Here are excerpts from some of the winning essays, offering a snapshot of motherhood on Mother's Day 2000.</p>
        <p>DANIELA FEIBUSCH  Boerum Hill, Brooklyn  Edward R. Murrow High School</p>
        <p>I have a special bond with a woman I know almost nothing about; I don't know her age, where she lives or if she is even still alive. This woman carried me for nine months, gave birth and never saw me again. This woman is the one who gave me up for adoption 16 years ago.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN girls from around New York City, juniors in public schools, sat down to write about ''A Woman I Admire'' they chose subjects as celebrated as Princess Di, as memorable as Hester Prynne and as ancient as Eve. But many of the girls, in an annual essay contest sponsored by Barnard College and the CBS Foundation, wrote about mothers: mothers who struggled in a new country or changing circumstances, birth mothers who live in the imagination or heroic stepmothers who saved the day. Here are excerpts from some of the winning essays, offering a snapshot of motherhood on Mother's Day 2000.</p>
        <p>DANIELA FEIBUSCH  Boerum Hill, Brooklyn  Edward R. Murrow High School</p>
        <p>I have a special bond with a woman I know almost nothing about; I don't know her age, where she lives or if she is even still alive. This woman carried me for nine months, gave birth and never saw me again. This woman is the one who gave me up for adoption 16 years ago.</p>
        <p>When I was younger I never knew what to think about my biological mother. It was after a trip to Korea that I realized who this woman was to me. While in Korea, I met with mothers who gave their babies up for adoption. They told us how hard it was and how they think of their babies every day hoping they made the right decision. After this trip, I admired my birth mother. I used to be angry with her and never understood how anyone could give up her child. As I grew up I saw her very differently.</p>
        <p>I still think about my birth mother and if she wonders about me the way I wonder about her. I admire my birth mother for so many reasons, and I have just started uncovering our relationship and although I might never fully understand it, I know it is there.</p>
        <p>JHOSNAYDA FRIAS  Highbridge, the Bronx  Bronx School for Law, Government and Justice</p>
        <p>Some people would look at my family life and say I was unlucky, but they would be wrong. Unfortunately, my mother left me when I was only a baby. But, an angel came into my life, and she is the woman I most admire. Her name is Juana and she is my stepmother.</p>
        <p>When I was a baby my biological mother left me and my father put me in the care of a lady I hardly remember. When I turned 3, my father and Juana took me. It's hard to believe that a person that doesn't carry your blood could love you unconditionally, but that is what Juana has done.</p>
        <p>She has stuck by me. My father used to drink, and when he did he became violent. Sometimes I wanted to strike at him, but I was too frightened. It tortured me because I wanted to protect Juana. I am surprised but relieved that Juana did not leave my father. She thought about her three children and would not leave. We came before her safety.</p>
        <p>Several years ago, my father stopped drinking. Now he is a good father all the time and I am thankful for that. What I am most thankful for is that my stepmother has been a source of love, courage and devotion.</p>
        <p>JUNE POON  Lower East Side, Manhattan  Bronx High School of Science</p>
        <p>I watch my mother from the worn kitchen table. The table was once pure white with a clean surface; now it is old with jagged edges. It has been through many years of happiness and sadness with the family it serves. My mother is packing our lunches mechanically. She seems dulled by the mundane events of her life. I cannot remember the last time she smiled. Was it when the entire family went to Six Flags? Or was it the time we all threw her a surprise birthday party?</p>
        <p>My mother is not a 90's career woman. She does not swing a brown leather briefcase, nor does she walk with a smart stride. She's a housewife, a homemaker. She always wanted to go back to school, but she never did. Instead she chose to take care of my brother and me, making our education her life's work.</p>
        <p>At night, I can hear her silently weeping, but in the morning, she's up at dawn packing turkey sandwiches into brown paper bags as though nothing has happened. My mother is like the once clean white table; she has seen happiness and sadness within our family, and consequently is rough around the edges with memories.</p>
        <p>LINDSEY WARD  Midwood, Brooklyn  Edward R. Murrow High School</p>
        <p>You'd never know from a picture that my mother was amazingly strong. She had a gentle face and friendly smile. She wasn't raised to be strong. She left Brooklyn to attend college at 16. Armed with a hunger for knowledge, she earned a Ph.D. Always one to share, she taught college English on weekends and kindergarten on weekdays.</p>
        <p>She always tried to be the best mother she could. She gave me and my brothers ''after-dinner hugs'' nightly and would frequently ask, ''Have I told you yet today that I love you?'' She unselfishly poured her energy into her family.</p>
        <p>My mother had strength to fight for what she loved and never abandon her beliefs, no matter how difficult that fight became. In the last years of her life, my mother struggled with cancer. It was a losing battle, but she never gave up. The doctors told her that she would not live more than 10 years and she responded, ''I'm going to live to dance at my children's weddings.''</p>
        <p>My mother astounds me. She was a loving, unselfish person with phenomenal strength. In her high school yearbook, the words ''To give of oneself, to leave the world a bit better -- this is to have succeeded'' are inscribed above her photograph.</p>
        <p>FIRST PERSON</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
