<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE GUIDE</title>
    <meta content="14GUID$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000519T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199279"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E5DB1F38F937A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1471" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE GUIDE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA DELATINER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Best Bet</p>
        <p>In ''Auf Wiedersehen, David,'' David Lockington conducts his final performance as the music director of the Long Island Philharmonic Saturday at 8 p.m. and next Sunday at 7:30 p.m. at Tilles Center in Brookville. The finale to both the orchestra's season and Mr. Lockington's career with it features Mahler's Symphony No. 2 (''Resurrection''), performed by the Philharmonic and its chorus, directed by Frances C. Roberts, with Margaret Cusack, soprano, and Petra Lang, mezzo-soprano, (631) 293-2222.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Best Bet</p>
        <p>In ''Auf Wiedersehen, David,'' David Lockington conducts his final performance as the music director of the Long Island Philharmonic Saturday at 8 p.m. and next Sunday at 7:30 p.m. at Tilles Center in Brookville. The finale to both the orchestra's season and Mr. Lockington's career with it features Mahler's Symphony No. 2 (''Resurrection''), performed by the Philharmonic and its chorus, directed by Frances C. Roberts, with Margaret Cusack, soprano, and Petra Lang, mezzo-soprano, (631) 293-2222.</p>
        <p>Two community orchestras also take to the stage on Saturday: the Long Beach Symphony, with Dorothy Lawson, cellist, play works by Beethoven, Haydn, Rossini and Tchaikovsky at 8 p.m. at the Lindell Boulevard School (516) 432-6730, and the South Shore Symphony, with Stephen Hopkins, pianist and the winner of its Young Musicians in Performance Competition, perform music by Beethoven and Grieg, at 8 p.m. at South Side High School on Shepherd Street in Rockville Centre (516) 764-1558.</p>
        <p>Happy Mother's Day</p>
        <p>Family togetherness, either outdoors or in museums, rules in today's celebration of Mother's Day. So the Museums at Stony Brook on Route 25A, with a horse-drawn carriage collection that's the largest in the United States, and current exhibitions like ''New Neighbors: The Changing Face of Long Island,'' will charge everyone $1 admission from noon to 5 p.m. today (631) 751-0066. Mothers will be admitted free to the Gregory Museum on Heitz Place in Hicksville, from 12:30 to 5 p.m., to see the museum's extensive mineral, shell and butterfly collections (516) 822-7505. At the Heckscher Museum of Art on Prime Avenue in Huntington from 1:30 to 4:30 p.m. when they participate in ''Discovering Art Together,'' mothers receive a free carnation (631) 351-3250. At Old Westbury Gardens, the 88 acres of gardens and the historic mansion, Westbury House, are gearing up to welcome mom to a classical music concert by a Juilliard student at 2:30 p.m. in the mansion or a ''Talk and Tour'' on ''Using Annuals in a Perennial Garden'' at 2 p.m. (516) 333-0048. Or how about, a ''Mother's Day Shelter Island Paddle?'' It's a Group for the South Fork kayak tour of the Island's creeks and inlets at noon (631) 537-1400.</p>
        <p>Festival Time</p>
        <p>With the calendar beginning to fill up with fairs and festivals, two events this week warrant special attention. In Riverhead, at the Hallockville Museum Farm and Folklife Center on Sound Avenue, there is a three-day ''Civil War Encampment,'' 9 a.m. to 4 p.m. Friday, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m. and 6:30 to 8:30 p.m. Saturday and 10 a.m. to 2 p.m. next Sunday. Such re-enactment groups as the 14th Brooklyn Company H, Jackson's Virginia Flying Artillery and the C. S. Field Hospital will demonstrate camp and military life and even stage some battles (631) 298-5292. In Port Washington, the emphasis in the ''10th Annual Harborfest Dock Day Festival'' is on the community's nautical heritage, with tall-ship cruises, noon to 6:30 p.m.; concerts, 11:30 a.m. through 6 p.m.; a fun run for children, 9:30 a.m.; a family fun stage, 11 a.m. to 4 p.m.; a model boat regatta; and environmental exhibits. This all takes place from 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. at the Town Dock and Lower Main Street (516) 883-6566.</p>
        <p>For Youngsters</p>
        <p>With a film festival and three puppet shows, Saturday is a great day to be a child. With more than 10 films from countries like Canada, Finland, Iceland, Iran, Ireland, the Netherlands and the United States, and a hands-on animation workshop, the ''International Children's Film Festival'' comes to the Cinema Arts Center on Park Avenue in Huntington with screenings of short films at 11 a.m., the workshop at 12:45 p.m. and the showing of ''The Little Man'' from Iran at 1:45 p.m. There will be more shorts at 11 a.m. next Sunday and ''Count Me Out'' from Iceland at 12:30 p.m. (631) 423-7610. Paul Peabody's marionettes bring characters like Mrs. Tiggy Winkle and Pigling Bland to life in a ''Beatrix Potter Festival'' at 11 a.m. at the Heckscher Museum of Art on Prime Avenue in Huntington (631) 351-3250. In Oakdale at 4 p.m. at the Connetquot River State Park, Native America presents ''The Sycamore Kids,'' an outdoor puppet show about the natural history of this American tree (631) 582-7375. In St. James at the Mills Pond House on Route 25A, Katie Polk, a Long Island puppeteer, offers workshops at 10 and 11:30 a.m. and 1 p.m. on how to make three simple bird puppets and then put on a ''Flying in Colors'' performance for their families (631) 862-6575.</p>
        <p>Huntington Pottery</p>
        <p>Once upon a time, a pottery industry thrived in Huntington. And while the local historical society has records of Huntington clay being sold as early as 1751, potters were in commercial vogue throughout the 19th century, producing the highly prized Huntington redware. Anthony Butera Jr., a mason from Port Jefferson, has made the collecting and study of this pottery his hobby and on Thursday he will appear at the historical society's David Conklin Farmhouse Museum on High Street to discuss the redware, from its medieval roots through its mid-19th century prominence. Using slides and actual pieces to show how the industry emerged from its folk art origins to its commercial importance, he will speak at 7:30 p.m., following refreshments at 7 p.m. (631) 427-7045.</p>
        <p>Vocal Music</p>
        <p>Vocal music, provided by both choruses and single practitioners, dominates Saturday's lineup. In a program of ''American Music of the 20th Century,'' the Waldorf Choral Society sings works by Barber, Copland, Stravinsky and others at 8 p.m. at the Cathedral of the Incarnation on Cathedral Avenue in Garden City (516) 747-4457, while the Twin Shore Chorus of the Society for the Preservation and Encouragement of Barber Shop Quartet Singing in America offers its ''Spring Show: Music in Our Lives'' at 7:30 p.m. at Central Islip High School on Wheeler Road. The concert will be repeated at 3 p.m. next Sunday at St. Joseph's College in Patchogue (631) 234-9404. Those going it alone are folk artists: John Sebastian, joined by Paul Richell and Annie Raines, the folk-blues singers; Buddy Merriam and Back Roads and Pete Fornatale, appear at 8 p.m. at the Landmark on Main Street in Port Washington (516) 767-6444, and Michele Monte and Stuart Markus, singer-songwriters, perform for the Folk Music Society of Huntington at 8 p.m. at the Congregational Church on Washington Drive in Centerport (631) 473-7193.</p>
        <p>Musicals, Musicals</p>
        <p>Taking stock of summer's theater scene means musicals. And the Gateway Playhouse, the major surviving straw circuit outlet on the Island, opens Wednesday with ''Pippin,''  Stephen Schwartze's hip, tongue-in-cheek fairy tale that made Broadway history with its original Bob Fosse choreography. It runs through June 3 at the theater on South Country Road in Bellport and will be followed by ''The Best Little Whorehouse in Texas,'' June 7 through 24; the world premiere of ''Yankee Doodle Dandy: The George M. Cohan Story,'' June 28 through July 15; ''South Pacific,'' July 19 through Aug. 5; ''Big,'' Aug. 9 through 26, and ''The Will Rogers Follies,'' Aug. 30 through Sept. 16 (631) 286-1133.</p>
        <p>Four other local theaters come in with musicals this week, too. In Huntington, at Touro Law Center on Nassau Road, the Village Theater Company performs ''My Fair Lady'' on weekends from Saturday through June 11 (631) 424-4600, while in Mattituck, the North Fork Community Theater on Sound Avenue stages ''Jerry's Girls'' Friday and weekends through June 4 (631) 298-6328. The Stage on Hewlett Avenue in Merrick contributes ''Grease'' from Saturday through June 25 (516) 868-6400. In Port Jefferson, Theater Three takes off with ''Peter Pan'' on Saturday. Complete with flying equipment by ZFX, which sent the recent Broadway revival airborne, the fantasy runs through July 1 at the theater on Main Street (631) 928-9100.</p>
        <p>Free Choices</p>
        <p>THURSDAY -- Carl Djerassi, the scientist who first synthesized the oral contraceptive known as ''the pill,'' will discuss ''Technology and Human Reproduction: 1950-2050'' at 4 p.m. in Berkner Hall on the Upton campus of Brookhaven National Laboratory (631) 344-2345.</p>
        <p>FRIDAY -- ''The Misfits,'' Arthur Miller's fable about a disillusioned divorcee and her cowboy friends, which turned out to be the last film made by Marilyn Monroe and Clark Gable, gets the ''Cinema Classics'' treatment at 7:30 p.m. at the Half Hollow Hills Library on Vanderbilt Parkway in Dix Hills (631) 421-4530.</p>
        <p>SATURDAY -- Afro Dysia plays Latin, classical, funk and jazz at 2 p.m. at the Freeport Library on South Ocean Avenue (516) 379-3274, and the Hester Street Troupe, a klezmer-vaudeville act, performs at 8 p.m. at the Plainview-Old Bethpage Library on Old Country Road in Plainview (516) 938-0077.</p>
        <p>BARBARA DELATINER</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 19, 2000, Friday  A benefits listing in the Long Island section on Sunday about a five-kilometer run, walkathon and bike athon for United Cerebral Palsy of Greater Suffolk misstated the date. The event is scheduled for Heckscher State Park in East Islip at 9 a.m. this Sunday, not Saturday. Information: (631) 232-0015.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 19, 2000, Friday</p>
        <p>A benefits listing in the Long Island section on Sunday about a five-kilometer run, walkathon and bike athon for United Cerebral Palsy of Greater Suffolk misstated the date. The event is scheduled for Heckscher State Park in East Islip at 9 a.m. this Sunday, not Saturday. Information: (631) 232-0015.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
