<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BOOKS IN BRIEF: NONFICTION</title>
    <meta content="RV090838" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="34" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199174"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cho, Christina</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Crunden, Robert M</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Body and Soul (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E7DB1738F937A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="405" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BOOKS IN BRIEF: NONFICTION</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Christina Cho</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cho, Christina</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Christina Cho reviews book Body and Soul: The Making of American Modernism by Robert M Crunden (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BODY AND SOUL</p>
        <p>The Making of American Modernism.</p>
        <p>By Robert M. Crunden.</p>
        <p>Basic Books, $35.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BODY AND SOUL</p>
        <p>The Making of American Modernism.</p>
        <p>By Robert M. Crunden.</p>
        <p>Basic Books, $35.</p>
        <p>Modernism in America arose out of chaos and noise, out of World War I and metropolises pervaded by blaring advertisements, sirens and trains. In his broad chronicle ''Body and Soul,'' Robert M. Crunden, a professor of history and American studies at the University of Texas, Austin, who died last year, also adopts a form reflecting that fragmented world that created ''the crazy quilt of modernism,'' offering less a linear narrative than a collage of vignettes profiling the myriad personalities, like Jelly Roll Morton, Wallace Stevens and Georgia O'Keeffe, who contributed to its development. The resulting portrait, vivid and complex, of this flourishing movement reveals the numerous intersections -- or perhaps collisions -- between the radically diverse cast of characters who encountered, inspired, influenced, sponsored or despised one another. This vast web of egos encompassed disparate disciplines like music, architecture, poetry and photography and such far-flung realms as the Storyville district of New Orleans, Alfred Stieglitz's 291 Gallery in New York and Nadia Boulanger's classroom at the Conservatoire Americain in Fountainbleau. Crunden's individual sketches often resemble narratives of education as much as critical texts; in a chapter on John Dos Passos, for instance, he provides an account of the writer's miserable boyhood as ''an illegitimate child of privilege'' who was ''nowhere really at home,'' proceeds to his days as an ambulance driver stationed in Europe, witnessing the horrific spectacle of World War I while sampling the cultural offerings of Paris and Venice, and eventually arrives at the 1925 publication of ''Manhattan Transfer,'' which Crunden calls ''the American city novel'' that ''captured the most important city in the hemisphere . . . in a new style that made use of cinematic grammar, Cubist conceptions of planes and perspectives, jazz rhythms, the collage and other such modernist innovations.'' ''Body and Soul'' is also a coming-of-age tale of a nation of manifold, at times uncertain lineage discovering and learning to define itself.</p>
        <p>Christina Cho</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
