<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A 2-Month-Old Fund, Carrying a Big Stick</title>
    <meta content="14RAID$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199463"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="INVESTING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Employee Solutions</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Allied Owners Action Fund</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">e.Raider.com</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Privateer Asset Management</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berry, Kate</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brown, Aaron</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, Quentin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E0DE153BF937A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="659" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A 2-Month-Old Fund, Carrying a Big Stick</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATE BERRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Berry, Kate</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Rece</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MOST mutual funds keep their distance from companies on matters of corporate governance, but the $3 million Allied Owners Action fund, introduced on March 10, jumps in with both feet.</p>
        <p>Its goal is to buy shares of companies with underperforming assets or subpar management, then to lobby for change -- helped by a network of investors called to arms through a companion Web site, eRaider.com.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MOST mutual funds keep their distance from companies on matters of corporate governance, but the $3 million Allied Owners Action fund, introduced on March 10, jumps in with both feet.</p>
        <p>Its goal is to buy shares of companies with underperforming assets or subpar management, then to lobby for change -- helped by a network of investors called to arms through a companion Web site, eRaider.com.</p>
        <p>On April 27, the fund posted its first target on the site: Employee Solutions of Phoenix, a staff leasing firm in which the fund had acquired a 5 percent stake.</p>
        <p>The raid may already have had an effect on the company, according to Aaron Brown, president of Privateer Asset Management, which oversees both the fund and the Web site: On May 5, Employee Solutions announced that Quentin Smith, its president, chief executive and chairman, would relinquish the chairman's position. The move was one of several supported by Privateer, Mr. Brown said.</p>
        <p>The fund is also clamoring for changes to a management restructuring plan. And it wants a separate shareholder vote on a new contract for Mr. Smith.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for Employee Solutions, James Donnelly, declined to comment last week about the restructuring or the fund's campaign.</p>
        <p>The company, which had 1999 sales of $938.9 million, was once a hot stock. In 1996, it was rated as one of America's best small companies by Forbes magazine. Shares hit a weekly high of $28.375 in February 1997; they now are at 43 cents.</p>
        <p>Employee Solutions ran into problems because of skyrocketing workers' compensation rates and a growth-by-acquisition strategy that saddled it with debt. The current management took charge in 1998; by then, the shares had tumbled into penny-stock territory. It posted a loss of $56.1 million last year, and on April 20, its auditor said the company might not be able to continue as a going concern.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brown, who says he has been in discussions with Mr. Smith on the proposed restructuring, describes his dealings with Employee Solutions as amicable. ''They have treated us from the beginning as a large investor and someone who communicates honestly with shareholders,'' he said.</p>
        <p>One area of disagreement: According to Mr. Brown, management  would prefer to gain concessions from holders of the company's $85 million in debt, including forbearance on interest payments, and seek a capital injection from outside investors once its stock price has risen.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brown, for his part, said he would prefer raising capital now to extinguish the debt, even if it diluted the value of existing shares.</p>
        <p>Hal Diamond, an analyst at Standard &amp; Poor's, said the company ''is trying to reorganize its capital structure to avoid bankruptcy.'' S.&amp; P. has downgraded Employee Solutions' debt three times since August, to a D rating.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brown said he wants an independent party to render a fairness opinion on both the restructuring and Mr. Smith's contract -- and has not ruled out a proxy fight. He says he is  in contact with shareholders who -- together with his fund's position -- control about one-quarter of Employee Solutions' shares.</p>
        <p>Last Wednesday, Employee Solutions hired a new auditor, a move that Mr. Brown said would delay the introduction of the company's plan.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brown is upbeat about the raid. ''This has already been a success, because we've taken a process that was behind closed doors and we've made it transparent,'' he said. And he will continue to be busy: The fund, which is down 2.7 percent since its start, has investments in five other companies, whose identities it has not yet disclosed.</p>
        <p>INVESTING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
