<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sisterhood Is Powerful</title>
    <meta content="14OCONNT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199153"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="CHILDREN'S BOOKS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'Conner, Patricia T</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cole, Brock</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Buttons (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Columns/Children's Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E3D71F39F937A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="741" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sisterhood Is Powerful</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Patricia T. O'Conner</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">O'Conner, Patricia T</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Patricia T O'Conner reviews book Buttons by Brock Cole; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BUTTONS</p>
        <p>Written and illustrated by Brock Cole.</p>
        <p>Unpaged. New York:</p>
        <p>Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux. $16.</p>
        <p>(Ages 5 and up)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BUTTONS</p>
        <p>Written and illustrated by Brock Cole.</p>
        <p>Unpaged. New York:</p>
        <p>Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux. $16.</p>
        <p>(Ages 5 and up)</p>
        <p>In tall tales, siblings often come in threes, and of course they're as different as different can be. The three sisters in ''Buttons,'' Brock Cole's sumptuous picture book, are a clever beauty, a courageous warrior and a silly, impractical bubblehead. Guess who gets the family out of a jam?</p>
        <p>From the outset, the story's period (once upon a time), setting (quaint old village, possibly Dutch) and plot (highly unlikely) identify it as a fairy tale. In this case, the problem to be resolved is a sartorial one.</p>
        <p>Papa, a well-fed old burgher, is enjoying a between-meals snack when suddenly his britches burst and his buttons pop into the fire. His pants are undone and so, apparently, is the family, because he modestly takes to his bed until someone can figure out a way to replace the missing buttons.</p>
        <p>The sisters spring into action. The eldest dons her best gown and jewelry and sets out to snare a rich husband, presumably someone well provided with buttons. The second sister plans to dress as a boy and join the army, because a soldier's uniform has buttons to spare. The dimwitted third sister, who ''was young and rabbity and still picked her nose when she thought no one was looking,'' thinks and thinks and thinks. At last she comes up with a strategy: ''I will run in the meadows along the river, and I will hold my apron out so that if any buttons should fall from the sky, I will catch them before they get lost in the tall grass.''</p>
        <p>We know what will happen, naturally. Somehow the capable sisters will blow it and the ditzy one will save the day, even if buttons have to fall from the sky. Since fairy-tale quests usually involve romance too, each sister will fall in love along the way and live happily ever after.</p>
        <p>But familiarity is an asset in a fairy tale (sure enough, the sisters are a brunette, a blonde and a redhead), so the story's predictability makes it all the more satisfying. And the author's light-drenched watercolors are a feast in themselves, especially the luscious double-page spreads of village life, battle scenes, seascapes and countryside.</p>
        <p>Brock Cole, whose other picture books include ''The Giant's Toe'' and ''Alpha and the Dirty Baby,'' has also written novels for older children and young adults, including ''The Goats,'' an extraordinary book about an adolescent boy and girl who are humiliated and abandoned on a lonely island during a hazing incident at a summer camp. Even that dark and often disturbing novel reveals a certain fairy-tale sensibility. The characters in ''The Goats'' -- who, like those in ''Buttons,'' are mostly nameless -- are reminiscent of Hansel and Gretel as they wander deeper and deeper into the forest.</p>
        <p>''Buttons'' has its dark moments, too. A ''band of ruffians'' robs the eldest sister, and war breaks out just as the second sister joins the army, so she's ordered to the front. But the setbacks are benign, and turn out to be blessings in disguise.</p>
        <p>THE silliness quotient is high, even for a down-to-earth story with no special effects, like magic spells or supernatural gizmos. Take the issue of the buttons, for instance. We're shown a prosperous, well-dressed family, engaging in genteel pursuits like drawing and needlework amid a backdrop of tasteful interiors (potted palms, no less). Why does life come to a halt just because Papa loses a few buttons? He has only one pair of pants? And there aren't any spare buttons at all? Not even in Mama's sewing basket? Not even on the ''boy's rough jacket and leather britches'' that sister No. 2 puts on to join the army? Then why not buy a few, maybe by pawning sister No. 1's jewels?</p>
        <p>But this is, after all, a fairy tale. Silliness goes with the territory. And if you ask me, Papa set up the whole scheme to get those three grown daughters off his hands.</p>
        <p>CHILDREN'S BOOKS Patricia T. O'Conner is the author of ''Words Fail Me,'' a book about writing, and ''Woe Is I,'' a grammar guide.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Patricia T. O'Conner is the author of ''Words Fail Me,'' a book about writing, and ''Woe Is I,'' a grammar guide.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
