<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>PLAYING IN THE NEIGHBORHOOD</title>
    <meta content="14PLAY$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199408"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E0D9143BF937A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="677" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>PLAYING IN THE NEIGHBORHOOD</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREA DELBANCO</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SUNSET PARK  Chinese Exhibition Invites Visitors to Talk Back</p>
        <p>An exhibition that is family-oriented and hands-on, ''New Neighbors'' tells the story of Sunset Park's rapidly growing Chinese community. In this show at the Chinese Cultural School, ''story cards'' offer first-person accounts of recent immigrants, and visitors can tell their own stories on ''talk back'' cards.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SUNSET PARK  Chinese Exhibition Invites Visitors to Talk Back</p>
        <p>An exhibition that is family-oriented and hands-on, ''New Neighbors'' tells the story of Sunset Park's rapidly growing Chinese community. In this show at the Chinese Cultural School, ''story cards'' offer first-person accounts of recent immigrants, and visitors can tell their own stories on ''talk back'' cards.</p>
        <p>There will also be a display in which Chinese phrases are spoken in the four dialects most commonly used in Sunset Park. An audio theater production about a family in Sunset Park based on oral histories will be told in both Chinese and English.</p>
        <p>''Bat Dai Do/New Neighbors: Sunset Park's Chinese Community''; Mondays through Fridays 2 p.m. to 5 p.m.; Brooklyn Chinese-American Association, Chinese Cultural School, 5002 Eighth Avenue, between 50th and 51st Streets, Brooklyn; free; (718) 254-9830.</p>
        <p>CHELSEA  From Market to Modern: Neighborhood Regeneration</p>
        <p>Years ago in Chelsea, a farmer brought her pig to market in what is now a gallery, and a woman sold newspapers on a corner where people now get cash from an A.T.M. Visitors can witness a live intersection of the past and present in ''Night Light,'' in which Ann Carlson, a choreographer and performer, will transform Chelsea into a living stage.</p>
        <p>Performers recreate scenes like those above from archival photographs in the locations they were originally taken, including a recreation of the picture shown below, which was taken of a Turkish bath on 23rd Street in 1904.</p>
        <p>Walking tours will wind through churches, gardens, apartments and back alleys to view the performance photos. Ms. Carlson said, ''It is my hope that this archaeology of a neighborhood creates a structure for the viewer to reflect on the past while providing the space to contemplate a vision for the future.''</p>
        <p>''Night Light''; Wednesday through Saturday and May 24 through May 27, 8 p.m.; call box office weekdays 2 p.m. to 6 p.m. for location information and tickets, $15, students and people over 65, $10; (212) 255-5793, ext. 11.</p>
        <p>MIDTOWN  A Perfect City Marriage: Photos and Eavesdropping</p>
        <p>''I am so late that I don't show up'' and ''My travel agent died; I don't know where to go anymore'' are among the phrases captured by Judith Henry, artist and eavesdroper.</p>
        <p>Her work ''Overheard in New York'' consists of sentences she has overheard on the streets of the city over the last 15 years. In three Fifth Avenue windows at Bergdorf Goodman, each measuring 20 feet by 10 feet, 500 quotes will be interspersed with 500 of her black and white photographs of New York street scenes in a grid of 10-inch squares like the ones shown above. The effect is a colorful checkerboard pattern.</p>
        <p>''I'm an eavesdropper,'' Ms. Henry said, ''so for me, New York is heaven.'' She added, ''When privacy can't be achieved by physical distance, just pretend no one's listening. But people are, especially me.''</p>
        <p>''Overheard in New York''; tomorrow through June 1; Bergdorf Goodman, the Fifth Avenue windows at 57th Street; free; (212) 753-7300.</p>
        <p>Also Around Town</p>
        <p>DOG DAY -- At ''Paws Walk 2000'' dogs can compete in Frisbee catching and a pet-owner look-alike event; a dog with personality will win a workshop with Bashkim Dibra, dog trainer; the Queens stop of this five-borough event is Saturday 11 a.m. to 3 p.m.; Flushing Meadows-Corona Park, ball field No. 1; $15; registration begins at the gate at 9:45 a.m.; the Manhattan event will be June 3 in Central Park; to pre-register, (718) 601-1460.</p>
        <p>GARDEN GUARDS -- Gardeners dressed as pea pods and 15-foot floral puppets will act as guardians of gardens at the 10th annual ''Earth Celebrations' Rites of Spring: Procession to Save Our Gardens,'' Saturday 10 a.m. to 6 p.m.; begins at Forsyth Street between Broome and Delancey; free; (212) 777-7969.</p>
        <p>MUSIC HONOR -- The Manhattan Virtuosi will perform a memorial concert in honor of the conductor Natan Rakhlin; the program will include works by Bach, Tchaikovsky and Berlioz; today 3 p.m.; Great Hall at Cooper Union, 7 East Seventh Street, at Third Avenue; $15; students and people over 65, $10; (212) 866-2958.</p>
        <p>ANDREA DELBANCO</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
