<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From Ireland, A Palette That's Dark Yet Humane</title>
    <meta content="14FRIC$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199250"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Island: Arts From Ireland Festival</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fricker, Karen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carr, Marina</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kelly, Cara</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hickey, Tom</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">On Raftery's Hill (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E0D71138F937A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1749" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From Ireland, A Palette That's Dark Yet Humane</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KAREN FRICKER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fricker, Karen</byline>
      <dateline>GALWAY, Ireland</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Karen Fricker article on Marina Carr, perhaps foremost female dramatist of Ireland, focuses on her play On Raftery's Hill, which will be performed as part of Island: Arts From Ireland festival at Kennedy Center in Washington; production stars Tom Hickey and Cara Kelly; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>OUTSIDERS who might think of the rural Irish as an innocent and fun-loving people have very likely never encountered the plays of Marina Carr, perhaps the foremost female dramatist  in Ireland today. Her deeply troubled characters inhabit a fallen paradise.</p>
        <p>Ms. Carr's darkly lyrical family tragedies are written in the dialect of the Midlands region, halfway between Dublin and Galway, where they are set, an area that people even within Ireland tend to overlook. Her characters love too much and too deeply; they reject the roles that society assigns them; they curse and are cursed; they fight and they kill.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>OUTSIDERS who might think of the rural Irish as an innocent and fun-loving people have very likely never encountered the plays of Marina Carr, perhaps the foremost female dramatist  in Ireland today. Her deeply troubled characters inhabit a fallen paradise.</p>
        <p>Ms. Carr's darkly lyrical family tragedies are written in the dialect of the Midlands region, halfway between Dublin and Galway, where they are set, an area that people even within Ireland tend to overlook. Her characters love too much and too deeply; they reject the roles that society assigns them; they curse and are cursed; they fight and they kill.</p>
        <p>And yet for all their darkness, Ms. Carr's plays reveal a vivid sense of black comedy and poetic turns of phrase. A character in her latest work, ''On Raftery's Hill,'' calls his depressive father ''one sad picnic in the rain''; another remembers a particularly cold season: ''That was a winter put manners on lovers, the whole mountain and valley courtin' with gloves on.''</p>
        <p>American audiences will have a chance to see a home-grown production of ''On Raftery's Hill'' in Washington this week. It is part of the ''Island: Arts From Ireland'' festival at the Kennedy Center, which began yesterday and which includes theater, music, dance, the visual arts and film. The theater segment, running from Wednesday through May 27, involves two other plays: ''Catalpa,'' a solo show written and performed by Donal O'Kelly, about a 19th-century sea captain's voyage to rescue Irish prisoners from Australia; and ''Pentecost,'' set in 1974 Belfast during a Protestant workers' strike and written by the late Northern Irish playwright Stewart Parker.</p>
        <p>Two earlier plays by Ms. Carr, ''The Mai'' and ''Portia Coughlin,'' have been well-received at the McCarter Theater in Princeton, N.J. But ''On Raftery's Hill'' is so new that it had its world premiere this past Tuesday at the Town Hall Theater here. A co-production of the Druid Theater Company in Galway and the Royal Court Theater in London, it will be presented at the Kennedy Center's Eisenhower Theater from Thursday through next Sunday. The director is Garry Hynes, the artistic chief of the Druid company.</p>
        <p>Ms. Hynes has, she said, ''been close to Marina's writing from the beginning.'' She commissioned ''The Mai'' during her stint as artistic director of the Abbey Theater in the early 1990's and directed the world premiere of ''Portia Coughlin'' in 1996. Ms. Hynes was the first woman to win a Tony Award for directing a play on Broadway, winning for Martin McDonagh's ''Beauty Queen of Leenane,'' which also had its world premiere here.</p>
        <p>Speaking of Ms. Carr, Ms. Hynes said: ''Marina has returned again and again to the family, to that central unit by which we organize our society, and has challenged how it works. What she's doing is extremely courageous. It has an extraordinary, terrible beauty.''</p>
        <p>Joyce McMillan, a theater critic for The Scotsman in Edinburgh, said of Ms. Carr's work: ''I am not aware of another woman who writes about tragedy with such grandeur. She goes to a deep place that has not just to do with society now but that touches an inner tragedy of existence. The female quality of her writing comes through not only in the way she writes about women, it's in the physicality in her writing. She is right in there with the cycles of life, with the blood and the dirt.''</p>
        <p>Where does Ms. Carr's dystopian vision come from? The last person to offer easy answers is the writer herself. A sweet-faced, quiet-spoken 35-year-old, Ms. Carr is quite uninterested in explaining her plays or the impulses behind them. She rarely gives interviews and prefers not to discuss her private life. ''My plays are not autobiographical,'' she said gently (twice) during a recent conversation in the Druid offices here.</p>
        <p>The general details of Ms. Carr's life, however, are known in Ireland. She was born in the romantic-sounding village of Pallas Lake in County Offaly, in the Midlands. Her parents both had literary interests and wrote part time; her father wrote plays and her mother poems in the Irish language. ''Everyone in the house was always writing,'' she told an audience at a recent reading in Galway. Ms. Carr left when she was 18 for college in Dublin, where she still lives. She is married and expecting her second child in June.</p>
        <p>One subject that Ms. Carr will discuss is current affairs, particularly a troubling strain of racism that has recently emerged in Ireland as the country struggles to cope with an influx of refugees and asylum seekers from Eastern Europe and Africa. One of the attractions for immigrants may be the current economic boom in Ireland.</p>
        <p>Speaking of the new arrivals, Ms. Carr said: ''These people come here desiring a better life in another country, and they have every right to try for that. Our grandparents and other generations emigrated from Ireland and suffered the same kind of prejudice abroad. This fear that the Irish are now expressing, it's about recognizing yourself in the mirror. The savage rises in people; it's dark, the cruelty that's there, 20 centuries of civilization flying off.''</p>
        <p>It may be this ability to identify, articulate and yet not judge the negative side of the human spirit -- particularly in an Irish context -- that gives Ms. Carr her distinctive voice. Her first three mature plays -- ''The Mai,''  ''Portia Coughlin'' and ''By the Bog of Cats'' (which won the Irish Theater Award for best play last year) -- involve female characters at the extremes of existence. Not surprisingly, most critical comment about her work has focused on her depictions of women and the feminist tone of her writing.</p>
        <p>''On Raftery's Hill'' seems poised to shift the debate to where, perhaps,  it has belonged all along: Ms. Carr's troubling portraits of Irish families.</p>
        <p>Ms. Hynes has said that Ms. Carr's depictions of dysfunctional families make her a worthy descendant of the great Irish-American playwright Eugene O'Neill. The director is not the first to do so. In 1994, the critic Michael Coveney, writing in The Observer in London about the play ''The Mai,'' said that its author ''articulates deep-seated woes and resentments in a manner you rarely find outside Eugene O'Neill.''</p>
        <p>As with her previous plays, Ms. Carr sets ''On Raftery's Hill'' among an extended family in the contemporary Midlands. The central figure is the patriarch Red Raftery. The play concerns his troubled relationships with his two daughters, the 40-year-old Dinah and the 20-ish Sorrel. It is clear from the earliest moments that something is awry in the Raftery world: the neglected family farm is covered with the rotting corpses of cows and sheep, the slow-witted son, Ded, sleeps in the barn, and the grandmother, Shalome, repeatedly tries to leave the house to seek her long-dead father.</p>
        <p>The audience eventually discovers  secrets that the family is desperately engaged in avoiding, including the fact that Red and Dinah are incestuously involved.</p>
        <p>Ms. Carr is confronting the issue of incest in an unusually forthright way on the Irish stage; while previous plays in the 1980's and 1990's, including Ms. Carr's own ''Portia Coughlin,'' have hinted at sexual relations among family members, ''On Raftery's Hill'' makes the subject its central theme.</p>
        <p>''The play reflects an increasing awareness of an issue that as recently as the 1980's did not officially exist in public discourse,'' said Kieran McGrath, editor of The Irish Social Worker, a quarterly professional journal.</p>
        <p>''There was a culture of secrecy in the past,'' Mr. McGrath said. ''But in the 1990's there have been several high-profile court cases that have brought the issue to light. And out of the woodwork started to come some serious situations, like the one depicted in this play: deeply enmeshed families, where sex abuse is longstanding and rampant.''</p>
        <p>The playwright, however, does not condemn her characters. ''I like Red Raftery,'' she said. '''I know people might find that difficult, but I do. He may not have much humanity, but it's there. His humanity is that he realizes he's bad. He realizes he's fallen. He realizes he's got it all wrong. The inhuman impulses are struggling alongside the impulse to be humane.''</p>
        <p>While there is an implication that the cycles of incest go back for generations and that the family members are thus governed by forces larger than themselves, Ms. Carr said she does not want to create a world in which ''you remove responsibility from the individual.''</p>
        <p>''There is a point where a woman is responsible,'' she said. ''Dinah is not a victim anymore. She may have been when she was younger but she is no longer. She is in the thick of it, too. They are all implicated. The idea of the monster coming out of the vacuum I just don't buy.''</p>
        <p>Red asks Sorrel's suitor in ''On Raftery's Hill'': ''D'ya know whah ud manes to be young . . .? Do ya? Manes your slate is clane, manes the muck on your boots stays on your boots and dont sape up to your unploughed soul. Manes ya know . . . all abouh the dirty world, how and why men and women fall.''</p>
        <p>Two Weeks of Arts From the Emerald Isle</p>
        <p>THE 15-day ''Island: Arts From Ireland'' festival at the John F. Kennedy Center for the Performing Arts in Washington continues through May 28 with a variety of events. Among them are:</p>
        <p>Tomorrow at 6 p.m.:</p>
        <p>''Atlantic Voices -- Prose Writers From Ireland and America'': William Kennedy and Frank McCourt are among the speakers. Theater Lab.</p>
        <p>Wednesday at 8:30 p.m.:</p>
        <p>''The Poet and the Piper'': The poet Seamus Heaney and the traditional piper Liam O'Flynn join forces in a program of poems and airs. Concert Hall.</p>
        <p>Wednesday-next Sunday:</p>
        <p>''Catalpa,'' a one-man play presented by the Red Kettle Theater Company of Waterford and Andrews Lane Theater of Dublin. AFI Theater.</p>
        <p>Thursday-next Sunday:</p>
        <p>''On Raftery's Hill,'' a play by Marina Carr. Eisenhower Theater.</p>
        <p>Friday at 7:30 p.m.:</p>
        <p>The Irish Chamber Orchestra in a world premiere by Bill Whelan, the composer of the music for ''Riverdance.'' Terrace Theater.</p>
        <p>May 22-28:</p>
        <p>''Irish Film'': Screenings of documentaries, animated shorts and features. AFI Theater.</p>
        <p>May 23-27:</p>
        <p>''Pentecost,'' a play presented by the Rough Magic Theater Company of Dublin. Terrace Theater.</p>
        <p>Information:</p>
        <p>Telephone: (800) 444-1324.</p>
        <p>Web site: kennedy-center.org /irishfestival</p>
        <p>THEATER Karen Fricker is an American theater critic who lives in Dublin.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Karen Fricker is an American theater critic who lives in Dublin.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
