<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Parking Lot Will Intrude On a Nature Trail at Pace</title>
    <meta content="14PACE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199284"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ENVIRONMENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parking Garages and Lots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pace University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rosenberg, Merri</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E5DA1F38F937A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="490" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Parking Lot Will Intrude On a Nature Trail at Pace</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MERRI ROSENBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rosenberg, Merri</byline>
      <dateline>PLEASANTVILLE</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pace University officials reach compromise with faculty members that will scale back plans to raze woodlands and meadows near environmental center's nature trail for parking lot; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT'S not majestic, nor even particularly scenic as such things go, but it is possible to stroll along the scrubby outer edges of the nature trail here at Pace University and imagine that you are in a rural retreat rather than an otherwise manicured suburban campus.</p>
        <p>Granted, the environmental center's nature trail may not be paradise. Still, a recent decision by the university to convert about half of the quarter-mile nature trail to a parking lot comes close to the Joni Mitchell lament that ''They paved paradise and put up a parking lot.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT'S not majestic, nor even particularly scenic as such things go, but it is possible to stroll along the scrubby outer edges of the nature trail here at Pace University and imagine that you are in a rural retreat rather than an otherwise manicured suburban campus.</p>
        <p>Granted, the environmental center's nature trail may not be paradise. Still, a recent decision by the university to convert about half of the quarter-mile nature trail to a parking lot comes close to the Joni Mitchell lament that ''They paved paradise and put up a parking lot.''</p>
        <p>This corner of the campus is a beloved landmark where generations of the county's schoolchildren and, in the summer, campers have taken part in outdoor activities. It is close to the university's environmental center, where a farm menagerie, including goats and donkeys, welcomes visitors.</p>
        <p>For Caroline Crowley of nearby Ossining, who had brought her young son, Jimmy, and one of his friends to see the animals, it was a good outing. ''We had wanted to go to the Bronx Zoo, but we came here instead,'' said Mrs. Crowley, who mentioned that her father-in-law, as a Pace alumnus, frequently took her son to the nature trail and environmental center for a low-key excursion.</p>
        <p>With Pace's need to build a new health and fitness center -- although on the other side of the campus -- the university had to come up with additional parking, said Michael Roberts, chairman of the biology department, which oversees the environmental center.</p>
        <p>''The parking is not for the fitness center,'' Dr. Roberts said. ''We just need the parking spaces.''</p>
        <p>The university has scaled back from its original proposal, which Joe Checco, an environmental studies major and president of the environmental club, said would have taken away more woodlands and meadows.</p>
        <p>Concerns about that plan were voiced by members of the environmental science department and others at Pace, leading to a meeting earlier this month and a compromise.</p>
        <p>''The original plan would have obliterated the entire meadow area,'' Dr. Roberts said. ''Now it eliminates one extreme end of the nature trails. In terms of the environmental center, it won't be affected.''</p>
        <p>Leonard Sippel, treasurer and executive vice president for finance and administration at Pace, added: ''We're trying to solve the parking problem and address issues of the environment. We do have lots of open land and woodlands around campus and are trying to preserve open space. We'll be building the parking, but until the town of Mount Pleasant approves the site plan, we can't do anything.''</p>
        <p>While pleased that the administration has pared down its plans, Mr. Checco still has concerns.</p>
        <p>''This is our outdoor classroom,'' he said. ''We'd rather not see any of it impacted.''</p>
        <p>And he warned, ''I'll still be going to town meetings and holding the administration to their word.''</p>
        <p>ENVIRONMENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
