<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Fed, in a Supporting Role for the Euro</title>
    <meta content="14PORT$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000521T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199481"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PORTFOLIOS, ETC."/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Currency</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Foreign Investments</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Reserve System</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fuerbringer, Jonathan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Portfolios Etc</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Investments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Currency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06EEDB153BF937A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="772" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Fed, in a Supporting Role for the Euro</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN FUERBRINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fuerbringer, Jonathan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jonathan Fuerbringer column on outlook for euro and investing in European stocks; holds Federal Reserve interest rate increases could help boost euro if Fed seems to be succeeding in slowing United States economic growth; notes improvement in euro would make European stocks more valuable in dollar terms; graph of rise in Federal funds target rate and drop in value of euro (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE European Central Bank has not been the best friend of the beleaguered euro over its 16 1/2-month life. The confusing signals that bank officials have sent about the euro, the unified currency of 11 European nations, have clearly contributed to its 21 percent decline against the dollar.</p>
        <p>And while hints of European Central Bank intervention to support the euro helped it rally last week, to 91.96 cents as of Friday, it remains near its record low of 89.48 cents, reached on May 3. Several American currency analysts still expect the euro to fall as low as 85 cents.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE European Central Bank has not been the best friend of the beleaguered euro over its 16 1/2-month life. The confusing signals that bank officials have sent about the euro, the unified currency of 11 European nations, have clearly contributed to its 21 percent decline against the dollar.</p>
        <p>And while hints of European Central Bank intervention to support the euro helped it rally last week, to 91.96 cents as of Friday, it remains near its record low of 89.48 cents, reached on May 3. Several American currency analysts still expect the euro to fall as low as 85 cents.</p>
        <p>So where can Europeans turn for help? Try the United States Federal Reserve, whose policy makers on Tuesday are expected to raise their short-term interest rate target for the sixth time since last June. The only debate is whether the rate increase will be a quarter of a percentage point, like the previous five, or a half-point, in response to recent signs of inflationary pressure.</p>
        <p>How could Fed action help Europe?</p>
        <p>There are several possible scripts, some of which have the euro continuing to fall -- and the dollar continuing to rise -- in the near term. But longer term, if it finally becomes clear that the Fed is not only determined to slow the American economy but that it is also accomplishing that goal, then the dollar will lose its lift against the euro. And that is important for American investors who have bet on European stocks. The euro's plunge this year has turned almost all of Europe's stock market gains to minuses for American investors.</p>
        <p>One possibility is probably best for the euro: a half-point increase in interest rates by the Fed. That would help cement the view that the Fed will not stop raising rates until the annual pace of economic growth slows in the United States from the 5 percent pace of the last four quarters to something closer to 3 or 3.5 percent.</p>
        <p>The Fed could underline that message with a statement that ''the risks are weighted mainly toward conditions that may generate heightened inflation pressures in the foreseeable future.'' In fact, those words were included with the announcement of the quarter-point increase in March. Repeating it would signal that there are more rate increases to come.</p>
        <p>Adding to the market tension on Tuesday will be the government report on the Consumer Price Index for April. It was the unexpected March jump of 0.4 percent in the core index, which excludes food and energy, that raised the specter of a more aggressive Fed. Another high number would increase inflation fears, making investors even more leery of future rate increases.</p>
        <p>Karen E. Parker, director of currency research at Chase Securities, said a high consumer price number and a half-point rate increase would suggest that the United States economy was headed for a hard landing -- and equities would take a hit. Further stock market declines could help break the confidence of European investors in the American market, meaning they would sell American stocks and convert their dollars back to euros.</p>
        <p>In the longer term, the slowing of growth in the United States, in comparison with Europe, is what will weaken the dollar and strengthen the euro. ''More convincing than ever is the notion that the United States economy is going to slow,'' said James McCormick, currency strategist at J. P. Morgan Securities. ''If the Fed goes half a percentage point and comes up with a strong statement, that is telling you that the growth is going to slow.''</p>
        <p>That does not mean the euro will turn on a dime. Mr. McCormick expects the euro to fall to 86 cents, because direct European investment in the United States is strong, and there are no sure signs yet that the American economy is slowing. The 0.2 percent downturn in retail sales in April, the first decline since August 1998, buoyed some equity investors. But one month's numbers do not a trend make.</p>
        <p>Still, an American investor who believes that the euro can turn in the months ahead would do well to buy European stocks now -- they are cheaper when the dollar is stronger -- and then get the benefit when the euro rallies, making European stocks more valuable in dollar terms.</p>
        <p>PORTFOLIOS, ETC.  Correction:  May 21, 2000, Sunday  A chart last Sunday with the Portfolios, Etc. column, about the prospects for the euro amid rising interest rates in the United States, carried an incorrect scale label. Figures charted for the euro's value were expressed in dollars to the euro, not the reverse.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 21, 2000, Sunday</p>
        <p>A chart last Sunday with the Portfolios, Etc. column, about the prospects for the euro amid rising interest rates in the United States, carried an incorrect scale label. Figures charted for the euro's value were expressed in dollars to the euro, not the reverse.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
