<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nashville Is Going Up-Tempo</title>
    <meta content="NASH.$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199188"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="AMERICAN CITIES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Nashville (Tenn)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Strauss, Neil</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Tennessee/Nashville</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Tennessee</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E6D91338F937A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2522" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nashville Is Going Up-Tempo</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NEIL STRAUSS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Strauss, Neil</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Neil Strauss article on Nashville's country music scene and other attractions; photos; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ON arriving in downtown Nashville, look up. You will see the city's future looming overhead as cranes duck and pivot in the sky above the gleaming scaffolds of a dozen works in progress. There is no better time to be a construction worker: there's a new arena and stadium for the professional teams that have been imported, a sports hall of fame, a giant consumer complex on a par with the Mall of America; and, still under construction, a speedway, a new zoo, a downtown pedestrian bridge across the Cumberland River, a massive office complex with an eye-catching traffic circle with a $2 million sculpture, luxury hotels like the Marriott, Hilton Suites, Embassy Suites and possibly a Ritz-Carlton, an art gallery, and a Country Music Hall of Fame that resembles a piano (not the first instrument one associates with the genre). With the metropolitan area population having just surpassed one million, Nashville is booming.</p>
        <p>But there is another side to Nashville: its past. Yesterday's Nashville, the one Tom T. Hall sang about in ''Nashville Is a Groovy Little Town,'' lies on a scrap heap. Many of the city's oldest, quaintest attractions are either moving or closing or have already been leveled. For the country music tourist, not much in the guidebook still exists: recent years have seen the closing of the Hank Williams Jr. Museum, the House of Cash (as in Johnny), Twitty City (as in Conway), Barbara Mandrell Country, the Country Music Wax Museum and the Opryland amusement park. Even less kitschy places of note, like a house where Hank Williams is said to have lived, have been torn down -- all victims of Nashville's march toward modernity.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ON arriving in downtown Nashville, look up. You will see the city's future looming overhead as cranes duck and pivot in the sky above the gleaming scaffolds of a dozen works in progress. There is no better time to be a construction worker: there's a new arena and stadium for the professional teams that have been imported, a sports hall of fame, a giant consumer complex on a par with the Mall of America; and, still under construction, a speedway, a new zoo, a downtown pedestrian bridge across the Cumberland River, a massive office complex with an eye-catching traffic circle with a $2 million sculpture, luxury hotels like the Marriott, Hilton Suites, Embassy Suites and possibly a Ritz-Carlton, an art gallery, and a Country Music Hall of Fame that resembles a piano (not the first instrument one associates with the genre). With the metropolitan area population having just surpassed one million, Nashville is booming.</p>
        <p>But there is another side to Nashville: its past. Yesterday's Nashville, the one Tom T. Hall sang about in ''Nashville Is a Groovy Little Town,'' lies on a scrap heap. Many of the city's oldest, quaintest attractions are either moving or closing or have already been leveled. For the country music tourist, not much in the guidebook still exists: recent years have seen the closing of the Hank Williams Jr. Museum, the House of Cash (as in Johnny), Twitty City (as in Conway), Barbara Mandrell Country, the Country Music Wax Museum and the Opryland amusement park. Even less kitschy places of note, like a house where Hank Williams is said to have lived, have been torn down -- all victims of Nashville's march toward modernity.</p>
        <p>The authentic attractions that remain, like the legendary honky-tonks on Lower Broadway, not only have to compete with Planet Hollywood and the Hard Rock Cafe but are also being targeted by the police, who have been citing them for noise violations.</p>
        <p>All of this is one reason why Nashville is in a tourism slump, with 15 percent fewer visitors over the past two summers. Wait until 2001 to visit, city officials say, when the Opry Mills shopping center (scheduled to open this past week), the enormous Frist Center for the Visual Arts, the new Country Music Hall of Fame, the Tennessee Sports Hall of Fame, the zoo and the big new hotels are up and running.</p>
        <p>But who goes to Nashville for fine arts, elephants and mall shopping? Despite appearances, now may be one of the best times to visit, while it is in the throes of its personality crisis. With health care ahead of country music as the city's biggest revenue generator and Dell Computer moving part of its facilities to town, there are two Nashvilles to see: the country and the corporate. And then there is the friction that occurs when new and old coexist, butting heads on every street corner. The traditional, the quaint, the country may be harder to find now that the city is trying to attract convention business (while ceding kitschier attractions to Pigeon Forge, Tenn., and Branson, Mo.). But it still exists. You just have to know where to go.</p>
        <p>Take, for example, the Longhorn Steakhouse. This is not a restaurant written up in guidebooks as a great meal, nor by any means a stop on the itinerary of most tourists. Yet step inside and enter another world, where almost every person in every chair is a songwriter or a musician with a tale to tell. During a meal on a recent five-day trip to Nashville, I turned to talk to two men sitting behind me at a bar overlooking the packed dining room, which resonated with talk of publishing deals, royalty checks and recording sessions. A man with long gray hair, who introduced himself as Earl Bud Lee, wrote one of Garth Brooks's biggest hits, ''Friends in Low Places.''</p>
        <p>His shorter, black-haired friend, Boris, was French and had never been to the United States before, yet he spoke with a Southern accent. He explained that this was because he was a musician in a country-and-western saloon at Euro Disney. He was in town to write songs with Mr. Lee.</p>
        <p>''This is like a hub, a watering hole,'' Mr. Lee said. ''I've been coming here for 20 years. I ran up a $1,200 bar tab here once and was going to be put in jail because I didn't have enough money to pay it. I had just written 'Friends In Low Places,' so out of desperation I sold it to three publishers, who each paid me $400 so I could pay my bar tab. The song went on to make millions of dollars, and I didn't see any of it.''</p>
        <p>The Longhorn occupies one corner of a triangle that any country hopeful in Nashville knows only too well, with the Quality Inn Hall of Fame Lounge and a Shoney's marking the other points. The triangle crowns the area known as Music Row -- two streets along which almost every record label, publisher and Internet music company has an office.</p>
        <p>While music row has been modernizing, with quaint offices in houses giving way to towering steel-and-glass structures, the ambition surrounding it remains unchanged. Step into the restaurants in the afternoon, and the bar any night, and you will find the soul of Nashville: its dreamers. Some have been holding fast to a waning country fantasy for decades, others are new in town with rhinestone stars in their eyes, and still others have realized their dreams only to find themselves living a nightmare. At least half a dozen characters I met admitted to having been homeless after arriving in town, sleeping in the parking lot at Shoney's or in dumpsters on Music Row while trying to make it in the Hollywood of the South.</p>
        <p>Country-music aficionados often complain about an ever-widening gap between the traditional and the new, between the country charm of Loretta Lynn and the urban sophistication of Shania Twain. Similarly, Nashville itself is split between old country and new country, between the small-town and the cosmopolitan.</p>
        <p>For an old-country night out, I watched the aspirants at the Hall of Fame lounge and the Broken Spoke, a complex in a Ramada Inn consisting of a bar and a songwriters' cafe. Afterward, I went on a honky-tonk hop downtown on Lower Broadway. Though the area is becoming increasingly touristy, high-quality music could still be found at Robert's Western Wear (particularly when the band Brazilbilly is performing), at Tootsie's, and at Legends Corner, where one of the most exciting new voices to emerge in Nashville is that of an 11-year-old English girl named Sammie Jay. Pete Fisher, the director of the Grand Ole Opry, said that on first hearing her perform, he invited her to sing on the Opry that night. Also essential to visit are the bluegrass club the Station Inn and the famous but uptight songwriters' showcase, the Bluebird Cafe.</p>
        <p>There is, however, a certain stratum in Nashville who wouldn't be caught dead at Tootsie's or the Broken Spoke. They are the harbingers of new country, who hang out not at music bars but at more chic night spots where the music is piped in and not just country. These are clustered several miles west of Music Row near a strip of shops known as Hillsboro Village (most famously home to the jam-packed breakfast spot the Pancake Pantry and the tool shop Honky-Tonk Hardware, which often features music on weekends). Walking into the Trace feels like stepping into a dimly lighted Los Angeles lounge. Whereas paying your dues at  the Hall of Fame Lounge means playing five nights a week for little or no money, paying your dues at the Trace means flirting with executives, managers and producers. Whereas cowboy hats and tight jeans are de rigueur at old country haunts, at the Trace and the Sunset Grill across the street, tight black dresses and button-down designer shirts are the norm.</p>
        <p>These places are reminders that Nashville is a mid-South city that has always looked elsewhere for a more cosmopolitan identity: to Los Angeles, Atlanta, New York and beyond. Its most famous landmark is a full-scale replica of the Parthenon first built in 1897 (and covered in scaffolding at the moment). It was inspired by the city's misleading nickname: the Athens of the South. Even today, the Nashville Convention and Visitors Bureau has earmarked $4 million for advertising to play down the city's music image in favor of pitching it as a cultural capital, like a Southern Manhattan. What they don't realize is that there already is a Manhattan and an Athens, but people like Boris need a Nashville. (Perhaps it is not a coincidence that as Nashville's tourism has slumped, so have country music sales.)</p>
        <p>The split in Nashville between the country and the cosmopolitan (or, as the studio productions of Chet Atkins were called four decades ago, the countrypolitan) extends beyond the night life. It's also in the food. One can eat some of the South's finest home-cooking at the family-style restaurant Monell's, the lunchroom cafeteria Arnold's, the meat-and-three restaurant Rotier's, the curt-and-friendly Pie Wagon, or the old-fashioned Belle Meade Cafeteria. But at the same time, Nashville is home to upscale restaurants like the Wild Boar, and hip fusion food has arrived, as has stuffy service. I prefer the old country places. At my first meal at Arnold's, where the gravy is so good you could eat it with a soup spoon, I arrived at the counter only to discover that I had left my wallet at the hotel. ''That's O.K.,'' the woman at the counter said, ''you can pay us next time.''</p>
        <p>Many in Nashville fear that this small-town trust is disappearing as the city turns into a clone of its northern and eastern neighbors. But it just may be the New Yorkers who save Nashville. Many have moved into the city with visions of George Jones, Hank Williams, Patsy Cline and Merle Haggard dancing in their heads. And when Nashville doesn't meet their country fantasy, they often end up creating it (or sometimes subverting it, as do Nashville's first out gay country duo, Y'all, two Manhattan transplants).</p>
        <p>''They're embarrassed about all the things that I moved down here for,'' said Katy K of Nashville's city planners. An ex-New Yorker, she moved to Nashville and started my favorite clothing store in the area, Katy K's Ranch Dressing, where 60's suits designed by Nudie the Rodeo Tailor and shirts by the clothier-cum-cult-leader Tony Alamo can often be found.</p>
        <p>Claire Mullally, another ex-New Yorker, opened an ice cream stand just a few weeks ago. Abandoning her law practice, she now scoops ice cream at Bobbie's Dairy Dip, a 1950's stand that she bought when she saw a for-sale sign there. The place is a flashback, with kids celebrating birthdays outside and everyone from businesswomen to construction workers waiting for ice cream.</p>
        <p>Many tourists never make it into the city: they are shuttled away to an artificial neighborhood on the outskirts known as Music Valley, home to the passionless and immense Opryland Hotel and the relocated Grand Ole Opry, perhaps the best place to see old and new country come together on neutral ground. The live radio and TV show begins celebrating its 75th anniversary in June, with free outdoor concerts and other events that its director, Mr. Fisher, said he hoped would ease Nashville's ''transition into a new destination.''</p>
        <p>Though the Grand Ole Opry may be the most enduring symbol of Nashville for many tourists, I have my own, at the Country Music Hall of Fame, a barn-shaped cinder block building at the head of Music Row. (It moves to its piano-shaped home next May.) It is the car belonging to the 50's honky-tonk star Webb Pierce. A customized Bonneville convertible, it features rifles and pistols mounted on the hood, trunk, sides and interior (even serving as door handles); horseshoes and saddles in place of normal pedals and the center console; and hundreds of silver dollars fastened all over the interior. At once over-the-top tacky and breathtakingly charming, a car that was once comfortable cruising the streets of old Nashville, it would look sadly out of place in the revitalized downtown that city planners hope will spring from country music's ashes next year.</p>
        <p>Where to go, what to see</p>
        <p>Music</p>
        <p>Bluebird Cafe, 4104 Hillsboro Road; (615) 383-1461. Mike Henderson and the Bluebloods perform every Monday; songwriter showcases Tuesday to Saturday at 9:30 p.m.</p>
        <p>The Broken Spoke, 1412 Brick Church Pike; (615) 262-7524.</p>
        <p>Grand Ole Opry, 2804 Opryland Drive; (615) 889-6611. Shows Friday and Saturday nights. Tickets $22.50 and $20.50.</p>
        <p>Honky-Tonk Hardware, 1818 21st Avenue South; (615) 383-2840.</p>
        <p>Legends Corner, 428 Broadway; (615) 248-6334.</p>
        <p>Quality Inn Hall of Fame Lounge, 1407 Division Street; (615) 242-0800.</p>
        <p>Robert's Western Wear, 416 Broadway; (615) 256-7937.</p>
        <p>Station Inn, 402 12th Avenue South; (615) 255-3307.</p>
        <p>Sunset Grill, 2001 Belcourt Avenue; (615) 386-3663.</p>
        <p>Tootsie's Orchid Lounge, 422 Broadway; (615) 726-0463.</p>
        <p>The Trace, 2000 Belcourt Avenue; (615) 385-2200.</p>
        <p>Food</p>
        <p>Arnold's, 605 Eighth Avenue South; (615) 256-4455.</p>
        <p>Belle Meade Cafeteria, 4534 Harding Road; (615) 298-5571.</p>
        <p>Bobbie's Dairy Dip, corner of Charlotte Avenue and 53rd Street; (615) 292-2112.</p>
        <p>Brown's Diner, 2102 Blair Boulevard; (615) 269-5509.</p>
        <p>Longhorn Steakhouse, 110 Lyle Avenue; (615) 329-9195.</p>
        <p>Monell's, 1235 Sixth Avenue North; (615) 248-4747.</p>
        <p>Pancake Pantry, 1796 21st Avenue South; (615) 383-9333.</p>
        <p>Rotier's, 2413 Elliston Place; (615) 327-9892.</p>
        <p>Shoney's Inn and Restaurant, 1521 Demonbreun Street; (615) 244-2243.</p>
        <p>The Wild Boar, 2014 Broadway; (615) 329-1313.</p>
        <p>Attractions</p>
        <p>Country Music Hall of Fame, 4 Music Square East; (615) 416-2001. Open daily 9 a.m. to 5 p.m.; admission $10.75, $5.75 ages 6 to 11.</p>
        <p>George Jones Records, 1530 Demonbreun Street; (615) 242-2466 (may be going out of business this summer).</p>
        <p>Katy K's Ranch Dressing, 2407 12th Avenue South; (615) 297-4242.</p>
        <p>The Parthenon, Centennial Park; (615) 862-8431.</p>
        <p>Where to Stay</p>
        <p>The Union Station Hotel, 1001 Broadway, has 124 comfortable rooms in a beautiful converted train station; (615) 726-1001, fax (615) 248-3554. Doubles: $139 to $159.</p>
        <p>The Loews Vanderbilt Plaza, 2100 West End Avenue, is a 340-room luxury hotel where many touring bands stay; (615) 320-1700, fax (615) 320-5019. Doubles: $119 to $259.</p>
        <p>The 120-suite Hermitage Hotel, 231 Sixth Avenue North, is a classic old hotel on the fringe of downtown; (615) 244-3121, fax (615) 254-6909. Doubles: $109 to $199.</p>
        <p>AMERICAN CITIES NEIL STRAUSS is a cultural correspondent in the Los Angeles bureau of The Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">NEIL STRAUSS is a cultural correspondent in the Los Angeles bureau of The Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
