<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Oaxaca</title>
    <meta content="14OAXAT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sophisticated Traveler Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel; Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199124"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Indians, American</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Zapotec Tribe</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mexico</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Oaxaca (Mexico)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smiley, Jane</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sophisticated Traveler Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Indians, American</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE4D71339F937A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2902" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Oaxaca</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE SMILEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smiley, Jane</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jane Smiley profiles Oaxaca, Mexico; notes that Oaxaca State contains largest percentage of indigenous Indian peoples in Western Hemisphere, most of them descendants of very same Zapotecs who built Monte Alban between 250 BC and AD 750, or of Mixtecs who came later; some hotels and restaurants noted; photos; map (L) (Special section, The Sophisticated Traveler) (Part 2 of 2-part section)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When I ask a friend of mine who comes from Mexico City what other Mexicans say about Oaxacans, she begins, of course, with the fact that they are widely considered to be incredibly hard workers.</p>
        <p>Then she gives me an impish look and says, ''They like to have more than one woman in the house.'' Hmm.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When I ask a friend of mine who comes from Mexico City what other Mexicans say about Oaxacans, she begins, of course, with the fact that they are widely considered to be incredibly hard workers.</p>
        <p>Then she gives me an impish look and says, ''They like to have more than one woman in the house.'' Hmm.</p>
        <p>Well, yes. Right there in the palace building at the extensive Zapotec ruins known as Monte Alban, about six miles outside Oaxaca, we are shown one of those compounds -- a large central atrium surrounded by several smaller quarters, where, according to our guide, the king or prince probably maintained his several wives and families of children. I suppose some preferences might persist. In this case, such a preference would have persisted for some 2,500 years.</p>
        <p>Persisting certainly seems to be a general quality of Oaxaca, which overlooks the conjunction of two broad and fertile valleys in the southern waist of Mexico, where the Pacific coastline curves sharply toward Guatemala.</p>
        <p>Themselves productive and welcoming, the valleys are cut off from the coast to the south and west, and the rest of Mexico, to the northwest, by steep mountains and arduous roads. The foods, the people, the arts and crafts and the commerce are largely home-grown, and Oaxaca State contains the largest percentage of indigenous Indian peoples in the Western Hemisphere, most of them (some 100,000) descendants of the very same Zapotecs who built Monte Alban between 250 B.C. and A.D. 750, or of the Mixtecs who came later, after the inhabitants of Monte Alban abandoned their mountain city and moved into the valleys.</p>
        <p>At the end of October and the beginning of November, the charm of Oaxaca seems as pervasive as the brilliant, balmy mountain air. The land is green, unlike the dry California landscape we've left behind us, and fugitive sweet fragrances catch our attention time and again. When we get lost in our rental car the first night, it is simple to flag a cab and explain to the driver, with hand gestures, that we would like to hire him to lead us out of this maze of poorly mapped streets. He does so inexpensively, good-naturedly and with dispatch. At our hotel, the Victoria -- a grand though somewhat faded place on the hill overlooking town -- our wish to try several rooms until we can exchange our bed, which is muy duro, for another that is mas blandas is met with patient amusement. The way we lick our chops and ask about the dishes on the breakfast buffet (the chilaquiles, fried tortilla chips topped with salsa and cheese, and a local dish, tabaso, a dry, spicy pork and onion concoction, are especially seductive) provokes further benevolence as the cook and the waiter (who don't speak English) explain to me how they are made (I don't speak Spanish). In fact, in six days we encounter nothing but benevolence, friendliness, helpfulness.</p>
        <p>When I smile at strangers in the street, their return smiles are quick and full. I am disarmed. Now, for five days, Oaxaca is celebrating the Feast of All Saints, Nov. 1, the Day of the Dead. Every establishment we visit -- restaurant, art gallery, hotel, museum -- prominently features a commemorative display, an altar of sorts, to a particular loved one who has passed on. Nestled among brilliant sprays of orange marigolds are pictures of the dead, surrounded by their favorite things and offerings from their admirers. Below one picture sits an ashtray, four cigarettes carefully burned to ash and four empty Sol beer bottles. There are plates of food, little pumpkins, chocolate, vegetables and fruits. Scattered among the flowers in every display are white sugar skulls with names on them -- not the names of the dead, but the names of those who worked on the altar.</p>
        <p>This year, the city of Oaxaca has chosen to commemorate the 100th birthday of Rufino Tamayo, the Oaxacan painter considered to be one of the great Mexican artists of the 20th century. (He died in 1991, at the age of 91; in the 1970's, he donated to the city his personal collection of pre-Columbian art, now housed in the Rufino Tamayo Museum of Pre-Hispanic Mexican Art.) An elaborate shrine at our hotel, just inside the door, has large pictures of him, surrounded by marigolds and honorific memorabilia.</p>
        <p>Tamayo was a great lover of color, though he stayed with only five or six basic hues. A special exhibit in the Regional Museum of Oaxaca includes an interactive educational display designed to show how color and form figure in his work. Downtown, in the zocalo, in front of the cathedral, art students have created out of sand and powdered paint huge depictions of some of Tamayo's more famous paintings, many of which include skulls or skeletons.</p>
        <p>But the celebration of life's pleasures is a year-round theme of Oaxacan life. Oaxaca and the surrounding villages are famous for arts and crafts. In the village of San Bartolo Coyotepec, everyone makes a famous black-glazed pottery. In the village of San Martin Tilcajete, families produce brightly painted animals in fantastic shapes, and boxes and furniture. In many villages, hand-loomed shawls and bags are the specialty. At Monte Alban, women sell strings of beautiful, semiprecious beads. As we negotiate a price, tiny, pure azure beads of aquamarine fall out of one woman's pocket into a fold of her skirt. Oaxaca is full of commerce and full of art. After a few days, we notice that we have seen few franchises from abroad -- no McDonalds, no Marriott, no Hilton, only one little Vespa with a Domino's Pizza box on the back. What is for sale is made here, and often sold by the artisans themselves or their families.</p>
        <p>One day, we stop by Aripo, a cooperatively run gallery for local artisans, to admire a painting of a postcoital man and woman. The man, and the two candles in the room, are limp with exhaustion; the woman sits up, staring and full of energy. We ask if we might be put in touch with the artist, Gerardo Navarro. The next day, we find ourselves driving out of town to the village of Zaachila, where he lives. The town is the setting for a famous market, but not today.</p>
        <p>Today all is quiet, and when we ask the few passers-by where Avenida Benito Juarez is, they can't say, until we name the man we are looking for. Ah. El pintado! And then we are creeping in our rented Jetta up his rutted street, and then his daughter, in the same cotton dress and apron as the other women in town, opens his gate for us, and then we are inside, where a painting Gerardo has just finished is drying on a chair placed in the sun. Bright flowers and stars float in an arc over a man and a woman dancing below. The figures are simply drawn but expressive. Many of his paintings have an explicitly erotic content, sometimes joyful, sometimes dark, but always witty. He tells us that some of his favorite paintings, all erotic ones, were recently stolen by bandits.</p>
        <p>Gerardo is probably about 40, short and powerfully built. His easel is set in the dappled shade of a cypress tree (the region is famous for its huge, shapely, many-trunked cypresses). Full of smiles, he and his mother and wife and daughter bring many oils and several watercolors out into the courtyard for us to look at. We buy one called ''Romance Campesino'' -- a man and a woman, big orange and lavender flowers, a jug, a picnic basket, a stump, a tree -- the first erotic picture he has completed since the robbery.</p>
        <p>Out of the sun, his mother and wife keep their hand looms. The materials of their art, bright red and orange wools, are looped in long hanks against a white-painted wall.</p>
        <p>On the way back to Oaxaca, we stop in San Martin Tilcajete, one of the towns where the bright animal figures are painted. Family homes that are also workshops and shops line the street into town. The exterior walls are painted cantaloupe, grass green, banana yellow, apricot, periwinkle blue. Most workshops do certain animals, such as cats or snakes, but each workshop also has a specialty -- perhaps large peacocks or fantastic flying dragons. The fence around the village churchyard is freshly and brightly painted white, trimmed with blue and gold. The flat fields around the town rattle with the dried stalks and husk-covered ears of unharvested corn.</p>
        <p>in 1994, the state of oaxaca began to renovate the vast Dominican cloister that sits next to the church of Santo Domingo, about a mile up the hill from the town's cathedral and zocalo. Santo Domingo is a justly famous church. Built at the end of the 16th century, it is perhaps one of the finest examples of Spanish colonial church-building in the Western Hemisphere. It is astonishingly ornate. The vast altar is entirely swathed in gold leaf, every statue is elaborately dressed, every square foot of every wall and ceiling in the main transept and in every side chapel is decorated. It is almost too much to look at, the glorification of God and empire through the unlimited application of worldly wealth, the ultimate example of a certain type of religious gesture.</p>
        <p>In a graceful contrast to the church, the former cloister, now the Regional Museum of Oaxaca, housing treasures from all the local archaeological sites, remains spacious, clean and simple, with wide arching hallways leading to the galleries, large windows looking down upon spare courtyards of clean, pale stone, beautifully crafted new woodwork -- and only a moderate amount of gold paint over the doorways. Even the roofline is interesting, a grid of red-tiled domes. Workmen can be seen kneeling among them, breaking square tiles into the shapes they need to construct the diminishing curve of the dome.</p>
        <p>The galleries, of course, are filled with rich displays, because the area has been so long inhabited. The best- known of these is from Monte Alban's Tomb No. 7, a tomb of a Mixtec king, buried with his sacrificed servants in about 1400, discovered in 1931 by the Mexican archaeologist Alfonso Caso. The great prize was the hoard of golden treasures, including a fine pectoral and other pieces, as well as beautifully worked turquoise, silver, coral, jade and other precious stones and metals. A dramatization of the discovery plays on a videotape in the gallery. Outside the museum, on the grounds where the soldiers who were quartered here not too long ago used to drill, a large garden of native plants, with cactus fences, is being built.</p>
        <p>Monte Alban itself is Oaxaca's most famous tourist attraction. The site is about 20 percent excavated and, as interesting as it is, it is so vast and so thickly covered with vegetation that it is possible that the best finds are yet to come. As we walk toward the site, a little disappointed that the museum is closed because of damage from a recent earthquake, a woman greets us in English. She is a freelance guide, originally from Germany. She speaks Spanish, English, German and Italian, though she's also guided Japanese, Norwegian and Dutch tourists around the site. Only the palace and religious buildings on the south side of the site are open, and even some of those are cordoned off with yellow tape (the earthquake again). Still, there is plenty to see. Our guide points out, for example, the carefully aligned stones in the lowest rows of the stone walls around the ball court -- in spite of centuries of earthquake activity, these earliest examples of Zapotec construction remain in perfect condition. Our guide tells us that what we see rising from the north end of the site is a reconstruction -- what remain of the original buildings are footings. Nevertheless, the vastness of the area is imposing, as is its view of the valleys below and the sharp peaks above. Of particular interest is an oddly shaped building set at a different angle from the other buildings in the plaza. Its alignment suggests that it was an astronomical observatory.</p>
        <p>And along the western side of the plaza stand a series of steles called the Dancers. On each stele is a carved figure. Because the figures look distorted, they were for a long time thought to be dancing. They are often described as representing captured enemies, but our guide tells us that they are probably figures of hunchbacked or crippled members of the community, who were thought to have special powers. There are also figures of pregnant women and women giving birth, their babies and the umbilical cords clearly recognizable. The faces of all the figures are distinctly Zapotecan, with wide cheekbones and prominent lips. More than anything else about the site, the steles make the ancient inhabitants seem present, another group of the dead who are all about, doing many of the same things the rest of us are doing.</p>
        <p>It is a windy day and we are 8,000 feet up, so we are ready to return to the valley. Life on the promontory seems arduous, which is, perhaps, how the Zapotecans came to feel before they abandoned the mountain for the valleys.</p>
        <p>Life in Oaxaca seems exactly the opposite of arduous. The food -- especially the rich and spicy mole sauces and the locally produced chocolate -- is famously good (vegetarians find much more to eat here than in other parts of Mexico) and the weather combines the cool clarity of high altitude with the warmth of proximity to the tropics. The people are friendly and welcoming in the way that those who feel comfortable at home can afford to be. There is plenty to see, but somehow it gets seen without a sense of touristic obligation; there is plenty to buy but nothing frantic about its purchasing.</p>
        <p>We are in a world that is new to us, but feel no sense of isolation. No wonder people come back here, natives, other Mexicans and foreigners, time and time again.</p>
        <p>Oaxacan Ways</p>
        <p>The city has dozens of HOTELS in all price ranges. The three described are typical.  HOTEL VICTORIA, 1 Lomas del Fortin, at Kilometer 545, Carretera Panamericana (telephone: 800-223-9868 or 52-951-528-12; fax: 52-951-524-11), is set on a hill overlooking the town, amid extensive gardens. There are 150 rooms and suites, 34 villas and a pool; rates for a double room range from about $135 to about $210. The restaurant, EL TULE, serves Mexican and Continental specialties.  HOTEL CAMINO REAL, Calle Cinco de Mayo 300 Centro (800-722-6466 or 52-951-606-11; fax: 52-951-607-32), has 91 rooms and suites installed in the former convent of Santa Catalina, built in 1576. Rates for a double room range from about $190 to $210, and there are a pool, a coffee shop and a restaurant, EL REFECTORIO LAS NOVICIAS.  POSADA DEL CENTRO, 403 Avenida Independencia (52-951-618-74; fax: 52-951-670-07), is another converted mansion, also two blocks from the zocalo, with 24 rooms opening onto 2 patios. Rates range from about $25, for a double room with shared bath, to about $50, for a large double room with private bath. No restaurant, although breakfast is available.  While Oaxacan RESTAURANTS serve local variations on such familiar pan-Mexican items as tacos, enchiladas, tamales and stuffed chilies, there is also a distinctive regional cuisine, of which the most famous dishes are those dressed with one of the seven moles -- sauces composed of ingredients as disparate as tomatoes, chilies, cinnamon and bitter chocolate. Fiesta foods include barbacoa, goat, beef or lamb grilled in a pit between layers of avocado leaves, particularly popular for Day of the Dead celebrations. Other specialties are zucchini blossoms stuffed with the local white cheese; chicken broth with fresh corn and zucchini blossoms; and crunchy fried grasshoppers, eaten plain, sprinkled over tortillas or filling tacos. Fresh seafood is abundant, and the local white cheese is famous throughout the country.</p>
        <p>The city has many informal, family-style restaurants where Oaxacan specialties are served. Three in the moderate-price range (about $25 to $30 for two, with beer): MARIA BONITA RESTAURANT AND BAR, Macedonia Alcala 706B (951-672-33), near the church of Santo Domingo, which is open daily for breakfast, lunch and dinner; and two second-floor establishments that share a corner at Avenida Hidalgo and Portal de las Flores, MI CASITA, 612 Avenida Hidalgo (951-629-17), which is open daily for lunch (until 7:30), and LA CASA DE LA ABUELA, 616 Avenida de Hildalgo (951-635-44), which is open daily for lunch and dinner.  Jane Smiley is the author of ''Horse Heaven'' (Alfred A. Knopf), a novel.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Jane Smiley is the author of ''Horse Heaven'' (Alfred A. Knopf), a novel.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
