<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Summer Fun Yields Lasting Friendship</title>
    <meta content="14FRES$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="38" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199548"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE FRESH AIR FUND"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Fresh Air Fund</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Donovan, Aaron</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shelley, Larry</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shelley, Donna (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E5DD133BF937A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="740" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Summer Fun Yields Lasting Friendship</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AARON DONOVAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Donovan, Aaron</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on participation of Manhattan residents Larry and Donna Shelley in Fresh Air Fund, volunteering to take child from New York City as part of program that pairs needy children with rural and suburban families for two weeks each summer; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Larry and Donna Shelley decided last year that their three boys were finally old enough to be playmates for a disadvantaged child. Acting on an idea they had had for years, the couple volunteered to take in a child from New York City as part of a program that pairs needy children with rural and suburban families for two weeks a summer.</p>
        <p>They joined 3,000 other families who live as far away as Maine and Virginia in opening their home to a child for the Fresh Air Fund, a nonprofit agency that has been giving city children summer vacations in the country since 1877.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Larry and Donna Shelley decided last year that their three boys were finally old enough to be playmates for a disadvantaged child. Acting on an idea they had had for years, the couple volunteered to take in a child from New York City as part of a program that pairs needy children with rural and suburban families for two weeks a summer.</p>
        <p>They joined 3,000 other families who live as far away as Maine and Virginia in opening their home to a child for the Fresh Air Fund, a nonprofit agency that has been giving city children summer vacations in the country since 1877.</p>
        <p>But the Shelley family differs from most host families in one respect: they live less than two miles from the child they were paired with.</p>
        <p>The vast majority of host families live in suburban and rural areas, but about 30 families in the city volunteer to take children with them to their summer homes in the metropolitan region and beyond.</p>
        <p>The Shelleys live on Park Avenue on the Upper East Side most of the year but also spend time at their home in Rye, N.Y. Mr. Shelley, a venture capitalist, and his wife, a  doctor who is director of New York City's Tobacco Control Program, said that last summer, their sons, Sam, now 9, Jake, 6, and Ben, 5, enjoyed the company of a new playmate, Daquan Prescod, a 9-year-old from Harlem.</p>
        <p>The boys played pool, attended the Shelley boys' day camp in Westchester, and went in-line skating and read books together every night before going to sleep.</p>
        <p>Daquan said his favorite part of the vacation was swimming in the Shelleys' pool, where he learned to swim in just a few days. ''I had to go under water,'' he said, ''and hold my nose.''</p>
        <p>As fun and informative as the vacations are for the children, the host parents also learn a great deal about a different world. Dr. Shelley said  she developed a profound respect for Daquan's mother, Sharon, after the two met, and was particularly moved one day after she dropped Daquan off at his apartment and saw a group of children playing football on St. Nicholas Avenue.</p>
        <p>''If my kids' only backyard was the street I guess I'd let them play in the street,'' Dr. Shelley said. ''If you see what kids are reduced to in terms of their access to fields and parks and play space, I think it does raise your sensitivity to what a summer like that would mean to a child.''</p>
        <p>Because they live in the city, the Shelleys witness firsthand what a hot summer is like in an urban environment, and fully realize the importance of helping a youngster escape, however briefly. ''You pass the kids playing in the hydrants, playing in the streets,'' Dr. Shelley said, ''and it really hits home to me. You want to help them get away, and it's so easy to do that. It really is so simple.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Prescod, a home health aide who lives with her two daughters, two sons and a granddaughter in a three-bedroom apartment, said she was thankful Daquan got the opportunity to enjoy a summer out in the country. ''He was blessed with a very nice family,'' she said. ''He got a chance to do a lot of things.''</p>
        <p>After two weeks of fun, it was difficult for the fast friends to say goodbye. But the parting was eased by the families' proximity. The Shelleys spent time with Daquan in January, February and March, playing three-on-three basketball in a league sponsored by the West Side Jewish Community Center.</p>
        <p>When asked whether he wanted to stay with the Shelleys again this summer, Daquan replied with ''an automatic 'Yes,' an excited 'Yes!' '' his mother said.</p>
        <p>Families who are interested in having a child stay with them or who wish to inquire about registering their children for a Fresh Air summer vacation can call (800) 367-0003. Anyone interested in making a tax-deductible contribution to the fund can send a check to the Fresh Air Fund, 1040 Avenue of the Americas, New York, N.Y., 10018.</p>
        <p>THE FRESH AIR FUND</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
