<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dispute Flares in Florida Over Licensing of Cuban Doctors</title>
    <meta content="14DOCT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199534"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cuban-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Florida</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Cuba</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Nicaragua</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kilborn, Peter T</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Cuba</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Nicaragua</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Nicaragua</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Cuba</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cuban-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E5DF133BF937A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1377" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dispute Flares in Florida Over Licensing of Cuban Doctors</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER T. KILBORN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kilborn, Peter T</byline>
      <dateline>MIAMI</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Long dispute over licensing of foreign-trained Cuban doctors pits Florida's Cuban-American lobby against state medical establishment; 400 doctors, Cubans and Nicaraguans, do not have proof of training to get licenses and have been unable to pass national test; photo; Florida legislature set up separate test and eliminated internships and residencies, but more than 90 percent failed that test and third one translated into Spanish; lobbyists now want to eliminate test altogether; national medical groups are strongly opposed (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A decade-long dispute over the licensing of a group of Cubans who want to practice medicine here is testing the power of the Cuban-American lobby in Florida against that of the state's medical establishment and is about to involve the American Medical Association.</p>
        <p>The outcome will affect the futures of Cuban refugees who have been struggling for the right to be licensed as doctors in the United States. Also at stake, representatives of the medical establishment say, are standards of care for the profession.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A decade-long dispute over the licensing of a group of Cubans who want to practice medicine here is testing the power of the Cuban-American lobby in Florida against that of the state's medical establishment and is about to involve the American Medical Association.</p>
        <p>The outcome will affect the futures of Cuban refugees who have been struggling for the right to be licensed as doctors in the United States. Also at stake, representatives of the medical establishment say, are standards of care for the profession.</p>
        <p>The majority of the 400 would-be doctors are Cuban immigrants who came to Florida in the 1980's, a time of heavy migration from Cuba. Nicaraguans make up about a third of the group. While contending that they had medical training or had been licensed in their homeland, they have been unable to produce sufficient evidence to obtain licenses here or to pass a national exam required for all doctors by all states.</p>
        <p>To accommodate them, the Florida Legislature, at the urging of the Cuban-American Caucus, has established a separate test for this group, in the hopes of making it easier to pass. It has placed less emphasis on pure science and more on treatment and diagnosis, for example, and made special courses available to help these immigrants prepare for the test.</p>
        <p>The Legislature has also eliminated internships and hospital residency as preconditions for licensing for this group.</p>
        <p>The test was actually revised twice. After more than 90 percent of the immigrant doctors failed the modified exam when they first took it last May, the state rewrote it again and translated it into Spanish. Again, more than 90 percent failed the easier version when they took it in November. With still further revisions, the exam will be offered yet again late this month.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the Cuban-American doctors' lobby says it will press the Legislature to eliminate licensing exams entirely for the group and to require instead that the doctors work under the close supervision of licensed physicians before setting off on their own.</p>
        <p>While many Cuban exiles have passed the test required of other  doctors, the fact that one group of exiles is getting so much special attention has raised concerns among members of the medical establishment in Florida and beyond.</p>
        <p>At its September meeting, the Florida Medical Association adopted a resolution urging the Legislature to abolish the special exam and rely solely on the national exam. And at its annual meeting in June, the American Medical Association's House of Delegates will vote on a resolution supporting the Florida association's resolution.</p>
        <p>''It's important not to open the medical system to testing for a particular group,'' said Dr. Yank Coble, an endocrinologist in Jacksonville, Fla., and a member of the A.M.A.'s board of trustees. ''It's important not to be perceived as making special exceptions for political reasons.''</p>
        <p>Other medical organizations have expressed opposition as well, contending that these accommodations are, in effect, unleashing an underqualified group of doctors on an unsuspecting public.</p>
        <p>''The public needs to be concerned,'' said Dr. L. Thomas Bowles, president of the National Board of Medical Examiners in Philadelphia. ''No other state has found it necessary to create an alternate pathway for a special cohort of physicians.''</p>
        <p>Political experts contend that the fact that the Legislature has persisted in its efforts to help these immigrants illustrates the power of a relatively small group of Cuban legislators who make up the Cuban-American Caucus.</p>
        <p>For their part, the Cuban-American legislators maintain that they are trying to right injustices against their fellow exiles. They say the Florida Medical Association and the American Medical Association want to restrict competition for patients and exert unfair influence over the State Health Department and its Board of Medicine, which administers the tests.</p>
        <p>''This is an issue of fairness,'' said State Representative Rudy Garcia Jr., a Republican from Hialeah and a prominent spokesman for South Florida's 800,000 Cuban-Americans. The content and scoring of the tests that the state devised for the immigrants seem to discriminate against them, Mr. Garcia said.</p>
        <p>The story of Camilo Lopez is typical of the group of immigrants whom the Legislature is trying to help.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lopez, 39, said he fled Cuba for Miami in March 1980, having completed a year of medical school in his homeland. Unable to afford the high cost of medical school here, he went to the Dominican Republic, where, he says, he completed his medical studies at Utesa University. He then returned to Florida, where he was granted a temporary license to become a physician's assistant, which allowed him to provide much of the care of a doctor.</p>
        <p>At the same time, Mr. Lopez, who is married and the father of two teenagers, has been trying to become a licensed doctor. Like some of his colleagues, he could not produce credible evidence of his training and as a result could not be certified to take a national licensing exam.</p>
        <p>In another special privilege that the Legislature created for the group, a two-semester course was designed to prepare the Cubans for the exam. The course was offered in 1990 and 1992 by the University of Miami and by a private company.</p>
        <p>But as they were completing the course, the National Board of Medical Examiners, Dr. Bowles's organization, and the Federation of State Medical Boards in Chicago introduced a new national exam, the United States Medical Licensing Examination, replacing the one for which the students had been studying. The students, who had paid the University of Miami $10,000 each for tuition, were ill-prepared to take the new exam. Some took it and failed it; some did not take it.</p>
        <p>''They did everything they were supposed to do,'' said State Senator Mario Diaz-Balart, a Miami Republican who is leaving the Senate this month because of term limits. ''And oops. Wrong exam.''</p>
        <p>Tanya Williams, executive director of the State Board of Medicine, said, ''They got caught, and the Legislature decided they were victims of a change in national policy.''</p>
        <p>The Legislature then asked the University of South Florida to prepare a special licensing exam for the group. In spite of the change, 250 of 260 candidates, including Mr. Lopez, failed the special exam when it was offered last May.</p>
        <p>State Senator Alberto Gutman, a Cuban-American Republican from Miami who has been sentenced to prison for Medicare fraud and gave up his seat last year after he was indicted, persuaded the Board of Medicine to change some questions and translate the exam into Spanish.</p>
        <p>In November, 87 candidates took the revised exam, and 79 failed. Saying he believed that the second exam was stacked against him, Mr. Lopez did not take it.</p>
        <p>Nationwide, about 40 percent of foreign-trained doctors fail the national exam on the first try, four times the rate of American-trained physicians. Doctor organizations attribute the failures mostly to differences in medical school training, difficulties with English and unfamiliarity with American medicine.</p>
        <p>In a comprehensive study of physician licensing and discipline five years ago, the Florida Legislature's nonpartisan Office of Program Policy Analysis and Government Accountability called the licensing process neutral and thorough. ''If an applicant satisfies all the requirements prescribed by statute and rule,'' the office concluded, ''the license will be issued.''</p>
        <p>The group's special treatment upsets many doctors, including some of the state's 12,000 other foreign-trained physicians, a third of the total of 37,500 practicing in Florida, who earned their licenses without special help.</p>
        <p>''They're are not bad doctors,'' said Dr. Juan Wester, a surgeon in Hollywood, Fla., who was born in Argentina and went to medical school there. ''They're probably as good as many of us. But we have always felt that as international medical graduates, we wanted to be treated exactly the same as anybody else.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
