<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>It's a Protest. What's the Cause?</title>
    <meta content="14PROT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199269"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Huntington (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Woliver, Robbie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E6DE1F38F937A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1675" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>It's a Protest. What's the Cause?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBBIE WOLIVER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Woliver, Robbie</byline>
      <dateline>HUNTINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on recent protest by group of mostly teenagers and young adults in Huntington, Long Island, who were apparently representing many causes; some of causes listed; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>JEANNETTE HENRY was on her front porch with her daughter, Kaitlin Byrne, visiting from Bayville, enjoying a lazy, warm Saturday afternoon, when they heard chanting, singing and drums on nearby New York Avenue. Intrigued, they walked down the block to find a colorful, noisy parade of mostly teenagers and twentysomethings chanting, ''These are our streets!''</p>
        <p>''What are they protesting against?'' Ms. Henry asked.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>JEANNETTE HENRY was on her front porch with her daughter, Kaitlin Byrne, visiting from Bayville, enjoying a lazy, warm Saturday afternoon, when they heard chanting, singing and drums on nearby New York Avenue. Intrigued, they walked down the block to find a colorful, noisy parade of mostly teenagers and twentysomethings chanting, ''These are our streets!''</p>
        <p>''What are they protesting against?'' Ms. Henry asked.</p>
        <p>The question was repeated by commuters who encountered the marchers at their start-off point at the Huntington train station, drivers who passed them on the road and pedestrians they encountered on the street.</p>
        <p>But the vague message and what initially appeared to be a modest turnout last Saturday was nevertheless a display of political activism not seen recently in Huntington: 21st-century radicalism that harkened back to protests of the 1960's.</p>
        <p>Fifteen people, including one bystander, were arrested during the peaceful protest against -- well, that depended on whom you asked.</p>
        <p>Dyane Adamson, 23, of West Babylon, wore short-cropped neon orange hair and a matching sign on her back that read, ''Bikes good, cars bad.''</p>
        <p>''We're the voice for those who can't speak,'' she said.</p>
        <p>''We're here representing many causes,'' said Frank Richards, 45, a Mineola woodworker. ''Global capitalism, loss of autonomy, privatization, sweat shops, it all converges. But we're also protesting the overwhelming presence of commercial space on Long Island.''</p>
        <p>Brian McKenzie, 29, was in a group of bicycle enthusiasts who joined the rally to protest cycling conditions on the Island. ''There is a lack of viable alternatives to motor vehicle transportation here,'' he said. ''I want to draw attention to cycle safety, lack of public transportation, lack of dedicated bike routes.''</p>
        <p>Bryan Josephs, 19, a student from Stony Brook, also brought his bike to the rally. But his yellow-and-black bumblebee-striped hair set him apart from the older cyclists there specifically to protest bicycle issues.</p>
        <p>''People use cars way too much on Long Island,'' he said. ''These are just as much our streets as anyone else's.''</p>
        <p>The rally was sponsored by the Long Island Direct Action Network, a loose coalition of activists inspired by the recent Seattle and Washington demonstrations against the World Trade Organization and the International Monetary Fund, which attracted more than 70,000 protesters and resulted in more than 1,000 arrests.</p>
        <p>Stephen Burzio, a 25-year-old law student from Baldwin and a spokesman for the Huntington event, said he attended the I.M.F. demonstration in Washington last month and wanted to bring home its serious themes in a more festive atmosphere.</p>
        <p>''We want to perform a symbolic action to demonstrate our sentiment that the streets should be more than a conduit for the functions of capitalism,'' Mr. Burzio said.</p>
        <p>The demonstrators began gathering at 1 p.m. at the Long Island Rail Road station on Route 110 in Huntington. Although the organizers had pointedly refused to seek a permit for a demonstration, relations between the protesters and the police were cordial at first. Before the number of protesters had grown beyond 10, Lt. Robert Bellittieri of the Suffolk County Police suggested that they move into the parking lot where ''it would be safer.'' They agreed.</p>
        <p>Over the next 90 minutes, under a hot sun, the crowd swelled to about 50, according to a police count. One young woman walked through the crowd distributing string beans. Others banged makeshift drums.</p>
        <p>Taking it all in were a gaggle of former protesters from a different era who gathered in the station's shaded stairwell, spiritedly discussing politics, dissent and the differences between the generations.</p>
        <p>''Some might say that the stakes were greater back then,'' said Arnie Silverman, a Nassau Community College sociology professor and a veteran of civil rights and antiwar protests of the 60's. He and his wife, Ruth, who teaches sociology and women's studies at N.C.C., were keeping an eye on their son, Ari, who was planning to join the protest but had not yet arrived.</p>
        <p>Ari's parents said they appreciated the causes with which their son was concerned but were a bit apprehensive about the civil disobedience aspect. ''We can't prevent him from doing this,'' Ms. Silverman said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Silverman sensed a change in the pendulum of youthful activism. ''I'm beginning to notice more campus activism,'' he said. ''This is the first time a substantial number of students at a variety of levels are becoming interested in causes. That hasn't happened in a long while.''</p>
        <p>Rosario Renda, a Rockville Centre lawyer, was there as a legal observer for the protesters.</p>
        <p>''I don't understand their anarchistic mission,'' Mr. Renda said, ''but they're the only ones focusing globally. Even the socialists aren't.''</p>
        <p>''In the 60's,'' Mr. Silverman said, ''we were more ideologically coherent. But the same arguments are taking place: 'There's too much organization, too much party line. We don't have a voice.' ''</p>
        <p>As the protesters prepared to march to their still-undisclosed destination, Mr. Silverman announced, ''There goes our future faculty.''</p>
        <p>By 2:30 p.m., the demonstrators began an orderly march north on Route 110 by bike, skateboard and on foot. A mile and a half later they were at the intersection of New York Avenue and Elm Street, a block south of Main Street, where they were met by another group of protesters, including Ari Silverman and about 30 others. Within seconds, a 25-foot metal scaffolding tripod was erected in the street and Connor Cash of Sound Beach scurried to the top, unfurling a 25-foot red banner that proclaimed, ''This Is What Democracy Looks Like.'' The demonstrators banged on makeshift drums, chanting ''Our streets!''</p>
        <p>The 10 police officers there called for backup. ''We didn't quite expect this,'' Lt. Fred Kuebler said later.</p>
        <p>Across the street at Super Runners, a sports shop, Question No. 1 was being raised again. ''I don't know what they're objecting to,'' said Jane Muhrcke, the owner.</p>
        <p>''I think they want bike safety,'' one woman offered. ''No, they want the streets,'' responded her male companion. ''Whatever that means.''</p>
        <p>Across the street from the tripod were Ms. Henry and Ms. Byrne, who had followed the demonstration to town. ''I think what they're doing is great,'' Ms. Byrne said. ''All their issues are interesting. And we do need better cycle safety.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Henry was puzzled. ''They say they are environmentalists,'' she said, ''and I'm an environmentalist, but they don't look like environmentalists. They have blue hair and nose rings.'' Her daughter answered, ''That's what environmentalists look like now.''</p>
        <p>Two protesters were arrested after the police said they ordered the crowd to disperse. ''They're making us look horrible,'' one nervous-looking young officer said, ''and this is not what democracy looks like.''</p>
        <p>As soon as a 25-officer police backup force arrived, arrests began in earnest. The Silvermans' son was one of those apprehended.</p>
        <p>Patricia Barrow, a 53-year-old graphic artist from Huntington, said she was leaving a restaurant and stopped to see what was going on.</p>
        <p>''I saw all these kids out there on Elm Street, chanting,'' Ms. Barrow said, ''and I asked them what they were standing for. They were very intelligent, articulate kids. I was just standing there. A cop came by and asked us to move. I did, along with the crowd. I asked the cop why they were arresting the kids, and he said they were blocking traffic, which they actually weren't.</p>
        <p>''I said to him: 'But you're the ones blocking traffic, closing up New York Avenue. These kids are just on a small side street.' He began pulling the police tape across my chest, pushing me backwards with the crowd. He said if I didn't get off the street, I'd be arrested. Before I knew it, I was arrested.''</p>
        <p>Those arrested were taken to Second Precinct headquarters on Park Avenue. Of 15 arrested, 14 were charged with two counts of disorderly conduct: obstructing traffic and failing to obey a lawful order to disperse. Each count carries a maximum 15-day jail term. Bail was set at $200. Ms. Barrow had an additional charge of resisting arrest, which carries a maximum penalty of one year in jail, and her bail was $700. Most of the protesters were released by 9 p.m. All have a July 2 court date.</p>
        <p>''It was a very well-planned event,'' Lt. Kuebler said. ''It all happened very quickly, setting up that tripod. They started chanting, 'We have taken over the streets,' but we took the streets back. What they did could have been dangerous to them and to the public. It was a public safety issue.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Burzio was satisfied with the results.</p>
        <p>''Everything went exceptionally well,'' he said. ''There was no violence. We all behaved very well and I think we got our message across. I think we impressed a lot of people with our concerns and peacefulness. Long Island is famous for its political apathy, and we made something happen that never happened before.</p>
        <p>''It's a learning process,'' Mr. Burzio said, hinting at more demonstrations. ''The more we do them, the more savvy and the better we get at getting our message across.''</p>
        <p>At the Silverman house a day later, young Ari also pronounced the event a success. ''We reclaimed the streets,'' he said. ''We proved the people's power to organize and get things done through their own action without answering to preset rules like trivial permits.''</p>
        <p>''I was greatly influenced by my parents' liberalism,'' he said. But his parents weren't exactly applauding.</p>
        <p>''Let's just say we weren't pleased with what he did yesterday,'' said his mother, a political activist but still a mother.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
