<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Putnam Sheriff Investigated for Abuse of Power</title>
    <meta content="14SHER" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Editors' Note Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000514T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199315"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sheriffs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police Brutality and Misconduct</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Putnam County (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pataki, George E (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rowe, Claudia</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police Brutality and Misconduct</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E5D7163BF937A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="557" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Putnam Sheriff Investigated for Abuse of Power</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLAUDIA ROWE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rowe, Claudia</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Gov George Pataki asks state to open probe of Putnam County Sheriff's Department following several federal suits alleging department abused power and violated citizens' civil rights (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>GOV. GEORGE E. PATAKI has asked for a state investigation of the Putnam County Sheriff's Department after several federal lawsuits alleged that the department had abused its power and violated citizens' civil rights.</p>
        <p>Earlier this year, a federal jury in a civil suit found that the sheriff, Robert Thoubboron, had singled out John Leather, the county's former fire coordinator, for drunken driving arrests in 1995 because Mr. Leather opposed the sheriff's stand on how to introduce a 911 emergency system  Court transcripts showed that others who had been drinking and driving -- including members of the sheriff's department -- were not charged.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>GOV. GEORGE E. PATAKI has asked for a state investigation of the Putnam County Sheriff's Department after several federal lawsuits alleged that the department had abused its power and violated citizens' civil rights.</p>
        <p>Earlier this year, a federal jury in a civil suit found that the sheriff, Robert Thoubboron, had singled out John Leather, the county's former fire coordinator, for drunken driving arrests in 1995 because Mr. Leather opposed the sheriff's stand on how to introduce a 911 emergency system  Court transcripts showed that others who had been drinking and driving -- including members of the sheriff's department -- were not charged.</p>
        <p>The jury awarded Mr. Leather $645,000 in punitive and compensatory damages, the bulk of which were to be paid by the sheriff, with $200,000 assessed to the county.  Sheriff Thoubboron, a Republican, who has held the post for 14 years, has said he would appeal. He did not return calls seeking comment.</p>
        <p>In April, the nine-member County Legislature, seven of whom are Republicans, voted to settle the case with Mr. Leather for a total of $275,000, absolving the sheriff of making any payments. But County Executive Robert Bondi, who had urged the board to let the appeals process take its course, vetoed that decision. He said, in effect, that making county residents pay for the sheriff's alleged wrongdoing would be unfair, adding, ''How can any of us look the citizens of Putnam County in the eye after settling this case, using taxpayer dollars, if the sheriff is ultimately exonerated?''</p>
        <p>His deputy, Donald Smith, said this week: ''You can't have it both ways. You can't say you're innocent and then expect the taxpayers to pay these punitive damages.''</p>
        <p>To get an independent perspective, the Legislature voted unanimously to seek a state investigation of the Sheriff's Department. Most troubling to Mr. Bondi and the legislators was the suspicion and uncertainty swirling around the 150-member department.</p>
        <p>Arne Nordstrom, chairman of the County Legislature, said ''a string of 10 to 14'' other cases had been filed against Sheriff Thoubborron's office in the last five years, among them claims of sexual harassment, assault and civil rights violations. While Mr. Nordstrom said it was not uncommon for law-enforcement agencies to be sued, ''It's a concern here because we're getting a lot more.''</p>
        <p>Sheriff Thoubboron has denied abusing his authority, and in April he said he would welcome an investigation of his department.</p>
        <p>Sheriff Thoubboron has his defenders. One legislator, Michael K. Semo, called the Sheriff's Department ''one of the most professional'' law-enforcement agencies he has ever seen.</p>
        <p>The fallout, however, has created a morale problem, Mr. Semo said.</p>
        <p>''Are guys going to be able to protect and serve the same way now?'' he asked. ''One deputy's wife told me that her husband can't wait to retire now, and that is so sad. You're going from a place that's the safest county in the nation to one where you're going to have someone out there wondering if he's going to be sued for giving out a D.W.I., and that's not healthy.''</p>
        <p>The inquiry will be handled by the State Commission of Investigation, which is charged with studying allegations of impropriety by public officials.</p>
        <p>Editors' Note:  May 14, 2000, Sunday  An article on Page 7 of the Westchester section today about Gov. George E. Pataki's decision to investigate allegations of misconduct by the Putnam County Sheriff's Department refers to a civil suit in which a jury awarded $645,000 to a man who said he was a victim of selective prosecution. Of that amount, $435,000 was to be paid by the sheriff himself, Robert Thoubboron. On Thursday, after the article had gone to press, Judge Charles L. Brieant of Federal District Court in White Plains cut the sheriff's liability to $3,000, saying the original award ''shocks the conscience of the court.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Editors' Note: May 14, 2000, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article on Page 7 of the Westchester section today about Gov. George E. Pataki's decision to investigate allegations of misconduct by the Putnam County Sheriff's Department refers to a civil suit in which a jury awarded $645,000 to a man who said he was a victim of selective prosecution. Of that amount, $435,000 was to be paid by the sheriff himself, Robert Thoubboron. On Thursday, after the article had gone to press, Judge Charles L. Brieant of Federal District Court in White Plains cut the sheriff's liability to $3,000, saying the original award ''shocks the conscience of the court.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
