<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In the Region/New Jersey; Housing for the Aged: Is Supply Outpacing Demand?</title>
    <meta content="14NJZO$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199319"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Edgewater (NJ)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sunrise Assisted Living Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Garbarine, Rachelle</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/In the Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Luxury and Vacations/Active Adult</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Aged</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E0D7163BF937A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1576" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In the Region/New Jersey; Housing for the Aged: Is Supply Outpacing Demand?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RACHELLE GARBARINE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Garbarine, Rachelle</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sunrise Assisted Living is building $10 million, 70-unit building for elderly in Edgewater, NJ; porject is going up at time when assisted-living market in New Jersey is suffering from temporary saturation in certain locations; some key questions for developing such residences are where to build and what services to offer; photo (In the Region/New Jersey) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE three-story Victorian-style building under construction along the Hudson River in Edgewater breaks the pattern of mid- and high-rise apartment projects that have sprouted up and down the New Jersey shoreline in the last few years.</p>
        <p>The 70-unit building, which will open this fall, will be the first assisted-living residence for the elderly to rise at the water's edge. Instead of offering just rental apartments, assisted-living residences combine housing with social services, three meals a day and when needed, personal care.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE three-story Victorian-style building under construction along the Hudson River in Edgewater breaks the pattern of mid- and high-rise apartment projects that have sprouted up and down the New Jersey shoreline in the last few years.</p>
        <p>The 70-unit building, which will open this fall, will be the first assisted-living residence for the elderly to rise at the water's edge. Instead of offering just rental apartments, assisted-living residences combine housing with social services, three meals a day and when needed, personal care.</p>
        <p>The $10 million project on River Road is being developed by Sunrise Assisted Living, a public company in Alexandria, Va. It will be its 11th project in New Jersey, said Joseph F. McElwee, a senior vice president for development, and Sunrise operates some 160 communities in 28 states.</p>
        <p>The Sunrise project is going up at time  when the assisted-living market in the state, as in the nation, is suffering from a temporary saturation in certain locations, industry executives said. In turn, they said, the earnings of some companies have fallen, Wall Street's enthusiasm for the industry has been dampened, and construction financing has tightened.</p>
        <p>Barbara Kleger, a director of ZA Consulting in Jenkintown, Pa., which advises the housing industry for the elderly, said that in the last nine months, ''too much was built too fast, and it is taking longer for the market to absorb the units.''</p>
        <p>Since mid-1995 in New Jersey, 9,430 new and renovated assisted-living units have been developed in 115 projects, and an additional 31,850 units in 427 more developments have been approved, according to the state's Department of Health and Senior Services, which licenses assisted-living projects.</p>
        <p>''We are licensing three or four projects a month, and that has been consistent,'' said Andrew P. Aronson, the director of long-term care licensing and certification at the state's Department of Health. ''From that perspective we're not seeing much of a slowdown.''</p>
        <p>That worries industry executives like Rick Abrams, the president of the New Jersey Association of Health Care Facilities in Trenton. Also worrisome, he said, is the recommendation made earlier this month by a state commission that the current review process for certification for assisted-living projects remain unchanged. It currently takes three months, Mr. Abrams said, and the state primarily looks at the developer's record in running such projects elsewhere. Mr. Abrams's group had proposed a longer, more stringent process.</p>
        <p>''To a degree the proverbial horse is out of the barn,'' Mr. Abrams said, ''but the real damage will come with the next wave of construction.'' By his estimate, there are about 100 projects under construction, which, he said, could cause ''occupancy rates to plummet.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Aronson countered that there are ''fewer than 100 projects under way and that no one knows how many of the 31,000 units approved will get built.'' The state is not inclined to put a ceiling on the industry.  ''The market will dictate,'' he said. ''This is a market-driven product.''</p>
        <p>Whitney Redding, a spokeswoman for the Assisted Living Federation of America, a trade group in Fairfax Va., said the market is in the process ''of sorting itself out.'' ''The trend in general is a slowing of development,'' she added.</p>
        <p>Robert G. Kramer, the executive director at the National Investment Center for Seniors Housing &amp; Care Industries, a nonprofit group in Annapolis, Md., said, ''There is a shift toward the operational side of the business and acquisitions, and away from development.'' He said the construction slowdown is expected to last into 2001.</p>
        <p>Still, financing is available, he added, but  lenders are requiring developers to invest at least 25 percent of their own money in their  projects, compared with 10 to 20 percent two years ago.</p>
        <p>And, he said, the demographics support the industry's growth. By 2010, New Jersey's population is projected to be 8.5 million, with 1.4 million people age 60 and older and 604,900 age 75 and older, pointing toward the need for specialized housing that provides some health care.</p>
        <p>T HE good news for consumers,'' said Ms. Kleger of ZA Consulting, ''is that operators are forced to give more value.'' While that has not translated into lower rents, she said, it has given rise to incentives like no rent for the first month or help with moving expenses.</p>
        <p>Developers are also responding to the temporary saturation in some locations by pulling back development plans or by building projects aimed at people with moderate incomes, not for the affluent elderly. Still others are going into underserved locations.</p>
        <p>That was part of Sunrise's decision to build on the riverfront in Edgewater,  ''where there is limited competition and the demographics are strong,'' said Mr. McElwee, the Sunrise executive.</p>
        <p>Diagonally across River Road from Sunrise's project, Daibes Construction of Edgewater is developing 374 one- and two-bedroom ''independent living'' apartments for the elderly. This project will offer meals and such amenities as a health club but no personal care. Demand still exceeds supply for these independent units, industry executives said. The $60 million project will be  financed with $55 million in state bonds. The two housing projects will complement rather than compete with each other, the developers said. Monthly rents for the apartments, with 700 to 1,200 square feet, are expected to be $2,000 to $3,000. Because of the public financing, 23 percent are reserved for people with low incomes, no more than $27,225 a year.</p>
        <p>Sunrise is taking a conservative approach on its Edgewater project, which is being built a two-acre parcel. Depending on its success, Mr. McElwee said, the company will tailor the second phase of the project to public demand. A second two-acre site could accommodate up to 78 more units.</p>
        <p>Monthly rents for semiprivate units, which will have 450 to 650 square feet and will accommodate two people, will be $2,100 to $3,000. Private units with up to 650 square feet will be $4,500. Rents include all services, meals and personal care. As many as 24 of the units will be for residents with Alzheimer's disease.</p>
        <p>''We're still bullish on New Jersey,'' Mr. McElwee said, noting that the company has two more projects, totaling 143 units, under way and four others with 264 additional residences in various stages of the approval process.</p>
        <p>Marriott Senior Living Services, the hotel chain's division that has developed nine  projects with 1,365 units in New Jersey, has slowed down its construction for the elderly in the state. Michael J. Giacopelli Jr., the senior vice president for development, said, ''We're keeping two sites on hold until the existing inventory is absorbed.''</p>
        <p>Castle Senior Living of Teaneck, with seven assisted-living projects and 825 units in the state, is following suit. ''Our appetite for new construction will be limited,'' said  Stanley Diamond, Castle's chairman. ''There is more opportunity to acquire existing properties at less cost than building new ones.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Diamond said that there is still a strong demand for independent-living apartments, and Castle plans to begin construction this summer on a $65 million project in Franklin Township, in Somerset County. Of the 337 apartments, 249 will be independent units. The project, on 42 acres on Eastern Road, will also have 61 assisted-living residences and 27 units for residents with Alzheimer's.</p>
        <p>Like the company's other projects, it will be affiliated with a hospital, in this case St.  Peter's Medical Center in New Brunswick, which will lease space in the 25,000-square-foot medical mall that Castle plans to build on the site. There is already a nursing home there, reflecting the trend back to campus-style projects offering a continuum of care.</p>
        <p>Mr. Diamond said the independent units -- studios, one- and two-bedrooms -- would be built first. Rents are expected to be $1,800 to $2,850 a month and will include two meals a day and the use of a swimming pool but no personal care. Construction of the assisted-living units will not begin until late 2001, he said.</p>
        <p>This summer the Colbrook Development Corporation of Manhattan and the Wallick Companies of Columbus, Ohio, expect to start the conversion of a nine-story hotel in downtown Elizabeth into 99 assisted-living units, their first project in New Jersey. The partners are seeking $9 million in financing from the state for the conversion of the 1927 hotel on East Jersey Street; 20 percent of the units will be set aside for people with low incomes, no more than $26,475 a year. The project is expected to cost over $10 million, said Howard Wallick, the president of Colbrook and a principal in the Wallick Companies.</p>
        <p>The plans call for 69 studio and one-bedroom assisted-living units with expected  monthly rents, including all services and meals, of $2,400 to $3,000. The remaining 30 units will be for residents with Alzheimer's.</p>
        <p>''There is an untapped market for this kind of relatively affordable project,'' Mr. Wallick said, ''one that may be possible to replicate.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
