<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>IN THE STUDIO WITH/Linda Jean Fisher; Sketches and Notes, And Pieces Take Shape</title>
    <meta content="14ART.$22" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199326"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fisher, Linda Jean</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lombardi, D Dominick</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E1D6163BF937A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="737" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>IN THE STUDIO WITH/Linda Jean Fisher; Sketches and Notes, And Pieces Take Shape</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By D. DOMINICK LOMBARDI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lombardi, D Dominick</byline>
      <dateline>PEEKSKILL</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Artist Linda Jean Fisher of Peekskill, NY, answers questions on her work, her childhood, Peekskill and future plans; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR almost a decade, artists have been setting up studios in office buildings, carriage houses, forgotten storefronts and a vacated church -- all in downtown Peekskill.</p>
        <p>Since February 1992, Linda Jean Fisher has had a studio in converted office space in the Flat Iron Building here.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR almost a decade, artists have been setting up studios in office buildings, carriage houses, forgotten storefronts and a vacated church -- all in downtown Peekskill.</p>
        <p>Since February 1992, Linda Jean Fisher has had a studio in converted office space in the Flat Iron Building here.</p>
        <p>Now she looks forward to the possibility of being chosen for one of the 28 units in Art Loft, a new development a few blocks away, which was  specifically designed as living and working space for artists.</p>
        <p>Ms. Fisher talked recently about influences on her work -- including Peekskill itself.</p>
        <p>Q. Looking around your studio, there are numerous drawings, notes, reference materials, scale models and finished works, all systematically designed, and in different stages of completion. What drives you to fabricate such an obsessive and seemingly endless supply of notes, sketches, plans and objects?</p>
        <p>A. I think of myself, primarily, as a problem solver. Every aspect of each project that I undertake is carefully and meticulously designed and documented. In 1997, I started my current project, ''Leonardo's Uterus,'' which is based on the great master's sketchbook drawing titled ''The Infant in the Womb.'' I started with the figure. The head was created separately, which helped me to finalize the body: a 72-inch tall, sewn-fabric, soft sculpture of an adult male. Now I'm designing and producing a series of paper spheres to represent the uterine form.</p>
        <p>Q. Why did you turn Da Vinci's infant into a full-size adult?</p>
        <p>A. When I was a child, my father used to tell me stories about the people who built reinforced metal barrels with the express purpose of riding over Niagara Falls. This fantasy of going over and through the water at Niagara Falls prompted me to think about re-entering my mother's womb, to a peaceful place, where I could look out at life through an imagined window: a viewing portal at my mother's belly button. This led me to create the life-size figure, an adult encased within a protective sphere that could experience life in a totally safe environment.</p>
        <p>Q.  Is it safe to say that your art is a never-ending, seamless process from one idea to the next?</p>
        <p>A. There is always overlap. The ideas come constantly. A good friend of mine said about me, When I think of something and I get scared, I know I am on to something. I want a project that will make me stretch my mind or my thoughts. What I choose to do has to challenge my ability to conceive of and fabricate objects.  Once the challenge is gone, then I find something new.</p>
        <p>Q. About 100 artists are living and working in Peekskill. Why did you move here?</p>
        <p>A. I was prompted to come here by an article given to me by a friend. The article stated that Peekskill had a burgeoning artists' colony. I think there were about 50 artists in Peekskill at that time, and I saw it as a logical and a progressive move for me. I wanted to be around other artists. It's easier to share information about grants or exhibition opportunities when you have a community around you with shared concerns.</p>
        <p>Q. What is it about Peekskill that you like?</p>
        <p>A. Peekskill has some of the area's most interesting architecture. I can walk across the street to the Paramount and see a live concert and a rare movie. The restaurants and shops are innovative, and the river views are stunning. I can walk to the train from here. I also like Peekskill because it is a culturally diverse community. I like the blend of ideas and ideologies.</p>
        <p>Q. Earlier, you talked about a deeper connection to the area. Can you expand on that?</p>
        <p>A. Working here connects me with the lives of my mother and grandmother. They both worked in Peekskill.</p>
        <p>My mother worked at the Paramount as a teenager, and my grandmother worked in the five and dime around the corner. She's 91, and she still lives in Peekskill.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
