<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Indiana Bones</title>
    <meta content="14DOWNEST" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199144"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="CHILDREN'S BOOKS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Downes, Lawrence</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Floca, Brian</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Dinosaurs at the Ends of the Earth (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Columns/Children's Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E4D71F39F937A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="630" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Indiana Bones</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Lawrence Downes</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Downes, Lawrence</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lawrence Downes reviews book Dinosaurs at the Ends of the Earth: The Story of the Central Asiatic Expeditions by Brian Floca; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DINOSAURS</p>
        <p>AT THE ENDS</p>
        <p>OF THE EARTH</p>
        <p>The Story of the</p>
        <p>Central Asiatic Expeditions.</p>
        <p>Written and illustrated</p>
        <p>by Brian Floca.</p>
        <p>Unpaged. New York:</p>
        <p>A Richard Jackson Book/</p>
        <p>DK Ink. $15.95. (Ages 5 to 8)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DINOSAURS</p>
        <p>AT THE ENDS</p>
        <p>OF THE EARTH</p>
        <p>The Story of the</p>
        <p>Central Asiatic Expeditions.</p>
        <p>Written and illustrated</p>
        <p>by Brian Floca.</p>
        <p>Unpaged. New York:</p>
        <p>A Richard Jackson Book/</p>
        <p>DK Ink. $15.95. (Ages 5 to 8)</p>
        <p>HERE is a dinosaur book in which the science-text stuff is pushed to the margins, literally. Basic facts about the dinosaurs in question (their scientific names, sizes, eating habits and places along the geologic time line) are dispensed with inside the front and back covers, and in two helpful pages at the end.</p>
        <p>It's a clever move. While not neglecting his paleontology -- the dinosaur biographies and illustrations are meticulous and lucid -- Brian Floca leaves plenty of room for a thrilling human tale: the 1920's expeditions to Mongolia by fossil hunters from the American Museum of Natural History.</p>
        <p>''Dinosaurs at the Ends of the Earth'' is rich with obligatory dinosaur data, but here the facts essentially become the opening and closing credits of a real-life adventure movie. Its heroes are Roy Chapman Andrews, zoologist and expedition leader; Walter Granger, chief paleontologist and second in command; and George Olsen, assistant in paleontology, looking a lot like Tintin with his felt cap and inquisitive round face.</p>
        <p>By leading an expedition into the Gobi Desert, Andrews had hoped to find evidence of prehistoric humans in Asia. Instead, Floca notes, his team made a discovery that ''amazed the world'' -- one of the world's richest troves of dinosaur fossils, including the first dinosaur eggs ever found.</p>
        <p>This is natural history retold as a David Lean film, in vivid watercolors instead of Cinemascope. Using only one image for each double page gives Floca a wide screen, and he exploits it well to capture the Gobi's vastness: a line of tiny motorcars creeping along under a blazing orange and yellow sky; a supply caravan of 75 camels (I counted) snaking to the horizon.</p>
        <p>There are other classic movie scenes: Voyagers musing by firelight under a black canopy of stars. A wicked sandstorm. A young scientist making a stunning discovery after tumbling down a cliffside. There is even the threat of armed attack, when the expedition is tailed by mysterious horsemen carrying rifles. Asked who they might be, Floca's laconic hero gives a reply worthy of Indiana Jones: '' 'Bandits, most likely,' Andrews said. 'Kula, if our luck's run out. Or maybe renegade Mongolian soldiers. Or renegade Chinese soldiers, and we shouldn't rule out the Russian Bolsheviks. Of course, even czarists are a possibility.' ''</p>
        <p>FLOCA admits taking fictional liberties with his story, but his careful research shows. Children absorbing this tale will probably come away knowing more than they did about the painstaking delicacy of unearthing fossils, the techniques of protecting and packing them for shipment (flour, camel wool and underwear come in handy), the geography of Mongolia, what its nomadic tribespeople wear and even how they build their yurts.</p>
        <p>There's a final pleasant surprise on the back cover of the book: a photograph of the real Roy Chapman Andrews, looking every bit the daring explorer as he cradles a dinosaur egg, a broad-brimmed hat shielding his face from the noonday Gobi sun, a pickax at his feet and a revolver on his hip.</p>
        <p>CHILDREN'S BOOKS Lawrence Downes is an assistant metropolitan editor of The Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Lawrence Downes is an assistant metropolitan editor of The Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
