<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From Last Year's Drought Bloom This Year's Strategies</title>
    <meta content="14WILT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199328"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drought</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ginsburg, Elisabeth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drought</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00EFD6163BF937A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1224" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From Last Year's Drought Bloom This Year's Strategies</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELISABETH GINSBURG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ginsburg, Elisabeth</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on 1999 northeast drought, which is serving as catalyst for New Jersey gardeners to embrace xeriscaping and plant more drought-tolerant varieties; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DROUGHT withers gardens and gardeners alike. The absence of rain last summer acted as a two-edged sword, weakening plants but doing little to deter hungry deer, who are not choosy about whether their vegetation is served up moist or extra-crispy. The parched days, dry winds, voracious varmints and watering restrictions created havoc in gardens all over the tristate area.</p>
        <p>In Pound Ridge, N.Y., azaleas, lovingly swathed in deer fencing, wilted and died in the August heat. In northern New Jersey, purple echinacea, that ''drought-tolerant'' stalwart of the garden, ended up looking like a series of fried cones on brown sticks. People who labored to maintain pristine planting schemes during the early weeks of the drought returned after vacations to find little that was not dried and desolate.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DROUGHT withers gardens and gardeners alike. The absence of rain last summer acted as a two-edged sword, weakening plants but doing little to deter hungry deer, who are not choosy about whether their vegetation is served up moist or extra-crispy. The parched days, dry winds, voracious varmints and watering restrictions created havoc in gardens all over the tristate area.</p>
        <p>In Pound Ridge, N.Y., azaleas, lovingly swathed in deer fencing, wilted and died in the August heat. In northern New Jersey, purple echinacea, that ''drought-tolerant'' stalwart of the garden, ended up looking like a series of fried cones on brown sticks. People who labored to maintain pristine planting schemes during the early weeks of the drought returned after vacations to find little that was not dried and desolate.</p>
        <p>One of the few positive thing about drought is that it can be a catalyst for change in the lives of gardeners who are too timid or tender-hearted to dispatch ailing specimens to the compost pile.</p>
        <p>''Things that died last summer were struggling to begin with,'' said Diane Clark of Freehold. Libby Wagner of White Plains, N.Y., echoed those sentiments, noting that dryness over the past two years resulted in ''cumulative loss,'' especially among shrubs, last summer. Mrs. Clark noted that she had especially bad luck with skimmias, a spring-blooming shrub that prefers moist, shady conditions.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clark and her fellow Freehold gardeners were lucky last summer, because watering restrictions were less stringent than those imposed elsewhere. In Mrs. Clark's five-year-old garden many of the plants were quite young, and needed the  water to compensate for underdeveloped root systems. Despite her best efforts, shallow-rooted plants like dogwoods and azaleas suffered.</p>
        <p>To minimize damage, she used a water meter to gauge the amount of rainfall her garden received every week. Supplemental water was added, when permissible, if rain levels fell below one inch every seven days.</p>
        <p>As the growing season began to wind down, she remained conscientious, ministering to the afflicted specimens. ''Last winter my plants went to sleep with wet feet,'' she said, explaining that those ''wet feet'' will help her plants survive this summer's expected water shortages.</p>
        <p>When Libby Wagner remembers last summer's losses, she thinks about the containers of juniper and the mature shrubs that adorned the grounds of the local women's club where she helps oversee the plantings. On her own property, a ''gorgeous old bay laurel'' lost much of its top growth to the combination of rainless days and dry winds. With luck and a bit of top pruning, the laurel will probably survive.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Wagner said the perennials at the women's club lived through the drought because club members had ''xeriscaped'' the property, using drought-tolerant plant varieties. She is looking into the acquisition of ornamental grass cultivars, which also have a good reputation for survival in lean times. At the women's club, last year's dead shrubs have led to this year's soaker hoses, to be augmented by lots of mulch.</p>
        <p>Even in times of drought, Cornelia Kraft and the other green thumbs who live on Long Island's South Shore can keep their gardens green. The problem, last summer as in summers before, was too much water.  Mrs. Kraft has learned that she cannot plant bulbs in her boggy soil in Islip, because if the deer don't eat them, the surplus moisture rots them.</p>
        <p>As the machinery in the Kraft basement ''pumps out the tide,'' she tends the assortment of primroses, hostas and other plants that thrive in her wet beds. Those beds are enclosed by an eight-foot-tall deer fence to avert other garden horrors. But sometimes even a fence is not enough: a young deer from the nature preserve that bounds her property found a hole in the fence and gorged itself on the well-tended ornamentals. ''There went my lilies,'' said Mrs. Kraft, who also lost a number of other prized plants.</p>
        <p>Outside the deer fence -- now mended --  she installs only plants that deer don't like, such as andromeda and Korean boxwood.  The moisture-loving azaleas and rhododendrons that are so well suited to the damp site and so well loved by the resident deer are swathed in protective netting.</p>
        <p>''A drought does terrible things,'' said Louise Dunn of the Hubbard Heights Gardening Club in Stamford, Conn. Mrs. Dunn was able to get her garden through last summerby watering every other day in accordance with local drought restrictions.  Despite her efforts, she saw many of her annuals fade. ''Impatiens and New Guinea impatiens wilted after a day without watering,'' she said. Potted plants and those in hanging baskets also drooped. Her big hydrangeas ''just wilted,'' eventually producing smaller flower heads than normal.</p>
        <p>Once the restrictions were lifted, Mrs. Dunn was able to revive her suffering annuals with regular doses of water. In anticipation of another dry spell, she has considered substituting less thirsty varieties like ivy geraniums and scaveola for the water-guzzling impatiens. Her husband, who has a passion for dahlias, did not have to worry last summer, and will be able to rest easy this year. The showpiece plants are native to the dry climes of Mexico, and are less sensitive to drought. While some people have installed various irrigation systems in their beds, Mr. and Mrs. Dunn will continue watering the old-fashioned way. ''We are the automatic system,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Like many public-spirited gardeners, Connie Schwaninger of Hicksville, N.Y., labors regularly in a garden that is not her own. In this case the garden is at Good Shepherd Lutheran Church in Hicksville.  Last summer was especially hard on the church's plantings. ''We were away,'' said Mrs. Schwaninger, ''and a three-year-old dogwood did not get deep watering. It shriveled.''</p>
        <p>After her vacation, Mrs. Schwaninger watered and fed the young tree, coaxing it back to health. Now she is planning ahead.  ''We're going away again this summer and I told the minister that someone has to deep water,'' she added.</p>
        <p>Cherry Provost of Glen Ridge y lost two rhododendrons to the summer's heat. ''They were old ones -- 50 to 60 years old,'' she said, ''and they didn't get any water.'' Mrs. Provost has replaced them with five native rhododendron plants in the hope that they will adapt better to local climatic conditions.</p>
        <p>In Mary Patterson's garden, in Greenwich, Conn., plants fared well last summer, but trees were not as lucky. Wooly adelgid, a tenacious pest, populated the drought-stressed hemlocks, and a Douglas fir was afflicted with a fungus. Although she does not usually spray, Mrs. Patterson had the hemlocks sprayed and injected with systemic pesticides to treat the adelgid infestation. The fir tree also received fungicide.</p>
        <p>As a landscape designer, Mrs. Patterson saw pines last summer that had been ''sadly weakened'' by drought and parasitic mites.  This weakening can be at least partly remedied by irrigation, but she called such watering ''a mixed blessing.'' In the garden, drought and disaster survival may have more to do with tough love than tender treatment, said Mrs. Patterson, who summed up the simple plant care philosophy of one of her gardening mentors -- ''They need to be toughened up.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
