<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A New Side of a Familiar Man</title>
    <meta content="14GIUL$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="33" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199561"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prostate Gland</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mayors</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hanover, Donna</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barry, Dan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Prostate Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mayors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prostate Gland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E0DC133BF937A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1721" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A New Side of a Familiar Man</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAN BARRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barry, Dan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York City Mayor Rudolph Giuliani, whose aura of control and invincibility has been admired by many and loathed by others, seems suddenly vulnerable as he tries to cope with breakup of marriage to Donna Hanover, who has publicly accused him of having relationship with another woman, and as he battles recently-diagnosed prostate cancer; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>He has been the man so in control that he could almost be heard setting his jaw. He has been the man who knows what is best for everybody, the man who takes it upon himself to restore morality to Gomorrah on the Hudson. For better, for worse, for seven years, he has been the man.</p>
        <p>Then, over a span of a few days that culminated with an extraordinary news conference on Wednesday, he became someone other than the mayor a city thought it knew. That aura of unquestioning confidence had evaporated; in its wake was revealed a man in pain, ailing and dispirited. Suddenly, Rudolph W. Giuliani seemed on the verge of tears.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>He has been the man so in control that he could almost be heard setting his jaw. He has been the man who knows what is best for everybody, the man who takes it upon himself to restore morality to Gomorrah on the Hudson. For better, for worse, for seven years, he has been the man.</p>
        <p>Then, over a span of a few days that culminated with an extraordinary news conference on Wednesday, he became someone other than the mayor a city thought it knew. That aura of unquestioning confidence had evaporated; in its wake was revealed a man in pain, ailing and dispirited. Suddenly, Rudolph W. Giuliani seemed on the verge of tears.</p>
        <p>The very qualities that some admired and others loathed seemed to have been turned upside down. Here was the man who advocated posting the Ten Commandments in public classrooms, now admitting to a relationship with a woman other than his wife. Here was the champion of public integrity now accused by his wife of having had a relationship with a third woman, a much younger aide who now heads a city-financed agency. Here was the invincible mayor now acknowledging, so very publicly, human weakness.</p>
        <p>It is hard to separate what all this might mean for Rudolph Giuliani the man as opposed to Rudolph Giuliani the presumed candidate for the United States Senate. So blurred is the line between his private and public lives that he announced his desire for a legal separation from his wife, Donna Hanover, at a news conference. Not only did his public sharing stun his wife, it recalled the many times he had dismissed some government study because it had been released before he had been given a copy.</p>
        <p>Asked later why he had delivered the news in a manner that wounded his family and flabbergasted the public, Mr. Giuliani suggested that his performance reflected his sense of leadership. ''It was the most honest, direct and decent way to deal with something that is enormously complex,'' he said. ''So I felt that was the moment that it had to be made.''</p>
        <p>At the close of last week, some people were saying that Mr. Giuliani had handled his personal crises with typical decisiveness. Others were saying that his performance was typical in its harshness; he had devastated his wife in a public forum. Then there were those who were talking as though a new mayor -- a new man -- had been revealed to them.</p>
        <p>''Before, he seemed like a dictator -- you know? -- like iron,'' said Orlando Cienfuegos, 37, an auto mechanic in Nyack, N.Y. ''But now he looks like he wants to cry. Can you see that? Rudy crying?''</p>
        <p>Karen Pettingel, a graphic designer on a break from jury duty in downtown Brooklyn on Thursday, said she, too, was struck by Mr. Giuliani's uncharacteristic display of raw emotion.</p>
        <p>''I always thought of Rudy as some coldblooded reptile kind of thing,'' she said. ''Not to be insulting, but that's how he came off. But now he has problems that all of us can relate to. And watching him on the TV last night just nearly broke my heart.''</p>
        <p>Some of Mr. Giuliani's friends and advisers agree. A few said they did not care whether he runs for the Senate; they were more concerned about his wife, his two young children, his overall well-being. Matters have temporarily spun out of control for the controlling mayor, they said, and understandably so.</p>
        <p>He has an extremely difficult job, he is running for higher office, his own actions have led to the probable breakup of his marriage -- and he just learned that he has the disease that killed his beloved father.</p>
        <p>Cancer has a way of getting one's attention, even if early detection means a likely cure. In cases of prostate cancer, the kind that the mayor has, treatment can also lead to impotence or incontinence. And the blithe discussion in some quarters of the mayor's cancer being treatable does not reflect the terror he may feel, or the need he might sense for reassessing his priorities.</p>
        <p>As with any person faced with such issues, someone close to Mr. Giuliani said, ''he has started to review his life.'' The only wrinkle is, that review is unfolding in public.</p>
        <p>There was a time, not so long ago, when Mr. Giuliani's friends and advisers struggled to convince skeptical reporters that the mayor did indeed have a warm, personal side. Fault him for not always being empathetic, they would say, but know that he is an intensely dedicated family man whose moral leadership is needed by a city at sea.</p>
        <p>But the comments of the mayor and his wife last week confirm what has been long suspected. Despite his  ''Father Knows Best'' public persona, Mr. Giuliani's private decisions are far from black and white.</p>
        <p>A shaken Ms. Hanover announced that for a long time she did not participate in her husband's public life because of his close relationship with his communications director, Cristyne Lategano-Nicholas. Although the mayor and his former aide repeated their longstanding denials of an affair, Ms. Hanover's comments indicate that the emotional attachment the mayor shared with Ms. Lategano-Nicholas deeply hurt her.</p>
        <p>Ms. Hanover said that last May -- the same month that Ms. Lategano-Nicholas left the administration -- she made a ''major effort'' to restore her marital bond with Mr. Giuliani. ''Rudy and I re-established some of our personal intimacy through the fall,'' she said. ''At that point he chose another path.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Hanover was alluding to a relationship that her husband had developed with Judith Nathan, a divorced executive who lives with her teenage daughter on the Upper East Side. Through the fall and into this year, Ms. Nathan has been, in effect, hiding in plain sight -- attending various events at Gracie Mansion and City Hall, dining out with the mayor and having him as a guest at her condominium in Southampton, N.Y.</p>
        <p>It was a side of Mr. Giuliani never quite seen before. Having long maintained that his private life was no one's business but his own, he was now stopping just short of flaunting a relationship with someone other than his wife. He began appearing without his wedding ring.</p>
        <p>At the same time, Mr. Giuliani was running a Senate campaign that seemed to rely more on verbal brickbats than on statewide travel. A traditionally moderate Republican, he suddenly sought to distinguish his views from those of his would-be Democratic opponent, Hillary Rodham Clinton, by attacking her as hostile to ''America's religious traditions'' and opposed to posting the Ten Commandments in public schools.</p>
        <p>He then delivered a curious taunt: As a joke, he flashed a picture of the Ten Commandments at the end of a slide presentation at City Hall.</p>
        <p>Much of the laughter ended 18 days ago when, with refreshing and reassuring candor, Mr. Giuliani revealed that he had prostate cancer. Since then, it seems, time has been marked by tabloid headlines:</p>
        <p>''Cancer News Moved Rudy to Tears, Pal Says''; ''Dinner Belle: Rudy Eats With Gal Pal 'Every Night' ''; ''Donna's Dilemma: Mayor's Wife Says 'Decisions' Have to Be Made''; ''GOP Honcho's Advice to Rudy on Marriage Mess: Work It Out.''</p>
        <p>That last headline, from The New York Post, referred to concerns that the State Senate majority leader, Joseph L. Bruno, had expressed about the mayor's Senate campaign, concerns that are said to be shared by other state Republican leaders. Mr. Giuliani later said that it was the headline that moved him to go public with his private problems.</p>
        <p>''It seemed to me that I had to move forward, and that something had to move forward,'' he said. ''Because the whole complex of the decisions that I have to make -- including about my health -- and I guess part of that is also straightening out your personal life.''</p>
        <p>And so last Wednesday, at Bryant Park, a different Rudy Giuliani spoke to the city's press corps: one with averting eyes and an apologetic manner. He said that he would be seeking a legal separation from his wife; that he accepted responsibility for everything he had done; that he and those close to him had been going through a very painful period; that given his illness, he might rely on Ms. Nathan ''more now than maybe I did before.''</p>
        <p>''My emotional state is, I'm very sad,'' he said. ''And I feel terrible.''</p>
        <p>Afterward, even those close to him asked why he had done it. He had rattled the Republican leadership, given tacit license to the media to delve further into the lives of those around him, and all but invited Ms. Hanover to lash back. It was as though he had turned the mayor's lectern into a confessional.</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani is clearly in the throes of a personal evaluation, they say -- about his political future, about his sources of comfort, about the preciousness of life. And such evaluations are rarely neat, especially those partially conducted in public.</p>
        <p>''It's a tough time,'' one adviser said. ''Certainly his human side is showing in a way he's never allowed to be shown before. If anything, it shows that he has that side -- that he's mortal like the rest of us, vulnerable like the rest of us.''</p>
        <p>Some people have not been so understanding. One former public official said that what the mayor presented to the public last week was ''puritanical self-destruction'' -- a rigid prosecutor ''now turning on himself.'' Another former official said the mayor was in the midst of learning what the mighty and sanctimonious sometimes forget: ''Yo, you too are a human being, and no one's bigger than the game.''</p>
        <p>But Susan Orlean, a 40-year-old bank teller in Nyack, said she had been left with a different impression, one informed by the fact that she is going through an amicable divorce after 10 years of marriage.</p>
        <p>''I don't like the mayor,'' she said. ''I think he runs the city like it was his own, and not the people's. But if I don't vote for him -- and I really don't think I will -- it won't be because of his marriage problems. That part of him I sort of understand.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
