<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>INVESTING WITH: Kent Simons; Neuberger Berman Focus Fund</title>
    <meta content="14INVO$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199468"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gould, Carole</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Simons, Kent</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Investing With</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E3DD153BF937A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1010" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>INVESTING WITH: Kent Simons; Neuberger Berman Focus Fund</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAROLE GOULD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gould, Carole</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with Newuberger Berman Forcus fund m</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ONCE a month, Kent Simons plays poker with six friends at a neighbor's apartment, on Manhattan's East Side. ''I'm a very disciplined investor,'' he said, ''but as a poker player, I'm the equivalent of an online day trader.'' The stakes are small: an ante of 50 cents and a limit on bets of $1. Still, Mr. Simons, who runs the $1.91 billion Neuberger  Berman Focus fund, figures that he has broken even over time.</p>
        <p>But he has done far better with his portfolio. The fund returned 19.6 percent a year, on average, for the three years through May 5, versus 11.0  percent for its peers in the large value category, according to Morningstar Inc.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ONCE a month, Kent Simons plays poker with six friends at a neighbor's apartment, on Manhattan's East Side. ''I'm a very disciplined investor,'' he said, ''but as a poker player, I'm the equivalent of an online day trader.'' The stakes are small: an ante of 50 cents and a limit on bets of $1. Still, Mr. Simons, who runs the $1.91 billion Neuberger  Berman Focus fund, figures that he has broken even over time.</p>
        <p>But he has done far better with his portfolio. The fund returned 19.6 percent a year, on average, for the three years through May 5, versus 11.0  percent for its peers in the large value category, according to Morningstar Inc.</p>
        <p>Mr. Simons, 65, looks for companies that sell at fat discounts to the price-to-earnings multiple of the Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index but that have five-year earnings growth projections exceeding that of the index. The current average multiple of the portfolio's 30 companies is 15.4, just 60 percent of the S.&amp; P.'s, while estimates of the portfolio's five-year earnings growth average 18.6 percent, annualized, versus 17.7 percent for the index.</p>
        <p>Mr. Simons dismisses some of the most common tools of value investing. ''Book value can be misleading,'' he said, ''and I haven't found dividend yields to be a valuable way to screen for good companies.''</p>
        <p>Nor does he spend much time looking for the elusive so-called catalysts  that many value investors see as the key to finding beaten-down companies whose stocks are about to climb. ''Usually at the time companies are most attractive,'' he said, ''no one can think of a catalyst that will reverse its out-of-favor status.''</p>
        <p>Of course, many mutual fund managers -- of either value or growth portfolios -- try to maintain sector weightings similar to those of the S. &amp; P. 500. That strategy is wrong, Mr. Simons contended.</p>
        <p>''Most of the time, value is not evenly distributed across all sectors of the market,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Simons uses a computer model that screens for companies with superior earnings characteristics and picks companies whose returns on equity exceed that of the S.&amp; P. 500 average, now 24 percent.</p>
        <p>He then delves into the specifics of each company, looking closely at the track record of management and asking it about its goals and its plans for achieving them.</p>
        <p>The fund's prospectus mandates that Mr. Simons invest 90 percent of the fund's assets in no more than 6 of the 13 sectors of the S.&amp; P. 500. It now  has about 30 percent of its assets in technology stocks and less than 10 percent each in retailing, health care and transportation.</p>
        <p>But the remainder of the portfolio -- about half the total -- is in financial services. ''I think the outlook for the sector is better than it has been in years -- maybe ever,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Although the five interest-rate increases by the Federal Reserve have affected the psychology of investors,  prompting them to sell off financial stocks over the last year, Mr. Simons said, the earnings of the companies themselves have remained healthy. ''People are finally realizing that if interest rates rise, especially in an orderly fashion, financial service companies can adapt,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Simons' favorites are global powerhouses -- those with both institutional and retail presences, as well as strong balance sheets and plenty of equity to make acquisitions.</p>
        <p>He likes Chase Manhattan, which accounts for about 5 percent of the portfolio. ''It's viewed as a money center bank,'' he said, ''but it's transformed itself into a full-service financial services company.''</p>
        <p>CHASE'S $7.7 billion acquisition of Robert Fleming Holdings, the British investment bank, announced last month, will accelerate profit growth, he said. He predicts a three-year earnings growth rate of 15 percent, annualized; the company's 12-month return on equity is 26 percent.</p>
        <p>He first bought shares in September 1997 at $59.25; they closed on Friday at $71.625, or 10.2 times his earnings estimate of $7 a share for next year.</p>
        <p>Another favorite is Citigroup, which accounts for about 10 percent of assets. It stands to benefit from consumers' growing attraction to one-stop financial shopping, he said, adding, ''No one else can match their product breadth.''</p>
        <p>Some people contend that Sanford I. Weill, the Citigroup chief executive, is running a one-man show, in part because of the departure last month of John S. Reed, the former co-chief executive. But Mr. Simons calls management ''stronger and deeper than Wall Street gives them credit for,'' citing as an example the hiring of former Treasury Secretary Robert E. Rubin as chairman of the executive committee last October.</p>
        <p>Mr. Simons began buying the stock of a Citigroup predecessor, Primerica, more than 10 years ago at the prorated equivalent of $2.75 a share; Citigroup now trades at $60.1875, or 14.7 times his 2001 earnings estimate of $4.10 a share. Its 12-month return on equity is 30 percent.</p>
        <p>In technology stocks, Mr. Simons likes Tech Data, a Clearwater, Fla., distributor of personal computers, software, and networking gear. But is it a true technology concern? ''I would argue that it certainly benefits from favorable trends in technology,'' he said. ''And you don't have to guess which company will win the software, networking or PC wars.''</p>
        <p>He expects the company's earnings to grow 15 to 20 percent a year. Its 12-month return on equity is 13 percent. He originally bought shares in July at an average price of $30; they now trade at $39.625, or 14.2 times his earnings estimate of $2.80 a share.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
