<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Street-Name Plan Sparks a Jeffersonian Debate</title>
    <meta content="14HEMM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199532"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Deoxyribonucleic Acid</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Streets</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Charlottesville (Va)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Monticello Assn</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jefferson, Thomas (1743-1826)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hemings, Sally</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Westerinen, Dorothy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Daugherty, Virginia (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clines, Francis X</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Virginia/Charlottesville</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">DNA (Deoxyribonucleic Acid)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03EED6123BF937A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1037" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Street-Name Plan Sparks a Jeffersonian Debate</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANCIS X. CLINES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Clines, Francis X</byline>
      <dateline>CHARLOTTESVILLE, Va., May 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Proposal to name street in Charlottesville, Virginia, for Sally Hemings sparks debate among descendants of Thomas Jefferson and area blacks uncomfortable with story of Hemings as his slave and possible mistress; photo; Mayor Virginia Daugherty notes Hemings family's importance in town; Dorothy Westerinen, descendant of Hemings and possibly Jefferson as well, reports on continuing arguments within Monticello Assn on validity of recent DNA evidence (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>This American classic city is about to acknowledge a Faulknerian chapter and consider naming a street Hemings Way after Sally Hemings, the slave of Thomas Jefferson who, the scholars of Monticello concede, was almost certainly the mother of at least one of his children.</p>
        <p>''For people raised with the belief that this was a moral impossibility, it's not an easy transition,'' said Cinder Stanton, one of the Monticello historians in the eye of a double-edged storm.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>This American classic city is about to acknowledge a Faulknerian chapter and consider naming a street Hemings Way after Sally Hemings, the slave of Thomas Jefferson who, the scholars of Monticello concede, was almost certainly the mother of at least one of his children.</p>
        <p>''For people raised with the belief that this was a moral impossibility, it's not an easy transition,'' said Cinder Stanton, one of the Monticello historians in the eye of a double-edged storm.</p>
        <p>On one front, dissenters in the Jefferson bloodline are fighting the latest DNA evidence of Jefferson's paternity as they heatedly deny the kinship claims of Hemings's African-American descendants.</p>
        <p>On the other front, the street-naming proposal, which is expected to move to the City Council next month, is being denounced by some black residents as an affront to the countless other former slave families who helped build this city with all manner of distinction.</p>
        <p>''In naming Hemings to this supposed status, we are not honoring her but Jefferson and the institution of slavery that defiled and demeaned our ancestors,'' said Agnes Cross-White, editor of The Tribune, the local black community newspaper. Ms. Cross-White has been thundering against the street naming and arguing for a public memorial far more inclusive of local slave history.</p>
        <p>''Are we so devoid of self-esteem that we will accept and cling to anything white because it makes us feel more valuable, more American?'' Ms. Cross-White asked. She dismissed the street-name proposal as an attempt to mine tourist gold from a bit of underground history long denied by the white establishment until modern science rendered the issue moot, at least for the keepers of Monticello, the Jefferson family estate.</p>
        <p>On a human level, the controversy bubbling here suggests that Jefferson's continuing legacy in this fruitful Blue Ridge Valley region includes all the fighting that typically defines one man's family.</p>
        <p>''We're white, we're black and we're in between,'' said Dorothy Westerinen, more proud of bearing Hemings's blood than any tincture of Jefferson's. She holds that both the Hemings family and American history would be well honored by having the Hemings name on a strip of West 10th Street, next to a Main Street motel that is now on a plot where Sally Hemings lived and died after slavery.</p>
        <p>Ms. Westerinen journeyed here from her home in Staten Island last weekend with other Hemings descendants from across the nation. They held another inconclusive meeting with the Monticello Association, a group of Jefferson descendants wrestling with the question of whether to admit Hemings kin to membership in the association, a privilege that includes the right of burial in the cemetery on the grounds of Monticello.</p>
        <p>''It got pretty ugly,'' Ms. Westerinen said of the closed meeting. ''Most of the association members were lovely toward us, but a faction that's splintering off from the main group grew particularly insulting, especially toward the Monticello historians trying to explain the facts.''</p>
        <p>After the meeting, the association said in a statement that the delay was due to ''the complexity of the issues.'' But the new splinter group, led by John H. Works Jr., a Jefferson descendant, is resolved to fight the paternity finding.</p>
        <p>In November 1998, DNA test results linked the two family lines by way of Jefferson, and in January the likelihood was confirmed on the basis of parallel historic evidence by scholars at the Thomas Jefferson Memorial Foundation, which runs Monticello.</p>
        <p>''They did not pin it on Thomas Jefferson,'' Mr. Works insisted. He is among those who deny the evidence and argue that even if it is true, some other Jefferson male might have been the father.</p>
        <p>''I just want to see the truth remembered,'' said Kevin Cox, a resident concerned that this city of 40,000 not shy away from the rough edges of its history.</p>
        <p>As the two extended families ponder their disunity, the city fathers will go ahead with consideration of the Hemings Way proposal, Mayor Virginia Daugherty said.</p>
        <p>''I'm supporting it because the whole Hemings family was very important in our early history here,'' Ms. Daugherty said. ''Her family eventually owned 12 different pieces of property around town. This issue is all about our own sense of ourselves as a city and what we would like to pass along to our children.''</p>
        <p>The mayor is supported by Dianne Swann-Wright, one of the Monticello historians who confirmed the paternity evidence. Ms. Swann-Wright stresses that the Hemings tale embraces ''unknown acts of courage, discipline and steadfastness'' that are universal in human experience.</p>
        <p>''I say, name the corridor after all of them, in honor of them and in honor of us,'' Ms. Swann-Wright said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Cross-White, the editor of The Tribune, raised the Groucho Marx question, asking ''why anyone would want to belong to this association based on the fact that Jefferson was a man who took lecherous advantage of his property.'' Local blacks, she said, laugh off the romantic television docudramas about the affair but pay tribute to Hemings for having prevailed through unimaginably difficult trials.</p>
        <p>''If she could make her life and the lives of her children more tolerable by being the physical interest of the master, then more power to the sister,'' Ms. Cross-White said.</p>
        <p>But Hemings's descendants emphasize that the issue actually involves the larger family of America itself. They promise to continue pressing Jeffersonian bluebloods to acknowledge their black enrichment.</p>
        <p>''Personally, I couldn't care less about membership or where I'm buried,'' Ms. Westerinen said. ''We want our family to recognize us, to embrace us. And that's a very important symbolic gesture for the rest of the nation to see. I'm proud of Sally Hemings. She put up with a hell of a lot from him.''</p>
        <p>And so must this city, Ms. Cross-White said.</p>
        <p>''We're living with Thomas Jefferson every single day,'' she noted wearily. ''He's still walking the streets of this city.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
