<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Owners' Insurance In a Co-op</title>
    <meta content="14QAQA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199230"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="Q. &amp; A."/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E0DC1138F937A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="558" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Owners' Insurance In a Co-op</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Q I am involved in the ownership of a co-op building in New York. Recently, we had a pipe freeze in the building and three apartments were damaged. The owners of two of the apartments did not have homeowners insurance. Can we require all shareholders to carry homeowners insurance? . . . Howard Rosenthal, Flushing, Queens.</p>
        <p>A Eliot H. Zuckerman, a Manhattan co-op lawyer, said that all tenant-shareholders of a co-op can be required to carry homeowners insurance if the proprietary lease contains a provision to that effect. If it does not, Mr. Zuckerman said, the lease can be amended to include such a requirement.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Q I am involved in the ownership of a co-op building in New York. Recently, we had a pipe freeze in the building and three apartments were damaged. The owners of two of the apartments did not have homeowners insurance. Can we require all shareholders to carry homeowners insurance? . . . Howard Rosenthal, Flushing, Queens.</p>
        <p>A Eliot H. Zuckerman, a Manhattan co-op lawyer, said that all tenant-shareholders of a co-op can be required to carry homeowners insurance if the proprietary lease contains a provision to that effect. If it does not, Mr. Zuckerman said, the lease can be amended to include such a requirement.</p>
        <p>In most cases, he said, to amend the proprietary lease, a notice of the proposed amendment must be included in a notice of a shareholders meeting.</p>
        <p>''Passing such an amendment would likely require the affirmative vote of holders of at least two-thirds, and in some cases three-quarters, of all of the outstanding stock of the co-op,'' Mr. Zuckerman said.</p>
        <p>He added that the required homeowners insurance should include both property-loss coverage and liability coverage. The minimum coverages required should be specified in the proposed amendment, Mr. Zuckerman said, and, for the benefit of those who do not already carry such coverage, estimates of one or more premium quotes for the amount of minimum coverage should also be made available.</p>
        <p>Business Use Of a Co-op Sublet</p>
        <p>Q I am a tenant in a co-op sublet. My sublease agreement states that the apartment may be used for residential purposes only. With the Internet and breakthroughs in electronic communications, however, it is now unnecessary for me to commute to my office for work. Would a home office violate my sublease if I merely receive business mail and packages at home, but do not see any clients? . . . Avi Kvaran, Bronx.</p>
        <p>A Peter Schwartz, a Manhattan landlord-tenant lawyer, said that even though the lease provides that the apartment may be used for residential purposes only, it is unlikely that a court would consider the use of the apartment as a home office as a substantial violation of the lease.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schwartz said that the courts will generally permit a residential tenant to use an apartment as a home office as long as the business use does not disturb other tenants, damage the property, materially affect the character of the building or violate the New York City Zoning Code.</p>
        <p>''The courts basically look at whether the business use has a negative impact on the building,'' he said.  ''And it would seem to me that if the letter writer merely receives business mail and packages at his apartment, that should not affect the character of the building or disturb other tenants.''</p>
        <p>He added that the New York City Zoning Code generally permits the use of a residential premises for professional purposes as long as the business use is incidental to the residential use. ''That means that you live there and are using a part of your home as your office,'' Mr. Schwartz said.</p>
        <p>Q. &amp; A.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
