<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sierra Leone's Slide Back to Warlord Rule Draws In U.N.</title>
    <meta content="14LEON$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199567"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Diamonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mines and Mining</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sierra Leone</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kabbah, Ahmed Tejan (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Koroma, Johnny Paul</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sankoh, Foday</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Onishi, Norimitsu</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Sierra Leone</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Sierra Leone</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mines and Mining</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diamonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geography</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E0DB133BF937A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1648" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sierra Leone's Slide Back to Warlord Rule Draws In U.N.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NORIMITSU ONISHI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Onishi, Norimitsu</byline>
      <dateline>FREETOWN, Sierra Leone, May 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sierra Leone, state in name only, slides back into rule by warlords ensconced in different regions, each with access to enough diamond mines to buy arms; nine-month-old peace accord collapses and Pres Ahmed Tejan Kabbah is rendered powerless by rise of warlords like Foday Sankoh and Johnny Paul Koroma; photos; map; difference now is that UN peacekeepers are in midst of chaos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For years, warlordism has ruled over Sierra Leone, a state in name alone. With the authority of the government barely extending beyond Freetown, warlords have been ensconced in different corners of the country, each with access to enough diamond mines to buy arms. The balance of power shifted occasionally, depending on the energies of a Nigerian-led intervention force or mercenaries hired by the government.</p>
        <p>Today, with the apparent collapse of a nine-month-old peace accord, Sierra Leone is on the verge of slipping back into warlordism. The Nigerians, whose departure less than two weeks ago led the top warlord, Foday Sankoh, to challenge the United Nations force, are on their way back.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For years, warlordism has ruled over Sierra Leone, a state in name alone. With the authority of the government barely extending beyond Freetown, warlords have been ensconced in different corners of the country, each with access to enough diamond mines to buy arms. The balance of power shifted occasionally, depending on the energies of a Nigerian-led intervention force or mercenaries hired by the government.</p>
        <p>Today, with the apparent collapse of a nine-month-old peace accord, Sierra Leone is on the verge of slipping back into warlordism. The Nigerians, whose departure less than two weeks ago led the top warlord, Foday Sankoh, to challenge the United Nations force, are on their way back.</p>
        <p>The big difference now is that United Nations peacekeepers are in the middle of all this, and an increasing number of British paratroopers is under pressure to provide more muscle. While the peacekeepers arrived with the understanding that they would be a neutral force, they have become allied with the Sierra Leone Army; the soldiers of another warlord, a born-again Christian named Lt. Col. Johnny Paul Koroma, and a militia controlled by Hinga Norman, nominally a deputy defense minister, all against Mr. Sankoh.</p>
        <p>Having clambered over the back wall of his house this week when United Nations peacekeepers were not around, Mr. Sankoh, a potbellied 63-year-old with a reportedly bad heart, is on the run. Many suspect that he has somehow fled far from the capital, perhaps as far as Liberia, a redoubt from which he has often marshaled his forces during this country's nine-year civil war.</p>
        <p>In his absence, two men who have long commanded personal militias of their own have re-emerged as power brokers. Their troops helped repel an assault on Freetown by Mr. Sankoh's Revolutionary United Front, known as the R.U.F., when it became clear that the United Nations force was unable to do that by itself.</p>
        <p>At ease inside his home office, wearing a green robe and slippers, Colonel Koroma, retired from the Sierra Leonean army since he briefly held power after a coup in 1997, smiled when he was asked the number of soldiers at his disposal.</p>
        <p>He declined to say. But the number was significant, judging from the thousands of loyalists who surfaced on the streets, armed with automatic rifles, after he spoke on national radio. Colonel Koroma told his men to rearm, though not before shouting ''Jesus'' for five minutes at 6 P.M.</p>
        <p>Across town, Mr. Norman gave orders from his office inside the Ministry of Defense. He derives his power from his Kamajor militia, the thousands of tribal hunters who have traditionally sided with the government. Mr. Norman's men gird themselves for battle by applying oil on their skin, putting on wigs, mirrors, horns, and reciting verses from the Koran and Bible -- so that ''they will be saved from R.U.F. bullets,'' Mr. Norman said.</p>
        <p>''I believe these things can work,'' the deputy defense minister said.</p>
        <p>The reemergence of warlordism in Sierra Leone has led experts to draw parallels with Somalia, the West's traumatic experience with peacekeeping in Africa. The comparison is one reason why Washington seems ready to weather criticism rather than become directly engaged in Sierra Leone, and why the British keep insisting that they are here merely to evacuate Europeans and offer technical assistance, even as their presence at the front line becomes clearer day by day.</p>
        <p>''Sierra Leone is in serious danger of being mired in violence again with the looming possibility of turning into another Somalia, a state now being run by bands of warlords,'' Roble Olhaye, the ambassador from Djibouti to the United Nations, said at the Security Council's first public debate on Sierra Leone on Thursday. Mr. Olhaye, whose country borders Somalia, added, ''We cannot abandon Sierra Leone.''</p>
        <p>In Somalia, the United Nations also found itself trying to keep peace in a stateless territory riven by clan warfare, alongside American troops under direct American command. There, too, they came to oppose one warlord, Gen. Mohammed Farah Aideed. The operation came to a disastrous end when 18 American soldiers were killed during an attack on General Aideed, and one American's body was dragged through the streets of Mogadishu.</p>
        <p>Somalia traumatized the West, especially the United States, in such a way that the United Nations remained paralyzed in the face of large-scale massacres in Rwanda in 1994. At least half a million Tutsi were killed in an event that directly led to the later war in the Congo.</p>
        <p>If Sierra Leone is considered a test of the West's resolve in African peacekeeping, it is because Congo presents the same problems -- though on a grander scale. Congo, where the United Nations is considering sending a peacekeeping force, is the size of Western Europe. There, too, the government's authority is limited to the capital, Kinshasa.</p>
        <p>During the cold war, the late dictator Mobutu Sese Seko could count on the West to provide money and arms. Now, Congolese warlords, armies from five foreign countries, and innumerable militias have carved up the Congo into various strongholds, plundering its mineral riches to buy arms. President Laurent Kabila, who was for decades a small-scale warlord in the Congo's northeast, is the head of the country's central government.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kabila may not be a warlord, technically. But in his persistent efforts to block his country's peace negotiations, he is surely one of the ''national leaders who are so insular, whose vision is so narrow, that in their concerns about their own power and survival, the interests of their people don't count,'' as Secretary General Kofi Annan said on Friday, describing leaders who made peacekeeping a much more complex operation than in the past.</p>
        <p>Here in Sierra Leone, the warlords seem to be back at war with one another. Even if the fighting is contained in the near future, the warlords have gained legitimacy and power as the government and United Nations had no choice but to become allied with them.</p>
        <p>It is an uneasy alliance, especially the one between the government and Colonel Koroma. The government in theory has 5,000 soldiers, but Colonel Koroma is considered the real force behind the military.</p>
        <p>In 1997, Colonel Koroma, now 40, overthrew the elected government of Ahmed Tejan Kabbah and then invited Mr. Sankoh's group to join him in power. At his home on Friday, he said he had done so ''in the interest of peace.''</p>
        <p>''The only way we can end this war is to call these guys out of the bush and talk to them,'' he said. ''So we invited them to come out. If we said we are going to end it militarily, we will never succeed.''</p>
        <p>Whatever his real motives, the Nigerians expelled him in 1998 and reinstalled President Kabbah. Over the next year, Colonel Koroma and Mr. Sankoh's followers fought together to regain power, culminating in a January 1999 attack on Freetown, during which thousands of civilians were killed, raped or maimed.</p>
        <p>Since the peace accord was signed last July, Colonel Koroma had served as the chairman of the committee for the consolidation of peace in a power-sharing government.</p>
        <p>''We found him to be reasonably remorseful of whatever it is that he may have done in the past,'' said Septimus Kaikai, President Kabbah's spokesman. He added, for example, that Colonel Koroma on his own had visited a Freetown camp for amputees, whereas Mr. Sankoh never had. ''We found that he was willing to work with us to resolve the crisis in the country. And we were reasonably happy with some of the things that he has been doing.''</p>
        <p>''Is there a risk here?'' Mr. Kaikai added. ''If you take note of the fact that there is risk involved in everything we do, yes, there's a certain amount of risk involved.''</p>
        <p>President Kabbah, a former United Nations Development Program official, has proven to be a powerless, nearly irrelevant, figure who seldom leaves his hilltop mansion. And so a greater amount of risk may derive from Colonel Koroma's alliance with Mr. Norman.</p>
        <p>The two groups had fought each other for years, but now find themselves allied against Mr. Sankoh.</p>
        <p>The Kamajors, who are mostly traditional hunters from the south, began fighting in the early 1990's. Mr. Norman, 60, a former soldier who was convicted of treason and  jailed from 1968 to 1974, became the Kamajors' leader in 1994.</p>
        <p>Made up entirely of volunteers, the Kamajor militia are thought to number around 15,000, though Mr. Norman claims that their real number is 100,000.</p>
        <p>''We are quarreling bedmates,'' Mr. Norman said of his new alliance with Colonel Koroma. ''We are trying hard to build confidence.''</p>
        <p>As for Mr. Sankoh, he has not been spotted in Freetown since climbing over his back wall. Many believe that without him, his rebel group will splinter into various factions led by sub-warlords.</p>
        <p>His most serious rival, Sam ''Mosquito'' Bockarie, fled to Liberia after a falling out with Mr. Sankoh late last year. ''Mosquito,'' as he is known, is believed to be waiting for a chance to return. But a few months ago, a man purporting to be an opponent of Mr. Bockarie called BBC radio and made wild threats.</p>
        <p>The caller's name? ''Mosquito Spray.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
