<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In New Haven, It's an Adventure in Cuisine</title>
    <meta content="14DINE$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199290"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DINING OUT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Lalibela (New Haven, Conn, Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brooks, Patricia</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E0DA1F38F937A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="879" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In New Haven, It's an Adventure in Cuisine</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICIA BROOKS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brooks, Patricia</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Patricia Brooks reviews Lalibela, Ethiopian restaurant in New Haven, Conn (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NEW HAVEN continues to surprise us with its varied ethnic restaurants. The latest is Lalibela, named in honor of an ancient Ethiopian king and specializing in the food of that African country. This small, attractive newcomer seems well-suited to a college town for three reasons: modest prices, vegetarian dishes and an informal style of dining.</p>
        <p>We cherished fond memories of dining Ethiopian style in Chicago and New York with sizeable groups of friends, when everyone dug in with gusto, scooping up the food with torn segments of an unusual spongy bread called injera. No forks required or provided.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NEW HAVEN continues to surprise us with its varied ethnic restaurants. The latest is Lalibela, named in honor of an ancient Ethiopian king and specializing in the food of that African country. This small, attractive newcomer seems well-suited to a college town for three reasons: modest prices, vegetarian dishes and an informal style of dining.</p>
        <p>We cherished fond memories of dining Ethiopian style in Chicago and New York with sizeable groups of friends, when everyone dug in with gusto, scooping up the food with torn segments of an unusual spongy bread called injera. No forks required or provided.</p>
        <p>We were a much smaller group in New Haven, but four of us managed to make quick work of a number of dishes on Lalibela's short menu.</p>
        <p>First, our friendly waitress, wearing a long traditional Ethiopian dress, brought one of our appetizers, senge karya, which consisted of two long uncooked peppers filled with a mixture of sauteed fresh tomato, onion, garlic and shallots. With the dish came a basket of what looked like Ace bandages. These turned out to be rolled-up injera, the thin, soft sourdough bread. We broke off pieces to shovel up bits of the pepper and its filling -- and quickly discovered how fiery the pepper itself was. The injera came in handy also with keyser selata, a salad of finely chopped beets, potatoes, carrots, shallots and green peppers, though forks were provided. This too proved to be a fresh-tasting dish, mildly seasoned.</p>
        <p>A favorite appetizer was sambusa, two large, crisp and flaky pastry tricorns filled with ground beef, served oven-hot, reminiscent in shape of the Indian appetizer samosa. The crust in this case had excellent flavor and complemented the filling. The dish was pepped up by a chickpea paste with red pepper, jalapenos, parsley and garlic.</p>
        <p>The real communal fun began with our entrees. First, the waitress appeared with a large round platter, lined with a huge, thin crepe-like injera. On the injera, well separated, were three additions. One was chopped, cooked collard greens. A second was well-simmered red lentils, vigorously spiced with garlic, cardamom and berbere, an Ethiopian seasoning made with sun-dried chili peppers. The mild third consisted of yellow split peas mixed with ginger, garlic and white pepper. All three provided welcome accents to our entrees, which arrived in little bowls, along with more of the bandage-roll injera.</p>
        <p>The drill was to spoon portions of the entrees on to the platter, then scoop up bites with the smaller pieces of injera. Our best dish was shuro wat, one of seven vegetarian offerings. It consisted of highly seasoned chickpeas, cooked almost to a pudding stage in a fiery berbere sauce. Its soft texture lent itself to easy manipulation with the injera. One might call this an Ethiopian version of nursery food, but considerably spicier.</p>
        <p>Doro wat consisted of pieces of chicken cooked in butter, then simmered in a rich, dark brown, aromatic sauce made with onions, garlic, fresh ginger, berbere and herbs. Also pleasing was fosolia, a casserole of green beans, carrots and onions, simmered together with herbs.</p>
        <p>Not quite up to the level of the rest of the meal was gored gored, a generous bowl of cubed beef marinated in red wine and rosemary, then sauteed in nitir kibe (clarified butter), with onion, garlic, chili pepper and herbs. The meat, despite all the cooking, was tough and the sauce oily. Even the injera couldn't neutralize it.</p>
        <p>There are several Western style desserts served at Lalibela. The chocolate mousse cake in a graham cracker crust made an especially sweet ending to our meal.</p>
        <p>A three-course dinner for four, before drinks, tax or tip, came to $70. There is a very modest wine list and a few specialty beers, all reasonably priced.</p>
        <p>If you are feeling adventurous, willing to try something different and experience palate-expanding sensations and combinations, dining at Lalibela can provide a convivial and rewarding evening, especially if you go in a group of four or more. Goodness knows, the price is right.</p>
        <p>Lalibela</p>
        <p>176 Temple Street, New Haven  (203) 789-1232</p>
        <p>Good</p>
        <p>ATMOSPHERE -- A long narrow dining room, light and airy, decorated with Ethiopean art and artifacts. Noise level: Subdued, conversational.</p>
        <p>SERVICE -- Friendly, sweet and helpful.</p>
        <p>RECOMMENDED DISHES -- Sambusa, keyser selata, senge karya, fosolia, shuro wat, doro wat, chocolate mousse cheesecake.</p>
        <p>PRICE RANGE -- Lunch entrees $6 to $15, dinner entrees $8.25 to $15.</p>
        <p>CREDIT CARDS -- American Express, Mastercard, Visa.</p>
        <p>HOURS -- Noon to 2 p.m. Monday through Friday, 5 to 10 p.m. Sunday through Thursday, 5 to 11 p.m. Friday and Saturday.</p>
        <p>RESERVATIONS -- Accepted.</p>
        <p>WHEELCHAIR ACCESSIBILITY -- Dining rooms and restrooms at ground level.</p>
        <p>THE RATINGS Extraordinary, Excellent, Very Good, Good, Poor to Satisfactory.</p>
        <p>Ratings reflect the reviewer's reaction to food, ambiance and service, with price taken into consideration. Menu listings and prices are subject to change.</p>
        <p>DINING OUT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
