<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Nation; Who's Left (or Right) To Cast the First Stone?</title>
    <meta content="14HENN$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Washington; Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199497"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Henneberger, Melinda</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E0D6153BF937A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1014" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Nation; Who's Left (or Right) To Cast the First Stone?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MELINDA HENNEBERGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Henneberger, Melinda</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Comment on changes in political rules now that Americans seem to be drawing line between public and private behavior that media no longer draws for them; example is lack of public reaction to New York Mayor Rudolph Giuliani's marital estrangement; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE presumptive Senate candidate tells reporters that his marriage is kaput -- possibly even before informing the mother of his children. He has already announced his high regard for the ''very good friend'' who accompanied him to a recent press dinner. A few hours later, his wife counters with her own press conference, choking on tears as she says that her husband has not only been unfaithful but serially unfaithful, previously with a member of his staff.</p>
        <p>And the public's reaction? Instant statewide polling suggested that Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani's personal problems would have no effect on how most New York voters would view his candidacy. A Daily News headline summed it up: ''Voters Don't Care.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE presumptive Senate candidate tells reporters that his marriage is kaput -- possibly even before informing the mother of his children. He has already announced his high regard for the ''very good friend'' who accompanied him to a recent press dinner. A few hours later, his wife counters with her own press conference, choking on tears as she says that her husband has not only been unfaithful but serially unfaithful, previously with a member of his staff.</p>
        <p>And the public's reaction? Instant statewide polling suggested that Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani's personal problems would have no effect on how most New York voters would view his candidacy. A Daily News headline summed it up: ''Voters Don't Care.''</p>
        <p>But it isn't that Americans are no longer concerned with moral issues; they may simply be drawing the line between public and private behavior that the media no longer draws for them.</p>
        <p>In the past, Americans have punished candidates who made them aware of their messy intimate lives.</p>
        <p>When Gov. Nelson A. Rockefeller divorced Mary Todhunter Clark to marry Margaretta Fitler Murphy, the public was scandalized, and his presidential chances crippled. When Ronald Reagan was elected president in 1980, a mere 28 years into his second marriage, it was considered a big deal.</p>
        <p>Voters never got the chance to judge House Speaker Newt Gingrich, who surely deserves a place in the chutzpah hall of fame for wagging his finger at President Clinton during the impeachment debate. Mr. Gingrich was no longer in power when Americans learned that he was involved with a Congressional staff member at the same time.</p>
        <p>Representative Bob Livingston of Louisiana, who was about to replace Mr. Gingrich as speaker, decided to step down after his own past indiscretions were revealed by Larry Flynt, the publisher of Hustler and self-appointed hypocrisy cop.</p>
        <p>But the very fact that there is a continuing debate over whether Mr. Giuliani still has a political future shows how far the public has come since, as William J. Bennett, a conservative writer and former secretary of education, says, ''the ancient standards were in place in the days of yore -- 1987,'' when Gary Hart's presidential campaign went pfft after the story broke about his affair with Donna Rice. Even his wife's decision to stand by him did no good.</p>
        <p>Dr. Bennett said adultery, by itself, is no longer fatal for candidates for higher office, and even such ''complicating factors'' as lying about an affair, or carrying on with an underling, seem to matter less and less. While he believes that those factors should end any campaign for higher office, Dr. Bennett said, ''I'm not having a lot of agreement on that, even around my own office.''</p>
        <p>Perhaps most surprisingly, several Republicans said they do not think that Mr. Clinton's affair with Monica S. Lewinsky is responsible for the shift in public opinion. Instead they feel that Mr. Clinton's popular success is just more evidence that the culture was moving in that direction anyway: Voters elected him -- twice -- knowing they were not getting Ozzie Nelson.</p>
        <p>''The public is anesthetized to all of this in-your-face stuff about private lives,'' said Michael Forbes, a Long Island congressman who switched parties and became a Democrat last year.</p>
        <p>''It doesn't mean they don't have concerns and opinions,'' Mr. Forbes said. ''But what the public really doesn't like is when you beat your chest with righteous indignation about somebody else's behavior and then do the same thing.''</p>
        <p>SUSAN ESTRICH, who closely followed the Hart drama while running Michael Dukakis's 1988 presidential campaign, says the country seems to have moved so far so fast since Mr. Hart's downfall that today a messy affair can actually be a plus for a candidate, especially one that seems to need a little humanizing.</p>
        <p>''If anything, right now it helps in the weird political world in which we live,'' she said, ''because watching them be human, even if it's because they're having an affair, is better than watching them be politicians.''</p>
        <p>New York voters certainly were responding sympathetically when they recently learned that Mayor Giuliani also has prostate cancer, which he has said will be the prime consideration in deciding whether he stays in the Senate race against Hillary Rodham Clinton, a Democrat.</p>
        <p>With divorce so common, fewer voters and candidates are in a position to judge others for the same problems they have.</p>
        <p>There would obviously be no arms buildup on this issue in a Giuliani-Clinton matchup, and no commercials from Mrs. Clinton's campaign featuring footage of her opponent's distraught wife.</p>
        <p>Though most political analysts say the public still holds women candidates to a higher moral standard, even that appears to be changing: Helen Chenoweth, an Idaho Republican with strong ties to the religious right, recently survived revelations of a long-past affair and was subsequently re-elected.</p>
        <p>But a number of other, perhaps more subtle factors now influence whether the public will tolerate private indiscretion from any given elected official.</p>
        <p>Other considerations for voters include how the (apparently) wronged or exiting spouse reacts. And how well the public likes the replacement.</p>
        <p>''I keep seeing Judith Nathan described as a nurse and a single mom,'' Ms. Estrich said, referring to Mr. Giuliani's friend, who is 45. ''And I think the situation  would be different if she were a 25-year-old aspiring model.''</p>
        <p>Has the candidate been hypocritical?</p>
        <p>Can he or she take the heat?</p>
        <p>How conservative are constituents? (Last year, supporters of Gary Bauer, the family values presidential candidate, criticized him simply for meeting alone with a female staff member.)</p>
        <p>And most important of all: How well did voters like the guy in the first place?</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
