<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Actress From Connecticut Heads Back Home to Help</title>
    <meta content="14AMY.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199314"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">St Joseph's College</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brennerman, Amy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lang, Marty</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Judging Amy (Tv Progam)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E6D7163BF937A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1311" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Actress From Connecticut Heads Back Home to Help</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARTY LANG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lang, Marty</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of actress Amy Brenneman, native of Glastonbury, Conn, who stars in television series Judging Amy and will host benefit for Connecticut Children's Law Center and receive honorary degree from St Joseph College in West Hartford; photos</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AMY BRENNEMAN'S life has a funny way of repeating itself.</p>
        <p>The Glastonbury native grew up immersed in law. Both parents graduated from Harvard Law School, and her mother, Frederica, was the second woman appointed as a Connecticut judge, spending 32 years in juvenile court.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AMY BRENNEMAN'S life has a funny way of repeating itself.</p>
        <p>The Glastonbury native grew up immersed in law. Both parents graduated from Harvard Law School, and her mother, Frederica, was the second woman appointed as a Connecticut judge, spending 32 years in juvenile court.</p>
        <p>After graduating from Harvard herself, Ms. Brenneman followed in her parents' legal footsteps, but not as a lawyer -- as an actress. She used her lifelong legal exposure to create a television series based on her mother's career. As executive producer and star of the CBS drama ''Judging Amy,'' Ms. Brenneman plays Amy Gray, a Manhattan lawyer and mother who moves home to Hartford to become a juvenile judge, as well as to strengthen family ties.</p>
        <p>Law will once again play a prominent role when Ms. Brenneman returns to Connecticut this week. She will be host to a benefit for the Connecticut Children's Law Center in Hartford on Friday and she will receive an honorary degree from Saint Joseph College in West Hartford next Sunday.</p>
        <p>At the Connecticut Children's Law Center benefit, Ms. Brenneman will present a dialog she wrote called ''How I Became a Judge.'' She will also host an auction afterward, with the proceeds helping to provide lawyers to children who otherwise would not have them because of family finances.</p>
        <p>Ms. Brenneman can thank her mother for getting involved with this fund-raiser. She said her mom acts as her eyes and ears in Connecticut while she works on the show, assisting her in finding ways to help.</p>
        <p>''This one was one that really appealed to me,'' Ms. Brenneman said. ''I truly let my mom steer me on these things. This is something my mom is very obsessed with, good legal representation for kids. So often, that doesn't occur. It seemed like a pretty wonderful thing to do.''</p>
        <p>Wonderful is also how Ms. Brenneman described her mood when told she would receive an honorary degree, along with her mother, from Saint Joseph College.</p>
        <p>''I thought it was a hoot,'' Ms. Brenneman said of the announcement. ''I thought it was great. I have my B.A., but no higher degree, so it's good to just skip to the doctorate.''</p>
        <p>Tracing Ms. Brenneman's path as she grew up in Connecticut, a love for performing began far before her involvement in her show. Born in New London, she spent her first three years in Essex before her mother took the bench in Hartford. When her family moved to Glastonbury, she found an affinity for theater in a community program called Creative Experiences.</p>
        <p>''I was 11, and I was in the chorus of ''The Music Man,'' and it was really fun,'' she said. ''It was always very emotional for all the kids involved in it, and this emotion came up in me as it was ending. And I was only in the chorus; it wasn't like 'Yeah, I did a great job,' or 'I'm really good at this,' but 'I have to do this again.' There was something mystical happening there.''</p>
        <p>She stayed with the seasonal program during her years at Glastonbury High School. She also ran cross-country and track and field, but the theater was her passion, one that helped her through a rough social period.</p>
        <p>''In the hierarchy that is high school, I was not on top,'' Ms. Brenneman said, laughing. ''I had a hard time in high school. I think it was painful, like it is for most kids, but luckily, I had this other world. I had this family in the theater.''</p>
        <p>Academically, Ms. Brenneman said she was a ''medium good'' student. She loved history, social studies and English classes, and hated math and science classes. She also had her mother and father, an environmental lawyer, pushing her, not toward law, but toward college.</p>
        <p>''For both of them, education had opened up a lot of doors,'' Ms. Brenneman said. ''It wasn't snobbism, but a true belief that going to a good place and meeting smart people will really shape the rest of your life.''</p>
        <p>After narrowing her college choices to Harvard, Georgetown and Barnard College, she decided to attend Harvard. After being accepted early, however, she finished high school a semester early and spent eight months in France, working with a friend as an au pair.</p>
        <p>''That was great,'' she said of the experience. ''It was wonderful to break out of who you are in high school. It was a great thing to do before college.''</p>
        <p>Once on campus at Harvard, Ms. Brenneman quickly took to that which she loved. She declared a major in comparative religion and got involved in the theater, befriending students who helped her found the Cornerstone Theater Company. This group, with which Ms. Brenneman serves as chairman, specializes in community-based theater. Institutions will often invite the entire company to live and work with them, helping the community become reacquainted with the theater. Performances have been done in Mississippi, on Indian reservations in Nevada and in Connecticut.</p>
        <p>''We're based in Los Angeles, but we're doing a show at the Long Wharf'' in New Haven, she said. ''Cornerstone was there over the course of two years, doing workshops, and they adapted a play called 'The Good Person of New Haven.' It's a really incredible show, and it's adapted to be all about New Haven.'' The show runs until June 4.</p>
        <p>After five years of traveling with Cornerstone, Ms. Brenneman began building her Hollywood career. She was nominated for an Emmy for her portrayal of Officer Janice Licalsi on ''N.Y.P.D. Blue'' and appeared in movies such as ''Casper,'' ''Heat,'' and ''Your Friends and Neighbors.'' But it wasn't until she and her husband, the director Brad Silberling, traveled back to Hartford to make a video for her mother's birthday when she got the inspiration to develop ''Judging Amy.''</p>
        <p>''My mom had actually pitched the idea for the show about a year before that,'' Ms. Brenneman recalls. She said 'Why doesn't anybody do a show about this world?' I spent some time with people that she works with, and I was just very moved by these folks. When I came back to television, I said I know some stories and I know some people that I don't think you've seen before. I knew if I could get people involved, it could happen.''</p>
        <p>CBS took interest in the series, and ''Judging Amy'' is watched by more than 15 million people each week. To add realism to the show, Ms. Brenneman said an episode will be filmed in the state, most likely in September.</p>
        <p>''I've been hounded by the state of Connecticut,'' she said. ''We're also going to send a second unit back in winter. It's impossible to recreate winter in California, so I just need some bare trees and frozen ground.''</p>
        <p>The lure of the real-life Amy coming home has also entered her mind. Ms. Brenneman said she would consider moving back to Connecticut when she starts her family.</p>
        <p>''I don't want to leave L.A. yet, because all my friends are there,'' she said, ''but the lack of seasons is profound. You don't get to touch all the parts of your brain and your spirit that you do when you have seasons. There is something organic you're missing when you say 'Look, another bright, sunny day!' ''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
