<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>First Came the Car. Then the Wrong Turn. Voila: The Map.</title>
    <meta content="11NEWM$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cars" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="H" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237794"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="COLLECTING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Maps</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">History</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Rand Mcnally</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Newman, Andy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Maps</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001011T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E0D8163DF932A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1209" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>First Came the Car. Then the Wrong Turn. Voila: The Map.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDY NEWMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Newman, Andy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on history of automobile driving maps, starting with 1905 sketch of boulevards and byways on Staten Island; photos of early Rand McNally guides, which used photographs of intersections and landmarks because there were few street signs (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SOMETIME in 1905, a New York draftsman whose name is lost in the mists of history took up a crow-quill pen and scratched on a sheet of linen the boulevards and byways of a nearby bucolic area for the use of devotees of the upstart touring device known as the automobile.</p>
        <p>The result was a map of Staten Island.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SOMETIME in 1905, a New York draftsman whose name is lost in the mists of history took up a crow-quill pen and scratched on a sheet of linen the boulevards and byways of a nearby bucolic area for the use of devotees of the upstart touring device known as the automobile.</p>
        <p>The result was a map of Staten Island.</p>
        <p>It was not the first automobile road map ever produced (that honor goes to an 1895 advertisement for the first automobile road race ever, through the streets of Chicago), but it was one of the earliest. And while crow quill and linen gave way to the scribing blade and then the computer, the design and look of the road map itself -- that neatly foldable security blanket, the motorist's best friend -- have never really changed.</p>
        <p>The earliest motorists navigated by using bicycle touring maps that were drawn up by organizations like the League of American Wheelmen. ''The same roads that would have been suitable for bicyclists were also suitable for automobiles because they were almost as fragile,'' said James Akerman, a pre-eminent road map historian and the director of the Hermon Dunlap Smith Center for the History of Cartography at the Newberry Library in Chicago. ''The first cars were a lot like bicycling mechanisms with a motor on them.''</p>
        <p>In 1904, Mr. Akerman said, Rand McNally produced what is generally agreed to be the first road map intended for the ''automobilist,'' adapted from bicycling maps and called ''The Country Around New York.'' A year later, that map of Staten Island became significant because it was the first to be produced by the American Automobile Association, which as its membership swelled -- to a million in 1940, 5 million in 1955 and 43 million today -- became one of the twin behemoths of the road-map industry, along with Rand McNally.</p>
        <p>Though the Staten Island map has been lost, a collection of AAA maps from 1906, housed at the New York Public Library, gives a sense of what the earliest maps looked like. The map of central New Jersey, about as big as a foldout road map for a whole state today, seems to show every single road, though none are marked with a name.</p>
        <p>To make navigating easier on a road system where signs were almost nonexistent, Rand McNally came up with a ''photo-auto guide'' in 1907. The guides were a series of photographs of intersections or landmarks like a big tree or a barn, with text along the lines of ''turn left here.'' The first one was put together by Andrew McNally II, the founder's grandson, and shows the route he took on his honeymoon from Chicago to Milwaukee.</p>
        <p>In 1910, AAA started using scouts to find the best routes. In 1911, one of them, a Norwegian engineer named William O. L. Westgard, led a series of expeditions through New York and produced AAA's first full-fledged state map, showing ''main traveled routes'' through the state. Aside from the absence of Interstates, toll roads and route numbers, the map does not look much different from a small-scale map of New York today.</p>
        <p>In fact, once the state and federal highway numbering system was set up in the 20's -- a development that Rand McNally says it prompted by coming up with the idea for a numbering system and actually sending drivers out to post signs and paint symbols on phone poles -- road maps acquired the look they have now.</p>
        <p>A 1927 AAA map of the north-central states shows the familiar shield symbol for a federal highway and a circle for a state highway, mileages between towns and dotted lines for incomplete or unpaved roads. In a pinch, it could probably be used today.</p>
        <p>Mr. Akerman, the map historian, says the familiarity and ubiquity of road maps work against innovation. ''It's very hard to change perceptions and the basic look of a map because people have certain expectations,'' he said. ''If you have to add another explanatory level and explain to people what you're doing, you're going to lose them right away.''</p>
        <p>So even in the age of Web sites like MapQuest -- which tell you exactly how to get from Point A to Point B, a road map still resembles a road map. But recent years have seen some retooling.</p>
        <p>After oil companies stopped giving away road maps at gas stations in the 80's to cut costs, and motorists  grew accustomed to paying for maps, the market filled up with new products.</p>
        <p>In 1988, Michelin began producing United States maps similar to its European ones, which are printed on thicker paper and have a precision and depth that standard American maps do not approach. The Michelin maps use color and shading to show topographic features like forest cover and elevation.</p>
        <p>SOME experiments did not quite take off. In 1990,  the designer Richard Saul Wurman put out an atlas in which each page was a section of the national grid, rather than a particular state. All 48 continental states were mapped at the same scale, all the roads were white, all the land was olive-drab, and the wide margins were filled with ''fun facts.'' Though the book is out of print, it was a breezy read, but the paucity of detail on the maps, especially in the dense Eastern states, would have made navigating difficult.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the most impressive current American road atlas is one produced by National Geographic in conjunction with MapQuest. It shows a heavy European influence, using ''cased'' roads -- black borders around every road -- and, like the Michelin maps, heavy paper and shading to achieve an almost three-dimensional feel. But what is most remarkable is how uncluttered the maps look despite their considerable detail, thanks to judicious use of color and typography and an open design that makes them look bigger than they are.</p>
        <p>Allen Carroll, the National Geographic Society's head cartographer, said that this was the society's intention. ''I got my love of maps staring at the road atlas on family trips,'' he said, ''and I was always vaguely dissatisfied with them. For the most part they were ugly. I couldn't articulate this as a kid, but they didn't sort information hierarchically well, making the big places and major roads stand out but with the minor features all there.''</p>
        <p>But for its members, AAA is still showing the way to the most noteworthy sights, though it leaves some out. Its most detailed current map of Staten Island, a street-by-street plan on the Metro New York map, shows only a blank field of buttery yellow for the Fresh Kills landfill, which is famous for being one of the few features on earth visible from space. Nearby, however, the AAA map shows in cheerful green, ''Fresh Kills Park (Undeveloped).''</p>
        <p>COLLECTING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
