<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Clinton, After Courting Arafat, Feels Frustrated by Latest Turn</title>
    <meta content="11DIPL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/11/world/11DIPL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237908"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="WHOSE HOLY LAND? DIPLOMACY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arafat, Yasir</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perlez, Jane</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001011T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E4DA1F3CF932A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1233" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Clinton, After Courting Arafat, Feels Frustrated by Latest Turn</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE PERLEZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Perlez, Jane</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Clinton, who has lavished more attention on Yasir Arafat than on any world leader, feels exasperated and even betrayed as Palestinian leader turns aside entreaties to restore calm in Palestinian areas; Clinton has spoken to Arafat daily in last week, impressing on him, location by location, how he must bring rioting under control; officials, who say Arafat allowed violence to drift for his own advantage, finally began sounding worried, but still resists Clinton's request to issue statement to his people; he demands Israel issue parallel statement, and also apparently fears losing face if he fails; question of his control over rampaging discussed; Clinton's long courting of Arafat includes $300 million in US aid after Oslo peace accord and another $300 million after 1998 Wye accord (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After nearly eight years of dealing with Yasir Arafat, of lavishing more attention on him than on any other world leader, the White House feels exasperated, bewildered, even betrayed, as the Palestinian leader eludes their entreaties for the restoration of calm, officials said today.</p>
        <p>President Clinton has spoken to Mr. Arafat daily since Friday, sometimes three times a day, impressing upon him, location by location, how things must be brought under control, aides said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After nearly eight years of dealing with Yasir Arafat, of lavishing more attention on him than on any other world leader, the White House feels exasperated, bewildered, even betrayed, as the Palestinian leader eludes their entreaties for the restoration of calm, officials said today.</p>
        <p>President Clinton has spoken to Mr. Arafat daily since Friday, sometimes three times a day, impressing upon him, location by location, how things must be brought under control, aides said.</p>
        <p>On Monday night, for the first time, according to a senior administration official who has listened to the calls, Mr. Arafat promised to take some security measures to quell the violence.</p>
        <p>In that conversation, Mr. Arafat sounded worried that the violence, which administration officials say he allowed to drift for his own advantage, might have gone too far. By today, officials were beginning to see concrete signs that the Palestinian security forces were taking measures to control events on the ground.</p>
        <p>But in today's telephone talk with Mr. Clinton, Mr. Arafat was again in a resistant mood, apparently, the official said, because his lieutenants on the West Bank were barred by Israeli roadblocks from visiting him in Gaza.</p>
        <p>Mr. Arafat and Mr. Clinton are politicians who both put great stock in personal relationships. They both believe that the personal can change history, and in an odd way, they both have similar styles, publicly hugging and embracing counterparts to show empathy and understanding.</p>
        <p>But for Mr. Clinton, who has overseen the American-Palestinian relationship since 1993, when the United States first started sending money to the Palestinians through aid organizations, this latest squall with Mr. Arafat is one of the most frustrating.</p>
        <p>In the conversations with Mr. Arafat, administration aides said, Mr. Clinton has asked him to make a public appeal to his people to curb the violence, but so far, Mr. Arafat has resisted.</p>
        <p>This is in part, they said, because Mr. Arafat is demanding that the Israeli prime minister, Ehud Barak, make a parallel statement about restraint to Israelis. Also, Mr. Arafat is afraid that he may not be able to shut down the action on the street and would thus suffer a loss of prestige, these officials added.</p>
        <p>And beyond that, Mr. Arafat is riding the kind of Arab support that he has long hankered for but rarely had: from Rabat in Morocco to Amman, crowds are behind the Palestinian cause.</p>
        <p>The administration now hopes that with the plethora of international diplomats descending on Mr. Barak and Mr. Arafat -- the United Nations secretary general took the unusual step of staying overnight with Mr. Arafat in Gaza on Monday night -- the Palestinian leader will be more responsive.</p>
        <p>But how much control does the administration believe Mr. Arafat has over the Palestinian rampaging?</p>
        <p>''The notion that he can turn it on and off is exaggerated,'' said a White House official. ''There was a lot of frustration that preceded the latest events -- seven years of a peace process and a feeling that not much has been gained. Added to that have been the constant daily funerals, which generate a lot of emotion.''</p>
        <p>Controlling the violence was a difficult equation for Mr. Arafat, the official said. ''Certainly more should be done,'' he said. But at the same time, the administration understood that the Palestinian had to consider the political price of clamping down too hard.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton's relationship with Mr. Arafat has gone through ups and downs ever since the president was the master of ceremonies of the famous handshake between the Israeli prime minister, Yitzhak Rabin, and Mr. Arafat on the White House lawn in 1993.</p>
        <p>Since then, Mr. Arafat has been at the White House a dozen times -- more than any other foreign leader -- and the photographs of them in the high-backed chairs of the Oval Office have become an enduring image of the relationship, of the former guerrilla leader formally conferring with the American president.</p>
        <p>And during Mr. Clinton's presidency, the United States for the first time sent financial assistance to the Palestinian Authority, through nongovernmental agencies and commercial contractors. About $300 million was spent in the first four years after the Oslo peace accord of 1993. In 1998, after the accord at Wye, Md., another $300 million was authorized for the Palestinians.</p>
        <p>It was at Wye that Mr. Clinton, according to aides, finally made a breakthrough in his relationship with Mr. Arafat by standing up for him after the Israeli prime minister then, Benjamin Netanyahu, made an insulting barb. In tandem with Mr. Clinton, Secretary of State Madeleine K. Albright tried to nourish Mr. Arafat's understanding of American policy, inviting him to her Georgetown home.</p>
        <p>But from the start of the Camp David summit talks in July, Mr. Clinton and Dr. Albright have had enormous difficulty in capitalizing on investment they had made in Mr. Arafat.</p>
        <p>Before the administration convened the Camp David meeting, Mr. Arafat warned Dr. Albright in a conversation at his headquarters in Ramallah that the timing was premature and that the Palestinians were not ready for a meeting in July.</p>
        <p>During the 15 days at Camp David, Mr. Arafat was maddeningly remote and disengaged, administration officials said.</p>
        <p>On the last night at Camp David, Mr. Clinton presented Mr. Arafat with a yes-or-no vote on options that could have led to an agreement.</p>
        <p>Mr. Arafat said no.</p>
        <p>Even though Mr. Barak had gone much further at Camp David in his proposals on Jerusalem than most Israelis had thought possible, moderate Arab diplomats were not surprised at Mr. Arafat's rejection.</p>
        <p>The Clinton White House, they said, had failed to do its homework before the summit talks in garnering Arab support that would bolster Mr. Arafat during the meeting.</p>
        <p>After Camp David, the White House tried to conjure up various ways to get Mr. Arafat back into the endgame of a peace deal. But administration officials, who acknowledge that they have had trouble really understanding Mr. Arafat, say that in the last several months, they have been unable to read him at all. In Paris last week, Mr. Arafat was opaque and then angry, storming out of a meeting and forcing Dr. Albright to run after him.</p>
        <p>Were his constant delays a tactical move to squeeze ever more out of the Israelis? they wondered. In their bleakest moments, they would ask whether Mr. Arafat was really considering a unilateral declaration of a Palestinian state.</p>
        <p>Most recently, administration officials have begun to believe that Mr. Arafat wants to wait until after the presidential election before considering a peace accord.</p>
        <p>Mr. Arafat apparently believes that Mr. Clinton, free of the election constraints put on him by the candidacies of Al Gore and Hillary Rodham Clinton, will be better able to serve the Palestinians' needs as a lame duck president.</p>
        <p>But this formulation by Mr. Arafat demonstrates his lack of understanding of the American political system, which administration officials have been at pains to explain to him over the years.</p>
        <p>As far as the peace process is concerned Mr. Clinton will not be a ''lame duck but a dead duck,'' one official said.</p>
        <p>WHOSE HOLY LAND? DIPLOMACY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
