<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="11DIGE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237912"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001011T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E1DA1F3CF932A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1203" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>China Trade Law Enacted, But U.S. Issues a Warning  President Clinton sent his top trade negotiator to Beijing to warn the Chinese leadership that its apparent efforts to back away from key trade concessions threaten the trading rights it won after a prolonged fight in Congress.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton signed into law the legislation granting China permanent normal trade relations, but American officials acknowledged that China was slipping on pledges that it had made as part of its efforts to join the World Trade Organization. [Page A1.]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>China Trade Law Enacted, But U.S. Issues a Warning  President Clinton sent his top trade negotiator to Beijing to warn the Chinese leadership that its apparent efforts to back away from key trade concessions threaten the trading rights it won after a prolonged fight in Congress.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton signed into law the legislation granting China permanent normal trade relations, but American officials acknowledged that China was slipping on pledges that it had made as part of its efforts to join the World Trade Organization. [Page A1.]</p>
        <p>$1 Billion Offered for Online Broker  Deutsche Bank offered more than a $1 billion to acquire National Discount Brokers Group, whose public face is that of an online brokerage firm but whose market-making unit, NDB Capital Markets, makes it attractive as a takeover target. And banks seem to have a voracious appetite for buying market makers of late, exemplified by Goldman Sachs's recent acquisition of Spear Leeds &amp; Kellogg and Merrill Lynch's takeover of Herzog Heine Geduld. Shares of National Discount increased $22.44, to $47.69. Market Place. [C14.]</p>
        <p>Vitamin Makers to Pay $255 Million  New York State will receive $25 million out of the $255 million that six leading vitamin producers will pay to most states in the latest settlement of cases stemming from a decade-long international price-fixing scheme, the state's attorney general said. [C6.]</p>
        <p>Chief of Firestone Steps Down  The chief executive of Bridgestone/Firestone, Masatoshi Ono, resigned from those jobs and was succeeded by John Lampe, the executive vice president of Firestone. [C2.]</p>
        <p>Intel Defends Its Mobile-Chip Turf  Intel executives took the stage at an industry gathering to deflect the first inroads of Transmeta, a tiny but highly visible competitor, in the lucrative chip market for portable computers. Intel said that its current generation of mobile Pentium processors already consumed less power on average than Transmeta's and that a set of technologies on the horizon would keep Intel comfortably in the lead. [C4.]</p>
        <p>Hiring Attracts Unwanted Attention  In its start-up phase, Cardima, a maker of medical devices, had to hire employees in a hurry. Cardima turned to independent contractors until it could find permanent employees. The move made good business sense, but it also created a management problem. Because companies do not withhold taxes or make Social Security payments on the earnings of such workers, any decision to rely on large numbers of them usually sounds an alarm bell at the I.R.S. and state employment agencies. Management. [C5.]</p>
        <p>A Dean's School of Hard Knocks  When he was a student at the University of Chicago, William G. Christie, now dean of the Owen Graduate School of Management at Vanderbilt University, house-sat for his former doctoral adviser, Merton H. Miller. Despite their early friendly relationship, he later found himself on the opposite side of his mentor -- a Nobel Prize winner -- in co-writing a study critical of the Nasdaq market. [C5.]</p>
        <p>Oil Prices Climb Above $33 a Barrel  Crude oil rose 4 percent, to $33.18 a barrel, after a cold spell in the United States raised demand, and tensions in the Middle East raised concern about supply disruptions. [C13.]</p>
        <p>I.B.M. to Build New York Chip Plant  I.B.M. said that it would spend $2.5 billion to build ''the world's most technologically advanced'' chip factory in East Fishkill, N.Y., seven years after the company rocked the region with sweeping cutbacks. [B1.]</p>
        <p>A Rebound in Business Aviation  The business aviation industry has recovered from a slump after the 1980's. With more companies clamoring to own, lease or buy shares of corporate aircraft, and with manufacturers scrambling to dish up luxury products, the only question is how long the good times will last. Joe Sharkey: Business Travel. [C6.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
