<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Hunting Club Built From Scrap; Members Tend Dogs and Swap Boasts in the Bronx</title>
    <meta content="11HUNT$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/11/nyregion/11HUNT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237881"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hunting and Trapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dogs</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Highbridge Hunting Club (Bronx)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kleinfield, N R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dogs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hunting and Trapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001011T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E2DE1F3CF932A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1889" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Hunting Club Built From Scrap; Members Tend Dogs and Swap Boasts in the Bronx</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By N. R. KLEINFIELD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kleinfield, N R</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article describes scene at Highbridge Hunting Club in Bronx; club is home to about 35 hunting dogs who live in cluster of 14 enclosures along banks of Harlem River; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lewis Jones parked his car outside the gate and went in to feed his hunting dogs. The sun was strong. The sky was radiant and cloudless. ''O.K., Lady. O.K., Pepper,'' he said, his tone smooth, as he unlocked the makeshift wooden pen. Inside, he could hear the beagles skittering around. There were four of them.</p>
        <p>Day in, day out, he comes here, an indelible part of his routine. Hearing voices, he shifted his calm gaze to several arriving hunters, fellow members of the club. They were coming to visit their own dogs. This is on a sliver of land hugging the Harlem River in the Bronx. A couple of raucous birds wheeled overhead. When they were done shaking out food and cleaning out the pens, the men gentled themselves into old chairs arranged in a semicircle inside a creaky clubhouse they had built years ago.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Lewis Jones parked his car outside the gate and went in to feed his hunting dogs. The sun was strong. The sky was radiant and cloudless. ''O.K., Lady. O.K., Pepper,'' he said, his tone smooth, as he unlocked the makeshift wooden pen. Inside, he could hear the beagles skittering around. There were four of them.</p>
        <p>Day in, day out, he comes here, an indelible part of his routine. Hearing voices, he shifted his calm gaze to several arriving hunters, fellow members of the club. They were coming to visit their own dogs. This is on a sliver of land hugging the Harlem River in the Bronx. A couple of raucous birds wheeled overhead. When they were done shaking out food and cleaning out the pens, the men gentled themselves into old chairs arranged in a semicircle inside a creaky clubhouse they had built years ago.</p>
        <p>They talked about this and that, but mostly they talked about their hunting dogs, and mostly they talked about who had the best dogs and so forth. Naturally, each of the hunters felt his dogs were superior. (''Sure, mine are.'' ''Nope, they can't beat mine.'') For these men, their hunting dogs and what they do with them, well, that is their abiding love.</p>
        <p>The dogs, about 35 of them, live in a cluster of 14 enclosures that the members have built, a dog town of sorts. It is a little-known encampment in the middle of nowhere that constitutes one of the city's quirkier and more enduring organizations. This is the Highbridge Hunting Club.</p>
        <p>That, at least, is the official name bestowed on it by its 14 motley members. Informally, they call it simply the Yard or the Dog Pen. Some of the local residents allude to the yard as ''Ghost Town'' because at night the pens look to them like places only ghosts would inhabit.</p>
        <p>The club occupies a 150-yard stretch of scruffy land near 167th Street and Sedgwick Avenue in the Highbridge section of the Bronx. Hunting dogs have been kept in the vicinity as far back as the 1940's. Without sufficient space or landlord permission or the willingness to keep their dogs where they live, the men have learned of this area and housed the animals here. A chain-link fence protects the domiciles, and there are padlocks on the two gates and on each pen.</p>
        <p>Nearly all the dogs are beagles, used for rabbit hunting. There are a few coon dogs, as well as a cocker spaniel and a Labrador, which hunt rabbits and pheasant. The men usually like to venture upstate, west of Albany, to hunt. Some of the men hunt squirrels and deer, too, but not with the dogs. They also fish. Whatever they catch, for the most part, they eat.</p>
        <p>Except for the men and their dogs, there was not much going on in the area. Next to the yard, a couple of men worked lethargically on cars and trucks. Beyond them was a storage yard for a scaffolding business and beyond that a sign-building business. That was about it.</p>
        <p>Mr. Jones is 67, and has been keeping dogs at the Yard for upward of 35 years. He is considered the head of the club. Before coming here, he had his dogs in a pen in a vacant lot in upper Manhattan. Neighbors complained. Some hunters he knew told him about the Harlem River site and he moved his dogs. Currently, he has three females and a newly acquired male. ''I hate to say it, but I think the females are smarter,'' he said. ''I'm only referring to dogs.''</p>
        <p>The men talked about why they liked to keep their dogs here. ''Nobody gets bothered if the dogs bark,'' said Lawrence Dabney, 70, a former tractor-trailer driver who has five beagles at the Yard. ''There's nothing to bother.''</p>
        <p>Johnny Goble, 75, a retired printing press operator, said: ''And you don't want to keep hunting dogs in the house. They become pets. Then they won't hunt as good.''</p>
        <p>Most of the club's members live in the Bronx or Manhattan -- one man comes from New Jersey -- and many like Mr. Jones are retired. He used to be a private chauffeur and do home improvement work. But there are some younger members. There's Juan Puig, a carpenter, who is 45. Ernest Greene, a sanitation truck driver known as Rabbit, is 50. Clifford Shellman, who used to be a mine worker but is now on disability, is 53. A few members are in their 20's.</p>
        <p>Leon Robinson, 79, one of the club's elder statesmen, though he no longer keeps dogs here, said that hunting dogs have been housed in the area since around the time of World War II. No one seemed to know how it started. In the 1960's, Mr. Robinson said, there were as many as 25 members of the club and more than 75 dogs. Before the dogs came, the place was known as Shanty Town, and hobos and Gypsies lived on the land.</p>
        <p>Originally, the pens were slightly north of where they now are, on city-owned land. The hunters had no formal arrangement with the city, and a couple of years ago city officials ordered them off the property. A man with a construction business owned the nearby sliver. He retired, and Mr. Jones spoke to him about preserving the hunting club. The owner wanted to donate the plot to a nonprofit organization. From his days singing in a gospel choir, Mr. Jones was acquainted with the Rev. James Staggers of the New Tabernacle Baptist Church near the Bronx Zoo. It was arranged that the land be given to the church, which, in turn, agreed to let the hunters use it for their pens.</p>
        <p>''They just bring me a rabbit or a fish now and then, and it's O.K.,'' Mr. Staggers said. ''They keep my pot full.''</p>
        <p>The men filter in irregularly through the day. Most stop by every day, or if they can't, arrange for one of the others to care for their dogs. One man, who has an automatic feeder in his pen, comes every other day. The hunters give the dogs food and fetch them water from a fire hydrant up the street. They clean out the pens. Sometimes, they walk the dogs down the street or take them to Long Island or some open space to run them to keep them fit. In the winter, they add straw to the bedding and insert insulation.</p>
        <p>Now and then, someone wandering past gets to wondering about the dogs and whether they are being cared for properly. A few months ago, a women riding around on a boat cruise spied the encampment and phoned the American Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals. An agent was sent down to investigate. The A.S.P.C.A. said it concluded that the legal requirements were satisfied and that the dogs were healthy.</p>
        <p>Each man made his pen himself. Most are imperfect. Much of the material is abandoned scrap, though some supplies were bought at the lumberyard or at Home Depot. One man has a forsaken metal apartment door on his pen, complete with a bell and a peephole.</p>
        <p>Near the clubhouse is a rusty truck trailer. Inside there are bunk beds and a TV and a stove, and the men used to hang out there, sleeping overnight before an early morning hunting trip, but they have stopped using it. The TV is broken.</p>
        <p>Mr. Jones spoke dismissively of a couple of men who kept hunting dogs at the Yard but did not hunt. It was a status thing with them. They liked to boast to friends about how they had hunting dogs. It won them approval. They would join in on discussions in the clubhouse, even the fencing over who had the best hunting dogs. They would nominate theirs, and yet what was their evidence? They didn't hunt the dogs.</p>
        <p>Women are not brought around much. Mr. Jones said he once took his girlfriend with him on a hunting trip. She didn't much like it, because she said you had to be too quiet. He did not invite her again.</p>
        <p>The other morning, the sky clear and bright, Mr. Jones and several of the others met at the Yard and loaded six of their dogs into two cars. They were taking them for some exercise. Hunting season was about to open for rabbits, and anticipation of game had begun to flutter in them. They wanted the dogs limbered up and ready.</p>
        <p>Johnny Goble had a beagle puppy named Hambone that he was still training. Roy Johnson, 44, a milkman, was taking out two beagles, King and Queen. William Thompson, 55, a handyman, had no dogs of his own, but assisted Mr. Jones with his.</p>
        <p>They drove to a small wooded area in Pelham Bay, parked and walked the dogs across the roadway to the woods. They set them loose.</p>
        <p>Hambone didn't quite get the idea. Almost immediately, he wandered into the road as cars hummed by. Mr. Goble hurriedly put him back on the leash. ''Bad idea, Hambone,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Johnson inspected the bottom of some of the stalks of the underbrush. They had been gnawed. ''That's rabbits,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He used to keep his dogs in the backyard of his uncle's place in Queens. Neighborhood kids would let them out and they would get away. So he moved them to the Yard.</p>
        <p>He exhorted King and Queen on: ''Pick him up. Pick him up. Where is he? Find him. Where is he?''</p>
        <p>They began barking and converged in the distance. But it was not a rabbit. The dogs had happened on a homeless man who lived in a tent in the woods.</p>
        <p>Mr. Johnson was having problems with King. He showed pitiably little interest in the notion of chasing rabbits. He much preferred to hang around Mr. Johnson. Dread crept over him. ''Very annoying,'' he said. ''Very annoying.'' Meanwhile, Queen went sniffing through the underbrush. Mr. Jones's dogs were doing fine.</p>
        <p>They started baying. A rabbit had been detected. The underbrush shook with the chase.</p>
        <p>''Get him,'' Mr. Jones said.</p>
        <p>There was no catching the rabbit, nor any need to. The dogs had had a good run.</p>
        <p>The hunters drove the dogs back to the Yard. A few club members were languidly sitting around chewing over life's moments. There was a spark in their eyes. Next week, they were figuring to go hunting.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
