<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mariners Showing No Sign of Fading</title>
    <meta content="11SEAT$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/11/sports/11SEAT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237989"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="2000 PLAYOFFS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Seattle Mariners</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lapointe, Joe</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Seattle Mariners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001011T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E2D71F3CF932A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="707" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mariners Showing No Sign of Fading</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE LAPOINTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lapointe, Joe</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses Seattle Mariners victory over New York Yankees in first game of American League Championship Series; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The big sign, with red letters on a white background, asked ''Subway Series???'' and it hung last night from the edge of the third deck near the left-field foul pole in Yankee Stadium.</p>
        <p>The ball, off the bat of Alex Rodriguez, the Seattle shortstop, soared very near that optimistic sign, crashed into that tall yellow pole and drew a gasp from the capacity crowd of 54,481.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The big sign, with red letters on a white background, asked ''Subway Series???'' and it hung last night from the edge of the third deck near the left-field foul pole in Yankee Stadium.</p>
        <p>The ball, off the bat of Alex Rodriguez, the Seattle shortstop, soared very near that optimistic sign, crashed into that tall yellow pole and drew a gasp from the capacity crowd of 54,481.</p>
        <p>That sixth-inning home run gave the Mariners their final run in a 2-0 victory over the Yankees in Game 1 of the four-of-seven-game American League Championship Series.</p>
        <p>While it did not derail the hopes of New Yorkers that the Yankees would meet the Mets in a World Series accessible by local mass transit, it certainly served as a figurative underline for those question marks.</p>
        <p>''It means that -- we're one up,'' Rodriguez said of the series. ''We've seen the Yankees many times under a little adversity. Obviously, there's not a sense of urgency for them. But they are going to come out fighting.''</p>
        <p>Rodriguez showed that, even without the traded slugger Ken Griffey Jr., the Mariners are capable of knocking an occasional ball over the fence and even one or two decks of grandstands.</p>
        <p>''I was apprehensive when I hit it; I didn't know if it was going to stay fair or not,'' Rodriguez said, adding that he felt ''just a sense of relief when I saw it hit the foul pole.''</p>
        <p>In the first inning, he recalled, he hit a similar shot that went foul. Rodriguez said he detected a pitching patter from Denny Neagle, the starter for New York, who threw him that 3-2 pitch for the home run.</p>
        <p>''He was trying to jam me, tie up my hands,'' Rodriguez said. ''I was focused on a fastball and I got it.''</p>
        <p>The home run was an echo of the way the Mariners used to play, but now they are a much more balanced team and they employed their variety of tools to qualify for the tournament as a wild-card team, to sweep the Chicago White Sox in three games in the first round and to get the edge on the Yankees last night.</p>
        <p>The primary weapon on this chilly evening was the starting pitcher, Freddy Garcia, who left with two out in the seventh inning after giving up no runs and only three hits while striking out eight batters.</p>
        <p>''We came here, we played the Yankees, and it's tough to win here,'' Garcia said. ''We did it. We have to keep going.''</p>
        <p>Then came the Mariners' bullpen, three relief pitchers, the last of them a shaky but successful ninth inning from the closer, Kazuhiro Sasaki.</p>
        <p>''They've been there for us all year,'' Seattle Manager Lou Piniella said of his bullpen. ''I've got some good power arms and they are resilient. They all want the ball.''</p>
        <p>There were a couple good plays in the field, too, including a 1-4-6-3 double play and John Olerud's backhanded stab of David Justice's hard-hit hopper.</p>
        <p>There was also a two-out single by Rickey Henderson in the fifth inning to drive in a run and atone for a first-inning base-running gaffe. The Mariners managed only five hits against five New York pitchers.</p>
        <p>The Yankees had a chance to win it with two out in the bottom of the ninth when, with two men on base, Luis Sojo's pop fly to right field softly drifted and drifted before carrying over the fence -- just to the foul side of the pole and into the seats.</p>
        <p>By then, after nearly four hours, many of those seats were empty. People had to get home to bed and to work in the morning.</p>
        <p>The subways were full and running.</p>
        <p>Even the starter Garcia gave up his seat in the dugout. ''I was in here,'' he said of the clubhouse. ''Too cold.''</p>
        <p>2000 PLAYOFFS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
