<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Messier Returns as Garden's Featured Performer</title>
    <meta content="11RANG" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/11/sports/11RANG.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237865"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Rangers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Montreal Canadiens</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Diamos, Jason</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Montreal Canadiens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001011T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E7DF1F3CF932A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="588" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Messier Returns as Garden's Featured Performer</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JASON DIAMOS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Diamos, Jason</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on New York Rangers preparing for season home opener against Montreal Canadiens; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Perhaps more than any other professional athlete in New York City, Mark Messier has been at the center of some of the most unforgettable performances at Madison Square Garden.</p>
        <p>On Oct. 7, 1991, Messier made his Rangers debut and the crowd welcomed him, with his five Stanley Cups, as a messiah.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Perhaps more than any other professional athlete in New York City, Mark Messier has been at the center of some of the most unforgettable performances at Madison Square Garden.</p>
        <p>On Oct. 7, 1991, Messier made his Rangers debut and the crowd welcomed him, with his five Stanley Cups, as a messiah.</p>
        <p>On June 14, 1994, Messier hoisted the cup over his head to end over a half-century of Rangers futility.</p>
        <p>On Jan. 20, 1995, the Stanley Cup banner was finally raised in a season that was delayed by a lockout.</p>
        <p>On Nov. 25, 1997, Messier returned to the Garden as a member of the Vancouver Canucks and cried watching the Rangers' video tribute to him.</p>
        <p>Tonight figures to be another emotional night. Messier, arguably the most popular Rangers player ever, will wear his familiar No. 11 with the ''C'' stitched on his sweater as the Rangers celebrate their 75th anniversary.</p>
        <p>''It's important for me to just let it happen,'' Messier said yesterday at practice in Rye, N.Y., when asked if he knew what to expect.</p>
        <p>The celebration begins at 7 p.m., before the home opener against the Montreal Canadiens. The evening will have the feel of an old-timer's game. The G.A.G. (goal-a-game) line of Vic Hadfield, Jean Ratelle and Rod Gilbert is scheduled to be reunited. There will be appearances by Andy Bathgate, Walt Tkaczuk, Brad Park, Harry Howell, Ron Greschner, Dave Maloney, Eddie Giacomin, Gump Worsley and Chuck Rayner.</p>
        <p>Emile Francis and Mike Keenan, former Rangers coaches, will be on hand. Clint Smith, 86, and a member of the Rangers' Stanley Cup-winning team of 1940, is flying in from Vancouver, British Columbia. The Rangers were still hoping that Murray Murdoch, 96, the oldest living Ranger and the oldest living National Hockey League player, would be there to share the spotlight, too.</p>
        <p>''Hopefully, it will be a celebration,'' Messier said. ''Of the 75th anniversary. Of the past players and coaches. Of this year's edition of the Rangers. And of the fans.''</p>
        <p>But the real celebration, of course, will be reserved for Messier, who will skate on the Garden ice as a member of the Rangers for the first time since the 1997 postseason.</p>
        <p>''It's a combination of all those things,'' said Glen Sather, the Rangers' president and general manager, and a former Rangers player. ''And as little as Mark wants to admit something like that, he is part of the tradition around here. He carries that heritage with him.''</p>
        <p>Sather was speaking at City Hall, where Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani proclaimed yesterday to be New York Rangers' 75th Anniversary Day in New York City. It was the first time Messier had been back to City Hall since the team's ride down the Canyon of Heroes for a ticker-tape parade in 1994.</p>
        <p>During yesterday's ceremony, Messier spoke of trying to restore pride and tradition into a Rangers organization that has not qualified for the playoffs in the three years since Messier's acrimonious departure to the Canucks.</p>
        <p>Re-signing Messier was the Rangers' first step in that direction. Sather was asked yesterday if he thought there would be tears in Messier's eyes, as there were when he re-signed with the team in July.</p>
        <p>''I hope he saves them until he gets the Stanley Cup presented to him again,'' Sather said.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
