<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Jim, I Have a Feeling We're Not in Indiana Anymore</title>
    <meta content="11JAME" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/11/arts/11JAME.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237838"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cbs Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">James, Caryn</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Welcome to New York (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001011T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E0DB1E3CF932A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="749" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Jim, I Have a Feeling We're Not in Indiana Anymore</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CARYN JAMES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">James, Caryn</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Caryn James reviews CBS sitcom Welcome to New York; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Like most sitcoms, ''Welcome to New York'' has a sledgehammer concept: a Midwestern weatherman moves to New York City. Unlike most sitcoms, this sharply written and acted series has genuine wit. It works slyly, not with punch lines but by transforming the obvious premise into winning satire, taking a droll view of how we lock other people into stereotypes. Though the show's humor creeps up instead of bashing you over the head, it has the strongest premiere episode and is the most promising comedy of the season.</p>
        <p>Jim Gaffigan plays the weatherman, also named Jim Gaffigan, though almost no one knows who he is. An actor and stand-up comic, the real-life Jim Gaffigan has experience but no fame. Naming the character after him is one of the series' lesser jokes, but this wry comment on the trite celebrity-playing-himself strategy reveals the fresher attitude of ''Welcome to New York.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Like most sitcoms, ''Welcome to New York'' has a sledgehammer concept: a Midwestern weatherman moves to New York City. Unlike most sitcoms, this sharply written and acted series has genuine wit. It works slyly, not with punch lines but by transforming the obvious premise into winning satire, taking a droll view of how we lock other people into stereotypes. Though the show's humor creeps up instead of bashing you over the head, it has the strongest premiere episode and is the most promising comedy of the season.</p>
        <p>Jim Gaffigan plays the weatherman, also named Jim Gaffigan, though almost no one knows who he is. An actor and stand-up comic, the real-life Jim Gaffigan has experience but no fame. Naming the character after him is one of the series' lesser jokes, but this wry comment on the trite celebrity-playing-himself strategy reveals the fresher attitude of ''Welcome to New York.''</p>
        <p>The series was produced by David Letterman's company, and Mr. Gaffigan's character reproduces not only the Letterman career (he started out as an Indiana weatherman, too) but also his look. Mr. Gaffigan has a similar round face, receding hairline and genial grin. And like Dave, the fictional Jim is no bumpkin, though he will have to get used to the shark-infested newsroom of a typically insipid morning show, ''A.M. New York.'' He tries to make a good impression by ordering a cheese basket for his co-workers. Nice gesture. Not in New York.</p>
        <p>He has been hired by the show's producer, Marsha Bickner, played by Christine Baranski with killer comic timing and a delivery that captures the hauteur of so many successful, secretly insecure New Yorkers. Though she tells Jim, ''Everyone is really looking forward to your Garrison Keilloresque approach to weather,'' she is disappointed by his unsophisticated fashion sense.</p>
        <p>''Somehow you looked . . .'' she tells him, pausing while she searches for the mot juste, ''elegant in Indiana surrounded by the'' . . . longer pause here to highlight the inspired phrase,  ''pear-shaped folk.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gaffigan's performance is just as solid as he creates his warmer, more natural character. Together they are a good balance, offering viewers two possibilities to identify with. The series does not ignore the partial truth behind stereotypes or the fuller personalities that prove their limits.</p>
        <p>In the pilot (the only episode available in advance), the supporting characters are still mere caricatures. Rocky Carroll, better known as a doctor on ''Chicago Hope,'' shows a lighter flair as a vain, nattily dressed anchor who wears nonprescription glasses as a fashion statement and is convinced that Jim's similar frames mean the weatherman is trying to steal his look.</p>
        <p>Sara Gilbert is Marsha's assistant, with an even flatter running joke about how she does what she wants, not what she's told. Mary Birdsong makes a bigger splash as a woman who works behind the counter at a gourmet food store and becomes Jim's confidante. She has one of the best scenes, in which she mistakes Jim for a tourist. Like much of the show, the scene is written with shrewd attention to the details that make satire work.</p>
        <p>''Welcome to New York'' is the second Letterman-produced series to arrive this season, and the two send their heroes in opposite directions. In ''Ed'' a New York lawyer returns home to the Midwest, almost crossing paths with Jim in midair. And though the winsome ''Ed'' tries too hard to be charming, the shows take a similar understated approach to humor. That could turn into the season's happiest minitrend.</p>
        <p>WELCOME TO NEW YORK  CBS, tonight at 8:30  (Channel 2 in New York)</p>
        <p>Barbara Wallace, Thomas R. Wolfe and Christine Baranski, executive producers; produced by CBS Productions in association with Studios USA Television and Worldwide Pants Inc.</p>
        <p>WITH: Christine Baranski (Marsha Bickner), Jim Gaffigan (Jim Gaffigan), Rocky Carroll (Adrian Spencer), Mary Birdsong (Connie) and Sara Gilbert (Amy Manning).</p>
        <p>TELEVISION REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
