<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Elevating the Kinks to a Losers Pantheon</title>
    <meta content="11LOUN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/11/arts/11LOUN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237817"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="POP REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Losers Lounge (Music Group)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Kinks (Rock Group)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Powers, Ann</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001011T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407EFDE1E3CF932A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="497" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Elevating the Kinks to a Losers Pantheon</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANN POWERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Powers, Ann</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Losers Lounge gives concert in tribute to the Kinks, Westbeth Theater; photo; Ann Powers review (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A question hung in the air on Thursday at Westbeth Theater: Could Joe McGinty take the Losers out of the Lounge? On the second of four sold-out nights in new digs, the Losers Lounge concert series was in the midst of a transformation.</p>
        <p>With Mr. McGinty, the keyboardist about town, as host since 1993, Losers Lounge pays homage to pop artists from Abba to the Zombies by siccing a mob of self-styled superstars from New York bands on their songbooks. For years Mr. McGinty staged the concerts at the Fez, the cozy nightclub in the basement of the Time Cafe. Westbeth is a larger and chillier space. This tribute to the Kinks would give the crowd elbow room but test the portability of the Losers Lounge vibe.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A question hung in the air on Thursday at Westbeth Theater: Could Joe McGinty take the Losers out of the Lounge? On the second of four sold-out nights in new digs, the Losers Lounge concert series was in the midst of a transformation.</p>
        <p>With Mr. McGinty, the keyboardist about town, as host since 1993, Losers Lounge pays homage to pop artists from Abba to the Zombies by siccing a mob of self-styled superstars from New York bands on their songbooks. For years Mr. McGinty staged the concerts at the Fez, the cozy nightclub in the basement of the Time Cafe. Westbeth is a larger and chillier space. This tribute to the Kinks would give the crowd elbow room but test the portability of the Losers Lounge vibe.</p>
        <p>Choosing the Kinks involved a different kind of risk. Losers Lounge is in the business of redemption; honoring cartoon pop stars like the Bee Gees or cult artists like Randy Newman validates the zeal of music fans. The series gets its frisson from giving permission to love pop, that throwaway stuff, with every ounce of your heart. By choosing the Kinks, a universally respected classic rock band, Losers Lounge challenged its participants to try something more subtle than pure enthusiasm.</p>
        <p>Luckily for everyone involved, Ray Davies of the Kinks is also the songwriter who made camp serious business in rock. Thursday's best moments tapped into that paradox. The high point came when the hilarious Robin Goldwasser assayed ''Alcohol'' as if it were a lost collaboration between Bertolt Brecht and Barbra Streisand. Wailing in her beehive wig, Ms. Goldwasser tread Mr. Davies's favorite line, between parody and pathos.</p>
        <p>Performing ''Lola,'' the Kinks's famous ode to transvestitism, Richard Barone hit another high, making the song theater when the inevitable huge, hairy, unidentified drag queen emerged to court him. Right before that climax, Owen McCarthy gave a rock star turn on the jumpy ''All Day and All of the Night,'' echoing Lianne Smith's earlier loose-limbed romp through ''You Really Got Me.'' The bronze medal, however, had to go to the Losers Lounge co-founder Nick Danger for his total embodiment of the self-explanatory ''Apeman.''</p>
        <p>The night's more purely musicianly types also had room to show off their chops. The house band, the Kustard Kings, crashed through rockers like ''I Need You'' and nailed more complicated, vaudeville-influenced songs like ''Waterloo Sunset.'' Especially notable was a rapturous ''Shangri La,'' performed by the Terhune Brothers.</p>
        <p>The transition to Westbeth had bumps. Some singers couldn't bridge the distance between themselves and the audience. The sound sometimes went flat, and the lighting was harsh. But these technicalities can be addressed. It's inspiring to watch Losers Lounge grow, as it tests its own definitions of the rock lifestyle.</p>
        <p>POP REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
