<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Enduring Battle Over Choice</title>
    <meta content="11WED1$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="34" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/11/opinion/11WED1.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237911"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="CAMPAIGN 2000: TODAY -- ABORTION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Supreme Court (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001011T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E2DA1F3CF932A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="906" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Enduring Battle Over Choice</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial says that while states have increased attacks on abortion, it is the president, Congress and Supreme Court that will utlimately determine limits of reproductive freedom; says majority of Americans continue to support abortion rights, and for many that issue will be a key factor in their vote for next president</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The subject of reproductive rights has long been difficult terrain for politicians. Abortion is an intensely private question and a moral issue for many Americans, but the debate over reproductive rights is also about the broader cultural struggle over women's social and economic autonomy and the role of government in policing the most private sphere of American life.</p>
        <p>So it is not surprising that though abortion rights have been constitutionally protected for a generation, the political and cultural battle over this issue rages undiminished 27 years after Roe v. Wade. As Vice President Al Gore said in his first debate with Gov. George W. Bush, the issue of abortion rights ''is on the ballot in this election, make no mistake about it.'' It emerged as a point of difference in the vice-presidential debate and the one on Sunday between Hillary Rodham Clinton and Rick Lazio in the Senate race in New York, and is animating Congressional and state legislative races across the nation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The subject of reproductive rights has long been difficult terrain for politicians. Abortion is an intensely private question and a moral issue for many Americans, but the debate over reproductive rights is also about the broader cultural struggle over women's social and economic autonomy and the role of government in policing the most private sphere of American life.</p>
        <p>So it is not surprising that though abortion rights have been constitutionally protected for a generation, the political and cultural battle over this issue rages undiminished 27 years after Roe v. Wade. As Vice President Al Gore said in his first debate with Gov. George W. Bush, the issue of abortion rights ''is on the ballot in this election, make no mistake about it.'' It emerged as a point of difference in the vice-presidential debate and the one on Sunday between Hillary Rodham Clinton and Rick Lazio in the Senate race in New York, and is animating Congressional and state legislative races across the nation.</p>
        <p>The fact is that in the nearly three decades since the Roe decision, a woman's right to choose abortion is becoming ever more fragile. In thousands of communities it is nonexistent. Years of violent attacks on medical clinics by anti-abortion protesters and increasing efforts by state legislatures to hinder abortion rights have taken an enormous toll. The number of abortion providers has dropped by 30 percent since 1982. Some 86 percent of counties in the country have no abortion services.</p>
        <p>In 1992 the Supreme Court upheld the right to choose abortion, but gave states greater latitude to discourage the practice. Anti-abortion forces have since seized on the opportunity to impose waiting periods, mandatory counseling and requirements for parental notification and consent before abortions can be performed. In 1999 alone, state legislatures enacted more than 50 measures to restrict choice. Some 31 states have enacted bans on so-called partial birth abortions that could apply to even common abortion procedures at any stage of a pregnancy. Versions of that ban were ruled unconstitutional by a divided Supreme Court this year.</p>
        <p>While states have increased attacks on abortion, it is the president, Congress and the Supreme Court that will ultimately determine the limits of reproductive freedom in this country. Twice in the past five years Congress has passed partial birth abortion bans, which were vetoed by President Clinton. Congress's hostility to reproductive rights is evident in measures that barred American military hospitals overseas from providing abortions and made drastic cuts in international family planning aid. Anti-choice Republicans even now are fighting to bar international women's health groups from receiving American aid, even if they use their own money to lobby foreign governments on abortion policies.</p>
        <p>The harshest limits on abortion have been imposed on poor women in this country. Under federal law, Medicaid and other federal health insurance programs may not pay for abortions except in cases of rape, incest or endangerment of a woman's life. Currently only 18 states use their own funds to pay for abortions for low-income women for health reasons.</p>
        <p>The next president will determine whether a woman's ability to make this private decision will be strengthened or dismantled. For starters, he may well make two or more appointments to the Supreme Court that could result in a profound shift on privacy and abortion rights.</p>
        <p>The two presidential candidates have starkly different positions. Mr. Gore, who early in his political career opposed federal funding for abortion, now supports federal funding and is resolutely pro-choice. Mr. Bush is pro-life, though he seems eager to avoid extended debate on this matter so as not to alienate moderate voters. Mr. Gore says he will appoint justices who will respect women's reproductive rights. Mr. Bush, who says he will not impose a pro-life litmus test on a Supreme Court nominee, cites Justices Antonin Scalia and Clarence Thomas as his models. Both justices believe the Roe decision was wrong and should be overturned.</p>
        <p>The president's power in this arena is not limited to Supreme Court appointments. Veto threats by President Clinton have killed several measures in Congress to limit abortion rights, and his pro-choice stance has also helped to curb efforts to restrict access to contraception. Just last week a bill was introduced in the House to severely restrict the use of RU-486, the abortion pill recently approved by the Food and Drug Administration. Mr. Gore has said he fully supports the F.D.A. decision on the drug. Mr. Bush, however, has questioned the F.D.A.'s review process. Although he has said he cannot overturn the approval, he might have to decide whether to sign or veto a bill to deny vast numbers of women access to the drug.</p>
        <p>The majority of Americans continue to support abortion rights, and for many that issue will be a key factor in their vote. This is a pivotal moment in the long struggle to allow women the right to make medical decisions about their own bodies. The next president's views will have much to do with whether reproductive freedom is protected here and promoted abroad.</p>
        <p>CAMPAIGN 2000: TODAY -- ABORTION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
