<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Metro Matters; 2 Candidates Who Stick To the Script</title>
    <meta content="11MATT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/11/nyregion/11MATT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237910"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Purnick, Joyce</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lazio, Rick A (Repr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Metro Matters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001011T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E2DA1F3CF932A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="812" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Metro Matters; 2 Candidates Who Stick To the Script</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOYCE PURNICK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Purnick, Joyce</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Joyce Purnick Metro Matters column on debate between Senate candidates Hillary Rodham Clinton and Repr Rick Lazio; says both candidates stuck to carefuly conceived game plan and rarely, if ever, responded emotionally to questions they were asked (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A FEW minutes before airtime last Sunday morning, the reporters' panel in the second Senate debate met to go over the format, make sure no questions overlapped, and muse about what the candidates would say -- especially if the moderator really did ask Hillary Rodham Clinton why she stayed with her husband.</p>
        <p>Wouldn't it be interesting, a few of us wondered after the moderator left to freshen her hair and makeup, if Mrs. Clinton answered, ''Because I love him.'' Period. That would be direct, we figured, and effective.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A FEW minutes before airtime last Sunday morning, the reporters' panel in the second Senate debate met to go over the format, make sure no questions overlapped, and muse about what the candidates would say -- especially if the moderator really did ask Hillary Rodham Clinton why she stayed with her husband.</p>
        <p>Wouldn't it be interesting, a few of us wondered after the moderator left to freshen her hair and makeup, if Mrs. Clinton answered, ''Because I love him.'' Period. That would be direct, we figured, and effective.</p>
        <p>But Mrs. Clinton gave a careful, brittle answer that could be a metaphor for this and most political debates. ''For my entire life,'' she said, ''I have worked to make sure women had the choices they could make in their own lives that were right for them. I've made my choices.'' And, ''We have a family that means a lot to us. . . .'' And, ''I want to go to the Senate to stand up for women's choices and women's rights.''</p>
        <p>Of course she didn't speak personally. She does not discuss this subject, period. And an emotional response would risk offending those feminists who complain she hasn't been independent enough.</p>
        <p>So the answer sounded programmed, as did the whole hour between Mrs. Clinton and Representative Rick A. Lazio. As are most so-called campaign debates. With rare exception (last week's Cheney-Lieberman debate being one of them) they are merely chances for candidates to give their campaign spiels and grab attention (as when Mr. Lazio demanded in their first debate that Mrs. Clinton sign a soft-money pledge). The questions? Springboards for the candidates to say what they want.</p>
        <p>That relegates journalists to being props. Which is oddly appropriate and worth mentioning only because members of Sunday's panel did try to make the most of their little assignment -- to ask one question of each candidate. We (Jeff Greenfield of CNN, Lars-Erik Nelson of The Daily News, Gregg Birnbaum of The New York Post and I) tried to phrase questions that could inform people, and elude candidate manipulation. Good luck.</p>
        <p>For instance, Mr. Greenfield pondered asking Mrs. Clinton whether she could consider making abortion illegal in any circumstances, now that a woman can get an abortion for just about any reason, even if she is carrying a girl and wants a boy. But wouldn't she just articulate her standard position in favor of abortion rights? Maybe viewers would learn something, said Mr. Greenfield.</p>
        <p>He wound up directing the question to Mr. Lazio, who as usual cited what he called his ''pro-choice record,'' and accused Mrs. Clinton of opposing a ban on what he termed partial-birth abortions. In her rebuttal, Mrs. Clinton said once again that she would support a bill banning late-term abortions if it protected the health and life of the mother.</p>
        <p>FAMILIAR stances. The panel members might just as well have held up signs: abortion, the Middle East, health care, campaign finance reform. In fact, we could have guessed the answers, even to the question from the moderator, Marcia Kramer of WCBS-TV, about a bill to levy a 5-cent surcharge on each e-mail message. There is no such bill. Unbeknownst at the time to Ms. Kramer and the candidates, it is a hoax. But both candidates denounced the concept anyway, knowing voters want a free Internet.</p>
        <p>They also know that a campaign is no place for subtleties. So both also denounced the United States's abstention on the United Nations Security Council's resolution censuring Israel for what it called the excessive use of force against Palestinians.</p>
        <p>Senator Joseph I. Lieberman said Sunday that he understood why the administration abstained: to preserve its diplomatic leverage. ''To veto, I think, would've broken some of the lines of communication that we are going to need in this crisis,'' he said. He can say that, being Jewish.</p>
        <p>Even if Mrs. Clinton or Mr. Lazio understood and respected the administration's motives, they had no choice but to be critical in New York, with its hefty Jewish vote.</p>
        <p>Neither candidate deviated from the script. Which is why the biggest debate news came from Gov. George E. Pataki, with his proud boast in the ''spin room'' that he'd never heard of E. B. White, the writer Mrs. Clinton cited for his insights into New Yorkers (without explaining what about his classic essay touched her).</p>
        <p>Mr. Pataki isn't currently running for anything. But as a breathless Beth J. Harpaz of The Associated Press said as she ran to her computer on Sunday: ''He screwed up. It's a story!''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
