<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>European Union Moves to Embrace Yugoslav Leadership</title>
    <meta content="11YUGO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/11/world/11YUGO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237904"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Serbia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Yugoslavia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">France</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">European Union</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kostunica, Vojislav (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vedrine, Hubert (Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Milosevic, Slobodan (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Seselj, Vojislav</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Erlanger, Steven</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Montenegro</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001011T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E2DB1F3CF932A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1166" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>European Union Moves to Embrace Yugoslav Leadership</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN ERLANGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Erlanger, Steven</byline>
      <dateline>BELGRADE, Serbia, Oct. 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>French foreign minister Hubert Vedrine, representing European Union, visits Belgrade and praises new Yugoslav Pres Vojislav Kostunica; photo; European Union lifts some major sanctions and promises $2 billion in aid; Kostunica will attend European summit meeting, and also moves to improve relations with US; political situation remains muddled as Kustinica and allies try to assert control over powerful Serb government and its parliament, which will be disbanded for elections in December; new resistance comes from parties of Slobodan Milosevic and ultra-nationalist Vojislav Seselj (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The world began to embrace the new Yugoslavia and its new president, Vojislav Kostunica, in earnest today, with the visit here of the French foreign minister, Hubert Vedrine, representing the European Union.</p>
        <p>Praising the ousting of Slobodan Milosevic, Mr. Vedrine said: ''I have come here to express my admiration to Mr. Kostunica and the Serbian people. Together they have written a huge page in the democratic history of Europe.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The world began to embrace the new Yugoslavia and its new president, Vojislav Kostunica, in earnest today, with the visit here of the French foreign minister, Hubert Vedrine, representing the European Union.</p>
        <p>Praising the ousting of Slobodan Milosevic, Mr. Vedrine said: ''I have come here to express my admiration to Mr. Kostunica and the Serbian people. Together they have written a huge page in the democratic history of Europe.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Vedrine arrived the day after the European Union lifted some major sanctions against Yugoslavia and  promised $2 billion in aid. Mr. Kostunica will attend a European Union summit meeting in Biarritz, France, probably on Friday.</p>
        <p>Though his own domestic politics remained unsettled, with a good deal of political jockeying, Mr. Kostunica also moved to improve relations with the United States, whose policies he has often criticized, not least NATO's bombing of Yugoslavia over Kosovo. James C. O'Brien, the chief Balkan adviser to President Clinton and Secretary of State Madeleine K. Albright, is expected here Thursday.</p>
        <p>The United States is eager to restore diplomatic relations with Yugoslavia after Mr. Milosevic's departure and to build a relationship with Mr. Kostunica.</p>
        <p>In a telephone interview, Mr. O'Brien said he ''looks forward to a good discussion'' with Mr. Kostunica, hoping ''to begin to create a normal relationship'' and offer help, if wanted, to build democratic institutions after 13 years of Mr. Milosevic's rule.</p>
        <p>Mr. Vedrine has kept close touch with Mr. Kostunica, who regards improving relations with Europe as more important and less harmful to Serbia's interests than warming ties with the United States. Still, Mr. Kostunica describes himself as by no means anti-American, but wary of a superpower that, as the guarantor of the 1995 Dayton agreement, kept Mr. Milosevic in power much longer than necessary.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kostunica said today that the European Union's decision to lift sanctions against Yugoslavia will ''enable us to move closer to what always has been our natural environment -- Europe.'' The United States is also expected to lift most sanctions, but the process is more cumbersome legally.</p>
        <p>The situation remained muddled with the government of Serbia, the dominant republic in Yugoslavia. Mr. Kostunica and his allies in the 18-party coalition that supported his candidacy continued trying to assert control over the powerful government of Serbia and its Parliament, which was not up for election on Sept. 24. But they found new resistance from Mr. Milosevic's Socialist Party and the Radical Party of the ultranationalist Vojislav Seselj.</p>
        <p>The Serbian Parliament will be disbanded for new elections on Dec. 17, but there is bitter fighting over ministries in the temporary government that is supposed to rule until then.</p>
        <p>Both the Socialists and the Radicals said they were suspending talks on a new, provisional, all-party Serbian government until ''the end of riots, violence and lawlessness in cities and against the citizens of Serbia.''</p>
        <p>The complaint is seen as a bit disingenuous, given the pattern of Mr. Milosevic's rule, and seems a cover for bargaining about jobs -- in particular the Interior Ministry, which controls the police. Mr. Seselj wants that job for his party, and the Socialists want it for themselves, but Mr. Kostunica's allies insist that they must have it to protect their victory over Mr. Milosevic.</p>
        <p>Some Kostunica allies warned tonight that they would bring more popular protest and pressure to bear on the Serbian Parliament if it did not stop obstructing the new order. Velimir Ilic, the mayor of Cacak, a center of the opposition to Mr. Milosevic, said today, ''Serbs are so eager to see changes, and I do not know who will protect Socialists, and how, if they continue to drag their feet.''</p>
        <p>But the way Mr. Kostunica's more revolutionary allies have moved to assert control over the police, customs operations and some state-owned companies, sometimes with the aid of armed men, has caused wider complaints.</p>
        <p>Major banks, ministries, university faculties and important companies and factories were being taken over, but often by employees who are trying to restore rights, like university autonomy, stripped from them by the Milosevic government. Often, too, companies are removing managers imposed on them by the ruling parties, often the Yugoslav United Left party of Mr. Milosevic's wife, Mirjana Markovic.</p>
        <p>There is concern among the Kostunica group, too. A statement from his economic and policy advisers today appealed to ''all employees and those in managing positions in institutions and companies to protect property and prevent various abuses.''</p>
        <p>Today, for example, former Prime Minister Milan Panic, a Serbian-American, regained control of a pharmaceutical plant that had belonged to his ICN Pharmaceuticals and was taken over by the Serbian government last year. The government failed to pay the factory for its goods and then took it over. This evening, after a visit and calls by Mr. Panic, shareholders of the Galenika factory met at the request of workers and agreed to return majority ownership to ICN.</p>
        <p>An important member of the coalition that backed Mr. Kostunica, Zoran Djindjic, complained today that the Socialists and their allies were also meddling with the police. State Security, led by a Milosevic ally, Rade Markovic, ''is still closed to us,'' Mr. Djindjic said, warning that telephone tapping had resumed after a break of a few days.</p>
        <p>''There are attempts of consolidation within Secret Service,'' Mr. Djindjic said. ''We have warned them we do not want conflicts. We expect that the people from that service realize that the situation has changed.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kostunica is also trying to mend fences with Serbia's smaller sister republic, Montenegro, and its president, Milo Djukanovic, who wants a new constitutional arrangement with Serbia in a Yugoslavia that would look more like a confederation.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kostunica, as federal president, is chairman of the Supreme  Defense Council, which consists of the Serbian and Montenegrin presidents. He announced that the council would meet on Wednesday -- the first time it has met in years and the first time Mr. Djukanovic has attended since he broke away from Mr. Milosevic in 1998. But the meeting has been delayed because Mr. Djukanovic is recovering from a minor road accident.</p>
        <p>After meeting Mr. Kostunica, Mr. Vedrine and his wife took a walk in central Belgrade and discovered the ambivalence felt by many here toward the NATO countries that bombed Yugoslavia last year over Kosovo.</p>
        <p>France and Serbia have traditionally warm relations, and Mr. Vedrine began his walk at a large monument to the two countries' alliance in World War I.</p>
        <p>One man said, ''Vive la France!'' and others clapped. But another man shouted: ''Aren't you ashamed to show your face here? I have my children here. You bombed them.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
