<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With Hole in Middle, Knicks Laze to Victory</title>
    <meta content="11KNIC$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/11/sports/11KNIC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237975"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Chicago Bulls</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Broussard, Chris</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New York Knicks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Chicago Bulls</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001011T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEED81F3CF932A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="895" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With Hole in Middle, Knicks Laze to Victory</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRIS BROUSSARD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Broussard, Chris</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Knickerbockers defeat Chicago Bulls, 96-91, in preseason game; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With the focal point of the franchise for the past 15 years on the other side of the country in Seattle, the Knicks tiptoed tentatively into the preseason last night with a lackluster opening half against the young and below average Chicago Bulls. Looking unsure of themselves without Patrick Ewing leading them and uncomfortable with their new additions and responsibilities, they aimlessly tossed the ball all over the court and seemed to find the Bulls unguardable.</p>
        <p>But pride gave the Knicks fire, and a much more palatable second-half performance resulted.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With the focal point of the franchise for the past 15 years on the other side of the country in Seattle, the Knicks tiptoed tentatively into the preseason last night with a lackluster opening half against the young and below average Chicago Bulls. Looking unsure of themselves without Patrick Ewing leading them and uncomfortable with their new additions and responsibilities, they aimlessly tossed the ball all over the court and seemed to find the Bulls unguardable.</p>
        <p>But pride gave the Knicks fire, and a much more palatable second-half performance resulted.</p>
        <p>After committing 11 turnovers and allowing the Bulls to score 50 points in the first half, the Knicks snapped out of their slumber. They took the lead late in the third quarter and held on for a 96-91 victory before an announced crowd of 18,412 fans at a nearly half-empty Madison Square Garden.</p>
        <p>''This is a learning experience, the first game,'' Chris Childs said. ''We do not have No. 33 out there. It felt weird for me because this is my fifth year and without him being here it took some time for me to adjust until we got into the flow of the game and everybody just started to play.''</p>
        <p>Besides the slow start, the Knicks were a bit concerned about Glen Rice, who bruised his left knee while being fouled by Elton Brand. Rice, who had a knot on his knee, indicated that the injury was not serious.</p>
        <p>Allan Houston, the Knicks' leading scorer last season, missed the game with a mildly sprained left ankle. But it was the first look at the Knicks in the post-Ewing era and Rice's first game in a Knick uniform.</p>
        <p>While Houston's injury kept New York from playing Houston, Rice and Latrell Sprewell together, it did give the Knicks the opportunity to play as a perimeter-dominated team and gage whether they could survive on the backboards without Ewing.</p>
        <p>Sprewell was outstanding, scoring a game-high 21 points and giving the Knicks, who trailed by 50-40 at halftime, their first lead, 65-63, with a 3-pointer with 1 minute 44 seconds left in the third quarter.</p>
        <p>Rice, who started at small forward, hit just 2 of 9 shots. But he was aggressive on offense and was a perfect 16 for 16 at the free-throw line in scoring 20 points.</p>
        <p>Seemingly unable to jump high, he did not show the vaunted post-up game that had impressed the Knicks.</p>
        <p>''My legs were shaking a little bit,'' Rice said. ''I couldn't get the proper lift on my shots. I was so eager to be perfect and when you do that things do go your way. But for the most part, I worked hard and we won.''</p>
        <p>Rice said he injured his left knee when he was fouled by Brand on a drive to the basket. Though he was wincing and shaking his leg, he continued to play after the foul.</p>
        <p>With Sprewell and Rice leading the way, the Knicks' offense was very much a drive-and-kick scheme, and not necessarily by design.</p>
        <p>''We had guys all out of whack,'' Marcus Camby said. ''We were all out of sync offensively. We were supposed to run one play and we ended up running something else.''</p>
        <p>One good byproduct of the penetration-heavy attack was that the Knicks, who committed just four second-half turnovers, attempted 48 free throws. One of their greatest weaknesses last season was their infrequent trips to the foul line.</p>
        <p>The Knicks also outrebounded the Bulls, 37-35, including a 13-9 advantage on the offensive end. But Camby, going against the little-known and the little-accomplished Michael Ruffin, finished with only 3 points and 2 rebounds in 26 minutes.</p>
        <p>The former St. John's star Lavor Postell, who received an ovation upon entering the game in the second quarter, played fairly well, scoring 8 points. Travis Knight also impressed, finishing with 7 rebounds and scoring 4 of his 6 points on late baskets that kept the Knicks ahead in the final minutes. Kurt Thomas led the Knicks with eight rebounds.</p>
        <p>Erick Strickland, whose decision-making had been criticized by Coach Jeff Van Gundy, was both aggressive and wild. He had 10 points, but hit just 1 of 8 shots and made several questionable decisions.</p>
        <p>Rice was a picture of contentment before the game, sitting in the locker room smiling and feeling almost giddy about being in a Knick uniform.</p>
        <p>''It's a great feeling,'' Rice said. ''It really is. When I think of New York, you've got that tradition behind the Garden and it makes me a little more nervous because I know about all the wars that went on on that court. Regardless of whether I score 10 or 25 points, you want to go out and have fun and do what you can to help the team, and that's going to be very important.''</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
