<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From Motown to Paris, Another Opening, Another Show</title>
    <meta content="11SMIT$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cars" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="H" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles; Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237807"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Paris International Automobile Show</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">North American International Auto Show</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, Jack</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trade Shows and Fairs</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001011T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E0DF153DF932A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1536" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From Motown to Paris, Another Opening, Another Show</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK SMITH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smith, Jack</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on major international auto shows, including venerable biennial in Paris and North American International Auto Show; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THESE have been trying times for the French.</p>
        <p>In September, the prime minister of Australia refused to speak French, the official language of the Olympics, at the opening of the games in Sydney. With the shadow of the dreaded Golden Arches lengthening over French cuisine, the usually staid Le Monde urged its readers, as a ''cultural imperative,'' to resist the lure of le hamburger.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THESE have been trying times for the French.</p>
        <p>In September, the prime minister of Australia refused to speak French, the official language of the Olympics, at the opening of the games in Sydney. With the shadow of the dreaded Golden Arches lengthening over French cuisine, the usually staid Le Monde urged its readers, as a ''cultural imperative,'' to resist the lure of le hamburger.</p>
        <p>Yet with the return of autumn, dreams of grandeur glimmered anew at Le Mondiale de l'Automobile, the biennial Paris International Automobile Show, which runs through Oct. 15.</p>
        <p>''It is the biggest car show in the world,'' said Thierry Hesse, its executive director, two weeks before the Sept. 30 opening. ''When you combine the numbers of visitors, the numbers of exhibitions, new introductions, prestige and tradition, it is the most important.''</p>
        <p>Few dispassionate experts would agree with that assertion. While Paris is unquestionably the world's oldest auto show, dating to 1898, the biennial Frankfurt International Auto Show, which alternates with the French show, has long since surpassed it in size, with half again as many exhibitors. Even the annual show in Bologna, Italy, attracts more visitors than the 1.25 million expected in Paris.</p>
        <p>David E. Davis, editor and publisher of Automobile Magazine, said the world's most important shows are in Detroit, Frankfurt, Geneva and Tokyo.</p>
        <p>But whether Paris is No. 1 or an also-ran, it typifies the way auto shows are being planned these days. Not long ago, an audience could be dazzled by sexy sheet metal and gleaming, high-performance engines. Today, shows like Le Mondiale are as remarkable for their theatrics as for the technology on display. Carmakers are going to great lengths to sell sizzle as well as steak.</p>
        <p>At the North American International Auto Show in Detroit last January, BMW promoted its new convertible on a 750-square-foot display of light-emitting diodes. Land Rover brought its own waterfall and poured 53,000 gallons an hour over an 18-foot precipice to demonstrate its ability to ''go anywhere.''</p>
        <p>General Motors spent millions (it will not say exactly how much) on a ''G.M. Experience,'' which clustered its  brands, including Opel, Subaru and Saab, in a 160,000-square-foot, two-tiered building within a building, featuring an amphitheater, the ''Experience Cafe,'' V.I.P. lounges and even a tribute to the United Auto Workers.</p>
        <p>Stateside or abroad, every show has its personality.</p>
        <p>''Detroit is eclectic; there's something of everything,'' said Ed Lechtzin, G.M.'s director for event planning. ''Los Angeles is heavy on design, and New York is important because it's the world media center. Frankfurt is a technology show, with lots of emphasis on high performance. Geneva is a social show; Switzerland doesn't make any cars, so nobody owns the place. Tokyo is the toy show; you see lots of gimmicks and environmental stuff. It's also a place where you still see girls draped over cars. Paris is more style-oriented; there's lots of fashion involved.''</p>
        <p>It all started in 1898, when the French Automobile Club, which had been founded three years earlier, created the International Exhibition of the Automobile, the Cycle and Sports. Some 220 exhibitors turned up. To prove that the cars actually ran, the exhibitors were required to drive from Paris to Versailles and back.</p>
        <p>That show proved to be the birth of a global institution. The idea traveled quickly across the Atlantic, and in 1900 three car shows were held in Manhattan. Visitors to one show, the Madison Square Garden exposition, were invited to ride the horseless carriages along an indoor board track 1.125 miles long.</p>
        <p>THE 1923 New York International Automobile Show starred Will Rogers, the national everyman, who chewed gum while entertaining auto executives, telling them that outside of bankers, they were ''the grandest bunch of gyps I have ever seen.'' At that same New York show, Edsel Ford, who was then president of the family firm, opined, ''The automobile in this country is looked upon as a staple product, much like clothes or food.''</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, in the land of the Sun King, the emphasis was on richesse and splendor. Music festivals and galas marked the Paris auto shows of the 1920's, and in 1924 a Decorative Arts show made a debut. Le Figaro was moved to write, ''The entire world has its eyes fixed on the Grand Palais, where, each year, the French taste is displayed along with the vitality of one of our most glorious industries.''</p>
        <p>Since then, car shows have become bigger than ever. Automotive News, a trade publication, reported that 103 shows were scheduled for this year, in cities as far-flung as Riyadh, Saudi Arabia, Maputo, Mozambique, and Pasay City, Philippines.</p>
        <p>The reason for their popularity is simple: they sell.</p>
        <p>''Carmakers overseas don't rely on television advertising to sell cars the way we do in the United States,'' said James Hall, a vice president for industry analysis at AutoPacific, an automotive product and marketing research firm.</p>
        <p>''Once a car, say, a Ford Focus, has been introduced,'' Mr. Hall continued, ''there's no constant barrage of Ford Focus advertising; the equivalent budget is spent on the show.''</p>
        <p>But even where television is king, car shows remain a crucial element of marketing. The G.M. Experience extravaganza, at the Detroit show, grew out of the company's desire ''to create an automotive showcase nobody else can compare to, with a consistent global vision,'' said Joe Meagher, G.M. manager for strategic projects, auto shows and exhibitions.</p>
        <p>''Look,'' Mr. Meagher continued, displaying a tabletop scale model of the G.M. Experience exhibit. ''It's got the largest proscenium stage ever built, 242 feet, end to end. It's 20 feet longer than the stage at Radio City Music Hall. See, there are the different stands for each brand: Chevy, Buick, Subaru, Saab. They're integrated, but each maintains its own identity.''</p>
        <p>TO help designers get the identity right, the walls of the ''war room'' at G.M.'s creative services center, outside Detroit, were hung with ''brand boards'' expressing the company's idea of each car's distinctive psyche. Pontiac symbols included a red biking helmet, snowshoes and a high-performance steering wheel. A Chevy truck board was festooned with work gloves, a kayak paddle, pine cones and a box of dirt.</p>
        <p>Presumably, the brand boards get a lot of use; along with the big-name international shows, General Motors participates in about 65 domestic shows a year, with a total audience of 20 million. ''Our research shows that of those 20 million people, 60 percent are in the market for new car,'' Mr. Meagher said. ''Of that 60 percent, 40 percent intend to buy a new car within one year; of that 40 percent, 20 percent will change minds at a show. People spend 42 to 43 minutes at an exhibit.</p>
        <p>''While advertising is important to us,'' he added, ''it's far more important to spend one-on-one time with a new-car buyer at the exhibit. And each time you gain one point of the domestic market share, it's worth $1 billion. So the car show is a great place to get conquests. On the other hand, when G.M. loses an owner to another brand it costs five times as much to get him back.''</p>
        <p>James Hossack, a senior vice president at AutoPacific, recalled such a situation, the 1997 introduction of the C-5 Corvette. ''It was the first new Corvette since 1983,'' Mr. Hossack said. ''I wanted to see some smoke and hear engines roar and smell rubber burning. Instead, what we got was a magician who made the car disappear. What a wasted opportunity.''</p>
        <p>(General Motors disagrees, noting that the Corvette rollout got prominent play on television. ''You've got to get that 30-second clip on the evening news,'' said Mr. Lechtzin, the company's director for event planning.)</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Chrysler in the 1990's was dazzling the media with car show events that smashed a Grand Cherokee through a window in 1993, dropped a Ram pickup from the sky in 1994 and had minivans jumping over Chrysler executives in 1995. These are not the kinds of things they do in Paris, said Mr. Hesse, the show's director. Even the G.M. Experience, sedate in contrast with the Chrysler events, has been toned down.</p>
        <p>''There is a cultural problem,'' said Jean-Claude  Mosconi, the manager of G.M.'s European exhibitions. ''Americans see things differently from the French. The decor will not be so heavy, and the lights will be softer. In Detroit, there were spotlights to show power, because in the United States, everything is so big and huge.''</p>
        <p>The image business is tricky, but Mr. Mosconi's task was alleviated a few days before the show, when, in the wake of European fuel protests, G.M. scrapped plans to introduce the Chevrolet Super Sport Roadster at the Paris show. As a hot-rod pickup truck with retro hood and fenders and voracious six-liter V-8 power plant, it was quintessentially American. Like the hamburger.</p>
        <p>Jack Smith, a Pennsylvania writer, is connoisseur-at-large for The Robb Report.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Jack Smith, a Pennsylvania writer, is connoisseur-at-large for The Robb Report.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
