<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>???</title>
    <meta content="11ROTH$26" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cars" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="32" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="H" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237806"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="???"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001011T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04EED6143DF932A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1754" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>???</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFF ROTHMAN</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on presidential cars from Taft to Clinton; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CARS and presidents. Two national obsessions. Both stem from that most American phenomenon, which is a form of self-invention: we can be whoever we want to be, including president.</p>
        <p>Cars may be transportation, but they're our alter egos, just like our presidents. They signal who we are, who we want to be and how we want to be seen. They are part performance art, part self-expression, part self-invention and reinvention.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CARS and presidents. Two national obsessions. Both stem from that most American phenomenon, which is a form of self-invention: we can be whoever we want to be, including president.</p>
        <p>Cars may be transportation, but they're our alter egos, just like our presidents. They signal who we are, who we want to be and how we want to be seen. They are part performance art, part self-expression, part self-invention and reinvention.</p>
        <p>And if you want to talk about presidents and cars, you have to start with Lyndon Baines Johnson.</p>
        <p>L.B.J. car stories are as over the top as anything in the Johnson lore, evidence of his outsize personality -- earthy, fearless, profane, flamboyant, jocular, occasionally sadistic.</p>
        <p>Consider the time he took a group of visitors to his Texas ranch across a river in a fierce rainstorm. It was in 1960 -- the year Johnson, then the Senate majority leader, was John F. Kennedy's running mate -- but Murray Froman, a former NBC correspondent, remembers it as vividly as last night's bad dream.</p>
        <p>The bridge is swaying back and forth. It's night, pitch-black. The passengers are Mr. Froman; Bill Becker, a correspondent for The New York Times; and Representative Jim Wright of Texas, later speaker of the House.</p>
        <p>Bill Moyers, Johnson's special assistant, has called the senator's car phone to warn him that the river is flooding the bridge. Johnson tells him to get a truck over to their side of the bridge. The men watch the truck cross over, sliding from side to side. Two ranch hands get out. They're ashen. Then  Johnson says, ''O.K., now let's cross and go back.''</p>
        <p>At this point, recalled Mr. Froman, now a professor of journalism at the University of Southern California: ''I turn to the Times reporter, and say, 'Nah, it's all for show, he just wants to show what a macho guy he is.' But Johnson jumps in and straddles the gearshift. He pulls me in on top of his lap. The other cowhand, Becker and the other guys are in the back.''</p>
        <p>The ride is hair-raising. ''That's my anecdote,'' Mr. Froman recalled. ''Sitting on the lap of the future president of the United States.''</p>
        <p>Even in normal conditions, Johnson liked to gun the motor to 80 or 90 miles an hour -- though the actual speed is anyone's guess, because he liked to hold his big gray Stetson over the speedometer. ''He'd give me a can of beer; he had a can or two,'' Mr. Froman said. ''Hey, he was a senator. Nobody was going to get in his way.''</p>
        <p>Johnson may have set a standard, but he was hardly the only future president with a heavy foot. Before Bill Clinton became governor of Arkansas, he ''was a wild driver, a wild reckless driver,'' said David Maraniss, author of the Clinton biography ''First in His Class.''</p>
        <p>''Nobody ever wanted to ride with him,'' Mr. Maraniss said. ''He was talking and gesticulating with his hands, speeding and passing people.'' A White House spokesman had no comment.</p>
        <p>What was Mr. Clinton's favorite car? Not surprisingly, Mr. Maraniss said, it was that ultimate 1960's cool-guy car of the boomer generation -- a Mustang -- which he finally bought for himself when he was governor of Arkansas. It was a convertible.</p>
        <p>Similarly, John F. Kennedy used to race from his Washington office to his home in Georgetown, running red lights and clocking himself to see how fast he could get there. ''As a young student at Harvard, he loved to get his hands on a sporty car for a spin,'' said the presidential historian Douglas Brinkley, who is working on a biography of Henry Ford. ''He was a speed freak and an action addict, and the auto provided him the same exhilaration as standing on the bow of a boat, his face in the wind.''</p>
        <p>Kennedy was the first president brought up on the automobile. The first car he bought for himself, in 1940, was a green Buick convertible with red leather seats. Cars were another suit of clothing to burnish an image, and one of the ways he defined his new administration after the staid Eisenhower years. ''Eisenhower had this glass bubble top to protect him when it rained,'' Mr. Brinkley said. ''Then you picture Kennedy in his convertible with his sunglasses. You get two stark images.''</p>
        <p>In fact, for the whole past century, cars functioned in various ways as presidential spin. They compensated for physical handicaps, like Franklin Delano Roosevelt's polio, or William Howard Taft's obesity. They were visual shorthand for being technologically progressive, in Coolidge's case.</p>
        <p>Taft was the first president identified with the automobile (his predecessor, Theodore Roosevelt, was very much a horseman), and he sank into it with gusto. Because he weighed 300 pounds, Taft found horses uncomfortable (the horses weren't too happy either), and in 1909 he bought two big Pierce-Arrows.</p>
        <p>BY the 1920's, the Model T was the rage, and cars were transforming modern life. The stables and horses were gone from the White House. Calvin Coolidge was seen virtually everywhere in his seven-passenger Lincoln phaeton.</p>
        <p>Among the most indelibly linked images of president and car is Franklin D. Roosevelt's 1939 Lincoln Convertible, nicknamed the Sunshine Special. ''F.D.R. was in a wheelchair with polio,'' Mr. Brinkley said. ''His way of interacting with people was in the convertible with the top down. It became the famous presidential car. He would take it down to Warm Springs, Ga., drive the piney, windy roads of Georgia, and do press conferences and talk to people from the back of the Sunshine Special.''</p>
        <p>Harry S. Truman was as sensible in his car choices as in the way he governed -- throughout his life faithfully buying Chrysler cars, including Plymouths and Dodges. In the spring of 1953, just after he left office and returned to Independence, Mo., he and his wife, Bess, decided to drive back to Washington to visit friends. They just got in their car -- no motorcades, no Secret Service, no protection -- and drove.</p>
        <p>''There is a picture of them leaving their home,'' Mr. Brinkley said. ''Mrs. Truman is a typical 1953 lady in her hat and gloves; he's driving and looking very happy. It seems unbelievable today to think of Jimmy Carter or Gerald Ford driving with their wives and stopping at Howard Johnson's.''</p>
        <p>Richard M. Nixon's cars were like his wife's ''Republican cloth coat'': nonflashy, mundane, solidly presidential. His limousine was restored -- by Nevada inmates working in a prison auto shop -- for a car collection at the Imperial Palace casino in Las Vegas. The prisoners also made the license plate, which reads PARDON ME.</p>
        <p>Jimmy Carter eschewed the limo during his inauguration, as a sign of his common-man status, but Ronald Reagan brought back the pomp. As a successful radio announcer and future actor, he was a peacock in both clothes and car. ''He bought himself a Lafayette in 1933,'' said Edmund Morris, author of ''Dutch: A Memoir of Ronald Reagan.'' ''It was a brown car. He was in his brown phase: brown clothes, brown pen, smoking a brown pipe. He saw his car as a cosmetic addition to himself. He knew how good he looked getting out of a car and standing beside it. But he was younger then and much more conscious of his personal glamour. By the time he was president, he had mentally moved on to other things.''</p>
        <p>On his farm, in later years, he preferred an old truck. ''He needed to be in touch with ordinary people and ordinary life,'' said Dinesh D'Souza, author of ''Ronald Reagan:  How an Ordinary Man Became an Extraordinary Leader.'' ''It's the source of Reagan's power, staying in touch with normalcy.''</p>
        <p>George Bush has the distinction of ordering the largest presidential limousine ever made. ''Bush wanted to be seen in the biggest car imaginable,'' Mr. Brinkley said. ''It was 263 inches, with a 7.5-liter V-8 engine and C-6 auto transmission. Compare that to Truman's Lincoln Continental, at 145 inches. It was called the Bushmobile.''</p>
        <p>As for the next president, Al Gore or George W. Bush, their driving habits appear to be the opposite of their public personas.</p>
        <p>Despite a famous drunken incident in Washington in 1973, when he drove along the street late at night dragging a clanking garbage can, Mr. Bush is known as a sturdy, cautious driver with a penchant for nondescript cars.</p>
        <p>''When he drove down to Midland, Tex., he was driving a 1970 Cutlass, which was really worn out,'' said Elizabeth Mitchell, who wrote ''W: Revenge of the Bush Dynasty.'' ''His friends used to make fun of him for it. There's actually no indication that he was a wild driver. He is a guy who was extremely spontaneous and wild in many ways, but driving was not one of the examples.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore, whose perceived stolidity and goody-goody nature plagued his presidential quest before he started to loosen up, is actually the wilder of the two drivers. ''In his early days in Congress, he had kind of a lead foot,'' said Bill Turque, a Newsweek columnist and author of ''Inventing Al Gore: A Biography.'' ''Tom Luken, the Ohio congressman, told me that they were at this event at the Four Seasons in Georgetown. They got word that they had 15 minutes to get back to the House for a vote. Well, Luken says, 'We have no chance to do this, there's rush-hour traffic.' Gore says, 'Watch me,' and jumps into the car, invoking the tradition that allows members of Congress to break traffic rules if it's on a vote.''</p>
        <p>???</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
