<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>France Telecom Seen in Talks On Data Networking Merger</title>
    <meta content="Y11PHO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/11/technology/11PHON.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237873"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Netherlands</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">France</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">France Telecom</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Equant Nv</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Global One</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kapner, Suzanne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Netherlands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Netherlands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001011T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E2DF1F3CF932A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="491" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>France Telecom Seen in Talks On Data Networking Merger</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUZANNE KAPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kapner, Suzanne</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, Oct. 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>France Telecom is in talks to take control of Equant NV, Dutch-based operator of huge data communications network, in deal that would combine Equant with French company's Global One division (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>France Telecom is in talks to take control of Equant N.V., a Dutch-based operator of a huge data communications network, in a deal that would combine Equant with the French company's Global One division, people close to the negotiations said today.</p>
        <p>The complicated transaction would take several steps to complete and could value Equant at roughly $9 billion, these people said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>France Telecom is in talks to take control of Equant N.V., a Dutch-based operator of a huge data communications network, in a deal that would combine Equant with the French company's Global One division, people close to the negotiations said today.</p>
        <p>The complicated transaction would take several steps to complete and could value Equant at roughly $9 billion, these people said.</p>
        <p>One option under consideration, they said, is for France Telecom to buy the 34 percent of Equant owned by SITA, a consortium of major airlines, for $3 billion in cash. France Telecom would then merge its Global One assets with Equant in return for additional Equant shares that would increase its stake to more than 50 percent.</p>
        <p>Equant has been talking to numerous potential partners in the last year, including Global Crossing of Bermuda and Infonet Services of the United States. Initial talks with France Telecom broke down over the summer, but discussions resumed several weeks ago. A major stumbling block to any deal had been the valuation placed on SITA's stake and its demand for cash.</p>
        <p>By combining Equant with its Global One business, France Telecom would gain economies of scale in data communications networking, which could help it toward profitability. Global One's sales are projected to reach $2.2 billion this year, or 9 percent of France Telecom's overall sales, but profits are not expected to materialize until 2002, analysts said.</p>
        <p>Earlier this year, France Telecom gained full ownership of Global One when it bought out Sprint and Deutsche Telekom, with whom it had created the company in 1996, for $4.36 billion in cash.</p>
        <p>For Equant -- which lost $34.5 million after special charges last year on sales of $1 billion -- joining a larger company would bolster its existing network. Created in 1995 by transforming an airline reservations system into a global communications provider, Equant now operates in more than 220 countries. In addition to offering voice, data and Web host services, Equant, in conjunction with Reuters, established Radianz in June to provide a secure Internet network for financial services companies.</p>
        <p>Equant and Global One between them would have clients like British Airways, Samsung, Coca-Cola and Hewlett-Packard.</p>
        <p>SITA -- for the Societe Internationale de Telecommunciations Aeronautiques -- has been looking to get out of its initial investment in Equant for some time. It sold shares in Equant's February 1999 secondary offering as did Morgan Stanley Capital Partners, a division of Morgan Stanley Dean Witter, which now owns 1.9 percent of Equant.</p>
        <p>It is likely that France Telecom would be obliged to offer Equant's other shareholders, who hold 66 percent of the company, terms similar to a deal reached with SITA, a person close to the France Telecom situation said.</p>
        <p>France Telecom, Equant and Morgan Stanley all declined to comment. SITA could not be reached for comment.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
