<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>One Suspect Is Arrested In Beating Of Immigrants</title>
    <meta content="11IMMI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/11/nyregion/11IMMI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237950"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Migrant Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mexican-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Assaults</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hate Crimes</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Farmingville (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kelley, Tina</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wagner, Ryan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perez, Israel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Escamilla, Magdaleno</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Assaults</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Migrant Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hate Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mexican-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001011T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06EED91F3CF932A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="568" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>One Suspect Is Arrested In Beating Of Immigrants</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TINA KELLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kelley, Tina</byline>
      <dateline>GARDEN CITY, N.Y., Oct. 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Suffolk County, NY, police say that they have arrested one of two men suspected in the Sept 17 beating of two Mexican immigrant workers in Farmingville; Ryan Wagner, 19, is charged with second-degree attempted murder (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Suffolk County police said today that they had arrested one of two men suspected in the Sept. 17 beating of two Mexican immigrant workers in Farmingville.</p>
        <p>Ryan Wagner, 19, of Maspeth, Queens, was charged with second-degree attempted murder and second-degree aggravated harassment, said Officer Sonny Di Stefano. But the police would not release any details in the case, saying they would hold a news conference Wednesday morning to discuss the arrest.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Suffolk County police said today that they had arrested one of two men suspected in the Sept. 17 beating of two Mexican immigrant workers in Farmingville.</p>
        <p>Ryan Wagner, 19, of Maspeth, Queens, was charged with second-degree attempted murder and second-degree aggravated harassment, said Officer Sonny Di Stefano. But the police would not release any details in the case, saying they would hold a news conference Wednesday morning to discuss the arrest.</p>
        <p>In the beatings, two men posing as contractors lured the Mexican laborers to an abandoned building in Shirley, promising them work. They then attacked Israel Perez, 19, and Magdaleno Escamilla, 28, with a knife, shovel and crowbar. The workers  managed to escape and wave down a driver on the Long Island Expressway.</p>
        <p>Officer Mike Lettich of the Fifth Precinct in Patchogue confirmed that Mr. Wagner would be taken  there for the night, after bias detectives completed their investigation.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wagner's family on 60th Lane in Maspeth hung up when a reporter called the house tonight. But a neighbor said Ryan Wagner was a familiar face in the neighborhood.</p>
        <p>She recalled being on the roof on July 4 to watch the fireworks, and watching as Mr. Wagner left his house, apparently in a rage, and gunned the engine of his car.</p>
        <p>''He was revving it so that the wheels were spinning and they were burning and making this smell,'' recalled the woman, who refused to give her name. ''Then his father came out and calmed him down.''</p>
        <p>Paul J. Tonna, the Republican majority leader of the Suffolk County Legislature, praised the police work in the case, and said an anonymous tip had helped the investigation.</p>
        <p>''It just goes to show again you can't commit these type of crimes and get away with it,'' he said. ''Hopefully it will send a message to the people in the Hispanic community that there is equal enforcement of the law, and it will send a message to anybody motivated by hate and race-bashing that they will get the full extent of the law.''</p>
        <p>In a statement released by his lawyer, Mr. Wagner said he had turned himself in. He said he was employed and had a high school equivalency diploma, and said his problems were related to drinking. ''I do not hate anyone,'' the statement said. ''I have an alcohol problem, which causes me to become angry. I now understand it is an illness that is treatable.''</p>
        <p>The Rev. Allan B. Ramirez, pastor of the Brookville Reformed Church, who has been acting as an adviser to the victims, welcomed news of the arrest.</p>
        <p>''I hope that we will now begin to feel the beginning of the end of something horrific,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He said the two victims have been unable to work since the beatings.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ramirez said the men had applied for help from New York Crime Victims Bureau, and meanwhile are relying on a fund raised through the Brookville Reformed Church to pay their rent and basic expenses.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wagner is scheduled to be arraigned Wednesday at the First District Court in Islip. The police are continuing their investigation into the second assailant.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
