<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>These Days, 'Used' Definitely Does Not Mean 'Cheap'</title>
    <meta content="11STRA$18" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cars" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="H" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237792"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Used Cars</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Strauss, Robert (Byliner)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001011T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03EED9163DF932A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1751" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>These Days, 'Used' Definitely Does Not Mean 'Cheap'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT STRAUSS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Strauss, Robert (Byliner)</byline>
      <dateline>PHILADELPHIA</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on used car market and some typical prices; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SPANKY'S Auto Sales, tucked into an odd-shaped corner across from a slew of junkyards near the refinery district of southwest Philadelphia, is the last reasonable resort for used-car buyers in these parts. But even at Spanky's, shoppers get awfully picky sometimes.</p>
        <p>''I get people here who come in and want to spend $2,195 on a low-mileage car,'' Ray Johnston, a Spanky's salesman, said with a laugh. ''We want to keep things in the $2,000 to $5,000 range, but this isn't the old days.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SPANKY'S Auto Sales, tucked into an odd-shaped corner across from a slew of junkyards near the refinery district of southwest Philadelphia, is the last reasonable resort for used-car buyers in these parts. But even at Spanky's, shoppers get awfully picky sometimes.</p>
        <p>''I get people here who come in and want to spend $2,195 on a low-mileage car,'' Ray Johnston, a Spanky's salesman, said with a laugh. ''We want to keep things in the $2,000 to $5,000 range, but this isn't the old days.''</p>
        <p>The cheapest machine at Spanky's one sunny September day was a 1990 four-speed Hyundai Excel, red with gray cloth interior and an AM-FM cassette player. It had 66,000 miles on the odometer, and Mr. Johnston was offering it for $1,295. ''It isn't fancy,'' he said. ''But it will get you where you want to go.''</p>
        <p>More than 17 million new cars and light trucks were sold in the United States in 1999 (a similar number is expected for 2000), and 80 percent of them involved a trade-in. Add to that all those cars coming off two- and three-year leases and going directly onto lots, and what you end up with is a huge number of used cars in circulation. Given the average price of a new automobile, about $24,000, such a glut would seem to offer relief to the average car buyer -- plenty of bargains out there.</p>
        <p>As a recent informal survey of dealerships in Philadelphia and the nearby New Jersey suburbs showed, however, it does not. The survey's aim was to find out what was available in a range of prices. There were plenty of cars, many of them fully equipped late models carrying decidedly un-Spankylike price tags. In these days of used vehicles, sticker shock is not limited to those shopping for brand-new models.</p>
        <p>Take Marion Smith, a 37-year-old teacher from Philadelphia who had been searching up and down the Auto Mall, a strip of dealerships along Essington Avenue near the Philadelphia International Airport, and was getting frustrated finding anything in her price range.</p>
        <p>''I used to think $5,000 was a good amount of money to spend on a car,'' said Ms. Smith with an exasperated sigh. ''But I guess times are so good, that's like chicken feed. There sure isn't much selection. I am not going to come home with a Jag.''</p>
        <p>Or maybe not even a Toyota. ''We just don't sell much below $8,000,'' said Joe Tamburro, standing amid several dozen well-appointed used cars in the Pacifico Lincoln-Mercury lot here. ''Anything less than that doesn't pass through quality checkpoints. It isn't worth risking our reputation these days on something lesser. And since you can't finance anything older than, say, 1994, we don't do much of that either.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Tamburro pointed to a 1997 BMW 328i, with power everything and a 2.8-liter, six-cylinder engine, a prime car at a prime price, $25,000. ''Sometimes people look at that and say, 'I can get a new, fully loaded Mazda for that,' '' he said. ''So there is a downside at times when you have these luxury used cars.''</p>
        <p>At Meissner Chevy Geo, there were only two cars with stickers under $5,000, the less expensive being a 1992 Toyota Paseo automatic two-door white coupe with a lot of miles, 93,105, and a tag of $4,142. The other was a 1994 Chevrolet Cavalier two-door coupe, teal in color, with a 2.2-liter, four-cylinder engine. It had 64,000 miles and an asking price of $4,990.</p>
        <p>PHILADELPHIA Honda, just  north of Meissner on the Auto Mall, offered a small red 1995 Neon four-door automatic with 73,108 miles for $5,550 and a white 1995 Honda Civic DX for $6,800. But the Honda had 123,000 miles on the odometer. Nearby at Cherry Hill Subaru, in Cherry Hill, N.J., a salesman said he could offer a 1998 Subaru for $5,000, but it had 175,000 miles on it.</p>
        <p>''Everything depends on what our shop says, but we don't put things on the lot we can't really warranty,'' said Dominic Russo, a Meissner salesman.</p>
        <p>He continued: ''If it has heavy miles on it, especially in urban areas, we pretty much end up wholesaling it. Sometimes you get, say, an old Ford Escort some woman had in her garage most of the time that you can sell cheaply. But I wouldn't come to a big dealer and expect that.''</p>
        <p>Buyers who want a midsize or larger car can expect to pay $10,000 to $18,000. At Metro Nissan on the Auto Mall, for instance, you could  drive away in a white 1997 Buick Skylark four-door sedan, with a 3.1-liter, six-cylinder engine, automatic transmission, cruise control and 44,000 miles on the odometer, for $12,550, or about the same as a new Toyota Corolla.</p>
        <p>At Burns Pontiac GMC in Marlton, N.J., a sampling in this range included a 1995 white four-door Nissan Maxima with a 3.0-liter, six-cylinder engine with 44,298 miles, cruise control, antilock brakes and an AM-FM cassette player. The asking price: $12,995.</p>
        <p>For something newer in that price range, there was a dark green 1997 Acura Integra GS two-door coupe with 35,168 miles for $16,990 or, newer still but smaller, a white 1999 Chevrolet Cavalier Z24 two-door with a 2.4-liter, four-cylinder engine for $14,460.</p>
        <p>In the minivan category, there was a 1995 Ford Windstar with 68,540 miles for $10,860, while for the sport-utility-vehicle fans, the asking price for a 1995 red Jeep Wrangler 4-by-4 with a beige vinyl roof and 16,115 miles was $11,995.</p>
        <p>What will $17,000 get you? At Burns Pontiac in Marlton, it was a fully loaded 1997 two-door green Acura Integra GS with a 1.8-liter, four-cylinder engine and just over 35,000 miles. (Actually, the asking price was $16,990.)</p>
        <p>The same dealer was offering a low-mileage (17,811) 1999 silver New Beetle with a 2.0-liter, four-cylinder engine, and all the standard extras,  for $18,905.</p>
        <p>There is, of course, much available for $20,000 and more. Metro Nissan on the Auto Mall had a green '99 Mitsubishi Eclipse GS Spyder convertible with a 2.4 liter, four-cylinder engine and slightly more than 24,000 miles for $21,925.</p>
        <p>For $26,485, Burns was offering a 1997 Chevy Suburban 1500, with its big 5.7-liter, eight-cylinder engine and 41,245 miles of wear. And at Cherry Hill Classic Cars, a 1994 Jaguar XJS convertible with a 6.0-liter, V-12 fuel-injected engine and the usual laminated wood and leather interior was priced at $29,995.</p>
        <p>Right next to the Jaguar in the showroom was a 1996 Porsche 911 Carrera two-door coupe with a six-speed manual transmission, sunroof, halogen lights, alloy wheels, leather interior and 33,257 miles, for $56,995. The price on a 1998 Jaguar XKS convertible with 21,774 miles was $2,000 more.</p>
        <p>After looking at those five-figure price tags, it was a pleasure to drive up to Family Dodge at the Auto Mall, which has a big sign proclaiming its ''best value'' -- its least expensive used car -- right by the main entrance. On this day, it was a bright red 1990 Pontiac Grand Am, a four-door automatic with an AM-FM cassette and 70,000 miles on the odometer, for $2,799.</p>
        <p>''People come in and complain that it has some scratches,'' a salesman said. ''I tell them, 'The car goes, and if you can't afford anything else, I'd jump on it.' ''</p>
        <p>Avoiding Lemons: 6 Tips</p>
        <p>HOW to find the right used car at the right price? There are no foolproof techniques, but Pete Perrotta, an editor at WD&amp;S, an automotive information and service publishing company in Metuchen, N.J., offered these tips:</p>
        <p>GO ONLINE -- Spend some time doing Internet research. Mr. Perrotta suggested searching Kbb.com, the Web site for Kelley Blue Book, which gives general prices for used cars based on make, model, year and condition.</p>
        <p>He also recommended a consumer-oriented Web site, Edmunds.com, and the Web sites of dealers in your area.</p>
        <p>''The more you come in armed with information, the better off you are,'' he said. ''Kelley tends to be a little high in its prices, so dealers like to quote it, while Edmunds leans a little more toward the customer at its site.''</p>
        <p>HAGGLE WISELY -- There is always wiggle room in the sticker price and now, with more information about used cars available on the Internet, consumers can use it. ''You can say, 'I read something in Edmunds that said . . .,' '' Mr. Perrotta said. ''But don't be belligerent. Be subtle. You want the dealer to know you are prepared, not to make him think that you think he is out to rip you off.''</p>
        <p>LOOK AROUND -- You may well find the best price for the Toyota you want at a Ford lot. ''More than 60 percent of dealerships' used cars come from trade-ins,'' Mr. Perrotta said. That's why it is important to look at the dealer Web sites, where, he added, most will list all the used cars they have on the lot, with sticker prices.</p>
        <p>TAKE A RIDE -- Always test-drive a used car. ''And don't just drive down the block,'' Mr. Perrotta said. Take it on a highway and in traffic. Make sure the brakes (and clutch, if it has a manual transmission) get a workout. Fifteen minutes is a minimum to test whether the car will suit you.</p>
        <p>DIG DEEPER -- With an expensive used car, it is worth checking the ownership history. Carfax keeps records by vehicle identification number, which tell whether a car has been in accidents, floods or fires and how many times the title has changed hands. Web sites like Vehix.com will provide a Carfax report for $14.95.</p>
        <p>BUY AN EXTENDED WARRANTY -- ''You will probably only be offered a six-month powertrain and engine warranty,'' Mr. Perrotta said, ''so you will want something better than that, especially if you are financing the car.'' He suggested a warranty for at least the length of the loan period.</p>
        <p>ROBERT STRAUSS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
