<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Canseco To Sit In This Series</title>
    <meta content="11PINS$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/11/sports/11PINS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237985"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="2000 PLAYOFFS: NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Seattle Mariners</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olney, Buster</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Canseco, Jose</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Seattle Mariners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001011T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E4D71F3CF932A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="791" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Canseco To Sit In This Series</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olney, Buster</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Yankees roster moves for American League Championship Series against Seattle Mariners noted; Jose Canseco will not be on active roster for series; he comments (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jose Canseco, whose 446 career homers would have been the most for any player in the American League Championship Series, was dropped from the Yankees' active roster yesterday and replaced by Jason Grimsley.</p>
        <p>With Chuck Knoblauch entrenched as the designated hitter, Canseco had no role in the way Manager Joe Torre has been using his players. The Yankees have only one or two regulars for whom Torre might pinch-hit, third baseman Scott Brosius and second baseman Luis Sojo. The Yankees' two most effective pinch-hitters are Glenallen Hill and Luis Polonia.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jose Canseco, whose 446 career homers would have been the most for any player in the American League Championship Series, was dropped from the Yankees' active roster yesterday and replaced by Jason Grimsley.</p>
        <p>With Chuck Knoblauch entrenched as the designated hitter, Canseco had no role in the way Manager Joe Torre has been using his players. The Yankees have only one or two regulars for whom Torre might pinch-hit, third baseman Scott Brosius and second baseman Luis Sojo. The Yankees' two most effective pinch-hitters are Glenallen Hill and Luis Polonia.</p>
        <p>Canseco spoke with Torre behind the batting cage before Game 4 of the division series to discuss the situation, and when Canseco arrived at the ballpark yesterday, Torre called him into his office and informed him of the decision. Canseco said he was not surprised.</p>
        <p>''I've never been in this position before,'' Canseco said, ''but it's probably the right move. I think you always want to be a part of the team, even if sometimes you're playing daily and you don't produce.''</p>
        <p>Canseco has not consistently produced for the Yankees after being claimed on waivers from the Tampa Bay Devil Rays on Aug. 7. Torre was initially leery of the move because he was not sure he would be able to incorporate Canseco and keep him comfortable at the plate. The veteran initially hit well, drawing walks and presenting a power threat, but unlike Polonia and Hill, Canseco is not accustomed to sporadic playing time, and he finished poorly.</p>
        <p>The Yankees were so desperate for offense in the last two weeks of the regular season that if Canseco had gotten hot, he would have stayed in the lineup into the postseason. But Canseco had only 5 hits in 35 at-bats in his last 10 games, with no homers.</p>
        <p>''It was tough to try to get him in there consistently because of all the people we have used in the designated-hitter role,'' Torre said. ''He has not been a problem in any way. He has been as quiet as can be. He does all of his work. He does what he needs to do and he's worked very hard at trying to get his arm in shape because he didn't do a whole lot of playing other than D.H.''</p>
        <p>But Torre is settled, for now, on starting Luis Sojo at second base and keeping Knoblauch as his leadoff batter. ''Right now, Knoblauch will be my D.H. because I think that's more of the type of club that I'm used to having,'' Torre said.</p>
        <p>Grimsley began feeling pain in his elbow about two months ago and tried to pitch with it, without informing the Yankees' trainers. But his elbow began to swell Sept. 29, and Grimsley's problem was diagnosed as a bone chip and bone spur in the joint. He will need surgery after the season. But with Denny Neagle moving into the rotation for at least one game in this series, Torre felt that he needed to add another pitcher for middle relief. This is the first time Torre has carried 11 pitchers on his postseason roster.</p>
        <p>If the Yankees advance to the World Series, Torre said, then Canseco could be added to the roster. The Yankees would have more need for him in the middle three games of the World Series, in the National League city, where the designated hitter is not used.</p>
        <p>Pivotal Matchup</p>
        <p>A matchup to monitor as this series begins: The Yankees closer Mariano Rivera dominates most hitters, but the Seattle designated hitter Edgar Martinez has 10 hits in 12 career at-bats against Rivera, for a .833 average.</p>
        <p>''Edgar's a great hitter, and Rivera throws the ball at one speed and usually in the same part of the plate,'' one scout said. ''He just dries that cutter to the opposite field.''</p>
        <p>Two Coaches Draw Interest</p>
        <p>The Los Angeles Dodgers have asked for permission to interview the Yankees coaches Willie Randolph and Chris Chambliss for their managerial opening, and Dodgers officials are expected to talk to both men when this series shifts to Seattle.</p>
        <p>Randolph is one of the candidates for the Philadelphia Phillies' managerial job, and Chambliss will talk to the Arizona Diamondbacks about possibly replacing Buck Showalter. Club officials say privately what Torre said publicly the other day -- they hope that the inquiries about Chambliss and Randolph are serious, and not just an effort to satisfy the dictum of Commissioner Bud Selig that teams consider minorities.</p>
        <p>2000 PLAYOFFS: NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
