<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>3 Men Vital to the Internet Share Nobel Prize in Physics</title>
    <meta content="11PHYS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/11/science/11PHYS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237914"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Physics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nobel Prizes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fiber Optics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Satellites</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Swedish Academy</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kroemer, Herbert (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Alferov, Zhores I (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kilby, Jack S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Glanz, James</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fiber Optics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Physics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Satellites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nobel Prizes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001011T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E1DA1F3CF932A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="867" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>3 Men Vital to the Internet Share Nobel Prize in Physics</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES GLANZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Glanz, James</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>2000 Nobel Prize in Physics is awarded to Herbert Kroemer, Zhores I Alferov and Jack S Kilby for development of electrical components that facilitate rapid communications using fiber optics and satellites, and are central to personal computers; Swedish Academy cites worldwide impact of Internet; emphasis on applied rather than basic science is sharp departure for academy; their photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Citing the worldwide impact of the Internet enabled by their work, the Royal Swedish Academy of Sciences has awarded the 2000 Nobel Prize in Physics to three scientists who developed electrical components that allow for fast communication using fiber optics and satellites and that serve as the soul of the personal computer.</p>
        <p>The emphasis on applied rather than basic science represents a sharp departure by the Swedish Academy, which has for decades favored abstract breakthroughs like the discovery of new subatomic particles or the creation of unusual states of matter, said scientists both inside and outside the academy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Citing the worldwide impact of the Internet enabled by their work, the Royal Swedish Academy of Sciences has awarded the 2000 Nobel Prize in Physics to three scientists who developed electrical components that allow for fast communication using fiber optics and satellites and that serve as the soul of the personal computer.</p>
        <p>The emphasis on applied rather than basic science represents a sharp departure by the Swedish Academy, which has for decades favored abstract breakthroughs like the discovery of new subatomic particles or the creation of unusual states of matter, said scientists both inside and outside the academy.</p>
        <p>Half of this year's prize money, which totals 9 million kronor or about $913,000, will go to Jack S. Kilby, a 76-year-old retired engineer for Texas Instruments in Dallas, for his part in the invention of the integrated circuit, the miniaturized electronic chip that drives computers.</p>
        <p>The other half is to be split by Dr. Zhores I. Alferov, the director of the A. F. Ioffe Physico-Technical Institute in St. Petersburg, Russia, and Dr. Herbert Kroemer, a physicist and professor at the University of California at Santa Barbara.</p>
        <p>Dr. Alferov, who is 70, and Dr. Kroemer, who is 72, were cited for independently developing electronic components called heterostructures that turned small, solid-state lasers into practical devices and greatly accelerated communications circuitry. The lasers are used in compact-disc players, bar-code readers and fiber optics; the circuitry is important in the operation of cell phones and satellite communications.</p>
        <p>First conceived in the late 1950's and early 1960's, the heterostructures, involving what were then novel materials, had their biggest impact on small lasers, Dr. Kroemer said. ''It was a question of making something possible that without heterostructures simply couldn't have been done at all.'' Without the structures, he added, ''there would be no CD players and no CD's.''</p>
        <p>Creating integrated circuits required building numerous electrical components like transistors from a single block of material, rather than assembling them with wires and other components. Integrated circuits have continued to shrink since Mr. Kilby built some of the first ones in 1958; he said that ''the process has been refined to a degree that would have seemed unbelievable.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kilby was involved in a long and complex patent fight with Dr. Robert N. Noyce, who built an integrated circuit at about the same time and later helped found the Intel Corporation. Many scientists said that if Dr. Noyce, who died in 1990, were still alive, he would have shared a prize with Mr. Kilby.</p>
        <p>The focus on what some physicists regard as engineering rather than pure science sparked widely differing reactions among scientists.</p>
        <p>Unlike the particle discoveries oftenhonored by the Nobels, said Dr. Carver Mead, an emeritus professor of engineering and applied science at the California Institute of Technology, ''Each of these innovations has made the world a much better place and changed a lot of people's lives. So I think it's about time we got centered back on the stuff that really matters to real people.''</p>
        <p>But Dr. Michael Riordan, a physicist at the Stanford Linear Accelerator Center and the co-author of ''Crystal Fire'' (W. W. Norton), a history of the transistor, called the integrated circuit ''an engineering feat, not a scientific one,'' involving a rearrangement of known elements.</p>
        <p>By contrast, he said, the invention of the transistor itself, for which a Nobel Prize was awarded in 1956, required an intimate understanding of how electrons behave in semiconducting materials like silicon.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kilby disputed that assessment, saying that the writers of the news release accompanying the award ''did choose to point out the fact that there was some new physics involved.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Alferov said the criticism did not apply to the research on heterostructures. ''This is a basic science achievement -- basic science with a lot of applications in engineering.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Anders Barany, a professor of physics at Stockholm University and the secretary of the Nobel Committee for Physics, which recommends winners to the full Swedish Academy, admitted that this year's award was ''not in line with the other prizes'' in recent times and is of a more applied nature.</p>
        <p>''Whether this marks a new direction is still a question,'' he said. The theme, however, is clear, he said. ''If you really think about it, what are these three inventions doing? They are the three inventions that are driving the Internet.''</p>
        <p>Even some scientists involved in semiconductor research found the turn of events surprising. ''I frankly didn't think it would go in this direction,'' said Dr. Nick Holonyak Jr., a professor of electrical and computer engineering and physics at the Urbana-Champaign campus of the University of Illinois.</p>
        <p>Scientists in other fields were more critical. This year's physics prize, said Dr. John Learned, a particle astrophysicist at the University of Hawaii, has ''little to do with fundamental science. I guess it is the tilt of our commercial era.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
