<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Old Pro Learns Some New Tricks</title>
    <meta content="11KITC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/11/living/11KITC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237812"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TEST KITCHEN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Food Processors</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cuisinart</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fabricant, Florence</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001011T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E2DF1E3CF932A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="599" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Old Pro Learns Some New Tricks</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FLORENCE FABRICANT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fabricant, Florence</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Comment on latest Cuisinart model, the PowerPrep Plus, which has reconfigured base, new dough setting and stainless-steel dough blade; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE Cuisinart's profile, so familiar for more than 25 years, has had a curvaceous makeover. The latest model, the PowerPrep Plus, has a sleek white rounded base instead of an angular one. Also new are touch-pad buttons, which replace levers, and a work bowl made of clear, not smoky, plastic. The feed tube, originally in the front, is there again.</p>
        <p>But this new machine is not just comelier. A new setting has been added, for mixing and kneading yeast doughs, and a reconfigured stainless-steel dough blade has replaced the barely adequate plastic one.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE Cuisinart's profile, so familiar for more than 25 years, has had a curvaceous makeover. The latest model, the PowerPrep Plus, has a sleek white rounded base instead of an angular one. Also new are touch-pad buttons, which replace levers, and a work bowl made of clear, not smoky, plastic. The feed tube, originally in the front, is there again.</p>
        <p>But this new machine is not just comelier. A new setting has been added, for mixing and kneading yeast doughs, and a reconfigured stainless-steel dough blade has replaced the barely adequate plastic one.</p>
        <p>Over the years, there have been subtle changes in the machine, which was introduced in 1973. Machine capacity grew from 7 cups to 14, the feed tube was moved to the back on many models, the motor was strengthened and the pulse button was added. But this is the first time a new feature has been incorporated into a total redesign.</p>
        <p>So, do I spend more than $300 on the new model and wind up with two food processors, or consign my reliable DLC-7 Super Pro to a thrift shop? (It would be nice if I could trade it in, like a used car.)</p>
        <p>As a baker, I would probably spring for the PowerPrep Plus. While the new machine performs much the same as my 15-year-old one, the added dough setting and the curved but blunt metal dough blade are most effective. I tried a heavy yeast bread recipe, one calling for six cups of flour, and the blade and setting handled it beautifully, kneading the dough in 45 seconds.</p>
        <p>''We wanted to refine the machine for the high-end user, for hobbyist cooks,'' said Kerry Cooper, the senior marketing manager for food processors at Cuisinart, which has its headquarters in Stamford, Conn. ''We worked with Charles van Over to engineer the dough setting and the blade.''</p>
        <p>Mr. van Over is the author of ''The Best Bread Ever'' (Broadway Books, 1997), which outlined the connection between temperature, time and oxidation in bread baking. Mr. van Over came up with virtually foolproof food processor methods. Some of his recipes are in the instruction booklet.</p>
        <p>With the new dough setting, dough is mixed and kneaded at 1,350 r.p.m.'s instead of 1,750 at the regular setting. At the slower speed there is less aeration, Mr. Cooper said, ''so you get a better mix and your dough is much more tolerant if you happen to use a little too much liquid.''</p>
        <p>Because the work bowl capacity and the blade housing are the same in the new model and in my old machine, I tried mixing the six-cup bread recipe in the old model, using the new dough blade. The machine struggled. I finished the recipe in the new machine. A pizza recipe using just three cups of flour came out about as fine using the new dough blade in my old machine as in the new one.</p>
        <p>I also found that walnuts pulsed with the regular metal knife blade on the slower dough setting came out more evenly chopped than they did on the regular, faster speed; another bonus for a baker.</p>
        <p>The Cuisinart PowerPrep Plus, with a suggested retail price of $425, is sold in many housewares stores for around $325. The dough blade, which comes with the machine, can be bought separately for $30.</p>
        <p>TEST KITCHEN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
