<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Store of Their Very Own</title>
    <meta content="22TWEE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240724"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="IN BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Boo Girls (Katonah, Ny, Shop)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rosenberg, Merri</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001022T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE0DF153EF931A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1205" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Store of Their Very Own</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MERRI ROSENBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rosenberg, Merri</byline>
      <dateline>KATONAH</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article describes scene at Boo Girls, retail store in Katonah, NY, that caters to pre-teen girls; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LIKE hunters circling their prey, Nicole Pucci and Adrienne Hayes assessed the racks of clothes at Boo Girls.  Would their quarry be the sequined skirt? That velvet top? Or perhaps the paisley dress?</p>
        <p>Shopping as purposeful excursion, suburban pastime and high art is nothing new, particularly among elegant women in Westchester.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LIKE hunters circling their prey, Nicole Pucci and Adrienne Hayes assessed the racks of clothes at Boo Girls.  Would their quarry be the sequined skirt? That velvet top? Or perhaps the paisley dress?</p>
        <p>Shopping as purposeful excursion, suburban pastime and high art is nothing new, particularly among elegant women in Westchester.</p>
        <p>But Nicole and Adrienne are sixth graders at the Rippowam-Cisqua School, and they represent a new target market for clothing retailers: fashion-conscious 8-  to 12-year-olds who are eager to adapt runway looks for the schoolyard. Such buyers, known in the industry as ''tweens,'' have an estimated spending power of $20 billion a year.</p>
        <p>None of this surprises those who follow the buying patterns of the younger generation.</p>
        <p>''Kids are not being kids anymore,'' said Britt Bivens, an account executive with Promostyl in Manhattan, a trend forecasting company. ''It's age compression. The phenomenon of childhood is getting shorter. There's so much influence from older siblings and the media. By the time they're 8, these girls are not playing with Barbie. They want to look like the people they see on TV.</p>
        <p>''These tweens are the next big population group. One major brand has even started making 0 and 00 sizes so that tweens could buy the clothes in the junior department.''</p>
        <p>Boo Girls is an offshoot of Sticky Fingers, a seven-year-old children's clothing boutique next door. It was started last April when Gaynor Scott, the owner, realized that she was losing some customers, those who shunned shopping at what they perceived to be a children's store even if they were only in fourth grade.</p>
        <p>''I had always carried up to size 16 for girls,'' said Ms. Scott, the mother of two boys. She admitted that she herself is not much of a shopper. ''Two years ago I had noticed that the sales in that area of sizes 10 to 16 had slowed down and that the girls weren't coming in. They were going off to the mall. Girls who were 8 and 9 perceived the store as a 'baby store.'</p>
        <p>''This space opened up, and I had wanted to open a separate store for the tweens and juniors. Since I opened in April, it's exceeded expectations. The customers came back.''</p>
        <p>Other boutiques in the county, like Curiouser &amp; Curiouser in Mount Kisco, Times Gone By in Dobbs Ferry and the Star-Spangled Carousel in Armonk, among others, also cater to the more sophisticated tweens in their shops. And there are other shopping destinations, like the Brass Plum department at Nordstrom, The Gap Kids, Old Navy, Delia's, and Limited Too, which also appeal to this age group. But unlike Boo Girls, those stores do not have separate shopping spaces just for tweens.</p>
        <p>It's clearly not just about the clothes.</p>
        <p>Part clubhouse and part boutique, Boo Girls is the kind of place where on any given Friday, the customers -- and their mothers -- are likely to run into neighbors, classmates and friends and spend nearly as much time pointing out adorable outfits for others to wear as to find the perfect ensemble for themselves.</p>
        <p>With birthday parties a major feature of this group's social life, the store has also become a popular place to buy gifts, whether it's brushed aluminum picture frames, plush slippers, bath and cosmetic products or zebra-printed lamps.</p>
        <p>''The girls were thrilled to have a shop of their own,'' said Ms. Scott, many of whose customers travel from Connecticut and  Manhattan as well as Scarsdale, Chappaqua, Ossining and other communities in the county. ''They could walk into town with a friend after school. I have some customers who check in every week. They're happy to have a place to go to consider their little boutique where they can find new and  trendy clothes.''</p>
        <p>What also separates Ms. Scott's shops from mall stores, she said, is her focus on providing stylish clothes that recognize that her customers haven't yet reached adolescence.</p>
        <p>''These are girls who are very sophisticated,'' she said. ''Their mothers can't shop without them. They know what they want. The mothers don't want the daughters to look sexy or tacky. They want nice, appropriate clothing, with a little bit of trendiness, a little edgy. It's a younger version of what their mothers wear.''</p>
        <p>Her offerings from designers like Monkey Wear, Les Touts Petits, Maxou, Nicole Miller and Metropolitan Prairie are clearly culled to negotiate the delicate balance between her customers' desire to be fashionable and their mothers' desire to see them dress appropriately. The look that the tweens covet at Boo Girls is more individual, not mass-market fashions.</p>
        <p>So Ms. Scott offers trimmed cotton jeans, decorated T-shirts or even long dresses in simple silhouettes and good quality fabrics that make a 10-year-old look fashionable without looking as if she's ready to hit the club scene. Recently, the racks at Boo Girls featured studded fringe tops and a fringed zebra-print skirt, along with a brown floral embossed jacket and skirt set.</p>
        <p>Melissa Perlstein, manager of Curiouser &amp; Curiouser in Mount Kisco, said: ''Things really changed with shows like ''90210.'' Twelve-year-olds are like 16-year-olds. It's less little-girly. They want trendy now.''</p>
        <p>In the Boo Girls compact store, there are ottomans in plush fabric where customers can read magazines like Teen, Jump, Twist and Cosmo Girl while waiting for a fitting room or a friend.</p>
        <p>''It's one of my favorite stores,'' said 12-year-old Adrienne, who comes from Cross River about once a week.</p>
        <p>And while some customers drop $200 to $300 in a visit -- and well in excess of $500 for back-to-school outfitting -- Ms. Scott said that she keeps enough modestly priced items so a tween with baby-sitting money can find appealing products in the $15 to $20 range, or even less if all she craves is an eye-shadow or nail polish.</p>
        <p>''I come in about three times a month,'' said Leah Horowitz, 12, who was looking for a new top for an outfit. ''I like the accessories and nice skirts.''</p>
        <p>Since Rippowam-Cisqua requires its students to wear uniforms, students like Adrienne and Nicole can express their individuality on weekends and vacations. Nicole laughed when asked how often she checked out the new stock at Boo Girls and explained that since her brother's soccer games are in town she is a frequent visitor.</p>
        <p>Jocelyn Hayes, mother to Adrienne and Chloe, 8, said: ''I can give them more freedom here. There really is a range here, and they love the store. They shouldn't look like their mothers, but they shouldn't look like Britney Spears either.''</p>
        <p>IN BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
