<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Nation; The Legal Profession Smells a Rat</title>
    <meta content="22GLAB$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/22/weekinreview/22GLAB.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240968"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Legal Profession</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Rats</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Glaberson, William</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dundes, Alan (Prof)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Galanter, Marc (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legal Profession</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001022T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6DD1E3EF931A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="941" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Nation; The Legal Profession Smells a Rat</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM GLABERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Glaberson, William</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Treacherous rat seems to be emerging as dominant symbolic stand-in for lawyers; Internet is crawling with animated cartoons of lawyers portrayed as rats; Alan Dundes, folklorist and professor of anthropology at University of California at Berkeley, and Prof Marc Galanter, leading scholar of legal humor, comment; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR at least a few centuries, lawyers have been portrayed in jokes, cartoons and other expressions of popular culture as maggots, vipers, sharks, locusts and other creatures you wouldn't necessarily ask for a dance. But these days one of the most persistent images -- the treacherous rat -- seems to be emerging as the dominant symbolic stand-in for members of the legal profession.</p>
        <p>There are signs aplenty of the rat-lawyer correlation. Consider, for example, that jokes comparing lawyers and rats have multiplied like, well, crazy. There is even new scholarship suggesting that one particular lawyer-as-rat joke has become the most popular of all lawyer jokes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR at least a few centuries, lawyers have been portrayed in jokes, cartoons and other expressions of popular culture as maggots, vipers, sharks, locusts and other creatures you wouldn't necessarily ask for a dance. But these days one of the most persistent images -- the treacherous rat -- seems to be emerging as the dominant symbolic stand-in for members of the legal profession.</p>
        <p>There are signs aplenty of the rat-lawyer correlation. Consider, for example, that jokes comparing lawyers and rats have multiplied like, well, crazy. There is even new scholarship suggesting that one particular lawyer-as-rat joke has become the most popular of all lawyer jokes.</p>
        <p>In addition, the Internet is virtually crawling with animated cartoons of lawyers portrayed as rats. And one cannot neglect the somewhat mysterious West Coast lawyer who goes by the pen name The Rodent and sometimes wears a rat-head costume. He has been satirizing the legal profession since the 1990's with columns in legal newspapers, a newsletter and a book including such ratly pearls of wisdom as, ''Lawyers are attracted to each other because we repel everyone else.''</p>
        <p>Does this and other evidence suggest the rat's pre-eminence as a pop-culture surrogate for lawyers? The data were collected and presented to Alan Dundes, a renowned folklorist and a professor of anthropology at the University of California at Berkeley.</p>
        <p>True, Professor Dundes was recovering from a back injury and more or less had to answer the phone next to his bed. But he did listen cheerfully to a catalog of lawyer-rat jokes and references.</p>
        <p>Both rats and lawyers seem to multiply quickly like ''a kind of plague,'' he noted, and are popularly associated with dishonesty and betrayal. ''The fact that we have this high incidence of the association of rats and lawyers is a telling point,'' he said. ''It is a folk judgment. Folklore, after all, is the voice of the people.''</p>
        <p>Obviously, dissenters can be found to all cutting-edge observations. So some people interviewed for this article insisted that the skunk or perhaps the weasel could overtake the rat as a legal icon. Officials at the American Bar Association had an entirely different response, but why dwell on unpleasantness?</p>
        <p>It might be more amusing to report that a forthcoming book by Prof. Marc Galanter, who may be the nation's leading scholar of legal humor, concludes that the current front-runner among lawyer jokes is a verminous barb born in the 1980's. (Why have laboratories started using lawyers instead of rats in experiments? One: There are more of them. Two: The lab assistants don't get attached to them. And three: There are some things a rat just won't do.)</p>
        <p>Professor Galanter teaches at the University of Wisconsin Law School and the London School of Economics. At first, he said he wasn't sure his findings on the popularity of the lab-rats joke led to any broader conclusions. ''A few years ago,'' he said tentatively, ''there was a kind of a lizard thing.''</p>
        <p>But on reflection, he warmed to the rat-lawyer correlation. It turns out his study of legal humor, ''Lowering the Bar,'' to be published by Oxford University Press next year, contains quite a few rat references. (A prominent law firm, for example, was overrun by rats while the partners were seeing clients, and one lawyer wondered why the rats didn't wait to show up until after business hours -- as a professional courtesy.) ''It has clearly become prevalent now, this lawyer-rat association,'' Professor Galanter said finally.</p>
        <p>He found, for example, that the 1998 Lawyer Joke-a-Day Calendar featured 10 separate rat jokes. And he found endless permutations of the lab-rat joke (one disadvantage of substituting lawyers for rats in experiments is that, ''It is harder to extrapolate the test results to human beings,'' though on the plus side, ''Animal rights activists don't care if you torture them.'')</p>
        <p>PROFESSOR GALANTER is not alone in discovering the rat-lawyer linkage. Three weeks ago, Matt Fleischer, a reporter for The National Law Journal, turned over a rather significant rock when he took note of two ratlike animations of lawyers appearing or about to appear on different Web sites. Mr. Fleischer also reported something of a lawyer-rat infestation: he came upon an artist who said he had done four other rat-lawyer animations on the Net in recent years and knew of at least 11 in all.</p>
        <p>The new cyberrodents cited by Mr. Fleischer are Dax, seen on shockwave.com, and Gary the Rat, set to pop up next month on Mediatrip.com. Dax is a cigar-chomping celebrity rat lawyer assisted by the able Lolita, supposedly a former law clerk for Associate Justice Clarence Thomas of the Supreme Court. Gary is a materialistic, self-centered lawyer-turned-rat whose voice will be supplied by the actor Kelsey Grammer.</p>
        <p>In an interview for this article, the brothers who created Gary the Rat, Mark and Rob Cullen, explained why creative people are drawn to the lawyer-rat image. They wanted their animation to explore the materialism and insensitivity of modern life, they said. ''Well, for me, a lawyer personified that,'' said Mark Cullen. ''And I thought, What's the other most hated being on the planet? And that would be the rat.''</p>
        <p>The Rodent, too, agreed to an interview on the condition that his real name and the company where he works as a lawyer not be disclosed. He said the rat association seemed so natural for an underground lawyer-satirist that people rarely questioned him about his nom de plume: ''If I had picked Anteater, say, people would have said, 'Why that?' ''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
