<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Little Havana</title>
    <meta content="22DINE$10" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20001029T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240802"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="RESTAURANTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Martino's (Somerville, Nj, Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Corcoran, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001022T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E1D6123EF931A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1193" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Little Havana</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID CORCORAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Corcoran, David</byline>
      <dateline>SOMERVILLE</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>David Corcoran reviews Martino's, Cuban restaurant in Somerville, NJ; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT was a spring evening in 1994, and Martino Linares was lost. His mood was dark. He had just lost his job as a chef at an Italian restaurant in Warren. Driving home to Dover, he somehow detoured onto Main Street in this well-worn town. He saw a man standing at a corner and stopped to ask directions.</p>
        <p>A lifetime of wandering had led him to this spot. Born in Cuba, he emigrated to Miami as a young man in 1950, volunteered in the Bay of Pigs invasion in 1961, was captured and spent three years in a Cuban prison, returned to the United States, cooked in French and Italian and kosher restaurants along the Eastern Seaboard, and finally found himself, jobless, on this desolate corner.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT was a spring evening in 1994, and Martino Linares was lost. His mood was dark. He had just lost his job as a chef at an Italian restaurant in Warren. Driving home to Dover, he somehow detoured onto Main Street in this well-worn town. He saw a man standing at a corner and stopped to ask directions.</p>
        <p>A lifetime of wandering had led him to this spot. Born in Cuba, he emigrated to Miami as a young man in 1950, volunteered in the Bay of Pigs invasion in 1961, was captured and spent three years in a Cuban prison, returned to the United States, cooked in French and Italian and kosher restaurants along the Eastern Seaboard, and finally found himself, jobless, on this desolate corner.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Linares will, he fell into animated conversation with the stranger, who turned out to be the owner of the corner building, whose ground-floor storefront just happened to be vacant. One thing led to another, and within two months Mr. Linares took out a lease and opened his own Italian restaurant -- Martino's Ristorante, whose name is on the front door to this day.</p>
        <p>''Wait, there's more,'' Mr. Linares's son Ulysses told me. A few months after the ristorante opened, none too successfully, a self-appointed local food critic began badgering the elder Mr. Linares about the menu. ''What does Somerville need with one more Italian restaurant?'' he demanded. ''You're Cuban. Why don't you serve Cuban food?''</p>
        <p>It was great advice. Nobody will ever mistake Somerville for Little Havana, and on paper it's an unlikely restaurant capital -- a borough of 13,000 whose chief distinctions are that it's the Somerset County seat and the boyhood home of Paul Robeson. Nevertheless, it seems to thrive on diversity and pluck. When the Bridgewater Commons mall went up in the early 1980's, downtown Somerville refused to concede its commercial vitality; restaurants and antique shops took the place of stores that fled to the highway. Now the town has dozens of restaurants, eight of them listed in the Zagat Survey.</p>
        <p>To judge by the happy crowds who kept the place hopping on two recent Saturday evenings, Martino's is prospering, and it's easy to see why. The mood is ebullient. Large families eat at the large tables. Latin music plays, and if you hang in long enough you may see Martino Linares himself, an elfin man with a flowing gray mane, bound out of the kitchen and mambo across the dining room with a waitress.</p>
        <p>The food is far from subtle, but it is very easy to eat. A sign on the wall boasts of ''pre-Castro old style Cuban cooking,'' and while I can't testify that people actually dined this way in the Cuba of Mr. Linares's youth, it is generous, full-flavored and very gently priced.</p>
        <p>Even the appetizers are huge and rich: a dozen good-sized clams, for example, in a thick and assertive lemon-garlic broth fragrant with cilantro, tomatoes and peppers. Mr. Linares's tostones rellenos are a wonder, rounds of mild plantains that are breaded, stuffed with mashed potatoes, deep-fried and then bathed in a long-simmered sauce of tomatoes, peppers, olives and coriander. Somehow, through all this, they retain their crunch and a nutty flavor that sets off the electric-hot glow of the sauce. A pair of monster shrimp on the side seem irrelevant, though they make you wonder how Martino's can charge only $8.95 for this production.</p>
        <p>A Cuban appetizer sampler comprises two fried croquettes of chopped, breaded Virginia ham and two tasty cornmeal empanadas stuffed with ground pork and served with a cumin-scented tomato sauce. But if you're only having lunch, or want to spare your appetite for the onslaught of main courses, you might have nothing more than a $1.95 cup of some of the best black bean soup in New Jersey -- simple, powerful and elemental, with bits of ham and raw onion.</p>
        <p>Entrees are more abundant still, vast platters of meat or seafood surrounded by rice, black beans and disks of fried sweet plantains. The menu seems to go on forever, like a speech by Fidel Castro, offering not only Cuban but also Costa Rican, Colombian and Puerto Rican dishes. You could return here for months and never sample everything.</p>
        <p>One night, however, I hit the jackpot: I noticed a pan of roast suckling pig coming out of the kitchen, and though it wasn't on the menu, I asked and was rewarded with a great mound of it. The skin was rubbery, but the meat was moist, rich, powerful and sensuous.</p>
        <p>We enjoyed the standard pork dishes: roast pork Cuban style, tender chunks of meat sauteed in a mild garlic sauce; and pork mole, in which slabs of pork are slightly but not fatally tough and the sauce gains sweetness and bite from apples, green olives and jalapenos. The seafood -- shrimp, flounder, cod, striped bass, paella mariscada -- is straightforwardly cooked but tends to be overwhelmed by the sauces.</p>
        <p>Desserts are limited and utterly superfluous. But for $2.50 each there's a wonderful assortment of tropical shakes, notably passion fruit and soursop.</p>
        <p>I've saved the decor for last, because after two visits I still have no idea what to make of it. The ground-floor exterior of this fine turn-of-the-century brick building has been swathed in wood planks painted an angry red, a theme picked up in a sort of overhanging roof that dominates the larger of two dining rooms. From the eaves hang those little icicle lights that have become suburban staples at Christmastime, and a flock of cutout paper lambs that might have hung in your second-grade classroom at Easter. The look is rounded out by a random collection of garage-sale gewgaws and the occasional tiring poinsettia.</p>
        <p>Maybe this is a joke I'm not getting. But it does have one useful side effect: it lowers expectations for a meal and an evening that turn out to be delightful.</p>
        <p>Martino's</p>
        <p>212 West Main Street, Somerville</p>
        <p>(908) 722-8602</p>
        <p>GOOD</p>
        <p>ATMOSPHERE -- Festive and agreeably noisy, with wildly eccentric decor.  SERVICE -- Friendly but slow and often confused.  SMOKING -- None.  WINE LIST -- B.Y.O.  RECOMMENDED DISHES -- Black bean soup, tostones rellenos, clams, empanadas; roast pork Cuban style, pork mole, roast suckling pig; tropical fruit shakes.  PRICE RANGE -- Appetizers: $1.95 to $10.95; entrees: $8.95 to $20.95; shakes: $2.50; desserts: $3.  HOURS -- Closed Tuesdays. Wednesdays through Mondays, 11 a.m. to 10 p.m.  CREDIT CARDS -- American Express, MasterCard, Visa, Diners Club.  RESERVATIONS -- Recommended.  WHEELCHAIR ACCESS -- Everything on one level.</p>
        <p>RATINGS -- Poor, Fair, Satisfactory, Good, Very Good, Excellent,  Extraordinary.</p>
        <p>Ratings reflect the reviewer's reaction to food, ambience and service, with price taken into consideration. Menu listings and prices are subject to change.</p>
        <p>RESTAURANTS  Correction:  October 29, 2000, Sunday  A picture last Sunday with a restaurant review of Martino's, in Somerville, was published in error. It showed Encore, in Larchmont, N.Y.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: October 29, 2000, Sunday</p>
        <p>A picture last Sunday with a restaurant review of Martino's, in Somerville, was published in error. It showed Encore, in Larchmont, N.Y.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
