<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From Baltimore Warehouse to Giant Office Building</title>
    <meta content="22AFOC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240710"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Office Buildings and Other Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Baltimore (Md)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Belfoure, Charles</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Maryland/Baltimore</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Maryland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001022T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E3D8143EF931A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1241" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From Baltimore Warehouse to Giant Office Building</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLES BELFOURE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Belfoure, Charles</byline>
      <dateline>BALTIMORE</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Old Montgomery Ward warehouse in Baltimore is being transformed into Montgomery Park, $75 million complex that will be Baltimore's largest office building; photos; maps (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AN old Montgomery Ward warehouse is being transformed into what will be Baltimore's largest office building. In the largest adaptive use project under one roof in the city, the 1.3 million square foot building on 28 acres is to become office space that will eventually house up to 5,000 workers. The rehab will be based on a ''green'' design approach that reduces energy consumption costs and uses sustainable materials that are environmentally sensitive.</p>
        <p>Montgomery Park, as the new $75 million office and business complex will be called, is an eight-story reinforced-concrete building with 143,000 square feet per floor. It once housed Montgomery Ward's East Coast catalog operation and a retail store but has been vacant since 1985, when the venerable retailer closed the store and ceased catalog sales nationwide.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AN old Montgomery Ward warehouse is being transformed into what will be Baltimore's largest office building. In the largest adaptive use project under one roof in the city, the 1.3 million square foot building on 28 acres is to become office space that will eventually house up to 5,000 workers. The rehab will be based on a ''green'' design approach that reduces energy consumption costs and uses sustainable materials that are environmentally sensitive.</p>
        <p>Montgomery Park, as the new $75 million office and business complex will be called, is an eight-story reinforced-concrete building with 143,000 square feet per floor. It once housed Montgomery Ward's East Coast catalog operation and a retail store but has been vacant since 1985, when the venerable retailer closed the store and ceased catalog sales nationwide.</p>
        <p>Samuel K. Himmelrich Jr. and his partner, David F. Tufaro, formed Carroll Park L.L.C. and purchased the building in April from Montgomery Ward for more than $5 million. Mr. Himmelrich is a Baltimore developer with a successful track record in redeveloping old industrial properties.</p>
        <p>Until now, most major development projects in Baltimore have centered on the Inner Harbor, but Montgomery Park is a mile and a half to the southwest in an area that is dominated by parks and low-rise industrial buildings. The complex is across the street from Carroll Park, once the plantation of Charles Carroll, a barrister whose 18th century home, Mount Clare, can be seen from the building's upper-floor windows. Beyond the park is a spectacular view of the city skyline.</p>
        <p>Although not within walking distance of the harbor, the complex is three blocks from Interstate 95, which connects to the Baltimore Beltway, making commuting quite convenient for workers, who will have access to 3,500 free parking spaces.</p>
        <p>While some in the real estate industry thought the venture a gamble because of its distance from the harbor, many minds were changed when the Maryland Department of the Environment made a commitment in September for parts of four floors of space totaling 262,000 square feet.</p>
        <p>The building's vast expanse of floor space along with the adjacent parking could pull in tenants who have extra-large space needs. ''We've had a great surge of interest from prospective tenants,'' said Mr. Himmelrich, who noted that rents will be in the range of $15 to $20 a square foot annually.</p>
        <p>In addition to renting space for offices, Mr. Himmelrich plans to use about one quarter of the building as a ''telecom hotel,'' space rented by telecommunication and Internet companies to house the types of equipment that are the backbone and nerves of electronic commerce. Railroad rights of way that surround the complex get little use by trains nowadays but have been given a second life by telecommunications companies as pathways for underground fiber-optic lines. ''Telecom hotels need to be adjacent to these routes,'' Mr. Himmelrich explained.</p>
        <p>WHEN it issued its notice that it was seeking office space, the Department of the Environment said it was looking for a landlord that shared its interest in green design. The rehab of Montgomery Park will use recycled material in its new partitions, ceiling tile and resilient flooring, including 100 percent recycled carpeting. Sensors will adjust interior lighting depending on the amount of natural lighting during the day. About 75 percent of demolition debris like radiators and piping will be salvaged or recycled as well.</p>
        <p>Rainwater that hits the immense roof area of the building will be collected in underground tanks and pumped up to a 10,000 gallon tank, then used to flush toilets. Ice will be generated at night, when energy rates are low, then used for cooling during the day. Energy costs for the complex are expected to be about 98 cents a square foot annually, compared with about $2 in an average office building.</p>
        <p>The environmental agency was also looking for a site in keeping with Maryland's Smart Growth Initiative, which encourages rehabilitation of older buildings in areas with existing infrastructure. The department expects to move in by Sept. 1 next year.</p>
        <p>The building is basically U-shaped, and during its days as a catalog operation, trains pulled in under a train shed to unload merchandise. The shed -- about as long as a football field -- and its 22-foot-high steel trusses will be preserved, becoming the central organizing element of the complex, housing four glass-enclosed elevators at the main entry.</p>
        <p>It will also contain a garden atrium, a food court, a health club and an auditorium. As part of the environmentally driven design, the part of the shed's roof that is not skylit will literally be green, planted with grass and shrubbery reduce storm water runoff.</p>
        <p>The building, which was built in 1925, is under review by the National Park Service for consideration for the National Register of Historic Places as an excellent example of poured-in-place concrete industrial architecture and an important historical site as the biggest mercantile building in the city. If it qualifies as a historic building, some of the renovation cost may qualify for special tax benefits.</p>
        <p>The industrial aesthetic of the building will be embraced in its interior design, according to the project's architect, Werner A. Mueller of the Baltimore office of Daniel, Mann, Johnson, &amp; Mendenhall, a Los Angeles-based architecture, engineering and construction services firm.</p>
        <p>The building's floors are punctuated by concrete columns that are topped by mushroom capitals, and to keep this distinctive feature exposed, Mr. Mueller designed separate suspended canopies between them that will house lighting fixtures and will hide the heating and cooling trunk ducts above. A raised floor will allow under-floor wiring to all spaces and eliminate the need to cut troughs in the thick concrete floors.</p>
        <p>With some alteration, many existing pieces of infrastructure will be reused, including the sprinkler system, utility shafts, storm-water drains and the electrical conduit embedded in the ceilings. The rooftop structure that once held the 14 letters spelling out Montgomery Ward will be reused for Montgomery Park.</p>
        <p>Because they provide a great deal of natural daylight as well as being original to the complex, the tall industrial steel sash windows along the entire perimeter are to be restored and completely reglazed with insulating glass.</p>
        <p>Flaking paint on the entire Art Deco detailed facade is being removed and will be repainted the original color, an off white. A canopy erected in the 1960's along the ground floor will be removed, and the grand entry to the first floor store that was demolished at that time will be re-created, Mr. Himmelrich said. The only building on the site to be demolished will be a one-story automotive repair garage and garden shop on the Washington Boulevard side.</p>
        <p>When it opened, the Montgomery Ward complex was the first department store outside the downtown shopping district. The location was considered suburban, and the store emphasized its free parking in its advertising.</p>
        <p>Mr. Himmelrich also considers his project suburban, even though it is in the city, because it offers amenities like free parking, highway access and security. ''Montgomery Park will definitely interest those who might otherwise locate out in the suburbs,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
