<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A County Consumed by Supermarket Envy</title>
    <meta content="22SHOP$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240796"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Supermarkets</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Foderaro, Lisa W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Supermarkets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001022T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E3D7123EF931A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="2778" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A County Consumed by Supermarket Envy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LISA W. FODERARO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Foderaro, Lisa W</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on dearth of quality supermarkets in Westchester County, NY; retail analysts say that despite county's affluence it has some of the worst supermarkets, in terms of size, service and selection in US; county is poising for supermarket renaissance as new stores and superstores open; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WITH all the variables confronting home buyers in Westchester -- cost, commute, schools, mortgage rates, taxes, termites -- it's no wonder that the local supermarket rarely enters the equation.</p>
        <p>But after moving in, many new residents quickly come down with a social ill that seems particularly acute in Westchester: supermarket envy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WITH all the variables confronting home buyers in Westchester -- cost, commute, schools, mortgage rates, taxes, termites -- it's no wonder that the local supermarket rarely enters the equation.</p>
        <p>But after moving in, many new residents quickly come down with a social ill that seems particularly acute in Westchester: supermarket envy.</p>
        <p>Retail analysts and supermarket consultants say that for years Westchester has suffered a severe lack of supermarkets and that, for the most part, the stores that are here come up short in terms of size, service and selection, when compared with their counterparts across the country.</p>
        <p>''Westchester has one of the 10 highest incomes in the country but some of the worst supermarkets in the entire United States, regardless of income,'' said Burt P. Flickinger III, managing director of Reach Marketing in Westport, Conn., a marketing and retailing consulting firm. ''The Westchester consumer will go to the boroughs of New York and to Fairfield County rather than to experience the pain of supermarket shopping in Westchester.''</p>
        <p>In interviews with two dozen shoppers, the majority bemoaned their local market's produce section, groused about long checkout lines and universally complained about high prices.</p>
        <p>Adjectives like ''horrible,'' ''outdated,'' ''cramped'' and ''dingy'' cropped up again and again. Driving another 10 minutes or even a half hour to reach a favorite supermarket or specialty store was commonplace.</p>
        <p>Geoff Thompson, a public relations consultant who lives and works in central Westchester, rattled off a handful of supermarket choices within a 10-minute drive of his home: a C-Town in Ossining, a Food Emporium in Briarcliff Manor, a Shoprite in Croton-on-Hudson and an A.&amp;P. in Millwood. ''We kind of dance around between these various stores, not being particularly happy with any of them,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The closest one is the smallish A.&amp;P. in Millwood, a hamlet in the town of New Castle. With flourescent lights radiating from a ceiling that shows signs of water damage, it is his least favorite. ''We sort of grit our teeth and get what we have to get,'' he said. ''You won't see rats in the aisles. It doesn't feel like Calcutta. It's just that people have higher expectations.''</p>
        <p>But things are changing. Westchester is poised for a supermarket renaissance.</p>
        <p>In just the last year, the Stop &amp; Shop chain, based in Quincy, Mass., has made an aggressive push into the county. It has two  new superstores in New Rochelle and another in North White Plains, a store under construction in the Cross County Shopping Center in Yonkers and approvals for stores in Port Chester and White Plains.</p>
        <p>Last year also saw the opening of a few alternatives to traditional supermarkets, from the carnivalesque Stew Leonard's in Yonkers to the hugely popular Turco's. Beloved for its produce and fresh fish, Turco's opened a second store in Yorktown Heights after drawing shoppers for years from all over the county to the original in Hartsdale.</p>
        <p>At the same time, the few specialty food stores already here, as well as markets eager to break into the county, could realize an opportunity to expand, given the recent bankruptcy protection filing by Grand Union. It is the third Chapter 11 filing in six years for the struggling chain, based in Wayne, N.J., and the company says it is looking for a buyer.</p>
        <p>Supermarket consultants say the chain's nine stores in Westchester, ranging in size from 8,000 square feet to 40,000 square feet in affluent communities like Chappaqua and Larchmont, might end up being auctioned off individually to markets that do not require the kind of space a large supermarket chain demands.</p>
        <p>''You've got upscale markets like Gourmet Garage and Fairway and Wild Oats, all looking to come into Westchester County, and you've got all these Grand Unions coming available,'' said Martin A. Deitch of Aries Deitch &amp; Endelson, a leading commercial real estate company in Hartsdale. ''The demise of Grand Union is here. And these Grand Unions are going to turn into some absolutely phenomenal retail and specialty stores.''</p>
        <p>Howard Glickberg, an owner of Fairway, whose two stores -- in Harlem and on the Upper West Side -- are meccas for cost-conscious foodies, said he was eying the Grand Union in Dobbs Ferry, five minutes from his home in Irvington. ''I think Westchester would be wonderful,'' he said.</p>
        <p>There are many reasons, it seems, for the county's stunted food-retailing landcape.</p>
        <p>Developers cite restrictive zoning, the lack of available land, hilly terrain and the riddle that residents present by demanding a spacious, modern, supermarket convenient to them while shunning any proposed development close to home. Retail consultants like Mr. Flickinger point to the domination of the Grand Union Company and the Great Atlantic &amp; Pacific Tea Company, which owns Food Emporium, A.&amp;P. and Waldbaum's, among other chains.</p>
        <p>They had a ''half nelson on the market for far too long,'' Mr. Flickinger said of the two companies, ''and finally the consumers said, 'We quit, we can't take it, we'll drive as far as it takes.' ''</p>
        <p>Some say the fault lies, too, with consumers, many of them former Manhattanites who, fresh out of college, wheeled their first shopping carts through some of the tiniest, most overpriced supermarkets anywhere.</p>
        <p>''I privately speculate that that's one of the reasons we don't have better supermarkets here, because of the low expectations of people coming out of Manhattan,'' said P. Gilbert Mercurio, executive vice president of the Westchester County Board of Realtors, who emphasized that he was speaking as a county resident (who happens to live in White Plains but drives outside his city's borders to shop for food).</p>
        <p>''When I drive to Florida or New Jersey,'' he said, ''they have splendid supermarkets -- supermarkets that far surpass anything you'll see in Westchester in terms of size and choice. Westchester is just not up to par with the rest of the metropolitan region in my opinion.''</p>
        <p>That seems to be the view of many county residents, though certainly not all. Priscilla Painton, an assistant managing editor at Time magazine and a resident of the Cedar Knolls section of Yonkers, believes she is strategically situated for first-rate food shopping. And her buying patterns illustrate just how fractured and complex food shopping has become.</p>
        <p>''Within eight minutes of my home I have Stew Leonard's and for bulk food, Costco, and a very high-end Food Emporium in Bronxville,'' Ms. Painton said. ''If I have a really fancy dinner party, I will drive to Fairway on 125th Street. There's no problem parking, and it has the best cheese, as far as I can tell, on the East Coast. What I like is the complete diversity in price and kind of food.''</p>
        <p>But Ms. Painton lives in the more densely populated southern half of the county where there are simply more stores. In the northern half, supermarkets are more spread out, and some communities like Armonk, Chappaqua and Millwood feel especially dissatisfied with lackluster food outlets.</p>
        <p>A prime exception is Yorktown Heights, in northwest Westchester, which boasts a new Food Emporium, a remodeled A.&amp;P. superstore and a new Turco's. A&amp;P had tried without success to block Turco's from opening. But all three stores appeal to different consumers and the cluster draws shoppers from beyond the area.</p>
        <p>Ms. Painton's colleague, Dan Kadlec, who writes the column ''Your Money'' for Time, calls food shopping around his Chappaqua home ''abyssmal'' and longs for the ''palaces they have'' in the Midwest where he grew up.</p>
        <p>He and his wife do not enjoy shopping at the Grand Union in Chappaqua. (''I went in there to get a steak one time,'' he said, ''and I think the thickest steak they had was a quarter inch.'') Increasingly, they have given their business to the smaller gourmet shops in the hamlet, although Mr. Kadlec said he resents paying a premium.</p>
        <p>''Chappaqua is supposed to be this high-end, trendy little suburb, and yet there are real basic things we don't have,'' he said. ''For all the million-dollar houses in town you still don't have a decent grocery store. It cracks me up when I think about it.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kadlec surmises that Grand Union has not spruced itself up because people are willing to drive only so far to shop. ''Basically, you want to get it over with,'' he said. ''It's not how you want to spend Saturday.'' Experts on the supermarket industry add that another reason mediocre supermarkets can stay open is that many have cheap long-term leases, allowing them to be profitable even without doing a brisk business.</p>
        <p>But some Westchester residents say they do travel considerable distances to shop for food, regularly bypassing a supermarket around the corner with wilted red-leaf lettuce and sullen cashiers.</p>
        <p>Cecile Rothschild, a graphic designer in Armonk, is such a shopper. ''The supermarkets in Westchester are horrible,'' she said as she escorted her 5-year-old daughter, Lea, into the local Food Emporium, where, she said, she reluctantly goes a few times a week. Once a month she drives an extra 10 minutes to do extensive shopping at the new Stop &amp; Shop in North White Plains, and she also visits Zabar's in Manhattan monthly for cheese and coffee. Every week or so, she drives 18 to 20 minutes to Greenwich to a Fresh Fields Whole Foods Market, a store prized for its organic produce.</p>
        <p>It's the same for Patty Clark, a program manager in the aviation department at the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey. When she moved to Sleepy Hollow from Manhattan, she asked her neighbors where they shop for food. They suggested a supermarket 15 minutes north in Ossining, since there was no supermarket in Sleepy Hollow. ''I remember thinking, 'You have to go all the way to Ossining to get food?' and then I realized, 'Wow, we do have to go all the way to Ossining to get food,' '' Ms. Clark said.</p>
        <p>But she soon discovered an independently owned store called Scotts Corner Market in Pound Ridge, near the home of a friend but 35 minutes from her own. She was so taken by the fruits and vegetables, whose colors, she said, are ''out of a Matisse,'' that she drives across the county to shop there.</p>
        <p>In most parts of the United States, experts on the supermarket industry say, such treks are unheard of. In California or in the Washington area, the average shopper drives no more than three to five minutes to get to a favorite store, but in Westchester shoppers typically drive anywhere from 5 to 25 minutes, Mr. Flickinger said.</p>
        <p>Those contrasts have recently made supermarket developers more enthusiastic about building here, despite the obstacles.</p>
        <p>''The market got so tight and the demand got so great that the economics started to justify greater investment that really allowed the real estate to work,'' said Kenneth D. Narva, a managing partner of Street-Works in White Plains, a development and consulting concern specializing in mixed-use retail projects.</p>
        <p>Anthony Colavolpe, vice president of real estate for Stop &amp; Shop, recalled the difficult logistics of assembling land for the new store in White Plains. Working with another developer, the supermarket chain is relocating the city's department of public works and will then raze a bowling alley and bank. ''All of this to build a supermarket,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Turco's seems ideally positioned to take advantage of the harried Westchester shopper, with its copious takeout selection. The store smokes its own fish, makes 100 types of pastas and 30 different salads and employs a French baker, previously with Eli's Bread in Manhattan. ''It's just service and quality and reasonable prices,'' said Preston Turco, the president, who got his start with produce stores in the Bronx. ''You give the people what they want, not what they don't want.''</p>
        <p>A.&amp;P., of course, has seen the proliferation of alternative grocery outlets, but insists that its two-year-old campaign of self-improvement, called ''Project Great Renewal,'' was not a response to competition but an effort to ''proactively improve'' both the stores and service, said Richard De Santa, A.&amp;P.'s vice president for corporate affairs. The chain, based in Montvale, N.J., is closing underperforming stores and revamping existing Food Emporiums and A.&amp;P.'s as well as building new ones.</p>
        <p>The company, with 415 supermarkets in the East, wants to convert the entire store network over the next few years to one that is dominated by superstores, ranging in size from 45,000 square feet to 65,000 square feet. Indeed, the whole thrust in the industry has been toward larger and larger stores, with bakeries, pharmacies and coffee bars.</p>
        <p>A.&amp;P.'s chief executive officer, Christian Haub, began the campaign when he took over the company two years ago. ''He said we know we're not getting the job done in terms of customer service, and the other thing that hampers us is having too many smaller, older stores,'' Mr. De Santa said.</p>
        <p>Mr. De Santa said the chain still has a number of small, uninspired supermarkets that have not yet been scrutinized by the company. As leases expire on those stores, he said, the company could well decide to close them.</p>
        <p>But such closings can create new problems for a community, as is the case in Briarcliff Manor, where an A.&amp;P. was shuttered more than two years ago and now sits empty in a commercial district.</p>
        <p>''Prior to the closing, the Briarcliff Manor A.&amp;P. was overwhelmingly the most hated supermarket in the area,'' Keith Austin, the village's mayor, said. ''I can understand the business proposition of closing marginal stores, but it's hurting us. You have a big empty storefront and the remaining stores are getting killed.''</p>
        <p>The village's insistence that whatever replaces the A.&amp;P. be modest in scale illustrates the kind of Catch-22 facing both shoppers and the industry. Shoppers seem eager for giant stores able to offer competitive prices and a staggering selection, but they do not want them in their neighborhoods.</p>
        <p>''Nowadays everyone wants a 65,000-square-foot big box, but we're not interested in that,'' Mr. Austin said. ''We're trying to preserve a rather small village feel.''</p>
        <p>The ideal combination, many shoppers say, would be a specialty store down the street and a superstore maybe 10 minutes away, causing traffic snarls in someone else's neighborhood. Indeed, in Armonk two years ago, residents came out to fight proposals for two supermarkets, and Mr. Thompson, the public relations consultant who had represented one of the two developers, remembers hearing people chant ''Hay Day, Hay Day.''</p>
        <p>It was a reference to a small chain of sumptuous food markets, with prices to match, owned by Sutton Place Gourmet in Bethesda, Md., which merged with Balducci's in Manhattan last year. There is a Hay Day in Scarsdale and three in Fairfield County.</p>
        <p>In the end, the two supermarket proposals for Armonk, a hamlet in the town of North Castle, were withdrawn. Now, one of the developers, McCann Real Equities Development, has returned with a proposal for a new Food Emporium that does not require a variance, only site-plan approval. It would replace the existing Food Emporium, the one residents seem to love to hate, on a site a mile away. Although it would be small for a new supermarket, at 31,000 square feet, the store would be almost twice the size of the one there now.</p>
        <p>Still, there is opposition, especially from residents in a new development of $700,000 houses adjacent to the charming cider mill that would be torn down to accommodate the new supermarket.</p>
        <p>''It's one of those great Westchester dilemmas,'' Mr. Thompson said. ''On the one hand you have people clamoring for a better supermarket, but on the other hand they don't want to have anything built. And you know what ends up happening? Nothing.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
