<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'Red Menace' to Warhol's Factory: The City as Bohemia</title>
    <meta content="22BOOK$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Books; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240863"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEW YORK BOOKSHELF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Powers, Ann</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stansell, Christine</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kerouac, Jack</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnson, Joyce</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">American Moderns (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Door Wide Open: A Beat Love Affair In Letters, 1957-1958 (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Weird Like Us: My Bohemian America (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001022T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502EFD9103EF931A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="947" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'Red Menace' to Warhol's Factory: The City as Bohemia</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Excerpts from books American Moderns: Bohemian New York and the Creation of a New Century by Christine Stansell, Door Wide Open: A Beat Love Affair in Letters, 1957-1958 by Jack Kerouac and Joyce Johnson and Weird Like Us: My Bohemian America by Ann Powers; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Early in the 20th century, a tide of modernism swept from Europe to the shores of America, carrying new forms of art and literature. It was also a time of political radicalism and changing sexual mores. ''Nowhere did the instinct for the new flourish more extravagantly than in New York City,'' Christine Stansell writes in ''American Moderns: Bohemian New York and the Creation of a New Century.'' Ms. Stansell describes the city's ''willful, ambitious arrivistes'' who came to be known as bohemians. Their spiritual heirs have continued to find a home in the city, among them the beats of the 50's like Jack Kerouac and the latter-day bohemians described by Ann Powers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Early in the 20th century, a tide of modernism swept from Europe to the shores of America, carrying new forms of art and literature. It was also a time of political radicalism and changing sexual mores. ''Nowhere did the instinct for the new flourish more extravagantly than in New York City,'' Christine Stansell writes in ''American Moderns: Bohemian New York and the Creation of a New Century.'' Ms. Stansell describes the city's ''willful, ambitious arrivistes'' who came to be known as bohemians. Their spiritual heirs have continued to find a home in the city, among them the beats of the 50's like Jack Kerouac and the latter-day bohemians described by Ann Powers.</p>
        <p>AMERICAN MODERNS: Bohemian New York and the Creation of a New Century  By Christine Stansell  Metropolitan Books ($30, hardcover)</p>
        <p>Despite the bellicose urgings of its financial elites, New York had initially been an antiwar stronghold. It was, in its inimitable way, a haven for insurrectionaries: among the huddled masses in the immigrant districts in 1916 were the Russians Alexandra Kollontai, Nikolai Bukharin, and Leon Trotsky, biding their time; and there were Indian, Dutch, Japanese, Italian, and Finnish radicals, too, plotting various revolutions.</p>
        <p>This Red menace was obscure, however, hidden away in the tenements; what really alarmed conservatives was a strong showing by the Socialist Party in the municipal and state elections of 1917. Mob violence and spying cropped up in the city.  Passersby picked up ''seditious'' pamphlets on the streets and turned them over to the authorities. Soldiers and sailors based in New York led roving mobs looking for radicals to intimidate. Columbia University turned into a nest of patriotic zeal as the autocratic president, Nicholas Murray Butler, restructured schools and departments among military lines and announced that faculty debate about the wisdom of intervention was ''intolerable . . . what had been folly was now treason.'' Firings, dismissals, and resignations of antiwar faculty followed.</p>
        <p>For the first time, radicals encountered physical danger in New York.  For Emma Goldman and Alexander Berkman, the organizers of a No-Conscription League, the meetings to encourage conscientious objection were tests of physical courage. During a suffrage protest against President Wilson, who was still vacillating on votes for women, angry soldiers attacked marchers of both sexes.  The playing of the ''Star-Spangled Banner'' was a flash point: Fred Boyd, a British socialist and habitue of the Village scene, was beaten up in a New York restaurant for remaining in his seat during the anthem; he was lucky to escape since someone in Washington, D.C., had been killed for the same reason.</p>
        <p>DOOR WIDE OPEN: A Beat Love Affair in Letters, 1957-1958  By Jack Kerouac and Joyce Johnson  Viking ($24.95, hardcover)</p>
        <p>From commentary on the letters by Joyce Johnson:</p>
        <p>Many of my new acquaintances didn't live in apartments like most New Yorkers. Instead they inhabited old commercial lofts illegally, hiding their mattresses in ingenious ways in case a building inspector came to check on the premises. On Friday nights, everyone turned up at openings at the cooperative storefront galleries on Tenth Street, where works by unknown artists excluded from the snooty galleries uptown were being exhibited in exuberant group shows.</p>
        <p>The next stop would often be the Five Spot, the new Bowery jazz joint whose walls were covered with flyers from the neighborhood galleries.  I began going there with Elise. We'd buy our 25-cent beers and listen to John Coltrane. We were there the unforgettable night Billie Holiday suddenly stood up at her table and sang as Mal Waldron played the piano.  (She had recently been deprived of her cabaret card by the police.) I'd always longed to go to Paris -- the destination of the heroine in the novel I was writing -- but now there was something in the air that made New York seem the most exciting place in the world.</p>
        <p>WEIRD LIKE US: My Bohemian America  By Ann Powers  Simon &amp; Schuster ($23, hardcover)</p>
        <p>''Bohemian?'' said Amy, incredulous, as we slurped overpriced pasta in an East Village bistro. ''I'd never call myself that.'' She's a veteran of Warhol's Factory scene who's lived in SoHo since the days when rents were cheap; she wears almost nothing but black, cares for seven cats and no man, spends her days watching films and her nights writing. She is not an average person. That doesn't matter.</p>
        <p>''I'm not a bohemian. You're not a bohemian,'' insisted Evelyn over a pint at McHale's, a crusty old stagehands' bar near Times Square. Ev got married wearing a gorilla mask on the shores of Lake Michigan; she and her then-husband wrote their own marriage manifesto and didn't seek the sanction of the law. They published a little magazine focusing on feminism and postmodern ranting until the marriage soured; now she's writing a novel in her flat on East Fifth Street. She fits the profile, but that isn't the point.</p>
        <p>''O course you're a bohemian!'' shouted Bob and Carola, who live with their daughter, Nina, just down Second Avenue from Evelyn in a chaotic, slightly remodeled co-op building, along with a bunch of pals who also contribute to The Village Voice.  Sixties idealists, Bob and Carola want the tradition that changed their lives to carry their successors into the next century. But when pressed for evidence of my bohemian credentials, they hem and haw: Well, so far I'd avoided middle class conventions like marriage and a decent-paying job. But so did my cousin, who's a waitress in Washington State.</p>
        <p>NEW YORK BOOKSHELF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
