<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Julie Mosow, Sasha Dichter</title>
    <meta content="22MOSO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Society Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240826"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="WEDDINGS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEDDINGS AND ENGAGEMENTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">MOSOW, JULIE ELIZABETH</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DICHTER, ALEXANDER</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Weddings and Celebrations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001022T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E5DC133EF931A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="561" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Julie Mosow, Sasha Dichter</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Julie Elizabeth Mosow, a daughter of Carol and David Mosow of Nashville, was married there yesterday evening to Alexander Dichter, a son of the concert pianists Cipa and Misha Dichter of New York. Rabbi Kenneth Kanter performed the ceremony at Congregation Micah.</p>
        <p>The bride, 25, and the bridegroom, 27, graduated from Harvard University, she cum laude and he magna cum laude. Mr. Dichter, who is known as Sasha, is a candidate for an M.B.A. at Harvard Business School and for a master's degree in public administration at Harvard's Kennedy School of Government. Ms. Mosow, who is keeping her name, is an account executive at Feinstein Kean Healthcare, a public relations firm in Cambridge, Mass., that specializes in biotechnology companies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Julie Elizabeth Mosow, a daughter of Carol and David Mosow of Nashville, was married there yesterday evening to Alexander Dichter, a son of the concert pianists Cipa and Misha Dichter of New York. Rabbi Kenneth Kanter performed the ceremony at Congregation Micah.</p>
        <p>The bride, 25, and the bridegroom, 27, graduated from Harvard University, she cum laude and he magna cum laude. Mr. Dichter, who is known as Sasha, is a candidate for an M.B.A. at Harvard Business School and for a master's degree in public administration at Harvard's Kennedy School of Government. Ms. Mosow, who is keeping her name, is an account executive at Feinstein Kean Healthcare, a public relations firm in Cambridge, Mass., that specializes in biotechnology companies.</p>
        <p>After Harvard, the bride was a Rotary Scholar at the University of Seville in Spain and then received a master's degree in international relations from the Diplomatic School of Madrid. Her mother teaches middle-school math at the University School of Nashville, a private elementary, middle and high school. Her father owns Charpier's Bakery in Nashville.</p>
        <p>The couple met in April 1995, when they were undergraduates. A group of Ms. Mosow's friends, who were acquainted with Mr. Dichter, met up with him in a restaurant during a spring-break ski vacation in Aspen, Colo., and were particularly taken by his sense of humor.</p>
        <p>Ms. Mosow remembered that upon the friends' return to Cambridge, they announced, ''He's the perfect guy for you.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Dichter, however, was blissfully unaware of the good impression he had made on Ms. Mosow's friends. ''I thought that her friends had had the worst time that night,'' he recalled.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, with the friends' encouragement, Ms. Mosow and Mr. Dichter got together for lunch at the cafeterialike Lowell House dining hall at Harvard. But the meeting was a failure. ''I was told he had this great sense of humor, and he just sat there and was really glum,'' Ms. Mosow said. In his defense, Mr. Dichter said he was in the middle of breaking up with someone and did not know that he was being ''screened.''</p>
        <p>They parted and didn't see each other again until a chance meeting on the first night of the fall 1995 semester. ''I was coming home from a party and ran into him in the entrance hall to the dorm, and I knew his roommate, who reintroduced me to him,'' Ms. Mosow said. ''When I met him again, I was intrigued.''</p>
        <p>So was Mr. Dichter. Over the next few weeks, Mr. Dichter said, ''we started to spend more meal times together.'' He added, ''We'd start at 6 and find that at 8:30 we were the only two people talking.''</p>
        <p>One day, Mr. Dichter asked Ms. Mosow to go in-line skating with him along the Charles River.</p>
        <p>''I said, 'Yes,' '' Ms. Mosow recalled. ''But little did he know that I had to run off to the store to buy a pair.''</p>
        <p>WEDDINGS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
