<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Last Victorian</title>
    <meta content="22NOONANT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240600"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Noonan, John T Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hill, Roland</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Acton, John Emerich Edward Dalberg-Acton (Lord) (1834-1902)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Lord Acton (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001022T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E7DF143FF931A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1146" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Last Victorian</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By John T. Noonan Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Noonan, John T Jr</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>John T Noonan Jr reviews biography Lord Acton by Roland Hill (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lord Acton</p>
        <p>By Roland Hill.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 548 pp. New Haven:</p>
        <p>Yale University Press. $ 39.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Lord Acton</p>
        <p>By Roland Hill.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 548 pp. New Haven:</p>
        <p>Yale University Press. $ 39.95.</p>
        <p>In 1804, on Nelson's flagship at Palermo, the 64-year-old English prime minister of the Bourbon kingdom of Naples married his 14-year-old niece, Marie Anne. Their first child, Richard, inherited the baronetcy of Aldenham in Shropshire from his father and successfully wooed another Marie, the only daughter of the Duke of Dalberg. This English-German marriage came to an end when Marie, one cold January night in 1837, had Richard locked out of their house in Paris, and he, drunk, did not seek shelter but caught pneumonia and died. The couple's 3-year-old son, Johnny, returned with his penitent mother to England, where both were naturalized by an act of Parliament.</p>
        <p>Marie married again, choosing a husband who became a star of the Liberal Party as Lord Granville. She had little time for Johnny, who at 8 was boarded at a Parisian boys school and from 9 to 14 at St. Mary's, Oscott. At 15 and 16 he was privately tutored in Edinburgh. He was then denied admission to three Cambridge colleges because he was a Roman Catholic. At 17 he was dispatched to Munich, to study with Ignaz von DRated PG-13llinger, a learned ecclesiastical historian.</p>
        <p>In Father DRated PG-13llinger Johnny found a friend. He had the run of DRated PG-13llinger's library of some 30,000 books, and acquired a love of history. Nearby, in his 37-year-old cousin, Anna Marescalchi von Arco-Valley, he found maternal love, and she became ''Maman'' in his letters to her. Eventually he married her daughter, Marie.</p>
        <p>Such was the rich background and educational formation of the protagonist of ''Lord Acton,'' Roland Hill's splendid biography, the most complete yet made of this complex Victorian. As a child he lacked parental affection, in adolescence he lacked peers. He was a driven, a self-driven, individual. A young baronet in the 1850's, he tried two careers. He was elected a member of Parliament from Carlow, Ireland. That led nowhere in politics, except to a friendship with Gladstone, which was to prove invaluable. He became editor of two small periodicals that showed too much independence on sensitive topics like the temporal authority of the pope for the stomach of church authority. Eventually he moved to Rome to study the popes in their lair, the archives of the Vatican. As rumors spread of a council to be convoked to declare the pope's infallibility, he lined up with DRated PG-13llinger in opposition.</p>
        <p>From December 1869 to June 1870, he monitored the First Vatican Council. Gladstone had just made him a lord, no doubt to boost his prestige in Rome. He was an active but ineffective agent in organizing and animating the minority in opposition. He was too impatient of fine distinctions to take in his allies' nuanced positions, let alone give full measure to the majority; but he fed information and gossip to DRated PG-13llinger in Munich for letters the priest wrote for newspapers, signed Quirinus, picturing Pope Pius IX as bullying the minority; Acton wrote 15 of the letters himself. He and DRated PG-13llinger were to Vatican I what the priest who called himself Xavier Rynne was to Vatican II. But with a difference: Acton saw nothing improper in trying to draw the great powers of Europe into intervening to stop a declaration he thought was wrong. These seven months were no doubt the most exciting of his life. He left Rome unconvinced by the council's teaching on infallibility, but unwilling to go into schism.</p>
        <p>Between 1870 and 1895, his middle years, he planned a great history of liberty. Henry James's 1873 story, ''The Madonna of the Future,'' became emblematic for him. ''I chose never to manifest myself by imperfection,'' James's fatally procrastinating painter declared. Acton's great history became an essay, posthumously published.</p>
        <p>Acton had one constant friend: Gladstone. In 1890 when he was strapped for cash, Gladstone found a buyer for his 60,000 books in Andrew Carnegie, who paid</p>
        <p>John T. Noonan Jr.'s most recent book is ''The Lustre of Our Country: The American Experience of Religious Freedom.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">John T. Noonan Jr.'s most recent book is ''The Lustre of Our Country: The American Experience of Religious Freedom.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
