<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After 20-Year Effort, Shadmoor's a State Park</title>
    <meta content="22PARK$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240759"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Montauk (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Suffolk County (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">East Hampton (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nature Conservancy</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rather, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island/The Hamptons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leisure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001022T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E7DA153EF931A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1415" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After 20-Year Effort, Shadmoor's a State Park</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN RATHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rather, John</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York State, Suffolk County, Town of East Hampton and Nature Conservancy pay total of about $17.7 million to two private owners for nearly 100-acre Shadmoor property in Montauk, which will soon become 162d state park and third state park created on Long Island in two years; photo; maps (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE Shadmoor property, nearly 100 acres of Montauk moorland with spectacular views from shoreline bluffs overlooking the Atlantic Ocean, will become the 162nd state park and the third state park created on Long Island in two years.</p>
        <p>In the culmination of nearly 20 years of government and grass-roots efforts -- all of which seemed on the brink of failure a year ago -- New York State, Suffolk County, the Town of East Hampton and the Nature Conservancy on Long Island paid a total of about $17.7 million to buy the land from two private owners. The closing was held at the Riverhead county center on Oct. 13.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE Shadmoor property, nearly 100 acres of Montauk moorland with spectacular views from shoreline bluffs overlooking the Atlantic Ocean, will become the 162nd state park and the third state park created on Long Island in two years.</p>
        <p>In the culmination of nearly 20 years of government and grass-roots efforts -- all of which seemed on the brink of failure a year ago -- New York State, Suffolk County, the Town of East Hampton and the Nature Conservancy on Long Island paid a total of about $17.7 million to buy the land from two private owners. The closing was held at the Riverhead county center on Oct. 13.</p>
        <p>The purchase assures that one of the last remaining undeveloped oceanfront areas in Montauk will remain accessible to the public for ing. The tract includes almost half a mile of 100-foot-high bluffs, part of the seven miles of coastal bluffs that run from Hither Hills to Montauk Point. The bluffs are unusual on the East Coast; in fact, there are none like them south of Long Island. A rare plant, the sandplain gerardia, which is on the federal endangered-species list, can also be found there.</p>
        <p>Under the plans for Shadmoor State Park, as it will be known, a pair of stairways will descend from the bluffs to the wide, sandy beach. There are currently no plans for a bathhouse or other visitors' services.</p>
        <p>The state has recently created two other parks on Long Island: Nissequogue River last year and Cold Spring Harbor this year.</p>
        <p>The prospect of a park at Shadmoor seemed in jeopardy in May 1999, when the owners, Peter Schub and Robert Bear of Bridgehampton, received approval from the East Hampton Planning Board to subdivide the property into four lots for oceanfront residences. That plan included a large conservation area but would have ended public access.</p>
        <p>With development looming, local residents and groups including the Concerned Citizens of Montauk lobbied intensively for a public park, perhaps most visibly at a rally on the bluffs last October attended by some 200 people.</p>
        <p>''A lot of people all of a sudden became aware of what was happening, and they wrote or e-mailed Governor Pataki and county legislators,'' said Myriam Braunschvig of Montauk, a holistic health and fitness teacher at Gurney's Inn who produced a video about the property. Entitled ''Cliffs of the Heart,'' it was narrated by Dick Cavett and was presented several times on local cable television.</p>
        <p>People familiar with the negotiations said a breakthrough came when the appraised value of the property finally approximated what the owners believed it was worth.</p>
        <p>The property had been appraised at least three times in the last five years of negotiations. ''It has been a real roller-coaster ride in terms of believing it would be preserved and then seeing the deal fall apart,'' said Jay Schneiderman, the East Hampton supervisor. ''So many times there was a sense it just was not going to happen.''</p>
        <p>New York State provided $5.6 million for the purchase from the 1996 Environmental Quality Bond Act, and the Town of East Hampton provided $5.5 million. Suffolk County contributed $5.4 million. The Nature Conservancy donated $1 million and will also manage conservation efforts at Shadmoor.</p>
        <p>''It is a wonderful acquisition that demonstrates the power of partnerships,'' said Stuart Lowrie, the director of government relations for the Nature Conservancy. ''It is also a model we hope to carry forward for other projects of this magnitude.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lowrie and others said crucial support at the state level came from Gov. George E. Pataki, who said in a statement that the acquisition protected ''the unparalleled beauty and wonder of this unique and environmentally significant property,'' and from Assemblyman Fred W. Thiele Jr. and State Senator Kenneth P. LaValle, Republicans whose districts include Montauk.</p>
        <p>Suffolk County Legislator George O. Guldi, a Democrat from Westhampton Beach who led the effort to secure county financing, said that Robert J. Gaffney, the Republican county executive, made the acquisition a high priority. ''When he said, 'Let's do this,' his administration really did pull out all the stops,'' Mr. Guldi said.</p>
        <p>Appraisals of the property varied widely, Mr. Guldi said, mainly because it is difficult to assign a value when nothing like it has been sold in years. ''This is 100 acres of moors and ocean bluffs on Long Island,'' he said. ''There are no equivalent properties anywhere in the world.'' He said the county would sell bonds to pay for its share of the purchase rather than relying on existing environmental funds.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schneiderman, the East Hampton supervisor, said $3 million of the town's share would come from a preservation fund created by the 2 percent real estate transfer tax approved by voters in 1998. The town will borrow the remaining $2.5 million, he said.</p>
        <p>A federal role in the purchase ended in March 1999 when the Fish and Wildlife Service withdrew from the effort. The agency had appraised the land at only $5 million, far below the minimum $15 million the owners said they would accept.</p>
        <p>The state's plan calls for adapting the two concrete bunkers erected during World War II, when 16-inch guns were trained on offshore waters, as platforms for bird-watching and sightseeing.</p>
        <p>Atop the bluffs, the property is a rolling landscape covered with thickets. The name Shadmoor has been used for years and refers to the geography and to the shadbush, also known as shadblow or Juneberry, which grows there. So does the sandplain gerardia, a low-growing wildflower that bears pink or purple flowers in August or September. The tract is a habitat for birds, wildlife and black cherry trees and other shrubs kept low by wind-driven salt spray that dries out foliage and stunts growth. Trails and dirt roadways lead to the bluffs from an entrance on Montauk Highway just east of Montauk Village.</p>
        <p>Larry Penny, East Hampton's director of natural resources, called the tract ''a remnant of the last advances of the Ice Age, which ended about 18,000 years ago.'' The bluffs, he said, are peculiarly fluted with vertical, razor-sharp parallel ridges.</p>
        <p>The owners had taken a lenient attitude to public access, so the property is familiar territory to many residents. ''A lot of people didn't realize it wasn't a public park,'' Mr. Schneiderman said.</p>
        <p>The owners, Mr. Schub and Mr. Bear, are business partners and land developers. Mr. Schub said that they  had allowed access because they believed that ''land should be used by people unless you are building something on it.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Schub said he had visited frequently. ''It is breathtaking at sunset,'' he said. ''Now we will all have many, many more years of pleasure. I have all along been hoping that this would be the solution,  and now it has come to pass. A lot of local people worked very hard for it.''</p>
        <p>Bill Akin, the president of the Concerned Citizens of Montauk, said the group was very pleased that the land would not be developed. ''To people out here there is an almost spiritual quality to that land,'' he said. ''To have it locked away in private hands would have been criminal. Some have suggested the price is excessive, but you have to point out its unique nature.''</p>
        <p>A past president of the group, Carol Morrison of Montauk, said acquisition efforts gathered steam in 1981 when the owners proposed building more than 60 houses on the property. ''Our problem back then was that Bear and Schub didn't want to sell,'' she said. ''The whole thing turned around once we had a seller.''</p>
        <p>She said last year's rally on the bluffs was ''so revealing of how strongly people felt that the land should be preserved.'' ''The idea of letting it be squandered on a few mansions drives me up the wall,'' she added.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
