<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tag Sale Archaeology</title>
    <meta content="22COLU" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240720"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="COUNTY LINES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Yard Sales</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gross, Jane</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001022T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE5DF153EF931A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="681" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tag Sale Archaeology</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE GROSS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gross, Jane</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jane Gross County Lines column holds fall tag sale season in Westchester County, NY, may be research opportunity for suburban archaeologists; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE detritus of suburban life is on display on front lawns these fine fall weekends, the height of tag sale season here, when we spread our used and useless goods, outgrown or outmoded, on blankets and card tables, priced at a dime or a dollar.</p>
        <p>The goal for the sellers is to collect a little mad money, clear space in the basement and pass some time with neighbors as the leaves flame and fall. The goal for the buyers is to pick up some hand-me-downs for the children, find a Robert Ludlum novel for a nickel or just take a drive on a pretty day.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE detritus of suburban life is on display on front lawns these fine fall weekends, the height of tag sale season here, when we spread our used and useless goods, outgrown or outmoded, on blankets and card tables, priced at a dime or a dollar.</p>
        <p>The goal for the sellers is to collect a little mad money, clear space in the basement and pass some time with neighbors as the leaves flame and fall. The goal for the buyers is to pick up some hand-me-downs for the children, find a Robert Ludlum novel for a nickel or just take a drive on a pretty day.</p>
        <p>But the ubiquitous tag sales may also be a research opportunity for suburban archaeologists, a chance to peek into other people's junk drawers and speculate about their lives.</p>
        <p>Just a tally of the goods on display, as in a Walt Whitman poem or a Tim O'Brien novel, can be the map of a world; everything there is to know about a time and a place, separated by commas.</p>
        <p>The tag sale ritual begins with the arrival of the local weekly, which lists the coming weekend's shopping opportunities. Then comes the Saturday morning crunch of tires outside 57 Church Lane in Scarsdale, 57 Meadow Way in Irvington or 20 Ashley Road in Hastings-on-Hudson, to name a few recent tag sales in lower Westchester.</p>
        <p>Otherwise quiet streets are lined with cars from 10 to 3, double-parked at the choicest locations, usually where several neighbors have banded together and pooled their castoffs. Enterprising children sell lemonade as their parents market what they would otherwise throw away, which will probably be the merchandise on someone else's lawn a year from now.</p>
        <p>So what are they selling?</p>
        <p>NordicTracks that were bought with the best of intentions and rarely used. Books like ''Home Buying for Dummies,'' which have served their purpose, or ''Writers and Illustrators Market,'' which hint of careers abandoned. Musical instruments that children refused to play despite all manner of parental prodding.</p>
        <p>Tablecloths too small for the new dining room set. Breakfronts too big for the front hall of a down-sized, post-divorce house. Fuzzy toilet seat covers that Mrs. Smith loves but Mr. Smith hates. Fish tanks with no purpose since the cat ate the guppies. Truly hideous lamps.</p>
        <p>Clunky first-generation microwave ovens, telephone answering machines and electric typewriters that look like museum pieces. Bottles of perfume bought by well-meaning but misguided husbands. Chafing dishes, flower vases and crystal decanters from mothers-in-law who hopefully won't notice they are missing.</p>
        <p>Rollerblades and gourmet cookbooks that a new mom with twins sees no hope of ever using again. Discarded eyeglasses with recyclable Armani frames. Outgrown belts from men with thickening waistlines and nursing bras from women who have had their last child.</p>
        <p>Holiday paraphernalia of all kinds: glittery New Year's hats from parties past. Strings of Christmas lights that twinkle when tested at the tag sale but short-circuit the moment you get them home. Outgrown Halloween costumes, ready for the next child. Candy dishes painted with reindeer and mistletoe.</p>
        <p>Shoulder pads and hair scrunchies that have multiplied in dresser drawers. Ties that are too wide for current fashion. Vinyl pocketbooks and open-toed, high-heeled shoes. Compact disks that didn't live up to their reviews. Windshield sun guards and plastic ice cube trays. A queen-size bedframe for a king-size couple. One unmatched ski mitten.</p>
        <p>A cornucopia of children's footwear, including sneakers, moccasins, boat shoes, sandals, mary janes, snow boots, rain boots and aqua-socks. A similarly vast array of kid-related equipment: snugglies, diaper sacks, crib bumpers, high chairs, Star Wars games and Casper cartoon videos.</p>
        <p>Together, it seems a still life of small pleasures and disappointments. We make resolutions, break them and make them again. Children grow up and spouses grow old. Families endure or come asunder. We have more than we need and want more than we have. And one person's trash is another person's treasure.</p>
        <p>Next week: Inveterate tag sale shoppers.</p>
        <p>COUNTY LINES E-mail: Countylines@nytimes.com.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: Countylines@nytimes.com.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
