<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Way We Live Now: 10-22-00: On Language; Enjoy!</title>
    <meta content="WLN092934" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="38" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240669"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">English Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Safire, William</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine/Columns/On Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">English Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Language and Languages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001022T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E1DB163EF931A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="931" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Way We Live Now: 10-22-00: On Language; Enjoy!</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By William Safire</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Safire, William</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William Safire On Language column on use and misuse of word enjoy by restaurant waiters (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Alissome Japanese waitress at the Yosaku restaurant in Bethesda, Md., presented me with a bowl of Nabayaki Udon -- thick noodles in broth with bits of chicken and shrimp -- smiled and said, ''Enjoy.''</p>
        <p>That is not a Japanese word. Indeed, that invitation to pleasure in eating is not an Asian attitude. According to my Times colleague Nicholas D. Kristof, author with his wife, Sheryl WuDunn, of ''Thunder From the East: Portrait of a Rising Asia,'' servers of food in Japan are likely to say honno okuchi yogoshi de gozaimasuga, ''here's a little something that will make your mouth dirty.'' The idea is to apologize for the meal and to suggest humbly that it will not be enjoyable at all to the honored guest. The Chinese equivalent, as a mouthwatering repast is placed before the eater, is meishemma cai, or ''this food is nothing much.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Alissome Japanese waitress at the Yosaku restaurant in Bethesda, Md., presented me with a bowl of Nabayaki Udon -- thick noodles in broth with bits of chicken and shrimp -- smiled and said, ''Enjoy.''</p>
        <p>That is not a Japanese word. Indeed, that invitation to pleasure in eating is not an Asian attitude. According to my Times colleague Nicholas D. Kristof, author with his wife, Sheryl WuDunn, of ''Thunder From the East: Portrait of a Rising Asia,'' servers of food in Japan are likely to say honno okuchi yogoshi de gozaimasuga, ''here's a little something that will make your mouth dirty.'' The idea is to apologize for the meal and to suggest humbly that it will not be enjoyable at all to the honored guest. The Chinese equivalent, as a mouthwatering repast is placed before the eater, is meishemma cai, or ''this food is nothing much.''</p>
        <p>In American eateries, however, and in restaurants around the world that cater to English-speaking patrons, the new server's imperative -- enjoy! -- can be heard. The mock-stern but cheerful command is spreading like the Asian leguminous vine kudzu, rivaling the readily understood O.K. and the widely accepted no problem as a major American contribution to a universal language.</p>
        <p>Waiters (or servers, as the unisexy prefer to be called) in every culture have their national phrases to accompany the placement of a plate. Bon appetit, say the French, and the wish for a hearty appetite is expressed in Greek as kali orexi, in Spanish as buen provecho and in German as guten Appetit.</p>
        <p>A German waiter is as likely to say simply bitte, which usually means ''please,'' and the same idea is expressed in New York's Russian Tea Room as pozhaluista. The closest translation of these would be the neutral comment of American hash slingers as they plonk down the plate: ''There you go.''</p>
        <p>A British butler is likely to warn, ''The plate is hot, Madam.'' Until a decade or so ago, the Yiddish term was es gezunterheyt, ''eat in good health''; the Gaelic equivalent is slainte, ''health.''</p>
        <p>But then along came the imperative, intransitive enjoy! That exhortation has become so ubiquitous that in a Diner's Bill of Rights concocted recently by Zagat's restaurant survey, one of the inalienable rights of patrons was ''for the waiter NOT to say 'enjoy' after the food is served.''</p>
        <p>How did it all begin? In his 1958 book, ''For 2 Cents Plain,'' Harry Golden wrote: ''When my mother served our meals . . . she would always say, 'Enjoy, enjoy.' . . . The word enjoy was seldom used by itself. It was always repeated.'' Accordingly, Golden's next best seller was titled ''Enjoy, Enjoy!'' In 1968, the New York Times reporter Marylin Bender quoted the furrier Jacques Kaplan on the effects of inflation: ''Whenever they felt money would lose its value, people would gorge themselves. It's a dancing over the volcano attitude, an enjoy-enjoy philosophy.''</p>
        <p>Even as the dialectically duplicated verb lost its duplication on its journey to general usage, lexicographers noticed the way the hortatory ''Enjoy!'' did not transmit action to an object. Lillian Feinsilver wrote in her Yiddish dictionary in 1970 that enjoy as an intransitive verb ''has become fairly common in recent years. . . . Enjoy yourself' was abbreviated to the simple 'Enjoy' by the solicitous Jewish mother.'' She noted the oddly intransitive usage by the violinist Mischa Elman: ''I get a great kick out of life. I know how to enjoy.''</p>
        <p>Now, as a service to philological scholars, we examine the grammatical puzzlement contained in this seemingly simple food fiat. Enjoy yourself, meaning ''have a good time,'' is clearly reflexive, turning the verb's action back on you, the understood subject. But the simple and now far more common enjoy! poses the question: Enjoy what? The food? Yourself gorging the food? The object is indeterminate; the verb's action does not know where to go.</p>
        <p>''When used solely in the imperative mood,'' says Mike Agnes, editor in chief of Webster's New World Dictionaries, ''the intransitive verb 'enjoy' may well qualify as a 'defective paradigm,' whereby a word fails to exhibit the full range of expected inflections. How odd that a word of such felicitous intent seems to reveal itself only in the stern imperative.''</p>
        <p>Jeffrey McQuain, the new editor of the newsletter Copy Editor, calls the new use of enjoy! ''the implied intransitive'' because it has no direct object but implies there should be one. He tracks the construction back to the ancient ''Eat!'' or the Italian ''Mangia! Mangia!''</p>
        <p>''The implied intransitive is especially popular in sports shorthand,'' McQuain says. ''Coaches and fans yell their advice in the imperative mood without the subject (you) and without the object.'' Thus, ''Bunt!'' could mean either ''Bunt the ball'' or ''Bunt, you miserable hitter.''</p>
        <p>Beware the loss of clarity in the defective paradigm or the implied intransitive. Until recently, verbs could be transitive (I love you) or intransitive (I love). Ron Meyers of New York deplores the de-transitivizing trend, using as his examples ''please wait while your credit card is authorizing'' and ''this book usually ships in three days.'' What subject of the sentence is doing the authorizing or shipping? What object is the verb's action being done to?</p>
        <p>Grammarians, lexicographers and all those living in syntax will find delectation in plunging into a deep, delicious analysis of this emerging phenomenon. And to those happy linguists we can only say. . . .</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
