<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>ON THE TOWNS</title>
    <meta content="22TOWN$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240830"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001022T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E2DC133EF931A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="4083" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>ON THE TOWNS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A guide to cultural and recreational goings-on around the state this week. Items may be submitted by mail to On the Towns, Sunday New Jersey Section, The New York Times, 229 West 43rd Street, New York, N.Y. 10036; by fax to (212) 556-7219; or by e-mail to njtowns@nytimes.com</p>
        <p>MUSIC</p>
        <p>APPEL FARM ARTS AND MUSIC CENTER Guy Clark, with Jesse Winchester. Friday at 8 p.m.  Tickets: $20 (advance); $23 (day of performance). 457 Shirley Road, Elmer. (800) 394-1211.</p>
        <p>THE ATRIUM ''Jazz Priorities: Vital Voices'' presents Grady Tate. Thursday at 7 p.m. and 9 p.m. Tickets: $25. St. Joseph Plaza, 233 West Market Street. Newark. (973) 639-7892 or (973)  242-8012.</p>
        <p>COMMUNITY THEATER OF MORRISTOWN ''Brazil Night,'' featuring Ivan Lins, Leila Pinheiro, Ed Motta and Batacoto. Thursday at 8 p.m. Tickets: $25 to $35. 100 South Street, Morristown. (973) 539-8008.</p>
        <p>THE CORNERSTONE Sarah Jane Cion Trio. Wednesday at 7:30 p.m. Sarah Partridge Quartet. Friday at 9 p.m. Saturday at 9 p.m. 25 New Street, Metuchen. (732) 549-5306.</p>
        <p>FIRST REFORMED CHURCH Lunchtime Recital Series featuring Amabile String Quartet.  Wednesday, 12:15 p.m. to 12:45 p.m. Free; free luncheon to follow. 9 Bayard Street, New Brunswick. (732) 545-6262.</p>
        <p>JOHN HARMS CENTER FOR THE ARTS Paul Anka. Tuesday at 8 p.m. Tickets: $30 to $60.  Carnegie Hall Jazz Band: A Tribute to the Harlem Renaissance. Wednesday at 8 p.m.  Tickets: $18 to $38. The Artist Curates Series, featuring Michael Feinstein, Maynard Ferguson and His Big Bop Nouveau Band. Next Sunday at 3 p.m. and 7 p.m. Tickets: $24 to $42. 30 North Van Brunt Street, Englewood. (201) 567-3600.</p>
        <p>McCARTER THEATER Richard Thompson. Tomorrow at 8 p.m. Tickets: 91 University Place, Princeton. (609) 258-2787.</p>
        <p>MONMOUTH UNIVERSITY Richard Thompson.  Today at 7 p.m. Tickets: $26.50 and $30. Vienna Choir Boys. Friday at 8 p.m. Tickets: $26 and $28. Pollak Auditorium, Cedar Avenue, West Long Branch. (732) 571-3483.</p>
        <p>MORROW MEMORIAL METHODIST CHURCH Mostly Music presents Ani Kavafian and Benny Kim, violinists; Paul Neubauer, violist; and Carter Brey, cellist. Today at 3 p.m. Tickets: $20; $18 for older people; $10 for students. 600 Ridgewood Road, Maplewood. (973) 762-0108.</p>
        <p>NASSAU PRESBYTERIAN CHURCH Princeton Folk Music Society presents Ramblin' Jack Elliott, Debby McClatchy and Les Sampou.  Saturday at 8 p.m. Tickets: $18. 61 Nassau Street, Princeton. (609) 799-0944.</p>
        <p>NEWARK SYMPHONY HALL Gladys Knight in Concert. Today at 8 p.m. Tickets: $45 to $60. Sarah Vaughan Concert Hall, 1020 Broad Street, Newark. (973) 643-8009.</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY PERFORMING ARTS CENTER New Jersey Symphony Orchestra, ''Debussy and Brahms,'' Gerard Schwarz, conductor. Today at 3 p.m. Tickets: $15 to $61. New Jersey Symphony Orchestra, ''Jeffrey Swann Performs Chopin.'' Thursday at 7:30 p.m.; Oct. 31 and Nov. 1 at 1:30 p.m. Tickets: $13 to $54. Buena Vista Social Club presents: Omara Portuondo with Barbarito Torres. Friday at 8 p.m. Tickets: $14 to $48. Prudential Hall. 1 Center Street, Newark. (888) 466-5722.</p>
        <p>PRINCETON UNIVERSITY RICHARDSON AUDITORIUM Concert Royal, James Richman, artistic director with New York Baroque Dance Company. Today at 3 p.m. Tickets: $27, $19; $5 for students. Princeton University Concerts Richardson Recitals Series featuring Mark Kaplan, violinist. Wednesday and Thursday at 8 p.m. Tickets (for both days):  $29, $24, $19; $2 for students. New Jersey Symphony Orchestra, ''Jeffrey Swann Performs Chopin.'' Friday at 8 p.m. Tickets: $13 to $54. Alexander Hall, Princeton. (609) 258-5000.</p>
        <p>PRINCETON UNIVERSITY TAPLIN AUDITORIUM Friends of Music event featuring the Minneapolis Guitar Quartet. Today at 8 p.m. Free.  Taplin Auditorium, Fine Hall. Washington Road, Princeton. (609) 258-4239.</p>
        <p>STATE THEATER Paul Anka. Today at 8 p.m.  Tickets: $25 and $40. Ray Charles. Wednesday at 8 p.m. Tickets: $25. 15 Livingston Avenue, New Brunswick. (732) 246-7469.</p>
        <p>TEMPLE EMANU-EL Mostly Music presents Ani Kavafian and Benny Kim, violinists; Paul Neubauer, violist; and Carter Brey, cellist. Today at 7:30 p.m. Tickets: $20; $18 for older people; $13 for students. 756 East Broad Street, Westfield. (973) 762-0108.</p>
        <p>MUSEUMS AND GALLERIES</p>
        <p>ABC GALLERY ''Organic Movement'' of works by Monica McNulty. Through Nov. 16. Hours: Mondays and Thursdays, 1 to 9 p.m.; Tuesdays and Wednesdays, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Fridays, 1 p.m. to 5 p.m. ; Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Lambertville Public Library, 6 Lilly Street, Lambertville. (609) 397-0275.</p>
        <p>AFRICAN ART MUSEUM OF THE S.M.A. FATHERS ''African Containers: Clay, Gourd, Leather, Wood and Fiber'' and ''African Currency and Prestige Objects.'' Through Dec. 2001. ''Eloquent Threads: The Language of African Costumes and Textiles.'' Through Dec. 31. Hours: daily, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. 23 Bliss Avenue, Tenafly. (201) 894-8611.</p>
        <p>ALBA VINEYARD ''Realistic Portrayals'' of scenic landscapes, floral settings and man-made structures by Jean Olliver. Through Nov. 30. Hours: Wednesdays, Thursdays, Fridays and Sundays, noon to 5 p.m.; Saturdays, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. Musconetcong Gallery, 269 Route 627, Village of Finesville, Milford.  (908) 995-7800.</p>
        <p>AMERICAN LABOR MUSEUM ''Workers' Portraits,'' photodocumentary exhibit by Robert Gumpert. Through Dec. 31. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 9 a.m. to 5 p.m.; other times by appointment. Botto House National Landmark, 83 Norwood Street, Haledon. (973) 595-7953.</p>
        <p>APPEL ART GALLERY ''Artists of Roosevelt, N.J.'' Through October. Hours: Sundays, 9 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Mondays through Thursdays, 9 a.m. to 9:30 p.m.; Fridays, 9 a.m. to 3 p.m. Katz Jewish Community Center, Springdale and Kresson Roads, Cherry Hill. (856) 751-9500, extension 203.</p>
        <p>ATELIER FINE ART GALLERY ''Mike Filipiak, Recent Works of Maine and Hunterdon County.'' Through Oct. 30. Hours: Thursdays to Sundays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. 108 Harrison Street, Frenchtown. (908) 996-9992.</p>
        <p>ATLANTIC CAPE COMMUNITY COLLEGE ''Father/Son,'' drawings and paintings by Kevin Sprouls and Brendan Sprouls, his son. Through Friday. Call for gallery times. Art Gallery, 5100 Black Horse Pike, May Landing. (609) 343-5040.</p>
        <p>BARRON ARTS CENTER ''Vintage Motorcycles Exhibition.'' Through Nov. 5. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 11 a.m. to 4 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 2 to 4 p.m. 582 Rahway Avenue, Woodbridge. (732) 634-0413.</p>
        <p>BLAIR ACADEMY ''Paintings in Gouache,'' by  Virginia Cuppaidge, Australian abstract artist. Through Nov. 12. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m. The Clinton Gallery, Blairstown. (908) 362-6121, ext. 5690.</p>
        <p>HIRAM BLAUVELT ART MUSEUM ''Kindred Spirits,'' exhibition of works of John Pitcher and Sue Westin, painters, and Patti Stajcar, sculptor. Through Dec. 10. Hours: Wednesdays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 2 to 5 p.m. 705 Kinderkamack Road, Oradell. (201) 261-0012.</p>
        <p>BRION GALLERIES ''High Energy: Paintings by Jim Fuess and Alex Lombardo,'' and ''Oils, Pastels and Original Prints by Linda Kohl-Orton,'' both through Jan. 28, 2001. ''Halloween and Christmas: Victorian Era to the 1950's,'' features a folk art Christmas village circa 1910, vintage decorations, Victorian dresses and more. Through Feb. 2001. Free. Hours: Wednesdays and Thursdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Fridays and Saturdays, 9 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Sundays, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. 1293 Route 179, Lambertville. (609) 397-7030.</p>
        <p>BRISTOL-MYERS SQUIBB GALLERY ''Winning: Overcoming Obstacles.'' Through Nov. 8. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 9 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Route 206, Lawrenceville, three miles south of Princeton. (609) 252-6275.</p>
        <p>CAMDEN COUNTY CULTURAL AND HERITAGE COMMISSION ''Artists of Roosevelt, New Jersey''; Deborah Gross-Zuchman, watercolors, prints and collages; and historic photographs of Roosevelt, New Jersey. Through Nov. 17. Hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 1 p.m. and 2 to 4 p.m.; Saturdays, noon to 4 p.m. Hopkins House, 250 South Park Drive, Haddon Township. (609) 858-0040.</p>
        <p>CERULEAN FINE ARTS GALLERY ''Arville Pustroem, Landscapes in Oil,'' through Nov. 27. Hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, 11:30 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Saturdays, 4 to 9 p.m. Headquarters Plaza Mall, Speedwell Avenue (Route 202), Morristown. (973) 267-3730.</p>
        <p>CHAMOT GALLERY ''Paint and Clay,'' paintings by Richard Estell and sculptures by Bruce Morozko. Through Nov. 12. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, noon to 6 p.m. 111 First Street, Jersey City. (201) 610-1468.</p>
        <p>EXTENSION GALLERY ''Animal, Mineral and Vegetable'' exhibition of sculptures and photographs by Rory Mahon. Through Nov. 9.  Hours: Mondays through Thursdays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m.; other times by appointment. 60 Ward Avenue Extension, Mercerville. (609) 890-7777.</p>
        <p>GROUNDS FOR SCULPTURE ''James Dinerstein: New Sculpture,'' works in cast bronze. Through April 8, 2001. Hours: Thursdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m.; Tuesday and Wednesday by appointment. 18 Fairgrounds Road, Hamilton Township. (609) 586-0616.</p>
        <p>HUNTERDON MUSEUM OF ART ''Runway:  Photographs by Larry Fink,'' an exhibition of behind-the-scenes photos from the world of fashion and haute couture. Through Nov. 26. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. 7 Lower Center Street, Clinton. (908) 735-8415.</p>
        <p>JERSEY CITY MUSEUM ''2000 Millennium Exhibition'' of the Jersey City Public Schools Permanent Student Art Collection. Through Dec. 1. Hours: Tuesdays, Thursdays, Fridays and Saturdays, 10:30 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Wednesdays, 10:30 a.m.to 8 p.m. 472 Jersey Avenue, Jersey City. (201) 547-4514.</p>
        <p>LIBERTY HALL MUSEUM ''Tea Is Served.'' A complete Afternoon Tea, in the style of Mary Alice Barney Kean, the last family to reside at Liberty Hall. Every Wednesday, 2 p.m. to 4 p.m. Cost: $15 per person; reservations required. Hours: Wednesdays through Sundays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m. 1003 Morris Avenue (across from Kean University), Union. (908) 527-0400.</p>
        <p>LIBERTY SCIENCE CENTER ''Extreme Deep:  Mission to the Abyss.'' Through Jan. 7, 2001.  ''Antarctica.'' Through Jan. 14, 2001. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, 9:30 to 5:30 p.m. Environment Level, Liberty State Park, 251 Phillip Street, Jersey City. (201) 200-1000.</p>
        <p>MID-ATLANTIC CENTER FOR THE ARTS ''Once Upon a Time: Clocks and Victorian Style'' Exhibition featuring more than 45 timepieces. Through Jan. 1, 2001. Carriage House Gallery, Emlen Physick Estate, 1048 Washington Street, Cape May. (609) 884-5404 or (800) 275-4278.</p>
        <p>MIDDAY GALLERY ''Etchings 2000.'' Saturday through November. Hours: Tuesday through Saturday, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. 8 North Dean Street, Englewood. (201) 568-4454.</p>
        <p>MORRIS MUSEUM New Jersey Arts Annual:  ''Everything for the Home'' juried exhibition.  Through Nov. 17. ''Art and Nature: The Hudson River School'' exhibition. Through Nov. 19. Hours: Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m.; Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Thursdays to 8 p.m. Admission: $6; $4 for older people and children under age 3. 6 Normandy Heights Road, Morristown. (973) 538-0454.</p>
        <p>MUSEUM OF EARLY TRADES AND CRAFTS ''Time Made Visible: An Exhibit on Time and Timepieces.'' Through Dec. 30. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Admission: $3.50; $2 for students, children over 5 and older people.  Main Street at Green Village Road, Madison. (973) 377-2982.</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY STATE MUSEUM ''Woven by Tradition and Design: A Selection of American Indian Weavings, Textiles and Baskets.''  Through Dec. 31. ''Click! The Marvelous in American Vernacular Photography.'' Through Dec. 31. ''Dinosaurs, Ammonites and Asteroids.'' Through Jan. 21, 2001. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 9 a.m. to 4:45 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Free. 205 West State Street, Trenton. (609) 292-6464.</p>
        <p>NEWARK MUSEUM ''Narratives of African-American Art and Identity: The David C. Driskell Collection.'' Wednesday through Feb. 25, 2001. ''Night Skies: The Art of Deep Space,'' astral photographs by David Malin.  Through Feb. 25, 2001. ''Katherine Choy: A Promise Unfulfilled'' ceramic showcase. Through Jan. 21, 2001. ''Treasures of 19th-Century American Art.'' Through Dec. 3. ''Year of the Dragon: The Calligraphy of Wang Fangyu.'' Through Nov. 12. ''Needless Necessity: Jewelry, Silver and Personal Meaning.'' Through December. Hours: Wednesdays through Sundays, noon to 5 p.m.; Thursdays (after hours) until 8:30 p.m. 49 Washington Street, Newark. (973) 596-6550.</p>
        <p>PRINTMAKING COUNCIL OF NEW JERSEY ''Art as Healing.'' Through Dec. 29. Hours: Wednesdays through Fridays, 11 a.m. to 4 p.m.; Saturdays, 1 to 4 p.m. 440 River Road, North Branch. (908) 725-2110.</p>
        <p>RUTGERS UNIVERSITY - NEWARK ''Faces of the Ironbound: Newark 1937-1939.'' Through Dec. 14. Hours: Monday through Thursday, 8 a.m. to midnight; Friday, 8 a.m. to 7 p.m.; Saturday, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Sunday, noon to 10 p.m. Dana Library, 185 University Avenue, Newark. (973) 353-5111.</p>
        <p>YOGI BERRA MUSEUM ''El Beisbol Latino:  From Clemente to El Duque,'' an exhibition of baseball art, celebrating the greatest Latin American players and their influence.  Through Nov. 3. Artifacts from the life of the baseball player and exhibits on the history of the Yankees, baseball in New Jersey, Negro Leagues, evolution of equipment, and baseball during World War II. Ongoing. Hours: Wednesdays through Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Tickets: $4; $2 for children. Montclair State University, 8 Quarry Road, Little Falls. (973) 655-2377.</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
        <p>BERGEN COUNTY PLAYERS ''Communicating Doors.'' Through Nov. 11. Fridays and Saturdays at 8:30 p.m.; Sunday matinees at 2 p.m.  Tickets: $15 (Fridays and Saturdays); $12 (Sundays). The Little Firehouse Theater, 298 Kinderkamack Road, Oradell. (201) 261-4200.</p>
        <p>COMMUNITY THEATER OF MORRISTOWN Veriovka Ukrainian National Dance Company.  Wednesday at 8 p.m. Tickets: $25 to $35.  Weird Al Yancovic. Next Sunday at 7 p.m.  Tickets: $25 to $35. 100 South Street, Morristown. (973) 539-8008.</p>
        <p>DREAMCATCHER REPERTORY THEATER ''Crumbs From the Table of Joy.'' Through Nov. 4. Thursdays through Saturdays at 8 p.m.  Tickets: $20; $15 for students and older people. Van Fossan Theater, Bloomfield College, Franklin and Fremont Streets, Bloomfield. (973) 748-9008, ext. 995.</p>
        <p>GEORGE STREET PLAYHOUSE ''Wit,'' by Margaret Edson. Through Nov. 12. Performances are Tuesdays through Saturdays at 8 p.m.; Sundays at 2 p.m. and 7 p.m. Additional performance on Thursday at 2 p.m. Tickets:  $24 to $40. 9 Livingston Avenue, New Brunswick. (732) 246-7717.</p>
        <p>JOHN HARMS CENTER FOR THE ARTS George Carlin. Saturday at 7 p.m. and 10 p.m. Tickets:  $24 to $36. 30 North Van Brunt Street, Englewood. (201) 567-3600.</p>
        <p>KELSEY THEATER ''Little Shop of Horrors.'' Today at 3 p.m. Tickets: $12; $10 for students, children and older people. Mercer County Community College, 1200 Trenton Road, Trenton. (609) 584-9444.</p>
        <p>LUMIA THEATER The New Jersey Repertory Company presents ''In Search of Red River Dog.'' Through Nov. 5. Performances at Thursdays, Fridays and Saturdays at 8 p.m.; Sunday matinees at 2 p.m. Tickets: $25 to $27. 179 Broadway, Long Branch. (732) 229-3166.</p>
        <p>LUNA STAGE ''Rapture,'' by Jeanne Marshall. Through Nov. 12. Performances are Thursdays, Fridays and Saturdays at 8 p.m.; Sundays at 2 p.m. Tickets: $15 (Thursday); $22 (Fridays and Sundays); $18 (students and older people; $25 (Saturdays); $22 (students and old people on Saturdays). 7 Oak Place, Montclair. (973) 744-3309.</p>
        <p>McCARTER THEATER Lily Tomlin in ''The Search for Signs of Intelligent Life in the Universe.'' Through Nov. 5. Tickets: $26 to $42. ''Dialogue on Drama'' discussion featuring Lily Tomlin today at 4:30 p.m. Center for the Performing Arts, 91 University Place, Princeton. (609) 258-2787.</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY SHAKESPEARE FESTIVAL ''The Merchant of Venice.'' Tuesday through Nov. 19. Call for show times. Tickets: $21 to $38.  F. M. Kirby Shakespeare Theater, 36 Madison Avenue, Madison. (973) 408-5600.</p>
        <p>RAMAPO COLLEGE ''SubUrbia,'' Eric Bogosian's play about post-high school angst.  Wednesday through Friday at 8 p.m.; Saturday at 5 p.m. and 10 p.m.; next Sunday at 3 p.m. Tickets: $10; $5 for students and older people. Chicago City Limits. Friday at 8 p.m.  Tickets: $5, $10 and $15. Sharp Theater, 505 Ramapo Valley Road, Mahwah. (201) 684-7888.</p>
        <p>RITZ THEATER ''Victor/Victoria.'' Through Nov. 18. Performances are Fridays and Saturdays at 8 p.m.; Sundays at 2 p.m.; Nov. 1 and 15 at 7:30 p.m. Tickets: $16 (Fridays and Saturdays); $12.50 (Sundays); $15 (Nov. 1 and 15). 915 White Horse Pike, Oaklyn. (609) 858-5230.</p>
        <p>RUTGERS UNIVERSITY ''The Scenario,'' suspense drama written by Michele Raper Rittenhouse. Performances are today and next Sunday at 2:30 p.m.; Thursday, Friday and Saturday at 7 p.m. Bradley Hall Theater, 110 Warren Street, Newark. (973) 353-5119, extension 17.</p>
        <p>STATE THEATER Veriovka Ukrainian National Song and Dance Company. Tuesday at 8 p.m. Tickets: $20 to $38. Western Opera Theater presents ''Die Fledermaus.'' Thursday at 8 p.m. Tickets: $25 to $45. Mark Russell, political satire. Saturday at 8 p.m. Tickets: $20 to $34. 15 Livingston Avenue, New Brunswick. (732) 246-7469.</p>
        <p>STOCKTON PERFORMING ARTS CENTER ''As You Like It,'' by William Shakespeare. Wednesday, Thursday and Saturday at 8 p.m.;  Friday at 10:30 a.m. and 8 p.m.; next Sunday at 3 p.m. Tickets: $7; $5 for students and older people; $3 for Friday's performance. Jim Leeds Road, Pomona. (609) 652-9000.</p>
        <p>TRENTON WAR MEMORIAL Boheme Opera presents Puccini's ''Tosca.'' Friday at 8 p.m. and next Sunday at 3 p.m. Tickets: $20 to $50.  Lafayette and Willow Streets, Trenton. (609) 581-7200.</p>
        <p>TWELVE MILES WEST THEATRE COMPANY ''Italian-American Reconciliation'' by John Patrick Shanley. Thursday through Nov. 18.  Performances are Thursdays, Fridays and Saturdays at 8 p.m.; Sundays at 3 p.m. Tickets: $20; $15 for students and older people. 488 Bloomfield Avenue, Montclair. (973) 746-7181.</p>
        <p>VILLAGERS THEATER ''City of Angels.'' Friday through Nov. 18. Performances are Fridays and Saturdays at 8 p.m.; Sundays at 2 p.m. Tickets: $18; $12 for students and older people. 475 DeMott Lane, Somerset. (732) 873-2710.</p>
        <p>WILLIAM PATERSON UNIVERSITY ''Crimes of the Heart'' by Beth Henley. Today at 6 p.m.; Wednesday, Thursday and Friday at 8 p.m.; Wednesday also at 12:30 p.m. at the Hunziker Theater on campus. Tickets: $7; $5 for older people.Shea Center For Performing Arts, 300 Pompton Road, Wayne. (973) 720-2371.</p>
        <p>FOR CHILDREN</p>
        <p>FORUM THEATER COMPANY ''The Legend of Sleepy Hollow.'' Through Nov. 4. Performances are every Saturday at 11 a.m. Tickets:  $9. 314 Main Street, Metuchen. (732) 548-0582.</p>
        <p>MONTCLAIR STATE UNIVERSITY ''Franklin the Turtle: Franklin's Big Adventure.'' Friday at 10 a.m., 12:30 p.m. and 5 p.m. Tickets: $15 for 5 p.m.; $6 for 10 a.m. and 12:30 p.m.  Memorial Theater, Valley Road and Normal Avenue, Upper Montclair. (973) 655-5112.</p>
        <p>NEW BRUNSWICK FREE PUBLIC LIBRARY ''Family Story Hour.'' Thursdays at 7 p.m. through Nov. 16. For children ages 3 to 4. ''Babies and Books.'' Fridays at 10:30 a.m. through Nov. 17. For children ages 12 to 24 months. Registration is necessary for both. 60 Livingston Avenue, New Brunswick. (732) 745-5118, extension 15 or 16.</p>
        <p>RITZ THEATER ''The Legend of Sleepy Hollow.'' Thursday and Friday at 10 a.m.; Saturday at 10 a.m. and 1 p.m. Tickets: $5. Children are invited to wear their Halloween costumes.  915 White Horse Pike, Oaklyn. (856) 858-5230.</p>
        <p>STOCKTON PERFORMING ARTS CENTER ''As You Like It,'' by William Shakespeare. Friday at 10:30 a.m. Tickets: $3. Jim Leeds Road, Pomona. (609) 652-9000.</p>
        <p>WILLIAM PATERSON UNIVERSITY Tom Chapin and Friends. Saturday at 2 p.m.; for children (prekindergarten through 12 years).  Tickets: $7. Shea Center for Performing Arts, 300 Pompton Road, Wayne. (973) 720-2371.</p>
        <p>SPOKEN WORD</p>
        <p>BARNES &amp; NOBLE Brian Gilroy, author, will discuss and sign copies of his book ''Counseling Kids: It's Magic!: Manual of Therapeutic Uses of Magic With Children and Teens.'' Tomorrow at 7:30 p.m. Free. 1180 Raritan Road, Clark. (732) 574-1818.</p>
        <p>BARNES &amp; NOBLE Mary Jane Clark, author, will discuss and sign copies of her new book ''Let Me Whisper in Your Ear'' and discuss her debut novel ''Do You Want to Know a Secret.'' Thursday at 7 p.m. 3981 Highway 9, Freehold. (732) 409-2929.</p>
        <p>BOOKENDS BOOKSTORE Jennifer Lauck, author, will discuss and sign copies of her book ''Blackbird: A Childhood Lost.'' Today at 1 p.m. Mary Higgins Clark and Carol Higgins Clark, mother and daughter suspense authors, will discuss and sign copies of their joint thriller ''Deck the Halls.'' Next Sunday at noon. Free. 232 East Ridgewood Avenue, Ridgewood. (201) 445-0726.</p>
        <p>ENGLEWOOD PULIC LIBRARY Carlos Manzano, New York State Democratic Committeeman, 64th Assembly District, will discuss ''The Role of the Latino Community in the New Millennium.'' Today at 4 p.m. Free. 31 Engle Street, Englewood. (201) 568-2215, ext. 244.</p>
        <p>MONTCLAIR ART MUSEUM Ben Jones, artist, will discuss on ''Creating Art: Conversations with African-American Artists.'' Today at 3 p.m. Free, with admission. Admission: $5; $4 for older people and students; free for children under 12. (973) 746-5555.</p>
        <p>RUTGERS UNIVERSITY Jose Saramago, novelist and winner of the 1998 Nobel Prize in Literature, will give a talk as part of the campus's celebration of its new minor program in Portuguese studies. Today at 2 p.m. Free.  Robeson Campus Center, 350 Dr. Martin Luther King Boulevard, Newark. (973) 353-5262.</p>
        <p>ETC.</p>
        <p>CHILLER THEATER TOY, MODEL AND FILM EXPO Science fiction, fantasy, horror, film and television memorabilia show. Friday, 6 p.m. to 11 p.m.; Saturday, 11 a.m. to 7 p.m.; next Sunday, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. Tickets: $15; $10 (advance); $25 for three-day pass; free for children under 12. Sheraton Meadowlands,  East Rutherford. (201) 804-8040.</p>
        <p>ENGLEWOOD PUBLIC LIBRARY Annual Used Book Sale. Today, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m. Renaissance Office Center, 15 Engle Street (next to the Library), 31 Engle Street, Englewood. (201) 568-2215, ext. 244.</p>
        <p>FALL FINE ART AND CRAFTS AT BROOKDALE PARK SHOW Featuring more than 150 professional artists, craftspeople and photographers displaying and selling their handcrafted work. Today, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Free. Watchung, Bellevue and Grove Avenues, Montclair. (908) 874-5247.</p>
        <p>HERITAGE FESTIVAL 2000 ''Four Centuries in a Weekend: A Journey Through Union County's History.'' Saturday, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. and next Sunday, noon to 5 p.m. Visit 22 historic sites in Union County. (908) 558-2550.</p>
        <p>LAMBERTVILLE HISTORICAL SOCIETY'S HOUSE TOUR Today, noon to 5 p.m. Tour includes Victorian houses, a bed and breakfast, an elegant Queen Anne-style house and more.  Tickets: $15. (609) 397-0770 or (609) 397-2303.</p>
        <p>MORRISTOWN CRAFTMARKET Friday, 6 p.m. to 9 p.m.; Saturday, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m.; and next Sunday, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Showcase of contemporary American crafts, furniture, glass; silent auction; talks and more. Admission: $6 (all three days); free for children under 12.  National Guard Armory, Western Avenue, Morristown. (973) 895-3356 or (973) 631-6277.</p>
        <p>SIX FLAGS GREAT ADVENTURE ''9th Annual Fright Fest.'' Today, Friday evening, Saturday and next Sunday. Includes Halloween-themed rides, attractions, shows. Free with admission, $43.96 (adult); $21.98 (child). Northern Star Arena, exit 7A off the New Jersey Turnpike. (732) 928-1821.</p>
        <p>WHISTLE STOP FLOWERS AND FARM ''Annual Great Hayride Robbery.'' Today, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. ''Search for the Golden Pumpkin.'' Saturday and next Sunday, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Free. Route 579 (John Ringo Road) (seven miles south of Flemington off of Route 202 South), Ringoes. (908) 788-8552.</p>
        <p>AT THE CASINOS</p>
        <p>All tickets are available through Ticketmaster, (800) 736-1420.</p>
        <p>ATLANTIC CITY HILTON Dion. Friday at 9 p.m. and Saturday at 8 p.m. Tickets: $25 and $30.  Grand Theater, Boston and Pacific Avenues. (609) 340-7200.</p>
        <p>BALLY'S PARK PLACE Natalie Cole. Today at 8 p.m. Tickets: $35 and $40. Main Ballroom.  (609) 340-2709. ''Legends in Concert.'' impersonations of Stevie Wonder, Little Richard, Elvis Presley, Linda Ronstadt and Barbra Streisand. Mondays through Thursdays at 3:30 and 7:30 p.m.; Saturdays at 8 and 10:30 p.m.; Sundays at 7:30 and 10 p.m. Tickets: $15 to $25. Park Cabaret, Boardwalk and Park Place. (800) 225-5977.</p>
        <p>CAESARS ATLANTIC CITY Howie Mandel. Today at 8 p.m. Tickets: $45. LeAnn Rimes. Friday at 10 p.m.; Saturday at at 9 p.m., next Sunday at 8 p.m. Tickets: $75. Circus Maximus Theater, 2100 Pacific Avenue. (800) 677-7469.</p>
        <p>CLARIDGE HOTEL ''Jeff McBride's Abracadazzle.'' Through Nov. 16. Mondays through Thursdays at 8 p.m.; Saturdays at 8 p.m. and 11 p.m.; Sundays at 7 p.m. Tickets: $15, Sundays through Thursdays; $19, Saturdays. Palace Theater, Boardwalk and Park Place. (609) 340-3400.</p>
        <p>TROPICANA Kenny Rogers, in concert with Linda Davies. Friday at 9 p.m.; Saturday at 8 p.m.; next Sunday at 7 p.m. Tickets: $30 to $55. ''Tribute to Liberace,'' starring Daryl Wagner; the Lovely Liebowitz Sisters, guests.  Through Dec. 3; call for show times. Tickets:  $15. ''Dresses of Diana, Princess of Wales Exhibit.'' Through Dec. 28. Hours: daily, 10 a.m. to 10 p.m. Tickets: $13.95; $11.95 for older people; $6.95 for children, aged 5 to 11. Boardwalk and Brighton Avenue. (609) 340-3020.</p>
        <p>TRUMP MARINA ''3rd Annual Rock 'n' Roll Memorabilia Auction'' and sneak preview debut of ''Grendel's Lair,'' an original rock opera -- both to benefit the the VH1 Save the Music Foundation. Friday at 3 p.m.; ''Grendel's Lair'' at 7 p.m. Free. The Wave. (800) 841-4687. The Rev. Al Green. Friday at 10 p.m.; Saturday at 9 p.m. Tickets: $45 and $65. Grand Cayman. Huron Avenue and Brigantine Boulevard. (800) 777-8477.</p>
        <p>TRUMP TAJ MAHAL 7th Annual Oktoberfest.  Saturday and next Sunday, 8 a.m. to noon.  Mark G. Etess Arena. Free with a Taj Card. 1000 Boardwalk. (609) 449-5230.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A guide to cultural and recreational goings-on around the state this week. Items may be submitted by mail to On the Towns, Sunday New Jersey Section, The New York Times, 229 West 43rd Street, New York, N.Y. 10036; by fax to (212) 556-7219; or by e-mail to njtowns@nytimes.com</p>
        <p>MUSIC</p>
        <p>APPEL FARM ARTS AND MUSIC CENTER Guy Clark, with Jesse Winchester. Friday at 8 p.m.  Tickets: $20 (advance); $23 (day of performance). 457 Shirley Road, Elmer. (800) 394-1211.</p>
        <p>THE ATRIUM ''Jazz Priorities: Vital Voices'' presents Grady Tate. Thursday at 7 p.m. and 9 p.m. Tickets: $25. St. Joseph Plaza, 233 West Market Street. Newark. (973) 639-7892 or (973)  242-8012.</p>
        <p>COMMUNITY THEATER OF MORRISTOWN ''Brazil Night,'' featuring Ivan Lins, Leila Pinheiro, Ed Motta and Batacoto. Thursday at 8 p.m. Tickets: $25 to $35. 100 South Street, Morristown. (973) 539-8008.</p>
        <p>THE CORNERSTONE Sarah Jane Cion Trio. Wednesday at 7:30 p.m. Sarah Partridge Quartet. Friday at 9 p.m. Saturday at 9 p.m. 25 New Street, Metuchen. (732) 549-5306.</p>
        <p>FIRST REFORMED CHURCH Lunchtime Recital Series featuring Amabile String Quartet.  Wednesday, 12:15 p.m. to 12:45 p.m. Free; free luncheon to follow. 9 Bayard Street, New Brunswick. (732) 545-6262.</p>
        <p>JOHN HARMS CENTER FOR THE ARTS Paul Anka. Tuesday at 8 p.m. Tickets: $30 to $60.  Carnegie Hall Jazz Band: A Tribute to the Harlem Renaissance. Wednesday at 8 p.m.  Tickets: $18 to $38. The Artist Curates Series, featuring Michael Feinstein, Maynard Ferguson and His Big Bop Nouveau Band. Next Sunday at 3 p.m. and 7 p.m. Tickets: $24 to $42. 30 North Van Brunt Street, Englewood. (201) 567-3600.</p>
        <p>McCARTER THEATER Richard Thompson. Tomorrow at 8 p.m. Tickets: 91 University Place, Princeton. (609) 258-2787.</p>
        <p>MONMOUTH UNIVERSITY Richard Thompson.  Today at 7 p.m. Tickets: $26.50 and $30. Vienna Choir Boys. Friday at 8 p.m. Tickets: $26 and $28. Pollak Auditorium, Cedar Avenue, West Long Branch. (732) 571-3483.</p>
        <p>MORROW MEMORIAL METHODIST CHURCH Mostly Music presents Ani Kavafian and Benny Kim, violinists; Paul Neubauer, violist; and Carter Brey, cellist. Today at 3 p.m. Tickets: $20; $18 for older people; $10 for students. 600 Ridgewood Road, Maplewood. (973) 762-0108.</p>
        <p>NASSAU PRESBYTERIAN CHURCH Princeton Folk Music Society presents Ramblin' Jack Elliott, Debby McClatchy and Les Sampou.  Saturday at 8 p.m. Tickets: $18. 61 Nassau Street, Princeton. (609) 799-0944.</p>
        <p>NEWARK SYMPHONY HALL Gladys Knight in Concert. Today at 8 p.m. Tickets: $45 to $60. Sarah Vaughan Concert Hall, 1020 Broad Street, Newark. (973) 643-8009.</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY PERFORMING ARTS CENTER New Jersey Symphony Orchestra, ''Debussy and Brahms,'' Gerard Schwarz, conductor. Today at 3 p.m. Tickets: $15 to $61. New Jersey Symphony Orchestra, ''Jeffrey Swann Performs Chopin.'' Thursday at 7:30 p.m.; Oct. 31 and Nov. 1 at 1:30 p.m. Tickets: $13 to $54. Buena Vista Social Club presents: Omara Portuondo with Barbarito Torres. Friday at 8 p.m. Tickets: $14 to $48. Prudential Hall. 1 Center Street, Newark. (888) 466-5722.</p>
        <p>PRINCETON UNIVERSITY RICHARDSON AUDITORIUM Concert Royal, James Richman, artistic director with New York Baroque Dance Company. Today at 3 p.m. Tickets: $27, $19; $5 for students. Princeton University Concerts Richardson Recitals Series featuring Mark Kaplan, violinist. Wednesday and Thursday at 8 p.m. Tickets (for both days):  $29, $24, $19; $2 for students. New Jersey Symphony Orchestra, ''Jeffrey Swann Performs Chopin.'' Friday at 8 p.m. Tickets: $13 to $54. Alexander Hall, Princeton. (609) 258-5000.</p>
        <p>PRINCETON UNIVERSITY TAPLIN AUDITORIUM Friends of Music event featuring the Minneapolis Guitar Quartet. Today at 8 p.m. Free.  Taplin Auditorium, Fine Hall. Washington Road, Princeton. (609) 258-4239.</p>
        <p>STATE THEATER Paul Anka. Today at 8 p.m.  Tickets: $25 and $40. Ray Charles. Wednesday at 8 p.m. Tickets: $25. 15 Livingston Avenue, New Brunswick. (732) 246-7469.</p>
        <p>TEMPLE EMANU-EL Mostly Music presents Ani Kavafian and Benny Kim, violinists; Paul Neubauer, violist; and Carter Brey, cellist. Today at 7:30 p.m. Tickets: $20; $18 for older people; $13 for students. 756 East Broad Street, Westfield. (973) 762-0108.</p>
        <p>MUSEUMS AND GALLERIES</p>
        <p>ABC GALLERY ''Organic Movement'' of works by Monica McNulty. Through Nov. 16. Hours: Mondays and Thursdays, 1 to 9 p.m.; Tuesdays and Wednesdays, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Fridays, 1 p.m. to 5 p.m. ; Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Lambertville Public Library, 6 Lilly Street, Lambertville. (609) 397-0275.</p>
        <p>AFRICAN ART MUSEUM OF THE S.M.A. FATHERS ''African Containers: Clay, Gourd, Leather, Wood and Fiber'' and ''African Currency and Prestige Objects.'' Through Dec. 2001. ''Eloquent Threads: The Language of African Costumes and Textiles.'' Through Dec. 31. Hours: daily, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. 23 Bliss Avenue, Tenafly. (201) 894-8611.</p>
        <p>ALBA VINEYARD ''Realistic Portrayals'' of scenic landscapes, floral settings and man-made structures by Jean Olliver. Through Nov. 30. Hours: Wednesdays, Thursdays, Fridays and Sundays, noon to 5 p.m.; Saturdays, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. Musconetcong Gallery, 269 Route 627, Village of Finesville, Milford.  (908) 995-7800.</p>
        <p>AMERICAN LABOR MUSEUM ''Workers' Portraits,'' photodocumentary exhibit by Robert Gumpert. Through Dec. 31. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 9 a.m. to 5 p.m.; other times by appointment. Botto House National Landmark, 83 Norwood Street, Haledon. (973) 595-7953.</p>
        <p>APPEL ART GALLERY ''Artists of Roosevelt, N.J.'' Through October. Hours: Sundays, 9 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Mondays through Thursdays, 9 a.m. to 9:30 p.m.; Fridays, 9 a.m. to 3 p.m. Katz Jewish Community Center, Springdale and Kresson Roads, Cherry Hill. (856) 751-9500, extension 203.</p>
        <p>ATELIER FINE ART GALLERY ''Mike Filipiak, Recent Works of Maine and Hunterdon County.'' Through Oct. 30. Hours: Thursdays to Sundays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. 108 Harrison Street, Frenchtown. (908) 996-9992.</p>
        <p>ATLANTIC CAPE COMMUNITY COLLEGE ''Father/Son,'' drawings and paintings by Kevin Sprouls and Brendan Sprouls, his son. Through Friday. Call for gallery times. Art Gallery, 5100 Black Horse Pike, May Landing. (609) 343-5040.</p>
        <p>BARRON ARTS CENTER ''Vintage Motorcycles Exhibition.'' Through Nov. 5. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 11 a.m. to 4 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 2 to 4 p.m. 582 Rahway Avenue, Woodbridge. (732) 634-0413.</p>
        <p>BLAIR ACADEMY ''Paintings in Gouache,'' by  Virginia Cuppaidge, Australian abstract artist. Through Nov. 12. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m. The Clinton Gallery, Blairstown. (908) 362-6121, ext. 5690.</p>
        <p>HIRAM BLAUVELT ART MUSEUM ''Kindred Spirits,'' exhibition of works of John Pitcher and Sue Westin, painters, and Patti Stajcar, sculptor. Through Dec. 10. Hours: Wednesdays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 2 to 5 p.m. 705 Kinderkamack Road, Oradell. (201) 261-0012.</p>
        <p>BRION GALLERIES ''High Energy: Paintings by Jim Fuess and Alex Lombardo,'' and ''Oils, Pastels and Original Prints by Linda Kohl-Orton,'' both through Jan. 28, 2001. ''Halloween and Christmas: Victorian Era to the 1950's,'' features a folk art Christmas village circa 1910, vintage decorations, Victorian dresses and more. Through Feb. 2001. Free. Hours: Wednesdays and Thursdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Fridays and Saturdays, 9 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Sundays, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. 1293 Route 179, Lambertville. (609) 397-7030.</p>
        <p>BRISTOL-MYERS SQUIBB GALLERY ''Winning: Overcoming Obstacles.'' Through Nov. 8. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 9 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Route 206, Lawrenceville, three miles south of Princeton. (609) 252-6275.</p>
        <p>CAMDEN COUNTY CULTURAL AND HERITAGE COMMISSION ''Artists of Roosevelt, New Jersey''; Deborah Gross-Zuchman, watercolors, prints and collages; and historic photographs of Roosevelt, New Jersey. Through Nov. 17. Hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 1 p.m. and 2 to 4 p.m.; Saturdays, noon to 4 p.m. Hopkins House, 250 South Park Drive, Haddon Township. (609) 858-0040.</p>
        <p>CERULEAN FINE ARTS GALLERY ''Arville Pustroem, Landscapes in Oil,'' through Nov. 27. Hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, 11:30 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Saturdays, 4 to 9 p.m. Headquarters Plaza Mall, Speedwell Avenue (Route 202), Morristown. (973) 267-3730.</p>
        <p>CHAMOT GALLERY ''Paint and Clay,'' paintings by Richard Estell and sculptures by Bruce Morozko. Through Nov. 12. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, noon to 6 p.m. 111 First Street, Jersey City. (201) 610-1468.</p>
        <p>EXTENSION GALLERY ''Animal, Mineral and Vegetable'' exhibition of sculptures and photographs by Rory Mahon. Through Nov. 9.  Hours: Mondays through Thursdays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m.; other times by appointment. 60 Ward Avenue Extension, Mercerville. (609) 890-7777.</p>
        <p>GROUNDS FOR SCULPTURE ''James Dinerstein: New Sculpture,'' works in cast bronze. Through April 8, 2001. Hours: Thursdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m.; Tuesday and Wednesday by appointment. 18 Fairgrounds Road, Hamilton Township. (609) 586-0616.</p>
        <p>HUNTERDON MUSEUM OF ART ''Runway:  Photographs by Larry Fink,'' an exhibition of behind-the-scenes photos from the world of fashion and haute couture. Through Nov. 26. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. 7 Lower Center Street, Clinton. (908) 735-8415.</p>
        <p>JERSEY CITY MUSEUM ''2000 Millennium Exhibition'' of the Jersey City Public Schools Permanent Student Art Collection. Through Dec. 1. Hours: Tuesdays, Thursdays, Fridays and Saturdays, 10:30 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Wednesdays, 10:30 a.m.to 8 p.m. 472 Jersey Avenue, Jersey City. (201) 547-4514.</p>
        <p>LIBERTY HALL MUSEUM ''Tea Is Served.'' A complete Afternoon Tea, in the style of Mary Alice Barney Kean, the last family to reside at Liberty Hall. Every Wednesday, 2 p.m. to 4 p.m. Cost: $15 per person; reservations required. Hours: Wednesdays through Sundays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m. 1003 Morris Avenue (across from Kean University), Union. (908) 527-0400.</p>
        <p>LIBERTY SCIENCE CENTER ''Extreme Deep:  Mission to the Abyss.'' Through Jan. 7, 2001.  ''Antarctica.'' Through Jan. 14, 2001. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, 9:30 to 5:30 p.m. Environment Level, Liberty State Park, 251 Phillip Street, Jersey City. (201) 200-1000.</p>
        <p>MID-ATLANTIC CENTER FOR THE ARTS ''Once Upon a Time: Clocks and Victorian Style'' Exhibition featuring more than 45 timepieces. Through Jan. 1, 2001. Carriage House Gallery, Emlen Physick Estate, 1048 Washington Street, Cape May. (609) 884-5404 or (800) 275-4278.</p>
        <p>MIDDAY GALLERY ''Etchings 2000.'' Saturday through November. Hours: Tuesday through Saturday, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. 8 North Dean Street, Englewood. (201) 568-4454.</p>
        <p>MORRIS MUSEUM New Jersey Arts Annual:  ''Everything for the Home'' juried exhibition.  Through Nov. 17. ''Art and Nature: The Hudson River School'' exhibition. Through Nov. 19. Hours: Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m.; Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Thursdays to 8 p.m. Admission: $6; $4 for older people and children under age 3. 6 Normandy Heights Road, Morristown. (973) 538-0454.</p>
        <p>MUSEUM OF EARLY TRADES AND CRAFTS ''Time Made Visible: An Exhibit on Time and Timepieces.'' Through Dec. 30. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Admission: $3.50; $2 for students, children over 5 and older people.  Main Street at Green Village Road, Madison. (973) 377-2982.</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY STATE MUSEUM ''Woven by Tradition and Design: A Selection of American Indian Weavings, Textiles and Baskets.''  Through Dec. 31. ''Click! The Marvelous in American Vernacular Photography.'' Through Dec. 31. ''Dinosaurs, Ammonites and Asteroids.'' Through Jan. 21, 2001. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 9 a.m. to 4:45 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Free. 205 West State Street, Trenton. (609) 292-6464.</p>
        <p>NEWARK MUSEUM ''Narratives of African-American Art and Identity: The David C. Driskell Collection.'' Wednesday through Feb. 25, 2001. ''Night Skies: The Art of Deep Space,'' astral photographs by David Malin.  Through Feb. 25, 2001. ''Katherine Choy: A Promise Unfulfilled'' ceramic showcase. Through Jan. 21, 2001. ''Treasures of 19th-Century American Art.'' Through Dec. 3. ''Year of the Dragon: The Calligraphy of Wang Fangyu.'' Through Nov. 12. ''Needless Necessity: Jewelry, Silver and Personal Meaning.'' Through December. Hours: Wednesdays through Sundays, noon to 5 p.m.; Thursdays (after hours) until 8:30 p.m. 49 Washington Street, Newark. (973) 596-6550.</p>
        <p>PRINTMAKING COUNCIL OF NEW JERSEY ''Art as Healing.'' Through Dec. 29. Hours: Wednesdays through Fridays, 11 a.m. to 4 p.m.; Saturdays, 1 to 4 p.m. 440 River Road, North Branch. (908) 725-2110.</p>
        <p>RUTGERS UNIVERSITY - NEWARK ''Faces of the Ironbound: Newark 1937-1939.'' Through Dec. 14. Hours: Monday through Thursday, 8 a.m. to midnight; Friday, 8 a.m. to 7 p.m.; Saturday, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Sunday, noon to 10 p.m. Dana Library, 185 University Avenue, Newark. (973) 353-5111.</p>
        <p>YOGI BERRA MUSEUM ''El Beisbol Latino:  From Clemente to El Duque,'' an exhibition of baseball art, celebrating the greatest Latin American players and their influence.  Through Nov. 3. Artifacts from the life of the baseball player and exhibits on the history of the Yankees, baseball in New Jersey, Negro Leagues, evolution of equipment, and baseball during World War II. Ongoing. Hours: Wednesdays through Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Tickets: $4; $2 for children. Montclair State University, 8 Quarry Road, Little Falls. (973) 655-2377.</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
        <p>BERGEN COUNTY PLAYERS ''Communicating Doors.'' Through Nov. 11. Fridays and Saturdays at 8:30 p.m.; Sunday matinees at 2 p.m.  Tickets: $15 (Fridays and Saturdays); $12 (Sundays). The Little Firehouse Theater, 298 Kinderkamack Road, Oradell. (201) 261-4200.</p>
        <p>COMMUNITY THEATER OF MORRISTOWN Veriovka Ukrainian National Dance Company.  Wednesday at 8 p.m. Tickets: $25 to $35.  Weird Al Yancovic. Next Sunday at 7 p.m.  Tickets: $25 to $35. 100 South Street, Morristown. (973) 539-8008.</p>
        <p>DREAMCATCHER REPERTORY THEATER ''Crumbs From the Table of Joy.'' Through Nov. 4. Thursdays through Saturdays at 8 p.m.  Tickets: $20; $15 for students and older people. Van Fossan Theater, Bloomfield College, Franklin and Fremont Streets, Bloomfield. (973) 748-9008, ext. 995.</p>
        <p>GEORGE STREET PLAYHOUSE ''Wit,'' by Margaret Edson. Through Nov. 12. Performances are Tuesdays through Saturdays at 8 p.m.; Sundays at 2 p.m. and 7 p.m. Additional performance on Thursday at 2 p.m. Tickets:  $24 to $40. 9 Livingston Avenue, New Brunswick. (732) 246-7717.</p>
        <p>JOHN HARMS CENTER FOR THE ARTS George Carlin. Saturday at 7 p.m. and 10 p.m. Tickets:  $24 to $36. 30 North Van Brunt Street, Englewood. (201) 567-3600.</p>
        <p>KELSEY THEATER ''Little Shop of Horrors.'' Today at 3 p.m. Tickets: $12; $10 for students, children and older people. Mercer County Community College, 1200 Trenton Road, Trenton. (609) 584-9444.</p>
        <p>LUMIA THEATER The New Jersey Repertory Company presents ''In Search of Red River Dog.'' Through Nov. 5. Performances at Thursdays, Fridays and Saturdays at 8 p.m.; Sunday matinees at 2 p.m. Tickets: $25 to $27. 179 Broadway, Long Branch. (732) 229-3166.</p>
        <p>LUNA STAGE ''Rapture,'' by Jeanne Marshall. Through Nov. 12. Performances are Thursdays, Fridays and Saturdays at 8 p.m.; Sundays at 2 p.m. Tickets: $15 (Thursday); $22 (Fridays and Sundays); $18 (students and older people; $25 (Saturdays); $22 (students and old people on Saturdays). 7 Oak Place, Montclair. (973) 744-3309.</p>
        <p>McCARTER THEATER Lily Tomlin in ''The Search for Signs of Intelligent Life in the Universe.'' Through Nov. 5. Tickets: $26 to $42. ''Dialogue on Drama'' discussion featuring Lily Tomlin today at 4:30 p.m. Center for the Performing Arts, 91 University Place, Princeton. (609) 258-2787.</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY SHAKESPEARE FESTIVAL ''The Merchant of Venice.'' Tuesday through Nov. 19. Call for show times. Tickets: $21 to $38.  F. M. Kirby Shakespeare Theater, 36 Madison Avenue, Madison. (973) 408-5600.</p>
        <p>RAMAPO COLLEGE ''SubUrbia,'' Eric Bogosian's play about post-high school angst.  Wednesday through Friday at 8 p.m.; Saturday at 5 p.m. and 10 p.m.; next Sunday at 3 p.m. Tickets: $10; $5 for students and older people. Chicago City Limits. Friday at 8 p.m.  Tickets: $5, $10 and $15. Sharp Theater, 505 Ramapo Valley Road, Mahwah. (201) 684-7888.</p>
        <p>RITZ THEATER ''Victor/Victoria.'' Through Nov. 18. Performances are Fridays and Saturdays at 8 p.m.; Sundays at 2 p.m.; Nov. 1 and 15 at 7:30 p.m. Tickets: $16 (Fridays and Saturdays); $12.50 (Sundays); $15 (Nov. 1 and 15). 915 White Horse Pike, Oaklyn. (609) 858-5230.</p>
        <p>RUTGERS UNIVERSITY ''The Scenario,'' suspense drama written by Michele Raper Rittenhouse. Performances are today and next Sunday at 2:30 p.m.; Thursday, Friday and Saturday at 7 p.m. Bradley Hall Theater, 110 Warren Street, Newark. (973) 353-5119, extension 17.</p>
        <p>STATE THEATER Veriovka Ukrainian National Song and Dance Company. Tuesday at 8 p.m. Tickets: $20 to $38. Western Opera Theater presents ''Die Fledermaus.'' Thursday at 8 p.m. Tickets: $25 to $45. Mark Russell, political satire. Saturday at 8 p.m. Tickets: $20 to $34. 15 Livingston Avenue, New Brunswick. (732) 246-7469.</p>
        <p>STOCKTON PERFORMING ARTS CENTER ''As You Like It,'' by William Shakespeare. Wednesday, Thursday and Saturday at 8 p.m.;  Friday at 10:30 a.m. and 8 p.m.; next Sunday at 3 p.m. Tickets: $7; $5 for students and older people; $3 for Friday's performance. Jim Leeds Road, Pomona. (609) 652-9000.</p>
        <p>TRENTON WAR MEMORIAL Boheme Opera presents Puccini's ''Tosca.'' Friday at 8 p.m. and next Sunday at 3 p.m. Tickets: $20 to $50.  Lafayette and Willow Streets, Trenton. (609) 581-7200.</p>
        <p>TWELVE MILES WEST THEATRE COMPANY ''Italian-American Reconciliation'' by John Patrick Shanley. Thursday through Nov. 18.  Performances are Thursdays, Fridays and Saturdays at 8 p.m.; Sundays at 3 p.m. Tickets: $20; $15 for students and older people. 488 Bloomfield Avenue, Montclair. (973) 746-7181.</p>
        <p>VILLAGERS THEATER ''City of Angels.'' Friday through Nov. 18. Performances are Fridays and Saturdays at 8 p.m.; Sundays at 2 p.m. Tickets: $18; $12 for students and older people. 475 DeMott Lane, Somerset. (732) 873-2710.</p>
        <p>WILLIAM PATERSON UNIVERSITY ''Crimes of the Heart'' by Beth Henley. Today at 6 p.m.; Wednesday, Thursday and Friday at 8 p.m.; Wednesday also at 12:30 p.m. at the Hunziker Theater on campus. Tickets: $7; $5 for older people.Shea Center For Performing Arts, 300 Pompton Road, Wayne. (973) 720-2371.</p>
        <p>FOR CHILDREN</p>
        <p>FORUM THEATER COMPANY ''The Legend of Sleepy Hollow.'' Through Nov. 4. Performances are every Saturday at 11 a.m. Tickets:  $9. 314 Main Street, Metuchen. (732) 548-0582.</p>
        <p>MONTCLAIR STATE UNIVERSITY ''Franklin the Turtle: Franklin's Big Adventure.'' Friday at 10 a.m., 12:30 p.m. and 5 p.m. Tickets: $15 for 5 p.m.; $6 for 10 a.m. and 12:30 p.m.  Memorial Theater, Valley Road and Normal Avenue, Upper Montclair. (973) 655-5112.</p>
        <p>NEW BRUNSWICK FREE PUBLIC LIBRARY ''Family Story Hour.'' Thursdays at 7 p.m. through Nov. 16. For children ages 3 to 4. ''Babies and Books.'' Fridays at 10:30 a.m. through Nov. 17. For children ages 12 to 24 months. Registration is necessary for both. 60 Livingston Avenue, New Brunswick. (732) 745-5118, extension 15 or 16.</p>
        <p>RITZ THEATER ''The Legend of Sleepy Hollow.'' Thursday and Friday at 10 a.m.; Saturday at 10 a.m. and 1 p.m. Tickets: $5. Children are invited to wear their Halloween costumes.  915 White Horse Pike, Oaklyn. (856) 858-5230.</p>
        <p>STOCKTON PERFORMING ARTS CENTER ''As You Like It,'' by William Shakespeare. Friday at 10:30 a.m. Tickets: $3. Jim Leeds Road, Pomona. (609) 652-9000.</p>
        <p>WILLIAM PATERSON UNIVERSITY Tom Chapin and Friends. Saturday at 2 p.m.; for children (prekindergarten through 12 years).  Tickets: $7. Shea Center for Performing Arts, 300 Pompton Road, Wayne. (973) 720-2371.</p>
        <p>SPOKEN WORD</p>
        <p>BARNES &amp; NOBLE Brian Gilroy, author, will discuss and sign copies of his book ''Counseling Kids: It's Magic!: Manual of Therapeutic Uses of Magic With Children and Teens.'' Tomorrow at 7:30 p.m. Free. 1180 Raritan Road, Clark. (732) 574-1818.</p>
        <p>BARNES &amp; NOBLE Mary Jane Clark, author, will discuss and sign copies of her new book ''Let Me Whisper in Your Ear'' and discuss her debut novel ''Do You Want to Know a Secret.'' Thursday at 7 p.m. 3981 Highway 9, Freehold. (732) 409-2929.</p>
        <p>BOOKENDS BOOKSTORE Jennifer Lauck, author, will discuss and sign copies of her book ''Blackbird: A Childhood Lost.'' Today at 1 p.m. Mary Higgins Clark and Carol Higgins Clark, mother and daughter suspense authors, will discuss and sign copies of their joint thriller ''Deck the Halls.'' Next Sunday at noon. Free. 232 East Ridgewood Avenue, Ridgewood. (201) 445-0726.</p>
        <p>ENGLEWOOD PULIC LIBRARY Carlos Manzano, New York State Democratic Committeeman, 64th Assembly District, will discuss ''The Role of the Latino Community in the New Millennium.'' Today at 4 p.m. Free. 31 Engle Street, Englewood. (201) 568-2215, ext. 244.</p>
        <p>MONTCLAIR ART MUSEUM Ben Jones, artist, will discuss on ''Creating Art: Conversations with African-American Artists.'' Today at 3 p.m. Free, with admission. Admission: $5; $4 for older people and students; free for children under 12. (973) 746-5555.</p>
        <p>RUTGERS UNIVERSITY Jose Saramago, novelist and winner of the 1998 Nobel Prize in Literature, will give a talk as part of the campus's celebration of its new minor program in Portuguese studies. Today at 2 p.m. Free.  Robeson Campus Center, 350 Dr. Martin Luther King Boulevard, Newark. (973) 353-5262.</p>
        <p>ETC.</p>
        <p>CHILLER THEATER TOY, MODEL AND FILM EXPO Science fiction, fantasy, horror, film and television memorabilia show. Friday, 6 p.m. to 11 p.m.; Saturday, 11 a.m. to 7 p.m.; next Sunday, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. Tickets: $15; $10 (advance); $25 for three-day pass; free for children under 12. Sheraton Meadowlands,  East Rutherford. (201) 804-8040.</p>
        <p>ENGLEWOOD PUBLIC LIBRARY Annual Used Book Sale. Today, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m. Renaissance Office Center, 15 Engle Street (next to the Library), 31 Engle Street, Englewood. (201) 568-2215, ext. 244.</p>
        <p>FALL FINE ART AND CRAFTS AT BROOKDALE PARK SHOW Featuring more than 150 professional artists, craftspeople and photographers displaying and selling their handcrafted work. Today, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Free. Watchung, Bellevue and Grove Avenues, Montclair. (908) 874-5247.</p>
        <p>HERITAGE FESTIVAL 2000 ''Four Centuries in a Weekend: A Journey Through Union County's History.'' Saturday, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. and next Sunday, noon to 5 p.m. Visit 22 historic sites in Union County. (908) 558-2550.</p>
        <p>LAMBERTVILLE HISTORICAL SOCIETY'S HOUSE TOUR Today, noon to 5 p.m. Tour includes Victorian houses, a bed and breakfast, an elegant Queen Anne-style house and more.  Tickets: $15. (609) 397-0770 or (609) 397-2303.</p>
        <p>MORRISTOWN CRAFTMARKET Friday, 6 p.m. to 9 p.m.; Saturday, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m.; and next Sunday, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Showcase of contemporary American crafts, furniture, glass; silent auction; talks and more. Admission: $6 (all three days); free for children under 12.  National Guard Armory, Western Avenue, Morristown. (973) 895-3356 or (973) 631-6277.</p>
        <p>SIX FLAGS GREAT ADVENTURE ''9th Annual Fright Fest.'' Today, Friday evening, Saturday and next Sunday. Includes Halloween-themed rides, attractions, shows. Free with admission, $43.96 (adult); $21.98 (child). Northern Star Arena, exit 7A off the New Jersey Turnpike. (732) 928-1821.</p>
        <p>WHISTLE STOP FLOWERS AND FARM ''Annual Great Hayride Robbery.'' Today, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. ''Search for the Golden Pumpkin.'' Saturday and next Sunday, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Free. Route 579 (John Ringo Road) (seven miles south of Flemington off of Route 202 South), Ringoes. (908) 788-8552.</p>
        <p>AT THE CASINOS</p>
        <p>All tickets are available through Ticketmaster, (800) 736-1420.</p>
        <p>ATLANTIC CITY HILTON Dion. Friday at 9 p.m. and Saturday at 8 p.m. Tickets: $25 and $30.  Grand Theater, Boston and Pacific Avenues. (609) 340-7200.</p>
        <p>BALLY'S PARK PLACE Natalie Cole. Today at 8 p.m. Tickets: $35 and $40. Main Ballroom.  (609) 340-2709. ''Legends in Concert.'' impersonations of Stevie Wonder, Little Richard, Elvis Presley, Linda Ronstadt and Barbra Streisand. Mondays through Thursdays at 3:30 and 7:30 p.m.; Saturdays at 8 and 10:30 p.m.; Sundays at 7:30 and 10 p.m. Tickets: $15 to $25. Park Cabaret, Boardwalk and Park Place. (800) 225-5977.</p>
        <p>CAESARS ATLANTIC CITY Howie Mandel. Today at 8 p.m. Tickets: $45. LeAnn Rimes. Friday at 10 p.m.; Saturday at at 9 p.m., next Sunday at 8 p.m. Tickets: $75. Circus Maximus Theater, 2100 Pacific Avenue. (800) 677-7469.</p>
        <p>CLARIDGE HOTEL ''Jeff McBride's Abracadazzle.'' Through Nov. 16. Mondays through Thursdays at 8 p.m.; Saturdays at 8 p.m. and 11 p.m.; Sundays at 7 p.m. Tickets: $15, Sundays through Thursdays; $19, Saturdays. Palace Theater, Boardwalk and Park Place. (609) 340-3400.</p>
        <p>TROPICANA Kenny Rogers, in concert with Linda Davies. Friday at 9 p.m.; Saturday at 8 p.m.; next Sunday at 7 p.m. Tickets: $30 to $55. ''Tribute to Liberace,'' starring Daryl Wagner; the Lovely Liebowitz Sisters, guests.  Through Dec. 3; call for show times. Tickets:  $15. ''Dresses of Diana, Princess of Wales Exhibit.'' Through Dec. 28. Hours: daily, 10 a.m. to 10 p.m. Tickets: $13.95; $11.95 for older people; $6.95 for children, aged 5 to 11. Boardwalk and Brighton Avenue. (609) 340-3020.</p>
        <p>TRUMP MARINA ''3rd Annual Rock 'n' Roll Memorabilia Auction'' and sneak preview debut of ''Grendel's Lair,'' an original rock opera -- both to benefit the the VH1 Save the Music Foundation. Friday at 3 p.m.; ''Grendel's Lair'' at 7 p.m. Free. The Wave. (800) 841-4687. The Rev. Al Green. Friday at 10 p.m.; Saturday at 9 p.m. Tickets: $45 and $65. Grand Cayman. Huron Avenue and Brigantine Boulevard. (800) 777-8477.</p>
        <p>TRUMP TAJ MAHAL 7th Annual Oktoberfest.  Saturday and next Sunday, 8 a.m. to noon.  Mark G. Etess Arena. Free with a Taj Card. 1000 Boardwalk. (609) 449-5230.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
