<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A French Bistro Beckons in Larchmont</title>
    <meta content="22DINE$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20001029T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240726"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DINING OUT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Encore (Larchmont, Ny, Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reed, M H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001022T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04EEDF153EF931A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="743" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A French Bistro Beckons in Larchmont</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By M. H. REED</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Reed, M H</byline>
      <dateline>LARCHMONT</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>M H Reed reviews Encore, Franch restaurant in Larchmont, NY; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FROM its place on the broadness of Chatsworth Avenue here, Encore glows its welcome. With sunny yellow walls and chandeliers and sconces of flowers in amber glass, this bright bistro francais delights the eye. As its name cleverly suggests, return visits are in order, and we would eat here again despite a few flaws.</p>
        <p>Open only since March, this fledgling shows wonderful promise. Even now, diners can have a satisfactory meal here, but they might have to ride herd on a sometimes careless kitchen to get it. Soups were barely warm, not hot. Promised warm, goat cheese came at room temperature. Other inaccuracies like switched sauces, for example, brought turbot laved with honey and lemon sauce instead of basil sauce, which came with monkfish instead of promised honey and lemon. Service also needed polish: one server was so aloof we felt we were intruding.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FROM its place on the broadness of Chatsworth Avenue here, Encore glows its welcome. With sunny yellow walls and chandeliers and sconces of flowers in amber glass, this bright bistro francais delights the eye. As its name cleverly suggests, return visits are in order, and we would eat here again despite a few flaws.</p>
        <p>Open only since March, this fledgling shows wonderful promise. Even now, diners can have a satisfactory meal here, but they might have to ride herd on a sometimes careless kitchen to get it. Soups were barely warm, not hot. Promised warm, goat cheese came at room temperature. Other inaccuracies like switched sauces, for example, brought turbot laved with honey and lemon sauce instead of basil sauce, which came with monkfish instead of promised honey and lemon. Service also needed polish: one server was so aloof we felt we were intruding.</p>
        <p>That being said, besides the informality and the appealing decor of the place, there is much at Encore worth going for. Vegetable soups are high on that list. The flavor of pure, deep orange carrot was enhanced by a spark of ginger and, we suspect, a hint of jarred garlic, which took a few points from this otherwise smashing dish. Fragrant fennel was the dominant, delicious force behind this pureed soup. We are pleased to report that cream, when it appeared, was used to a modicum. But thin-flavored and watery fish soup fell short of the standards set by those vegetable soups.</p>
        <p>A dish of steamed mussels (moules mariniere) was a model of its kind: fresh mussels, white wine, thyme, broth. Add a few twists of freshly ground pepper and mop up any remaining liquid with a chunk of bread -- marvelous. Good dressing glossed the mesclun base for three chunks of goat cheese, but too long marinating made rings of calamari soft and mealy, and this time the accompanying mesclun salad seemed to have been salted twice.</p>
        <p>Fish occupied most of the entree offerings, and despite the mixup in sauces, they were top notch. A piece of sauteed grouper was so thick we checked whether two filets hadn't been stacked. No, it was one generous, luscious slab in sheer red wine sauce. Beautifully braised monkfish (lotte), turbot and classic, buttery trout amandine were all true to form.</p>
        <p>Cooked medium-rare to our order, fresh, tender calf's liver arrived in an almost black balsamic sauce, a perfect astringent counterpoint to the richness of the liver. Judging by the success of this dish, we would not hesitate trying the few other meat dishes, especially steak frites.</p>
        <p>Vegetable accompaniments were delicious: couscous, haricots verts, grilled tomato, mashed potato and timbales of carrot.</p>
        <p>Good vanilla ice cream came with some of the desserts, of which two were standout. Served on lick of quintessentially berry raspberry sauce, a slice from an amazingly lovely terrine of three chocolates came stacked in four stripes: white, milk and dark chocolates on a thin layer of cake. Fresh fruits -- chunks of apple and mashed strawberries -- were folded into two lacy crepes.  While loaded with good apples, tarte Tatin had a wet crust, and tasteless, soggy peaches were an insult to peche Melba.</p>
        <p>A three-course dinner averages $33 without drinks, tax and tip. Encore is close to Route 1.</p>
        <p>Encore  22 Chatsworth Avenue, Larchmont.  (914) 833-1661.</p>
        <p>GOOD</p>
        <p>ATMOSPHERE -- Small, charming storefront with etched glass, warm wainscoting and old French menu boards and posters pleasingly helter-skelter on the walls. Paper table toppings. High noise level. Warm welcome; table service from helpful to bored and inattentive.  SMOKING -- None.  RECOMMENDED DISHES -- Carrot soup, fennel soup, moules marineere, goat cheese salad, trout amandine, monkfish, calf's liver lyonnaise, sauteed grouper, terrine of three chocolates, crepes with fresh fruits.  PRICES -- Lunch, main dishes, $7.50 to $14.50. Dinner, main dishes, $14.50 to $28.  CREDIT CARDS -- Major cards accepted.  HOURS -- Lunch, Mondays through Saturdays, noon to 2:30 p.m. Dinner, Mondays through Thursdays, 5:30 to 9:30 p.m.; Fridays and Saturdays, 5:30 to 10 p.m.; Sundays, 5 to 8:30 p.m.  RESERVATIONS -- Strongly suggested; necessary on weekends.  WHEELCHAIR ACCESS -- Street level.</p>
        <p>THE RATINGS -- Excellent, Very Good, Good, Satisfactory, Poor.  Ratings reflect the reviewer's reaction primarily to food, with ambience and service taken into consideration. Menu listings and prices are subject to change.</p>
        <p>DINING OUT  Correction:  October 29, 2000, Sunday  A picture last Sunday with a restaurant review of Encore in Larchmont was published in error. It showed the interior of Pascal's, also in Larchmont, which was reviewed on Oct. 8.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: October 29, 2000, Sunday</p>
        <p>A picture last Sunday with a restaurant review of Encore in Larchmont was published in error. It showed the interior of Pascal's, also in Larchmont, which was reviewed on Oct. 8.</p>
        <p></p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
