<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Giving a Theater Force His Due</title>
    <meta content="22ANDE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240735"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hofstra University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Anderson, Robert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Klein, Alvin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001022T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03EEDE153EF931A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="828" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Giving a Theater Force His Due</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALVIN KLEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Klein, Alvin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on celebrated theater and film playwright Robert Anderson, subject of upcoming retrospective at Hofstra University; Anderson, 83, and other participants comment; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAVE it to A. R. Gurney, a celebrated playwright of today, to sum up the significance of Hofstra University's tribute to Robert Anderson, a celebrated playwright of yesterday.</p>
        <p>''It's important to remind him, not just the world,'' Mr. Gurney said in a discussion of Mr. Anderson's place in contemporary American theater.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAVE it to A. R. Gurney, a celebrated playwright of today, to sum up the significance of Hofstra University's tribute to Robert Anderson, a celebrated playwright of yesterday.</p>
        <p>''It's important to remind him, not just the world,'' Mr. Gurney said in a discussion of Mr. Anderson's place in contemporary American theater.</p>
        <p>A critical and popular success from the 1950's into the 1970's, Mr. Anderson's oeuvre, highlighted by the 1953 play ''Tea and Sympathy'' and its film version three years later, is not so much forgotten as overlooked. If he is history, he is living history, with at least two new plays at the top of the trunk.</p>
        <p>On Thursday and Friday, Hofstra's cultural center, in Hempstead, offers ''A Robert Anderson Retrospective: Theater and Film.''</p>
        <p>The retrospective includes a screening of ''I Never Sang for My Father,'' Mr. Anderson's 1970 adaptation of his 1968 play, and performances of ''You Know I Can't Hear You When the Water's Running,'' his 1967 comedy, produced by Hofstra's theater company, under Ed Dennehy's direction, from Thursday through next Sunday.</p>
        <p>On Friday afternoon, two of the original stars of the comedy, Eileen Heckart and George Grizzard, will be performing ''I'm Herbert,'' one of the four one-acts that make up the play.</p>
        <p>A lesser-known play, ''Free and Clear,'' which was produced at the Long Wharf Theater Stage 2 in New Haven in 1983, will have a staged reading, a first hearing in New York, during the conference.</p>
        <p>The Hofstra discussions of Mr. Anderson's work will have a touch of celebrity. An interview with Mr. Anderson is scheduled for Thursday afternoon, and the playwright is to take part in panels both days.</p>
        <p>One panel, ''Robert Anderson, Fellow Playwright,'' will involve Mr. Gurney, Edward Albee and Donald Margulies, who is very emotional about the Anderson influence on his life and work.</p>
        <p>In 1976, Mr. Margulies was a reluctant art student at the State University of New York at Purchase, with his heart in the theater. That's when, Mr. Margulies said, he ''was thrilled at meeting my first living playwright'' and began a 20-year correspondence with Mr. Anderson.</p>
        <p>As part of the panel, Mr. Margulies said he planned to read excerpts of letters Mr. Anderson sent him.</p>
        <p>Taking part in a panel called ''Acting in a Robert Anderson Play'' are Mr. Grizzard, Ms. Heckart, John Kerr, the original leading actor in ''Tea and Sympathy,'' and Teresa Wright, who was married to Mr. Anderson for more than 20 years.</p>
        <p>''It was ridiculous, our separation and divorce,'' said Mr. Anderson, 83. ''It was her idea, but how did I let that happen?''</p>
        <p>He added, ''We started seeing each other immediately afterward.''</p>
        <p>On one of their dates last year, the notion of an Anderson retrospective was born. Ms. Wright and Mr. Anderson were attending Hofstra's tribute to Alfred Hitchcock when they met James M. Shuart, the university's president. Dr. Shuart was so thrilled to meet Mr. Anderson that he asked if the university could honor him this year. Mr. Anderson said he wasted no time thinking about it.</p>
        <p>Ruth Prigozy, professor of English and conference organizer, said it was easy to find people to participate this year. ''Everyone who was asked to this one loves Bob and wanted to come to do something for him,'' Dr. Prigozy said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kerr, 69, a theater dropout who has been a lawyer for more than 30 years, appeared in two of Mr. Anderson's plays, ''Tea and Sympathy'' and ''All Summer Long.''</p>
        <p>''Because of Bob, I knew what Broadway was, when I was just turning 22,'' Mr. Kerr said, adding: ''He is still one of the best friends in my life. No one had to twist my arm to be part of this.''</p>
        <p>To the argument that Mr. Anderson's plays are dated, Mr. Gurney said: ''He wrote about the restrictive roles society asks us to play, and the people who cannot fulfill themselves within those roles and those standards; we don't have to be what the world asks us to be -- and how do we reconcile our own integrity with those demands.''</p>
        <p>For all his acomplishments, Mr. Anderson may be best remembered for two lines. One is the pre-seduction curtain line in ''Tea and Sympathy,'' when the school headmaster's wife says to a student: ''Years from now . . . when you talk about this . . . and you will . . . be kind.''</p>
        <p>And in an interview, Mr. Anderson once said, ''You can make a killing in the theater, but not a living.''</p>
        <p>When he was reminded of that the other day, he recalled collaborating on a series of six textbooks for high school students.</p>
        <p>''From those, I made a living,'' he said. ''In the theater, you can make a life among interesting crazy people.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
