<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Incorrect Artifact With Aging Fans</title>
    <meta content="22HAGA$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="34" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/22/arts/22HAGA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240684"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Impersonations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vaudeville</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Baldwin, Clive</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jolson, Al (1886-1950)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hagan, Joe</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Entertainment and Amusements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vaudeville</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001022T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E3DE173EF931A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1819" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Incorrect Artifact With Aging Fans</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE HAGAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hagan, Joe</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Joe Hagan article on Clive Baldwin, one of small group of impersonators who perform nostalgia acts in US and abroad; Baldwin, despite some disapproval, wears blackface makeup while imitating Al Jolson; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN a ballroom at the Holiday Inn in Rockville Centre, on Long Island, Clive Baldwin was channeling the performance of the legendary vaudevillian Al Jolson in the 1927 movie ''The Jazz Singer'': his lips curled into a sorrowful grimace, his white-gloved hands opened wide in supplication, the whites of his eyes flashed with maudlin emotion. He crouched on one knee, hands over heart and pleaded to the rafters: ''Mammy! Mammy! I'm comin' home, Mammy!''</p>
        <p>Mr. Baldwin, the self-proclaimed ''last minstrel,'' was in blackface, a theatrical convention rarely seen on a stage since the civil rights movement of the 60's.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN a ballroom at the Holiday Inn in Rockville Centre, on Long Island, Clive Baldwin was channeling the performance of the legendary vaudevillian Al Jolson in the 1927 movie ''The Jazz Singer'': his lips curled into a sorrowful grimace, his white-gloved hands opened wide in supplication, the whites of his eyes flashed with maudlin emotion. He crouched on one knee, hands over heart and pleaded to the rafters: ''Mammy! Mammy! I'm comin' home, Mammy!''</p>
        <p>Mr. Baldwin, the self-proclaimed ''last minstrel,'' was in blackface, a theatrical convention rarely seen on a stage since the civil rights movement of the 60's.</p>
        <p>The 100-plus crowd -- the regional chapter of the Al Jolson Society, entirely white and mostly retired -- appeared transported by the act. The kinetic Mr. Baldwin winked and swayed, crooning into the microphone. But somewhere in the middle of ''Carolina in the Morning,'' a curious expression spread across his face; he had noticed a black man, one of the caterers, staring at him from the back of the room. Mr. Baldwin waited for a bridge in the song, then said: ''Look at my friend in the corner! He looks just like me!'' The man glared back. The audience turned to look.</p>
        <p>When the song ended, Mr. Baldwin kept at it. ''Come on in and enjoy the show!'' he yelled, waving to the caterers who stood in the doorway of an adjoining hall. The room was hushed, the tension palpable. ''Bring the boys! Bring 'em all out! We'll have a hoedown tonight!'' He turned to the audience, lowering his voice as if to bring the group into his confidence: ''All the black help here in the hotel are looking to see what's cookin' right here onstage. I'll tell you what: Al Jolson's paying tribute to black folks!'' The audience applauded approvingly. ''That's right, that's right,'' a woman said as the M.C. cued up another song, ''Swannee.''</p>
        <p>An hour later, after a confrontation with angry caterers -- and a decidedly uncomfortable hotel manager who was awaiting the arrival of a black wedding party -- Mr. Baldwin and the Jolson Society had been shown the door. Clive Baldwin had just stumbled one step further into his own personal twilight zone.</p>
        <p>Mr. Baldwin, who is 66, is among a small group of impersonators who perform nostalgia acts in the United States and abroad. He often performs with look- and sound-alike Eddie Cantors, Sophie Tuckers, Frank Sinatras and Bing Crosbys, whose entertainment stylings present soft-focus slices of the 1930's and 40's typically for older audiences. Unlike his peers, Mr. Baldwin opts for historical exactitude over the merely sentimental, bringing back an image of Al Jolson that has come to symbolize, for many, the less quaint aspects of the era.</p>
        <p>Mr. Baldwin began, as he put it, ''blacking up'' when he was 15 in his hometown of Kingston-upon-Hull, England, in 1950, a time when blackface performers still drew mainstream English audiences. It was not the racial burlesque that drew him to blackface, but rather the voice of Al Jolson crooning a medley of ''I'm Looking Over a Four-Leaf Clover'' and ''Babyface'' over the public address system at a fairground. ''I was transfixed,'' recalled Mr. Baldwin, who discovered shortly thereafter his own vocal likeness to a man once called ''the World's Greatest Entertainer.''</p>
        <p>In the intervening decades, his eerily accurate Jolson impression -- made authentic by the blackface -- has made him a man out of time. After years of performing on and off in minstrel acts while holding down a day job in the construction business, he moved to the United States in 1967. He discovered that social perceptions of blackface were transforming it from an old-fashioned shtick into a politically charged act of racism. As political correctness further marginalized him -- and the memory of Al Jolson receded -- Mr. Baldwin developed an embattled attitude. ''I shouldn't have to say that I'm passe, that you might as well bury me,'' he said, sipping on a soda in the ''Minstrel Manse,'' what he calls his Art Deco home just off Arthur Godfrey Road in Miami Beach. ''A man convinced against his will is of the same opinion still, and no matter what anybody says, I'm a dyed-in-the-wool minstrel. I can't be changed.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Baldwin sees blackface as a remnant of an idyllic world that existed before baby boomers and the counterculture of the 60's. Indeed, he regards blackface as an act of ''brotherly affection toward the black man'' and that performers like Jolson humanized blacks for white audiences, thereby laying the groundwork for racial equality. Then ''along comes this new generation to call it a day on all that I believe,'' he said. ''I'm preserving something. That makes me a conservative.''</p>
        <p>''A pre-servative,'' said his wife and manager, Lenore Baldwin, who sometimes performs as the vaudeville singer Sophie Tucker.</p>
        <p>''Since Jolson died,'' Mr. Baldwin continued, ''the whole world has gone to hell."</p>
        <p>He has fewer worries in England and Australia, where he regularly packs 1,200-seat music halls. England lags well behind the United States in sensitivity to blackface; a BBC television program called ''The Black and White Minstrel Show'' didn't go off the air until the late 1970's. Mr. Baldwin is currently on a 22-date tour called ''Give My Regards to Jolson,'' working his way through England, Scotland, Wales and Ireland.</p>
        <p>With the average age of Baldwin's audience well past 70, however, Mr. Baldwin finds himself becoming a historical artifact. ''I am the curator of a kind of museum,'' said Mr. Baldwin, who is one of the few people able to recreate the uncanny bird call that Jolson once did. ''I am a martyr for my time!'' he added. ''I could probably get lynched!''</p>
        <p>A century ago, Clive Baldwin's talents would have drawn large audiences across America. From the early 1840's until well into this century, blackface minstrel shows were the backbone of American popular entertainment. The first blackface acts sprang up around places like Catherine Market, a bustling bazaar where New York's immigrant communities converged across racial and class lines. A legendary performance by the Virginia Minstrels at the city's Chatham Theater in 1843 popularized what would become the basic minstrel-show format. The troupe, which spurred scores of imitators, advertised its ''delineations of the sports and pastimes of the Southern slave race of America,'' which its players would ''illustrate through the medium of songs, refrains, lectures and dances, accompanying themselves on instruments of a peculiar nature.''</p>
        <p>By the 1870's, blacks themselves had begun to embrace minstrelsy, blacking up their own skin. The stereotypes became more sharply defined by blacks as they made minstrelsy speak in ways black audiences could relate to. Just as Manhattan's Lower East Side had been a petri dish of racial and cultural crisscrossing in the 1820's, so, too, was it a century later. Al Jolson, ne Asa Yoelson, a Jewish immigrant from Lithuania, revived a flagging blackface tradition for Broadway and Hollywood and became a worldwide sensation, fusing the story of ''The Jazz Singer'' -- about an immigrant Jew groomed to be a cantor who forsakes his heritage to become a Broadway star -- with his own legend. By the mid-1930's, however, Jolson's career began to decline and so, too, did the popularity of blackface.</p>
        <p>Today, Baldwin is among a handful of obscure Jolson impersonators who still perform nostalgia acts in the United States. But his supporters -- a newsletter produced by his fans has a circulation of about 200,000 -- insist that he's no impersonator but ''the living voice of Al Jolson.''</p>
        <p>Roger Stone, 48, a Republican political consultant in Washington who is among Mr. Baldwin's younger fans, first saw him at a county fair in California in 1994. He was so impressed that he now assists him in finding venues for his act. ''Clive Baldwin is a phenomenal talent, and he has the same magnetism as Jolson,'' Mr. Stone said. But he criticizes the blackface mask as ''a terrible mistake.''</p>
        <p>''I can recognize why it might be acceptable in the U.K.,'' he said. ''I think it's unnecessarily provocative in the U.S. He doesn't need it. It's an anachronism.''</p>
        <p>Another Baldwin convert is Glenn Smith, a 47-year-old filmmaker and a collector of African-American folk art who lives in Southern California. Unlike Mr. Stone, Mr. Smith is particularly enthralled by the blackface. In 1998, he saw Baldwin perform at the New York cabaret Don't Tell Mama and was riveted by what he saw. ''I felt as if I was in a Tijuana pub watching a donkey show,'' he said. ''You cover your eyes, and you don't want to look, but you peek through your fingers and see this guy. I couldn't keep my eyes off of him.''</p>
        <p>The two later became friends, and Mr. Smith purchased from Mr. Baldwin the original wig worn by Jolson in ''The Jazz Singer,'' which Mr. Baldwin had received as a gift from the Al Jolson Society. (The wig was designed by Max Factor.) Mr. Smith is currently producing and directing a documentary about Mr. Baldwin entitled ''The Last Minstrel,'' which he expects to release next year.</p>
        <p>WORKING with Mr. Smith, who considers himself an authority on minstrel history, has given Mr. Baldwin a new way of looking at what he does. In fact, it was Mr. Smith who suggested that Mr. Baldwin call himself ''the last minstrel.'' ''I don't want to offend anybody, but it's part of theatrical history,'' Mr. Baldwin said of minstrelsy. ''As Glenn says, 'The inhibited white guy is released by putting on blackface.' And that may be true.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Baldwin is surprised that his act has lasted as long as it has, especially now that his audience ''is dying around me.'' When he's not performing, he writes poetry, distributing cassette tapes of his religious verse set to music. Mr. Baldwin -- who calls himself a ''biblical prophecist'' and who once built a floating bomb shelter called ''Noah's Arc'' in preparation for a nuclear apocalypse -- sees Jolson not only as a theatrical phenomenon but also as part of  his Judeo-Christian beliefs. In his poem ''Sweet Memories,'' he maintains that the Jolson legacy is about love, not racism:</p>
        <p>As the Cantor that he might have been his voice was heard on high,</p>
        <p>It gave the black man dignity, it made us laugh and cry,</p>
        <p>When we said we loved Jolson, we loved his black man too,</p>
        <p>If love is all that matters what more can one man do.</p>
        <p>MUSIC Joe Hagan, a staff writer at Worth magazine, has written extensively about culture and the arts.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Joe Hagan, a staff writer at Worth magazine, has written extensively about culture and the arts.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
