<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Virtue Is Its Own Punishment</title>
    <meta content="22SCHUEST" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240605"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schuessler, Jennifer</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Williams, Joy</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Quick and the Dead, The (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001022T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E7DF143FF931A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1492" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Virtue Is Its Own Punishment</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jennifer Schuessler</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schuessler, Jennifer</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jennifer Schuessler reviews novel The Quick and the Dead by Joy Williams; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE QUICK</p>
        <p>AND THE DEAD</p>
        <p>By Joy Williams.</p>
        <p>308 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Alfred A. Knopf. $25.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE QUICK</p>
        <p>AND THE DEAD</p>
        <p>By Joy Williams.</p>
        <p>308 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Alfred A. Knopf. $25.</p>
        <p>THREE years ago, Harper's Magazine published ''The Inhumanity of the Animal People,'' Joy Williams's fierce account of -- and declaration of sympathy with -- the radical animal rights movement. The essay contained the familiar brute facts of the slaughterhouse and the research lab, and the usual arguments about suffering, sympathy and the 98 percent of DNA we share with chimpanzees. But the essay was remarkable not so much for its reasons as for its insistence on unreason. Most people think of themselves as liking animals, Williams wrote, and are willing to hammer out sensible measures to ensure that they are treated more humanely. But the real animal people -- the ''flakes'' who refuse to shut up, to be comforted, to be, above all, reasonable -- are ''always plunging into the eschatological dark.''</p>
        <p>Alice, the 15-year-old protagonist of ''The Quick and the Dead,'' Williams's fourth novel and first book of fiction in more than a decade, is one of the animal people. A motherless child who lives with her grandparents somewhere in the desert Southwest, she's all hackles and hair-trigger judgments, mouthing off at the slightest provocation about air-conditioning, coral reefs, the representation of wildlife on tacky souvenirs. She's partial to T-shirts reading ''Thank You for Not Breeding'' and considers staging ''puke-ins'' at a local restaurant that serves veal. She's the kind of girl who gets voted ''most likely to be in charge of collecting bird carcasses on the shores of the Salton Sea.'' When she throws a rock at a renegade motorcyclist who's tearing up a protected area, she doesn't seem to mind that she gets a front tooth knocked out in return. If this prickly girl is a cactus-hugger, it's the plants that are likely to get hurt.</p>
        <p>Like Alice, ''The Quick and the Dead'' is odd, intelligent, unsettling and sometimes spectacularly uningratiating. (It's also beautifully written, and often very funny.) It proceeds not so much by means of a plot as by a chaotic ingathering of wounded characters who have made an early and ambiguous acquaintance with death. There's Alice's friend Corvus, who's slowly slipping into a mummifying silence after the freak drowning of her parents. There's rich, shallow Annabel, who lives with her father, Carter, in a big house that's literally haunted by the angry, wisecracking ghost of her mother, Ginger, who was run over by a car but sticks around to pass on recriminations, stock tips and sneak previews of the beyond. (Carter, eager to get on with his life with a Buddhist yard boy named Donald, tries to scare her off by reciting Lucretius, typical bedtime reading for this crowd: '' 'Cease thy whining, know no care.' You are dead, Ginger, dead! Give up!'')</p>
        <p>And then there are the minor characters who keep showing up like escapees from some pageant of atrocities: a teenage drifter deformed by a stroke and haunted by the lab monkey who died to develop his treatment; a melancholy trophy hunter who opens a taxidermy museum with a fortune made in ''gene research and embryo cryopreservation''; an 8-year old who starts a personal animal shelter by salvaging the taxidermist's botched, still-breathing throwaways. ''I'm distinguishing between life and death, which is more than anyone else in this place does,'' the girl declares. In the weirdly unnatural landscape of this book -- with its hectoring spirits and Jiffy Lube franchises where cacti used to be -- it's not always easy to tell the difference. ''The dead are coming back,'' Carter tells himself. ''And it had to do with the diminishment of everything else.''</p>
        <p>William's language runs with virtuosity across a wide range, from dead-on vernacular to the gorgeously, unabashed oracular. But even her perfect pitch can't keep this scattered, jumpy book from falling to pieces at times. Since the publication of her first novel, ''State of Grace,'' to wide acclaim in 1973, frustrated admirers have faulted her novels for their disjointed structures and increasingly wild leaps into fantasy and satire. Indeed, today her reputation rests largely on her taut, brilliantly controlled short stories written squarely in the realist mode. Read together, Williams the short-story writer and Williams the novelist sometimes seem to be writing from different planets.</p>
        <p>The stories gathered in her most recent collection, ''Escapes'' (1989), showed ordinary people suspended in a kind of emotional remission, with some lurking domestic horror -- disease, marital collapse, an unspeakable death in the family -- just barely kept at bay behind perfectly joined sentences. But the characters in ''The Quick and the Dead'' are living not so much in the everyday world as in an End Time where the dark forces have knocked down all the protective fences and crashed onto the homestead, like the deer that nearly drowns in Carter's swimming pool during one of his absurdist cocktail parties. The animals that appear everywhere -- frightened, butchered, stuffed -- are magical totems, clues to the ''nonhuman mystery'' beyond the comforts of language and psychology and narrative. (As Ginger tells Carter from the other side, ''Reading is so inconsequential. . . . You'll be shocked when you realize exactly how inconsequential.'') Sometimes the animals barge in awkwardly on the human stories Williams is telling, trying the reader's sympathies. But the need to disrupt the easy flow of sympathy -- to call into question the self-serving sentimentality that tends to get filed under ''affirmations of the human spirit'' -- is one of the book's themes, and part of its strange fascination. As Annabel says of Alice, ''She wasn't really savage or even malicious; it was just that if you weren't rebutting her preposterous sentiments every minute, you'd find yourself -- well, not mesmerized . . . but dismantled or something.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, for Williams, seeing the universe whole seems to demand a kind of radically refocused compassion that can sometimes look, well, like heartlessness. There's plenty of bloody violence in the book -- car wrecks, shootings, poisonings -- and much of it has a peculiar weightlessness. Here on slaughterhouse Earth, even murder is a more an existential event than a moral calamity.</p>
        <p>In one bizarre episode, the three girls meet Ray, the drifter haunted by the lab monkey in his head, as he staggers down a trail carrying the scavenged corpse of an endangered bighorn sheep. Alice knows this sad case with a twisted mouth is not a hunter, but to her it doesn't matter -- tying him up and leaving him for dead is a justifiable form of cosmic payback. ''Evil must be repaid,'' she tells herself, ''and not necessarily to the one who'd done the deed. You had to grab whoever was available and annoying and see what came of it.'' Don't even ask about the man who lynches Corvus's dog -- an episode that provokes some of Williams's most understated, and moving, prose. In a remarkable act of authorial rough justice, the man's penis is blown off by a letter bomb and then nonchalantly stuffed down a lizard hole. He and his ''Little Wonder'' (Williams can't resist adding insult to injury) are never heard from again.</p>
        <p>But not everyone is so easily composted. As the book draws to a close, Corvus takes up residence in the local nursing home, a garden of babbling grotesques where she, Alice and Annabel are volunteers. Corvus is there to fulfill her vow to ''die slowly, day by meaningless day, unenchanted, bitterly meaninglessly aware.'' Forget death with dignity. This place is a cruel dumping ground for empty shells who don't seem to notice or care that they're being fed tacos made of greyhound meat for dinner. ''Are you ready to enter our little charnel community, not as a docent or guide but as a living member?'' Corvus is asked by Nurse Daisy, the metaphysical, trash-talking monster who guards the door. ''Do you vow to keep your wits among the witless? Do you commit yourself to pondering ceaselessly the uselessness of caring, the uselessness of love?''</p>
        <p>Alice can't bring Corvus back from the living dead, and in the end she catches a glimpse of her own nightmare, a never-ending, all-purpose vigil for everything from fetuses and grizzlies to the Greenland ice sheet and ''unique deadly microbes that nevertheless were singular life-forms and should not be exterminated.'' ''Concern is the new consumerism,'' the operator of this sympathy franchise tells her. ''There's nothing like lighting your little candle when all around you others are lighting theirs. Nothing! Illumination. Extinguishment. Equilibrium. Then everybody goes home.'' Alice, ever antisocial, refuses to become another number, a mere instance of a peculiar species rather than a world unto herself. This strange, discomfiting novel captures, in flashes and flickers, the infinite, inconsequential mystery of the endangered human soul that's always on its way toward winking out in the dark.</p>
        <p>Jennifer Schuessler is on the staff of The New York Review of Books.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Jennifer Schuessler is on the staff of The New York Review of Books.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
