<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Taming Wagner And His Ilk, All in Good Time</title>
    <meta content="22TOMM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/22/arts/22TOMM.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240681"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Orchestra of the Royal Opera House</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tommasini, Anthony</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Domingo, Placido</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Voigt, Deborah</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pappano, Antonio</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001022T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E1D6163EF931A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1798" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Taming Wagner And His Ilk, All in Good Time</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY TOMMASINI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tommasini, Anthony</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anthony Tommasini reviews recording of Wagner love duets by Placido Domingo and Deborah Voigt and Orchestra of Royal Opera House, conducted by Antonio Pappano; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>PLACIDO DOMINGO'S venture into the German dramatic tenor repertory, a move that took many of his admirers by surprise, began much earlier in his career than is generally remembered. In January 1968, a few weeks before his 27th birthday, Mr. Domingo sang the title role of Wagner's ''Lohengrin'' with the Hamburg Opera. This was nine months before his Metropolitan Opera debut in Cilea's verismo melodrama ''Adriana Lecouvreur'' and seven years before his first performance as Otello, the role generally considered the pinnacle of the Italian dramatic tenor repertory.</p>
        <p>It was daring of Mr. Domingo to try out his first Wagner role in the composer's native land, and the reception was encouraging. Many critics praised the lyricism and freshness he brought to the music. Still, Mr. Domingo was unhappy with the results. Moreover, he later recalled, he hurt himself vocally by preparing Lohengrin so intensely without cutting back on other engagements. Obviously, he recovered, returning to the weightier Italian roles, for which his voice was ideal.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>PLACIDO DOMINGO'S venture into the German dramatic tenor repertory, a move that took many of his admirers by surprise, began much earlier in his career than is generally remembered. In January 1968, a few weeks before his 27th birthday, Mr. Domingo sang the title role of Wagner's ''Lohengrin'' with the Hamburg Opera. This was nine months before his Metropolitan Opera debut in Cilea's verismo melodrama ''Adriana Lecouvreur'' and seven years before his first performance as Otello, the role generally considered the pinnacle of the Italian dramatic tenor repertory.</p>
        <p>It was daring of Mr. Domingo to try out his first Wagner role in the composer's native land, and the reception was encouraging. Many critics praised the lyricism and freshness he brought to the music. Still, Mr. Domingo was unhappy with the results. Moreover, he later recalled, he hurt himself vocally by preparing Lohengrin so intensely without cutting back on other engagements. Obviously, he recovered, returning to the weightier Italian roles, for which his voice was ideal.</p>
        <p>Yet he kept working with German coaches and, in 1984, sang Lohengrin again, in the Met's production, having worked on the role thoroughly with the director, August Everding. And this time he was satisfied.</p>
        <p>Since then, Mr. Domingo has become an important interpreter of Lohengrin, Parsifal and Siegmund, Wagner roles that do not push his low-set tenor voice into an uncomfortably high tessitura and that benefit from his innate sense of lyricism. Some critics still find his German diction and the color of his voice too Latinate for Wagner. Yet it's hard to think of tenors from the last 15 years who have sung these roles any better.</p>
        <p>Mr. Domingo long hoped to take on the pinnacle of the Wagner tenor repertory: Tristan. Some years ago, he realized that he simply could not do it. Still, he talked of recording the role as well as a complete ''Ring'' in which he would sing both Siegmund in ''Die Walkure'' and Siegfried in the cycle's final two operas, ''Siegfried'' and ''Gotterdammerung.'' Even with Mr. Domingo's clout and selling power, no record company was going to assemble the forces necessary to add another ''Ring'' to the catalog just to accommodate the pipe dream of a tenor who had never sung the role of Siegfried on stage.</p>
        <p>Instead, in the summer of 1999 and early this year, Mr. Domingo, who is approaching 60 with as much inexhaustible drive as ever, recorded the extended love scenes from ''Tristan und Isolde'' and ''Siegfried'' with Deborah Voigt as his Isolde and Brunnhilde, and the Orchestra of the Royal Opera House, Covent Garden, conducted by Antonio Pappano. While splendid on its own terms, the new recording, ''Wagner Love Duets'' (EMI Classics 5 57004 2) is also historically meaningful: it captures Mr. Domingo in this repertory as he phases out his career, and it announces Ms. Voigt, now in her prime, as a tantalizing Isolde and Brunnhilde of the future.</p>
        <p>Considered along with Mr. Domingo's new recordings of Beethoven's ''Fidelio,'' conducted by Daniel Barenboim on Teldec, and Mahler's ''Lied von der Erde,'' with the Los Angeles Philharmonic conducted by Esa-Pekka Salonen on Sony Classical, this release will give German opera buffs a sense of what might have been, had Mr. Domingo decided to shift his focus earlier on.</p>
        <p>Mr. Domingo's Siegfried is the real surprise of the ''Wagner Love Duets.'' The role would seem to sit uncomfortably high for him. But it's thrilling to hear him sing without having to conserve his voice and pace himself, as he must in his live performances of Wagner. The essentially poignant timbre of his sound makes this dense, headstrong young character seem vulnerable. Yet Mr. Domingo brings the requisite ardor to the role as well as heroic, pinging top notes.</p>
        <p>From the first transfixing, timeless moments, when Brunnhilde, awakened from her sleeping spell by Siegfried's kiss, rises to greet the morning sun (''Heil dir, Sonne!''), Ms. Voigt is in radiant voice. She sings with tenderness and lyrical pliancy as well as richness and unforced power. Brunnhilde's vocal highs come easily to her.</p>
        <p>Given the stand-and-shout approach of many Wagner singers, the lyricism of Ms. Voigt's and Mr. Domingo's work here is deeply satisfying. Though Wagner made unprecedented demands on vocal stamina and power, he wrote for singers steeped in the bel canto heritage and expected his operas to be sung with elegance of line. Ms. Voigt and Mr. Domingo do so beautifully. And it is a pleasure to hear Wagner sung by highly intelligent musicians, impressively alert to rhythmic values, accents and dynamics.</p>
        <p>The love duet from ''Tristan und Isolde'' is also fine, if not quite on the level of the ''Siegfried,'' though the surprise factor in that opera may be what makes it seem more special. While she sings sumptuously, Ms. Voigt sounds as if she is still finding her way with the role. Mr. Domingo summons plenty of passion and vibrancy where they are called for. The softer phrases do not come as naturally to him. Even in the prime of his Italian tenor days, Mr. Domingo was sometimes faulted for an effortful quality in his pianissimo singing.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pappano conducts supple and incisive performances of both scenes, eliciting rich sound and colorings from the orchestra. A sense of occasion comes through, as if all involved knew that this recording would be significant.</p>
        <p>Lovers of ''Tristan und Isolde'' may well be shocked by the ending of the love scene used here, a concert ending that Wagner composed in 1862, apparently for a performance that never occurred, though you will not find a word about its history in the liner notes.</p>
        <p>The drug-enhanced passion of Tristan and Isolde builds and crests until, just at the moment of climax, King Marke turns up, catching his intended bride and the loyal Tristan, whom he loves like a son, in their act of betrayal. This is the most explicit rendering of coitus interruptus in all of music.</p>
        <p>The concert ending simply takes the lovers through that climactic moment and segues seamlessly into a blissful intimation of Isolde's ''Liebestod,'' which ends the opera. The lovers trade wistful phrases as the music fades into tranquillity. Though it works well musically, the concert ending totally changes the psychological thrust, so to speak, of the scene.</p>
        <p>Ms. Voigt is currently trying to maintain German and Italian roles in her repertory. This season she returns to the Metropolitan Opera as Aida and also has several Toscas on her calendar. That said, as this recording circulates, expect Wagnerites, conductors and opera house directors to pressure her into singing Isolde and Brunnhilde. Of course, if the roles feel wrong to her, she should resist the pressure. But her performances of these extended scenes make you pine for more.</p>
        <p>It's easy to understand why Mr. Domingo was drawn to Florestan in ''Fidelio,'' another German role that wants both heroic sound and lyrical elegance. The character, a Spanish nobleman with passionate liberal convictions, unjustly imprisoned during a vaguely right-wing crackdown, would seem a natural match.</p>
        <p>Mr. Domingo's performance on Teldec (3984-25249-2; two CD's) is at least an honorable effort. The high tessitura of the music challenges him, and he must work audibly at times to sustain legato lines. Yet his voice conveys just the right mix of torment and defiance in ''Gott! Welch Dunkel hier,'' the despairing aria sung by the shackled Florestan in the blackness of his prison chamber.</p>
        <p>In the end, though, Mr. Domingo is trying out a role rather than leaving a document of music he has lived with over time. And with the strong competition among complete recordings of ''Fidelio,'' this one does not stand out. There are impressive contributions from two excellent German singers: the bass-baritone Falk Struckmann as Don Pizarro and the bass Rene Pape as Rocco. The German soprano Waltraud Meier, a distinguished artist who has been sounding worn in recent years, does not fare well as Leonore. In the opera house her tone might not seem so edgy, but the microphone reveals all. Mr. Barenboim, conducting the Staatskapelle Berlin, leads a musically solid, perfectly intelligent though typically ponderous performance.</p>
        <p>The Sony recording of ''Das Lied von der Erde'' (SK 60646) is interesting. Mr. Salonen's work always compels attention, and the Los Angeles Philharmonic plays brilliantly. The baritone Bo Skovhus brings vocal luster and interpretive insight to the songs from this monumental orchestral cycle frequently performed by a mezzo-soprano.</p>
        <p>Mr. Domingo, quoted in the liner notes, points to Mahler's prowess as an opera conductor to argue that the three tenor songs from ''Das Lied'' were conceived with a big operatic voice in mind. He also asserts that Mahler's score reminds him of Puccini's ''Turandot,'' and the comparison is not far-fetched. ''Stylistically they are miles apart,'' he says. ''But both composers were drawn to a Chinese subject and incorporated what I might call 'musical chinoiserie' into their creations.''</p>
        <p>With ''Turandot'' in mind, Mr. Domingo sings the music like an ardent young Calaf. Though the approach is fresh, here, too, you miss the sense of a singer who has lived with the score, and the Mahler discography is filled with notable recordings of those who have.</p>
        <p>Mr. Domingo has said that he would like to perform more Mahler, not as a singer but as a conductor. Yet his work on the podium has been famously uneven. So don't expect to hear a Domingo performance of the ''Resurrection'' Symphony. He has said that if he had put his mind to it at an early age, he could have become a valuable conductor. It's not an idle boast. He is a decent pianist and a well-grounded musician who can study orchestral scores effectively on a plane. If he had truly focused on conducting from the start, worked with living composers and avoided the temptation to hop on stage now and then for a quick Cavaradossi, he just might have succeeded.</p>
        <p>But he chose the right path, as he also did, no doubt, by focusing on Italian repertory and saving his forays into Wagner for later in life. That's why his voice still sounds so good today. Just listen to ''Wagner Love Duets.''</p>
        <p>MUSIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
