<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Shopping the Mall Called Seoul</title>
    <meta content="22FRUG$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20001029T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240631"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FRUGAL TRAVELER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Seoul (South Korea)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mclane, Daisann</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Columns/Frugal Traveler</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/South Korea/Seoul</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/South Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001022T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907E2D71E3FF931A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="3057" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Shopping the Mall Called Seoul</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAISANN McLANE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mclane, Daisann</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Daisann McLane Frugal Travel article describes recent shopping experience in Seoul, South Korea, which she considers epitome of shopping places; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I'M proud of my shopping chops, honed in New Jersey bargain-basement sales, further sharpened on Orchard Street on the Lower East Side and buffed to a fine polish in the open-air markets of Southeast Asia. But there was a moment, during my visit to Seoul in September, when I realized that as a shopper I was still a lightweight. For Seoul is the World Series, the Indy 500, the Olympics of commerce. Even the main downtown business streets teem with sidewalk vendors hawking things I never realized I needed until that instant: Hello Kitty inflatable chairs, matchbox-size cell phones on neck chains, bags of French-fried yams, stuffed toy rabbits, live rabbits.</p>
        <p>Seoul's subways provide no break from the buy-and-sell throb; indeed, there's one shopping arcade that stretches through nearly a half mile of the underground corridors. (And if you run out of cash, there's usually an A.T.M. right by the subway turnstile.) The intensity level of Seoul's trading is dizzying: imagine the New York Mercantile Exchange suddenly expanding to 18 million people and declaring itself a city. For six days I wandered and shopped, got lost and energized on Seoul's supercharged entrepreneurial streets. And when overload set in, I escaped to centuries-old palaces and shrines that coexist with Seoul's hubbub.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I'M proud of my shopping chops, honed in New Jersey bargain-basement sales, further sharpened on Orchard Street on the Lower East Side and buffed to a fine polish in the open-air markets of Southeast Asia. But there was a moment, during my visit to Seoul in September, when I realized that as a shopper I was still a lightweight. For Seoul is the World Series, the Indy 500, the Olympics of commerce. Even the main downtown business streets teem with sidewalk vendors hawking things I never realized I needed until that instant: Hello Kitty inflatable chairs, matchbox-size cell phones on neck chains, bags of French-fried yams, stuffed toy rabbits, live rabbits.</p>
        <p>Seoul's subways provide no break from the buy-and-sell throb; indeed, there's one shopping arcade that stretches through nearly a half mile of the underground corridors. (And if you run out of cash, there's usually an A.T.M. right by the subway turnstile.) The intensity level of Seoul's trading is dizzying: imagine the New York Mercantile Exchange suddenly expanding to 18 million people and declaring itself a city. For six days I wandered and shopped, got lost and energized on Seoul's supercharged entrepreneurial streets. And when overload set in, I escaped to centuries-old palaces and shrines that coexist with Seoul's hubbub.</p>
        <p>Usually, when I am about to travel to a new place, I have some idea of what to expect -- images from guidebooks, popular culture and the arts, or from friends who have traveled there previously. But Seoul proved a difficult research subject. Korea has been in the headlines frequently in the past year, including the announcement on Oct. 13 that President Kim Dae Jung of South Korea had won the Nobel Peace Prize. South Korea and Japan have been trying to heal old wounds through diplomacy, and emotional reunions between North and South Korean families were taking place as I was packing for my trip.</p>
        <p>But current events and tourism don't always converge. The most up-to-date guidebook on Korea that I could find, the Lonely Planet, was published in 1997. The publisher's 1999 guidebook to Seoul is an expansion of the text of the older Korea book, with few updates. Fodor's and Frommer's didn't even have updated Korea guides in print. I was puzzled by the paucity of tourist information on a city that is the original home of so many Americans -- in New York City, not a day goes by in which I don't speak to someone Korean. It also suggested that tourists had yet to discover Seoul, which made it even more intriguing for me.</p>
        <p>Since the range of guidebooks was thin, I called the office of the Korean National Tourism Organization in Fort Lee, N.J., and asked for information. In a few days, there was a fat package in my mailbox with good maps, some handbooks and a booklet with lists of phone numbers (but no fax numbers) of South Korean budget inns, called yogwan. The yogwan are the Korean version of the Japanese budget hotels and family inns. Prices at the Seoul yogwan listed in the tourist organization's booklet ranged from $15 to $40 a night.</p>
        <p>Because there were no fax numbers for reservations, and the descriptions of each yogwan were sketchy, I decided to wait until arriving in Seoul to choose my budget hotel. For the first few days, I'd coddle my jet-lagged self in a Western-style hotel -- in this case, the Sofitel Ambassador. This hotel has a rack rate of $220, before taxes (10 percent in Seoul). But over the Internet, I found a Seoul-based hotel discounter, Business Associates, that booked me into the Sofitel for $152.56, taxes included. When booking hotels in Asian cities, Asian-based Internet services like this one, and www.asiatravel.com, are a terrific resource for those who might not otherwise be able to afford a mid-range or deluxe hotel.</p>
        <p>Outside the window of my 15th-floor room at the Sofitel I could see green hills; Seoul is nestled in a ring of mountains, on a site where the capital city of the Choson Dynasty was established in 1392. Skyscrapers were wrapped in twinkling lights of pink, blue and yellow that blinked in rhythmic patterns as twilight approached, and made the buildings seem like oversize Christmas trees.</p>
        <p>I took a short stroll outside the hotel, which is close to Dongguk University, and felt immediate culture shock. It seemed as if every surface of every building was covered with lighted billboards and printed information, but in an alphabet (Hangul) that I couldn't decipher. English, where it appeared, was sprinkled lightly over the Hangul like a condiment. I saw no street signs, and I didn't bother looking for building numbers, since I knew that South Korea used the Japanese system of addresses, which divides space into sectors and districts, and numbers buildings by age, not their location.</p>
        <p>I went back to the Sofitel and soaked my culture shock away in their ladies' sauna and spa; the hot bath is central to Korean culture, and most big Seoul hotels have one. It melts jet lag faster than any other system or herbal tonic I've tried. The next day, restored by hot water and steam, I was ready to tackle Seoul's challenging streets.</p>
        <p>First stop, the Seoul subway. Although the ticket seller didn't speak English, it was easy to communicate that I wanted a multiple-use pass -- at $9 it contained about 20 trips, enough to cover my whole stay. The trains are clean, with red plush velvet seats, and the system is well signed in Hangul and English. If you ride to the end of a line, a recording plays a snatch of Chopin.</p>
        <p>My second Seoul strategy I'd put in motion before leaving New York, by contacting everyone I knew to be put  in touch with a Korean friend. Soon I was trading e-mail messages with Alice Choy, a close friend of my former landlords, who also happened to be a former high school classmate of a friend of mine. Alice is an architect who oversees the Seoul Jazz Academy, which was founded by her mother, one of Korea's first jazz singers. Alice suggested I explore  the neighborhood around Insadong Street, in the heart of Seoul.</p>
        <p>And so, early on a Sunday morning, I took the subway out to Tapgol Park, a little oasis where elderly Koreans, some in traditional dress, meet to chat and play checkers. Strolling across the park, I came out onto Insadong, a narrow street lined with art galleries and antique shops selling Korean furniture, celadon pottery, calligraphy brushes, and traditional Korean dresses, hanboks. Among the traditional crafts and antiques lurked the odd vendor selling stuffed bunnies and mini cell phones.  The merchandise spilled out onto the street, which was closed to traffic.</p>
        <p>This was Insadong, heart of Seoul's cultural bohemia. I cruised along, stopping to listen to a band that had set up a stage and was playing Korean folk tunes. Two men in the crowd started to dance, spontaneously. I decided, right then, that I wanted to find a place to stay nearby.</p>
        <p>And so for the rest of the afternoon, with the tourism organization's  guide and the Lonely Planet in hand, I conducted my yogwan hunt. When I stopped in the first, the Minhwa, which had been given top marks by Lonely Planet, I was glad I was inspecting in person. The owner wasn't around, but one of the guests, a young Korean man who spoke a little English, let me see his room: a tiny square of linoleum with no window, and a Korean futon as thin as a quilt.</p>
        <p>The bathrooms were communal. ''Not so clean,'' he said. ''Clean enough for me, I guess. By the way, be careful, because some of the yogwan are for men and prostitutes.''</p>
        <p>With those encouraging words, I poked around a few more yogwan, and had almost given up on the idea of moving to one when I stumbled across the Han Hung Jang, on a lane a few steps off Insadong. The elderly woman in charge didn't speak English, but she understood what I wanted, and grabbed my hand and pulled me upstairs to show me a room.</p>
        <p>Tiny and clean, it had a double Western-style bed with a good firm mattress, a tiny window, air-conditioner, a little bathroom and cable TV. I rely on instinct a lot when choosing places to stay, and this place felt friendly. I took the room (about $23 a night) and was quite happy there for the next three days.</p>
        <p>I spent them browsing the cafes of Insadong (my favorite was the Artside, a sleek SoHo-like space that served delicious plum-flavored tea), sampling the Korean restaurants along the strip (Alice steered me to Imo Jip, which means Auntie's House), and, of course, shopping.</p>
        <p>The tourism organization's list of Seoul's attractions can almost be divided down the middle into two categories: palaces and markets. I happily bounced between both ancient and modern Seoul, first tackling the huge street market at Namdaemun, where I found a cool Korean-made hot pink hiking parka made of a quick-drying fiber for $40, then ducking into the subway and emerging at the Deoksugung Palace in time to catch the changing of the palace guard -- and some happy couples having wedding pictures taken against the backdrop of the impressive 15th-century wooden mansions.</p>
        <p>One day I took a subway ride to the end of the line, and then a bus, to the suburb of Suwon, and the Korean Folk Village, a Williamsburg-like enclave where guides in traditional clothes demonstrate village crafts and dancing. While such places often feel strained or touristy, this didn't, perhaps because the guides live in the village. Along with a hundred or so schoolchildren (the village is Class Trip Central), I cheered as a dozen young men leapt and turned cartwheels in a folk dance.</p>
        <p>ANOTHER morning I strolled in the serene gardens of Changgyeonggung Palace, which connect to Jongmyo Royal Shrine, where the burial tablets of Korea's kings are housed in a huge, spare wooden building surrounded by a vast courtyard; Alice had recommended Jongmyo as an example of Korean architectural aesthetics. Fast-forwarding to the 21st century (courtesy of Seoul's zippy subway), I hit the Yongsan Electronics Market, a district filled with warehouse-size buildings where thousands of small vendors sell computers, chips, music equipment, televisions and the latest models of Walkmans, mini-TV's and MP players. It's a dizzy, giddy maze of shops in which prices are highly negotiable. For $100, I walked home with a shiny new silver-blue cassette player unlike any I'd seen at home.</p>
        <p>In the basement of Doosan Tower, a gleaming silver skyscraper financed, astonishingly, by a cooperative of market-stall vendors, Seoul shopping overload finally began to set in. Would I be consumed with regret if I didn't buy the North Face backpack or the Hello Kitty Walkman earphones? Around me cell phones bleeped the chorus of ''Happy Birthday to You.'' I felt dizzy, and decided I needed to change gears -- perhaps an afternoon at a museum?</p>
        <p>At the airport, I'd seen banners advertising ''Media City Seoul 2000,'' a huge exposition of video and cyber-art installations from around the world at the Metropolitan Museum downtown. (It closes at the end of this month but is planned as a biennial, returning in 2002.) I was greeted at the museum by a phalanx of volunteers, one of whom became my personal guide as I walked through three buildings filled with installations, many of them interactive.</p>
        <p>My young guide didn't speak English, but he could show me which buttons to push, which lights to wave my hand over, and which sensors to jump on to make the lights flash on and off, the computer speakers go blap and bleep. We finished by dueling on a virtual cybergame in which I moved my hands and feet, like a kung fu practitioner, to control the hands and feet of an on-screen Wonder Woman. Wonder Woman, I'm sorry to say, was no match for her more cyberseasoned foe. She limped, embarrassed and defeated, back to the main museum building, to take one more look at the Nam June Paik installation at the entrance.</p>
        <p>A collage of cultures, Korean and global, and of elements traditional and postmodern, the installation was lighted by garish fluourescent bulbs, with a bank of television sets that ran a continuous tape of a documentary of traditional Korean folkways. Paik created the ultimate Seoul market stall -- topped off with a counter display of inexpensive push-up bras  and underwear. If someone had set this up in Namdaemun market, instead of in a museum, passers-by would probably just hover around and poke, idly, at the merchandise.</p>
        <p>Inspired by Nam June Paik's tribute to the enterprising energy of Seoul, I returned, refreshed, to shopping.</p>
        <p>The bottom line on shopping's major league</p>
        <p>I spent about $114 a day during six days and nights in Seoul on hotels, meals, local transit and admission fees. I bought a Korean Air ticket  from New York to Seoul with a side trip to Hong Kong from a discount ticket broker, Air Brokers International, (800) 883-3273, for $1,192.30.</p>
        <p>Hotels</p>
        <p>The Sofitel Ambassador, 186-54, 2-ga, Changchung-dong, Jung-gu, Seoul, phone (82-2) 2275-1101, fax (82-2) 2272-0773, Web site ambassadors  .co.kr/sofitel/main1.htm, is a Western-style hotel with amenities like  marble bathrooms with hair dryers and a well-equipped fitness center, and an attentive staff. A major attraction is the Korean-style baths,  consisting of a heated tub of water, sauna, steam room and washing area (separate baths for men and women). The rack rate is $220; I paid $152.56 through a Korean travel agency on the Web, Business Network Ltd. (andyou.com). That price includes tax and reflects an additional 10 percent discount because I booked three weeks ahead.</p>
        <p>At Han Hung Jang, 99 Kwanhun-dong, Jongro-ku, Seoul, (82-2) 734-4265, a yogwan, or no-frills guesthouse, my tiny room with double bed and private bath cost $22.75 a night, at 1,100 won to $1.</p>
        <p>Restaurants</p>
        <p>I spent a total of $114 on meals, but for enough food to easily feed another person (or two). Six to eight free side dishes -- kimchi (spicy pickled cabbage), vegetables, marinated tofu -- arrive with every meal.</p>
        <p>Pul Hyanggi, (82-2) 2265-1320, is in Jung-gu district in a little lane five minutes' walk from the Sofitel (call for directions). It serves a wide variety of vegetarian dishes, a Korean specialty. Meals are served traditional style, on low tables (you sit on the floor). The centerpiece of my set dinner ($12) was a bowl of rice with  unusual green vegetables and tofu.</p>
        <p>The Obseoye restaurant, Dongsung-dong 1-95, Jongno-gu, (82-2) 742-4848, across the street from the Seoul Jazz Academy, specializes in shabu-shabu, in which fresh raw vegetables, meat and seafood are cooked at the table in a pot of boiling water. A tasty meal for three with Korean beer came to about $32.</p>
        <p>The Artside cafe on Insadong serves cakes, light Western-style meals, wine and beer, and delicious  herbal and fruit teas; plum tea costs $4.50 a cup. It's at 170 Kwanhun-dong, Jongno-gu, (82-2) 725-1551.</p>
        <p>At Imo Jip (Auntie's House), my friend Alice and I shared bulgogi (Korean beef barbecue), a big plate of batter-dipped fried vegetables, and a small bottle of soju, Korean vodka. Dinner for two was $40. Imo Jip is across from the Han Hung Jang yogwan at 78-2 Kwanhun-dong, Jongno-gu; (82-2) 720-4688.</p>
        <p>I splurged on a multicourse dinner and show at Sanchon, 17 Kwanhun-dong, Jongno-gu, (82-2) 735-0312, which is geared to upscale tourists.  The set meal ($26.75) consists of almost 20 different vegetarian dishes. It's best to arrive at about 8, because at 9 p.m., the lights dim, and everyone stops to watch women in traditional dress perform Korean dances.</p>
        <p>Attractions</p>
        <p>Admission to the 14th-century  Jongmyo shrine and the Changgyeonggung Palace complex costs 40 cents.</p>
        <p>One of the highlights of a visit to Deoksugung Palace is watching the changing of the guards at around 2 p.m. on a traffic-choked street outside the palace. Admission: 40 cents.</p>
        <p>''Media City Seoul 2000,'' with the main installations at the Seoul Metropolitan Museum, will run until Oct. 31. Admission is $9.50.</p>
        <p>The students and faculty at the Seoul Jazz Academy, 39 Yeon-geon-dong, Jongno-gu, Seoul, (82-2) 766-7779, often give concerts near the campus. The show I attended cost $5.</p>
        <p>The Korean Folk Village, in the Seoul suburb of Suwon, (82-331) 286-2106, costs $7.75, including the bus between the Suwon subway station to the site. The trip from Seoul on subway and bus takes around two hours and costs about $2; a taxi back to the train station costs $10 if you don't want to wait for the free bus.</p>
        <p>Getting Around</p>
        <p>Seoul has an excellent subway system, which is marked in English and easy to use. A 20-trip ticket costs $9;  a single trip in the center city costs about 50 cents.</p>
        <p>A Korean Air bus took me from Kimpo Airport to my hotel in about an hour, for $4.50.</p>
        <p>As in Japan, streets in Korea have no numbers, and often no names.  Many lodgings print business cards with a map on the back.</p>
        <p>There are different ways to transliterate Hangul; street or district names spelled differently in various English guides or maps may refer to the same place. Kimpo Airport, for example, may be Gimpo; Pusan may show up as Busan.</p>
        <p>Information</p>
        <p>The Korean National Tourism Organization, 10 Ta-dong, Jung-gu, Seoul, (82-2) 729-9600, provides free maps and brochures in English; its helpful staff will even book hotels. It  also has a desk at Kimpo Airport and an office in Suite 100, First Floor,  1 Executive Drive, Fort Lee, N.J. 07024; (800) 868-7567, fax (201) 585-9041.</p>
        <p>DAISANN McLANE</p>
        <p>FRUGAL TRAVELER  Correction:  October 29, 2000, Sunday  A picture caption on Page 6 last Sunday with the Frugal Traveler column, about Seoul, misidentified a palace in the city. It was Changdeokgung Palace, not Deoksugung.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: October 29, 2000, Sunday</p>
        <p>A picture caption on Page 6 last Sunday with the Frugal Traveler column, about Seoul, misidentified a palace in the city. It was Changdeokgung Palace, not Deoksugung.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
