<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rivals for Congress Debate Who's More Middle Class</title>
    <meta content="22LARR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240734"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="POLITICS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">House of Representatives (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kelly, Sue W (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Graham, Lawrence Otis</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kilgannon, Corey</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001022T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906EEDE153EF931A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1013" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rivals for Congress Debate Who's More Middle Class</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By COREY KILGANNON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kilgannon, Corey</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on animosity between Democrat Larry Otis Graham and incumbent 19th Congressional District Republican Rep Sue W Kelly of Westchester County, NY, over issue of who is more middle class and more in touch with voters; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Even before Larry Otis Graham officially declared last spring that he would challenge Representative Sue W. Kelly for her Congressional seat, the incumbent went on the offensive.</p>
        <p>In a fund-raising letter sent out by her supporters last year, Mrs. Kelly, the Republican who has represented the 19th Congressional District since 1994, attacked Hillary Rodham Clinton as ''a carpetbagging opportunist'' and referred to Mr. Graham, a Democrat, as a ''liberal journalist'' recruited by the Clintons to defeat her.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Even before Larry Otis Graham officially declared last spring that he would challenge Representative Sue W. Kelly for her Congressional seat, the incumbent went on the offensive.</p>
        <p>In a fund-raising letter sent out by her supporters last year, Mrs. Kelly, the Republican who has represented the 19th Congressional District since 1994, attacked Hillary Rodham Clinton as ''a carpetbagging opportunist'' and referred to Mr. Graham, a Democrat, as a ''liberal journalist'' recruited by the Clintons to defeat her.</p>
        <p>If anything, relations between the two sides have deteriorated since then.</p>
        <p>Until last week, the candidates had not met to debate the issues, and now they are not only questioning each other's politics but also their truthfulness and their economic and social backgrounds. Each is claiming, in effect, to be more middle class than the other and more in touch with voters.</p>
        <p>There's no question that Mr. Graham, 38, has a certain star power for a first-time political candidate.</p>
        <p>A graduate of Princeton University and Harvard Law School, he has written 13 books on education, labor and racial issues and has been a television commentator. He is perhaps best known for his 1992 article in New York magazine about posing as a busboy at the Greenwich Country Club to find out about racism and anti-Semitism there.</p>
        <p>His efforts to research discrimination in large corporations helped lead to the successful class-action lawsuit against Texaco in 1997. His wife, Pamela Thomas-Graham, is chief executive of CNBC.com. They live with their 2-year-old son in Chappaqua, several blocks from the Clintons' house, and Mr. Graham said he has received campaign advice from the president.</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Graham faces an uphill battle.</p>
        <p>With $650,000 in her campaign treasury, Mrs. Kelly has twice as much money as Mr. Graham. And the district, which covers part of White Plains and all of Westchester to the north, as well as Putnam County and parts of Orange and Dutchess Counties, is predominantly Republican.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Kelly, 64, a former real estate broker, won the seat in 1994 and was re-elected handily in 1996 and 1998. She succeeded Hamilton Fish Jr., a moderate Republican, who held the seat for nearly three decades.</p>
        <p>Mr. Graham has been campaigning since May, trying to convince voters that Mrs. Kelly has sided with the conservative Republican leaders of Congress, voting against the interests of the district.</p>
        <p>''She claims to be a moderate, but she has not offered anything in moderation to this district except for service,'' he said in a forum last month in Chappaqua. He criticized her environmental record and her effectiveness in fighting for Medicare and aid to education.</p>
        <p>He also said she has received almost half her funds from special interest groups, like the National Rifle Association.</p>
        <p>He has called for more federal spending for education, specifically prekindergarten programs, and strengthening gun-control laws, including banning assault weapons.</p>
        <p>He called Mrs. Kelly's failure to attend debates and candidate forums ''a slap in the face of constituents who want dialogue.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Kelly called such criticism innuendo and fear tactics. ''I've worked really hard for the people in this district,'' she said, ''and I think they know that.''</p>
        <p>She said she could not take part in debates before this week because she was ''down in Washington, working for the people of my district.'' And she denied being in lock step with Republican leaders or being influenced by special-interest money.</p>
        <p>Her priorities include saving Social Security and reforming Medicare to give the elderly different plans to choose from and coverage for prescription drugs. She also favors tax breaks for college tuition and eliminating the inequity in income tax rates for married people and the inheritance tax.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Kelly supports the death penalty, while Mr. Graham supports a moratorium on it. Both candidates favor abortion rights, although Mrs. Kelly opposes so-called partial-birth abortion. She favors increased military spending, while he favors cuts.</p>
        <p>Mr. Graham is hoping to benefit from Mrs. Clinton's Senate campaign. He has campaigned alongside the first lady in the district, and the president offered suggestions on strategy and campaign consultants.</p>
        <p>The Kelly campaign, meanwhile, hopes to capitalize on antipathy toward the Clintons.</p>
        <p>Her campaign has also raised questions about the way Mr. Graham describes himself to voters.</p>
        <p>Long a prominent member of exclusive black social circles, Mr. Graham once lectured the intelligentsia. Now he is courting middle-class voters at Rotary Club meetings and train stations.</p>
        <p>Before running for office, Mr. Graham proudly discussed driving his Jaguar, wearing expensive suits and dining in the best Manhattan restaurants. His home in Chappaqua has a swimming pool, a tennis court and a guest house.</p>
        <p>Now, the Kelly campaign says, he is deceiving voters by offering himself up as a man of the people.</p>
        <p>Many articles over the years have portrayed him as coming from an affluent family with a ''a real estate developer'' father and ''a psychologist'' mother.</p>
        <p>But these days, Mr. Graham tells voters he grew up in a ''union labor household'' where his mother, a social worker, and his father, a mail carrier and firefighter, could not afford to pay his college tuition.</p>
        <p>''As a candidate, Larry Otis Graham claims he grew up in a blue-collar family,'' said Rob Ostrander, a campaign spokesman for Mrs. Kelly, ''but before running for political office, he described himself as 'elite.' It raises a question about who he is and where he comes from.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Graham dismissed such remarks as ''a race to the bottom'' strategy meant to skirt more substantive issues. His father only dabbled in real estate, he said, and their inheritance of an old family trucking fortune never amounted to much.</p>
        <p>''Proving one of us has more middle-class roots than the other is ridiculous,'' he said. ''She is the daughter of a doctor.''</p>
        <p>POLITICS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
