<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Options With Home Heating Systems</title>
    <meta content="LICLINIC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240806"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HOME CLINIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOME REPAIR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001022T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DEFD6123EF931A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="753" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Options With Home Heating Systems</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWARD R. LIPINSKI</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE heating system is an important factor to consider when buying or building a new home. The system is in two parts: the heat-producing unit, and the machinery that distributes the heat throughout the house. While it is important to consider both components when evaluating a heating system, the distribution system is a little more important and it should be considered first.</p>
        <p>The most common system in North America is forced-air heating. A furnace first heats air, then a fan pumps the hot air through metal ducts to floor registers in various rooms in the house. The incoming air creates a pressure differential that forces cooler air into return registers and ducts channel it back to the furnace for reheating and recirculation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE heating system is an important factor to consider when buying or building a new home. The system is in two parts: the heat-producing unit, and the machinery that distributes the heat throughout the house. While it is important to consider both components when evaluating a heating system, the distribution system is a little more important and it should be considered first.</p>
        <p>The most common system in North America is forced-air heating. A furnace first heats air, then a fan pumps the hot air through metal ducts to floor registers in various rooms in the house. The incoming air creates a pressure differential that forces cooler air into return registers and ducts channel it back to the furnace for reheating and recirculation.</p>
        <p>Forced-air systems deliver heat quickly and are easy to integrate with other climate-control systems, like air conditioners, humidifiers, dehumidifiers and air filters.</p>
        <p>The drawback of a forced-air system is that heat can be lost through the duct walls if they are not wrapped with insulation. In addition, the duct seals may deteriorate over time and allow air to leak out. Also it is difficult to set up zones for heating different parts of the house separately. (Sometimes this can be accomplished by selectively closing dampers in the ducts, but it takes time to do this properly.) Another disadvantage to the forced-air system is that the air handler and blower unit can be noisy, especially with older units.</p>
        <p>A good forced-air system should be designed to fit the house so the air flow is not obvious. This can be accomplished only if the air handler is the correct size and the registers are positioned where they will be the most effective.</p>
        <p>Another popular heating system is baseboard hydronic heating. In this system, water is heated in a boiler and then pumped through pipes to baseboard radiators throughout the house. This type of heating offers quiet operation and relatively little heat loss through the distribution system. Leaks are rare, but if they do occur, the hot water can cause major damage to floors and walls. Air-pressure imbalances are not a problem, and it is relatively easy to configure this type of system for zoned heating.</p>
        <p>The main disadvantages to hydronic heating systems are they cannot be adapted to accommodate other climate control systems, and the installation costs can be high. Also, the heaters along the baseboards can interfere with furniture placement.</p>
        <p>Radiant floor heating is another type of hot-water heating system. The heating element consists of specialized rubber or plastic tubing embedded in a concrete slab under the floor, and the water, or a water-antifreeze mix, heated by a boiler, turns the entire floor into a radiator. A radiant floor system can provide a high level of comfort because it gives uniform heat across the entire floor surface.</p>
        <p>On the downside, it takes time to heat a cold room with radiant floor heating because the heating elements must warm up a large slab of concrete before the heat can rise to the room above. It is also expensive to put in and requires the skills of trained designers and installers. And since the heating element is embedded in the floor slab, radiant floor heating is only practical for single-level houses.</p>
        <p>Another type of heating is called direct-space heating. Strictly speaking this is not a distribution system, because it consists of individual heating units positioned throughout the house. The heat is generated where it is used.</p>
        <p>Typical space heaters include kerosene heaters, portable electric heaters, and wood- or gas-fired fireplaces. In a modern home these are auxiliary heating systems at best, and are used by most homeowners to supplement another heating system. The main disadvantage to space heaters is that they use combustible fuels (with the exception of electric heaters) and unless they are vented properly, they can introduce noxious gases into the home.</p>
        <p>There is one type of space heater, however, that qualifies as a heating system. It is electric baseboard heating. Each unit generates the heat at the point of use so it can be considered to be a space heater, but because the heaters extend throughout the house, they can also be considered to be a whole house heating system. Installation costs for this system are low but, depending on electric rates, operation costs can be higher than for other systems.</p>
        <p>HOME CLINIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
