<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Rare Opportunity For Real Architecture Where It's Needed</title>
    <meta content="22MUSC$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/22/arts/22MUSC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240686"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ART/ARCHITECTURE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Times Square and 42nd Street (NYC)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Times</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Times</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Muschamp, Herbert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Piano, Renzo</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pelli, Cesar</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Foster, Norman (Sir)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Plains</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001022T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403EFDD173EF931A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="4686" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Rare Opportunity For Real Architecture Where It's Needed</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HERBERT MUSCHAMP</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Muschamp, Herbert</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Herbert Muschamp assessment of The New York Times plan for new headquarters, designed by Renzo Piano, on Eighth Avenue between 40th and 41st Streets; presents images of proposals and predicts building will be most important corporate skyscraper to be built in city since 1965; photos; drawings (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WE were getting a lot of mail from readers complaining that I never write about New York buildings, so my employers decided to build one. Not just any building, but a work of architecture, a project with the potential to raise the quality of building in New York. Last week, when I learned that Renzo Piano had been chosen to design the new headquarters for The New York Times, I knew that we had such a project.</p>
        <p>The intended site is the east side of Eighth Avenue, between 40th and 41st Streets, across from the Port Authority Bus Terminal. The plan depends on the approval of the board of directors of The New York Times Company, as well as city and state permits to lease the site. Piano was chosen from among three finalists. The others were the British architect Sir Norman Foster and Cesar Pelli of New Haven. The architects of a fourth proposal, Frank O. Gehry and David Childs of Skidmore Owings &amp; Merrill, withdrew from the competition several weeks before the final choice was made.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WE were getting a lot of mail from readers complaining that I never write about New York buildings, so my employers decided to build one. Not just any building, but a work of architecture, a project with the potential to raise the quality of building in New York. Last week, when I learned that Renzo Piano had been chosen to design the new headquarters for The New York Times, I knew that we had such a project.</p>
        <p>The intended site is the east side of Eighth Avenue, between 40th and 41st Streets, across from the Port Authority Bus Terminal. The plan depends on the approval of the board of directors of The New York Times Company, as well as city and state permits to lease the site. Piano was chosen from among three finalists. The others were the British architect Sir Norman Foster and Cesar Pelli of New Haven. The architects of a fourth proposal, Frank O. Gehry and David Childs of Skidmore Owings &amp; Merrill, withdrew from the competition several weeks before the final choice was made.</p>
        <p>The images of all four plans presented in these pages, including Piano's, are studies. The goal of the selection process was to choose an architect rather than a design. In a process like this, it is common for a proposal to undergo substantial revision after the architect is chosen. Architect and client may even decide to start again from scratch. The client is looking for a set of intangibles: a texture of thought, a feeling of compatibility, the sense that something historical has been set in motion by the first encounter.</p>
        <p>It is too soon to evaluate Piano's design, and it will never be possible to assess what the other finalists might have done. But it is not premature to talk about some of the issues raised by the proposals, and by the selection process itself. Nor is it too soon to state that Piano has been given the chance, and unquestionably possesses the skills, to design the most important corporate skyscraper to be built in New York since Eero Saarinen's CBS Building in 1965.</p>
        <p>I am a part of this story, a footnote who gets to tell the tale. At the invitation of Michael Golden, the vice chairman of The New York Times Company, and with the approval of my editors, I met periodically, over a six-month stretch, with the group responsible for choosing an architect for the new Times building.</p>
        <p>I had serious reservations about crossing the line from the news department to the corporate side of the paper. The Times does not permit its critics to serve on arts juries. This policy is wise, not only because it constrains us from abusing the authority of the newspaper and from potential conflicts of interest. More important, sitting on a jury removes us from our natural habitat -- the realm of ideas and values and their artistic expression -- where we go in search of stories. That realm is our reality.</p>
        <p>I am not a disengaged critic. The cultural dimension of building stirs me emotionally. I have minimal interest in personalities or politics, except as these play out on a symbolic or allegorical plane. Architecture's practical dimension is one of the things that make it exciting to write about, but the practicalities do not lack outspoken advocates. The metaphoric dimension is less easily grasped, particularly in a city like New York, which has seen solittle thoughtful architecture in recent years.</p>
        <p>THIS is where a critic can be useful. The symbolic level is where architecture itself kicks in. When it does, land use rises above the level of real estate speculation. Buildings earn the space they occupy on other than economic terms. Defining those terms is what a critic does. More important, his job is to insist that those terms, while not quantifiable, are as substantial as the materials from which buildings are made and the money it costs to build them. My job is to say: architecture is real. Over the months, I had ample opportunity to do my job. I also learned about factors that have eroded New York's status as a city where serious architecture is possible.</p>
        <p>The selection of an architect for The Times building was conducted as a 50-50 partnership between The New York Times Company and Forest City Ratner, a real estate development firm whose projects include Metrotech, the office complex in downtown Brooklyn. The Times building will be slightly under 700 feet, or 45 stories, tall. The lower half of the tower will be occupied by the paper's newsroom, its business division and corporate offices. Space in the top half will be leased to outside tenants. A six-story base will include an atrium for shops and restaurants and an auditorium for lectures, forums and other public events. Forest City plans to occupy one floor of office space. The Times assumed primary responsibility for selecting an architect.</p>
        <p>I attended meetings of the Design Advisory Group, composed of staff members of The Times and Forest City, occasionally joined by representatives of the 42nd Street Redevelopment Authority, a subsidiary of the Empire State Development Corporation, and of the Economic Development Corporation, a city agency. A smaller group was designated to arrive at a consensus on the final choice.</p>
        <p>I'm not going to report on what transpired behind closed doors. Here, I want to sort out some thoughts that occurred to me in the course of looking at the four finalists' designs At the last meeting I attended, when there was movement to revive a proposal that had been previously passed over, someone present observed aloud that we seemed to be on shifting ground. I felt I had been on shifting ground the entire six months.</p>
        <p>In fact, architecture itself is always on shifting ground. Architects try to pin down ideas that are floating in the cultural atmosphere, chief among them, perhaps, the evolving relationship of self to community in a modern democracy. There's nothing inherently stable in that relationship, or in the processes architects and clients use to articulate it in urban space.</p>
        <p>The guidelines for the selection process were prepared by the client partners and presented in impressively large, handsome books. The guidelines struck me as a road map to mediocrity. In the criteria for evaluating previous work of the firms being considered, ''architecture'' was folded in with objective standards, like whether a firm produces works within budget and has extensive experience with skyscraper design. The truth is that architecture can't be quantified. And to judge from recent additions to the New York cityscape, prior experience with skyscraper design struck me as possible grounds for disqualification.</p>
        <p>Architecture, meanwhile, was defined as ''compatible/compelling design vocabulary.'' If compatible meant contextual, this standard was an open invitation to all kinds of mischief. Architecture should contribute to, rather than fit in with, its surroundings. Compelling, besides being generally incompatible with compatible, suggested to me a standard of formal values more suitable for architectural photography and rendering than for architecture itself. The concept is oblivious of the relational values from which architecture is made: of outside to inside; top to bottom; structure to expression; content to form.</p>
        <p>Somehow, however, we got from that unpromising start to a stunning outcome.  Renzo Piano's design embodies those relational values, and others, in radiant form.</p>
        <p>Piano, who has offices in Genoa and Paris, is the world's greatest living practitioner of what I call ''normative'' architecture. Others call it ''the classical humanist tradition,'' which sounds more dignified. But why not just come out and say it? He's Italian.</p>
        <p>Piano's aesthetic is as much urban as it is architectural. All Italians know that when you get a bit of money, you do something to ornament the city. You put up a church, create a nice civic square, commission a statue. Then, when the money goes away, the church is still standing. The statue remains. As Piano mentioned to me, ''even when people are poor, they don't have to live in a poor way.'' They still have the richness of their surroundings. He has brought that philosophy to projects in Berlin, Paris, Sydney and other centers of cosmopolitan life.</p>
        <p>We're at the crest of a building boom in New York. The city is feeling very rich. But with a few exceptions -- Columbus Center, the Rose Earth and Space Center at the Museum of Natural History, LVMH Tower -- I see few buildings that will be worth preserving for the future. In fact, if it were possible to cancel most of the current construction, the world would be a better place. The 1980's, too, were a time of vast mediocrity. What Piano brings to the job, apart from his talent, is a deeply ingrained sense of civic responsibility, a conviction that The Times must give back, through architecture, the good fortune it has enjoyed.</p>
        <p>I don't want to make too much about Piano's Renaissance humanist lineage. He lives in different times. Nonetheless, he shares with Michelangelo, da Vinci and Brunelleschi the belief that art and science exist within the same cultural continuum. This idea has been evident from the first building that brought Piano wide recognition: the Pompidou Center in Paris, designed in collaboration with Richard Rogers and completed in 1977. Controversial when new, the this exoskeletal structure set off a debate that helped make it the most visited tourist attraction in Paris. For The Times project, Piano will employ new techniques in structural engineering, vertical circulation and curtain wall construction, in association with Fox &amp; Fowle, the architects of the Conde Nast and Reuters buildings in Times Square.</p>
        <p>ISEE The Times project, in its present form, as a work of urban landscape. The building's base, which Piano describes as Baroque, is made of concrete slabs that float, at 11 different levels, around three sides of a central atrium. The programming of this space needs work. The Baroque idea (to draw people in) is valid. Once there, people should experience something beautiful. Current renderings, however, show something like a media mall, in a Fun Palace configuration that recalls the work of the British architect Cedric Price from the 1960's. There is too little contrast with the city outside.</p>
        <p>Anyone who has gone for a ride on the Pompidou's escalator knows that Piano is a great poet of circulation. Now he is playing with ways to organize the tower's elevators. Instead of a central elevator core, he prefers a side arrangement that would give office floors the spaciousness of a piazza. What I'm waiting for, however, is to see how he plans to connect the building to the Eighth Avenue subway and Port Authority station. The connection could turn the tower into an infrastructural midtown gateway.</p>
        <p>Piano has planned additional landscape features for two upstairs levels. He envisions the roof of the base as the site for a water park, a shallow pool that would reflect the tower on its surface and bounce sunlight back up onto the tower's skin. This poetic device could become a setting for instant squalor, not to mention a source of leaks. There will be a garden on the roof, protected by extensions of the glass curtain wall above the building envelope.</p>
        <p>What is New York's cityscape about? Escaping gravity and heaviness without losing touch with the ground. The Brooklyn Bridge, Central Park, the Seagram Building and other New York landmarks embody this idea. For The Times tower, Piano has designed a triple-skin wall that lifts the material city's grid into a metaphysical realm. A thermal wall of double-pane panel is shielded on the exterior by a sunscreen of white ceramic rods. These last are interrupted at eye-level by bands of fixed, slender blinds. Inside the offices, movable blinds or shades will increase the layers to four.</p>
        <p>Piano has used this system before, usually in combination with orange masonry panels. Here, the metal, glass and ceramic surface will shimmer without interruption across the entire expanse of wall. Indentations at the corners will allow the expression of the walls as independent planes. This effect will be heightened by the extension of the glass high above the roof line.</p>
        <p>Piano uses terms like vibration, breathing and magic to describe what he calls the ''immaterials'' of architecture. It is with these qualities that the reality of his architecture resides. But he comes from a family of builders. And he works within a tradition of close collaboration between architects and those who fabricate their work. He reminds us that the term design originated in the Renaissance with the Italian word for drawing. The concept signified the architect's emergence as a specialist apart from building. From it, we derive the conception of architecture as the meeting ground for matter and mind. Piano will invite New York to revisit that ground.</p>
        <p>Cesar Pelli designed a perfect bullseye for those who can't help enlisting The Times as a target for resentment. Pelli is the house architect of the monoculture, a designer of iconic corporate towers that bear less relationship to their surroundings than to other corporate icons around the world. To create these, he often borrows forms from the iconography of ancient authoritarian regimes. At the World Financial Center in Battery Park City, for example, the four towers are variously crowned with a pyramid, a ziggurat, a dome and a mastaba.</p>
        <p>Pelli's use of these symbols reflects the formalist idea that they have been cleansed of their original meanings by subsequent usage and can now be appreciated as abstract geometric shapes. I never bought this idea, and Pelli's design for Petronas Towers in Kuala Lumpur, based as it is on regional motifs, suggests that Pelli himself is prepared to abandon it when he chooses. In any case, the triumph of formalism was never so complete that viewers aren't free to locate meanings even where the architect chooses to deny them.</p>
        <p>For The Times proposal, Pelli selected the obelisk, that most ancient authoritarian symbol. Since its appearance in ancient Egypt, the obelisk has been recontextualized many times over. Its meaning has changed in each context. In Baroque Rome, it represents the triumph of the Christian church over pagan superstition. In Washington, it is a tribute to the symbolic founder of the first modern democracy. In New York, it is the archetypal skyscraper, a sign of material aspiration.</p>
        <p>But we are living in a time when our liveliest minds are engaged in challenging forms of authority and the codes that represent it. Hierarchy, paternalism, control: visual symbols cannot, after all, be detached from the power relationships that govern social behavior. Indeed, globalization, and its monocultural effects, have made it ever more urgent to reject the idea that symbols can be used as purely abstract forms. It is an assertion of social and artistic responsibility to insist that forms have meanings.</p>
        <p>One of the things we know about the monoculture is that it is protean. Its appearance constantly morphs. This mutability diverts attention from the fact that the underlying economic power relationships remain the same. Pelli's design, for example, draws from a recent avant-garde preoccupation with folded planes. This motif has appeared in the work of Peter Eisenman and others. A high-style French version of it materialized in New York last year in Christian de Portzamparc's glass facade for the LVMH Tower on 57th Street.</p>
        <p>PELLI has regularized the folded plane motif, and in doing so turned its meaning into the opposite of that intended by architects associated with this motif. Others have used the folded plane to challenge classical notions of hierachy. Pelli's obelisk affirms them. It is symmetrical. It is without scale. The pattern of its window mullions is nearly identical throughout. From top almost to bottom, it is an authoritarian object.</p>
        <p>On the ground floor, the motif changes. The obelisk rests on a ''happy face'' base of retail shops. This, too, is part of the monocultural structure. Buy a pair of khakis. Consume the festival atmosphere. Literally support what some might call your oppressors, the folks who peer down from the structure's upper floors.</p>
        <p>I was disheartened by the inclusion of Pelli among the finalists. Evidently, my message about the reality of architecture wasn't getting through. I could accept that this slick corporate object might represent a developer's view of The Times. I could not accept that it represented the paper's view of itself. Yes, The Times is a powerful institution, but of a particular kind. It is not part of so-called ''black car'' culture. We take subways. The newsroom reaches daily toward the Enlightenment ideals of free speech and independent inquiry, however imperfectly. The newsroom itself, as well as its coverage of news, has been powerfully affected by debates over authority that have unfolded in architecture and throughout the culture. The paper has the responsibility to challenge and correct, not blindly affirm, the corporate world's view of itself.</p>
        <p>Pelli's obelisk stood as aloof from these issues as it did from the site's physical context. Aloofness, in fact, is what clients hire Pelli to provide. This arm's-length attitude extends to Pelli's relationship to his own buildings. The architect, an agreeable man, likes to tell potential clients that, in his native Spanish, pelli means skin, and thus he naturally came to think of the building skin as the essence of architecture. He leaves most of the rest to specialists in other fields.</p>
        <p>It is true that there are many historical precedents for emphasizing facade design over space and structure. It is also true that Mr. Pelli has designed some attractive building skins. But the thing to bear in mind is that the equation of architecture with building skins is what most developers want to believe. They want the image of architecture without the expense and inconvenience of the real thing. Pelli provides that image for people whose interest lies in denying architecture's reality. This denial goes far toward explaining why New York architecture is in such bad shape. Why go through this process to end up with more of the same?</p>
        <p>Norman Foster also creates power fetishes, but they are unquestionably works of architecture. Their elegance is mathematical as well as esthetic. Sir Norman Foster thinks holistically. He gets his mind around structure, space, program and image, making of them an integrated system. He turns problem-solving into art. And he is acutely responsible to the well being of those who inhabit his buildings.</p>
        <p>His proposal for The Times didn't work for the clients, who saw it as not sufficiently flexible to accommodate the building's lease tenants. The design is a space frame in the shape of a right triangle. Along the hypotenuse, winter gardens were planned at intervals of seven stories. Each seven-story segment was conceived as a village in a vertical urban stack. The effect was an apotheosis of the New York set-back.</p>
        <p>The combination of three (sides) and seven (floor intervals) illustrates the mystical-mathematical fascination of Foster's work. What I liked best about this plan was the implied shapes that would result if the triangle were multiplied. Double, turn upside-down, and you get a rectangular solid. Double this, and you arrive at a square. Viewers may well have perceived these ghost shapes in the midtown context.</p>
        <p>Anyone who is less than 100 percent enthusiastic for a Foster building in New York must feel like the ingrate of all time. I prize few qualities higher than rational thought. But I don't fully trust its architectural expression. My generation was strongly influenced by Robert Venturi's 1966 book, ''Complexity and Contradiction in Architecture.''  We came to appreciate the non-straightforward, the hybrid, the slightly deranged.  Some of also us came to suspect that pure rationality too often serves to mask a highly irrational will to power.</p>
        <p>At my last meeting with the group, someone asked which of the four proposals I preferred. I replied that if I were in their shoes, I would find it painful to choose between Piano and Gehry/Childs. The two teams had not designed equally good versions of the same thing. They had designed two different things. Two entirely different beasts. One rational and classic, the other Romantic and Gothic. Unlike the 19th-century critics who debated which style was best, we know that classical and Gothic represent more than different tastes. They correspond to different mental faculties, the right and left sides of the brain. Yet Piano's design is clearly sensuous, and Gehry/Childs's design incorporates the classicism of the International Style.</p>
        <p>The truth is, I was madly in love with the Gehry/Childs proposal. Gehry's work will do that to you. It doesn't want you to keep your distance. From the outset, Gehry had told the clients he intended to design them ''an object of desire.'' He and Childs made good on the promise. As I sit here, I'm looking at a six-inch-tall glass model of their design. Am I a masochist, or what?</p>
        <p>I will have the opportunity to write about the Gehry/Childs proposal next May, when models and sketches of it will be part of the Gehry retrospective at the Solomon R. Guggenheim Foundation. I need the distance, after all. For now, my attraction to it is based on my preoccupation with dualisms, on the cultural as well as the psychological plane. I believe collaboration between ''name'' architects is the wave of the future. The Gehry/Childs plan was a true collaboration, by two outstanding architects of different cities, skills and outlooks, who between them produced a major miracle.</p>
        <p>There has been speculation about why the Gehry/Childs team withdrew. Mine is that the proposal was defeated by the very factors that made it great: the attempt to create a shared reality from four different points of view. However much they may have agreed on economic and practical matters, The Times and the developers represented two cultures. This made for unusual discussions with all the teams but Pelli's, who alone among the four finalists has embraced with something like passion the pragmatics of commercial real estate development. With the Gehry/Childs proposal, the structure changed shape. What was, in effect, a three-way conversion was enlarged to four. The lines of communication increased exponentially.</p>
        <p>Partnerships between two firms are common in architecturally ambitious projects. Usually, however, tasks are divided between a signature, so-called ''design architect'' and an ''executive architect,'' reponsible for more detailed drawings and other construction documents. This will be the arrangement between Renzo Piano Building Workshop and Fox &amp; Fowle. The Gehry/Childs team, however, was not usual. The two firms had to devise novel ways to implement a pioneering arrangement. They, too, represented two cultures. The clients had to believe that the arrangement between them could work in practical terms.</p>
        <p>Could four cultures intertwine? Where would the design work be done? Would the architects' two staffs get along? Would David Childs feel overshadowed by Frank Gehry? Would there be overlap between tasks? Would this affect fees? The share value of Times stockholders? Who would be in charge? Would the curtain wall work? Could the clients accept that, under any circumstances, architecture cannot be achieved by relying on standard real estate procedures? Given the ambition of this proposal, and the city's virtual innocence of all things architectural for many years, such obstacles to realization were inevitable.</p>
        <p>Another factor must be confronted. Its name is love. In a 1959 essay on ''The Sublime and the Good,'' Iris Murdoch writes: ''Art and morality are, with certain provisos, one. Their essence is the same. Love is the perception of individuals. Love is the extremely difficult realization that something other than oneself is real.''</p>
        <p>Frank Gehry has always insisted that to do his best work, he needs a close relationship with a strong client. What he is really saying is that he needs a client's love. This is not a diva thing that suddenly came over him when he became the It Architect. To judge by a 1969 interview about the client-architect relationship, published in Designers West, Gehry has been saying the same thing all along. His job is to empathize with the client's reality. He expects the same</p>
        <p>IT has always been clear that Gehry packs emotion into his work. What is less apparent is that much of this emotion emanates from his relationship to the client. In the case of the Times project, Gehry believed that he had demonstrated his affection for the paper by entering a competition in the first place (something he no longer does), by devoting much time, money and energy to the design (the Gehry/Childs design was the most highly developed of the four), and by producing a work that differs substantially from the Bilbao Museum and is in no sense inferior to it.</p>
        <p>Gehry felt that his feelings were not reciprocated. This I understand completely. I once offered my resignation here for the simple reason that I felt I wasn't appreciated in proportion to the energy I was putting in. I was wrong, and so was Gehry. From the day he and Childs presented the project at 229 West 43rd Street, the tide of opinion began to shift in their direction.</p>
        <p>For me, this shift was the most extraordinary part of the process. Just a week before, the clients had regarded Gehry with suspicion, as someone who might produce something unacceptably funny, weird or arbitrary. By the time the presentation was over, roughly half the people present had psychologically moved into the building. (Or so indicated a poll that was taken shortly therafter.) In fact, there is a great deal of passion circulating through 229 West 43rd Street. But The Times does not typically wear its heart on its sleeve. And I suspect that any developer's ''due diligence'' procedures are about as tender and heartwarming as a visit from the I.R.S.</p>
        <p>This episode brings to mind a poem of Auden's:</p>
        <p>If you see a fair form, chase it</p>
        <p>And if possible embrace it,</p>
        <p>Be it a girl or boy.</p>
        <p>Don't be bashful: be brash, be fresh.</p>
        <p>Life is short, so enjoy</p>
        <p>Whatever contact your flesh</p>
        <p>May at the moment crave:</p>
        <p>There's no sex life in the grave.</p>
        <p>But is this lusty philosophy suitable for what is still widely thought of as the newspaper of record?</p>
        <p>Great buildings break rules. Piano will give us something subtler, more refined -- more normative -- than the design conceived by Gehry and Childs. Yet I'm confident that Piano's will be great. Since the 1970's, the reigning law in New York building has been: thou shalt not commit architecture here. That rule will now be shattered by Piano -- with luck, beyond repair.</p>
        <p>ART/ARCHITECTURE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
