<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Running Away From a Daunting Television Legacy</title>
    <meta content="22FISH$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/22/arts/22FISH.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240680"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION/RADIO"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fish, Stanley</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Janssen, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Daly, Tim</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Fugitive (Tv Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001022T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE7D6163EF931A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1982" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Running Away From a Daunting Television Legacy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STANLEY FISH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fish, Stanley</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Stanley Fish article compares first two episodes of new television series Fugitive starring Tim Daly with 1960's series starring David Janssen; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE two big moments in the first episode of the new ''Fugitive'' are physically spectacular. The first comes near the beginning when Dr. Richard Kimble, once again running from a justice system that has convicted him of killing his wife, escapes from his nemesis, Lieutenant Gerard, by jumping from an overpass onto a moving truck; he avoids being decapitated by executing a leap-and-grab maneuver that would have earned him gymnastic gold at the Sydney Olympics.</p>
        <p>The second big moment comes about 40 minutes into the hour, when Kimble is cornered by Gerard on a high ledge of a building under construction. In a nod to the 1993 Harrison Ford movie (produced by the same team responsible for this series), Kimble jumps off the ledge, falls into a net -- which then begins to rip apart beneath him -- and staves off certain death by grabbing what is left of the net and using it in Tarzan-fashion to swing himself back onto the ledge of a lower floor. Whew!</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE two big moments in the first episode of the new ''Fugitive'' are physically spectacular. The first comes near the beginning when Dr. Richard Kimble, once again running from a justice system that has convicted him of killing his wife, escapes from his nemesis, Lieutenant Gerard, by jumping from an overpass onto a moving truck; he avoids being decapitated by executing a leap-and-grab maneuver that would have earned him gymnastic gold at the Sydney Olympics.</p>
        <p>The second big moment comes about 40 minutes into the hour, when Kimble is cornered by Gerard on a high ledge of a building under construction. In a nod to the 1993 Harrison Ford movie (produced by the same team responsible for this series), Kimble jumps off the ledge, falls into a net -- which then begins to rip apart beneath him -- and staves off certain death by grabbing what is left of the net and using it in Tarzan-fashion to swing himself back onto the ledge of a lower floor. Whew!</p>
        <p>The likelihood of either of these highlights gracing an episode of the old (1963-1967) ''Fugitive'' is very small. The original fugitive's ''big'' moments would have found him crouching behind a door in a small, windowless room, or refusing one of the easy outs offered by the many men and women eager both to protect him and to hold on to him, or waiting passively while some troubled person -- often a child -- decides whether to betray him or to remain silent and allow him to begin running again.</p>
        <p>These were the big moments in the original ''Fugitive'' because they got to the heart of what that show was about: the formation of character in situations of intense and private moral choice, a choice that few will see made but one that will alter for better or worse the person who makes it. This new ''Fugitive'' (Friday nights at 8 on CBS) has no interest in character at all and stakes everything on the double plot that comes along with the concept: Gerard chasing Kimble and Kimble chasing the one-armed man who really killed his wife. The twin pressures of that plot were certainly utilized in the original, but only as bookends ushering Kimble into the scene of character formation and ushering him out when his work -- the work of a combination pediatrician, therapist and policeman -- was done. In between is where everything happened, as Kimble (played by the consummate television actor David Janssen) quickly developed relationships of dependence, complicity, brotherhood and parenthood with a small number of people closely linked to one another by ambitions, jealousies, aspirations and more forms of loneliness than one would have thought imaginable.</p>
        <p>By the end of an episode, none of those with whom Kimble interacted would be what they were when he first entered their lives; each would have learned a lesson or failed to learn it, with future consequences that were clear to viewers even if they were not spelled out. By contrast, the characters who populate the new ''Fugitive'' barely deserve the name: hastily sketched-in stereotypes (the crooked construction foreman, the attractive woman with a winsome little girl, the venal clerk in a seedy hotel), they are utterly dispensable and serve only to ferry Kimble from one moment of physical danger to the next. In the original, by the time of the fade-out we felt that we knew this town and its inhabitants better than we knew Kimble, who worked very hard at withholding himself from everyone, including us. When the new show returns Kimble to the road, we know and care about nothing, because everything we have been shown is one-dimensional and forgettable.</p>
        <p>This is true of Kimble himself as played by Tim Daly (brother of Tyne, and son of James, who appeared in two episodes of the original series). It's not simply that Mr. Daly is just another pretty face. Janssen was even prettier (especially in the early years, before the legendary hard living that led to his death at the age of 48). But when Lois Nettleton (one of the great character actresses who made repeat appearances during the original show's run) said to him, ''You sure have a face,'' she meant not only that he was physically attractive -- despite alarmingly big ears -- but that in his face she saw a complex mixture of fear, anxiety, outward turmoil and inner peace. When in the first episode of the new series, broadcast Oct. 6, the obligatory lonely-woman-who-falls-for-Kimble tells him that he is different and much more than he seems to be (a lowly day-laborer), the only thing she could possibly mean is that he's the star, for nothing at all separates him from all the other dark-haired wiry younger men who populate the generic ''dramas'' of the present television landscape. As Kimble is about to escape for the third time in a single hour, Gerard declares, ''I will never stop,'' and the fugitive replies, ''Neither will I''; but where similar exchanges in the original are energized by complicated patterns of interdependence and obsessiveness that bind the two together, here the urgency of their statements is energized only by the hope that the series will last for its season's run and that next year they will still have jobs.</p>
        <p>The falling off from one of the highest standards ever achieved in television is most obvious when the new show pays its respects to the old. At the top, credit is given to the concept's creator, Roy Huggins (responsible too for ''Maverick,''  ''The Rockford Files'' and ''77 Sunset Strip,'' among others), who is also listed as an executive producer. The names remain the same, including the name of the one-armed man, Fred Johnson. A newscaster is heard using the phrase ''mighty hand of fate,'' an allusion to the wonderfully portentous voice-over by William Conrad, who each week spoke of fate and flight in a famous introductory sequence. There are once again lots of buses and bus stations. The episode ends with the new Kimble walking along a railroad track and interacting inconclusively with a stray dog; Janssen's Kimble walked a similar railroad track at the end of his first episode (''Fear in a Desert City'') and was trailed for a while by a stray cat.</p>
        <p>Obviously the new guys have been looking at what the old guys did, but these homages amount to little more than tips of the cap, gestures of acknowledgment that remain stylistic and superficial and never penetrate to the core of the earlier achievement. You can see this most clearly in the changes. In the original, Kimble's wife was alone because the two had a big fight about adopting a child (he wanted to, she didn't). In the Year 2000 version, Kimble and his wife are rapturously happy as they run and clown along Chicago's lakefront, and it is only because he stumbles and suffers a minor injury that she gets home ahead of him and is assaulted by the one-armed man.</p>
        <p>What this means is that the first Kimble's insistence that he did not kill his wife was complicated and shadowed by the fact of a troubled relationship, and there was just the hint of a suggestion that in some respects he might be better off with her dead. (The Chicago columnist Mike Royko picked up on this in a hilarious parody-interview.) Moreover, this was a complication made use of in the many later episodes when Kimble found himself taking children (or child-like adult men and women) under his wing and thereby enjoying some small version of the parenthood his wife had denied him.</p>
        <p>NO such complexity attaches to the new Kimble. He is straightforwardly innocent of even a bad thought and is suspected in part because a bystander to the physical horseplay between him and his wife has mistaken it for abuse. (The other reason for his being a suspect is that his wife is rich and he's only a doctor!) No bystander saw Janssen's Kimble, and therefore no one could back up his account of what he did after the quarrel; we viewers knew that he drove angrily away from his house and sat alone in a deserted spot in a car (the perfect ''Fugitive'' setting) from which he spotted a boy fishing alone from a boat -- his double? the son he fears he'll never have? the solitary life he really longs for? -- a boy who didn't spot him, a failure of connection that would be echoed in many later episodes. There is nothing comparable to say about the person who misinterprets the camaraderie between the young couple in the new series; he's just a prop (unless he turns out to be in league with the one-armed man, a turn that would be ingenious but profoundly uninteresting), and is of no significance whatsoever.</p>
        <p>If we are lucky, this will be true too of the most salient change made by the producers and writers of the remake: the new Gerard is black. We will be lucky if nothing is made of this at all, for then it will mean only that one more African-American actor has work in a prime-time series, and that's a good thing. But I fear that we might be in for some social relevance -- the few times topical themes entered the old ''Fugitive,'' they were not the focus but were used to highlight the drama of moral choice -- and that in later episodes Kimble will wander into some minority communities pursued by a Gerard who will be confronted with the contradiction of his being a black enforcer of the white man's law.</p>
        <p>The prospect is dreary, but the temptation is one this new crew probably won't be able to avoid, if only because they seem to be operating without an idea. A fugitive running from the law and running after the real villain is not an idea; it's just a device on which to hang things -- locales (Miami is really wasted in the pilot), oddball types, hot-button issues and, above all, spectacular stunts -- things that have only an opportunistic relationship to a plot whose only point is to keep itself going.</p>
        <p>Roy Huggins had an idea. He wanted, he wrote in the early 60's, to transpose ''the existential situation of the lead in a western'' to a contemporary setting. He wanted to create a narrative structure that would ''relate to deep and responsive drives, needs and fantasies in the American audience'' and to ''the preoccupation with guilt and salvation which has been called the American Theme.'' He wanted to find a way to dramatize ''a man without roots, without obligations, without fixed goals, without anxiety about his place in the order of things,'' a man living a life of ''absolute freedom'' even as the threat of incarceration and death hangs over him. That was Huggins's mission and it proved not to be an impossible one, as 120 episodes amply show. Maybe this new ''Fugitive'' won't make it and CBS will have a hole in the Friday schedule and maybe they'll be smart enough to fill it by letting the real fugitive run again.</p>
        <p>TELEVISION/RADIO Stanley Fish is dean of the College of Liberal Arts and Sciences of the University of Illinois at Chicago. His most recent book is ''The Trouble With Principle'' (Harvard, 1999).</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Stanley Fish is dean of the College of Liberal Arts and Sciences of the University of Illinois at Chicago. His most recent book is ''The Trouble With Principle'' (Harvard, 1999).</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
