<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>JERSEY DIARY</title>
    <meta content="22DIAR$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240836"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001022T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E5D9133EF931A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="600" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>JERSEY DIARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DEAR DIARY:</p>
        <p>Two toll collectors on the New Jersey Turnpike were standing on the side of the highway at Interchange 15E when one of them recalled an incident from the moring rush:</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DEAR DIARY:</p>
        <p>Two toll collectors on the New Jersey Turnpike were standing on the side of the highway at Interchange 15E when one of them recalled an incident from the moring rush:</p>
        <p>A woman pulled up to a full service booth, he said, even though her car was equipped with an E-ZPass sensor. At that point the collector reminded her that she no longer had to wait in the cash lane.</p>
        <p>''I know I don't have to use these lanes,'' she said, ''but I need directions. E-ZPass can't give me them, but you can.''</p>
        <p>John Holl</p>
        <p>At a Radio Shack in West Caldwell recently, an elderly woman asked a sales clerk to demonstrate how to use a radar detector.</p>
        <p>''Surely you are not planning to break the law?'' a bystander asked.</p>
        <p>Seemingly insulted by the question, she replied: ''Certainly not. I'm perfectly capable of causing accidents at regular speeds.''</p>
        <p>Moments later -- after a well-dressed young woman arrived -- she said: ''It's a gift for her. She's my daughter. She needs it.''</p>
        <p>Peter Seckel</p>
        <p>A sign spotted on the lawn in front of St. Paul's Lutheran Church on Galloping Hill Road in Elizabeth: ''Sundays here are sweeter than Dairy Queen's.''</p>
        <p>Bernadette Dashiell</p>
        <p>TRANSIENTS</p>
        <p>Rent an arm. Rent a bat.</p>
        <p>Buy a pennant, just like that.</p>
        <p>See free agents come up big,</p>
        <p>Auditioning for next year's gig.</p>
        <p>Bob McKenty</p>
        <p>While I was jogging near New Providence, passengers in passing cars shouted from their windows as they passed me. This was startling, considering how I was enjoying the quiet reverie of the wooded road.</p>
        <p>Then I remembered that I had put on a 1999 Yankee Championship T-shirt in honor of the playoffs, and the shouts were hearty fan-to-fan hellos.</p>
        <p>It's like this: ''I apologize to all of you to whom I responded rather rudely. I just didn't get it. Drive by again this weekend, and I promise I'll react with equally positive enthusiasm.''</p>
        <p>Dennis Kennedy</p>
        <p>Two regulars got off the Midtown Direct in Pennsylvania Station one recent morning and confronted a mutual but -- until that moment -- unshared dilemma.</p>
        <p>''I never know which escalator goes up to the main floor and which only goes up part of the way until I'm already on it,'' the woman, a middle-aged advertising executive, complained.</p>
        <p>Her friend and neighbor -- still half-asleep -- eloquently agreed: ''Yeah, me neither.''</p>
        <p>Overhearing the conversation -- and probably hoping that he never reached that point in his life, a younger man explained good-naturedly: ''You can tell by the symbols on the sign and the word Amtrak. That goes all the way up.''</p>
        <p>The two, euphemistically speaking -- more-seasoned commuters -- wiped the egg from their faces and proceeded up the escalator to the main waiting area. They could tell by the little icons. Still, they wondered, why couldn't the signs simply say main level or Long Island Rail Road concourse?</p>
        <p>Perhaps the budget had been exhausted paying for the unending warning to hold onto the escalator's hand rail and other equally silly admonitions. Strange; they don't play those warnings in department stores, stadiums, malls and the millions of other places where escalators are found.</p>
        <p>THE SILENCE OF THE LEAVES</p>
        <p>God bestows</p>
        <p>and never takes.</p>
        <p>Man blows</p>
        <p>and never rakes.</p>
        <p>Edmund Conti</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
