<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Finally, Mets and Yankees Are Good Enough to Be the Best</title>
    <meta content="Y22HOR$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/22/sports/22HORN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240949"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BACK TALK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chass, Murray</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olney, Buster</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kepner, Tyler</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Curry, Jack</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001022T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E0DC113EF931A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1759" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Finally, Mets and Yankees Are Good Enough to Be the Best</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses both New York Yankees and New York Mets advancing to World Series and prospects for each team winning Series; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CHASS -- Over the years, there have been very few seasons, if any, where the Mets and the Yankees have both been good enough to reach the playoffs. For a while, it was the Yankees and then the Mets, and back to the Yankees, and then the Mets again. So they never had this opportunity.</p>
        <p>But now they've both done it and, I can't say that I feel it was inevitable because it's not in baseball. There are just too many things that can happen. Look at the Atlanta Braves, how often they get to the postseason. They've won nine consecutive division championships and they are not in the World Series. They didn't get past the first round this year. If they had, maybe the Mets wouldn't be in the World Series to have a Subway Series.</p>
        <p>CURRY -- What makes this more refreshing, too, is, as silly as this may sound since the Yankees were the defending champions and the Mets had a very good team, is that in a way this is still surprising. Last year, there was a lot of talk about it and people expected it. And then when the Mets lost to the Braves, there was a deflating feeling in baseball. That, ''Oh, it didn't happen. Who knows when it's going to happen again?''</p>
        <p>And because of those lousy Septembers that the Mets and the Yankees had, we didn't hear a lot of Subway Series talk. We certainly didn't hear as much as we had heard in 1999.</p>
        <p>OLNEY -- On Sept. 10, I absolutely thought that it was going to happen and then on Sept. 30, I thought there was absolutely no way it would happen after watching the Yankees struggle through the end of the year. After watching the Yankees win Game 3 against Seattle, I said, ''Oh my goodness, here we go.''</p>
        <p>I remember having a conversation with Paul O'Neill with about six weeks to play. And I said, ''You know, Paul, the Mets are playing great and you guys are doing well. I really think you guys are going to play a Subway Series.''</p>
        <p>And he looked at me and he goes: ''I just couldn't handle that. I just couldn't handle that,'' in the way that he talks. And it was so funny because he went on to say: ''You know, during the year we downplay it for you guys in the interleague series, and say it doesn't mean anything. And that time it would mean something.''</p>
        <p>And you could see that he was overwhelmed just by the thought of it. So I can't even imagine what's going to go through their minds when they take the field.</p>
        <p>CURRY -- The Mets are the team with less pressure on them because the Yankees are supposed to win. They've won two straight. They are going for something that has not happened since 1972, '73, '74, with the A's. And the Mets are the team that is still trying to catch up to that point.</p>
        <p>KEPNER -- If the Yankees win, and they're expected to win, the Mets are just another foe they've trampled in their path here the last few years.</p>
        <p>But if the Mets win, it's their first World Series, obviously, since '86. And to do it against the Yankees would seem to trump all of the Yankees' championships because none of those came against the Mets.</p>
        <p>So you'd have these arguments going back and forth. The Yankee fans would say, ''Well, so what? We lost to you. We've won 25; you've won three. We've won three in the last five years; you've only won once.'' And the Mets would say, ''Yeah, well, you've never beat us.''</p>
        <p>So there's a lot of bragging rights at stake certainly. But that's all perception. To the players themselves and the teams involved, I really don't think that matters except perhaps to the owners -- well, definitely to the owners. Fred Wilpon was positioning himself as the little guys in Queens just trying to live up to and emulate the mighty Yankees. And that was a great position to take in public, but we know what Mr. Steinbrenner thinks over there in the Bronx. I don't think he's looking at it the same way publicly or privately.</p>
        <p>CURRY -- Derek Jeter and Joe Torre talked about this being the type of Series that could split up families. I do believe that that is the case because we all know that there are thousands if not millions of households around New York where you have one Yankee fan, one Met fan, or a collection of Yankee fans teaming against one Met fan. It's going to be two weeks of mayhem. We're going to have a lot of back and forth. Get that one game and you're the guy who can brag the next morning.</p>
        <p>CHASS -- I have experienced this for quite some time with friends and acquaintances of mine, some of whom are Mets fans, some are Yankee fans, very zealous fans. And they go at each other constantly. It became a day-by-day thing if the Yankees won the night before and the Mets lost, the Yankee fans would get all over the Mets. If it were the reverse, the same thing would happen with the Mets fans getting on the Yankees fans. So it's very spirited. I just hope it doesn't get out of hand where people take it too seriously. Because we've heard crazy things happening during Super Bowls and such that I just hope this doesn't happen in New York.</p>
        <p>And I must say that the person who will probably have the most extreme reaction would not be a fan but the owner of the Yankees. If the Mets lose, Wilpon and Doubleday will take this in a classy way. They'll be disappointed, but that'll be the end of it. If the Yankees were to lose to the Mets in the World Series, the first one they've ever played, I would just have to remember that George Steinbrenner became enraged when the Yankees would lose to the Mets in exhibition games in Florida in spring training.</p>
        <p>There are many examples of things that happened, including the time that he followed Billy Martin into the clubhouse after a game and Billy Martin wanted to get away from him, so he went to the trainer's room and George followed him to the trainer's room and there was this big tub of water and ice on the trainer's table and Steinbrenner, for emphasis making a point, and he pounded the table and knocked the bucket, the tub of ice water all over Gabe Paul, the team president.</p>
        <p>That's something the Yankees will have to fear. And maybe that will drive them, as good as they are, to make them even better.</p>
        <p>OLNEY -- From the Yankees' perspective, a big thing for them will be to try to take care of Timo Perez. I would suspect that the Yankees are going to do what other teams probably didn't know Timo Perez well enough to try to do, which is to see if Timo Perez will swing at anything within six feet of the strike zone. I'd be shocked if he got a strike. I wouldn't be surprised if in Game 2, Clemens buzzes him.</p>
        <p>It will be interesting to see how the Mets react with the Yankees having more time to prepare their scouting reports on the hitters. One big difference between the teams, and we'll see how this manifests itself, is the Yankees players have all been a number of times in the World Series. We're going to see how Armando Benitez reacts, how Mike Piazza reacts, how John Franco, Timo Perez. It's going to be a great dynamic.</p>
        <p>As recently as two days ago I would have agreed that the Yankees have more to lose than the Mets and that the Yankees are sort of the team that doesn't really have anything to gain by winning the World Series. I'm beginning to think now the fact that the Yankees came back so far from the dead at the end of the regular season, that they're starting to play with a real abandon. I don't think they're feeling any pressure. In a sense they're starting to feel like, ''Hey, we're just starting to hit our stride right now.''</p>
        <p>KEPNER -- It will be interesting to watch the way the Yankees react to Mike Hampton and Al Leiter. The Mets' one-two combination is rounding into form at the best time. Yet, the Yankees have so much success against left-handers, especially Leiter. And they've had success against the Yankees with Hampton. It's going to be tough for the Yankees to handle Leiter and Hampton. That will be, considering they're starting four of the first six games, probably the key to the Series.</p>
        <p>CHASS -- We have to watch for the unexpected. The Mets could go into the World Series having no thoughts of gaining revenge, of getting even or whatever, and then something could trigger it. Look at what Jay Payton did in the last inning of the last game of the League Championship Series. He's hit by a pitch, hit in the helmet, and no question it had to hurt. But without thinking where he is, what the situation is, he jumps up and immediately charges the mound. You can't do that when you're three outs away from going to the World Series. You don't take a chance on injuring yourself or getting some of your teammates injured in a stupid fight. That sort of thing could happen.</p>
        <p>And I don't think there's any question that no matter where Clemens pitches that he will knock somebody down. He did it against Seattle with Alex Rodriguez, twice. That's the way he tries to intimidate a team's best hitter. And will he do it with Piazza again? Well, it would be interesting if he threw one up and in with a little better control.</p>
        <p>CURRY -- The dynamic obviously changes if he does what you said. He came in tight on A-Rod. They started screaming from the Mariners' dugout; people started booing. What did Clemens do? Came right back with the same pitch again.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CHASS -- Over the years, there have been very few seasons, if any, where the Mets and the Yankees have both been good enough to reach the playoffs. For a while, it was the Yankees and then the Mets, and back to the Yankees, and then the Mets again. So they never had this opportunity.</p>
        <p>But now they've both done it and, I can't say that I feel it was inevitable because it's not in baseball. There are just too many things that can happen. Look at the Atlanta Braves, how often they get to the postseason. They've won nine consecutive division championships and they are not in the World Series. They didn't get past the first round this year. If they had, maybe the Mets wouldn't be in the World Series to have a Subway Series.</p>
        <p>CURRY -- What makes this more refreshing, too, is, as silly as this may sound since the Yankees were the defending champions and the Mets had a very good team, is that in a way this is still surprising. Last year, there was a lot of talk about it and people expected it. And then when the Mets lost to the Braves, there was a deflating feeling in baseball. That, ''Oh, it didn't happen. Who knows when it's going to happen again?''</p>
        <p>And because of those lousy Septembers that the Mets and the Yankees had, we didn't hear a lot of Subway Series talk. We certainly didn't hear as much as we had heard in 1999.</p>
        <p>OLNEY -- On Sept. 10, I absolutely thought that it was going to happen and then on Sept. 30, I thought there was absolutely no way it would happen after watching the Yankees struggle through the end of the year. After watching the Yankees win Game 3 against Seattle, I said, ''Oh my goodness, here we go.''</p>
        <p>I remember having a conversation with Paul O'Neill with about six weeks to play. And I said, ''You know, Paul, the Mets are playing great and you guys are doing well. I really think you guys are going to play a Subway Series.''</p>
        <p>And he looked at me and he goes: ''I just couldn't handle that. I just couldn't handle that,'' in the way that he talks. And it was so funny because he went on to say: ''You know, during the year we downplay it for you guys in the interleague series, and say it doesn't mean anything. And that time it would mean something.''</p>
        <p>And you could see that he was overwhelmed just by the thought of it. So I can't even imagine what's going to go through their minds when they take the field.</p>
        <p>CURRY -- The Mets are the team with less pressure on them because the Yankees are supposed to win. They've won two straight. They are going for something that has not happened since 1972, '73, '74, with the A's. And the Mets are the team that is still trying to catch up to that point.</p>
        <p>KEPNER -- If the Yankees win, and they're expected to win, the Mets are just another foe they've trampled in their path here the last few years.</p>
        <p>But if the Mets win, it's their first World Series, obviously, since '86. And to do it against the Yankees would seem to trump all of the Yankees' championships because none of those came against the Mets.</p>
        <p>So you'd have these arguments going back and forth. The Yankee fans would say, ''Well, so what? We lost to you. We've won 25; you've won three. We've won three in the last five years; you've only won once.'' And the Mets would say, ''Yeah, well, you've never beat us.''</p>
        <p>So there's a lot of bragging rights at stake certainly. But that's all perception. To the players themselves and the teams involved, I really don't think that matters except perhaps to the owners -- well, definitely to the owners. Fred Wilpon was positioning himself as the little guys in Queens just trying to live up to and emulate the mighty Yankees. And that was a great position to take in public, but we know what Mr. Steinbrenner thinks over there in the Bronx. I don't think he's looking at it the same way publicly or privately.</p>
        <p>CURRY -- Derek Jeter and Joe Torre talked about this being the type of Series that could split up families. I do believe that that is the case because we all know that there are thousands if not millions of households around New York where you have one Yankee fan, one Met fan, or a collection of Yankee fans teaming against one Met fan. It's going to be two weeks of mayhem. We're going to have a lot of back and forth. Get that one game and you're the guy who can brag the next morning.</p>
        <p>CHASS -- I have experienced this for quite some time with friends and acquaintances of mine, some of whom are Mets fans, some are Yankee fans, very zealous fans. And they go at each other constantly. It became a day-by-day thing if the Yankees won the night before and the Mets lost, the Yankee fans would get all over the Mets. If it were the reverse, the same thing would happen with the Mets fans getting on the Yankees fans. So it's very spirited. I just hope it doesn't get out of hand where people take it too seriously. Because we've heard crazy things happening during Super Bowls and such that I just hope this doesn't happen in New York.</p>
        <p>And I must say that the person who will probably have the most extreme reaction would not be a fan but the owner of the Yankees. If the Mets lose, Wilpon and Doubleday will take this in a classy way. They'll be disappointed, but that'll be the end of it. If the Yankees were to lose to the Mets in the World Series, the first one they've ever played, I would just have to remember that George Steinbrenner became enraged when the Yankees would lose to the Mets in exhibition games in Florida in spring training.</p>
        <p>There are many examples of things that happened, including the time that he followed Billy Martin into the clubhouse after a game and Billy Martin wanted to get away from him, so he went to the trainer's room and George followed him to the trainer's room and there was this big tub of water and ice on the trainer's table and Steinbrenner, for emphasis making a point, and he pounded the table and knocked the bucket, the tub of ice water all over Gabe Paul, the team president.</p>
        <p>That's something the Yankees will have to fear. And maybe that will drive them, as good as they are, to make them even better.</p>
        <p>OLNEY -- From the Yankees' perspective, a big thing for them will be to try to take care of Timo Perez. I would suspect that the Yankees are going to do what other teams probably didn't know Timo Perez well enough to try to do, which is to see if Timo Perez will swing at anything within six feet of the strike zone. I'd be shocked if he got a strike. I wouldn't be surprised if in Game 2, Clemens buzzes him.</p>
        <p>It will be interesting to see how the Mets react with the Yankees having more time to prepare their scouting reports on the hitters. One big difference between the teams, and we'll see how this manifests itself, is the Yankees players have all been a number of times in the World Series. We're going to see how Armando Benitez reacts, how Mike Piazza reacts, how John Franco, Timo Perez. It's going to be a great dynamic.</p>
        <p>As recently as two days ago I would have agreed that the Yankees have more to lose than the Mets and that the Yankees are sort of the team that doesn't really have anything to gain by winning the World Series. I'm beginning to think now the fact that the Yankees came back so far from the dead at the end of the regular season, that they're starting to play with a real abandon. I don't think they're feeling any pressure. In a sense they're starting to feel like, ''Hey, we're just starting to hit our stride right now.''</p>
        <p>KEPNER -- It will be interesting to watch the way the Yankees react to Mike Hampton and Al Leiter. The Mets' one-two combination is rounding into form at the best time. Yet, the Yankees have so much success against left-handers, especially Leiter. And they've had success against the Yankees with Hampton. It's going to be tough for the Yankees to handle Leiter and Hampton. That will be, considering they're starting four of the first six games, probably the key to the Series.</p>
        <p>CHASS -- We have to watch for the unexpected. The Mets could go into the World Series having no thoughts of gaining revenge, of getting even or whatever, and then something could trigger it. Look at what Jay Payton did in the last inning of the last game of the League Championship Series. He's hit by a pitch, hit in the helmet, and no question it had to hurt. But without thinking where he is, what the situation is, he jumps up and immediately charges the mound. You can't do that when you're three outs away from going to the World Series. You don't take a chance on injuring yourself or getting some of your teammates injured in a stupid fight. That sort of thing could happen.</p>
        <p>And I don't think there's any question that no matter where Clemens pitches that he will knock somebody down. He did it against Seattle with Alex Rodriguez, twice. That's the way he tries to intimidate a team's best hitter. And will he do it with Piazza again? Well, it would be interesting if he threw one up and in with a little better control.</p>
        <p>CURRY -- The dynamic obviously changes if he does what you said. He came in tight on A-Rod. They started screaming from the Mariners' dugout; people started booing. What did Clemens do? Came right back with the same pitch again.</p>
        <p>BACK TALK With New York poised for its first Subway Series in 44 years, the four baseball writers for The New York Times, Murray Chass, Jack Curry, Buster Olney and Tyler Kepner, discussed the occasion, the teams, players and strategies.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">With New York poised for its first Subway Series in 44 years, the four baseball writers for The New York Times, Murray Chass, Jack Curry, Buster Olney and Tyler Kepner, discussed the occasion, the teams, players and strategies.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
