<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Child's World In No Man's Land</title>
    <meta content="22MALA$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/22/arts/22MALA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240691"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FILM"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Malanowski, Jamie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Green, David Gordon</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Evanofski, Candace</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holden, Donald</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">George Washington (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001022T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DEFDC173EF931A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1961" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Child's World In No Man's Land</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMIE MALANOWSKI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Malanowski, Jamie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jamie Malanowski reviews movie George Washington, written and directed by David Gordon Green and starring Candace Evanofski and Donald Holden; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE first thing you ought to know about ''George Washington'' -- the first clue that this is a film that isn't much interested in being about the obvious -- is that it is not at all about the Father of Our Country. In fact, it is a film that is mostly about 11- and 12-year-old children, poor and undersupervised, who spend large portions of their days in the dilapidated ruins of a factory in their rural Southern town, mulling their horizons. It is true that a central character is named George, and though his last name is not Washington, another character says she thinks of him as George Washington. Perhaps you are getting a feel for the patient way this film meditates on the subjects that cross its mind.</p>
        <p>''George Washington,'' which opens Friday, was written and directed by David Gordon Green, who is 25 and pretty nearly the definition of a beardless youth.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE first thing you ought to know about ''George Washington'' -- the first clue that this is a film that isn't much interested in being about the obvious -- is that it is not at all about the Father of Our Country. In fact, it is a film that is mostly about 11- and 12-year-old children, poor and undersupervised, who spend large portions of their days in the dilapidated ruins of a factory in their rural Southern town, mulling their horizons. It is true that a central character is named George, and though his last name is not Washington, another character says she thinks of him as George Washington. Perhaps you are getting a feel for the patient way this film meditates on the subjects that cross its mind.</p>
        <p>''George Washington,'' which opens Friday, was written and directed by David Gordon Green, who is 25 and pretty nearly the definition of a beardless youth.</p>
        <p>This is his first feature, and it has been winning acclaim at film festivals in Berlin, Newport, R.I. (where it was awarded the top prize), Toronto (where it was co-winner of the Discovery Award) and New York. Most critics have been enthusiastic. Roger Ebert of The Chicago Sun-Times said that ''it's original in every atom of its being''; Kenneth Turan of The Los Angeles Times called it ''languidly beautiful,'' and in The New York Times, Elvis Mitchell likened it to ''a fairly tale by Faulkner.'' But the praise has not been unanimous: ''Turn up your over-hype alert,'' Owen Gleiberman warned in Entertainment Weekly, finding the film pretentious.</p>
        <p>The movie is like one of those deep, prolonged dreams in which moods, images and bizarre moments, though unstructured, nonetheless hang together in a kind of logical continuity. The story is told through the eyes of Nasia (Candace Evanofski), a 12-year-old who drops her boyfriend when she becomes attracted to George (Donald Holden), an introverted boy who wears an old football helmet to protect his brain because the plates of his skull had never come together. There is a tragic accident, after which George becomes a hero. But every time the film seems to tilt into straightforwardness, something pops up to interfere: a boy sings his disturbed mother to sleep with the theme from ''Blazing Saddles''; a boy includes on his list of heroes the name of the basketball player World B. Free and the baseball player Dick Allen, both of whose playing days ended nearly 20 years ago.</p>
        <p>All in all, the film is less a story than an observation of character and a meditation on events. ''I write scripts for action movies that abide by the structures and rhythms of the Hollywood blockbuster,'' Mr. Green said in an interview in New York recently. ''But I also have films like ''George Washington' that I write, that are from a stream of consciousness, that evolve from sketch pads of characters and moods and thoughts I keep, sketch diaries of pictures and places, photographs, cutouts from magazines, a collage of ideas.''</p>
        <p>One of the film's most impressive features, and one which adds to the dreaminess, is Mr. Green's use of landscape. In the ruined factory in North Carolina where much of the film takes place, the tumbled brick and twisted beams meet overgrown bushes in a surreal no man's land in a war between industry and nature. It's not surprising that when asked to list his favorite movies, he mentions ''Badlands,''  ''Deliverance,''  ''McCabe and Mrs. Miller,''  ''Never Cry Wolf,''  ''The Black Stallion,''  ''Lawrence of Arabia'' and ''Dr. Zhivago'' -- films in which landscapes are key parts of the experience.</p>
        <p>''I love films where the location of the film is a character in the film,'' Mr. Green said. ''Like when you think of 'Giant' -- do you really think of the characters first, or do you think of that house on that amazing landscape?''</p>
        <p>Even more impressive are the performances of the young actors. Unlike most child actors, they underplay their scenes, lending the film an offhand, unstudied feel. To hear Mr. Green tell it, acting talent in North Carolina is as plentiful as scrub pine. ''I found the kids all over the place,'' he said. ''I found Candace from hanging out in a barber shop. A friend of mine who cuts kids' hair said come in and talk to this girl. And Candace just had this amazing charisma, this very realistic but stunning beauty, and was at the same time down to earth and not possessed of the staginess so many kid actors have. Other kids I met when I volunteered at teen centers throughout the area. I tried to get on a basketball team, play games with these kids, see them without having an open casting call.</p>
        <p>''I wanted to find kids I thought would be cool, and that had personalities and who weren't necessarily trying to sculpt themselves to my needs.</p>
        <p>''I wanted to find kids who could say more than that their idols were Michael Jordan, who had something new to say, who weren't just going to have the traditional vulgarities of 14-year-old kids.''</p>
        <p>Partly to save money and partly to create an intimate atmosphere, the cast and crew all lived together while on location. ''We rented a big house and set it up like summer camp, four to a room,'' Mr. Green said. ''It was mildly claustrophobic but intensely intimate.'' Mr. Green further eased his performers by getting the actors' input and rewriting the dialogue in their own words. ''The kids were into the fact that I wasn't feeding them line readings, and was leaving it up to them where to put inflections.''</p>
        <p>The rapport led to some of the strongest moments in the movie, among them the immediately involving opening shot of the movie, in which a girl and a boy -- Ms. Evanofski and Curtis Cotton 3rd -- are sitting in a tight, undefined space, and she's breaking up with him. ''The scene was based on a relationship that was happening off the set, during the production, between the actual actors,'' said Mr. Green. ''And it was getting to the point where it was actually affecting Curtis's performance. So I talked to him about what we could do. And he said, 'Turn the camera on me, and I'll give her a piece of my mind.' So I talked to Candace about it, and she said, 'Let's see what he has to say, and I'll see what I can come up with.' I put them in a place where he couldn't escape and they couldn't do anything but look in each other's eyes, and when I said action, he just froze up. Who knows what he was going to say? What kind of attack? Instead, he just sat there in silence, until she finally says, 'Tell me that you love me.' And he just looks off to the wall.</p>
        <p>I  find that moment so genuine and almost ridiculously dramatic, because it was so much a part of the reality that we captured, and it was so much better than what I had written.''</p>
        <p>''David really knew how to reach those kids,'' said Tim Orr, the film's cinematographer, whose work has been praised. ''He would take them aside, talk to them, play them a piece of music he wanted them to think about. It was a very private thing, but then they'd come out and do the scene. It was a very loose set, like a party. One time he directed a scene in this really stupid pair of glasses we had around. Another time he just wore his underwear.''</p>
        <p>''I took advantage of the fact that the kids didn't know the textbook ways of acting to show them what I thought acting is, which is just a hair beyond the 'let's pretend' school of acting. I tried to get them to understand how I feel when I see Denzel Washington in 'The Hurricane,' which I find such a phony, false performance in which I see him overdramatize every line he says. Instead I showed one of them, Damian Jewan Lee, who plays Vernon, 'The Thin Blue Line,' because I wanted Vernon to be as devoid of hope as that man on death row was.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Green is a Texan and is sparely built. He speaks with an accent but with no drawl. He's as angular and fast-talking as Holly Hunter. His father is a dean at Southwestern Medical School in Georgetown, Tex., his mother is a Lamaze instructor, and his three sisters are all involved in science and medicine; he says he is the black sheep who never loved anything but film.</p>
        <p>He studied at the North Carolina School of the Arts in Winston-Salem; after graduation, he gave himself a year to raise enough money to shoot ''George Washington.'' He spent that year in Los Angeles, working ceaselessly, often three or four jobs at a time, scrimping to save every penny and then investing those pennies in the stock market, where the dot-com bubble was very helpful to his ambitions. He raised most of the money he needed and pleaded for the rest.</p>
        <p>''We got so many people to get behind this and donate equipment and facilities,'' he said, ''based on me and Tim Orr telling people what we wanted to do, which was make a low-budget film that is far on the other side of the planet from 'Clerks' and all these other low-budget independent films that come out, to which we find no emotional attraction at all. And people got behind us.''</p>
        <p>So far, the best part of the experience for Mr. Green has been showing ''George Washington'' in Winston-Salem, one of the places where it where it was filmed. ''We showed it in the churches and the teen centers, and it was just powerful,'' he said. ''The people didn't know what to expect, and to see the results so big and so loud, with music -- it was amazing. The kid who dies in the film was crying at his own death scene, and his mother was screaming. Afterwards I got this big bear hug from this Baptist preacher.''</p>
        <p>Not every film Mr. Green plans to make will be as delicate as ''George Washington.'' ''Ultimately I want to make epic westerns and costume dramas,'' he said, adding that he is currently passing around two screenplays, a love story and science fiction adventure. He says that in three years he'd like to be where Paul Thomas Anderson (''Boogie Nights,''  ''Magnolia'') is today, and that one day he'd like to open a film at Mann's Chinese Theater in Hollywood. But mostly he wants to be original.</p>
        <p>''I don't really want to spend a year of my life making something that I can summarize in 25 words or less,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Right now he lives on the road, in his truck. ''I haven't had a home in two years,'' he said. ''It has its good points and bad points, but I have my freedom, and I don't have any responsibilities. At least not beyond keeping my cell phone working. ''</p>
        <p>FILM Jamie Malanowski's most recent article for Arts &amp; Leisure was about the television show ''Jackass.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Jamie Malanowski's most recent article for Arts &amp; Leisure was about the television show ''Jackass.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
