<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Because of the Pitcher's Eyes</title>
    <meta content="22MCCO$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/22/opinion/22MCCO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20001025T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240963"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Houston Astros</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccourt, Frank</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Scott, Mike</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Houston Astros</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001022T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E1D6113EF931A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="722" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Because of the Pitcher's Eyes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Frank McCourt</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mccourt, Frank</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Frank McCourt Op-Ed article recalls watching 1986 National League playoff series in Lion's Head bar in Greenwich Village, when he became at least somewhat interested in baseball while watching eyes of Mike Scott as he pitched against New York Mets (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If he's around, I would like Mike Scott, formerly of the Houston Astros, to know about this. I would like him to know that because of his eyes I am somewhat interested in baseball, that I even watched a whole game on television when the Yankees finally clinched the game that sent them to the Subway Series.</p>
        <p>It was you, Mike, and this is how it happened.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If he's around, I would like Mike Scott, formerly of the Houston Astros, to know about this. I would like him to know that because of his eyes I am somewhat interested in baseball, that I even watched a whole game on television when the Yankees finally clinched the game that sent them to the Subway Series.</p>
        <p>It was you, Mike, and this is how it happened.</p>
        <p>In October 1986, they were talking baseball at the Lion's Head bar in Greenwich Village -- Vic Siegel, Pete Hamill, Tommy Butler -- experts. They always talked baseball in October, and I didn't care because I didn't know the difference between a bunt and an R.B.I. I had grown up in Ireland with soccer, hurling, Gaelic football, rugby -- games that moved, man. I couldn't understand these American games, football and baseball, where they stopped for a conference every few minutes before they decided on the next move. Why couldn't they just get on with it? If they stopped like that in Limerick, things would be thrown -- insults about the players' mothers, any object at hand.</p>
        <p>The Experts -- Siegel, Hamill, Butler -- would pause to check up on whatever game was on television. There was no way of knowing if they liked what they saw since they all seemed to have attended the same academy of inscrutability. Tommy Butler would refill my beer glass and remark on the nice day outside but you could see his heart wasn't in the weather, that he was glad to return to baseball. At other times we would talk about jazz or the state of the world, but this was October and I might as well have had a communicable disease.</p>
        <p>I'd like to have joined The Experts as they summoned up ghosts of Octobers past, as they employed their remarkable memories to recall statistics and moves from games 50 years ago. Despite my ignorance of the game, its starting and stopping and gawking and tugging and chewing and spitting, I knew there was something in the air. You couldn't escape the headlines: the Mets were on the march and that, surely is what lay below the surface of The Experts' priestly talks. The New York Mets.</p>
        <p>But up there on the television a pair of eyes, the deadliest eyes I'd ever seen, a gunslinger's eyes. I ask Tommy Butler, ''Who's that?''</p>
        <p>''Mike Scott, Houston Astros.''</p>
        <p>His face fills the screen and his stare is enough to scorch anything in its way. He's staring at the batter, or is it the catcher? How am I to know? I can't ask The Experts for fear there might be pity for my ignorance. The catcher's fingers move. Mike Scott's eyes say ''no,'' and that's the moment of my conversion. He throws the ball and I don't care where it goes or what the other team is.</p>
        <p>Oh, I thought. So that's what it's all about. From Mike Scott's eyes an intimation of why there had to be a stopping and a starting, an epiphany that in the next few weeks helped me understand the battle between the Boston Red Sox and the Mets.</p>
        <p>Of course I wanted the Mets to win, and for a very simple reason: There were people I disliked who were Yankee fans, and I wanted them brought low. Of course I knew the Yankees weren't in the Series, but I had no doubt they were sneering at the Mets and rooting for the Red Sox. I wanted those Yankee fans to get their comeuppance.</p>
        <p>Now it's different. I am still an ignorant baseball fan, though learning more and more from my wife, Ellen, who, I'm sorry to say, is a Yankee fan. We are to baseball what James Carville and Mary Matalin are to politics. She loves the glamour and high elegance of the Yankees. I admire the come-from-behind rough and tumble of the Mets.</p>
        <p>To Mike Scott, wherever you are, thanks for the moment.</p>
        <p>Warm wishes to my wife and her fellow Yankee fans, but remember what Shakespeare said: ''Uneasy lies the head that wears a crown.''</p>
        <p>Frank McCourt is the author of ''Angela's Ashes'' and '' 'Tis.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  October 25, 2000, Wednesday  An Oct. 22 Op-Ed misspelled the name of a Daily News sportswriter; his name is Vic Ziegel, not Siegel.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: October 25, 2000, Wednesday</p>
        <p>An Oct. 22 Op-Ed misspelled the name of a Daily News sportswriter; his name is Vic Ziegel, not Siegel.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Frank McCourt is the author of ''Angela's Ashes'' and '' 'Tis.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
