<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Graying of the Arts: Who Will Take Over?</title>
    <meta content="22AGE.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240743"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Age, Chronological</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Delatiner, Barbara</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Age, Chronological</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001022T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E2DD153EF931A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1676" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Graying of the Arts: Who Will Take Over?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA DELATINER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Delatiner, Barbara</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article explores challenges cultural groups around Long Island, NY, may face as founders grow older and seek replacements to carry on their work; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ABOUT 30 years ago, when the second wave of city dwellers migrated to Long Island, many of them discovered a cultural wasteland in suburbia. To fill the void, they founded groups like the New Community Cinema, the Long Island Baroque Ensemble, Friends of the Arts, the Islip Arts Council and the American Chamber Ensemble.</p>
        <p>The organizations they established are alive and well, but the founders, still very much in control of their babies, are starting to approach retirement age, raising questions about the future of these and other founder-driven groups on the Island.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ABOUT 30 years ago, when the second wave of city dwellers migrated to Long Island, many of them discovered a cultural wasteland in suburbia. To fill the void, they founded groups like the New Community Cinema, the Long Island Baroque Ensemble, Friends of the Arts, the Islip Arts Council and the American Chamber Ensemble.</p>
        <p>The organizations they established are alive and well, but the founders, still very much in control of their babies, are starting to approach retirement age, raising questions about the future of these and other founder-driven groups on the Island.</p>
        <p>What will happen when Charlotte Sky and Vic Skolnick of the New Community Cinema, now the Cinema Arts Center, step down? Or when Sonia Grib leaves  the Baroque Ensemble? Or when Teddy Bookman of Friends of the Arts, Lillian Barbash of the Islip Arts Council and Blanche Abram and Naomi Drucker of the American Chamber Ensemble depart?</p>
        <p>Are the groups preparing for futures without the people who nurtured them? Can these dynamic, committed visionaries be replaced, especially now that arts professionals expect more than the token salaries that most of these founders earn? Are boards in place that will provide continuity and oversee smooth transitions?</p>
        <p>Or will these groups and others like them go the way of the Sea Cliff Chamber Players, a pioneering regional performing-arts group founded in 1970? After the death of its co-founder Herbert Sucoff in 1996 -- and despite the continued leadership of his wife and co-founder, Barbara Speer -- the troupe disbanded in 1998. The National Grand Opera folded during the 1995 season after its founder and main benefactor, Michael Scuderi, died.</p>
        <p>The situation on Long Island is not an isolated phenomenon, of course. While the New York State Council on the Arts has not conducted a formal study of the ''graying out'' of local leadership, anecdotal information pointed  to ''successorship problems and suggesting that we were reaching a point when this generational problem would become real and important,'' said Nicolette B. Clarke, the council's executive director.</p>
        <p>''True, there's the question of whether an institution should live beyond its founder,'' she said. ''The love and passion of one person may not be shared by the next. But then again, maybe the groups should survive if they are supplying a specific need in a community.</p>
        <p>''So we're committed to trying to see what role we might have, what technical assistance we could provide to help these founder-driven groups survive internally and externally,'' Ms. Clarke said. ''They can't start planning for a transition too soon.''</p>
        <p>In ''Renewing Nysca: A Five Year View, 1999-2003,'' a long-range plan that the council has adopted, continuity is considered a priority for community  groups, and the council pledges its support in planning for smooth transitions.</p>
        <p>The seven arts leaders on Long Island are determined to see their dreams continue. With the help of active boards that have taken on some leadership roles in organizations still very much founder-driven, some of the groups have actively begun planning for the future. And some haven't.</p>
        <p>Shirley Blanc Romaine, co-chairwoman of the Cinema Arts Center's board, talked about the center's  founders, Mr. Skolnick, 71, and his wife, Ms. Sky, 69.  ''The Cinema is so identified with Vic and Charlotte -- they are so at the heart of everything here -- that it's going to be very hard to even address the possibility of replacing them,'' she said. ''The subject of their retirement and successor hasn't come up, but I guess it eventually will.''</p>
        <p>The center, in Huntington, began in 1973 and grew from humble roots: the founders borrowed a copy of  ''Lilith,'' Robert Rossen's 1964 film, from the Huntington library and screened it for 40 people on a sheet hung from a dance studio ceiling. Now, after its latest expansion, the center has three theaters, a multipurpose room, a landscaped Cinema Garden, an annual budget of $1.3 million and 7 full-time and 10 part-time employees. Last year it sold about 200,000 tickets.</p>
        <p>Although the subject of succession has not been directly addressed at the Cinema Arts Center, it has been -- up to a point -- at the Islip Arts Council. The council has been closely  linked to Lillian Barbash, now 73,  since 1976 when she joined its board. Ms. Barbash -- almost single-handedly, her admirers say -- turned a moribund group that had not even spent its $5,000 town allocation into an organization with an annual budget of $350,000. It presents a chamber music series and free concerts throughout the year, including a  parks concert by the New York Philharmonic.</p>
        <p>About four years ago, bowing to the calendar and with the approval of her board, Ms. Barbash began training her assistant, Dawn Kraus, 27, to take her place. ''I have no plans to retire,'' Ms. Barbash said. ''But it's comforting to know that Dawn will be ready to step in in case of an emergency or if and when I do decide to leave.''</p>
        <p>At Friends of the Arts, the subject of a successor is only a glimmer in Teddy Bookman's eye. Friends, with a current budget of $1.5 million and a staff of six, now concentrates on presenting chamber music concerts,  children's events, a summer festival of mostly pop music at Planting Fields Arboretum and an extensive arts-in-education program.</p>
        <p>Ms. Bookman, who would not give her age, founded Friends in 1972 and has been its executive director ever since. Retirement is not a word in her vocabulary, she said, but she added that she has thought about hiring an associate executive director who could ''be groomed to share responsibilities'' and help make a ''smooth transition.''</p>
        <p>''But that is just a thought, not a reality,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Even in cases where the founders concede that they may have to turn over the reins, replacing them will not be easy. Directors of small community organizations do not earn the kind of salaries that executives in the arts now command.</p>
        <p>For example, at the Islip Arts Council, Ms. Barbash handles most of the programming, the fund-raising and the day-to-day activities. Her salary is $30,000 a year, which she donates back to the council.</p>
        <p>All of the full-timers on the Cinema Arts Center's payroll, including Mr. Skolnick and Ms. Sky, earn $28,500 a year. ''We've lost people in the past who just couldn't or wouldn't work for that kind of money, especially on Long Island, where housing is such a problem,'' Mr. Skolnick said.</p>
        <p>He and Ms. Sky do most of the programming along with overseeing the center's general operations. They insist they have no plans to retire, but someday, Ms. Sky said, they ''might like to take a day or two, or even a few weeks off.''</p>
        <p>They said that their son, Dylan Skolnick, 33, an associate programmer at the center, could take over when they retire. The goal is to find someone with comparable dedication to their philosophy of ''making entertainment more than just filling up a few hours of a person's time,'' Ms. Sky said. To Ms. Abram and Ms. Drucker of the American Chamber Ensemble, finding a musically kindred spirit to succeed them was the most important consideration.</p>
        <p>The two women, who teach at Hofstra University, ''never speak about age,'' Ms. Drucker said. They met at a concert 36 years ago, and they wanted to perform chamber music -- Ms. Abram is a pianist and Ms. Drucker a clarinetist -- without having to ''travel all over the place because we had young children,'' Ms. Abram said, so they created the chamber ensemble, which varies from four to eight musicians, depending on the program.</p>
        <p>It has a current budget of $30,000 and draws audiences of more than 200 people to each of the six to eight concerts it gives every year on the Island and in Manhattan. The ensemble frequently commissions works and now records regularly.</p>
        <p>Years ago, the founders said, they realized that they would retire someday, so they began looking for a successor. They settled on Ms. Abram's protege, Marilyn Sherman Lehman, a pianist who performs with the ensemble. They believe, Ms. Abram said, that she ''will continue the same sense of artistry, the same sensitivity that guides us.''</p>
        <p>Not that they are planning to retire. ''We're not ready to go yet,'' Ms. Drucker said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Abram added: ''Sure, normal people retire at my age. Pianists are not normal people. But we'll know when it's time.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Grib of the Long Island Baroque Ensemble has seen her group grow into a cultural fixture since she and a coterie of other musicians  founded it in 1969. The ensemble, now composed entirely of professional musicians like Ms. Grib, a harpsichordist, performs six programs a year in Nassau and Suffolk and has  an annual budget of $50,000.</p>
        <p>''There will come a time, for sure, when I will have to think about retiring,'' said Ms. Grib, 64. ''But not for a while, I hope. My creative juices are still flowing.''</p>
        <p>Recently, the ensemble hired a consultant, Patricia Berman, the associate director of the Alliance of New York State Arts Organizations, to serve as a paid part-time administrator. And Ms. Grib, who said that she draws ''a nominal salary'' as both a performer and artistic director, said a number of musicians who regularly appear with the group could take over her role.</p>
        <p>''We're the only professional ensemble on Long Island that does early music on period instruments,'' she said. ''And that's the important thing. It's important that the music go on, not the same people doing it.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
