<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Home Is Damaged After a Mercury Spill</title>
    <meta content="22MERC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240711"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mercury (Metal)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hazardous and Toxic Substances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Tarrytown (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giampiccolo, Susan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giampiccolo, Frank</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Worth, Robert</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/Upstate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hazardous and Toxic Substances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Metals and Minerals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001022T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E1D8143EF931A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1344" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Home Is Damaged After a Mercury Spill</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT WORTH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Worth, Robert</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on mercury spill and vaporization in basement of Frank and Susan Giampiccolo's home in Tarrytown, NY, during routine pressure test of gas lines following costly home renovation; family was forced to evacuate and much of their contaminated furniture and clothing has been destroyed; similar spills that have occurred across country noted; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN mercury spilled in the basement of Frank and Susan Giampiccolo's home in Tarrytown, N.Y., in August during a routine pressure test of the gas lines, it became a homeowner's nightmare.</p>
        <p>The family had just finished a costly renovation to their two-story house, but after the spill the County Health Department found high levels of vaporized mercury -- a dangerous neurotoxin -- in their home. The Giampiccolos and their three young children were forced to evacuate at once. Weeks later, they are still living in a rented one-bedroom apartment and much of their contaminated furniture and clothing has been destroyed, the family's lawyer, Joshua J. Grauer, said. County officials said the family should be able to move back soon.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN mercury spilled in the basement of Frank and Susan Giampiccolo's home in Tarrytown, N.Y., in August during a routine pressure test of the gas lines, it became a homeowner's nightmare.</p>
        <p>The family had just finished a costly renovation to their two-story house, but after the spill the County Health Department found high levels of vaporized mercury -- a dangerous neurotoxin -- in their home. The Giampiccolos and their three young children were forced to evacuate at once. Weeks later, they are still living in a rented one-bedroom apartment and much of their contaminated furniture and clothing has been destroyed, the family's lawyer, Joshua J. Grauer, said. County officials said the family should be able to move back soon.</p>
        <p>But the spill in the Giampiccolos' home was far from an isolated event, scientists said. Without anyone recognizing the risk, similar toxic spills have been occurring in basements all over the country for decades because of the widespread use of mercury in pressure gauges and gas regulators.</p>
        <p>Although mercury has long been recognized as a dangerous toxin, government officials and environmentalists are generally unaware of the risk posed by gauges and regulators containing mercury, said Gina Solomon, a senior scientist at the Natural Resources Defense Council. The federal Environmental Protection Agency does not generally require mercury spills under one pound to be reported, and the amounts in these spills are smaller than that.</p>
        <p>But a recent mercury-poisoning scare in Chicago may provide a taste of what could happen here if evidence of more spills is found. On July 20, a homeowner in a Chicago suburb found mercury in his basement after a gas meter, equipped with a regulator containing mercury, was removed. Since then, gas companies in Illinois have begun inspecting some 300,000 homes where similar gas meters have been replaced. Mercury has been found in 300 homes so far.</p>
        <p>The Tarrytown spill has already prompted White Plains to ban mercury testing of gas lines, and other communities may soon follow suit, said Robert W. Dapice, the city's chief plumbing inspector.</p>
        <p>''There is clearly a systemic problem,'' said Richard L. Brodsky, a Westchester assemblyman, who is sponsoring a bill to require that mercury gauges be replaced with nonmercury alternatives.</p>
        <p>Unlike New York, Connecticut has statewide regulations on pressure tests, and those regulations do not require that mercury gauges be used, said Robert Lesser, mechanical inspector for the City of Hartford. Jane Stahl, the deputy commissioner of the State Department of Environmental Protection, said she was not aware of any mercury spills from pressure tests.</p>
        <p>The spill in the Giampiccolo basement occurred when the gas lines were tested for adequate pressure using a portable gauge called a manometer -- a standard check that is mandated throughout the country.</p>
        <p>Although mercury manometers are being phased out in some areas, a number of Westchester towns, including Tarrytown, specifically require mercury tests before gas service can be turned on or after renovations, said Mario Bruni, the president of Independent Master Plumbers of Westchester, a trade association.</p>
        <p>If the test is not performed properly, the mercury in the manometer can burst up through the vial that contains it, spilling onto the floor.</p>
        <p>The amount of mercury in one commercially available manometer is about 88 grams, or just under two ounces. ''That is more than sufficient to overexpose people to a deadly toxin,'' said Dr. Clyde Johnson, an assistant professor and mercury researcher at Medgar Evers College of the City University of New York. It is particularly dangerous to children and pregnant women, because even small amounts of mercury can cause serious developmental problems, he said.</p>
        <p>''The liability is great,'' Mr. Dapice, the White Plains plumbing inspector said, ''and mercury spills can happen very easily, because of the fragility of these devices.''</p>
        <p>Spills can also occur when gas regulators containing mercury, which were commonly installed in surburban houses until about 1960, are replaced. Consolidated Edison has been replacing 1,500 regulators a year in Westchester and Queens since 1997, and there have been about 18 spills a year, said D. Joy Faber, a spokeswoman for Con Ed. All the spills were cleaned up without injury to the people in the buildings, she said.</p>
        <p>In Connecticut, only one of the state's three major gas companies -- Yankee Gas Services Company -- has mercury-containing gas regulators in the homes it services, said Nancy Andrews, a spokeswoman for the Department of Public Utility Control. The company has been gradually replacing them since the 1970's, and there are between 200 and 300 left, said Sandy St. Pierre, a spokeswoman for Yankee. There have been no reported spills during the removals, she added.</p>
        <p>It is difficult to tell how many spills have been caused by mercury gauges, which are far more widespread than the regulators, said Dr. Arnold Wendroff, a research associate at Brooklyn College's geology department, who has worked extensively on mercury poisoning. He has been concerned about the gauges since June, when his plumber casually mentioned that spills sometimes take place.</p>
        <p>Ms. Faber said Con Ed, however, had been aware of the risk since 1997, when it began urging plumbers not to use mercury gauges and asked the New York City Buildings Department to revise its code to allow nonmercury manometers for pressure testing.</p>
        <p>And early last month the Plumbing Foundation, a nonprofit group that oversees plumbing code and enforcement issues in New York City, sent a letter urging plumbers not to use mercury gauges, said the foundation's executive director, Stewart O'Brian. Mercury gauges sell for about $40, and nonmercury alternatives, known as digital or spring gauges, cost about $55.</p>
        <p>In January 1999 the New York City Buildings Department changed its policy to allow the use of nonmercury manometers, a spokeswoman, Ilyse Fink, said.</p>
        <p>The Giampiccolos are considering litigation against Tarrytown on the ground that it required the mercury test, even though safer alternatives are available, Mr. Grauer said. They are also suing the plumbers responsible for the spill, Thomas Treacy Contractors of Valhalla, and their subcontractor, C. N. Mechanical of Yonkers. Calls to the plumbers were not returned.</p>
        <p>Mr. Giampiccolo, a Tarrytown police officer, was home with his three children -- ages 12, 11 and 10 --  during the accident. A blood test taken afterward showed elevated levels of mercury in his blood, but his health does not appear to have been affected, Mr. Grauer, his lawyer, said. The children, who were not as close to the accident, were also tested but had normal mercury levels.</p>
        <p>Mr. Giampiccolo was in the basement helping the plumbers when the gauge ruptured. Mercury shot up to the ceiling and rained down onto the men, Mr. Grauer said. The plumbers then tried to vacuum up the mercury with a commercial vacuum cleaner, which vaporized it and spread it throughout the basement, making it far more dangerous.</p>
        <p>The plumbers should have contacted the regional office of the State Department of Environmental Conservation, which would have gotten a qualified technician to supervise the cleanup, Dan Farrell, a department spokesman, said.</p>
        <p>Elemental mercury, a silvery-white metal, which is liquid at room temperature, is not easily absorbed by the skin. But when vaporized it can be breathed in and may cause a range of effects, from tremors and nausea at low levels of exposure to irreversible brain and kidney damage at high levels.</p>
        <p>When the County Health Department first tested the Giampiccolo house on the day of the spill, ''the levels overwhelmed the instrumentation -- they were in the hundreds of micrograms per cubic meter of air,'' said a spokeswoman, Mary Landrigan. Houses must be evacuated above 12 micrograms per cubic meter, according to the State Department of Health.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
