<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Pacific Rim, a Continent Away; Asians, the State's Fastest-Growing Minority, Are Changing the Face of New Jersey</title>
    <meta content="22COV.$09" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240757"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Population</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Asian-Americans</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Far East, South and Southeast Asia and Pacific Areas</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weil, Lynne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Asian-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Population</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001022T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404EEDB153EF931A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="2818" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Pacific Rim, a Continent Away; Asians, the State's Fastest-Growing Minority, Are Changing the Face of New Jersey</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYNNE WEIL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Weil, Lynne</byline>
      <dateline>EDGEWATER</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on changing face of New Jersey, where, according to US Census Bureau estimates, Asian/Pacific Islander population has increased by 69.5 percent since 1990; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ON the western bank of the Hudson, right on the river's edge, stands a pagoda-roofed restaurant with postcard view of Manhattan and a serene rock garden in the rear. A few feet away, there is a warren of small, interconnected stores that sell everything from origami paper to kimonos to the latest Godzilla comic books.</p>
        <p>Among the many imported items at the nearby grocery story are 17 kinds of tofu and the Korean pickled vegetables known as kimchi. The pharmacy offers barley juice and shark cartilage pills.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ON the western bank of the Hudson, right on the river's edge, stands a pagoda-roofed restaurant with postcard view of Manhattan and a serene rock garden in the rear. A few feet away, there is a warren of small, interconnected stores that sell everything from origami paper to kimonos to the latest Godzilla comic books.</p>
        <p>Among the many imported items at the nearby grocery story are 17 kinds of tofu and the Korean pickled vegetables known as kimchi. The pharmacy offers barley juice and shark cartilage pills.</p>
        <p>The unusual collection of businesses -- called the Mitsuwa Marketplace -- is part of a nationwide network of enterprises that cater to an East Asian clientele. To the growing Asian population in New Jersey, it is a merchandise mecca, and for those who were not born here, one of the best places to put homesickness to rest.</p>
        <p>Whether they are visitors with visas, immigrants or citizens born in the United States, the state's Asian/ Pacific Islander population has increased by 69.5 percent since 1990, the largest comparative growth of any ethnic group, according to federal Census Bureau estimates.</p>
        <p>Put another way, in the last decade New Jersey's  total population has increased by 5 percent, to 8.14 million people. And while the white, non-Hispanic population has shrunk by about 1 percent, the group with the second highest rate of growth, the state's Hispanic population, has grown 37.4 percent during the same period.</p>
        <p>In five years, the Census Bureau says, New Jersey's current population of 475,000 Asians and Pacific Islanders will have grown to 578,000; the projected population in 2025 is 995,000.</p>
        <p>''The ethnic composition of New Jersey is changing in meaningful ways,'' said James W. Hughes, dean of the Edward J. Bloustein School of Planning and Public Policy at Rutgers University. ''That is likely to have an effect on how people identify themselves as New Jerseyans, and on the issues that the state faces in the future.''</p>
        <p>Nor is New Jersey simply following a national trend; it is leading one. With 28.5 percent of its population Asian-born, New Jersey had the second-highest proportion of Asian residents in 1997, the most recent year for which statistics were available. Only California, where 33.5 percent of the population was of Asian origin, outpaced New Jersey.</p>
        <p>One recent Sunday, Michael Usami, a product manager for Sony Electronics Inc., was browsing in the Kinokuniya Bookstore at the marketplace here.</p>
        <p>Mr. Usami, who moved to Ridgewood from his home near Tokyo two years ago, said: ''I come here maybe once a month. It feels good to be here. I think about Japan a lot.''</p>
        <p>Japanese friends and fishing buddies help him feel at home, Mr. Usami said. On the other hand, he added, his wife, Kaori, has become acquainted with people in their neighborhood, which is racially mixed. And their sons, Shin and Len, seem to ''know lots of American kids'' and prefer to speak English rather than Japanese.</p>
        <p>Peter and Rebecca Jen, who came to New Jersey from Taiwan three years ago to attend college, said they were considering making the move a permanent one. On this day, they drove an hour from their home in Denville to scour the Yaohan Food Market  for special sales on the everyday things that they took for granted back in Taipei.</p>
        <p>After one such excursion, they took turns holding their 15-month-old son, Jonah, and heaving 60 pounds of sticky rice in cloth bags into the back of their car.</p>
        <p>''We normally shop at the local grocery store near our home, and buy the usual things that people get,'' Rebecca Jen said. ''But often there are special items here on sale, so it is always worth the trip.''</p>
        <p>Whether it is Indians in Jersey City, Japanese in Bergen County or Chinese in Piscataway, Asians have been drawn to New Jersey by relatives who preceded them here as well as by the growing number of job opportunities. But unlike earlier migrations -- made up of people with little money or education -- many of today's Asian immigrants already have an education and have come here to capitalize.</p>
        <p>In the 1990 Census, which provided the latest reliable statistics, 71 percent of the state's Asian population said they had attended college.</p>
        <p>''Asian immigrants tend to be well-educated professionals,'' Mr. Hughes said. ''In New Jersey, Asians are finding employment especially in the burgeoning high-technology industry, in electronics and computer design.''</p>
        <p>The Asian-born in this country often are referred to as a model minority because of their relative success. But along with the population and its prosperity, tensions have also begun to rise. Incidents of bias -- including violent crime -- have prompted some to question how well accepted Asians in this country really are. Those concerns were heightened after a nuclear scientist at the national laboratory in Los Alamos, Wen Ho Lee, was accused of stealing nuclear secrets for China.</p>
        <p>Like all broad demographic brush strokes, being Asian can mean many things.  Mr. Hughes noted that in New Jersey, Asians made up about 90 percent of the people whom the Census Bureau categorize as ''Asian and Pacific Islander.''</p>
        <p>Data from the 2000 Census is not yet available. For now, experts say patterns established in the 1980's are the best indicators for the recent rise in the Asian population.</p>
        <p>In the 1990 Census, Indians comprised 1 percent of the 7.7 million people then living in New Jersey, the largest Asian community in the state. In addition, the Immigration and Naturalization Service says that more people have been coming to New Jersey as legal and permanent residents from India than from any other country -- 15,003 from 1996 to 1998, the most recent year for which figures are available.</p>
        <p>Residents of South Asian origin are spread throughout the state, but there are regions with comparatively larger concentrations of people from India, Pakistan and Bangladesh. Central Middlesex County is one such area, with an estimated 50,000 people of South Asian origin in and around  Woodbridge and Edison. Indeed, a several-mile stretch of Oak Tree Road has come to be widely known as Little India because of the concentration of Indian-owned restaurants, services and shops.</p>
        <p>Since 1990, Edison has been home to the annual Navratri, or Nine Nights Festival, which participants say is the largest celebration of Indian religion and culture in the country. The manager of the event, Jayesh Mehta, said that on an average Saturday night in mid-October, as many as 10,000 people were drawn to the festival.</p>
        <p>Run by the Iselin-based Indo-American Cultural Society, the Navratri festival features music, dance and foods from throughout the subcontinent. ''This is our big opportunity once a year to proudly share some of our cultural gifts with other people,'' said the president of the society, Pradip (Peter) Kothari.</p>
        <p>Not everyone has seen it that way since  the Raritan Center in Edison became the site of the festival. Complaints about excessive noise and crowds have led to several legal disputes.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kothari dismissed the grumbling as ''the irritation some people feel toward any community which is different from them.''  But, he said, ''It could be worse. Things have improved dramatically in that regard in recent years.''</p>
        <p>For instance, on the night after Mr. Kothari opened his travel agency in Iselin in May 1990, vandals smashed the windows. And he said it happened 10 more times in subsequent years.</p>
        <p>As bad as that experience was, it paled next to the wave of beatings and destruction of property visited on Indians in Jersey City in 1987 and 1988. The gang found responsible for much of violence called themselves  ''dotbusters'' -- a crude reference to the bindi cosmetic dot with which religious Hindus mark their foreheads.</p>
        <p>In a letter to a local newspaper, the dotbusters wrote that they would ''go to any extreme to get Indians to move out of Jersey City.''</p>
        <p>The group's tactics included ''Patel attacks'' in which they would select victims from the telephone book by name and harass them in their homes. The most infamous crime took place on Sept. 27, 1987, when a 30-year-old Indian man, Navraze Mody, was beaten to death by a gang of youths after he left a Hoboken cafe.</p>
        <p>That incident mobilized many in the state's Indian communities to protest what they viewed as police indifference to their safety, and a lack of prosecutorial rigor.</p>
        <p>These days, Asian leaders in the state agree that the most recent issue to galvanize opinion in their communities has been the case of Wen Ho Lee, who was accused of spying, lost his job and was jailed for nine months before his release in September. He pleaded guilty to one felony count of mishandling nuclear secrets, while the other 58 charges against him were dropped.</p>
        <p>''A large number of Asians in this state work in science and technology,'' said Marjorie Li, the president of the Asian American Political Association, based in New Brunswick. ''Many had great empathy for Dr. Lee. They felt they might have been faced with the same treatment, and it was really shocking.''</p>
        <p>Now the state's Asian communities are split over how best to get along in New Jersey: Keep a low profile or to become more visibly active and take more interest in public life.</p>
        <p>''Many first-generation Asian immigrants read only the newspapers in their own languages, and keep up only with the news from their old country,'' said John Bang, a staff assistant on immigration issues and Asian outreach for Senator Frank Lautenberg. ''The second generation comes in a little more savvy about U.S. current events. They also show a much greater interest in the political process.''</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Bang said the Asian-American community was not a very cohesive political force because it was made up of people of different nationalities.</p>
        <p>''But they are starting to come together in regional political groups,'' Mr. Bang said, ''so that they will have more political capital.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bang, a second-generation American whose parents are Korean-born, added: ''We don't have our own Jesse Jacksons or Al Sharptons. It's contrary to the Asian culture to be aggressive and toot your own horn. But that is what the communities will have to do to gain political recognition.''</p>
        <p>Michelle Kim, a junior who is majoring in political science at Rutgers, might be ready for the job. A second-generation Asian American, she was student body president at her high school and became active in campus politics at Rutgers in her freshman year.</p>
        <p>Now Ms. Kim says she is considering a career in public service when she graduates. ''I see the need for somebody to be out there as a voice for the Asian community,'' she said. ''Somebody has got to do it, and not many people are willing to do it, so it might as well be me.''</p>
        <p>In staking claim to that position, Ms. Kim considers herself unusual among second-generation Asian Americans because she has not been placed under intense pressure at home to earn good grades, but has always been encouraged to take part in social activities at school.</p>
        <p>Ms. Kim said: ''Maybe it's because my mother went to high school in the United States after moving here in 1970 from Taegu, South Korea. She recognized the importance of my being involved with things that other kids at school were doing. A lot of first-generation Asian parents are concerned only about their children's academic achievement and financial stability in the long term.''</p>
        <p>Upendra Chivukula, the Indian-born mayor of Franklin Township and one of the few people of Asian origin to hold municipal office in the state, is among those who is trying to raise the Asian profile.</p>
        <p>A past president of the local Lions' Club and former head of the Democratic Party for Franklin Township, Mr. Chivukula said Asian transplants to New Jersey did themselves no favor by remaining ''in close-knit, ethnically distinct societies, unseen by the rest of the world.''</p>
        <p>''The challenge they're going to be facing will be getting accepted in the communities where they live, and being integrated into them,'' Mr. Chivukula said. ''They should not appear clannish. There will also be a certain jealousy factor as more people of Asian origin are succeeding here.''</p>
        <p>If public opinion polls are any indication, however, most New Jersey residents do not resent the immigrants, and are more tolerant of immigration than the country as a whole.</p>
        <p>''Keys to Successful Immigration: Implications of the New Jersey Experience,'' published in 1997, explored various dimensions of immigrant life in the state, including public attitudes toward the foreign-born.</p>
        <p>Thomas Espenshade, chairman of Princeton University's sociology department and a faculty associate at the school's Office of Population Research, edited the study.</p>
        <p>In a Gallup poll commissioned by the university, slightly more than half of New Jersey adults surveyed welcomed the new immigrants, while 40 percent thought the number ought to be decreased. Those who wanted to see immigration reduced expressed anxiety over the availability of jobs and possible overcrowding, but no specific animosity toward immigrants themselves.</p>
        <p>The study contrasted this result with a 1993 CBS News/New York Times poll that found more than 60 percent of respondents nationwide wanted immigration to decrease.</p>
        <p>''One of the things that has actually helped in New Jersey's case is that the foreign-born population is better educated than the foreign-born population nationwide,'' Mr. Espenshade said. ''Those who are better educated tend to pass along the values of education and achievement to their children, and that's probably been good for the state.''</p>
        <p>Asked whether New Jerseyans' attitudes toward immigrants and native-born Asians might change as the Asian population here continued to rise, Mr. Espenshade said: ''That would be difficult to predict. But these attitudes tend to remain stable, as long as the economy is good.''</p>
        <p>For Asians who are newly arrived in New Jersey from overseas, getting acclimated and finding a job are more immediate challenges than the question of prejudice.</p>
        <p>''Maybe after living here many years, people begin thinking about their place in mainstream society, or whether they become the object of bias,'' said Mai Lieu, director of the migration and refugee office of the humanitarian agency Catholic Family and Community Services in Paterson. ''But first they think about are how cold the winter here is compared to their country, or how far they need to ride the bus to work.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Lieu's agency helps newly arrived refugees and immigrants obtain housing, become enrolled in the Social Security and Medicaid programs, and find employment. Initial job placements for many, she said, tend to be in electronics firms staffed by other Asian immigrants.</p>
        <p>Ms. Lieu currently is working to help Trang Khanh Huynh, a Vietnamese refuge, resolve some of these very issues. Ms. Huynh, 29, arrived in the United States from Saigon last February with her two younger brothers. Soon afterward, their father was admitted as a refugee in August 1999.</p>
        <p>Ms. Huynh is about to complete a six-month beauty school course that will entitle her to become a licensed manicurist.</p>
        <p>With Ms. Lieu as her interpreter, Ms. Huynh said: ''The first thing I would like to do is to get a job in a salon, so I do not have to depend on anyone else for support. When I have enough money, I hope to start taking English lessons.''</p>
        <p>Earlier this year, when Catholic Family and Community Services helped Ms. Huynh fill out her census form, she was living with relatives, had no job prospects and was uncertain what the future would bring. How does she envision her life in 10 years, when the next census is to be done?</p>
        <p>''I will speak English well and have more American friends,'' she said. ''And I will own a beauty salon.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
