<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TRANSACTIONS</title>
    <meta content="23BRFO$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241177"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001022T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E6DD1631F931A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="287" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TRANSACTIONS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BASEBALL  American League  TORONTO BLUE JAYS - Agreed to terms with 1B Carlos Delgado on a four-year contract.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BASEBALL  American League  TORONTO BLUE JAYS - Agreed to terms with 1B Carlos Delgado on a four-year contract.</p>
        <p>BASKETBALL  National Basketball Association  CHICAGO BULLS - Waived F Johnny Taylor.  NEW YORK KNICKS - Waived C Vladimir Stepania.  TORONTO RAPTORS - Signed F Tyrone Corbin. Claimed C Nick Sheppard off waivers from the Utah Jazz.</p>
        <p>FOOTBALL  National Football League  CLEVELAND BROWNS - Placed QB Tim Couch on injured reserve. Signed QB Kevin Thompson.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY  National Hockey League  ST. LOUIS BLUES - Signed F Justin Papineau. Re-signed F Derek Bekar and F Reed Low.  SAN JOSE SHARKS - Recalled D Greg Andrusak from Kentucky of the AHL.  PHOENIX COYOTES - Assigned C Daniel Briere to Springfield of the AHL.  VANCOUVER CANUCKS - Signed RW Trent Klatt to a two-year contract extension, through the 2002-03 season.  Ameican Hockey League  KENTUCKY THOROUGHBLADES - Announced D Greg Andrusak has been recalled by the San Jose Sharks.SAINT JOHN FLAMES - Signed G Sean Matile and loaned him to Providence.  SPRINGFIELD FALCONS - Acquired C Daniel Briere on loan from the Phoenix Coyotes.  ST. JOHN'S MAPLES LEAFS - Signed D Chad Alien.</p>
        <p>COLLEGES  TRANS AMERICA ATHLETIC CONFERENCE - Announced the addition of Belmont to the conference, effective July 1, 2001.  MONTANA STATE - Reinstated John Rushing, assistant football coach from suspension.  PACIFIC - Named Todd Smith director of athletic performance.  SAN DIEGO STATE - Named Jim VanHootegem assistant track and field coach.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
