<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Albright Heading to North Korea to Pave Way for Clinton</title>
    <meta content="22KORE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/22/world/22KORE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241031"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">North Korea-International Relations-US</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">North Korea</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Albright, Madeleine K (Sec)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perlez, Jane</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kim Jong Il</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/North Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/North Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001022T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E1DD1F3EF931A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1268" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Albright Heading to North Korea to Pave Way for Clinton</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE PERLEZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Perlez, Jane</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sec of State Madeleine K Albright will embark on landmark visit to North Korea, signaling accelerating thaw in relations between both countries; will meet with Pres Kim Jong Il, paving way for possible visit by Pres Clinton; she will be most senior American official to visit tightly controlled Stalinist state; hasty arrangements for visit are seen as signal of administration's desire to push ahead with improving relations before Clinton leaves office; some major issues on agenda for discussion with North Korean officials noted; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Embarking on a landmark visit that signals an accelerating thaw in relations, Secretary of State Madeleine K. Albright was to leave today for North Korea for a meeting with the Communist country's leader, Kim Jong Il, that could pave the way for a visit by President Clinton.</p>
        <p>Dr. Albright will be the most senior American official to visit the tightly controlled Stalinist state, and Mr. Clinton would be the first American president to go to North Korea since the Korean War began more than 50 years ago.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Embarking on a landmark visit that signals an accelerating thaw in relations, Secretary of State Madeleine K. Albright was to leave today for North Korea for a meeting with the Communist country's leader, Kim Jong Il, that could pave the way for a visit by President Clinton.</p>
        <p>Dr. Albright will be the most senior American official to visit the tightly controlled Stalinist state, and Mr. Clinton would be the first American president to go to North Korea since the Korean War began more than 50 years ago.</p>
        <p>The hasty arrangements for Dr. Albright's trip -- made in less than 10 days for a visit that would normally take months to choreograph -- were another signal of the Clinton administration's desire to push ahead with improving relations before Mr. Clinton leaves office.</p>
        <p>But the prospect of Mr. Clinton's making such an important foreign visit so late in his presidency to a state the United States has charged with supporting terrorism has raised mixed reactions from experts on the region and a heated discussion even within his own administration.</p>
        <p>The usually reclusive North Korean leader made a surprising debut on the world stage earlier this year, holding a first-ever summit meeting with a South Korean president, Kim Dae Jung, during which they made some progress in warming relations but left a raft of issues unresolved.</p>
        <p>At the top of Dr. Albright's agenda will be discussion of how far the North Korean president is prepared to go toward shutting down his country's missile program and its missile exports to countries hostile to the United States, senior administration officials said.</p>
        <p>North Korea's missile program has raised anxiety throughout the region, particularly in Japan, and was cited as one of the main reasons for the ambitious proposals in the United States to build a national missile defense system.</p>
        <p>Other issues on the table will be North Korea's support of terrorism and how to reduce military tensions between North and South Korea. The United States still maintains some 37,000 troops along a heavily militarized border that Mr. Clinton described at the start of his presidency as the ''scariest place on earth.''</p>
        <p>They will also discuss the possibility of opening liaison offices in each other's countries, officials said.</p>
        <p>The sudden decision for Dr. Albright to travel to North Korea follows a visit this month to the White House by Vice Marshal Jo Myong Rok, a senior North Korean military official, who issued an invitation for Mr. Clinton to go to Pyongyang, the North Korean capital.</p>
        <p>Senior White House officials believe that the progress made by the South Korean president in moving toward reconciliation between North and South Korea presents an ''opportunity'' that must be grasped by Mr. Clinton as a way of reducing tensions on the peninsula, one of the main foreign policy challenges left over from the cold war.</p>
        <p>But the Pentagon is less enthusiastic about a presidential visit. Last month it released a report with a pessimistic assessment about North Korea's military intentions, saying North Korea showed no fundamental change in its posture.</p>
        <p>The report said North Korea had stockpiled chemical weapons and continued to develop short- and long-range missiles, though it had honored its pledge to American negotiators last year that it would not flight-test them.</p>
        <p>The White House is clearly leaning toward going ahead with a Clinton visit. ''Tell me why I shouldn't go,'' will be Dr. Albright's mission on behalf of the president, a senior official said. The official stressed that Dr. Albright was not seeking a firm commitment that if the North Koreans ''do a, b, c and initial here, we will deliver the president.''</p>
        <p>Rather, the official said, Dr. Albright would be seeking to evaluate whether the North Koreans would be prepared to move forward on the issues if President Clinton does go.</p>
        <p>Criticism from outside the administration centered on the vagueness of what Mr. Clinton would gain from visiting a country with an abominable human rights record and concerns that the visit itself would be interpreted as an imprimatur for a repressive government.</p>
        <p>''For North Korea, the president's visit is itself the prize,'' said Arnold Kanter, a former under secretary of state in the Bush administration. ''The question is what the United States is getting in return that meets our needs to reduce the threat posed by North Korea.''</p>
        <p>As under secretary in 1992, Mr. Kanter was the first high-level American official to meet with a senior North Korean official.</p>
        <p>Another critique came from Michel Oksenberg, a China expert who served on the National Security Council during the Carter presidency. He said the stakes were too high to rush into a visit with a lame duck president. ''A presidential trip has to be exquisitely planned, and time is very short,'' Mr. Oksenberg said.</p>
        <p>But administration officials have defended a possible Clinton visit, saying they asked advice -- and got the approval -- from the South Korean president before going ahead with Dr. Albright's trip.</p>
        <p>They also make the case that the trip is part of a slow process of negotiations with the North, which have already borne fruit with the North's agreement last year to temporarily freeze flight tests of their missiles. That freeze was extended indefinitely with the visit of Marshal Jo this month, they said.</p>
        <p>Last month, the North also stockpiled the last of the spent fuel rods from its nuclear reactors, officials said, a move the United States has wanted to help ensure that the fuel would not be used to produce plutonium for nuclear weapons.</p>
        <p>And one of Dr. Albright's missions, they say, will be to further explore an idea raised in talks that Kim Jong Il had this summer with the Russian president, Vladimir V. Putin, when Mr. Kim said he would reduce the long-range missile program in exchange for foreign countries' launching North Korean satellites.</p>
        <p>Negotiations over the North's support of terrorism are close to bearing results as well, administration official argue. North Korea remains on the State Department's list of countries that support terrorism, a position that bars it from entering any of the international financial institutions, including the World Bank and the International Monetary Fund.</p>
        <p>But the North Koreans have begun to take the required steps that could soon remove them from the terrorist list, the officials said. This in turn could start the process of having North Korea join those financial institutions, but realistically, this is probably quite a way off, officials said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Albright's visit comes on the heels of a series of moves by North Korea to crack open the door to a society long closed and allow the outside world a peek inside, maneuvers that have begun to produce some benefits for Mr. Kim.</p>
        <p>Britain announced this week that it would recognize North Korea, and starting late last year, several Western countries, including Italy and Australia, took up North Korea's invitation to open diplomatic relations.</p>
        <p>Still, most experts view the moves by the North Korean leader as a way of ensuring the survival of his government, which rules over one of the world's most impoverished and constrained populations.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
