<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Again, Leiter Watches His Work Go to Waste</title>
    <meta content="22HERM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/22/sports/22HERM.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241113"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL: SUBWAY SERIES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hermoso, Rafael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leiter, Al</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001022T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03EFD81F3EF931A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="731" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Again, Leiter Watches His Work Go to Waste</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RAFAEL HERMOSO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hermoso, Rafael</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses performance of New York Mets pitcher Al Leiter in loss to New York Yankees in Game 1 of World Series (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>This has happened to Al Leiter before. Two previous times in the past two seasons, Leiter has pitched well enough to earn playoff victories only to see the Mets' usually dependable bullpen waste them.</p>
        <p>And it happened again last night.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>This has happened to Al Leiter before. Two previous times in the past two seasons, Leiter has pitched well enough to earn playoff victories only to see the Mets' usually dependable bullpen waste them.</p>
        <p>And it happened again last night.</p>
        <p>Leiter persevered through seven strong innings, long enough for the Mets to rally for the lead, and handed a one-run advantage to the bullpen. John Franco pitched a scoreless eighth before Armando Benitez again blew a save in the bottom of the ninth.</p>
        <p>It was the third time Benitez has blown a postseason victory for Leiter since the closer joined the Mets in 1999. In last year's division series, Benitez's blown save in Game 4 set up Todd Pratt's series-winning homer in the 10th inning. In this year's division series, Benitez allowed J. T. Snow's game-tying homer in the ninth inning of Game 2 before the Mets won in extra innings against San Francisco.</p>
        <p>And last night, again, Leiter was done in by Benitez.</p>
        <p>Asked about the frustration of seeing another victory tossed away, Leiter said: ''If you really want to keep it in your hands, you throw the whole game.'' But Leiter also said the failure to get a victory hardly matched the frustration of seeing his team fail to take a 1-0 series lead.</p>
        <p>''This time of year is a selfless time of year,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Leiter, who had beaten the Yankees three times in the last two seasons in interleague play, allowed two runs on just five hits in his seven innings. He shook off catcher Todd Pratt several times, but seemed in command for much of the game. Pratt was catching, because Mike Piazza, who had caught most of Leiter's games this season, was serving as the designated hitter.</p>
        <p>Manager Bobby Valentine explained his decision to start Leiter over Mike Hampton in Game 1 on the simple fact that it was Leiter's turn to pitch after Hampton finished the National League Championship Series with a three-hit shutout of the Cardinals on Monday. Leiter had started two World Series games for the Marlins in 1997, including Game 7. Leiter did not get a decision as the Marlins won in 11 innings, but he had a strong outing (six innings, two runs).</p>
        <p>Last night, Leiter allowed the Yankees to put runners on first and third in the second inning, on Paul O'Neill's two-out single, before Scott Brosius grounded out to end the inning. Leiter faced the minimum from then until the sixth inning, allowing only a walk to Chuck Knoblauch in the third inning that was erased when Leiter picked him off first base.</p>
        <p>For six innings, Leiter watched as his teammates fell over themselves with bad base-running. And then Leiter finally gave in to the Yankees in the bottom of the sixth. The No. 9 hitter Jose Vizcaino, a .526 (10 for 19) lifetime hitter against Leiter, led off with a single before Knoblauch bounced back to Leiter, who got the forceout at second base. With Knoblauch at first, Leiter walked Derek Jeter before David Justice lined a double off the warning track in the center field.</p>
        <p>Two runs scored, and Turk Wendell was warming in the Mets' bullpen. But Valentine let Leiter intentionally walk Bernie Williams before having him face the left-handed batter, Tino Martinez. Leiter got him to ground out to first, putting runners on second and third with two outs and the switch-hitter Jorge Posada due up. The pitching coach Dave Wallace approached the mound and Wendell was ready, but Leiter remained in the game. He got Posada to fly to center.</p>
        <p>Leiter had thrown 102 pitches at that point, but when the Mets rallied to take the lead in the top of the seventh, Valentine gave him a margin for error and kept him in the game. Leiter grimaced when Scott Brosius hit a one-out single in the bottom of the seventh, but he got Vizcaino to ground out before attacking Knoblauch. On a 2-2 count, Knoblauch swung through a 93-mile-an-hour fastball to end the inning. After nearly leaving the game in the sixth with a 2-0 deficit, Leiter now handed his bullpen a one-run lead. He had thrown 126 pitches, and he had passed the baton to the bullpen, which dropped it.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL: SUBWAY SERIES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
