<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hindu Hard-Liners Pressing To Keep Excluding Muslims</title>
    <meta content="Y22IND$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/22/world/22INDI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241001"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hinduism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">India</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dugger, Celia W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Laxman, Bangaru</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hinduism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001022T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E2DA1E3EF931A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1098" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hindu Hard-Liners Pressing To Keep Excluding Muslims</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CELIA W. DUGGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dugger, Celia W</byline>
      <dateline>NEW DELHI, Oct. 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Hindu nationalist hard-liners continue pressing anti-Muslim policies, despite efforts by new party president Bangaru Laxman to distanceparty from chauvinist thinking; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bangaru Laxman, the new president of the Bharatiya Janata Party, which leads India's coalition government, has been trying lately to distance the party from its Hindu nationalist roots and the Hindu chauvinist thinking that has long alienated Muslims and many others in this predominantly Hindu nation.</p>
        <p>In his inaugural address, Mr. Laxman argued that his party had hit a plateau in its share of the national vote -- about a quarter of the total -- and must begin aggressively courting Muslims, who make up about 12 percent of India's population. ''Muslims are the flesh of our flesh and the blood of our blood,'' he declared, quoting a political forebear. He also visited the foreign correspondents club, where he argued that his party should no longer be described as Hindu nationalist.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Bangaru Laxman, the new president of the Bharatiya Janata Party, which leads India's coalition government, has been trying lately to distance the party from its Hindu nationalist roots and the Hindu chauvinist thinking that has long alienated Muslims and many others in this predominantly Hindu nation.</p>
        <p>In his inaugural address, Mr. Laxman argued that his party had hit a plateau in its share of the national vote -- about a quarter of the total -- and must begin aggressively courting Muslims, who make up about 12 percent of India's population. ''Muslims are the flesh of our flesh and the blood of our blood,'' he declared, quoting a political forebear. He also visited the foreign correspondents club, where he argued that his party should no longer be described as Hindu nationalist.</p>
        <p>But events in the past week once again yoked the Bharatiya Janata Party to the very Hindu nationalist identity that Mr. Laxman has been trying to put at arm's length and made it seem that the party was torn between cultivating its hard-core constituency and broadening its base among Muslims and low-caste Hindus -- steps it must take if it is ever to hold power on its own.</p>
        <p>It started last Sunday in Agra at a  camp meeting of the Rashtriya Swayamsevak Sangh, or National Volunteers Association. This 75-year-old Hindu nationalist organization, known as the R.S.S., is the parent in a ''family'' of affiliated and like-minded groups that includes a political wing, the Bharatiya Janata Party.</p>
        <p>At the meeting, Lal Krishna Advani, second only to Prime Minister Atal Behari Vajpayee in the party's leadership, listened respectfully as K. S. Sudarshan, who heads the association, declared that Muslims must embrace what he described as their Hindu origins.</p>
        <p>He also said Muslims should not oppose construction of a Hindu temple to the god Ram on the site of a 16th-century mosque in the town of Ayodhya, a notion that is anathema to them. The mosque was demolished in 1992 by Hindu zealots, whose emotions had been inflamed by leaders in the R.S.S. family, including Mr. Advani of the Bharatiya Janata Party. Afterward, Hindu-Muslim riots raged across the country, leaving more than 1,200 people dead.</p>
        <p>''Most Muslim society is illiterate and in the hold of mullahs and they do not allow a harmonious relationship,'' Mr. Sudarshan said at a news conference.</p>
        <p>The next day, many national newspapers ran photographs of Mr. Advani, who serves as home minister and who may one day succeed the aging Mr. Vajpayee, giving the salute of the Rashtriya Swayamsevak Sangh, his hand held stiffly in front of his chest, palm down.</p>
        <p>His presence at such a huge gathering of the association's faithful -- arrayed across a dusty parade ground in khaki shorts and black caps -- served as a reminder that virtually all of the party's top officials, including Mr. Advani, Mr. Vajpayee and Mr. Laxman, were themselves for many years members of the Rashtriya Swayamsevak Sangh.</p>
        <p>It also brought predictably harsh condemnations from the leaders of  secular-minded political parties.</p>
        <p>Mr. Advani went on the offensive, warmly embracing the R.S.S. In articles splashed across the front pages of the major national dailies on Wednesday, he made it clear that the Bharatiya Janata Party would never sever its ties with the R.S.S. ''How could we disown an organization with which we have been associated since our childhood,'' he asked.</p>
        <p>He said the group had provided the Bharatiya Janata Party with the kind of moral guidance that the independence leader Mohandas K. Gandhi had given the Congress Party. Gandhi was assassinated in 1948 by a former R.S.S. member who felt Gandhi favored Islamic Pakistan over India. Though the R.S.S. itself was not implicated, it was banned for a time and was considered politically untouchable for many years -- a status it has since overcome.</p>
        <p>''Why all this hue and cry when we meet R.S.S. leaders?'' Mr. Advani asked. ''Is everybody not aware of the B.J.P. ideology?''</p>
        <p>The next day, in an interview at his home, Mr. Laxman, the B.J.P. president, said Mr. Sudarshan's remarks about Muslims ''were not what was needed.'' And in a statement issued that evening, he said the party's commitment to secularism was ''unconditional and irreversible.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Laxman himself joined the Rashtriya Swayamsevak Sangh as a 12-year-old boy and was an active volunteer in the organization until he was 30. He then joined its political affiliate. ''The R.S.S. teaches you discipline,'' he said. ''It creates patriotic fervor. It inculcates a sense of belonging to the motherland.''</p>
        <p>But he insisted that the party he now leads was not dominated by the group. ''The R.S.S. membership is open only to Hindus,'' he said. ''The B.J.P. is open to every Indian, to whatever religion he belongs.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Laxman, who has been a full-time party functionary for three decades, was annointed for the party presidency by the prime minister, who is generally seen as the party's liberal face. As the head of a coalition government that holds together only because the Bharatiya Janata Party has set aside his Hindu agenda, Mr. Vajpayee has led the country away from some of the policies dearest to the hearts of the Hindu nationalist association he sprang from.</p>
        <p>It wants an economy more closed to foreign investment, while Mr. Vajpayee has continued to slowly open India to globalization. It wants a Hindu temple to Ram in Ayodhya, a goal the party has set aside for now. It wants a nation united by the idea of Hindu culture, while Mr. Vajpayee has apparently sanctioned Mr. Laxman's pragmatic efforts to reach out to Muslims.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sudarshan's pointed comments on Muslims last week seemed intended to pull the party back into the Hindu nationalist fold.</p>
        <p>''The R.S.S. finds the B.J.P. diluting the venom and poison they've been giving every year,'' said Yogendra Yadav, a political scientist at the Center for the Study of Developing Societies in New Delhi. ''This is the way the pure ideologists remind the impure political wing to come back to its moorings.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
