<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Game Turns on a Pressure-Packed At-Bat</title>
    <meta content="22CURR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/22/sports/22CURR.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241094"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Curry, Jack</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'Neill, Paul</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Atlanta Braves</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001022T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06EED91F3EF931A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1010" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Game Turns on a Pressure-Packed At-Bat</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jack Curry</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Curry, Jack</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>On Baseball column discusses performance of New York Yankees outfielder Paul O'Neill in victory over New York Mets in first game of World Series; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It had been exactly four years since the Yankees, the powerful Yankees, had lost a World Series game. Enough time to serve a full term as president of the United States, enough time to earn a college degree and enough time for George Steinbrenner to once dismiss five managers. That is a long, long time.</p>
        <p>But last night the Yankees were tumbling toward their first World Series loss since Greg Maddux mesmerized them on Oct. 21, 1996, looking like a team that was about to wilt. The Mets had a 3-2 lead in the ninth inning and Armando Benitez needed two more outs to save Game 1 of the World Series. Benitez had a 1-2 count on Paul O'Neill, and there was more anxiety than excitement at Yankee Stadium.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It had been exactly four years since the Yankees, the powerful Yankees, had lost a World Series game. Enough time to serve a full term as president of the United States, enough time to earn a college degree and enough time for George Steinbrenner to once dismiss five managers. That is a long, long time.</p>
        <p>But last night the Yankees were tumbling toward their first World Series loss since Greg Maddux mesmerized them on Oct. 21, 1996, looking like a team that was about to wilt. The Mets had a 3-2 lead in the ninth inning and Armando Benitez needed two more outs to save Game 1 of the World Series. Benitez had a 1-2 count on Paul O'Neill, and there was more anxiety than excitement at Yankee Stadium.</p>
        <p>Still, O'Neill did not crumble. He fouled off one pitch, then a second, a third and a fourth as the count drifted to  3-2. Benitez has a 98-mile-an-hour fastball and O'Neill has one extra-base hit since Sept. 6, but, the longer the at-bat stretched, the more the advantage shifted to O'Neill. Benitez, the jittery closer, was more likely to falter. He did, firing an outside pitch for ball four and putting the potential tying run on base.</p>
        <p>''That was an unbelievable at-bat,'' Yankees Manager Joe Torre said. ''You could tell that he made up his mind that he wasn't going to give up the at-bat. It was sensational.''</p>
        <p>O'Neill's at-bat was crucial because he wound up scoring the tying run in the ninth inning, resuscitating the Yankees and exposing Benitez as a postseason flop. Benitez has mishandled four of his last six save opportunities in October, which is enough evidence to ponder a change to John Franco. The Mets cannot give postseason games away the way they did last night. With Mariano Rivera, the Yankees never do.</p>
        <p>Last night, after Jose Vizcaino lined a two-out, bases-loaded single off Turk Wendell, the Yankees stole a 4-3 victory in 12 draining innings to win the first game of the much-anticipated Subway Series and snatch their 13th straight World Series game. That imposing streak is a new record, a streak that looked as if it might die before the ninth inning. But the Yankees have done this so many times before, and that is why they survive in these games.</p>
        <p>''We came in with a little World Series experience and we got a lot in one night,'' said Mets Manager Bobby Valentine, following the longest game in World Series history, a 4-hour-51-minute marathon.</p>
        <p>Staring at their first World Series loss in 1,461 days, the Yankees showed their feistiness in the ninth and Benitez showed his fallibility. With one out, O'Neill fought Benitez through a 10-pitch at-bat before walking. It was easily O'Neill's best at-bat of October and maybe his best at-bat since August.</p>
        <p>The pinch-hitter Luis Polonia, a terrific fastball hitter, looped a single to right and Vizcaino stroked a single to left to load the bases. Chuck Knoblauch belted a sacrifice fly to left to tie the game, and Benitez had blown it again.</p>
        <p>When Valentine was asked to evaluate Benitez's performance, he explained a devastating situation simply by saying, ''He just missed getting O'Neill out and then they got a couple of singles.'' It was more than that. Benitez gave the best postseason team in baseball history a breath, and the Yankees won it in the 12th inning when Vizcaino knocked his fourth hit of the night.</p>
        <p>''We may not be as good as we've been in the past,'' reliever Mike Stanton said, ''but we're battlers.''</p>
        <p>On the night of Oct. 21, 1996, the Atlanta Braves strolled out of Yankee Stadium and onto their waiting buses as a confident team. Maddux had just halted the Yankees to give the Braves a 2-0 cushion in the World Series, so the verbal abuse from the rowdy fans bounced off the players like raindrops. They kept walking, knowing they had made the Yankees look like a beaten team.</p>
        <p>But the Yankees were not beaten. An annoyed David Cone saved them in the third game in Atlanta, and the Yankees wound up sweeping the last four games of the Series to shock the Braves and win their first title since 1981. The abuse the Braves heard on their slow walk to the bus after Game 6 stung them so much more, like the difference between being hit with a raindrop and an anvil.</p>
        <p>The night when Maddux stifled the Yankees is the last time they had lost a World Series game. The Yankees rolled over the Braves that year, then topped the San Diego Padres in four games in 1998 and then the Braves in four again in 1999. Add one more after last night's victory for a lucky 13.</p>
        <p>It had been exactly four years since the Yankees lost a World Series game, enough time for them to win three championships. The streak was two outs from ending, and a difficult loss would have made everyone wonder if these Yankees were as resilient as their predecessors. But the Yankees won. Now it is exactly four years and one day since the Yankees have lost. The streak goes on the line again tonight, a historic team chasing more history.</p>
        <p>''I'd like to believe,'' Torre said, ''that we find a way to win.'</p>
        <p>ON BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
