<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="22FSUM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241032"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001022T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E7DB1F3EF931A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="688" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>3-14</p>
        <p>Rethinking Cooperation, Israelis Think Separation  After three weeks of violence that may propel the Palestinians into declaring statehood, the Israelis are laying the groundwork for a ''unilateral separation.'' The new Middle East has collapsed quickly back into the old in recent weeks, and the ideas of building fences rather than bridges have resurfaced.</p>
        <p>1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>3-14</p>
        <p>Rethinking Cooperation, Israelis Think Separation  After three weeks of violence that may propel the Palestinians into declaring statehood, the Israelis are laying the groundwork for a ''unilateral separation.'' The new Middle East has collapsed quickly back into the old in recent weeks, and the ideas of building fences rather than bridges have resurfaced.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Arab leaders heaped criticism on Israel for its killing of more than 100 Palestinians in clashes over the past three weeks during a summit of 22 Arab nations in Cairo. Behind the passionate words, a temperate consensus appeared to be building.</p>
        <p>10</p>
        <p>A leader of Yasir Arafat's Fatah movement has vowed to continue big West Bank confrontations with Israeli forces until they withdraw from the entire West Bank and Gaza Strip, as they did from Lebanon earlier this year.</p>
        <p>10</p>
        <p>Albright to Visit North Korea  Secretary of State Madeleine K. Albright will leave to meet with the communist leader of North Korea, Kim Jong II, to pave the way for a trip by President Clinton.</p>
        <p>8</p>
        <p>Investigation in Yemeni Port  American and Yemeni investigators were seeking fresh clues to the identity of the two suicide bombers who launched a small boat before heading into Aden's harbor for the attack that killed 17 American sailors.</p>
        <p>8</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>16-32</p>
        <p>Interest Groups Mobilize Efforts to Get Out the Vote  Independent groups, including the National Rifle Association, evangelical churches, labor unions and environmentalists, are mobilizing one of the most expensive battles in recent history to get out the vote for the presidential election.</p>
        <p>18</p>
        <p>Vice President Al Gore has long been a Southern Baptist, but those roots are only one part of an intricate and eclectic spiritual life.</p>
        <p>20</p>
        <p>Dick Cheney is waging a decidedly macho campaign. He talks about fly-fishing, poses with bikers and watches lots of football games.</p>
        <p>22</p>
        <p>Battling Loan Discrimination  Class-action lawsuits filed against two of the nation's most prominent automobile finance companies have opened a new battlefront in efforts to combat racial discrimination in the consumer credit markets.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Wal-Mart Overtaking G.M.  Wal-Mart Stores sales are on track to exceed those of General Motors, the largest American company for much of the last half-century. And Wal-Mart's rise is transforming whole industries.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Gore Attacks Bush on Balkans  Mr. Gore and Secretary of State Madeleine K. Albright denounced a proposal by Gov. George W. Bush to withdraw United States ground forces from their peacekeeping mission in the Balkans.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>37-43</p>
        <p>Lazio's Love/Hate Relationship With the G.O.P. Leadership  In his campaign for the Senate, Representative Rick A. Lazio has portrayed himself as sufficiently independent of the Republican Party to defy it when New York's interests are at stake. His closeness to the House Republican leadership has helped make him effective in Congress but also restricted his freedom and independence.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Bilingualism Remains in City  A City Hall hearing and the tentative recommendations of a mayoral task force made clear that bilingual education is here to stay. New York, with its large immigrant population, is choosing a different path than California, which repudiated bilingual education in a statewide referendum, and Arizona, which is expected to do the same in November.</p>
        <p>37</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>45-46</p>
        <p>Zeke Manners  Once a popular hillbilly singer and disc jockey who wrote ''The Pennsylvania Polka,'' he was 89.</p>
        <p>46</p>
        <p>Katherine W. Fanning  The former editor of The Christian Science Monitor and The Anchorage Daily News was 73.</p>
        <p>45</p>
        <p>Chess</p>
        <p>45  Weather</p>
        <p>47</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
