<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Johnson Fights on Boards And at Table</title>
    <meta content="22KNIC$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/22/sports/22KNIC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241059"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Broussard, Chris</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnson, Larry</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001022T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E0DA1F3EF931A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="946" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Johnson Fights on Boards And at Table</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRIS BROUSSARD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Broussard, Chris</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Knickerbockers forward Larry Johnson discusses his preparations for season (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Larry Johnson knows that his test will soon come. He will arrive at a hotel late one night, wide-awake and hungry after a plane ride or a game. The menu will be full of temptation, everything from chicken fingers and french fries to filet mignon. And Johnson, a long-time heavy eater, will somehow have to find a way to resist.</p>
        <p>If he does, Johnson believes he will stay healthy, play in nearly every game, compete in most practices and increase his effectiveness on the floor. If he does not, as was the case last year, Johnson said his weight will balloon and his durability could become a problem.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Larry Johnson knows that his test will soon come. He will arrive at a hotel late one night, wide-awake and hungry after a plane ride or a game. The menu will be full of temptation, everything from chicken fingers and french fries to filet mignon. And Johnson, a long-time heavy eater, will somehow have to find a way to resist.</p>
        <p>If he does, Johnson believes he will stay healthy, play in nearly every game, compete in most practices and increase his effectiveness on the floor. If he does not, as was the case last year, Johnson said his weight will balloon and his durability could become a problem.</p>
        <p>The Knicks' co-captain really wants to do the right thing, but he knows it will be difficult.</p>
        <p>''The key for me is the way I take care of myself off the floor,'' Johnson said. ''Most people lose weight during the season, but I tend to gain weight during the season. For me to lose weight or maintain my weight is all about my diet, because I can come here and work two-and-a-half hours twice a day and if I get off my diet and eat like I normally eat, which is bad, I will gain weight.''</p>
        <p>Johnson, 31, entered training camp at a svelte 240 pounds, roughly a dozen pounds lighter than he was at the end of last season. His condition is largely the result of a strict diet he adheres to while living in his hometown of Dallas during the off-season. When in Texas, Johnson, who studies the teachings of the Nation of Islam, eats like many of the followers of Minister Louis Farrakhan.</p>
        <p>''In Dallas, I eat bean soup and bean pies every day,'' said Johnson, who has studied Islam for six years but never become a Muslim. ''On Saturdays, I treat myself to a veggie pizza. But here, when I'm traveling and staying in hotels, I have a problem. You get in at 2 o'clock in the morning and you just finished playing. You're hungry. You pick up a menu in the hotel. Ain't no bean soup or bean pie on the menu. Get on the airplane at 11, 12 o'clock at night after a game. They ain't got bean soup or bean pie on the plane. What are you going to do?</p>
        <p>''We haven't taken a lot of road trips so it hasn't been hectic on me right now. But I know there's going to come a stretch during the season where it's going to be tough.''</p>
        <p>This year more than ever, the Knicks need Johnson to stick to his diet. With Patrick Ewing having been traded to the Seattle Supersonics, the 6-foot-7-inch power forward is now the Knicks' No. 1 low-post option. He will need to score consistently against single coverage on the block, pass to the open man on the perimeter when double-teamed, and improve on the 5.5 rebounds per game he has averaged since joining the Knicks in 1996 -- all while being guarded by the opponent's top low-post defender.</p>
        <p>''He's always going to face the best post defender,'' Coach Jeff Van Gundy said. ''Before, when he had Pat, you'd never see the most size on him because they'd always put the most size on Pat. So we'll try to spread him on the floor more against size, use his shooting range to draw the defense out and hopefully, he can use his quickness to go by them on the dribble.''</p>
        <p>If Johnson experiences the chronic back problems that have plagued him since 1994, his effectiveness is likely to decrease. Last season, Johnson played in 70 games but sat out lots of practices. As a result, he experienced the worst season of his career, posting all-time lows in scoring (10.7 points per game) and field-goal percentage (.433) and grabbing only 5.4 rebounds a game. So far, at least from a health standpoint, Johnson has been fine. After missing parts of the first couple of practices, he has participated fully for the past two weeks and competed in all five preseason games. Last season, he was in only three preseason games.</p>
        <p>In this preseason, Johnson's results have been mixed. He has crashed the backboards impressively, averaging 8 rebounds in 24 minutes a game, but he has struggled with his shot. Though he has scored 27 points on 7-of-15 shooting the last two games, he is averaging 9.2 points on 34 percent shooting over all. Neither Johnson nor Van Gundy is worried about the lack of offensive production, though, because Johnson typically enters the season rusty after a summer away from the game. Because of his back problems, he cannot play or even run on a track during the off-season because the pounding aggravates his back.</p>
        <p>''I'm not concerned at all because, although Larry stays in great shape over the summer, he doesn't do any basketball stuff,'' Van Gundy said. ''It takes a little time to get that stuff back.''</p>
        <p>Johnson, who says he finds preseason games boring after nine years in the league, is excited about being his team's main low-post threat again. The last time he was in that position, the 1995-1996 season, he averaged 20.5 points and 8.4 rebounds for the Charlotte Hornets.</p>
        <p>''I think I'm pretty close to what I was in '96 because that was after my back injury,'' Johnson said. ''So yeah, I think I'm up to the task. This is an opportunity for me to show you cats what I can do. It's a good challenge.''</p>
        <p>So is avoiding those late-night feasts.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
