<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Economic Windfall Is Not Guaranteed</title>
    <meta content="22ECON$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/22/sports/22ECON.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241049"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL: SUBWAY SERIES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mckinley, James C Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001022T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E6DA1F3EF931A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1403" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Economic Windfall Is Not Guaranteed</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES C. McKINLEY JR.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mckinley, James C Jr</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses how World Series between New York Yankees and New York Mets will impact economically on New York City (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>No one doubts that the Subway Series has bathed New York in spiritual riches. It has lifted the morale of baseball fans all over the region and drawn national attention to the Big Apple; it is also a great spectacle, an epic contest between a long-reigning champion and a wild-card challenger.</p>
        <p>Local politicians have predicted glowingly that the World Series will also bring material riches to the city. But many economists say the odds that the Series will be an economic boon to New York are as great as the odds that the Chicago Cubs will win a pennant.</p>
        <p>Both Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani and Comptroller Alan G. Hevesi have said that having the Yankees and the Mets in the Series will inject hundreds of millions of dollars into the local economy and produce millions in taxes to the city.</p>
        <p>Hevesi released a report last week estimating that a seven-game Series would add, conservatively, $137.2 million to the city's economy, or between $18 million and $20 million for each game.</p>
        <p>The comptroller's economists arrived at this prediction by adding up rough estimates of revenues from sales of tickets, billboards, television and radio ads, and concession stands, then multiplying the sum by 1.5 to account for the second round of spending that is spurred when money is pumped into the local economy.</p>
        <p>For his part, Giuliani has boldly predicted that the Series will bring in between $40 million and $50 million in city taxes on everything from hotel rooms and players' salaries to sales of tickets  and merchandise.</p>
        <p>But independent economists are highly skeptical of both estimates. In fact, some say that a Series pitting a New York team against a team from another city might have been more lucrative, because it would bring in more fans from the rival metropolis.</p>
        <p>''There is no basis to think this is going to be a material lift to the New York City economy,'' said Andrew Zimbalist, a Smith College economist who is an authority on professional sports. ''The city would do better if the Mets were playing Seattle. Basically you have fewer people coming in bringing less money.''</p>
        <p>Hevesi's prediction rests on several questionable assumptions, many economists said. For example, many of the revenues the comptroller has counted as new economic activity would have come into New York's economy anyway, because Major League Baseball is based in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Take the revenues from ticket sales, the largest slice of new revenue in the comptroller's calculations. Hevesi's sports economist, John Tepper Marlin, projects at least $25 million from ticket revenues for each game at Yankee Stadium and $18.4 million for the games at Shea Stadium, counting all of it as new economic activity.</p>
        <p>But the World Series is like a traveling show produced by Major League Baseball. Every year the commissioner's office takes a third of the gate receipts for the first four games, no matter where they are played, and a larger percentage of the last three games, if they are played. In the past, about 12.5 percent of ticket revenues went to the participating teams, along with profits from concessions, billboard ads and parking fees, sports economists said.</p>
        <p>''The Yankees and the Mets will net about $3 million to $4 million, because they have some expenses,'' Zimbalist said.</p>
        <p>Of the rest of the money from ticket sales, 60 percent from the first four games goes into a pool for all major league players in the playoffs; most of that is divided among players on the winning and losing teams in the World Series. The remainder goes to other major league players.</p>
        <p>But there is no assurance that the money paid to players in New York will be spent in New York City or on products made here, economists said. Only a handful of the players on the Yankees and the Mets list their official residence in the state, and even fewer reside permanently in the city.</p>
        <p>Similar troubles arise when counting revenues from television advertisements, which the comptroller has estimated at between $2.6 million and $3.5 million for each game.</p>
        <p>Baseball officials say the playoff teams do not receive national advertising revenues. The company that does -- Fox Sports, which holds the broadcast rights to the World Series -- is based in Los Angeles. The fees paid to Major League Baseball for the broadcast rights come into the New York economy every year, no matter where the World Series is played.</p>
        <p>Dick Netzer, an economist at New York University, said that waves of tourists coming into New York to see the games would provide a true boost to the local economy, but it is unclear how many people have come for the Series.</p>
        <p>There are at least 1,400 reporters accredited to cover the games, many of them from other cities. There are also several thousand other people connected with Major League Baseball who get tickets, although baseball officials declined to give a precise number.</p>
        <p>About 3,000 tickets are given to other big-league teams for their employees. Another 400 tickets go to baseball writers around the country, while 1,500 tickets go to major league players not in the Series. Corporate sponsors also get large blocks of tickets as well, and some of those tickets may go to people from other cities.</p>
        <p>Still, the impact on New York's hotel industry is not very likely to be major, economists said, because October is already the busiest time for tourism in the city. In recent years, more than 90 percent of the city's 66,000 hotel rooms have been occupied in October, city tourism officials said.</p>
        <p>Even if one assumes that the nearly 6,000 rooms that are usually empty at this time of year are filled because of the Series, at $300 a night it would mean about $1.8 million in extra revenue, a tiny amount in a regional economy that generates about $1 billion of business a day, economists said. Looked at in that context, even the comptroller's estimate of $20 million a day in new economic activity would be a drop in the bucket.</p>
        <p>''This is going to have almost no effect,'' said Mark S. Rosentraub, an economist at Indiana University who has written extensively on the economics of baseball. ''There is going to be a small gain, but you're talking about the nation's largest regional economy.''</p>
        <p>Giuliani's visions of windfall tax revenues may also be wishful thinking. The city's effective tax rate -- the ratio between its revenues and its gross product -- is about 6 percent most years and never exceeds 8 percent. Even if one accepts the comptroller's questionable estimates of new economic activity, the extra taxes the city could expect would be between $8 million and $11 million, officials at the city's Independent Budget Office said.</p>
        <p>Among the flaws in the mayor's optimistic forecast is that income taxes on the ballplayers' additional income are not very likely to net the city much, because the vast majority of Mets and Yankees have legal residences outside New York State. Players who rent in the city pay city income tax based only on the number of days they reside here annually.</p>
        <p>One place where there has clearly been an effect is at sporting goods stores, where souvenir clothing, hats, pennants and other knickknacks have been flying off the shelves. Fans have been crowding into Modell's Sporting Goods outlets as if it were the day before Christmas.</p>
        <p>Mitch Modell, the chain's president, said sales at his 55 stores last Wednesday, the day after the Yankees won the American League Championship Series, were five times greater than on the comparable day last year.</p>
        <p>''There is a fever in New York that is absolutely incredible,'' Modell said.</p>
        <p>That means extra revenues for Modell's and Major League Baseball, which collects a fee on products bearing a team logo. Unfortunately for Giuliani, the city no longer taxes the sale of clothing that costs less than $110.</p>
        <p>In the end, economists say, the real boon to New York may not be economic at all, but the less easily definable effect of upbeat news reports and free advertising for the city. The games are being broadcast in 221 markets worldwide and 19 different languages.</p>
        <p>''This is simply a great show,'' said Rosentraub, a lifelong Yankees fan. ''Let's just have a good time.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>No one doubts that the Subway Series has bathed New York in spiritual riches. It has lifted the morale of baseball fans all over the region and drawn national attention to the Big Apple; it is also a great spectacle, an epic contest between a long-reigning champion and a wild-card challenger.</p>
        <p>Local politicians have predicted glowingly that the World Series will also bring material riches to the city. But many economists say the odds that the Series will be an economic boon to New York are as great as the odds that the Chicago Cubs will win a pennant.</p>
        <p>Both Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani and Comptroller Alan G. Hevesi have said that having the Yankees and the Mets in the Series will inject hundreds of millions of dollars into the local economy and produce millions in taxes to the city.</p>
        <p>Hevesi released a report last week estimating that a seven-game Series would add, conservatively, $137.2 million to the city's economy, or between $18 million and $20 million for each game.</p>
        <p>The comptroller's economists arrived at this prediction by adding up rough estimates of revenues from sales of tickets, billboards, television and radio ads, and concession stands, then multiplying the sum by 1.5 to account for the second round of spending that is spurred when money is pumped into the local economy.</p>
        <p>For his part, Giuliani has boldly predicted that the Series will bring in between $40 million and $50 million in city taxes on everything from hotel rooms and players' salaries to sales of tickets  and merchandise.</p>
        <p>But independent economists are highly skeptical of both estimates. In fact, some say that a Series pitting a New York team against a team from another city might have been more lucrative, because it would bring in more fans from the rival metropolis.</p>
        <p>''There is no basis to think this is going to be a material lift to the New York City economy,'' said Andrew Zimbalist, a Smith College economist who is an authority on professional sports. ''The city would do better if the Mets were playing Seattle. Basically you have fewer people coming in bringing less money.''</p>
        <p>Hevesi's prediction rests on several questionable assumptions, many economists said. For example, many of the revenues the comptroller has counted as new economic activity would have come into New York's economy anyway, because Major League Baseball is based in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Take the revenues from ticket sales, the largest slice of new revenue in the comptroller's calculations. Hevesi's sports economist, John Tepper Marlin, projects at least $25 million from ticket revenues for each game at Yankee Stadium and $18.4 million for the games at Shea Stadium, counting all of it as new economic activity.</p>
        <p>But the World Series is like a traveling show produced by Major League Baseball. Every year the commissioner's office takes a third of the gate receipts for the first four games, no matter where they are played, and a larger percentage of the last three games, if they are played. In the past, about 12.5 percent of ticket revenues went to the participating teams, along with profits from concessions, billboard ads and parking fees, sports economists said.</p>
        <p>''The Yankees and the Mets will net about $3 million to $4 million, because they have some expenses,'' Zimbalist said.</p>
        <p>Of the rest of the money from ticket sales, 60 percent from the first four games goes into a pool for all major league players in the playoffs; most of that is divided among players on the winning and losing teams in the World Series. The remainder goes to other major league players.</p>
        <p>But there is no assurance that the money paid to players in New York will be spent in New York City or on products made here, economists said. Only a handful of the players on the Yankees and the Mets list their official residence in the state, and even fewer reside permanently in the city.</p>
        <p>Similar troubles arise when counting revenues from television advertisements, which the comptroller has estimated at between $2.6 million and $3.5 million for each game.</p>
        <p>Baseball officials say the playoff teams do not receive national advertising revenues. The company that does -- Fox Sports, which holds the broadcast rights to the World Series -- is based in Los Angeles. The fees paid to Major League Baseball for the broadcast rights come into the New York economy every year, no matter where the World Series is played.</p>
        <p>Dick Netzer, an economist at New York University, said that waves of tourists coming into New York to see the games would provide a true boost to the local economy, but it is unclear how many people have come for the Series.</p>
        <p>There are at least 1,400 reporters accredited to cover the games, many of them from other cities. There are also several thousand other people connected with Major League Baseball who get tickets, although baseball officials declined to give a precise number.</p>
        <p>About 3,000 tickets are given to other big-league teams for their employees. Another 400 tickets go to baseball writers around the country, while 1,500 tickets go to major league players not in the Series. Corporate sponsors also get large blocks of tickets as well, and some of those tickets may go to people from other cities.</p>
        <p>Still, the impact on New York's hotel industry is not very likely to be major, economists said, because October is already the busiest time for tourism in the city. In recent years, more than 90 percent of the city's 66,000 hotel rooms have been occupied in October, city tourism officials said.</p>
        <p>Even if one assumes that the nearly 6,000 rooms that are usually empty at this time of year are filled because of the Series, at $300 a night it would mean about $1.8 million in extra revenue, a tiny amount in a regional economy that generates about $1 billion of business a day, economists said. Looked at in that context, even the comptroller's estimate of $20 million a day in new economic activity would be a drop in the bucket.</p>
        <p>''This is going to have almost no effect,'' said Mark S. Rosentraub, an economist at Indiana University who has written extensively on the economics of baseball. ''There is going to be a small gain, but you're talking about the nation's largest regional economy.''</p>
        <p>Giuliani's visions of windfall tax revenues may also be wishful thinking. The city's effective tax rate -- the ratio between its revenues and its gross product -- is about 6 percent most years and never exceeds 8 percent. Even if one accepts the comptroller's questionable estimates of new economic activity, the extra taxes the city could expect would be between $8 million and $11 million, officials at the city's Independent Budget Office said.</p>
        <p>Among the flaws in the mayor's optimistic forecast is that income taxes on the ballplayers' additional income are not very likely to net the city much, because the vast majority of Mets and Yankees have legal residences outside New York State. Players who rent in the city pay city income tax based only on the number of days they reside here annually.</p>
        <p>One place where there has clearly been an effect is at sporting goods stores, where souvenir clothing, hats, pennants and other knickknacks have been flying off the shelves. Fans have been crowding into Modell's Sporting Goods outlets as if it were the day before Christmas.</p>
        <p>Mitch Modell, the chain's president, said sales at his 55 stores last Wednesday, the day after the Yankees won the American League Championship Series, were five times greater than on the comparable day last year.</p>
        <p>''There is a fever in New York that is absolutely incredible,'' Modell said.</p>
        <p>That means extra revenues for Modell's and Major League Baseball, which collects a fee on products bearing a team logo. Unfortunately for Giuliani, the city no longer taxes the sale of clothing that costs less than $110.</p>
        <p>In the end, economists say, the real boon to New York may not be economic at all, but the less easily definable effect of upbeat news reports and free advertising for the city. The games are being broadcast in 221 markets worldwide and 19 different languages.</p>
        <p>''This is simply a great show,'' said Rosentraub, a lifelong Yankees fan. ''Let's just have a good time.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL: SUBWAY SERIES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
