<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEW FRONT OPENS IN EFFORT TO FIGHT RACE BIAS IN LOANS</title>
    <meta content="22LOAN$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/22/national/22LOAN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241047"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Class-Action Suits</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">General Motors Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nissan Motor Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Justice Department</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Henriques, Diana B</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001022T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06EFDB1F3EF931A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1956" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEW FRONT OPENS IN EFFORT TO FIGHT RACE BIAS IN LOANS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DIANA B. HENRIQUES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Henriques, Diana B</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Class-action lawsuits filed in Nashville charge that General Motors Acceptance Corp and Nissan Motor Acceptance Corp participated in lending arrangements with car dealers that have resulted in blacks paying higher finance charges than whites on dealer-arranged loans for buying cars; companies say that statistical studies on which plaintiffs rely are profoundly flawed and that interest rates paid on loans are result of private negotiations between consumers and car dealers, who are solely responsible for any discrimination; Justice Department argues that companies should be held responsible if dealers who originate their car loans are violating federal; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two class-action lawsuits filed in Nashville against two of the nation's most prominent automobile finance companies have opened a critical new battlefront in government efforts to combat racial discrimination in the consumer credit markets.</p>
        <p>The cases, filed under seal two years ago but recently unsealed on motions by The New York Times and the ABC News program ''20/20,'' accuse the General Motors Acceptance Corporation and the Nissan Motor Acceptance Corporation of participating in lending arrangements with car dealers that have resulted in blacks paying higher finance charges than whites on dealer-arranged loans for buying cars.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Two class-action lawsuits filed in Nashville against two of the nation's most prominent automobile finance companies have opened a critical new battlefront in government efforts to combat racial discrimination in the consumer credit markets.</p>
        <p>The cases, filed under seal two years ago but recently unsealed on motions by The New York Times and the ABC News program ''20/20,'' accuse the General Motors Acceptance Corporation and the Nissan Motor Acceptance Corporation of participating in lending arrangements with car dealers that have resulted in blacks paying higher finance charges than whites on dealer-arranged loans for buying cars.</p>
        <p>Both companies have denied that their finance charges are discriminatory, saying that the statistical studies on which the plaintiffs rely are profoundly flawed. They also assert that the interest rates paid on the loans are the results of private negotiations between consumers and car dealers, who profit directly from the higher rates. So the financing companies say they should not be held responsible for any discriminatory behavior involved in arranging the loans.</p>
        <p>But their defense is drawing fire from the Justice Department, which has intervened in one of the cases on the plaintiffs' side. The department argues that lenders like Nissan Motor Acceptance and General Motors Acceptance should indeed be held responsible if the dealers who originate their car loans are violating federal fair-lending laws.</p>
        <p>With its move, the government has raised the hopes of consumer advocates, who say the cases may produce supportive rulings and fresh data that can be used to combat racial discrimination elsewhere in the marketplace.</p>
        <p>The government's stance has also put the once-obscure cases on the radar of the nation's giant consumer-credit industry. The American Financial Services Association, which represents the biggest consumer lenders in the country, has already entered the cases in support of the defendants.</p>
        <p>And the cases are clearly significant for the companies involved. Nissan Motor Acceptance, in a recent appeal of the trial judge's refusal to dismiss the case, noted that the plaintiffs were seeking compensatory damages of at least $100 million, ''an amount that would cripple N.M.A.C.''</p>
        <p>The plaintiffs in the cases are three black Nashville residents, Robert and Betty Cason, who are suing Nissan Motor Acceptance, and Addie Coleman, who is suing General Motors Acceptance. They are represented by two Nashville lawyers, Clinton W. Watkins and Michael E. Terry, with backing from the National Consumer Law Center in Boston and the New York law firm of Bernstein  Litowitz Berger &amp; Grossman.</p>
        <p>In recent interviews, conducted as part of a joint reporting project by  The Times and ABC News, Mrs. Cason and Mrs. Coleman said that they had initially sought legal help because they were upset with the deals they had received on car purchases made in 1995. But they were moved to turn their legal complaints into class-action suits, they said, because of the pain and anger they felt over the evidence of racial discrimination that their lawyers said they had uncovered.</p>
        <p>''I have two children,'' said Mrs. Coleman, in an interview to be broadcast on ABC's ''20/20'' on Friday. ''I don't want them to have to go through the same thing, you know, just because they are black.''</p>
        <p>One Nashville auto dealer has been sued by Mrs. Coleman while the other dealer involved has been sued by Nissan Motor Acceptance, which argues that the dealer should be responsible for any damages Nissan might incur. In court papers, both dealers have denied any discriminatory practices. They declined to comment on the cases.</p>
        <p>Asked to comment about the cases, General Motors Acceptance and Nissan Motor Acceptance, the financing arms of their parent automakers, emphasized their opposition to any form of racial discrimination.</p>
        <p>''The company strictly adheres to a zero-tolerance policy on racial discrimination, and will vigorously contest the allegations in the Coleman case,'' said James E. Farmer, a vice president and spokesman for General Motors Acceptance.</p>
        <p>In a statement on Friday night, Nissan Motor Acceptance said that it ''is confident that its commitment to fair lending and equal credit opportunity will be demonstrated at trial, and that the plaintiffs' misguided statistical analysis will be proven 'junk science.' ''</p>
        <p>The accusations of discrimination arise from an auto industry practice that allows a car dealer arranging financing for a customer to quote a higher interest rate for a loan than the lender has set. The lender then buys the loan from the dealer, paying him the cash value of the extra percentage points he added to the consumer's loan rate. The lender's payment to the dealer, which can be more than $1,000, is variously known  as dealer participation, finance commission and dealer markup.</p>
        <p>When economists working for the Casons and Mrs. Coleman analyzed the extra interest charges that dealers had added to loans financed by General Motors Acceptance and Nissan Motor Acceptance in Tennessee, they found that blacks were more than twice as likely as whites to have had the interest rates on their car loans increased by the dealers, according to court records. They also concluded that the extra charges were likely to be twice as high as those paid by whites, according to the records.</p>
        <p>Court files show that Mrs. Coleman had a rocky credit history. But  General Motors Acceptance agreed to finance her 1995 car loan at 18.25 percent. Her dealer, however, quoted her a loan rate of 20.75 percent and collected the additional finance charges of 2.5 percentage points.</p>
        <p>Citing those findings in a brief filed in early August, lawyers for the Justice Department's civil rights division argued that auto lenders, like any creditor, have ''a non-delegable duty to refrain from discriminating'' under the Federal Equal Credit Opportunity Act, the 26-year-old law that prohibits the denial of credit on the basis of race, gender, marital status, age and national origin.</p>
        <p>To allow lenders to deny responsibility for discriminatory pricing of the car loans that they have approved and financed simply because those prices were negotiated by the dealers ''would significantly hinder the effectiveness'' of the fair-credit laws and undermine the government's efforts to enforce them, the Justice Department argued.</p>
        <p>The brief was filed only in the Nissan Motor Acceptance case, although a government lawyer said in court that the Justice Department was prepared to file similar arguments in the case against General Motors Acceptance, one of the largest auto financing companies.</p>
        <p>The defendants assert that the department's position is a sharp departure from earlier government views on the responsibilities of auto lenders and car dealers under fair-credit laws. They also argue that the government's position is based on a completely inaccurate picture of the relationship between car dealers and  lenders who finance car purchases.</p>
        <p>The question at the heart of the dispute is whether dealers are independent businesses beyond the lenders' control, as the lenders contend, or middlemen who originate loans in exchange for a share of the interest income from those loans, as the government asserts.</p>
        <p>The Justice Department considers car dealers and auto lenders jointly responsible for any violations of fair-lending laws, said Carolyn A. Evans, a lawyer in the department's civil rights division who represented the government at a court hearing on Aug. 22 in Nashville.</p>
        <p>At the hearing, Ms. Evans enumerated all the ways that finance companies like Nissan Motor influence the negotiations between dealers and customers, for example, by designing the application forms, setting limits on the dealers' share of the financing profits and steering their  Web-site visitors to dealers.</p>
        <p>Depositions in the two Nashville cases provide support for the government's position. Employees at the two dealerships cited in the lawsuits described their roles as middlemen between the consumers and the lenders. In addition, Ms. Evans said, Nissan Motor Acceptance is the only party to the loan that actually has any money at risk.</p>
        <p>Anne Fortney, the Washington lawyer representing Nissan Motor Acceptance, disagreed. Far from being in control of what the dealers do, she said, every auto lender is competing fiercely for each dealer's new loans.</p>
        <p>The lenders can buy only those loans that the dealers offer to them, Ms. Fortney said. Any lender that refused to let dealers play a role in setting customer loan rates would soon find that the dealers would no longer bring them new business, she said.</p>
        <p>Interpretations of the Equal Credit Opportunity Act by the Federal Reserve Board staff have held that ''assignees'' -- lenders that purchase loans from others -- will not be held responsible for any credit law violations that may have been committed before they bought the loan, she said.</p>
        <p>''The Federal Reserve Board was aware of what a law could do to the industry if the law attempted to make assignees liable for what somebody else was doing,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The credit industry's concern about the issues in the Nashville cases is evident in the detailed rebuttal that has been submitted by the American Financial Services Association. Lawyers for the association warned that there were serious ''economic dangers'' inherent in holding the purchasers of car loans and other retail installment sales contracts responsible for the acts of the originating dealers.</p>
        <p>''Competition among dealers would be reduced, as would competition among banks and finance companies for the financing business that a dealer controls,'' the association said. ''Reduced competition would drive up financing costs for consumers, limit financing options and reduce credit availability.''</p>
        <p>H. Randolph Lively, the president of the association, said in a recent interview that he was surprised and skeptical about the accusations of racial discrimination raised in the Nashville cases.</p>
        <p>''The finance industry has gone a long way over the past 15 to 20 years to ensure that there is no discrimination in their operations,'' Mr. Lively said.</p>
        <p>Big commercial lenders like General Motors Acceptance have spent millions of dollars to design credit rating technology that is insulated from subjective bias, he said.</p>
        <p>The accusations of racial discrimination in the Nashville cases rest on the statistical analysis of thousands of loans made by General Motors Acceptance and Nissan Motor Acceptance to Tennessee car buyers, based on documents obtained under subpoena by the lawyers for the Casons and Mrs. Coleman.</p>
        <p>The individual loan documents were racially coded, based on state motor vehicle records, and then were subjected to a statistical analysis by Debby A. Lindsey, a professor of business at Howard University.</p>
        <p>Dr. Lindsey said she found that the amounts that dealers added to the loan rates for black consumers over and above the rates set by lenders --  the so-called markup -- were, on average, significantly higher than those for whites with the same credit ratings.</p>
        <p>Dr. Lindsey said that the data from Nissan Motor Acceptance  showed that the average markup  paid by white customers had a cash value of $507.94; the average markup for blacks had a cash value of $969.91, or $461.97 higher. In data from General Motors Acceptance, Dr. Lindsey reported the average markup for white customers had a cash value of $643.83; for blacks, the average markup was worth $959.18, or $315.35 higher.</p>
        <p>Both finance companies have strenuously disputed the method that Dr. Lindsey used to arrive at those results, arguing that differences in credit worthiness -- not race -- explained the disparities.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
