<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>150 Nations Move to Curb Tobacco Use</title>
    <meta content="22TOBA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/22/world/22TOBA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241005"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Smoking and Tobacco</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">World Health Organization</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olson, Elizabeth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Smoking and Tobacco</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001022T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02EFD81E3EF931A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="685" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>150 Nations Move to Curb Tobacco Use</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELIZABETH OLSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olson, Elizabeth</byline>
      <dateline>GENEVA, Oct. 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Officials representing nearly 150 governments lay groundwork at World Health Organization summit in Geneva, Switzerland, for new global treaty to control tobacco use and stamp out adolescent smoking; agency is pushing for strong international accord with goal of finalizing treaty by 2003 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In an atmosphere of unexpected harmony, officials representing nearly 150 governments laid the groundwork this week for a new global treaty that aims to control tobacco use and stamp out adolescent smoking.</p>
        <p>The World Health Organization is pushing for a strong international accord with the goal of finalizing a treaty by 2003. The United Nations agency, which has made eradicating smoking the centerpiece of its global public health strategy, wants the treaty to ban multinational tobacco corporations from advertising and sponsoring sports events, increase taxes to make cigarettes more expensive, combat cigarette smuggling and introduce measures to stem the rise in adolescent smoking.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In an atmosphere of unexpected harmony, officials representing nearly 150 governments laid the groundwork this week for a new global treaty that aims to control tobacco use and stamp out adolescent smoking.</p>
        <p>The World Health Organization is pushing for a strong international accord with the goal of finalizing a treaty by 2003. The United Nations agency, which has made eradicating smoking the centerpiece of its global public health strategy, wants the treaty to ban multinational tobacco corporations from advertising and sponsoring sports events, increase taxes to make cigarettes more expensive, combat cigarette smuggling and introduce measures to stem the rise in adolescent smoking.</p>
        <p>At the end of the six-day negotiating session, the chairman of the talks, Celso Amorim of Brazil, a tobacco exporter, warned that working out the details to come up with a treaty in two years might be tougher than it appeared right now.</p>
        <p>For example, he noted that most governments went on record to oppose cigarette smuggling. But, Mr. Amorim said, there was no unanimity on how to combat the problem of cigarettes pouring across borders.</p>
        <p>''Some link this with harmonizing tax systems, but others say different measures are needed,'' he said. Such details will have to be worked out over the next two years, although antismoking groups worried openly whether consensus in Geneva might be eroded once officials faced lobbying by well-funded tobacco forces.</p>
        <p>Tobacco use, according to W.H.O. statistics, kills four million people annually and threatens to claim a yearly toll of 10 million by 2030.</p>
        <p>During the six-day opening negotiations, nations were almost unanimous in calling for a ban on tobacco advertising and sponsorships. Countries as diverse as Sri Lanka, Trinidad, Thailand and Turkey, another tobacco grower, supported barring advertising. The American government was in the middle. ''We stop short of supporting a complete ban,'' said top American negotiator, Dr. Thomas Novotny, of the Department  of Health and Human Services. Such a prohibition would run afoul of free speech guarantees.</p>
        <p>Even though a few countries, including Australia, already bar such advertising, a blanket ban is likely to raise free trade concerns. Earlier this month, the European Court of Justice ruled against the European Union's planned ban on grounds it blocked free movement of goods and services.</p>
        <p>Countries have yet to grapple with complicated questions like whether the treaty would ban indirect advertisements, which include ''branding'' clothing and other stores with symbols like a camel for the well-known cigarette name. Other contentious issues include cross-border advertising, particularly in sports events, where cigarette ads are seen via television in numerous countries.</p>
        <p>Antismoking groups said American negotiators had advocated tougher stands than anticipated. The American Lung Society praised American officials for backing measures against passive smoking in facilities for children, as well as in cafes, bars and restaurants. ''Our model is California,'' Mr. Novotny, a physician, said. Only California and Vermont have sweeping bans on public smoking.</p>
        <p>A key sticking point for tobacco-growing nations is whether they will receive any financial assistance while they wean their economies from the crop. The United States, along with Canada, proposed bilateral and voluntary assistance, instead of setting up a global fund with mandatory assessments that some poor countries favor.</p>
        <p>Little was heard from the giant tobacco companies, although Philip Morris and British American Tobacco (BAT) tried to disarm their critics last week by admitting that their products are deadly and addictive.</p>
        <p>Anti-tobacco groups are urging a treaty provision that would require the companies to disclose their political activities, as well as the amounts they spend on such lobbying efforts.</p>
        <p>Among the tougher measures to be considered is a plan that the jurisdiction of the International Court of Justice be expanded to decide whether tobacco companies have committed crimes against humanity.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
