<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Long Shot Comes to Front On Day for New York Breds</title>
    <meta content="22RACI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/22/sports/22RACI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241045"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HORSE RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Empire Classic (Horse Race)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Durso, Joseph</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Race</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001022T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E0DB1F3EF931A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="634" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Long Shot Comes to Front On Day for New York Breds</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSEPH DURSO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Durso, Joseph</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Turn of the century wins Empire Classic at Belmont Park (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On a day that featured seven stakes races for horses bred in New York State, the grandest horse yesterday turned out to be a 12-1 long shot named Turnofthecentury, who won the $250,000 Empire Classic by a length and a half.</p>
        <p>The Empire Classic was the centerpiece of Belmont Park's New York showcase day, which filled the starting gates with 72 horses bred in the state competing in $1 million worth of races. The winner of the Classic was sired by the former star Holy Bull and is owned by two of the state's celebrity horsemen, Barry K. Schwartz, the new chairman of the New York Racing Association, and the man who bred the horse, Eugene Hauman.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On a day that featured seven stakes races for horses bred in New York State, the grandest horse yesterday turned out to be a 12-1 long shot named Turnofthecentury, who won the $250,000 Empire Classic by a length and a half.</p>
        <p>The Empire Classic was the centerpiece of Belmont Park's New York showcase day, which filled the starting gates with 72 horses bred in the state competing in $1 million worth of races. The winner of the Classic was sired by the former star Holy Bull and is owned by two of the state's celebrity horsemen, Barry K. Schwartz, the new chairman of the New York Racing Association, and the man who bred the horse, Eugene Hauman.</p>
        <p>Turnofthecentury took the lead coming out of the gate and held it until he was caught in the homestretch by First Rodeo. But, racing along the rail under his regular jockey, Aaron Gryder, Turnofthecentury won with some daylight over First Rodeo, with Saratoga Sunrise third. It was the fifth victory in 10 starts this year for the 3-year-old colt, who had not raced since he finished third at Saratoga on Aug. 31 behind Gratiaen, who finished seventh this time.</p>
        <p>''It has always been our stable policy to go to the lead if we have the speed,'' said Mike Hushion, who trains Turnofthecentury. And Gryder said: ''There was no secret about our game plan. We were going to the front.''</p>
        <p>Turnofthecentury ran the mile and an eighth in 1:482/5 , paid $25.80 for a $2 bet to win and went home with $150,000.</p>
        <p>Sharing the bill with the Classic were twin grass races worth $150,000 each, the Ticonderoga for fillies and mares and the Mohawk for male horses. Jerry Bailey rode Shopping for Love to a slender victory in the Ticonderoga, while Mike Smith rode Adcat home first by a nose in a four-horse finish in the Mohawk.</p>
        <p>Shopping for Love, the 2-1 favorite in the field of 13, rallied from seventh place leaving the backstretch and seized the lead in the homestretch. She kept it by three-quarters of a length over Critical Eye, who had two lengths on Terreavigne. It was the eighth time in 11 starts that Shopping for Love had finished first or second.</p>
        <p>The winner's trainer, Ken Nesky, noted that this was her first turf victory in four starts, but remembered that she had twice lost grass races recently to Gaviola, the stakes-winning filly.</p>
        <p>In the Mohawk, it took a blanket finish and then a photo finish to determine the winner. Adcat, a 5-year-old son of Storm Cat trained by Mark Hennig with Mike Smith riding, scored by a neck over Pebo's Guy, who saved second place by the length of his nose over Doctor Cat, with Invitation closing for fourth. It was the first time that Adcat had made the winner's circle in 10 starts.</p>
        <p>''He's got to be wide of horses,'' Smith said, ''otherwise he gets real timid. He dug in real game on the outside.''</p>
        <p>Favorites won both races for 2-year-olds, the Sleepy Hollow for colts and the Maid of the Mist for fillies. In the Sleepy Hollow, it was Le Grande Danceur, trained by Dominic Galluscio, by a nose over Backstreet Blues; and in the filly race, My Lady Avie, trained by David Donk with John Velazquez aboard, scored by half a length over Indy Glory.</p>
        <p>The Hudson was won by Stalwart Member, a 7-year-old gelding trained by Cleveland Johnson with Jorge Chavez riding. The Iroquois was taken by a nose by Biogio's Rose, trained by Robby Ribaudo with Norberto Arroyo in the saddle, inches in front of Miss Thermal Tech.</p>
        <p>HORSE RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
