<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Newark Journal; A Slice of the Old City, On Rye, With Schmaltz</title>
    <meta content="22JOUR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="40" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/22/nyregion/22JOUR.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241017"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Delicatessens</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Newark (NJ)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hobby's Delicatessen (Newark, NJ)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jacobs, Andrew</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brummer, Sam</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001022T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E0D61E3EF931A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1159" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Newark Journal; A Slice of the Old City, On Rye, With Schmaltz</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW JACOBS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jacobs, Andrew</byline>
      <dateline>NEWARK, Oct. 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Hobby's, delicatessen on Branford Place in Newark, has been run by Sam Brummer for 40 years; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sam Brummer wants you to have lunch.</p>
        <p>Actually, it's far more serious than that.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sam Brummer wants you to have lunch.</p>
        <p>Actually, it's far more serious than that.</p>
        <p>''Sit down and eat,'' he says, the way a cop might advise you to drop your gun and put up your hands. ''Have a sandwich!''</p>
        <p>Just then a small herd of lawyers from Prudential pours through the door and Mr. Brummer, 77, is transformed into a delicatessen dervish. Backs are slapped, menus go flying, and tables begin to sag under the weight of artery-clogging wonders. No one will leave hungry.</p>
        <p>For 40 years Mr. Brummer has  lured the famished and the peckish to Hobby's, his knish-and-corned beef refuge on Branford Place. Here, where a dozen or so Jewish delicatessens once flourished, only Hobby's remains, sustained by a devoted stream of jurors, judges and nostalgia-craving suburbanites.</p>
        <p>''This is really the last outpost of what was Newark's glorious past,'' said Ben Slavitt, 65, a lawyer who, like his father before him, has eaten  here most of his life. ''Everything around it has changed, but Hobby's has stayed the same.'' He slurped off the rest of his Dr. Brown's black cherry soda as if to drive home his point.</p>
        <p>When a kitchen fire destroyed his restaurant in 1992, Mr. Brummer reconstructed the place, right down to the knotty-pine paneling and linoleum floor tiles. For months after he reopened, the faithful, spooked by the near death of their beloved luncheonette, formed lines around the block.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brummer, who bought the deli in 1962, says he never considered giving up on Newark, even when the last of the street's four movie houses  closed and most of Branford Place's law firms fled for suburban office parks. ''This town has been very, very good to me,'' he said in a voice made gravelly by cigarettes before a triple bypass put an end to his smoking. ''No matter how bad things got here, I always had business.''</p>
        <p>The Brummer clan has unwavering faith in Newark, which suffered  after the 1967 riots destroyed large swaths of the city and persuaded a few hundred thousand residents to leave. Mr. Brummer's wife, Rona, works here, as do their sons, Michael and Marc. Mrs. Brummer's mother, 89, still maintains a fierce grip on the restaurant's payroll.</p>
        <p>''I guess we have pastrami flowing through our veins,'' said Marc Brummer, 38, who went to law school and dabbled in advertising before returning to his true calling.</p>
        <p>Six days a week the Brummer boys get up before dawn to compose the platters that end up in corporate boardrooms by noon. Hobby's clocks are set 15 minutes fast, to make sure no one ever has to wait, God forbid, for his triple decker (tongue, turkey and pastrami) or No. 5 special (pastrami, corned beef, Russian dressing and cole slaw on rye).</p>
        <p>Like his deli, Sam Brummer is a  survivor. He left Poland in 1939 as a teenager, months before the Nazis arrived. The rest of his family was not as lucky, and Mr. Brummer can count dozens of relatives he never saw again. On D-Day in 1944, as a newly minted American, he was in the Normandy landing at Omaha Beach and witnessed the deaths of countless friends.</p>
        <p>''I still can't talk about it,'' he said  about the pain in his past. He shuffled through a wad of sandwich orders, as if they might block his tears. ''Somehow I've survived.''</p>
        <p>But with 100 hungry mouths to feed, there was no time to dwell on the past. By 1 p.m., lunchtime frenzy was in full swing. Mr. Brummer knew almost everyone by name and preferences. Carl Greenberg, a 40-year regular, was having his corned beef and cream soda. Artie Davidson was finishing off his tuna on white toast, as he does five days a week.</p>
        <p>At Table 14, Kelly and Dan Marx, father and son, were sharing the pastrami and Swiss. The elder Mr. Marx  confessed a loyalty that predated the invention of chopped liver and schmaltz. ''Growing up in Newark, we'd come down here every Friday night, have dinner and then go see a movie,'' said Mr. Marx, 67, whose family has owned Clinton Milk Company, a dairy, since 1921. Like most of the other old-timers, he cannot  help becoming misty-eyed over the Newark that once was. ''What a town,'' he said, shaking his head.</p>
        <p>Old Newark and its Jewish neighborhood of Weequahic live on in the memory of thousands of suburban Essex County residents. There were the restaurants: Brothers, Sinclair's and Perry's. On any given Saturday,  Frank Sinatra, Woody Herman, Harry James or the Three Stooges might be on stage, or at a booth, at the Tavern. Children were always well mannered, and no one ever locked his door at night.</p>
        <p>''It was a classy community, the premier community,'' said Monroe Krichman of Millburn, 63, who still goes to the reunions of Weequahic High athletes. ''No one had money and we all struggled, but I'd say we were all in love with it.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Brummer can always tell when long-lost Newarkers walk through the door. Overwhelmed by the aroma of warm brisket, they invariably shake their head as if they've seen a ghost. ''This is Newark?'' Mr. Brummer said, mimicking the usual response, a pencil wedged behind his ear. ''This is Newark? What's going on here?''</p>
        <p>These days, a lot is going on in Newark. There's the new performing arts center, the minor league baseball stadium and a growing cadre of office workers. If all goes according to plan, there may even be a new arena for the Nets and the Devils just down the block from Hobby's.</p>
        <p>''My generation only saw the hopelessness of Newark,'' said Michael Brummer, 35, just back from a delivery to Short Hills. ''I can't believe what's happening. I'm glad we're around to enjoy the good times.''</p>
        <p>Hobby's would probably not be around if it weren't for Sam Brummer's sons. They grew up busing tables and slicing lox weekends and summers, but he never imagined they'd wear deli aprons as adults.</p>
        <p>''As kids, my dad's mantra was, 'Do anything but this,' '' Marc Brummer said. ''We tried to, but we love this place. Where else can you work with your family and still speak to them at the end of the day?''</p>
        <p>What about the next generation of Brummers? Marc's son David, 8, is already talking about a career in the sandwich business, Marc said. ''If he can find something else that he likes to do, he should do it,'' Marc said. ''But then again, who am I to say no?''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
