<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bereft Russia Hears Putin's Mea Culpa on Sub Accident</title>
    <meta content="Y24RUS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224916"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Kursk (Submarine)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Submarines</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Barents Sea</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Putin, Vladimir V (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wines, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Submarines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000824T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E5D71731F937A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1319" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bereft Russia Hears Putin's Mea Culpa on Sub Accident</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL WINES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wines, Michael</byline>
      <dateline>MOSCOW, Aug. 23</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Vladimir V Putin moves decisively to contain political impact of the loss of the submarine Kursk, going on national television to say he feels the full sense of guilt and responsibility for the crisis; says measuring out responsibility must wait for a full investigation of what caused the submarine to explode and plunge to Barents Sea floor; suggests that tortuous pace of the military's rescue effort, and his own seeming diffidence at the start, played no role in sailors' deaths because they were doomed from the moment the submarine went down; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As Russia grieved for 118 seamen lost in the remains of the submarine Kursk, President Vladimir V. Putin moved decisively to contain the incident's political impact, going on national television tonight to take responsibility for what some Russians call a badly botched response.</p>
        <p>In an abruptly scheduled half-hour interview on the state-controlled television network RTR, Mr. Putin said a family member of a submarine crewman had told him that the sinking was his cross to bear as president, and that ''this person was right.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As Russia grieved for 118 seamen lost in the remains of the submarine Kursk, President Vladimir V. Putin moved decisively to contain the incident's political impact, going on national television tonight to take responsibility for what some Russians call a badly botched response.</p>
        <p>In an abruptly scheduled half-hour interview on the state-controlled television network RTR, Mr. Putin said a family member of a submarine crewman had told him that the sinking was his cross to bear as president, and that ''this person was right.''</p>
        <p>''In spite of the fact that I have been in office in the Kremlin a little over 100 days, I feel the full sense of guilt and responsibility for this crisis,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Putin said that Defense Minister Igor D. Sergeyev and the commander of the navy's Northern Fleet had offered their resignations on Tuesday and that they had been rejected, at least until experts found what caused the submarine to explode and plunge to the Barents Sea floor just before midnight on Aug. 12.</p>
        <p>''We have to get an objective picture of the reasons for this tragedy,'' Mr. Putin said. ''Only after that can we make some decisions.''</p>
        <p>But at the same time, he broadly suggested that the tortuous pace of the military's rescue effort, and his own seeming diffidence at the start of the incident, played no role in the sailors' deaths because they were doomed from the moment the submarine went down.</p>
        <p>Mr. Putin's somber mea culpa and explanation were clearly intended to quell criticism, which continued today even after he returned from a tightly scripted visit to the Arctic town of Vidyayevo to offer condolences to families of the perished sailors.</p>
        <p>The military has come under scathing attack for its inability to pry open the listing submarine in a week of attempts, especially after a crew of Norwegian and British deep-sea divers arrived and opened the submarine's damaged hatch with apparent ease.</p>
        <p>For his part, Mr. Putin has been criticized for staying on vacation in the Black Sea resort of Sochi, once the preserve of senior Communist Party officials, for days after one of modern Russia's worst military fiascos began to unfold.</p>
        <p>The affair has dented Mr. Putin's once-bulletproof reputation for competence and efficiency, though it is not clear whether the damage is either severe or lasting.</p>
        <p>A poll of 1,574 people released today by the All-Russian Public Opinion Center concluded that one in five respondents attribute the incident to the Kremlin's poor control of the military.</p>
        <p>A second poll suggested that Mr. Putin's popularity had also slipped, but that almost two in three Russians still approved of his performance, a level most politicians would envy.</p>
        <p>In his interview tonight, Mr. Putin insisted that it was premature to accuse the military of incompetence, and that a naval rescue effort began ''the moment contact with the submarine was lost.''</p>
        <p>Similarly, he said, Norway's offer to help in the rescue was immediately accepted, at least in principle, and that the much-criticized two-day delay in sending Norwegian divers to the site was dictated by unnamed ''technical parameters.''</p>
        <p>One question that Mr. Putin said investigators would explore is why the Russian Navy was unable to mount the type of deep-sea diving operation that Norway employed to open the hatch. Russia is not capable of sending divers to the 350-foot depth at which the Kursk now lies.</p>
        <p>While that alone would not have saved any crewmen, he said, investigators need to study why the Russian Navy was not prepared to rescue sailors trapped in one of its own submarines.</p>
        <p>The Kremlin said today that Mr. Putin had sent the head of the Federal Security Service -- the domestic successor to the K.G.B. -- and the government's general prosecutor to Murmansk, near the Kursk's home port of Severomorsk, to oversee a preliminary criminal inquiry.</p>
        <p>Although no evidence of a crime exists, military officials continued to insist today that the most likely cause of the Kursk's sinking was a collision with an unidentified foreign vessel that they claim to have detected with sonar on the sea floor near the submarine.</p>
        <p>A senior military official, quoted anonymously by the semiofficial Interfax news service, said today that the navy had dispatched three ships to scour the seabed off the Kola Peninsula for pieces of a second vessel.</p>
        <p>Russian sources have variously hinted that an American or British ship might have been involved in the incident, but both nations have flatly denied any role.</p>
        <p>On the day Mr. Putin had set aside for grieving over the naval disaster, it was apparent today that the Kursk's sinking has hit typically stoic Russians with unusual force.</p>
        <p>The Kursk incident continues to consume newspapers and television news broadcasts, which were filled today with somber music and roll calls of the dead, and both local governments and individuals were massing donations for the seamen's survivors. Flags everywhere were strung at half-staff.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Putin promised the families more than a dozen years of military pay to compensate for their loss, the total pay will amount only to about $7,000 per family, and charitable efforts to increase that figure have sprung up across the country.</p>
        <p>In Rostov-on-Don, Russian television reported, the government pledged 30,000 rubles, or about $1,100 per family, to the survivors of two crewmen who had lived there.</p>
        <p>In Moscow, Patriarch Aleksy, the leader of the Russian Orthodox Church, led a service for the crewmen in which he urged the nation to put aside finger-pointing and unite around the families of the crew.</p>
        <p>''I call on you today to come together before the face of the common calamity,'' he said, ''not to split, not to look for the guilty, not to draw fast conclusions, but to accept what happened as our common cross. And the cross, no matter what it can be, has to be carried.''</p>
        <p>Only in Vidyayevo were observances postponed -- at the families' request -- until the Kursk's crew is brought home for burial. When that might be was unclear.</p>
        <p>With the sailors' fate now sealed, officials here and in Norway began today to address the knotty questions of whether and when the huge submarine, now a grave for its crew and for two nuclear reactors, can be safely raised from the sea floor.</p>
        <p>Experts in both countries agreed today that the two reactors, which were shut down in the Kursk's plunge to the seabed, have not leaked radiation into the surrounding waters. But environmentalists likened the submarine to a radioactive time bomb, warning that sooner or later, a catastrophic leak was inevitable.</p>
        <p>At the same time, some officials studying ways to salvage the Kursk said any operation to raise the damaged submarine held some risk that the vessel would break apart as it rose to the surface.</p>
        <p>Still, the families pressed the government to recover the bodies immediately, before the severe Arctic winter sets in in a few weeks, and Russian officials were considering plans to cut holes in the submarine to remove the dead.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
