<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Critic's Notebook; Machiavelli, on a Desert Isle, Meets TV's Reality. Unreal.</title>
    <meta content="24CRIT$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224997"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cbs Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">James, Caryn</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hatch, Richard</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Survivor (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000824T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03EFDB1431F937A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1053" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Critic's Notebook; Machiavelli, on a Desert Isle, Meets TV's Reality. Unreal.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CARYN JAMES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">James, Caryn</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Caryn James Critic's Notebook on the CBS hit series Survivor, whose success she says is due less to any 'reality' it had than to the way it was structured and cast as a piece of psychological gripping entertainment; photo of Richard Hatch, winning survivor (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Last summer's cheery television phenomenon, ''Who Wants to Be a Millionaire,'' has been displaced this summer by a hit with a more scheming world view. ''Millionaire'' is the feel-good game show that says we're a happy country pulling together, but ''Survivor'' sends a countermessage: trust no one.</p>
        <p>''Survivor'' put 16 people on an island and forced the group to vote members off one by one, until last night's finale, when the sole survivor won a million dollars. The strongest contestants endure by banding together, but in the end were forced to vote against one another. The island was a microcosm of dog-eat-dog competition, staged at a safe distance. Just as murder mysteries transform our fear of death into a playful entertainment, ''Survivor'' turns the competitive nightmare of contemporary life into a benign game.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Last summer's cheery television phenomenon, ''Who Wants to Be a Millionaire,'' has been displaced this summer by a hit with a more scheming world view. ''Millionaire'' is the feel-good game show that says we're a happy country pulling together, but ''Survivor'' sends a countermessage: trust no one.</p>
        <p>''Survivor'' put 16 people on an island and forced the group to vote members off one by one, until last night's finale, when the sole survivor won a million dollars. The strongest contestants endure by banding together, but in the end were forced to vote against one another. The island was a microcosm of dog-eat-dog competition, staged at a safe distance. Just as murder mysteries transform our fear of death into a playful entertainment, ''Survivor'' turns the competitive nightmare of contemporary life into a benign game.</p>
        <p>The hype surrounding the show has generally glossed over the deeper reasons for its success, but the fact that Richard Hatch survived to win the million dollars at the end of last night's finale speaks directly to why the series has touched a chord. He coldbloodedly strategized from the start. It's no accident that he was always identified as a corporate trainer, almost the embodiment of cutthroat maneuvers.</p>
        <p>As two finalists faced a jury of those they had cast off, one said she was not so much for Richard as against Kelly Wiglesworth, the runner-up and a former ally who had turned against her. Richard was a snake, she said, but Kelly was a rat.  Kelly herself had asked in an aside to the camera in the final weeks, ''How do you stay true to yourself and maintain integrity and still play this game?'' She answered her own question: ''You can't.''</p>
        <p>The standard line about ''Survivor'' has been: it is a reality game show featuring ordinary people, plus one scheming villain to hiss at. But that is entirely backward. ''Survivor'' is as remote from reality as its setting, Pulau Tiga (likely translation: Island of the Product Placements) and as meticulously structured as a novel by Agatha Christie (whose ''Ten Little Indians'' plot it brilliantly mimics). And though its characters may be genuine to their family and friends, to the average viewer they are as real as Brad Pitt.</p>
        <p>That visceral response to Richard's conniving wouldn't have materialized if the show didn't work as pure entertainment. Even the best orchestrated hype (which CBS had) isn't enough to account for the endless chattering among viewers. ''Survivor'' drew a gigantic audience with a combination of sports challenges and the suspense of who gets kicked off the island: Agatha Christie goes to the Olympics. (The island itself was as realistic and as hokey as a haunted house.)</p>
        <p>And each episode was edited into a swift hour. ''Survivor'' never spent more than a few seconds watching someone eat rice. ''Elapsed time: 4 hours 11 minutes'' flashed on the screen after the minutes spent in last night's contest about who could stand the longest with a hand on a totem pole. Take away ruthless editing, and you end up watching people feed the chickens, as they have on CBS's tiresome ''Big Brother.''</p>
        <p>That totem pole contest, an ''immunity challenge,'' was part of this game's most wickedly unpredictable feature. In each episode one person won a contest and could not be voted out in that round; so-called immunity was the wild card that made every rational prediction moot. Kelly would have been gone weeks ago, but she won four immunity challenges in a row to become one of the final two survivors.</p>
        <p>But only part of the series's constantly growing ratings came from the suspense. The show got progressively more gripping as it became progressively more psychological. What started out as a sporting challenge (build a hut, eat a rat) turned into a tantalizing mind game, driven largely by Rich.</p>
        <p>The truest voyeurism, after all, is looking into someone else's thoughts, and that is what truly drove ''Survivor.'' The most compelling moments were those in which the contestants spoke directly to the camera, confidentially to us, letting us into the secrets of their sometimes backbiting strategies.</p>
        <p>In one episode Colleen sits in a tree, looks sweetly into the camera and says she'll vote Richard off the island because he's too bossy. (What an innocent.) In a later episode Richard, the supposed villain, looks into the camera and says coolly, ominously of Gretchen, ''She has to go because she is bright and is strong, and she is a threat.'' Gretchen is gone that night. The message about who wins in life is unmistakable. Of course the editors knew the winner in advance: they clearly edited to focus on Rich and make him the audience-drawing villain.</p>
        <p>The show's producers selected these contestants shrewdly, to cover the social spectrum, from Sean, a neurologist, to Susan, a truck driver so tough her husband boasted in an interview, ''She's a man in a woman's body.'' It was a dazzling stroke to bring the contestants videos from home a few weeks ago. Viewers saw Gervase's daughter toddling toward the camera and watched Jenna, the mother of twin girls, cry when she heard her video had not arrived. Those humanizing moments were the equivalent of up-close-and-personal profiles of sports stars.</p>
        <p>We do not actually know these people any better than we know the latest celebrity interviewed on ''Entertainment Tonight,'' of course. The irony is that the success of ''Survivor'' has made these real people less real to us, as they have taken on the flattened images of celebrities. (And their post-''Survivor'' show-business plans are just starting.) Richard had already achieved a measure of fame. Say ''the naked fat guy,'' and everyone knows who you mean. And admit it: you secretly like him. That may be the biggest, most revealing ''Survivor'' secret of all.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
