<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Arts of Many Cultures, From Quilts to Bridges</title>
    <meta content="24CAL.$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224873"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000824T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E2DE1731F937A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="685" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Arts of Many Cultures, From Quilts to Bridges</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>'A Promise Unfulfilled'  Newark Museum, 49 Washington Street at Central Avenue, Newark; (973) 596-6550.</p>
        <p>''Katherine Choy: A Promise Unfulfilled,'' an exhibition of works by the ceramics artist, who died in 1958 when she was 29, starts Wednesday and runs through Jan. 7.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>'A Promise Unfulfilled'  Newark Museum, 49 Washington Street at Central Avenue, Newark; (973) 596-6550.</p>
        <p>''Katherine Choy: A Promise Unfulfilled,'' an exhibition of works by the ceramics artist, who died in 1958 when she was 29, starts Wednesday and runs through Jan. 7.</p>
        <p>Ms. Choy, a Chinese immigrant, studied art in the United States and was part of a tradition in studio ceramics that drew from Chinese and Japanese design. In the late 1950's, she began experimenting with sculptural forms featuring broken shapes and brushed glazes that evoke Abstract Expressionist paintings.</p>
        <p>The museum is open Wednesday through Sunday, noon to 5 p.m. (Thursday until 8:30 p.m.) No charge for admission.</p>
        <p>By Norwegian Hands  Ellis Island Immigration Museum, Ellis Island; (212) 363-3200.</p>
        <p>''Norwegians in New York, 1825-2000: Builders of City, Community and Culture,'' will be at the museum through Oct. 14. The exhibition of photographs, architectural drawings, tools and personal belongings of immigrants examines the work of some of the Norwegian architects, engineers and carpenters who worked on New York sites like the Empire State and Chrysler buildings, the George Washington Bridge, the Holland and Lincoln tunnels and several of the subway lines. Open daily, 9:30 a.m. to 5 p.m. Tickets, including ferry service, $7; those 62 and older, $6; those 3 to 17 years old, $3.</p>
        <p>Folk Art Classes  Folk Art Institute, 555 West 57th Street; (212) 977-7170.</p>
        <p>The institute will offer several lecture courses, from 5 to 15 sessions long, starting on Sept. 6, on subjects including Latin American folk art; sculpture; American quilts; and the history and appreciation of folk art. The fees for the courses range from $100 to $200; participants may attend individual talks for $30 each.</p>
        <p>There are also five-day hands-on courses in furniture decorating or decorative finishes, and several daylong workshops, including introductory quilting, animal painting and making a Shaker-style basket. The fees, not including materials, are $150 for the five-day courses and $85 for the daylong workshops.</p>
        <p>Reservations are required for all programs. A complete schedule is available by calling.</p>
        <p>A Display of Ikebana  John P. Humes Japanese Stroll Garden, Dogwood Lane and Oyster Bay Road, Mill Neck, N.Y.; (516) 676-4486.</p>
        <p>On Saturday and Sunday, from 11:30 a.m. to 4:30 p.m., the garden will offer an exhibition of ikebana, or Japanese flower arranging. Admission is $5; children under 10, no charge.</p>
        <p>Crafts in Connecticut  Brookfield Craft Center, junction of Routes 25 and 7, Brookfield, Conn.; (203) 775-4526.</p>
        <p>An exhibition of women's artworks inspired by women's daily lives  starts Sunday and runs through Oct. 22. The works use such common objects as quilts, aprons, laundry baskets and ballet slippers to explore issues like nurturing, domesticity and femininity. Open Monday through Saturday, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sunday, noon to 5 p.m. No charge.</p>
        <p>The center's open house, which will introduce classes in quilting, jewelry making, woodworking, pottery, glass blowing, weaving and basketry, will be held on Sept. 3, from 1 to 4 p.m. No charge for admission.</p>
        <p>Textiles From Anatolia  Textile Museum, 2320 S Street NW, Washington; (202) 667-0441.</p>
        <p>''Tribal Traditions: Village and Nomadic Weavings From Anatolia,'' an exhibition of more than 35 textiles from the 19th and early 20th centuries, starts tomorrow and runs through Jan. 28.</p>
        <p>Anatolia is a historic area in western Asia roughly contained within the borders of Turkey. The textiles in the exhibition, which include bags, tent bands and rugs, feature colorful signature designs common to different groups.</p>
        <p>Open Monday through Saturday, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sunday, 1 to 5 p.m. Admission is by suggested donation of $5.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
