<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Eastern Fantasia, Asleep for a Century</title>
    <meta content="24LOCK$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224850"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DESIGN NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Interior Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Owens, Mitchell</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">de Forest, Lockwood</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Merchant, Ismail</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ivory, James</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden/Columns/Design Notebook</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interior Design</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000824T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE1D81631F937A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1730" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Eastern Fantasia, Asleep for a Century</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MITCHELL OWENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Owens, Mitchell</byline>
      <dateline>CLAVERACK, N.Y.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lockwood de Forest, turn-of-the-century artist and designer who rose to eminence then sank into obscurity, is on brink of rediscovery; exhibit of his work, notably by filmmakers Ismail Merchant and James Ivory in probably first one-man design show since 1893 World's Columbian Exhibition discussed; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TREND-WATCHERS, take note: Lockwood de Forest may be big. Very big.</p>
        <p>De Forest, a turn-of-the-century artist and designer who rose to eminence, then sank into obscurity, is now on the brink of rediscovery. A Manhattan gallery recently featured some of his oil sketches. A desk embodying his design philosophy is part of an exhibition on Orientalism at Williams College in Massachusetts. The Indian-style interiors he championed are being echoed by hip designers like Muriel Brandolini and Lulu Kwiatkowski. And in this Hudson River Valley village two hours north of New York City, furniture and architectural elements he produced have been brought together by the filmmakers Ismail Merchant and James Ivory in what must be his first one-man design show since the 1893 World's Columbian Exhibition.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TREND-WATCHERS, take note: Lockwood de Forest may be big. Very big.</p>
        <p>De Forest, a turn-of-the-century artist and designer who rose to eminence, then sank into obscurity, is now on the brink of rediscovery. A Manhattan gallery recently featured some of his oil sketches. A desk embodying his design philosophy is part of an exhibition on Orientalism at Williams College in Massachusetts. The Indian-style interiors he championed are being echoed by hip designers like Muriel Brandolini and Lulu Kwiatkowski. And in this Hudson River Valley village two hours north of New York City, furniture and architectural elements he produced have been brought together by the filmmakers Ismail Merchant and James Ivory in what must be his first one-man design show since the 1893 World's Columbian Exhibition.</p>
        <p>Scion of a New York clan whose family tree blossoms with myriad lawyers and the occasional flamboyant -- a great-uncle was the painter Frederic E. Church, and a great-niece was the Warhol superstar Edie Sedgwick -- Lockwood de Forest was a pivotal member of Associated Artists, a short-lived design firm founded by Louis Comfort Tiffany.</p>
        <p>Its specialty was self-conscious splendor, exotic interiors that were one part ABC Carpet &amp; Home, one part ''Arabian Nights.'' Brass lanterns hung from stenciled ceilings. Persian carpets were flung over harem-style balustrades. Fireplaces glimmered with Moorish tiles. And thanks to a woodcarving studio that de Forest discovered in Ahmadabad, on the Arabian Sea coast of India, his trendy ensembles for clients like the Baltimore &amp; Ohio Railroad heiress Mary Garrett and her lover Martha Carey Thomas, a president of Bryn Mawr College, incorporated exquisite teak furniture and architectural fittings that resemble petrified lace.</p>
        <p>The eight chairs, two tables, chest of drawers, fireplace surround, two doors, two settees and standing screen in ''Lockwood de Forest'' at the Merchant and Ivory Foundation exemplify the top-dollar exoticism that was de Forest's hallmark in the 1880's, the high point of a fitful career that ended when he died in 1932 at 82. Rendered in cinnamon-colored teak with delicately chiseled foliate and geometric designs -- there are a couple of cast-iron firebacks, too -- most of the pieces come from the collection of David L. Petrovsky, who owns an eponymous antiques shop in nearby Hudson.</p>
        <p>On a recent visit, Mr. Petrovsky gazed wide-eyed at the feet of a gleaming armchair produced by Indian woodcarvers working under de Forest's direction. ''Look at those,'' he said. ''They look like garlic bulbs with toenails.'' Eye-catchingly odd, yes, but no more so than the bizarre finials higher up: the heads of impassive Hindu deities surmounted by sawtooth tiaras. The show, which closes Sept. 4, is one of several marking the 10th anniversary of the Merchant and Ivory Foundation, an arts organization founded by the Oscar-winning filmmakers. Its headquarters are in red-painted gristmill buildings near their Greek Revival house, which have been turned into exhibition and performance spaces.</p>
        <p>''We've never had a show like this,'' said Mr. Ivory, whose latest film, an adaptation of Henry James's ''Golden Bowl,'' starring Uma Thurman, will open this fall. ''But a couple of months ago, David suggested it, and Ismail and I thought, 'Why not?' De Forest's work is very intriguing, and both Ismail and I are fascinated by everything to do with India, for obvious reasons.''</p>
        <p>Lockwood de Forest was not the only American aesthete of his time who fell under the spell of India, a country that became a pop-culture influence after Queen Victoria became its empress in 1876. But the largely self-taught artist, designer and architect was the most passionately pro-India Yankee of his time, the American equivalent of John Lockwood Kipling, father of the empire-thumping poet and curator of a museum in the Indian city of Lahore (now in Pakistan) in the days of the British Raj.</p>
        <p>Just as the elder Kipling's scholarship led him to create widely admired Indian-style rooms -- a dining room at Queen Victoria's Osborne House on the Isle of Wight and a billiard room for her son the Duke of Connaught at his country house in Surrey, Bagshot Park, now the home of Prince Edward -- de Forest's passion for the Mogul art and architecture of the subcontinent led him to install similar spaces from Ithaca to San Francisco.</p>
        <p>''The 1880's were his glory days,'' said Roberta A. Mayer, an art historian, who lives in Hopewell, N.J. De Forest's work was exhibited to acclaim at the Colonial and Indian Exhibition in London in 1886, and at the World's Columbian Exhibition seven years later, attracting an impressive array of clients: the steel king Andrew Carnegie, the transportation magnate Charles Tyson Yerkes, the hotelier Potter Palmer, even Mark Twain.</p>
        <p>Though he did not have a hand in its design, a stylistically related desk by Associated Artists is featured in ''Noble Dreams, Wicked Pleasures: Orientalism in America, 1870-1930,'' an exhibition that runs through Sept. 4 at the Sterling and Francine Clark Art Institute at Williams College in Williamstown, Mass. Made of satinwood, brass, pewter and leather, it embodies everything that Associated Artists and de Forest stood for in the late 19th century: Eastern exoticism conjured for Western millionaires.</p>
        <p>De Forest visited India on his honeymoon in 1879, a nearly two-year trip that he turned to his economic advantage, keeping his eye peeled for objects and inspirations that would benefit Associated Artists. In Ahmadabad, he met Muggunbhai Hutheesing, a philanthropist whose woodcarving studio would become crucial to de Forest's career. The studio was only a small component of a family fortune built on some of India's largest carpet and textile factories, as well as on opium trafficking.</p>
        <p>Unlike European Orientalists, many of whom looked upon Asia and the Middle East with colonialist superiority, de Forest wanted to help the cause of Indian woodworkers and preserve traditional Indian arts and crafts, which were being forgotten in the wake of brightly varnished knockoffs being made in Paris. His equally enthusiastic wife, Meta, had her couturier transform cheap Indian cottons into dresses that were the envy of her friends -- until they learned of the fabrics' ''lowly'' (i.e., non-Western) provenance.</p>
        <p>''Having committed themselves as to the beauty of the material, it was difficult for them to crawl out of it with either grace or success,'' Lockwood de Forest gleefully recalled. ''We had a fine chance to rub their ignorance in, which we often enjoyed doing.'' By directing Hutheesing's carvers to copy or adapt centuries-old details from mosques, temples, tombs and mansions --  designs that were used in de Forest's interiors, furniture and accessories, including a wall bracket at Olana, the house of Great-Uncle Frederic -- one small part of India's artistry could continue to flourish, albeit reinterpreted in costly Western settings.</p>
        <p>Part of him had a romantic response to all that beauty, but he was pragmatic, too, Ms. Mayer said: ''He wanted to make his art into a legitimate profession, a way to create beauty and make money at the same time.''</p>
        <p>Unfortunately, de Forest's Indian experiment appealed to a fickle audience too conscious of fads to be loyal to his narrow vision. By the turn of the century, his romantic rooms were passe, a victim of the Francophile chic popularized by Elsie de Wolfe and Ogden Codman Jr. By 1908, he had sold his stock of moldings and furniture to his old friend Tiffany and retired to Santa Barbara, Calif., where he spent much of his remaining life quietly painting. (His son, another Lockwood, would become one of the state's great landscape designers.)</p>
        <p>Apparently, not one de Forest interior survives intact, and even the bits and pieces remaining are not completely appreciated. His teak room for Andrew Carnegie, for instance, still occupies its second-floor spot in the Cooper-Hewitt Museum, the former Carnegie mansion, though its furniture was sold long ago and its carvings are obscured under temporary exhibition walls. As for de Forest's furniture, no one knows precisely how much was produced, a mystery that deepens when it becomes clear that none was labeled or marked, thus making it difficult to distinguish it from the often fine copies produced by competitors.</p>
        <p>But it does show up periodically, often misidentified, at auctions and other, less likely, places. In 1995, Mr. Petrovsky discovered a seven-piece suite of furniture in a consignment shop in New Canaan, Conn. He says that Mitchell Wolfson Jr., founder of the Wolfsonian museum in Miami Beach, recently bought more than 100 pieces of carved teak, each a different pattern and individually numbered, apparently a set of samples that the artist used to guide the Ahmadabad carvers.</p>
        <p>Even with the uncertainty, some of Lockwood de Forest's magic lingers. A house he designed in Baltimore is now an Indian restaurant called the Brass Elephant. His furnishings for Mary Garrett are scattered throughout several rooms in the Bryn Mawr alumnae house. As for the brick town house that de Forest built for himself at 7 East 10th Street between 1886 and 1888, once heralded as the most Indian house in America, it is now the Bronfman Center for Jewish Student Life at New York University. Its extraordinary lacelike interiors have suffered over time, but its teak-bedecked facade, like that of the elaborate Burmese-style Ava apartments next door, is splendidly unaltered, an incongruous reminder of a trendsetter who once reigned in a city that too often forgets.</p>
        <p>The Lockwood de Forest exhibition is open for the next two weekends, Aug. 25 to 27 and Sept. 1 to 4, at the Red Mills gallery, on Route 23 just east of Patroon Street in Claverack, N.Y. Hours: 1 to 5 P.M. Free admission. Information: (212) 586-6014.</p>
        <p>DESIGN NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
