<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hussein Aide Says Iraq Won't Cooperate With Arms Monitoring</title>
    <meta content="Y24IRA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224901"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biological and Chemical Warfare</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Crossette, Barbara</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Aziz, Tariq (Deputy Prime Min)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Biological and Chemical Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000824T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEFDA1731F937A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="585" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hussein Aide Says Iraq Won't Cooperate With Arms Monitoring</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA CROSSETTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Crossette, Barbara</byline>
      <dateline>UNITED NATIONS, Aug. 23</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Two-day meeting of international arms inspection experts convenes at United Nations to review new monitoring operations for Iraq, but Tariq Aziz, Iraq's deputy prime minister, denounces the inspection commission and vows again never to cooperate with it (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As a two-day meeting of international arms inspections experts convened today to review new monitoring operations for Iraq, a leading Iraqi official denounced the inspection commission and vowed again never to cooperate with it.</p>
        <p>The official, Tariq Aziz, Iraq's deputy prime minister and the person considered to be the most authoritative spokesman for President Saddam Hussein, said in Baghdad that his government would not allow the new arms inspection team to visit the country, as called for in a Security Council resolution last December.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As a two-day meeting of international arms inspections experts convened today to review new monitoring operations for Iraq, a leading Iraqi official denounced the inspection commission and vowed again never to cooperate with it.</p>
        <p>The official, Tariq Aziz, Iraq's deputy prime minister and the person considered to be the most authoritative spokesman for President Saddam Hussein, said in Baghdad that his government would not allow the new arms inspection team to visit the country, as called for in a Security Council resolution last December.</p>
        <p>Hans Blix, the executive chairman of the new arms panel, the United Nations Monitoring, Verification and Inspection Commission, said this week that a team of 44 inspectors from 19 countries had been trained and was ready to go to Iraq to restart inspections after a 20-month lapse. The last inspectors of an earlier commission were withdrawn from Iraq in advance of American and British bombing in December 1998.</p>
        <p>Mr. Aziz told reporters in Baghdad: ''I have said that Iraq will never cooperate with resolution 1284. This means it will not receive Blix or any person related to this resolution.''</p>
        <p>Iraq has also refused to allow entry to Yuli Voronstov, a Russian diplomat charged with studying the cases of 600 Kuwaitis and others still missing since the 1990 invasion and occupation of Kuwait by Iraq. And Peter van Walsum, the Dutch ambassador to the United Nations and chairman of the Security Council sanctions committee on Iraq, has also been refused entry. He said he has been eager to see for himself what effects a decade-long embargo is having on the people of Iraq. The embargo was imposed by the United Nations after Iraq's invasion of Kuwait in 1990.</p>
        <p>Dr. Blix, a former Swedish foreign minister and director general of the International Atomic Energy Agency during the period when it was discovered that Iraq had been working on a secret nuclear weapons program, was widely assumed to be more acceptable to Iraq as a chief inspector than his predecessor, Richard Butler of Australia. Mr. Butler headed the now-defunct commission known as Unscom.</p>
        <p>Nuclear inspectors under Dr. Blix had concluded several years ago that Iraq was free of nuclear weapons, but needed long-term monitoring. Mr. Butler's inspectors, who were responsible for destroying and monitoring biological, chemical and long-range missile programs, still had a list of questions for the Iraqis about missing arms components and materials for germ warfare, and were aggressive in demanding answers. Iraq objected, demanding more diplomatic treatment, which some United Nations officials also advocated.  Mr. Butler now says this undermined his work and gave the Iraqis the opening to become more defiant of all inspection systems.</p>
        <p>Iraq must be declared free of all prohibited weapons of mass destruction in order to have sanctions lifted, although the new commission, in a gesture to Iraq, is permitted to recommend a suspension of the embargo if the Iraqis cooperate on still-undefined ''key'' disarmament tasks for six months.</p>
        <p>Dr. Blix was expected to report today to his international advisory board, called a ''college of commissioners,'' on his readiness to return inspectors to Iraq and Iraq's rejection of the new program.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
