<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Can't Have Tutu Much, Serious Or Silly</title>
    <meta content="24TROC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224866"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ballets Trockadero De Monte Carlo, Les</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dunning, Jennifer</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000824T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E2DF1731F937A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="712" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Can't Have Tutu Much, Serious Or Silly</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER DUNNING</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dunning, Jennifer</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jennifer Dunning reviews performance by Les Ballets Trockadero de Monte Carlo, at Joyce Theater; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Les Ballets Trockadero de Monte Carlo may look nutty, with its male ballerinas, over-the-top stage names and mostly witty choreographic jokes. But on Tuesday night at the Joyce Theater, the company presented the kind of dream repertory one seldom sees these days. Although this second of two Joyce programs was mostly classical ballet fare by the big guns of Russian and French ballet in the 19th and early 20th centuries, there was also a dollop of dance by that stalwart American avant-gardist Merce Cunningham.</p>
        <p>The centerpiece of the program was a new staging by Elena Kunikova of Alexander Gorsky's ''Russian Dance,'' set to music by Tchaikovsky. Fetchingly danced by Vanya Verikosa, the solo incorporated a running gag with the kind of white handkerchief that features in such folk dances. What made the joke funnier was the way Ms. Kunikova incorporated folk-style moves into picking up and dropping the handkerchief.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Les Ballets Trockadero de Monte Carlo may look nutty, with its male ballerinas, over-the-top stage names and mostly witty choreographic jokes. But on Tuesday night at the Joyce Theater, the company presented the kind of dream repertory one seldom sees these days. Although this second of two Joyce programs was mostly classical ballet fare by the big guns of Russian and French ballet in the 19th and early 20th centuries, there was also a dollop of dance by that stalwart American avant-gardist Merce Cunningham.</p>
        <p>The centerpiece of the program was a new staging by Elena Kunikova of Alexander Gorsky's ''Russian Dance,'' set to music by Tchaikovsky. Fetchingly danced by Vanya Verikosa, the solo incorporated a running gag with the kind of white handkerchief that features in such folk dances. What made the joke funnier was the way Ms. Kunikova incorporated folk-style moves into picking up and dropping the handkerchief.</p>
        <p>One of the great pleasures of performances by the Trocks, as they are affectionately known, is the exquisitely detailed costumes. David Tetrault's gold and jewel-encrusted pinafore was beautiful in itself, but the skirt rippled up to reveal a bright, deep yellow underskirt that was a dazzling surprise.</p>
        <p>Mike Gonzales's costumes play an important part in the glittering success of the Trocks' ''Paquita,'' staged by Ms. Kunikova after the Petipa original. The tutus are a subtle rainbow of matte zinnia colors that enhance the fundamental seriousness of this production. The inept Igor Teupleze may look like Harry Potter as he wanders cluelessly but amiably about the stage. But Olga Supphozova, the company's reigning prima ballerina, proved that she is a seriously accomplished dancer, rightly drawing cheers as she spun out what looked like centuple multiple turns in the fouette section. Mme. Supphozova also lives in her ballerina persona as she dances. One reason audiences seem to love the Trocks so may well be that these male ballerinas aim for the impossible with such success.</p>
        <p>The fine cast was completed by Sveltlana Lofatkina, Nadia Rombova, a dogged little butterfly named Sylphia Belchick, and the imposing Ida Nevasayneva.</p>
        <p>The dancing in Trutti Gasparinetti's staging of ''Le Grand Pas de Quatre,'' an homage of sorts by Jules Perrot to four celebrated ballerinas of the mid-19th century, is on the verge of becoming a little broad. Less would definitely be more in Iona Trailer's playing of Fanny Cerrito. Anya Marx is adorable as Lucile  Grahn, however, dancing with a sweetness that suggested why the Danish ballerina, though contentious in her private life, was so acclaimed on the stage. Fifi Barkova was amusingly stolid as Carlotta Grisi. And Mme. Nevasayneva, dancing the austere Marie Taglioni, protected her turf with an awesomely chill ferocity that reminded one audience member of every bad ballet teacher she had ever studied with.</p>
        <p>The evening opened with Ms. Gasparinetti's staging of the second act of ''Swan Lake,'' which needs to lose a few of the pratfalls and other ballet jokes, though its imitation of bad mime is hilarious. The spunky little Maya Thickenthighya was a no-nonsense Odette, with the artist formerly known as Prince Myshkin as her Prince Siegfried. (Things tend to get complicated in Trockland.) Velour Pilleaux, who bore a striking resemblance to Mme. Nevasayneva in drag, was a silently cackling von Rothbart. He wore a red-and-black cape that had the intricate dull glitter of jet beads, one of Mr. Gonzales's most handsome designs.</p>
        <p>And Mr. Cunningham? He was represented by his 1964 ''Cross Currents,'' staged by Meg Harper and danced to taped and live music ''after'' Conlon Nancarrow and John Cage. The entertainingly grim danseuses -- Mme. Rombova, Gerd Tord and Nikolai Legupski -- were upstaged by the two uncredited musicians, whose contributions of found sound included the crackling of candy wrappers and the manipulation of a free-hanging zipper at several speeds.</p>
        <p>DANCE REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
