<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Raising More Than Consciousness Now</title>
    <meta content="24THEA$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224886"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="GENERATIONS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gornick, Vivian</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brown, Patricia Leigh</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000824T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E7DC1731F937A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="2187" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Raising More Than Consciousness Now</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICIA LEIGH BROWN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brown, Patricia Leigh</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Writer Vivian Gornick and colleagues have proposed building House of Elder Artists, 'un-retirement' home for aging female writers, artists and community activists; nonprofit residence and cultural center in Manhattan would have 100 rental apartments, many reserved for people of low to modest means; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BESS GORNICK was an only-in-New-York New Yorker. The kind of woman who, living alone at age 90 in a Manhattan apartment, thought nothing of bounding up to a police officer, with the back of her sweater half-fastened, and demanding, ''Button me!''</p>
        <p>The city and its tempestuous motion -- its bus drivers, cashiers, pretzel vendors, street talkers, dog walkers -- were a perpetual source of renewal to Mrs. Gornick, a ''working-class toughie from the Bronx,'' in the words of her daughter, the writer Vivian Gornick.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BESS GORNICK was an only-in-New-York New Yorker. The kind of woman who, living alone at age 90 in a Manhattan apartment, thought nothing of bounding up to a police officer, with the back of her sweater half-fastened, and demanding, ''Button me!''</p>
        <p>The city and its tempestuous motion -- its bus drivers, cashiers, pretzel vendors, street talkers, dog walkers -- were a perpetual source of renewal to Mrs. Gornick, a ''working-class toughie from the Bronx,'' in the words of her daughter, the writer Vivian Gornick.</p>
        <p>When Bess became housebound in the mid-1980's, unable to roam freely, her deterioration was rapid. Within herself, she began to drift, growing listless and withdrawn. ''For the first time in her life she lost definition,'' Ms. Gornick recalled. ''My mother had suddenly become a generic old woman.'' But one day, Ms. Gornick brought along a friend to visit, and in no time at all her mother and friend were deep in conversation. ''The change in my mother was astonishing,'' the writer recalled. ''She began to look again like herself.''</p>
        <p>Those last years of Bess Gornick's life made her daughter, who has inherited both her socialist mother's vigor and luminous skin, think about her own aging, and of the loss of connections that Bess craved. Their situations were strikingly similar. Like many creative city people, Ms. Gornick lives and works alone, one of the legions, she has written, who ''stare out the window of a room empty of companionship.'' Like many writers and artists, she finds herself growing old without a pension or benefits.</p>
        <p>''I looked around at my own soul,'' Ms. Gornick said the other day in Greenwich Village, while engaged in her mother's favorite activities, walking and talking fast. ''I discover as I go on that the loneliness is crippling.''</p>
        <p>Thus was born the idea for the House of Elder Artists, or Thea, a confederacy of kindred souls dedicated to creating an un-retirement home for female writers, artists, community activists -- and those game enough to grow old among them. They envision Thea, as yet unbuilt, as a sort of Yaddo with superintendents: a nonprofit residence and cultural center in Manhattan with 100 rental apartments, many reserved for people of low to modest means. To build it, the group has teamed up with the Women's Housing and Economic Development Corporation, a nonprofit organization dedicated to women's housing issues, although the project must still surmount major hurdles, from finding a site to securing financing. Today, communal living arrangements of various sorts are appealing to a broad group of single women. From shared housing, where housemates are often matched by nonprofit or religious groups like the National Shared Housing Resource Center, to golf resorts in Florida for those seeking the Dinah Shore lifestyle, housing is beginning to address profound statistical realities: between 1970 and 1998, the number of women living alone across the country doubled, from 7.3 million to 15.3 million, according to the American Association of Retired Persons. In New York City alone, 41.8 percent of all women age 65 and older live alone, versus 20.8 percent of the men.</p>
        <p>In many ways, the Gornicktchiks are following squarely in the tradition of the material feminists of the 19th century, women like Charlotte Perkins Gilman, who proposed a feminist apartment hotel in New York City and campaigned for redesigned spaces that would support women's public work and end their physical isolation.</p>
        <p>The group currently is made up of the advocates of yesteryear, as one puts it, including the novelist Helen Yglesias, 85, the writer Alix Kates Shulman, 67; the children's book illustrator and author Vera B. Williams, 72, the documentary filmmaker Lilly Rivlin, 62, and assorted lawyers, judges, painters and Village leftists, 53 and older.</p>
        <p>''You might say, Why now? Why us?'' Emily Goodman, a judge in her 50's, said over Italian food in a Manhattan restaurant one recent evening with some Thea sisters. They shared some dishes, rejecting the ones saturated in olive oil as too fattening. (''Are we going to do this at Thea?'' one wondered.)</p>
        <p>''We're a group who've always been involved in movements,'' Ms. Goodman said. ''If we sat around and waited, it would never happen.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Gornick, who pulls up a Murphy bed each morning to make space for her office at home, speaks of spiritual isolation as the great, largely unspoken fear. In her 1987 memoir, ''Fierce Attachments,'' she recalls life in the Bronx tenement apartment building where she grew up, the connection her mother felt each time she opened the window onto the alley, where women were calling to each other, ''the sound of their voices mixed with the smell of clothes drying in the sun.''</p>
        <p>As an old woman, she said, her mother had an even stronger desire to connect to the life of the city, but she became unable to reach out. ''My mother and her friends got old sealed off in little apartments,'' she said.</p>
        <p>As more women live alone and housing costs climb, ''shelter poverty'' among older women is rising, said Marci LeFevre, a consultant for the AARP, resulting in more and more older women pooling resources to live together.</p>
        <p>''When you think about it,'' said Ms. Williams, whose eyes exude youthful mischief, ''it's odd that it should be unusual that people who've had great autonomy get together to think about arranging their lives as they get older.''</p>
        <p>In contrast to the glory days of the feminist movement, middle-age women prefer sofas to the floor. Thea has gone through many permutations since Ms. Gornick went through her phone book three years ago and invited ''almost every woman I'd known in the past 20 years'' to think about her proposition.</p>
        <p>It was probably fortunate that David Letterman was not a fly on the wall. The original idea was a feminist retirement residence, a concept that was shot down almost immediately by the room of feminists.</p>
        <p>Ms. Gornick remembers the conversation:</p>
        <p>''Too broad.''</p>
        <p>''Too narrow.''</p>
        <p>''Too inclusive.''</p>
        <p>''Too restricting.''</p>
        <p>''What, no men?''</p>
        <p>The second suggestion was to make it a residence for women in the arts. But that didn't wash with the lawyers. (''What, no men?'') The third idea was to make Thea a residence for women active in political causes. (''Activists? What does that mean? They'll think were Communists.'' ''What, no men?'') The meetings went on -- and on -- with about 20 to 30 women in attendance. ''It was talk, talk, talk that went nowhere, like an academic faculty meeting,'' Ms. Gornick recalled.</p>
        <p>Then one night, Ms. Rivlin said, ''Why are we calling this a retirement home? Who's retiring? We have to be a part of the polis, the city, and have the city come to us.'' It was a galvanizing moment. ''Every face in the room lit up,'' Ms. Gornick said.</p>
        <p>The idea took hold of a residence organized around a strong shared public sense of things, in her words, where writers and artists would give back to the city and keep their own working minds alive by inviting the neighborhood in for master classes, readings and the like. The preliminary ideas call for a common dining room as well as studio space and rooms for public performances.</p>
        <p>But the endless tortured discussions about minutiae might have continued to eternity had Thea not hooked up with Nancy Biberman, a housing advocate, developer and lawyer, who founded the Women's Housing and Economic Development Corporation and was responsible for the $23 million transformation of the vacant Morrisania Hospital in the South Bronx into a low-income apartment building for 132 families, many of them formerly homeless.</p>
        <p>Ms. Biberman, 52, whose first experience with building was barricading Hamilton Hall at Columbia University in 1968, became a partner with Thea and the project's developer. To make Thea a reality in Manhattan, she said, as either a new building or a renovated one, would cost about $20 million. About $16 million would come from tax-exempt bonds through the city's Housing Development Corporation, a loan that would be repaid with rental income over 30 years.</p>
        <p>Thea also qualifies for tax credits, because it has committed itself to setting aside 20 percent of its one- and two-bedroom apartments for low-income tenants. The sliding scale of rents would range from $857 to $3,500, including two meals a day, with residents selected by lottery.  The design would allow spaces for  home health-care attendants, whose services might be shared.</p>
        <p>The women of Thea themselves will need to raise an additional $2 million. The project is so daunting that some members of the original group have dropped out, among them the writer Susan Brownmiller. ''Fund-raising wasn't my thing, and the whole project sounded fearfully expensive,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Given the current real estate climate, would the group consider living outside Manhattan? Ms. Gornick wouldn't hear of it, convinced not only of the long-term benefits of Manhattan's cultural richness but also of the contributions the group could make to it. She remembers once asking her mother, the ultimate Manhattanite, to consider moving to Florida. Not long afterward, Ms. Gornick went there on assignment.</p>
        <p>''Ma!'' she shrieked into the telephone. ''You were right! I hope you die in a blizzard running for the 23rd Street crosstown.''</p>
        <p>Last year, Ms. Biberman said, the group negotiated for an option to purchase a piece of vacant land on West 46th Street but chose not to pursue it because of a more desirable possibility. ''We're pursuing that now,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The walls of Thea, which could resemble a gray-haired version of a 60's college dorm, would be resonant with the rich experiences of women like Ms. Yglesias, whose latest novel, ''The Girls,'' is about four sisters in their 80's and 90's living in Miami. Ms. Yglesias, who has three children and five grandchildren, divides her time between a house in Maine, where she hires people to drive her around, and the Markle Residence in Greenwich Village, an intergenerational apartment building run by the Salvation Army.</p>
        <p>She published her first novel, ''How She Died,'' at age 54, after raising a family. ''Life intervenes for many women,'' she said. ''I was lucky.'' She remains committed despite the fact that she may not live to see the project's fruition. Ms. Yglesias, who describes herself as ''a seasoned voyager in the territory of the aged,'' continued, ''I don't really think in terms of Thea happening in time for me, not that I brood.''</p>
        <p>Like Ms. Gornick, Ms. Williams regards Thea not only as a personal solution but as a social model. She has already pioneered alternative housing: in 1955, she and a group of friends from Black Mountain College in North Carolina got together to establish a radical cooperative community at Stony Point, N.Y.</p>
        <p>Today, she shares a graffiti-spattered waterfront studio in the Village with fellow artists and, after years living alone, has begun sharing her apartment with a roommate. ''I'm not interested in the acquisition of property or furnishing places,'' she said. ''They don't fascinate me the way solving social problems does.''</p>
        <p>She wasn't sure at first she had the energy for Thea. ''There's a reluctance to make any plans for old age, because you're reluctant to be old,'' she said. ''You need solitude. But you also need crosscurrents. Here you would be in a place where you might be needed by other people, where there would be others around to talk about your work. It would be enlivening, harder to get into ruts. ''</p>
        <p>Most important, she said, eyes crinkling, ''It would be fun.''</p>
        <p>It would be a place where Ms. Gornick could continue writing about ''the lovely human bustle at noon, a density of urban appetites and absorptions.'' In an essay she describes the searing New York loneliness ''that engulfs me like dry heat.'' She finds an antidote walking the city streets -- as she hopes to do at age 95 -- grinning to herself at the exhilarating lengths people will go to to survive, the ''50 different ways people struggle to remain human until the very last minute.</p>
        <p>''I join the anxiety,'' she writes, ''I share the condition. I feel in my nerve endings the common refusal to go under.''</p>
        <p>GENERATIONS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
