<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Transformed Russia</title>
    <meta content="24ASSE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224944"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Submarines</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Kursk (Submarine)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Norway</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Barents Sea</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tyler, Patrick E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Norway</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Norway</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Submarines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000824T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E6DE1431F937A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1380" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Transformed Russia</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICK E. TYLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tyler, Patrick E</byline>
      <dateline>MOSCOW, Aug. 23</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Russia's response to sinking of nuclear submarine Kursk evolves into a repudiation of Soviet way of governing; Russian officials were true to Soviet form at first, dispensing misinformation or no information, ignoring human dimension of tragedy and jealously guarding the foundered submarine; but as days passed, they requested foreign help, became more forthcoming about what they knew and ended by apologizing publicly for their mishandling of the accident and promising accountability (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With a public confession tonight by President Vladimir V. Putin that he feels ''responsibility and guilt'' for the loss of the nuclear submarine Kursk, Russia's political evolution seems to be taking a new kind of post-Soviet turn.</p>
        <p>Military commanders are offering to resign. The government and the private sector are competing to raise millions of dollars for the families of the Kursk's crew. The airwaves are ringing with mea culpas from the haughty admirals of the once mighty Red Banner Fleet of the north.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With a public confession tonight by President Vladimir V. Putin that he feels ''responsibility and guilt'' for the loss of the nuclear submarine Kursk, Russia's political evolution seems to be taking a new kind of post-Soviet turn.</p>
        <p>Military commanders are offering to resign. The government and the private sector are competing to raise millions of dollars for the families of the Kursk's crew. The airwaves are ringing with mea culpas from the haughty admirals of the once mighty Red Banner Fleet of the north.</p>
        <p>And on the surface of the Barents Sea, in case anyone missed it, Russia for the first time cracked open the door to Norwegian and British seamen and asked them to enter the inner sanctum of a powerful cold war leviathan named Kursk and there to help retrieve 118 sons of the lost Soviet empire.</p>
        <p>It did not start out that way.</p>
        <p>When the Kursk exploded and crashed to the bottom of the Barents Sea on Aug. 12, Russians spontaneously reacted with indignation when military leaders dropped into a familiar defensive crouch, distorting and withholding information and paying little heed to the human dimension of the tragedy for the crewmen and their families, many of whom live in rank poverty in Russia's far north.</p>
        <p>And they were even more appalled when Mr. Putin, instead of rushing home like the disciplined and pragmatic public servant they voted for last March, tarried at his favorite resort on the Black Sea.</p>
        <p>Day after day he remained there as one of the most extraordinary rescue dramas at sea unfolded. Lives were at risk. Last breaths were being drawn, but still Mr. Putin vacationed.</p>
        <p>Parallels to the Soviet era raged from the front pages of the Russian press, and many Russians harked back to Chernobyl, where the worst nuclear accident in history spewed radiation into the heavens for days in late April and early May 1986 before Soviet leaders begrudgingly admitted that something had gone terribly wrong.</p>
        <p>But in the din of recriminations over the loss of the Kursk and with the sudden awakening of Mr. Putin, what many have missed is the repudiation of the Soviet era that is also present in this crisis.</p>
        <p>The Kursk families have expressed their outrage and pain, and this week Mr. Putin elevated their plight to a national priority.</p>
        <p>Politicians have said officials must be held accountable, but Mr. Putin said tonight that the old Soviet game of laying blame gratuitously would be set aside. ''It has been like that before,'' he said on national television, adding that ''nothing will be done'' until ''a full understanding has been gained about what happened and why.''</p>
        <p>Though Russia's military made mistakes and was too slow to ask for Western help, its officials also became surprisingly accessible and accountable. One admiral admitted that rescue gear was not available because it had been rented out to oil companies.</p>
        <p>And a veteran Russian television reporter, Arkady Momontov, known for his broadcasts from the front lines in Chechnya, was given exclusive access to the deck of a navy cruiser. Far from being a mouthpiece for the navy, he delivered a stream of video and reporting to an international audience that showed Russian journalists' determination to reach the same standards as their colleagues in the West.</p>
        <p>It is also impossible to ignore the moment when the former Soviet president, Mikhail S. Gorbachev, joined the ranks of critics chiding Mr. Putin for delaying Russia's request for Western aid too long.</p>
        <p>For it was Mr. Gorbachev who in 1986 let the flames of Chernobyl burn without warning his countrymen -- not to mention Europe -- that a radioactive cloud was headed their way. And, of course, Mr. Gorbachev refused all Western help to contain the worst nuclear disaster ever.</p>
        <p>But with his criticism, Mr. Gorbachev showed that he, too, was well beyond the Soviet era.</p>
        <p>Above all, the sinking of the Kursk foreshadows some reckoning ahead for the pared-down remains of the armed forces of the former Soviet empire, whose once vaunted technological prowess was already looking battered and bloodied by rebels in Chechnya.</p>
        <p>Whether an investigation proves that Russia's nuclear-powered leviathan Kursk was sunk by a collision with an elusive foreign submarine or by a misfired torpedo or a World War II mine, the lasting image from the surface of the Barents Sea will be the hapless attempts by otherwise heroic Russian rescuers to reach the Kursk's escape hatch in outdated minisubs powered by batteries too old to hold a charge.</p>
        <p>When the Norwegians and British arrived with their shining technology, underwater cameras and command centers that looked like a Circuit City showroom, these ''foreigners'' went to work in their deep-diving suits and cracked the stubborn hatch in 36 hours.</p>
        <p>The wrenching drama of the Kursk has been another painful step in the education of Mr. Putin, the youthful president and longtime K.G.B. officer who has taken a vow to strengthen the Russian state and rebuild its military forces to defend Russia's interests, whatever those turn out to be in the transition that still is under way on the Eurasian continent.</p>
        <p>Mr. Putin is discovering in the most poignant way that invoking the imagery of Russia's military tradition is not the same as exercising it effectively, and safely, every day.</p>
        <p>In his visit to Severomorsk on Monday, Mr. Putin was reminded again that though Russia possesses the nuclear arsenal of a global power, the Russian military has gone to rust, and that most of its personnel live in poverty.</p>
        <p>''The conditions in which our nuclear submarines are maintained do not meet any standards, and we could witness another serious accident at any moment,'' Aleksandr V. Rutskoi, the former vice president and war hero who led a political rebellion against President Boris N. Yeltsin in 1993, said on Monday.</p>
        <p>In a fiery denunciation of the navy, Mr. Rutskoi, now the governor of the Kursk region, for which the submarine was named, added, ''When the Russian fleet does not have the necessary means to conduct rescues, the very fact that submarines go to sea is already a crime.''</p>
        <p>After the Vietnam War, American commanders complained that a ''hollow'' military was the cause of a significant decline of American prestige in the world, one that would invite challenge from any adversary. And what ''hollow'' came to mean was a decline in the recruiting and training of professional cadres of soldiers and in the high level of spending on maintenance, spare parts and ever-improving technologies for weaponry -- and on safety for the most important weapon in any arsenal -- the soldier.</p>
        <p>Russia now faces a much broader hollowing of its military forces. Mr. Putin speaks as if he is determined to come to terms with that reality, but without acknowledging that rebuilding the Russian armed forces can be accomplished only through an inevitable contraction of Russian power and global pretension.</p>
        <p>Overreaching for the glory days of the Soviet past, when Moscow supported a blue-water navy that could compete for power and influence in the Atlantic and Pacific, could easily lead to the disasters that Mr. Rutskoi predicts.</p>
        <p>Russia's defense minister, Marshal Igor D. Sergeyev, venting his frustration on national television on Monday night, said the ''whole reason'' that there were no Russian deep-sea divers to race down to save the Kursk's crew was that the military ''over the course of the past several years'' had been ''robbed and stripped'' and the armed forces were being funded at ''less than 50 percent'' of their requirements.</p>
        <p>But requirements for what?</p>
        <p>Mr. Putin must now answer that question for the Russians and for his neighbors in Europe, whom he has alarmed with his ''strong state'' oratory.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, flags over the Kremlin flew at half-staff today, mourning not only the lost sailors, but the lost pride that so many Russians feel.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
