<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Putting a Stop to the Art In the Name of Activism</title>
    <meta content="24EDER" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224869"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eder, Richard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zagajewski, Adam</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Another Beauty (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000824T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05EFDF1731F937A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1093" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Putting a Stop to the Art In the Name of Activism</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD EDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eder, Richard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Richard Eder reviews Adam Zagajewski book Another Beauty; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ANOTHER BEAUTY  By Adam Zagajewski  Translated by Clare Cavanagh. 215 pages.  Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux. $23.</p>
        <p>We know that the greatest surgeons believe in something beyond cutting, that the greatest generals believe in something beyond war.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ANOTHER BEAUTY  By Adam Zagajewski  Translated by Clare Cavanagh. 215 pages.  Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux. $23.</p>
        <p>We know that the greatest surgeons believe in something beyond cutting, that the greatest generals believe in something beyond war.</p>
        <p>With artists it's not clear: art for art's sake or for something beyond?  Even if it is for the beyond -- truth or transformation, say -- do you get there by looking past the instruments (the surgeon putting aside the knife for a moment; the general silencing the guns) or by using them with greater exigency and abnegation? Perhaps it is not the artist's, general's or surgeon's vocation that is set aside, but the hyper-trophied modes and swollen ambitions that encrust themselves in it.</p>
        <p>It was a generational question for the distinguished Polish poet Adam Zagajewski. In the 1970's, along with many of his fellow artists and intellectuals, he interrupted his modernist ironies and aesthetic explorations -- involving mainly nonlethal clashes with the Communist censorship -- for outright activism.</p>
        <p>His group called itself Now. It sent rickety shuttle-loads of the black-sweatered (the garb favored by these ex-aesthetes) to unheated meeting halls in towns and cities around Poland. Instead of poetry they talked about justice and political and economic change. A police car stood outside, but in those erratically repressive years the policemen rarely stepped inside.</p>
        <p>Now offered Mr. Zagajewski ''the bitter bread of urgency, of contemporaneity,'' he writes in ''Another Beauty. ''It ripped me from the lovely sphere in which time doesn't count, where I could read Norwid one day and Kafka the next, as if the real, historical worlds in which they lived were completely extraneous. It was a descent from the clouds, a departure from the land of dreams, a brutal encounter with the ugliness of the present.</p>
        <p>''For this 'now' was uncommonly ugly: a graceless moment in an ugly country conquered by Moscow and sentenced to mediocrity in virtually every domain.''</p>
        <p>He continues: ''I proclaimed the primacy of 'obligation' over pleasure, sobriety over reverie, society over the solitary reader and poet. And amazingly enough, a program closer to self-flagellation than to art began at some point to attract the attention of a public that would no doubt have remained entirely indifferent if I had stayed true to my leisurely, 'eternal' dreams.''</p>
        <p>Indeed. But Mr. Zagajewski, unlike some of his black-sweatered fellows, has become neither a politician nor founder of a start-up money pot. He remains a poet; one whose distinction is to reconcile aesthetic exploration with what happened to him in Now's decrepit train-and-van trips. ''If,'' he writes, ''such a thing can be done.''</p>
        <p>Well it can be. If Mr. Zagajewski is not on the titan level of a Czeslaw Milosz (his mentor in some respects), it may be because, belonging to a younger, post-Stalin generation, he has not been plunged into Mr. Milosz's depths, nor had to work back up from such a profound sense of the tragic. He too is a healer, of sorts, but the wound is not so deep and the healing not so uncanny.</p>
        <p>At its best, though, it is remarkable and shines through this commonplace-book of sketches, reflections and bits of personal and poetic history. Mr. Zagajewski places himself at an opposite end from the French-Romanian E. M. Cioran, compiler of an epigrammatic encyclopedia of despair. He, to the contrary, can write only out of happiness. A touch of Panglossian uplift occasionally creeps into ''Another Beauty.'' Mostly the author -- sadder and wiser and nonetheless hopeful -- is a far-from-gullible Candide.</p>
        <p>There are moments of self-mockery, phrased with comic indirection. Mr. Zagajewski pictures himself typing a manifesto for Now, while Sunday Mass-goers clack by beneath his window.</p>
        <p>''The two kinds of tapping -- high heels and my typewriter -- mingled from time to time. There were no other sounds; the blackbirds hadn't started singing yet. Carpenters didn't saw wood on Sundays, ironworkers didn't labor in their cramped, noisy shops.'' As for him, ''I churned out leaflets and counted on the support of the working class.''</p>
        <p>The author describes the reading room at the Beaubourg library in Paris. Every little while a loudspeaker breaks into the readers' reveries, warning them to watch for pickpockets. ''Each reader glances up involuntarily, struggling to understand what's going on. But it's only pickpockets.'' He imagines the loudspeakers taking over: ''Would the lady seated at table four please cease her ecstasies over Baudelaire and pick up something pleasanter and easier to read?''</p>
        <p>He writes evocatively of strolls through Cracow, an architectural frontier between German Gothic and the lightness of Northern Renaissance. He longs for Mediterranean light but is loyal to his city's darkness. The stained glass windows in the churches are splotches of black, he recalls, contrasting them with the light-dazzled windows of Chartres Cathedral, which ''towered proudly  above a small provincial town like the Iliad over Greece.''</p>
        <p>There are melancholy portraits of his old professors, prewar stars bypassed and impoverished when the Communists took over. He writes of a retired clerk who preserves his three suits by lying down all day. ''If he used up anything it could only be oxygen and time.''</p>
        <p>He touches on poetry and a summer evening musicale. He cites a friend on what most impressed him traveling about the world: ''The ubiquity of sparrows.'' The writer Alexander Wat is quoted: ''Compare French and German string quartets. You'll see at once who has the stronger army.'' He evokes Cracow's cramped apartments, where broken things are retained, just in case (counter to the decreed utopian future) time were to run the other way suddenly and tick-tock broken things back into repair.</p>
        <p>Amid this lovely bric-a-brac, we read of a devout aunt who made friends with the parish priest next door and invited him to dinner. The priest hit it off with her philologist husband, a devout atheist. Friendship and regular dinners ensued. To the aunt's bemusement it was not piety but the whet and flash of argument that lured the visitor. A pleasant story, but beware the bomb concealed when a poet is being pleasant. The priest was Karol Wojtyla.</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
