<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>World Briefing</title>
    <meta content="Y24BRI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224978"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000824T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E0DC1431F937A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1200" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>World Briefing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by Terence Neilan</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MIDDLE EAST</p>
        <p>ISRAEL: SHAS CHIEF'S SENTENCE UPHELD -- The Supreme Court denied a request for a new hearing on a three-year jail term for fraud, bribery and breach of trust imposed on Aryeh Deri, former leader of the ultra-Orthodox Shas Party. It ordered Mr. Deri to begin his sentence on Sept. 3. Mr. Deri, a charismatic former interior minister of Moroccan descent who built Shas into a powerful legislative bloc, was convicted of taking bribes at the Interior Ministry.</p>
        <p>John F. Burns (NYT)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MIDDLE EAST</p>
        <p>ISRAEL: SHAS CHIEF'S SENTENCE UPHELD -- The Supreme Court denied a request for a new hearing on a three-year jail term for fraud, bribery and breach of trust imposed on Aryeh Deri, former leader of the ultra-Orthodox Shas Party. It ordered Mr. Deri to begin his sentence on Sept. 3. Mr. Deri, a charismatic former interior minister of Moroccan descent who built Shas into a powerful legislative bloc, was convicted of taking bribes at the Interior Ministry.</p>
        <p>John F. Burns (NYT)</p>
        <p>WEST BANK: BIN LADEN LINK DENIED -- The leader of the militant Islamic group Hamas denied an assertion by Israel that a Hamas member who was among 23 Arabs arrested on terrorism charges had been sent to Pakistan for terrorist training with the group headed by Osama bin Laden, the Saudi-born Islamic militant. ''Hamas and I have no connection with bin Laden,'' Sheik Ahmed Yassin told The Associated Press.</p>
        <p>John F. Burns (NYT)</p>
        <p>IRAN: DISSIDENT FREED -- A leading Iranian dissident jailed in June by the hard-line judiciary for attending a conference in Germany about Iran has been freed, a close associate said. Ezatollah Sahabi, a member of the Freedom Movement, which opposes clerical rule, was released after paying $62,500 bail, said Reza Alijani, an editor of the banned Iran-e-Farda magazine. Mr. Sahabi was director of the magazine, one of 25 publications banned since April.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>GERMANY: 3 DENY INTENT TO KILL -- Three rightist youths said they did not intend to kill Alberto Adriano, an African, when they assaulted him in June. Speaking in court, where they have been charged with murder, they admitted attacking Mr. Adriano and said they were drunk at the time. A murder conviction requires proof of an intention to kill. The case has become the focus of intense interest as Germany combats a wave of anti-immigrant violence.</p>
        <p>Roger Cohen (NYT)</p>
        <p>AUSTRIA: HAIDER HITS OUT -- Jorg Haider, the driving force behind Austria's extreme right Freedom Party, said the Czech Republic and Slovenia should not be allowed to join the European Union until they disavow decrees that led to the expulsion of ethnic Germans after World War II. Mr. Haider, whose father was a committed Nazi, has often said that German suffering in the war must also be recognized.</p>
        <p>Roger Cohen (NYT)</p>
        <p>NORTHERN IRELAND: PROTESTANT FEUD CONTINUES -- A Protestant man was shot to death at his home in north Belfast in what appeared to be another strike in a feud between loyalist paramilitary groups. No group claimed immediate responsibility. The shooting happened near where two Protestant militants were shot dead on Monday.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>NETHERLANDS: LOCKERBIE CASE DELAYED -- The testimony of a key witness in the Lockerbie bombing trial was delayed until Monday so the defense can ask the Central Intelligence Agency for unedited versions of interviews with him. The man, identified as a former Libyan spy named Abdul Majid Giaka who lives in the United States under the witness protection program, is said to be the only witness who can say that one of two defendants checked a bomb-laden suitcase onto a plane in Malta in 1998.</p>
        <p>Donald G. McNeil Jr. (NYT)</p>
        <p>LATVIA: LANGUAGE LAW EASED -- Bowing to critics, Latvia issued slightly more flexible rules for a law requiring use of the Latvian language in most activities. The new rules no longer require lawyers and doctors to speak fluent Latvian, and allow other languages to be spoken at international events. Russian-speaking Latvians, more than a quarter of the population, largely oppose the rules; some Europeans say the law does not meet anti-discrimination standards for joining the European Union.</p>
        <p>Michael Wines (NYT)</p>
        <p>SLOVAKIA: GYPSY MOTHER SLAIN -- Just three weeks after a United Nations report highlighted racism against Gypsies in Central and Eastern Europe, a Gypsy mother of eight was bludgeoned to death by three men in the town of Zilina. Four daughters of the woman, Anastazia Balazova, 49, were injured. Racial hatred and extreme-right groups have been growing in Slovakia, and a similar situation exists in the Czech Republic, Hungary, Romania and the Balkans.</p>
        <p>Ladka Bauerova (NYT)</p>
        <p>THE AMERICAS</p>
        <p>CANADA: CHURCH CHECKUP -- The United Church of Canada, which is being sued by hundreds of former students of its Indian boarding schools, has decided to submit all its ministers to mandatory police and sexual abuse registry checks every three years. An attempt to lower the church's liability insurance rates, the policy was adopted after lawsuits charged that sexual and physical abuse took place at the church's schools in the 1950's and 60's.</p>
        <p>James Brooke (NYT)</p>
        <p>ARGENTINA: I.B.M. WARRANTS WITHDRAWN -- A judge has annulled international arrest warrants issued in 1998 for two American executives with I.B.M. wanted for questioning in a 1994 corruption case, court officials said. The officials said the decision was intended to make it easier to interrogate the two, Steve Lew and Peter Rowley, and to gather evidence for an investigation in which investigators say some $30 million in bribes were paid in connection with a government contract.</p>
        <p>(Agence France-Presse)</p>
        <p>AFRICA</p>
        <p>CONGO: PEACE PACT SUSPENDED -- The government said it was suspending the carrying out of a 1999 accord aimed at ending the conflict in Congo. Human Rights Minister Leonard She Okitundu cited a substantial change in circumstances since the signing of the pact by warring parties in 1999 in Zambia. He said Congo wanted to hold direct talks with Rwanda, Uganda and Burundi, which all back rebel groups that took up arms against President Laurent Kabila in August 1998.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>BURUNDI: BLAST KILLS 8 -- A grenade exploded in a market in central Bujumbura, the capital, killing at least 4 people and injuring 50 others as tensions rose ahead of a deadline for an accord to end a civil war between Hutu and minority Tutsi that began in 1993. Tutsi militiamen are suspected of making the attack. Neither side says it is ready to sign a pact mediated by Nelson Mandela, and President Pierre Buyoya has asked him to postpone an Aug. 28 signing ceremony.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>ASIA</p>
        <p>INDIA: GANDHI TO SKIP NEW YORK -- The Congress Party president, Sonia Gandhi, leader of the opposition in Parliament, has decided not to attend a meeting of legislators in New York this month. Party officials say she has pressing party business and also wants to be home when her daughter, Priyanka Vadra, gives birth. Mrs. Vadra, who dazzled audiences when she campaigned for her mother last year, is carrying a child that family loyalists hope will one day inherit the Nehru-Gandhi dynasty.</p>
        <p>Celia W. Dugger (NYT)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
