<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>MetroStars Tie in a Duel at the Top</title>
    <meta content="24SOCC$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224990"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SOCCER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Metrostars</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Kansas City Wizards</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yannis, Alex</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Plains</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000824T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE5DB1431F937A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="638" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>MetroStars Tie in a Duel at the Top</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEX YANNIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Yannis, Alex</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., Aug. 23</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>MetroStars and Kansas City Wizards play to scoreless tie; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a battle of division leaders seeking first place overall in Major League Soccer, it was perhaps fitting that the MetroStars and the Kansas City Wizards fought to a scoreless tie tonight before a crowd of 16,898 at drizzly Giants Stadium.</p>
        <p>Kansas City maintained its one-point lead, 49 to 48, over the MetroStars in Major League Soccer with four games left for each team. The Wizards lead the Western Division with a record of 14-7-7 and the MetroStars lead the Eastern Division with a record of 15-10-3.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a battle of division leaders seeking first place overall in Major League Soccer, it was perhaps fitting that the MetroStars and the Kansas City Wizards fought to a scoreless tie tonight before a crowd of 16,898 at drizzly Giants Stadium.</p>
        <p>Kansas City maintained its one-point lead, 49 to 48, over the MetroStars in Major League Soccer with four games left for each team. The Wizards lead the Western Division with a record of 14-7-7 and the MetroStars lead the Eastern Division with a record of 15-10-3.</p>
        <p>While the score did not hurt either team, the game was rather costly for the MetroStars because Lothar Matthaus was given a yellow card with five minutes left in regulation and will miss Saturday's game at Dallas as a result of accumulating too many yellow-card points.</p>
        <p>Defense was the emphasis by Kansas City, while the MetroStars were looking to attack a great deal more. The MetroStars took 29 shots against Tony Meola, who registered his 14th shutout of the season, a league record. Meola made nine saves to tie a club record. Kansas City took 14 shots, but only a few caused any danger for Tim Howard, who played in place of the injured Mike Ammann and registered the shutout for the MetroStars.</p>
        <p>Kansas City's defense displayed strong evidence of why it has allowed the fewest goals in the league (26). The Wizards are very well organized defensively, and when the opposition finds a gap on defense, Meola is there for the save.</p>
        <p>''They came here to secure a point,'' Coach Octavio Zambrano of the MetroStars said about the Wizards. ''I think they showed why they hane not allowed that many goals.''</p>
        <p>The MetroStars have scored 52 goals, the most in their division, but they were unable to get one tonight. Adolfo Valencia and Clint Mathis were probably the most guilty of the Metrostars for not finding the target.</p>
        <p>The MetroStars had the territorial advantage for the greatest part of the game, especially in the first half, but Meola responded well. He denied Petter Villegas, Tab Ramos and Roy Myers from close range after some crisp and accurate passing by the MetroStars in Meola's penalty area.</p>
        <p>The man who caused the most trouble for the MetroStars' defenders was Ihor Dotsenko, who was promoted earlier in the day from Kansas City's affiliate, the Raleigh Capital Express of the A-League, where he was second in scoring in the league with 15 goals.</p>
        <p>Dotsenko was marked closely by Mike Petke in the middle of the defense, but he roamed from side to side and created space for others, especially Chris Henderson on the left, to enter the MetroStars' penalty area. Fortunately for the MetroStars, Coach Bob Gansler of Kansas City replaced Dotsenko with Francisco Gomez for the second half.</p>
        <p>The 26-year-old Dotsenko came to the United States from the Ukraine and graduated from Wake Forest in 1997. He is the fifth Ukrainian from the Dynamo Kiev youth system to play in the league, joining Sergi Daniv, Dema Kovalenko, Aleksey Korol and Yuri Lavrenko.</p>
        <p>Preki was Kansas City's most dangeorus man in the second half. He had two good opportunities, but he hit the post the first time during a moment of confusion in the MetroStars' defense and Howard punched away his shot the second time.</p>
        <p>SOCCER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
