<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Irresistible Lure of Subways Keeps Landing Impostor in Jail</title>
    <meta content="24SUBW" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/24/nyregion/24SUBW.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224938"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Impersonations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Subways</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">McCollum, Darius</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bloodsaw, Tracey</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Murphy, Dean E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Entertainment and Amusements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Subways</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000824T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07EED61731F937A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="2034" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Irresistible Lure of Subways Keeps Landing Impostor in Jail</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DEAN E. MURPHY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Murphy, Dean E</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Darius McCollum, 35, is behind bars for the 19th time in as many years for impersonating a New York City Transit worker or taking joy rides on subways; his lawyer, Tracey Bloodsaw, says that McCollum lives in a fantasy world and needs help and that she will fight latest charges with an insanity defense, even though her client insists that he is not insane and that everything would be OK if he were allowed to work legally on trains; his parents are at their wits' end over his obsession, which seemed funny when when he was in his teens; no one has ever been injured because of one of McCollum's escapades; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If Darius McCollum were a millionaire, he might be excused as an eccentric. If he were a genius, allowances probably would be made as well. But Mr. McCollum is neither. And his unusual problem -- his obsession, as he calls it -- has gotten him in so much trouble that people aren't even laughing anymore.</p>
        <p>Since he was a high school freshman, Mr. McCollum, who grew up in Queens and is now 35, has been in and out of jail for masquerading as a New York City Transit worker. He is back behind bars, for the 19th time in as many years, on charges that he pulled a subway emergency brake during rush hour and then, dressed for the part, came to the rescue as a fake transit supervisor.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If Darius McCollum were a millionaire, he might be excused as an eccentric. If he were a genius, allowances probably would be made as well. But Mr. McCollum is neither. And his unusual problem -- his obsession, as he calls it -- has gotten him in so much trouble that people aren't even laughing anymore.</p>
        <p>Since he was a high school freshman, Mr. McCollum, who grew up in Queens and is now 35, has been in and out of jail for masquerading as a New York City Transit worker. He is back behind bars, for the 19th time in as many years, on charges that he pulled a subway emergency brake during rush hour and then, dressed for the part, came to the rescue as a fake transit supervisor.</p>
        <p>Though little known outside the underground world he craves, Mr. McCollum is the city agency's biggest individual irritant. The police say his shenanigans are dangerous and they have distributed his picture to thousands of subway and bus workers with a stern warning: Be on the lookout. He has a sprawling rap sheet and has spent five years in prison.</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. McCollum refuses to be just a passenger.</p>
        <p>Even in a city of quirky people, the authorities say Mr. McCollum stands out, so expert at his chosen quirkiness that he has repeatedly fooled riders, subway employees and the police into believing he belongs in transit blues.</p>
        <p>At wits' end, his elderly parents have turned to a lawyer who is bent on proving that Mr. McCollum is not in his right mind. A done deal with the city's No. 1 subway nut? No one is expecting an easy ride.</p>
        <p>''I am not insane,'' Mr. McCollum said recently in an interview at Rikers Island. ''I am just your average guy who doesn't mind helping out. To tell you the truth, I wish they would just put me to work on the trains. It would be a lot easier.''</p>
        <p>Take a careful look. That self-satisfied smile is the only giveaway. You may know him as Manning or Morning, two of his most engaging personae, who, with a friendly wave and knowing nod, have driven off with city buses and transit agency trucks. He first got caught at the controls of a subway train at the age of 15, picking up passengers at the World Trade Center before he ever sat behind the wheel of an automobile.</p>
        <p>He has signed out two-way radios and cheerfully collected fares at ticket booths. (The radios have always been returned, and never has a penny gone missing from the till; his most costly blunder was leaving a commuter bus with a flat tire, the police say.) He has cleared debris from tracks and put out fires. In full uniform, he has glad-handed commuters and has even reported sick to the transit authority's infirmary to get aspirin for a headache.</p>
        <p>At last count, Mr. McCollum had the keys to three crew lockers at subway facilities, where he has kept everything from protective goggles to mud guards for his boots, all official transit agency issue.</p>
        <p>If someone questions his credentials, Mr. McCollum not only flashes an identity badge (he says he found it) but he produces a letter of authorization on official stationery (he admits to writing it himself, but insists the paper was a gift).</p>
        <p>When the police are in hot pursuit, as they have been on nearly two dozen occasions, his favorite hideout is the transit agency headquarters in Brooklyn. He exudes the confidence of someone who belongs there, and it is usually the last place the police think to look.</p>
        <p>''How can I describe it?'' Mr. McCollum said. ''It is one of those things, I guess I want to be seen, to get attention toward me. I like the activity. I like the noise. I like the people. I like the people who work there. There is not something that I can say I like the most. I like everything involved with it. I like the operations. I like the scenery. I like the schedules.''</p>
        <p>Mr. McCollum is in custody awaiting trial on a host of charges, including criminal impersonation. If found guilty, it will be his sixth felony conviction, according to correction officials, all related in one way or another to play-acting as a transit worker.</p>
        <p>His lawyer, Tracey Bloodsaw, says Mr. McCollum needs help. He has been living in a ''fake world'' and nobody has bothered to do anything about it, she says. She has filed notice with the State Supreme Court in Manhattan that she intends to fight the latest charges with an insanity defense; it will be the first time his state of mind has been raised as an explanation for his behavior, she said.</p>
        <p>''He doesn't think he is doing anything wrong,'' Ms. Bloodsaw said.</p>
        <p>Why nobody has offered such an argument before is anyone's guess. A spokesman for New York City Transit, the unit of the Metropolitan Transportation Authority that operates the city's buses and subways, would not comment. A police official familiar with his case said ''something is wrong'' with Mr. McCollum, but ''it is not like he has a condition where he needs to be medicated or anything like that.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Bloodsaw blames indifference on the part of Mr. McCollum's previous court-appointed lawyers and the judicial system bureaucracy. ''They just screwed up,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCollum, though skeptical, says insanity is worth a try. He was twice admitted to a psychiatric hospital as a child, according to records kept by his family, but he is lucid and articulate and knows how to chat up just about everyone. He serves on an inmate grievance committee at Rikers Island and volunteers to do typing and other work for a variety of prison programs.</p>
        <p>''You have to admit what this guy does is kind of wacky, but he is very much on the ball,'' said an official with the City Department of Correction.</p>
        <p>Most judges have considered Mr. McCollum more of a curiosity than a menace. During one sentence hearing, he said, the judge joked that he would like Mr. McCollum as his chauffeur. On another occasion, Mr. McCollum said he got rave reviews from court officials when he appeared in court in full transit uniform.</p>
        <p>''I know she is going to ask me that question, about why I do this,'' Mr. McCollum said of Justice Carol Berkman, who is hearing the current case. ''I will have to come up with something the best I can. I will say, 'Listen, I have an obsession with trains.' That is just it.''</p>
        <p>In the most recent incident, on Feb. 21, Mr. McCollum dressed up in transit blues, let himself into a control room with a key he had somehow obtained, and tripped the emergency switch at the 57th Street station, bringing a Queens-bound train to a screeching stop, the authorities say. He then went down on the track to sort out the mess, which, as in his previous escapades, caused no injuries but plenty of consternation. Mr. McCollum denies touching the switch, but admits to the other facts in the incident.</p>
        <p>''He has been doing this for so long that he knows all the terminology and he knows how to operate the equipment,'' said Sgt. Jack Cassidy, who heads police investigations of transit crimes. ''Honestly, just looking at him, you'd think he was an employee.''</p>
        <p>The truth, however, is that Mr. McCollum has never held a steady job. He says he has applied to the transit agency, but his name does not appear on any Civil Service lists. He once volunteered as a tour guide at the transit museum in Brooklyn, but was let go when police figured out who he was and became concerned that he would be inclined to take exhibits on he road.</p>
        <p>''He called me up and begged me to get that job back,'' Sergeant Cassidy said.</p>
        <p>Transit officials say there are umpteen train buffs who on occasion break the law, but none with the repeat compulsion that drives Mr. McCollum. His arrest in February came just six weeks after he was released from state prison for a previous offense, taking a joy ride in a transit agency vehicle.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCollum has been in custody 17 times in the last 15 years, city correction officials say. He has also served in state prisons in New York and North Carolina, where his parents moved 10 years ago and where Mr. McCollum once stole a car to sneak back to New York. Samuel and Elizabeth McCollum have given up posting bail for their only child. His fiancee, Nelly Rodriguez, a clothing designer from Ecuador who met Mr. McCollum on a subway platform in January, has called off their intended nuptials because there is no telling when he will be free again.</p>
        <p>''They can't let him out,'' said Samuel McCollum, 79. ''He is like an alcoholic or a drug addict. He has to first admit that he has a problem. Until he does that, we can't help him.''</p>
        <p>At first, the train thing seemed funny. As a teenager, he ended up in family court in 1981 for taking the controls of a subway train for six stops from 34th Street to the World Trade Center. In the days that followed, so many reporters and camera crews staked out his home in Jamaica, Queens, that he missed a week of school.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCollum said the trip was ''really very routine for me'' because he had been driving trains in the rail yards since he was 12.</p>
        <p>''It came to a point, where on different occasions, people would come to me and would say, 'Want to cover the yard for me?' I would say, 'Cool.' ''</p>
        <p>Elizabeth McCollum said she was advised at the time not to talk about her son's troubled childhood, but her calendar from January 1981, which she still keeps in a dog-eared manila folder, speaks volumes about his torment. Thursday, the 29th, is clearly marked as the day Darius drove the E train. But the rest of the tiny boxes also have scribbling in them, 14 with the word ''out.''</p>
        <p>''Those are the days Darius did not come home,'' Mrs. McCollum explained. ''He would run right down there into the subway. I would go down there and look for him, but the workers would say he wasn't there. But he was there.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. McCollum was right, said a former track worker who left a transit job two years ago on a disability pension. The man described Mr. McCollum as more Boy Scout than criminal, someone always looking to do a good deed.</p>
        <p>''He never felt part of anything, and people in transit made him feel welcome,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mrs. McCollum said that her son always had trouble fitting in at school, but that his troubles spiraled out of control when, at 10, he was stabbed in the back with a pair of scissors by a student in his special education class. Darius became so frightened, she said, that he would sit at a desk only if his back was against the wall.</p>
        <p>The McCollums sued the Board of Education for negligence over the stabbing but lost. They tried a half-dozen schools, including a military academy. He also got psychiatric treatment and counseling. But nothing helped. After class, Darius would descend into the subways. By 10th grade, he had dropped out.</p>
        <p>''He is a good kid,'' Mrs. McCollum said. ''He doesn't drink. He doesn't smoke. He doesn't gamble. His thing is to go down into that subway system. In his mind, he is still 15 driving that train.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
