<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Man of Many Stories, Both by Him and About Him</title>
    <meta content="Y24SOSI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/24/national/24SOSI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224924"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Deaths (Obituaries)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Miami News</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Associated Press</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sosin, Milt</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bragg, Rick</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Deaths (Obituaries)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000824T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E2D71731F937A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="780" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Man of Many Stories, Both by Him and About Him</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICK BRAGG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bragg, Rick</byline>
      <dateline>MIAMI, Aug. 23</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Newsmen recall stories about Milt Sosin, legendary reporter for defunct Miami News and later for AP, who died at age 92; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Milt Sosin lived for the story.</p>
        <p>As a reporter in South Florida, he interviewed Fidel Castro when Mr. Castro was just another guy with a beard, and Winston Churchill, and Meyer Lansky. He was in the police station in Dallas when Jack Ruby shot Lee Harvey Oswald, and was the first reporter to ride an airplane into the eye of a hurricane.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Milt Sosin lived for the story.</p>
        <p>As a reporter in South Florida, he interviewed Fidel Castro when Mr. Castro was just another guy with a beard, and Winston Churchill, and Meyer Lansky. He was in the police station in Dallas when Jack Ruby shot Lee Harvey Oswald, and was the first reporter to ride an airplane into the eye of a hurricane.</p>
        <p>He outlived his newspaper, The Miami News, which went under in 1988, and for more than two decades worked for The Associated Press, covering the wacky federal court beat in Miami. When he was 80 years old, he scooped the nation with the news that the Panamanian ruler Manuel Antonio Noriega had been indicted by the United States on drug charges. Only four months ago, he did it again, breaking word of the first federal court ruling in the Elian Gonzalez case. And last weekend, as he lay connected to an oxygen tank in his Miami Beach home, he phoned The Associated Press with a story idea.</p>
        <p>Sunday night, his heart stopped.</p>
        <p>And only then, his pen.</p>
        <p>He was 92.</p>
        <p>''Whatever story I sent him on, he got it,'' said Howard Kleinberg, who was Mr. Sosin's managing editor at The Miami News. ''He wouldn't take no for an answer.</p>
        <p>''He was the journalist you see in the movies. I'm not sure we'll ever see that again.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Sosin was a reporter who made his own news, created his own legend. Remembering him this week, and gathering for his burial in Miami today, his friends told Milt stories over and over. One of their favorites:</p>
        <p>Mr. Sosin, who often referred to editors as ''amateurs,'' reacted with his usual contempt when an editor at The News once ordered the staff to write shorter, punchier paragraphs.</p>
        <p>He sat down at his old typewriter, banged out his answer and stuck it on the bulletin board.</p>
        <p>''Quit,'' it said.</p>
        <p>''That's what reporter Milt Sosin did today.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Sosin was not a handsome man. He was tall and woefully thin, and had a neck like a turkey's and a long, cadaverous face dominated by a magnificent nose. He wore ascots and sport coats that looked as if they had come from Goodwill, and drove a Jaguar. He smoked a pipe.</p>
        <p>''His sport coats were older than some of the lawyers he wrote about,'' said Bill Cooke, a freelance photographer who chased the news in Miami with Mr. Sosin for decades. ''He liked pastels.''</p>
        <p>He regularly beat his competitors, scooping them even when he was old. In a time before cellular phones, when reporters raced to the courthouse pay phones to call in news of a verdict, Mr. Sosin carried a pad of yellow ''out of order'' stickers, which he would slap onto a phone before going into the courtroom.</p>
        <p>One day a young reporter, Martin Merzer, now with The Miami Herald, sat beside Mr. Sosin in the courtroom.</p>
        <p>''Hey, kid,'' Mr. Sosin asked him, ''have you filed yet?''</p>
        <p>Mr. Merzer told him the phone was out of order.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sosin reached into his pocket and showed him the pad of stickers.</p>
        <p>''He had this wonderful, evil smile on his face,'' Mr. Merzer remembered.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sosin often outsmarted editors who tried to change him.</p>
        <p>He was once given an assignment by The News that took him away from Miami's warm winter, and bought an overcoat.</p>
        <p>''He kept turning it in in his expense report, over and over again, and they kept rejecting it,'' said Will Lester, now an Associated Press political writer, who once worked with him. ''Finally he stopped. They asked him what happened, why he stopped filing it. He told them: 'It's in there. You find it.' ''</p>
        <p>Broken into little pieces, in the itemized accounts of meals and drinks and taxi rides, was Milt Sosin's overcoat.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kleinberg remembers his first confrontation with Mr. Sosin.</p>
        <p>''He told me, 'You'll find some rum somewhere in this office, and I'll expect you to keep it there,' '' Mr. Kleinberg said. ''I told him that alcohol is not allowed in the newsroom.</p>
        <p>''And he told me: 'I go out on fires for this newspaper. I get wet for this newspaper. And when I come back, I need my shot of rum. No rum, no fires. Your choice.' ''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kleinberg told his assistant, ''Leave the rum there, for Sosin.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
