<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cabinet Member's Death Puts Spotlight on India's Health System</title>
    <meta content="24INDI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224958"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">India</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dugger, Celia W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kumaramangalam, P Rangarajan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000824T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E5DD1431F937A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="570" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cabinet Member's Death Puts Spotlight on India's Health System</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CELIA W. DUGGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dugger, Celia W</byline>
      <dateline>NEW DELHI, Aug. 23</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Death of P Rangarajan Kumaramangalam, a popular and lively leader of India's governing party, shakes country's political elite, many of whom believe that he got faulty medical care at one of New Delhi's most prestigious privately run hospitals; quality of health care for hundreds of millions of Indians is acknowledged to be miserable, but country's elected officials, and especially cabinet ministers like Kumaramangalam, are expected to get only the best (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The death of a popular and lively leader of India's governing party today has shaken the capital's political elite, many of whom believe that he got faulty medical care at one of New Delhi's most prestigious privately run hospitals.</p>
        <p>P. Rangarajan Kumaramangalam, who at 48 was the power minister and a relatively young leader in the gerontocracy of the Hindu nationalist Bharatiya Janata Party, was treated for a fever four months ago at what is widely regarded as the city's premier private hospital.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The death of a popular and lively leader of India's governing party today has shaken the capital's political elite, many of whom believe that he got faulty medical care at one of New Delhi's most prestigious privately run hospitals.</p>
        <p>P. Rangarajan Kumaramangalam, who at 48 was the power minister and a relatively young leader in the gerontocracy of the Hindu nationalist Bharatiya Janata Party, was treated for a fever four months ago at what is widely regarded as the city's premier private hospital.</p>
        <p>But doctors there did not detect the cancer that contributed to his death, acute myeloid leukemia, and say they do not believe that he had cancer when he was there.</p>
        <p>While the quality of health care for hundreds of millions of Indians is miserable, the country's elected leaders are expected to get only the best. Government officials generally, and cabinet ministers especially, are a privileged class, entitled to free medical care, priority seats on trains and planes, use of government cars and virtually rent-free housing.</p>
        <p>So when Mr. Kumaramangalam, a fixture in the capital who was universally and affectionately known by the nickname Ranga, lapsed into a coma a week ago and was found to have leukemia only a few days later, there was disbelief among political colleagues and journalists.</p>
        <p>The Hindustan Times, a national daily newspaper, wrote, ''The common man may well wonder: if this is how a minister who has access to the best doctors and hospitals in the country is treated, what about the rest of us?''</p>
        <p>Leaders in the Bharatiya Janata Party, which heads the coalition government, are calling for an investigation of Indraprastha Apollo Hospital, which treated Mr. Kumaramangalam four months ago. The hospital has strongly denied any errors in its handling of the case.</p>
        <p>Prime Minister Atal Behari Vajpayee, 73, and a parade of the nation's aging political leaders called on Mr. Kumaramangalam's home today. Mr. Vajpayee said in a statement, ''The cruel hand of death has snatched away from our midst a young and dynamic national leader.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kumaramangalam, a longtime member of Parliament from the southern state of Tamil Nadu and a strong advocate of the privatization of government-owned enterprises, sought treatment for a persistent fever four months ago at Apollo, which is part of India's first corporate chain of hospitals.</p>
        <p>The hospital's statements about his care make clear that he was treated as what is generally known here as a ''V.V.I.P.'' -- a very, very important person.</p>
        <p>Provided with ''extreme care and all personal attention,'' he was given a battery of tests, was treated with antibiotics for malaria and left the hospital when he started feeling better, according to a press release. ''After his discharge, we continued following Sri Kumaramangalam's health because he was dear to us,'' the hospital said, using a Hindi term of respect for him.</p>
        <p>The hospital said that it had consulted experts in Boston who agreed with its care of the minister, and that he had not returned for recommended follow-up visits, ''probably because of his busy schedule.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kumaramangalam's illness was diagnosed only a few days ago after he was admitted to the All India Institute of Medical Sciences, the country's leading public hospital, also in New Delhi.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
