<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Metro Matters; Confession TV Is Legal; Is It Right?</title>
    <meta content="24MATT$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/24/nyregion/24MATT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224955"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings (Video)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Confessions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Court TV (Network)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Purnick, Joyce</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Confessions (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Metro Matters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Video)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000824T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEEDE1431F937A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="757" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Metro Matters; Confession TV Is Legal; Is It Right?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOYCE PURNICK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Purnick, Joyce</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Joyce Purnick column holds that Confessions, television program that will premiere on Court TV in Sept, has generated sharp debate in legal world; notes that critics say program, which will televise videotaped confessions of killers and other criminals, will hurt prisoners, crime victims and their families (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE man with the stringy long hair sits in a grimy room, laughing about pot one moment, swatting at a mosquito the next. He pulls a copy of ''Mein Kampf'' out of a plastic bag, mumbles something about Hitler and numbers, then, his face a blank, tells how he killed a friend and dismembered her body.</p>
        <p>The tinny-sounding videotape is an actual confession by Daniel Rakowitz, who killed and carved up a woman in the East Village 11 years ago. Now his bizarre confession is about to go public, in the premiere of a television program coming to Court TV next month. ''Confessions,'' it's called -- videotaped confessions of killers, rapists and other felons that will fill a half-hour every week starting Sept. 10.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE man with the stringy long hair sits in a grimy room, laughing about pot one moment, swatting at a mosquito the next. He pulls a copy of ''Mein Kampf'' out of a plastic bag, mumbles something about Hitler and numbers, then, his face a blank, tells how he killed a friend and dismembered her body.</p>
        <p>The tinny-sounding videotape is an actual confession by Daniel Rakowitz, who killed and carved up a woman in the East Village 11 years ago. Now his bizarre confession is about to go public, in the premiere of a television program coming to Court TV next month. ''Confessions,'' it's called -- videotaped confessions of killers, rapists and other felons that will fill a half-hour every week starting Sept. 10.</p>
        <p>Televising the confession of someone convicted or, as in Mr. Rakowitz's case, found not responsible for reasons of insanity, is legal. Unless someone is acquitted, a confession is a public record, accessible on First Amendment grounds, lawyers say.</p>
        <p>But is being legal good enough?</p>
        <p>Word of this latest incarnation of reality TV has generated an unusually sharp debate in the legal world. Supporters say the programs will educate. Critics say they will hurt prisoners, crime victims and their families and distort a complicated process.</p>
        <p>''There are arguments on both sides,'' said Court TV's chairman and chief executive, Henry Schleiff, who has a talent for understatement. In his view, ''Confessions'' will edify.</p>
        <p>Robert M. Morgenthau, the Manhattan district attorney, agrees. He told producers about the taped confessions a few months ago. He met with a producer, Eric Nadler, and his associate, Richard Kroehling, who had gone to talk with Mr. Morgenthau about program ideas; Mr. Nadler is an old friend.</p>
        <p>''Morgenthau said, 'You know what I have here?' '' Mr. Kroehling recalled. '' 'Something pretty interesting. Videotaped confessions.' Eric and I have a certain cultural sensitivity, a sense of the zeitgeist. Immediately we looked at each other, had an understanding we had something profound here. Something true.''</p>
        <p>Others have a less benign view. ''This is pandering to a kind of morbid curiosity,'' said Burt Neuborne, a professor at the New York University School of Law. Nancy Ruhe-Munch, executive director of the National Organization of Parents of Murdered Children Inc., said her organization would protest the program. ''Imagine a mother or parent or sibling sitting down, turning on Court TV and seeing their loved one's murderer confess.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Morgenthau said yesterday that his interest was to give the public insights into the criminal justice system: ''Videotaped confessions are the most significant development prior to DNA. Then there couldn't be any arguments, you've got a tamper-proof clock behind the witness, you can see the guy talking freely, no bruise marks on him. I wasn't even suggesting they show them. What they do with the tapes is their business. We are not censors. I thought maybe they'd do a program about videotaped statements.''</p>
        <p>COURT TV is planning to do at least 13 programs -- a season's worth -- using confessions from around the country. The programs will have no narration, no host. Viewers will see just wall-to-wall confessions, and learn about the defendant's sentence. They will see tapes of the crime scenes, too, some recreated. Further discussion of the case will be relegated to the cable channel's Web site.</p>
        <p>That, beyond taste, is the main problem, critics say. ''It is one thing to see a confession in the context of a fully developed case, but just to see a run of confessions, one after another, is diabolical and voyeuristic,'' said Stephen Gillers, an N.Y.U. law professor who specializes in legal ethics.</p>
        <p>The tapes, an hour or longer originally, will be edited down to 7 or 10 minutes each. ''I'd be a little worried about the impact on the public's concept of the criminal justice system,'' said Stephen J. Schulhofer, professor at the University of Chicago Law School. ''A confession is an incredibly self-destructive act. I worry this will create a selective and oversimplified view of what Frankfurter called the suction process.''</p>
        <p>He noted that prosecutors and police authorities use sophisticated techniques to elicit confessions. Interrogators are, for instance, often elaborately sympathetic to the defendant. How much of that will be televised, and if it is, will viewers understand what the authorities are doing without an explanation?</p>
        <p>It probably does not matter. If the public can fixate on a fake deserted island, why not on ''the ultimate perp walk,'' in Professor Neuborne's words, masquerading as educational TV?</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
