<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="24DIGE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224989"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000824T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE5DB1431F937A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="694" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>United Airlines Requires Overtime for Mechanics  To help overcome delays and cancellations that have plagued it this summer, United Airlines has issued an order requiring mechanics at five airports to work overtime if asked. About 50 of the airline's 10,000 mechanics have been working overtime in Chicago, Los Angeles, Washington and Indianapolis to try to make sure that flights take off on time.</p>
        <p>An order, called an operational emergency, was also issued in Denver, but no mechanics have been asked to work overtime there. United and union spokesmen said the airline does not often issue such an order. Shares of UAL, United's parent, fell $1, to $47.63. [Page A14.]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>United Airlines Requires Overtime for Mechanics  To help overcome delays and cancellations that have plagued it this summer, United Airlines has issued an order requiring mechanics at five airports to work overtime if asked. About 50 of the airline's 10,000 mechanics have been working overtime in Chicago, Los Angeles, Washington and Indianapolis to try to make sure that flights take off on time.</p>
        <p>An order, called an operational emergency, was also issued in Denver, but no mechanics have been asked to work overtime there. United and union spokesmen said the airline does not often issue such an order. Shares of UAL, United's parent, fell $1, to $47.63. [Page A14.]</p>
        <p>Stocks Edge Up After Fed Decision  Stocks closed modestly higher as investors surveyed a new economic outlook that apparently includes stable interest rates. The Dow Jones industrial average rose 5.50 points, to 11,144.65. The Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index climbed 7.84 points, or 0.5 percent, to 1,505.97, and the Nasdaq composite index was up 52.80 points, or 1.3 percent, to 4,011.01. [C11.]</p>
        <p>Agreement Reached in Phone Strike  Verizon Communications and a union representing more than 35,000 employees in several mid-Atlantic states settled an 18-day strike after the company agreed to reduce requirements for mandatory overtime and to pay a bilingual salary differential.[C5.]</p>
        <p>Dick Cheney's Business Record  Just how successful Dick Cheney, the Republican vice presidential nominee, was as chief executive of Halliburton is a matter of considerable dispute, judging by a broad survey of his record that included interviews with current and former company executives. [A1.]</p>
        <p>Simon &amp; Schuster to Sell E-Books  Simon &amp; Schuster announced a list of electronic books that it will sell this fall, making it the third major trade publisher to make books available for downloading. [C8.]</p>
        <p>Senate Hearings to Be Held on Tires  The Senate Commerce Committee is planning to conduct hearings on the Firestone tires that were recalled, a Congressional aide said. The committee will convene hearings next month to examine the recent problems that caused Bridgestone/Firestone to recall about 6.5 million tires, the staff member said. Senator John McCain of Arizona, chairman of the committee, requested the hearings. [C5.]</p>
        <p>Profit Falls 74% at Dillard's  Dillard's, the department store chain, said that its second-quarter profit plunged 74 percent, well below Wall Street forecasts, as same-store sales declined 3 percent. [C5.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
