<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Only 2 Developers Express Interest in Building Trading Complex for Stock Exchange</title>
    <meta content="24EXCH$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/24/nyregion/24EXCH.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224945"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Stock Exchange</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Tishman Speyer Properties</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Brookfield Financial Properties Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Rudin Organization</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Boston Properties</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bagli, Charles V</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000824T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E5DE1431F937A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1027" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Only 2 Developers Express Interest in Building Trading Complex for Stock Exchange</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLES V. BAGLI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bagli, Charles V</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York City officials say that Tishman Speyer Properties and Brookfield Financial Properties have indicated interest in building proposed $727 million trading complex and office tower for New York Stock Exchange in financial district; say that Rudin real estate family and Boston Properties said project was too complicated and risky (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>New York City officials are finding that the road to building a new trading complex for the New York Stock Exchange can be long and bumpy.</p>
        <p>In response to solicitations by the Giuliani administration, only two developers told the city last Friday that they were interested in building the proposed $727 million, 1.9-million-square-foot trading complex and office tower on a block bounded by Wall, Broad and William Streets and Exchange Place. Two other developers approached by the city's Economic Development Corporation decided that the project was too complicated and risky, according to real estate executives involved in the talks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>New York City officials are finding that the road to building a new trading complex for the New York Stock Exchange can be long and bumpy.</p>
        <p>In response to solicitations by the Giuliani administration, only two developers told the city last Friday that they were interested in building the proposed $727 million, 1.9-million-square-foot trading complex and office tower on a block bounded by Wall, Broad and William Streets and Exchange Place. Two other developers approached by the city's Economic Development Corporation decided that the project was too complicated and risky, according to real estate executives involved in the talks.</p>
        <p>And 20 months after Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani announced plans for the heavily subsidized project in the financial district, the New York Stock Exchange has still not signed a formal agreement with the Giuliani administration, although city officials say a deal is imminent, as they have been saying for more than a year.</p>
        <p>''I think we're getting close,'' said Michael Carey, president of the Economic Development Corporation. ''I continue to be optimistic that the project will go forward.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Carey said he was close to concluding a deal to buy the site from the property owners, J. P. Morgan and the Rockrose Development Corporation. The state would condemn one other parcel on the block.</p>
        <p>Tishman Speyer Properties and Brookfield Financial Properties both indicated interest in the stock exchange project, but the Rudin real estate family and Boston Properties took a pass. The city has told the applicants that it wanted to select a developer by Sept. 1.</p>
        <p>In one bright spot, the American International Group, one of the world's largest insurance companies, has expressed interest in occupying a part of the office tower over the trading complex, real estate executives and a city official said. But the company has made no commitments and says it is unsure yet how much space it needs.</p>
        <p>City officials are hoping that the sale of development rights for the office tower will more than offset the projected $350 million cost of acquiring the block across the street from the stock exchange's historic Wall Street home.</p>
        <p>''The trick is to get a tenant,'' said one real estate executive working with A.I.G. ''But this is not even close to being done. It's very murky.''</p>
        <p>The proposed project has been clouded by rapid changes in the financial industry -- toward electronic trading -- as well as by the complicated nature of the deal.</p>
        <p>Two years ago, the stock exchange threatened to move to New Jersey if the city could not help it expand beyond its cramped, 97-year-old quarters on Wall Street. Many urban planners and real estate executives doubted that the exchange would relocate, especially since most of the large investment banks that trade at the exchange had invested in Manhattan real estate and received tax breaks for promising to remain in New York.</p>
        <p>But Mayor Giuliani said the city could not risk losing the stock exchange, and in December 1998, city and state officials agreed to build a new trading complex and provide $160 million in tax breaks. The cost for the trading complex itself has since grown to $482 million.</p>
        <p>At the same time, some securities analysts have questioned the need for expanded trading floors, given the rapid growth of electronic trading. Electronic networks now account for 37 percent of the trades on the Nasdaq and about 3 percent of the volume on the New York Stock Exchange, according to the Tower Group, a research firm.</p>
        <p>Richard A. Grasso, chairman of the stock exchange, has insisted that the need for a new trading floor remains. But the plans for the new complex no longer call for two 50,000-square-foot trading floors.</p>
        <p>To offset the separate cost of buying the property to build the complex, the city proposed selling the right to build a large office tower over the project. There is very little vacant space downtown.</p>
        <p>Earlier this year, city officials, in consultation with the stock exchange, asked four developers to submit proposals to build the trading complex and office tower, which would be assessed full taxes. The developers were required to build whether or not they had a tenant for the tower, a risk that few builders were willing to undertake.</p>
        <p>''There was no way we could look the city in the eye and tell them we could go ahead without a tenant,'' said an executive who decided not to get involved. ''I saw something enormously complicated that would take years to build.''</p>
        <p>Some real estate executives were also worried that the security requirements imposed by the exchange and the uncertainty about the start of construction would scare away many potential tenants.</p>
        <p>But, according to real estate executives, Tishman Speyer, which has long sought to build the project, said it was willing to take the risk and pay millions of dollars in penalties if it failed to move ahead with the building. But it stopped short of saying it would build no matter what. Brookfield, another major landlord in the city, said it wanted to develop the project, but only under certain conditions.</p>
        <p>Many of the developers' misgivings would be allayed if A.I.G., or another company, agreed to lease a major block of space in what would otherwise be a speculative office tower. The insurance company has thousands of employees working in Lower Manhattan. But it has backed out of deals before. In 1989, A.I.G, scuttled a tentative commitment to take 500,000 square feet of space at Renaissance Plaza in downtown Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>Nearly four years ago, the Giuliani administration gave A.I.G. $55.7 million in tax breaks to stay in the city. The city had provided the company a round of subsidies in 1993 after it threatened to move to Georgia.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, A.I.G. is expanding and in need of office space.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
