<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nets' Martin Gets Ready to Play for Pay</title>
    <meta content="24NETS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224946"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Jersey Nets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Robbins, Liz</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Martin, Kenyon</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New Jersey Nets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000824T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E4DE1431F937A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="587" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nets' Martin Gets Ready to Play for Pay</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIZ ROBBINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Robbins, Liz</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., Aug. 23</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Kenyon Martin, NBA's No 1 draft pick, officially signs his $11.4 million, three-year contract with New Jersey Nets (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Kenyon Martin officially signed his contract with a disposable pen from the Ritz Carlton this afternoon in the Nets' Champion Center. And having finished that formality, Martin, the National Basketball Association's No. 1 draft pick, was eager to earn his salary.</p>
        <p>Martin has built his mother a house in Dallas, bought his sister and her family one on the same block and purchased a couple of cars with advances from his $3.5 million first-year salary, part of an $11.4 million, three-year contract.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Kenyon Martin officially signed his contract with a disposable pen from the Ritz Carlton this afternoon in the Nets' Champion Center. And having finished that formality, Martin, the National Basketball Association's No. 1 draft pick, was eager to earn his salary.</p>
        <p>Martin has built his mother a house in Dallas, bought his sister and her family one on the same block and purchased a couple of cars with advances from his $3.5 million first-year salary, part of an $11.4 million, three-year contract.</p>
        <p>But while the 22-year-old Martin was about to go house-hunting with his new wife, Fatimah, excited to spend his new money, he was careful not to be overwhelmed. ''There's been guys I've seen who are just glad they got their check,'' he said. ''But I'm not that type of person. I've been playing for free for so long and I've been playing hard for free for so long. If I don't play hard, I won't be able to sleep at night.''</p>
        <p>Martin, who played college ball at Cincinnati, played hard last week at the Pete Newell Big Man Camp in Hawaii. Playing competitively for the first time since breaking his leg in March, he impressed coaches and scouts with his shot-blocking and running. ''Now I just need to get into basketball shape,'' he said. ''This is an 82-game season and not a 32-game season. I'll get in shape and, hopefully, I'll play 40 minutes a game.''</p>
        <p>With that, Nets Coach Byron Scott just smiled.</p>
        <p>''He can make an immediate impact on our team,'' Scott said. ''We're not going to bring him along slowly. Kenyon is already marked in the starting lineup and he'll be playing, maybe not 40 minutes, but a lot of minutes. It's a lot of pressure being put on him at an early age and I think he can handle it.''</p>
        <p>Scott was pleased to hear reports about Martin's camp performance. When Martin passed the Nets' physical on Tuesday, that was confirmation that his leg had healed.</p>
        <p>At first, the coaches at the camp were reluctant to involve him in hard-contact drills. ''They wanted me to take it easy,'' Martin recalled, ''and I went as hard as I could go.''</p>
        <p>Having spent 10 days in Hawaii for his wedding and honeymoon, Martin was more than ready to play.</p>
        <p>''My father-in-law said I needed to go elbow people,'' Martin said, laughing.</p>
        <p>In one of the first camp drills, the 6-foot-9-inch Martin was going one-on-one with 6-10 Adonal Foyle of Golden State. He blocked Foyle's shot. ''He got the ball right back and then I blocked it again,'' Martin said. ''I knew right then I was fine.''</p>
        <p>But Martin does not want to talk about the leg anymore. ''I've got a lot to prove just because I was the No. 1 pick in the draft,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Scott will play Martin at small forward and power forward along with Keith Van Horn. The Nets' offense will be up-tempo and will not focus on center, with Evan Eschmeyer, Jim McIlvaine and Jamie Feick sharing the position.</p>
        <p>''Kenyon wants to be thrown in,'' Scott said. ''I'm not going to overdo it.''</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
