<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Assemblyman Says He's Fighting Harder in Rematch</title>
    <meta content="24PRIM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/24/nyregion/24PRIM.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="NEW YORK PRIMARY -- 43rd Assembly District" name="series_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224953"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hicks, Jonathan P</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Norman, Clarence Jr (Assemblyman)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Davis, James E (Police Officer)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000824T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404EEDE1431F937A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1177" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Assemblyman Says He's Fighting Harder in Rematch</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN P. HICKS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hicks, Jonathan P</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article in series New York Primary focuses on race between Assemblyman Clarence Norman Jr and James E Davis in 43rd Assembly District, Brooklyn; notes that Norman, chairman of borough's Democratic Party, beat Davis, police officer and minister, by only 677 votes in Democratic primary two years ago; map; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the chairman of the Democratic Party organization in Brooklyn, Assemblyman Clarence Norman Jr. has long been known for masterminding the strategies of a host of political races in his borough and beyond. And so the thinness of his re-election victory two years ago, by just 677 votes in the Democratic primary, was something of an embarrassment.</p>
        <p>In the Sept. 12 primary this year, Mr. Norman is once again facing James E. Davis, a police officer and minister who has devoted much of his energy over the last two years to this rematch.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As the chairman of the Democratic Party organization in Brooklyn, Assemblyman Clarence Norman Jr. has long been known for masterminding the strategies of a host of political races in his borough and beyond. And so the thinness of his re-election victory two years ago, by just 677 votes in the Democratic primary, was something of an embarrassment.</p>
        <p>In the Sept. 12 primary this year, Mr. Norman is once again facing James E. Davis, a police officer and minister who has devoted much of his energy over the last two years to this rematch.</p>
        <p>It is a race that Brooklyn politicians are paying close attention to, not only because of Mr. Norman's stature within the party, but also because the election could be affected if other hotly contested races in central Brooklyn generate a sizable turnout.</p>
        <p>Mr. Norman, who was first elected to the Assembly in 1982, is determined to make a more impressive showing this time, he said. And by his own admission, he is spending far more time on his re-election campaign than he did in 1998, when he was overwhelmed by his work on other campaigns.</p>
        <p>''This year, I am focusing solely on my race,'' said Mr. Norman, who is 49. ''Last time I was deeply involved in races outside of my district.'' In that year, he said, his top priorities were the campaign of Eliot L. Spitzer, who was elected the state's attorney general, and the unsuccessful attempt by Charles J. Hynes, the Brooklyn district attorney, to win the Democratic primary for governor.</p>
        <p>''Two years ago, my own race was subordinate,'' Mr. Norman said. ''This time, it is completely different. We have done aggressive outreach. I have been doing town hall-style meetings and meetings with tenant associations.'' Indeed, Mr. Norman is spending his days on the streets of the district, greeting voters at subway stations in the morning and meeting with civic associations in the evenings.</p>
        <p>But it is Mr. Norman's campaign activity that has served as fodder for  Mr. Davis's harshest criticism of the assemblyman, whom he portrays as being more concerned about politics outside the district than he is about the needs of his constituents.</p>
        <p>''The fact that he is visible now makes the people in this district more aware of how invisible he has been for the 20 years he has been in office,'' Mr. Davis said. ''We have drug dealing in our neighborhoods. We need youth programs. Clarence Norman has been in office for 20 years and his record is abysmal. People in our district don't even know who their assemblyman is.''</p>
        <p>Residents of the 43rd Assembly District, which includes the Crown Heights and East Flatbush sections of Brooklyn, have had several opportunities to know Mr. Davis. Apart from his campaign against Mr. Norman in 1998, Mr. Davis ran an unsuccessful campaign in the Democratic primary against City Councilwoman Mary Pinkett in 1997. And in 1996, he failed to get a spot on the ballot in a primary campaign against Representative Major Owens.</p>
        <p>In 1998, after losing the Democratic primary to Mr. Norman, Mr. Davis found his name on the ballot on the Liberal Party line. He was then dismissed from his job by the Police Department, which said that Mr. Davis violated the department's policy by being an active-duty officer while being the designated candidate of a political party for office.</p>
        <p>Mr. Davis, 38, argued that he had never been officially designated as the Liberal Party's candidate, a position supported by the party itself. Earlier this year, Mr. Davis won a court ruling saying that his dismissal was unjust, and he was reinstated.</p>
        <p>Mr. Davis has also made a name for himself as the chief organizer of an anti-violence march in Crown Heights each summer. Posters and billboards about the march appear throughout the district and carry photographs of Mr. Davis.</p>
        <p>It is that march that serves as the centerpiece of Mr. Norman's complaints about his opponent. Mr. Davis, he said, raises ''hundreds of thousands of dollars for a march that lasts a few hours once a year. I wonder, what does he do with all that money?''</p>
        <p>Mr. Davis said that Mr. Norman exaggerated the amount of money raised, and that the funds were used to publicize and operate the march.</p>
        <p>In addressing Mr. Davis's complaints, Mr. Norman criticized Mr. Davis for not having been involved in any community efforts aimed at easing the problems that he cites. ''He talks about the need for youth programs and initiatives to stop gang violence and other violence in the community. So, I have to ask, if he is so committed to those efforts, why hasn't he established any programs to help?''</p>
        <p>While acknowledging his deep involvement in the campaigns of other Democrats over the years, Mr. Norman insisted that it had not caused his work in the district to suffer.</p>
        <p>''He talks about the problems of youth,'' Mr. Norman said. ''But we have developed computer training programs at schools. We've worked closely with parent and teacher organizations. We have secured millions of dollars for the renovation of schools in this district.''</p>
        <p>Most Brooklyn politicians expect Mr. Norman to prevail. He is outspending his opponent heavily -- Mr. Davis said he was spending less than $15,000. And Mr. Norman's office in Crown Heights has been buzzing with activity, with campaign workers picking up materials and being deployed on the streets daily.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Davis insists that although he will be outspent, he will produce a stunning upset. He adds that he will benefit from the Congressional race between Mr. Owens and his challenger, City Councilwoman Una S. T. Clarke. Mr. Davis insists that many of Ms. Clarke's supporters will be motivated to vote for him, since Mr. Norman has been a strong opponent of her candidacy for Congress.</p>
        <p>''No one gave me much of a chance last time,'' Mr. Davis said. ''I didn't have much money but I still came close to knocking him down. This year, I have been working the areas where I didn't do well last time. I have listened to the complaints of the people. And you will see a difference in the results.''</p>
        <p>NEW YORK PRIMARY -- 43rd Assembly District</p>
        <p>Articles in this series are examining individual primary contests in Congressional and local districts.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
