<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Beijing Journal; For a While, Crime Paid. Then Came This Exhibit.</title>
    <meta content="Y24BEI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224961"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Embezzlement</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bribery</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Extortion and Blackmail</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Beijing (China)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eckholm, Erik</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China/Beijing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bribery</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Embezzlement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Extortion and Blackmail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000824T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E2DD1431F937A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1221" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Beijing Journal; For a While, Crime Paid. Then Came This Exhibit.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIK ECKHOLM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eckholm, Erik</byline>
      <dateline>BEIJING, Aug. 23</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>City government of Beijing mounts exhibit on evils of bribery, embezzlement and fraud as part of growing national propaganda campaign that officials hope will scare off potential economic criminals and convince an angry and skeptical population that the authorities are battling corruption; among cautionary exhibits are those on an embezzler sentenced to life in prison and a former legislator now on death row for extorting $5 million; many visitors leave the exhibition dissatisfied, for it fails to acknowledge depth to which corruption has infected Communist Party; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The multitudes visiting Beijing's newest museum exhibit are greeted by pretty young guides in neat white dresses. Providing nonstop fact-filled commentary through a half-hour tour, the escorts cheerfully explain highlights of the posters and showcases that fill two large halls of the Military Museum.</p>
        <p>The scene resembles a commercial fair or a convention, and you would hardly guess that the show is devoted to an evil that Communist leaders call one of the gravest threats to China's stability.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The multitudes visiting Beijing's newest museum exhibit are greeted by pretty young guides in neat white dresses. Providing nonstop fact-filled commentary through a half-hour tour, the escorts cheerfully explain highlights of the posters and showcases that fill two large halls of the Military Museum.</p>
        <p>The scene resembles a commercial fair or a convention, and you would hardly guess that the show is devoted to an evil that Communist leaders call one of the gravest threats to China's stability.</p>
        <p>This oddly toned ''Beijing Exhibition on Attacking and Preventing Economic Crime'' has been staged by the city government together with the police, prosecutors and courts. Ostensibly intended to educate the public about bribery, embezzlement and fraud, it will run for a month.</p>
        <p>It is part of a growing national propaganda campaign that officials hope will scare off potential miscreants and -- most important to the party's survival -- convince an angry and skeptical population that the authorities are battling corruption.</p>
        <p>While would-be voyeurs did not find any mink coats or pictures of errant officials' secret love nests, some of the tens of thousands who crowded the show in its opening days this week did shake their heads at the stories of audacious swindles. As one woman studied the picture of an embezzler sentenced to life in prison, she muttered, ''He should be shot.''</p>
        <p>Others were intrigued by the suitcase of counterfeit bills on display, or fascinated by the re-created living room -- with fine furniture and liquor bottles -- of an official, since executed, who with his wife stole millions from a state enterprise.</p>
        <p>But the exhibition also pulls its punches, reflecting the party's unease with full exposure of a cancer that has spread so deeply in its own ranks. And as a result, many concerned citizens left the halls expressing dissatisfaction.</p>
        <p>As he fanned himself outside the museum, Li Yushu, a retired teacher in his late 70's, said he had come ''because corruption is such a serious problem,'' but he added that ''exhibitions like this one can't get at the root of the problem.''</p>
        <p>''Dealing with corruption requires building up the rule of law and reforming the government,'' Mr. Li said. ''Ordinary people like me feel that the government's crackdown is not intense enough.''</p>
        <p>The most glaring omission in this exhibit of 70 major ''economic crimes'' is the infamous case of Chen Xitong, Beijing's former mayor and Communist Party chief as well as a member of the party's all-powerful Politburo, who is now serving time for his bribery schemes.</p>
        <p>This decision to ignore the country's most sensational and politically sensitive case did not escape notice. Many Beijing residents are skeptical about the consistency of law enforcement anyway, often repeating stories about well-connected senior officials who escaped prosecution.</p>
        <p>One notorious case does get good exposure: that of Cheng Kejie, until recently a vice chairman of the national Parliament and the former kingpin of a backward southern province who is on death row for extorting $5 million in payoffs. The crowds lingered longest before a giant photograph of the handcuffed Mr. Cheng in court and a small one of his mistress, Li Ping, who shared the money and got a life sentence.</p>
        <p>But many other exhibits involve private crimes like credit-card fraud or consumer swindles rather than the gross abuses of official power that are of greatest public concern. And lumping these two categories together as ''economic crimes'' tends to blur the crucial distinction.</p>
        <p>An editor with a government publication who brought along her teenage daughter said she had found the exhibit disappointing in ways she couldn't quite put her finger on.</p>
        <p>''Everybody already knows about these kinds of cases anyway; they're in the newspapers every day,'' said the editor, who would give only her surname, Li. ''I was expecting something more.''</p>
        <p>''For example, the papers said that the largest display was devoted to Cheng Kejie,'' she said, referring to the convicted legislator, whose bribery scandal had implicated many other officials. ''But it didn't tell us anything new at all. I'd like to know more of the inside story.''</p>
        <p>Unwilling to permit a free press or free elections -- which foreign analysts say are most vital to curbing corruption -- the government is relying on propaganda, showcase executions and the fitful strengthening of law enforcement.</p>
        <p>This week, officials trumpeted a new policy that could make a difference if consistently enforced: routine financial auditing of retiring senior officials and heads of state enterprises. An assumption is that officials facing retirement are especially likely to stash away money to supplement their pensions.</p>
        <p>Fighting back qualms about a double-edged message, top officials have also publicly endorsed a gripping new feature film that portrays the noble stand of a fictional city mayor against the corruption all around him -- vice that engulfs his brother, his party patron and even his wife.</p>
        <p>The movie, ''A Life and Death Choice,'' was adapted from a popular novel and produced by the Shanghai Film Studios. It has already opened in several cities and appears to have struck a chord. In Shanghai alone, the producers say, more than a million tickets have been sold, to private citizens as well as government employees required to attend.</p>
        <p>The film is to open in Beijing theaters on Friday, after a drumbeat of anticipation in the local papers. Last week, after an advance screening, Beijing's mayor, Liu Qi, and Communist Party secretary, Jia Qinglin, publicly praised the film and instructed all city workers to see it.</p>
        <p>By now, China's leaders can hardly avoid acknowledging that the party has harbored many bad apples. But a potential danger, as they strive to cleanse the one-party system while preserving it, is the unleashing of uncontrollable resentments.</p>
        <p>At the end of the new exhibition, next to the stack of fliers telling how to report fraud or bribery without fear of reprisals, is a sign of the new, more open China. Several city officials and private attorneys sit in a row, offering free legal consultations to museum visitors.</p>
        <p>An official from the prosecutor's office got more than she bargained for the other day. A man who had traveled from Jilin Province, in China's remote northeast, to pursue his grievance in the capital sat before her, waving old legal papers and a map of a forest area. Corrupt local officials there had cheated him out of land and logging revenues, he said.</p>
        <p>The legal official said she could only give him the phone numbers of authorities back in Jilin. But they, the man pointed out, had already refused to help. He became louder and more agitated, and refused to give up his seat. Finally a policeman came and led him away.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
