<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A National Tournament Ends With Two Lopsided Triumphs</title>
    <meta content="24CARD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224864"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BRIDGE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bridge (Card Game)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">American Contract Bridge League</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Truscott, Alan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Crossword and Games/Bridge</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bridge (Card Game)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000824T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E2DF1731F937A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="694" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A National Tournament Ends With Two Lopsided Triumphs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Alan Truscott</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Truscott, Alan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alan Truscott bridge column on finals of main knockout events at American Contract Bridge League's Spring Nationals, Anaheim, Calif; diagram (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The finals of the main knockout events at the American Contract Bridge League's Spring Nationals in Anaheim, Calif., last week were both one-sided affairs. The Spingold Teams was won, by a margin of 94, by Rose Johnson Meltzer and Peter Weichsel, both of Los Gatos, Calif.; Alan Sontag of Gaithersburg, Md.; Kyle Larsen of San Francisco; Lew Stansby of Castro Valley, Calif.; and Chip Martel of Davis, Calif. They overwhelmed Roy Welland and Brad Moss, both of Manhattan, Marc Jacobus of Las Vegas, Fred Gitelman of Toronto, and Magnus Lindqvist and Peter Fredin, both of Sweden, who had performed valiantly in ousting four higher-ranked teams in earlier rounds.</p>
        <p>In the Women's Knockout final, a highly experienced group that has won bunches of world and national titles prevailed. Kathie Wei-Sender of Nashville; Betty Ann Kennedy of Shreveport, La.; Juanita Chambers of Walpole, Mass.; Jill Levin of Riverdale, the Bronx; Janice Seamon-Molson of Miami; and Tobi Sokolow of Austin, Tex., won by 44 imps. The losers, who are to represent the United States in the world championships in the Netherlands next week, were a Texan group led by Joan Jackson.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The finals of the main knockout events at the American Contract Bridge League's Spring Nationals in Anaheim, Calif., last week were both one-sided affairs. The Spingold Teams was won, by a margin of 94, by Rose Johnson Meltzer and Peter Weichsel, both of Los Gatos, Calif.; Alan Sontag of Gaithersburg, Md.; Kyle Larsen of San Francisco; Lew Stansby of Castro Valley, Calif.; and Chip Martel of Davis, Calif. They overwhelmed Roy Welland and Brad Moss, both of Manhattan, Marc Jacobus of Las Vegas, Fred Gitelman of Toronto, and Magnus Lindqvist and Peter Fredin, both of Sweden, who had performed valiantly in ousting four higher-ranked teams in earlier rounds.</p>
        <p>In the Women's Knockout final, a highly experienced group that has won bunches of world and national titles prevailed. Kathie Wei-Sender of Nashville; Betty Ann Kennedy of Shreveport, La.; Juanita Chambers of Walpole, Mass.; Jill Levin of Riverdale, the Bronx; Janice Seamon-Molson of Miami; and Tobi Sokolow of Austin, Tex., won by 44 imps. The losers, who are to represent the United States in the world championships in the Netherlands next week, were a Texan group led by Joan Jackson.</p>
        <p>The real drama in the Spingold came 72 hours earlier, in the quarterfinal. With two deals remaining, the Meltzer team was apparently doomed, trailing by 15 imps against Rita Shugart of Pebble Beach, Calif., Andrew Robson and Tony Forrester, both of Britain, and Geir Helgemo of Norway.</p>
        <p>Then the fates served up the diagramed deal. Weichsel and Sontag, an old partnership recently revived with great success, appeared to have a bidding problem with the North-South cards. One club was strong and artificial, and the one-diamond response was negative. At his third turn Weichsel, as South, was unsure whether to head for three no-trump, or four spades, or five diamonds. To his surprise he did not reach any of those possible contracts.</p>
        <p>He temporized with a bid of three clubs and heard his partner raise. He retreated to four spades, which would have succeeded, as it happens, but North persisted in clubs. A contract of five of a minor in a four-three fit is a very rare bird, but South had no trouble at all. West led a trump, trying to cut down ruffs. South won, cashed the spade ace and ruffed a spade. He returned to his hand with a diamond lead to the ace and ruffed another spade. He then drew trumps and claimed 12 tricks without needing a favorable diamond position.</p>
        <p>This highly fortunate lie of the cards did not help North-South in the replay against Stansby and Martel, who have been one of the world's great partnerships for 20 years. Forrester arrived in a more normal three no-trump from the North position, and a heart was led. He played low from dummy, and West won with the king and drove out the ace.</p>
        <p>Now North's main chance was to run five diamond tricks, but he spotted a slight extra chance. If a defender happened to hold the queen-10 doubleton of clubs, he could make four tricks in that suit. He therefore cashed the club ace and was hopeful when the 10 appeared. He continued with the king and finished two down instead of one down. Stansby had thoughtfully dropped the 10 to encourage the play of the king, and gained an imp by doing so. The result was down two when the diamond jack did not fall.</p>
        <p>So the Meltzer team gained 11 imps, somewhat luckily, and trailed by 4. It gained another 9 on the final deal, won the match by 5 and eventually captured the title. But it was the unexpected five-club contract that did it. Without that, Rose Johnson Meltzer would not have become the first woman in 37 years to win the Spingold title. That honor might well have gone to another Californian, Rita Shugart.</p>
        <p>BRIDGE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
