<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rivera Still Confident, Just Not Invincible</title>
    <meta content="24BASE$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225037"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Curry, Jack</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rivera, Mariano</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000824T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E2DA1431F937A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="965" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rivera Still Confident, Just Not Invincible</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jack Curry</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Curry, Jack</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Yankees closer Mariano Rivera says he is still confident, but this has been frustrating season because he has not routinely dominated opponents; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mariano Rivera still jogs in confidently from the left-center-field bullpen with his piercing eyes staring at the mound while Metallica's ''Enter Sandman'' blares throughout Yankee Stadium. This scene usually occurs in the ninth inning, which has almost always been Rivera's special time.</p>
        <p>Rivera still has the same swagger and he still believes that he can pump fastballs past three hitters, end the game in style and safely deliver another victory. Rivera believes that he is the premier closer in the major leagues, a pitcher who shatters bats as if they were toothpicks and turns the ninth inning into a non-inning for opponents. His confidence is endless.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mariano Rivera still jogs in confidently from the left-center-field bullpen with his piercing eyes staring at the mound while Metallica's ''Enter Sandman'' blares throughout Yankee Stadium. This scene usually occurs in the ninth inning, which has almost always been Rivera's special time.</p>
        <p>Rivera still has the same swagger and he still believes that he can pump fastballs past three hitters, end the game in style and safely deliver another victory. Rivera believes that he is the premier closer in the major leagues, a pitcher who shatters bats as if they were toothpicks and turns the ninth inning into a non-inning for opponents. His confidence is endless.</p>
        <p>''I always, always, always feel that way,'' explained Rivera. ''I'll tell you something. When I lose that confidence, I won't be pitching anymore.''</p>
        <p>Rivera almost did not pitch last night. The Yankees built a 7-4 bulge against the Texas Rangers, but collapsed during a chaotic eighth inning filled with misplaced pitches, misplays and more booing than is usually heard in the Bronx for five nights.</p>
        <p>Mike Stanton, who relieved Roger Clemens to start the seventh inning, could not throw strikes and, when he finally did, Ricky Ledee drilled a three-run homer in the next inning against his former team. Jeff Nelson and Jorge Posada flubbed slow rollers in front of the plate, and then Luis Alicea slapped a single past Nelson to push the Texas Rangers in front, 9-7. Three outs before Rivera's time, the Yankees looked suspect.</p>
        <p>But Posada hammered a two-run homer in the bottom of the eighth, and Rivera squeezed out of a first-and-second, no-out jam in the ninth, with help from Jose Vizcaino's diving stab to start a double play. Tino Martinez then bounced a one-out single past first base in the bottom of the inning to secure a 10-9 triumph.</p>
        <p>''It was an ugly game, but it was good to win,'' Manager Joe Torre said.</p>
        <p>Despite Rivera's dangerous dance to his seventh victory, he acknowledged that this has been a frustrating season because he has not routinely dominated opponents. Rivera has botched 5 saves in 31 chances after mishandling only 4 in 55 tries in the 1999 regular-season and postseason, and he does not ooze with invincibility. There are some doubts, however minor, about Rivera and he knows it.</p>
        <p>''I'm human,'' Rivera said. ''I'm not a machine.''</p>
        <p>In some ways, the Rivera of 2000 is a microcosm of the Yankees of 2000. He is having a solid season and getting results that most closers would drool over. Just like the Yankees. They are having a solid season and would need to collapse in the next six weeks to miss the postseason, a position most teams would lust after. But the two-time defending World Series champions are not having a phenomenal season and, like Rivera, they are not invincible anymore.</p>
        <p>The Yankees thought their bullpen situation could not get worse after  they blew an 8-3 lead in the ninth to the Anaheim Angels and eventually tumbled, 9-8, in 11 innings last Friday. Then Nelson and Stanton botched a 3-0 lead and the Yankees lost to the Angels, 5-4, last Sunday. Torre spoke hopefully about uncorking a lengthy winning streak, but he watched Stanton and Nelson crumble last night before the Yankees rallied. That was similar to how Rivera failed last Friday in permitting a run-scoring double and Mo Vaughn's three-run homer.</p>
        <p>''That never happens to me,'' said Rivera, whose 2.98 earned run average is about a run higher than his combined E.R.A. for the last four seasons. ''Of course, I was shocked.''</p>
        <p>Torre said that the Yankees have been disjointed this season and that they have had to ''rally around'' the inferior areas. Rivera has certainly been one of the strongest links on a team that has underachieved. Even after the Yankees added eight new players since June, they have barely stayed ahead of the beleaguered Red Sox in the American League East.</p>
        <p>Rivera's sputtering from great to good is noticeable because he has always given the Yankees an edge by being automatic. He is still reliable, but he is not as automatic. Neither is the Yankees' bullpen, which has struggled after being mostly dependable.</p>
        <p>''They need to pitch better,'' Martinez said bluntly. ''And we need to play better as a team.''</p>
        <p>Stanton, the middle reliever who has allowed two homers and six earned runs in his last three games, stared at the crowd of reporters around him and said: ''I'd just as soon have you guys never talk to me. If you guys are talking to me, I'm not doing my job. You guys have been talking to me a lot lately.''</p>
        <p>As Rivera insisted that he would not make excuses, he explained how the new baseball this year feels slick in his hand, how the seams are not raised enough and how that has affected his control. Rivera admitted that he sometimes uses his sweat and some dirt and to rub on the ball to reduce the slickness.</p>
        <p>Rivera is a slightly different pitcher, someone who is still adjusting to the new baseball, which is not a positive sign. But Rivera smiled when he talked about his staggering postseason numbers: a 4-0 record, 13 saves and a 0.37 E.R.A. The best reliever ever in October, he said he gets satisfaction only from reaching the postseason and then ''getting it done.'' Rivera's performances will help decide if the Yankees can get it done for the third straight year.</p>
        <p>''We definitely have the team,'' Rivera said. ''It's up to us, but we have the team to do it again.''</p>
        <p>ON BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
