<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Comets Want to Secure Place on Highlight Reel</title>
    <meta content="24LIBE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225015"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Houston Comets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Liberty</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Robbins, Liz</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000824T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7DA1431F937A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="995" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Comets Want to Secure Place on Highlight Reel</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIZ ROBBINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Robbins, Liz</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on upcoming WNBA finals between Houston Comets and New York Liberty; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Teresa Weatherspoon's miraculous halfcourt shot that beat the Houston Comets in Game 2 of the Women's National Basketball Association finals last summer was the league's featured promotional clip this year.</p>
        <p>The Liberty players saw it on television and in their minds all season. Yesterday, they replayed Weatherspoon's shot as a miss. A miss of an opportunity, that is.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Teresa Weatherspoon's miraculous halfcourt shot that beat the Houston Comets in Game 2 of the Women's National Basketball Association finals last summer was the league's featured promotional clip this year.</p>
        <p>The Liberty players saw it on television and in their minds all season. Yesterday, they replayed Weatherspoon's shot as a miss. A miss of an opportunity, that is.</p>
        <p>To them it was a reminder, not simply of luck, but of fortune that could have gone their way had they won the first game in Madison Square Garden.</p>
        <p>If Weatherspoon's buzzer-beater in Houston's Compaq Center had been for the championship, ''that would have been one of the greatest moments in sports,'' Liberty forward Sue Wicks said. Instead, the shot became a glorified footnote, as the Comets went on to win Game 3 and their third straight title.</p>
        <p>''Sometimes you need a little luck,'' Wicks added. ''But we know from that experience, you really want to win when you have the opportunity to win at home.''</p>
        <p>The Liberty has that chance tonight when it entertains the Comets once again to open the two-of-three-game W.N.B.A. finals in the Garden before the series shifts to Houston for the final two games. The Comets have lost only two games at the Compaq Center this season, nine in the four years of the W.N.B.A. In Houston's 11 home playoff games, Weatherspoon provided the only blemish.</p>
        <p>This year, the Comets dispatched the favored Los Angeles Sparks in two games to win the Western Conference. ''We're the only champion this league has ever seen,'' forward Tina Thompson said yesterday. ''So we have a huge target on our back.''</p>
        <p>Still, they were hurt to be left out of the league's commercial.</p>
        <p>''It was frustrating to us,'' Sheryl Swoopes, the league's most valuable player, said. ''You would think that the Liberty was the team that won the championship and not the Comets. But it's motivating us to bring home another win.''</p>
        <p>As if they need more motivation. No team in professional sports has won four straight titles since the National Hockey League's Islanders from 1980 to 1983. The Comets have become the Chicago Bulls and Yankees of the W.N.B.A. ''I thought three-peat was really tough,'' Liberty Coach Richie Adubato said. ''I thought last year maybe they would have off nights, but that didn't happen.''</p>
        <p>Weatherspoon added: ''You look at them and you can see how they do it. Any time you have a Cynthia Cooper, you're not surprising me at all.''</p>
        <p>Cooper was the league's M.V.P. in its first two seasons. And even at 37, having announced that she will retire after this season, she still has the ability to lead the Comets every night. Swoopes can do that, too, and Thompson is getting there.</p>
        <p>''Those athletes are tremendous and they know what they want and they are motivated by constantly winning,'' Weatherspoon said.</p>
        <p>The Comets beat the Liberty for their first and third championships, but each time, the Liberty has seemed to inch closer, in talent and attitude, to Houston's skyscraping standard of basketball.</p>
        <p>This is the Liberty team, say its players, that can finally knock the Comets off their pedestal.</p>
        <p>''Right now we are playing our best basketball as a team and individuals,'' Vickie Johnson said. ''The one thing I think of is: We could have won the championship last year if we had been focused. We gave it up. We were just more content to be in the finals than to win the finals.''</p>
        <p>Winning the East, which the Liberty did in a three-game series against the Cleveland Rockers, is not enough this year.</p>
        <p>''Everyone talks about how they beat L.A. and they have already beat us two times in the finals, and everybody thinks it's a joke,'' Johnson said. ''We respect Houston a great deal. But at the same time, we're not going to step on the court and give it up. If we play together as a team, we can beat them.''</p>
        <p>The Liberty combats Houston's Big Three of Cooper (20.7 points a game), Swoopes (17.7) and Thompson (16.9), with center Tari Phillips, who anchors a revamped inside-outside game with Johnson and Becky Hammon. Phillips, however, averaged only 13.8 points in the regular season, followed by Johnson at 12.3  and Hammon with 11.</p>
        <p>The Liberty has thrived on defense, scoring an average of 67.1 points during the 32-game regular season. The Comets have a more explosive offense, with the potential to score in the high 70's and 80's, mostly off transition points. The Big Three, along with point guard Janeth Arcain are so quick and athletic, Adubato said, ''It's like four guards in transition.''</p>
        <p>The Liberty is hoping to contain at least one of them. The Liberty held Cooper to 14 points and Thompson to 11 in a 69-64 victory over the Comets on July 23 at the Garden. In that game, Houston jumped to a 12-point lead, but the Liberty scored 43 points in the second half.</p>
        <p>''We have to have a fast start,'' Adubato said. ''You can't get down and have deficits against this team.''</p>
        <p>And as much as the Liberty will feast upon the energy from the home crowd -- as of last night, the game was not sold out -- Adubato is realistic. ''We just won 13 games in a row here, but we haven't played them in a while,'' he said.</p>
        <p>For both teams, the one-year playoff anniversary passed quickly. ''We might have come out with a win, but every year we've played them, they've been tough,'' Cooper said.</p>
        <p>Wicks said: ''For a couple of lucky breaks, we could have three championships here in New York. It's the little things. They have great talent, but I don't think it's just talent -- they're tremendously competitive. They have a great will to win.''</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
