<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Indonesia Inquiry: Digging Up Agonies of the Past</title>
    <meta content="Y31JAK$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203653"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Indonesia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mydans, Seth</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Suharto</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Indonesia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Indonesia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000531T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE5D6173CF932A05756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="978" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Indonesia Inquiry: Digging Up Agonies of the Past</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SETH MYDANS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mydans, Seth</byline>
      <dateline>JAKARTA, Indonesia, May 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>News analysis of possible motivations behind decision by Indonesian government to place former Pres Suharto under house arrest while they investigate past abuses by his government; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Investigators who are struggling to break through the mental fog of former President Suharto as they question him are searching for something that is perhaps more valuable than the billions of dollars he is said to have stolen from his country.</p>
        <p>They are fighting to reclaim a piece of their nation's history.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Investigators who are struggling to break through the mental fog of former President Suharto as they question him are searching for something that is perhaps more valuable than the billions of dollars he is said to have stolen from his country.</p>
        <p>They are fighting to reclaim a piece of their nation's history.</p>
        <p>The fitful interrogations of the ailing 78-year-old former president, who was placed under house arrest on Monday, are one part of a broad campaign by President Abdurrahman Wahid to dig into a past that is filled with hidden abuses.</p>
        <p>As with the national treasury, which Mr. Suharto used as his personal bank account, he ravaged his country and then concealed the evidence. The abuses have ranged from shady business deals to dirty political tricks to military massacres.</p>
        <p>Now Mr. Wahid is pushing to dig up the bones of the past in a series of investigations and trials. In response, he is receiving mostly abuse, either from people who shout that he is moving too slowly or from others who fear instability or personal exposure.</p>
        <p>''The main motivation is a hunger to explore this period of Suharto's government,'' said Adam Schwarz, the author of ''A Nation in Waiting'' (Allen &amp; Unwin, 1999), the basic history of Indonesia's recent past. ''I don't think it's really about the money, and it's only partly about issues of justice. What is really driving this is a strong desire for an accounting of what happened in the past, whether in the case of human rights violations, judicial misconduct or corruption.</p>
        <p>''The positive thing is that Indonesians will to some extent be able to put the past behind them. The negative is that a lot of bad things will be dragged back up to the surface and confronted.''</p>
        <p>Some of Indonesia's most powerful people are resisting this process. Most of those who prospered during the 32 years of Mr. Suharto's rule were complicit to some degree in the abuses or corruption that were the order of the day.</p>
        <p>''If they are really serious,'' said one victim of a violent raid on an opposition party office in 1997, ''then the police headquarters would be empty, because everyone was involved.''</p>
        <p>As they push to uncover the truth about past abuses, the investigations  also have become a battleground of contemporary politics, enabling Mr. Wahid to keep some of his opponents from the Suharto years on the defensive.</p>
        <p>Some powerful people apparently are fighting back, instigating violent incidents in an attempt to derail Mr. Wahid's government and the threat it poses to them. Defense Minister Juwono Sudarsono, who was also a cabinet member in the previous government, said he knew of several former civilian and military officials who are paying to foment unrest.</p>
        <p>Some analysts have noted that on several occasions when a new investigation is opened or new charges are brought, a riot erupts or bombs go off somewhere in this volatile nation.</p>
        <p>The investigation of Mr. Suharto did not begin in earnest until Mr. Wahid took office in October. During the previous 17 months, after Mr. Suharto's forced resignation in May 1998, the interim government of  President B. J. Habibie -- stocked with Suharto loyalists -- protected him.</p>
        <p>The interrogations are moving slowly now because Mr. Suharto's mind has been affected by three strokes. The disability is apparently being maximized by his team of lawyers, and perhaps by Mr. Suharto himself, to hamper the questioning.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wahid and his attorney general, Marzuki Darusman, are also meeting resistance as they probe a number of other difficult areas of the past.</p>
        <p>The most startlingly successful initiative so far, perhaps because it was politically insulated, was the trial and conviction on May 18 of 24 soldiers and a civilian for the massacre of an Islamic teacher and more than 50 students last year in the province of Aceh. The defendants received jail terms of up to 10 years each, although human rights campaigners now ask why none of their superiors have been charged in the killings.</p>
        <p>It will be much more politically difficult to complete an investigation into a campaign of violence last year in East Timor after that former Indonesian province voted for independence. General Wiranto, the former military chief, resigned his cabinet post this month as he continued to undergo questioning as one of 21 high-ranking officers and civilians implicated by a government commission.</p>
        <p>Opening another highly sensitive investigation this month, the National Commission on Human Rights began summoning former generals for questioning about the killings of at least 50 Muslim protesters in the Tanjung Priok district of Jakarta in 1984. Among those questioned were the former military chief, Benny Murdani, and a former vice president, Try Sutrisno.</p>
        <p>So far there has been no full-scale investigation into the riots in May 1998 that helped bring down Mr. Suharto. It was clear from many accounts by witnesses that much of that violence was instigated and that a campaign of rapes of ethnic Chinese women was orchestrated and involved members of the military.</p>
        <p>And although Mr. Wahid has raised the issue, there has been no formal investigation yet into the massacres that began it all: the killing of 500,000 people and the jailing without trial of hundreds of thousands more in an anti-Communist purge that began in 1965.</p>
        <p>The origins and responsibility for those atrocities have never been fully explored, but their ultimate outcome was clear: Mr. Suharto became president of Indonesia.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
