<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A New Orleans Spot Worthy of a Great Tradition</title>
    <meta content="31UNDE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203624"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="$25 AND UNDER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Asimov, Eric</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bayou (NYC Restaurant)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Columns/$25 and Under</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000531T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07EEDB173CF932A05756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="832" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A New Orleans Spot Worthy of a Great Tradition</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Eric Asimov</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Asimov, Eric</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Eric Asimov reviews Bayou, Creole restaurant in Harlem (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ON a visit to New Orleans last year, a friend who has lived there most of his life took me to a highly touted new restaurant that left us both disappointed. Among the pallid, tasteless culprits was a punchless turtle soup that struck him as an embarrassment to the region's vaunted culinary order.</p>
        <p>''I can't allow you to go home with that taste in your mouth,'' he said, his New Orleans pride pierced, and dragged me off to Commander's Palace, where the turtle soup was so good it inspired us to sit through an entire second dinner.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ON a visit to New Orleans last year, a friend who has lived there most of his life took me to a highly touted new restaurant that left us both disappointed. Among the pallid, tasteless culprits was a punchless turtle soup that struck him as an embarrassment to the region's vaunted culinary order.</p>
        <p>''I can't allow you to go home with that taste in your mouth,'' he said, his New Orleans pride pierced, and dragged me off to Commander's Palace, where the turtle soup was so good it inspired us to sit through an entire second dinner.</p>
        <p>By the turtle soup test alone, Bayou, a handsome new Creole restaurant in Harlem, would do any New Orleans native proud. The rich soup ($5.95) is thick with bits of turtle meat and smoky andouille sausage, spiked with sherry and lemon.</p>
        <p>New York hasn't heard much from New Orleans since the vogue for blackened redfish waned in the 1980's. In truth, most of those restaurants were as woebegone as that sad turtle soup. But Bayou is the real thing. Its chef, Steve Manning, cooked for 10 years at Clancy's, an exceptional insider's restaurant in New Orleans. He brings the easy confidence of a man who knows the creole genre inside and out, not straying far from classics, yet never descending into blackened cliches.</p>
        <p>Mr. Manning moved to New York when his girlfriend took a job here, and he cooked briefly at several restaurants before teaming up with Michael Eberstadt, who was planning to open Bayou upstairs from Slice of Harlem, his pizzeria on Lenox Avenue. With its brick walls, retro brass lamps and woody touches, Bayou looks like countless other neighborhood bars and grills, but its big picture windows and second-floor setting offer an unusual New York panorama, unimpeded by tall buildings that might elsewhere blot out a view of a lightning storm or the sun setting over the Hudson.</p>
        <p>The menu is short, but includes standout appetizers like earthy chicken livers ($7.95) in a rich port wine sauce, and shrimp remoulade ($8.95), piquant with mustard and hot pepper and served with deviled eggs. Though I made a face at the idea of fried oysters and spinach topped with melted Brie ($8.95), the combination was exceptional. The oysters, dusted in cornmeal, were crisp and light, and the sharp cheese worked in precise counterpoint to the breading. I loved a special of creamy, lightly spicy crayfish bisque ($5.95). Shrimp and okra gumbo ($5.95) was peppery, but no match for the bisque or the turtle soup.</p>
        <p>In many ways New Orleans is a city closer to the 19th century than to the 21st, and I'd wager a dish like snapper Alexandria ($17.95) would have been quite at home on a menu 100 years ago. The sauteed fish, sprinkled with roasted pecans and drenched with lemon butter, was moist and altogether delicious. Robust crawfish etouffee ($13.95) was thick and mildly peppery, though to my taste the sauce could have used a little more kick. Same with shrimp creole ($14.95), which had plenty of shrimp but not quite enough pepper. Deep-fried catfish ($14.95) was light and perfectly crisp, served with fine salty fries and hush puppies, but grilled filet mignon, the most expensive dish, at $21.95, was also the least interesting.</p>
        <p>Bayou may have a veteran chef, but its young floor staff, short on crispness but long on charm, need a little seasoning. The 20-bottle wine list is terse but sensitively chosen, with bottles that go well with the food, like an Alsatian riesling from Dopff &amp; Irion ($24) and, especially, a California gewurztraminer from Handley ($27). Although at $45 it is expensive, an excellent zinfandel from Brown Estate, which may be California's only African-American-owned winery, is also on the list.</p>
        <p>Bayou has two desserts that pass the sweet equivalent of the turtle soup test. Both a bread pudding with a vanilla-whiskey sauce ($5) and a fudgy, wedge-shaped pecan brownie topped with peppermint ice cream and chocolate sauce ($5) were passed around the table of five. Nobody got seconds. I think my New Orleans friend would approve.</p>
        <p>Bayou  308 Lenox Avenue, near 125th Street, Harlem, (212) 426-3800.</p>
        <p>BEST DISHES: Turtle soup, sauteed chicken livers, shrimp remoulade, fried oysters with spinach and melted Brie, crawfish bisque, snapper Alexandria, crawfish etouffee, shrimp creole, fried catfish, bread pudding, pecan brownie.</p>
        <p>PRICE RANGE: Appetizers, $4.50 to $8.95; main courses, $12.95 to $21.95.</p>
        <p>CREDIT CARDS: American Express, Mastercard, Visa.</p>
        <p>HOURS: Monday-Thursday, 11 a.m. to 4 p.m., 6 to 10 p.m; Friday and Saturday to 11 p.m. Sunday, noon to 4 p.m.</p>
        <p>WHEELCHAIR ACCESS: Restaurant is up one flight of stairs.</p>
        <p>$25 AND UNDER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
