<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; Dudley Is Metaphor for Spirit of Knicks</title>
    <meta content="31BERK$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203759"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Indiana Pacers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berkow, Ira</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dudley, Chris</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Ira Berkow</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New York Knicks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Indiana Pacers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000531T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807E2D6143CF932A05756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="925" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; Dudley Is Metaphor for Spirit of Knicks</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By IRA BERKOW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Berkow, Ira</byline>
      <dateline>PURCHASE, N.Y.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ira Berkow Sports of The Times column discusses play of New York Knickerbockers reserve center Chris Dudley in playoff series against Indiana Pacers; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE native New Yorker Mark Jackson, in a lemon-colored suit, was chatting with a knot of people after the game on Monday. They were standing alongside the Madison Square Garden court about a half-hour after the Knicks had beaten Jackson's Indiana Pacers, 91-89, in Game 4 of the Eastern Conference finals. Jackson was approached by a reporter.</p>
        <p>''Mark,'' the reporter said, ''what did you think of Chris Dudley?''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE native New Yorker Mark Jackson, in a lemon-colored suit, was chatting with a knot of people after the game on Monday. They were standing alongside the Madison Square Garden court about a half-hour after the Knicks had beaten Jackson's Indiana Pacers, 91-89, in Game 4 of the Eastern Conference finals. Jackson was approached by a reporter.</p>
        <p>''Mark,'' the reporter said, ''what did you think of Chris Dudley?''</p>
        <p>Jackson looked at him with something close to crossed eyes.</p>
        <p>''You come here when I'm talking to my family and ask me about Chris Dudley?'' he said. Then he smiled a wan smile. ''He does what he's asked to do. He did a great job.''</p>
        <p>Indeed. A few minutes earlier, in another part of the Garden, the coach of the Pacers, one Larry Joe Bird, had a like thought. ''One of our main problems was not getting too many second-chance points,'' he said, ''especially when Dudley was in the game.''</p>
        <p>Dudley's own coach, Jeff Van Gundy, pointed to a moment in the third period when the Knicks, who had enjoyed a big lead, saw it shrink. ''Then we missed two straight shots but Chris got the offensive rebounds both times, passed out to Larry Johnson one time and Charlie Ward the other and turned them both into 3-pointers,'' Van Gundy said yesterday at the Knicks' practice here. ''They were huge plays for us.''</p>
        <p>It's unusual for someone to have such an impact when he played only eight minutes of the entire game, taking one shot and sinking none, and when he is given no opportunity to shoot a free throw, which, in general, is a blessing in disguise, for he is the single worst free-throw shooter in National Basketball Association history, at 46 percent.</p>
        <p>Dudley is also less than the most graceful basketball player. He is often in foul trouble. He is 6 feet 11 inches, with a square jaw as well as a square face, and, perhaps because of back problems and knee problems, his gait is uncommon. If you saw him at a curb, you might ask if he needed help to cross the street. If he were a trapeze artist, one could imagine him pulling down the the swinging bar and collapsing the rigging.</p>
        <p>Chris Childs, the Knick guard, calls him Dr. Crash. ''Because he crashes the boards for rebounds,'' Childs explained. ''He's not one to shy away from contact. He'll knock over a teammate as soon as he would a guy from the other team. He goes all out.''</p>
        <p>Dudley has been the starting center for the Knicks since Patrick Ewing went down with a foot injury in Game 2 against Indiana, and may be at that post tonight in Indianapolis for Game 5, if Ewing is still ailing. Before this, Dudley had played in just one game in the last month and a half of the regular season, and just 20 seconds of one game in the Toronto playoffs and seven-tenths of a seconds in his one game in the Miami series.</p>
        <p>But he is effective in blocking shots, running the floor, defending, rebounding and hustling for loose balls. In an odd way, he is a living metaphor for the spirit of the whole team. ''Even though he hadn't been playing,'' Van Gundy said, ''Chris stayed in shape, worked hard in practice -- and after practice -- and did the job when he was called on.'' Van Gundy also said that most people don't realize how ''banged up'' Dudley is. Like the rest of the Knicks, it seems.</p>
        <p>''After the Miami series, Chris came to me and said he wanted to play and believed he could help the team,'' Van Gundy said. ''I told him I couldn't make promises. He could have shut down and just collected his money. He didn't. He's the ultimate professional.''</p>
        <p>This is Dudley's 13th season in the league. He is 35 years old and is in the second year of a four-year, $28 million contract. He is also that rare N.B.A. specimen, an Ivy Leaguer -- an economics major and third-generation Yalie.</p>
        <p>''I've wondered if some of my shooting problems are because I overanalyze things too much,'' he said. But he's also, now, ''a little rusty.''</p>
        <p>He said: ''I had a wide-open shot in Game 3 but passed the ball because I was disoriented. I thought I was farther under the basket than I was.''</p>
        <p>As for his notorious free-throw shooting, he's been diligent recently at practicing.</p>
        <p>''He's much improved,'' said the Knicks assistant coach Brendan Malone, ''but it's hard for fans to tell because he doesn't go to the line that much.'' In Game 3, when he hit two straight free throws, the cheers shook rafters.</p>
        <p>Dudley is unassuming, a generous spirit -- he has a foundation for helping disadvantaged youngsters to a college education -- and a family man. He and his wife, Christine, have an 18-month-old boy, Charles, who, at games may be the only person in the Garden wearing a Knicks shirt with ''Dudley 14'' on the back. It appears he wears it with pride, like his dad.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
