<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Opener, The Stars Can't Find The Form</title>
    <meta content="31STAR$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203767"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="STANLEY CUP FINALS: DEVILS VS. STARS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Jersey Devils</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Dallas Stars</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Diamos, Jason</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Dallas Stars</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New Jersey Devils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000531T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404EFD6143CF932A05756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="728" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Opener, The Stars Can't Find The Form</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JASON DIAMOS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Diamos, Jason</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., May 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses New Jersey Devils victory over Dallas Stars in first game of NHL Stanley Cup championship series; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On Monday, Coach Ken Hitchcock proclaimed his Stars the favorites to defeat the Devils in the Stanley Cup finals and to repeat as the National Hockey League champions.</p>
        <p>After tonight, the Stars cannot be considered the favorites anymore.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On Monday, Coach Ken Hitchcock proclaimed his Stars the favorites to defeat the Devils in the Stanley Cup finals and to repeat as the National Hockey League champions.</p>
        <p>After tonight, the Stars cannot be considered the favorites anymore.</p>
        <p>Not after the bigger, stronger and, most important, faster Devils blew past the Stars in a 7-3 rout in Game 1 at Continental Arena.</p>
        <p>And not after the Stars' captain and meanest player, Derian Hatcher, left the game late in the third period apparently with an injury to his right leg after a knee-on-knee collision with the Devils' Alexander Mogilny. Hatcher was said to have a slight hyperextension of the knee and the Stars said he was expected to play Thursday in Game 2.</p>
        <p>As for the rest of the Stars, they need to regroup.</p>
        <p>''I don't think we have played against a group of forwards this quick before,'' Hitchcock said.</p>
        <p>Joe Nieuwendyk, who won the Conn Smythe trophy as the most valuable player of last season's playoffs, said: . ''We just weren't ready. We got it handed to us. It was a rude awakening.''</p>
        <p>Yes, the Stars lost Game 1 of the finals last season and went on to win the cup. And yes, the Stars lost Game 1 of this year's Western Conference finals against the Colorado Avalanche -- at home, no less -- and rebounded to take the series in seven games. And yes, the Devils routed the Philadelphia Flyers, 4-1, in Game 1 of the Eastern Conference finals -- on the road, no less -- and then dropped the next three games.</p>
        <p>But no once can question how dominant the underdog Devils were tonight.</p>
        <p>Goalie Ed Belfour, who had allowed two goals or fewer in 12 of his previous 13 playoff games, allowed six goals on 18 shots before being pulled 3 minutes 2 seconds into the final period. Afterward, Belfour complained that he had been bothered by the decongestants he was taking for a cold.</p>
        <p>When did he realize the decongestant was going to be a problem?</p>
        <p>''After six goals,'' Belfour said.</p>
        <p>The Devils' top line of Jason Arnott, Patrik Elias and Petr Sykora skated circles around the Stars. Arnott and Sykora each scored twice. All three controlled play every time they were on the ice.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the Stars' Sergei Zubov was on the ice for each of the Devils' first five goals. He finished with a plus-minus rating of minus-4. Brett Hull and Mike Modano were each minus-3.</p>
        <p>Trailing by 2-1 at 7:09 of the second period, the Stars had a goal disallowed, apparently because it came after a whistle. And then Martin Brodeur turned the game around with a magnificent double save -- first with his pad against Modano, then with his glove while falling backward on Hull's rebound shot from the top of the crease. That was at 9:59.</p>
        <p>At 10:28, Elias set up Sykora with a magnificent backhand drop pass from behind the left post that went between Zubov's legs. It was 3-1 Devils, and the result was never in doubt.</p>
        <p>Instead of sitting on the lead, as is their custom, the Devils continued to pour it on. Scott Stevens -- a strong Conn Smythe candidate if the Devils win the cup -- blasted a slap shot off Belfour and into the net at 16:04 to make it 4-1.</p>
        <p>This morning, Hitchcock said his team would match the Devils hit for hit.</p>
        <p>''Look, they've got a guy that takes people out,'' Hitchcock said, referring to Stevens. ''And we are not allowing that. He takes one of ours, we've got to take two of his.''</p>
        <p>And yet, the game's biggest hit belonged to another Devils defenseman, the rookie Colin White, who flattened Hatcher at the blue line late in the second period to bring on perhaps the sellout crowd's biggest roar.</p>
        <p>''All their goals came from turnovers from us,'' Dallas forward Mike Keane said. ''That's something we have to tighten up.''</p>
        <p>Kirk Muller said: ''They set the measuring stick. They outplayed us and outscored us in all areas.''</p>
        <p>And that is why the Stars cannot be considered the favorites anymore.</p>
        <p>STANLEY CUP FINALS: DEVILS VS. STARS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
