<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Beaujolais Presents Its Nobler Profile</title>
    <meta content="31WINE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203621"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="WINE TALK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">France</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Prial, Frank J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Columns/Wine Talk</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000531T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E1DB173CF932A05756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1000" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Beaujolais Presents Its Nobler Profile</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Frank J. Prial</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Prial, Frank J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Frank J Prial column on Beaujolais wines from small producers that are richer, darker, more intense and drier than what most Americans have come to expect from a Beaujolais; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SOMETIMES it's called real Beaujolais; sometimes Beaujolais for adults. What it means is not Duboeuf.</p>
        <p>So powerful a force are Duboeuf wines in the Beaujolais market, and so distinctive is their style, that most wine drinkers assume that all Beaujolais tastes like Georges Duboeuf's Beaujolais-Villages. And this assumption is not far from wrong.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SOMETIMES it's called real Beaujolais; sometimes Beaujolais for adults. What it means is not Duboeuf.</p>
        <p>So powerful a force are Duboeuf wines in the Beaujolais market, and so distinctive is their style, that most wine drinkers assume that all Beaujolais tastes like Georges Duboeuf's Beaujolais-Villages. And this assumption is not far from wrong.</p>
        <p>Most Beaujolais is produced by shippers, or negociants, who buy from growers and cooperatives, and turn out a refreshing, fruity wine, which can be served chilled or not, one that goes with just about everything but the most elegant meals.</p>
        <p>Some 35 million gallons of Beaujolais are produced each year. Half of that is simple Beaujolais; 25 percent, Beaujolais-Villages; and 25 percent, crus. About 55 percent is exported, some 12 percent to the United States.</p>
        <p>The critic Stephen Tanzer, commenting on the Beaujolais market some years ago in International Wine Cellar, his newsletter, said that the wines had taken on ''an overly perfumed, candied-fruit character,'' thanks to ''widespread use of a commercial yeast strain originally popularized by Duboeuf but now in vogue throughout the region, as well as high yields and heavy chaptilization.'' Chaptilization is the addition of sugar to the fermentation, not for sweetness but to raise the alcohol content of wines from what might be 10 percent or less to 12 percent or more.</p>
        <p>The immense popularity of Beaujolais, fueled by the nouveau Beaujolais craze, made it inevitable that serious wine drinkers would begin to look for something different. And it isn't difficult to find. Quantities are small, but the wines are out there.</p>
        <p>Dozens, perhaps many dozens, of small producers are intent on pushing the gamay grape, from which all Beaujolais must be made, as far as it will go. The result is a fascinating selection of Beaujolais wines that are richer, darker, more intense and drier than what most of us have come to expect from the Beaujolais region of southern Burgundy.</p>
        <p>Many of these small producers continue to supply the big negociants. But then they hold back a portion of what they make to produce a more complex wine.</p>
        <p>I discovered some of these wines, particularly those of Guy Breton and Jacky Janodet, in the early 1990's in Paris restaurants like the St.-Amarante, near the Bastille, and A la Courtille in the 20th Arrondissement, where small-batch Beaujolais were a feature. I say ''were'' because A la Courtille closed, and the St.-Amarante was sold to a couple less committed to these wines.</p>
        <p>Fortunately, many Paris bistros now offer this kind of Beaujolais. And it can be found in the United States if you know where to look. In New York, Al Hotchkin, at the Burgundy Wine Company, 373 West 11th Street in Greenwich Village, specializes in expensive Burgundies, but has a soft spot for good Beaujolais.</p>
        <p>He offers small quantities of Beaujolais from Patrick and Elizabeth Giloux, Brouilly from Alain Michaud, Morgon from the Domaine Savoye and Moulin-a-Vent from the Domaine du Granit. How small? The Gilouxes sell off their wines from younger vines. They hold back the wine from their 45-year-old vines, which rarely comes, even in good years, to more than 600 cases, and not all of those travel to our shores. Alain Michaud is lucky to make a few hundred cases of his Cuvee Prestige Brouilly from 90-year-old vines. Mr. Hotchkin advises laying down the 1998 vintage for five years. These are not mass-market wines.</p>
        <p>Burgundy Wine Company even has wines from Georges Duboeuf. Though Mr. Duboeuf buys from 400 growers, he also makes some special Beaujolais as well, often for top restaurants in his region like Georges Blanc, Paul Bocuse and Leon de Lyons and, most likely, for himself.</p>
        <p>Anyone who believes that Beaujolais doesn't age should try a couple of Duboeuf Moulin-a-Vents, the 1993 G.D.F. Cuvee or the aged-in-oak 1995 in magnum. I have had Beaujolais from the 50's with Mr. Duboeuf.</p>
        <p>More than half of all Beaujolais goes into simple Beaujolais and Beaujolais-Villages. But the region has areas where the wine is good enough and distinct enough to carry its own geographic name. These are the ''cru'' Beaujolais: Brouilly, Cotes de Brouilly, Chenas, Chiroubles, Fleurie, Julienas, Regnie, St.-Amour, Morgon and Moulin-a-Vent.</p>
        <p>Most of the big Beaujolais shippers are in the Beaujolais region, but most of the prominent Burgundy shippers like Louis Latour, Louis Jadot and Joseph Drouhin also sell Beaujolais. In 1966, Jadot bought a 66-acre estate in Moulin-a-Vent called Chateau de Jacques and is now offering five Moulin-a-Vents from separate vineyard parcels within the estate. These are traditional Beaujolais, full and rich, aged in oak and capable of improving even more with bottle age.</p>
        <p>Because these wines are imported in small quantities, it is not always easy to learn which are available in this country. But a few great traditional Beaujolais should be snapped up if you find them anywhere:  Fleurie, from Yves Metras; Morgon, from Jean Foillard; and Moulin-a-Vent, from Paul Janin.</p>
        <p>What makes these special Beaujolais attractive is the same thing that has always made Beaujolais attractive: the price. Given the insane prices of so many wines right now, Beaujolais and the delicious wines pouring in from southern Italy and Sicily keep many wine drinkers from switching to iced tea. Even now, fresh, fruity Beaujolais is widely available at less than $10, and most of these old-style small-batch cru Beaujolais still sell for $15 to $20 a bottle. The relationship between price and quality is hard to match in wine from any other region.</p>
        <p>WINE TALK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
