<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sprewell Enjoys Rapport With Fans</title>
    <meta content="31HOOP$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203744"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Popper, Steve</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sprewell, Latrell</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000531T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E7D6143CF932A05756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="828" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sprewell Enjoys Rapport With Fans</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVE POPPER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Popper, Steve</byline>
      <dateline>PURCHASE, N.Y., May 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses New York Knickerbockers forward Latrell Sprewell's popularity with fans (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Latrell Sprewell's name was announced in the starting lineup for the injury-riddled Knicks on Monday evening at Madison Square Garden, the noise level rose a little bit, prodding the fans out of their seats. The  fans' appreciation of Sprewell started long before that moment, as New York claimed the lost soul of the National Basketball Association as one of its own, but the 19,763 fans still seemed intent on creating their own moment.</p>
        <p>It may not have been Willis Reed hobbling onto the floor 30 years earlier, as Sprewell showed no sign of the incomplete fracture of his left foot as he hopped up from the bench, but the fans roared their thanks for his decision to play through the pain.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Latrell Sprewell's name was announced in the starting lineup for the injury-riddled Knicks on Monday evening at Madison Square Garden, the noise level rose a little bit, prodding the fans out of their seats. The  fans' appreciation of Sprewell started long before that moment, as New York claimed the lost soul of the National Basketball Association as one of its own, but the 19,763 fans still seemed intent on creating their own moment.</p>
        <p>It may not have been Willis Reed hobbling onto the floor 30 years earlier, as Sprewell showed no sign of the incomplete fracture of his left foot as he hopped up from the bench, but the fans roared their thanks for his decision to play through the pain.</p>
        <p>''I think we just have our own little thing going, me and these fans,'' Sprewell said after today's practice at SUNY-Purchase. ''We just get along well. I don't know if it's the foot, or they just love me or I love them or whatever it is. I'm glad it's there.''</p>
        <p>Sprewell still could not understand what all the fuss was about anyway. His foot hurt, but he was able to live with the pain, so he played. He stayed on the court for 44 minutes, tied for the most on the Knicks, giving them 12 points. It was hardly the sort of output he had the previous game, when he scored 32. But the point was that he was there, and with his help the Knicks had evened the series at 2-2 and had helped buy another day for the Knicks' other wounds to heal, particularly the aching right foot of Patrick Ewing, which kept him out of the lineup for the second straight game.</p>
        <p>Ewing has played for the Knicks for 15 seasons but has gained a less passionate response from the hometown fans than Sprewell has in just two.</p>
        <p>''The Garden fans are a big reason why I'm trying to make it happen for them,'' Sprewell said. ''Not just me, but I think they deserve it. New York fans are loyal fans. They're due for an N.B.A. championship.</p>
        <p>''This makes almost everything I went through worth it. To get here, and to be in a situation I'm in, I can't ask for more than anything than that. This is what it's all about, playing, being in the Eastern Conference finals, having a chance to play in the N.B.A. finals. All these things, when I was at Golden State, these were just dreams. I didn't have that type of team where I could realistically say I was going to get there.''</p>
        <p>It all explains why he shrugged off the word of team doctors, who warned him that by playing with the injury, he was taking a chance on breaking the fifth metatarsal, the bone near his little toe, and could then require surgery and miss the rest of the playoffs.</p>
        <p>''They were just saying that it's cracked, so if somebody steps on it, or something happens and it gets worse, it could be six weeks,'' Sprewell said. ''But the bottom line is, you can play with a broken toe. It's just a matter of how much pain you can take. I told them right afterward that I was going to play, that it didn't feel that bad. So if it is broken, I still expect to play.</p>
        <p>''I feel good. It feels a lot better. It's not as sore as it was last night. I could push off it, not real good last night, but better than I thought. I think, more than anything, it's a mental thing with me. The pain of it isn't really that bad. Just knowing it's there though is the thing that I have to get over.''</p>
        <p>Sprewell did not show many effects of the pain during Game 4, and he brought the fans to their feet again midway through the first quarter when he blew past Jalen Rose at the top of the key and split through the defense. As he darted into the clear, the crowd seemed to hold its breath for a moment, wondering just what he would do. Ignoring the pain, Sprewell pushed off, ascending to the basket and slamming the ball through with his usual ferocity.</p>
        <p>''With a fractured foot I was surprised he could take off from the dotted line and tomahawk dunk,'' Allan Houston said.</p>
        <p>''You do have to respect the fact that, no matter what, it's broken and he's out there playing.''</p>
        <p>Sprewell added: ''If anything, I wanted to be out there to give them something. I was more effective than I thought I would be, to be honest, so I expect the same the next game.''</p>
        <p>BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
