<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tough Call for Small Town On Improving Its Schools</title>
    <meta content="31LESS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Education Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203682"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="LESSONS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Government Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Dobbs Ferry (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Herring, Hubert B</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Government Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000531T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E2DC143CF932A05756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="940" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tough Call for Small Town On Improving Its Schools</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Hubert B. Herring</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Herring, Hubert B</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lessons column discusses Dobbs Ferry, NY, residents voting down bond issue that would have expanded and upgraded schools; arguments for and against issue discussed; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EDUCATION is the ultimate apple-pie issue: to vote against it is to be branded anti-child and un-American. Ask any group of suburbanites to say yea or nay to the proposition ''Should we do the best for our children?'' and the vote will surely be unanimous.</p>
        <p>But it is, alas, never that simple, as I discovered recently when the town where I live -- Dobbs Ferry, just up the Hudson from Manhattan -- voted on a bond issue to expand and upgrade the schools.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EDUCATION is the ultimate apple-pie issue: to vote against it is to be branded anti-child and un-American. Ask any group of suburbanites to say yea or nay to the proposition ''Should we do the best for our children?'' and the vote will surely be unanimous.</p>
        <p>But it is, alas, never that simple, as I discovered recently when the town where I live -- Dobbs Ferry, just up the Hudson from Manhattan -- voted on a bond issue to expand and upgrade the schools.</p>
        <p>My neighbors' opinions, often adamant, were all over the map. Many people rallied around the bond, but many others found fault. It cost too much. The construction estimates were inflated. The planning process was flawed. We hired the wrong architect. The students' needs were not being met. In the end, the doubters prevailed, and the bond failed.</p>
        <p>So, does that mean Dobbs Ferry is anti-education? Not at all. There were legitimate concerns about the process, especially since another bond had passed two years earlier but construction had never started. Now the district was asking for more, and many were puzzled.</p>
        <p>The stated reasons for hitting us twice included rising construction costs and necessary changes, but to a casual observer there was no real way to know if that was the truth or if the project, which included a much-needed gym and new classrooms for a growing student population, had been bungled.</p>
        <p>And that is precisely the problem: most voters on a small-town school bond will, of necessity, be casual observers. Those of us who are neither architects nor construction managers -- and lack the time for a crash course in such matters -- have little choice but to put our faith in the school board we elected, and the superintendent that board has chosen.</p>
        <p>Yes, I could be better informed. But I have a job, plus two teenagers. That combination puts a dent in my day. And many people are in a similar position.</p>
        <p>Some local people, of course, took the time to study the issue closely, but their conclusions varied widely. At least one couple split, with the husband voting no, the wife yes. One architect said that it was a good plan, while another said that it was a disaster from the start -- that if we had hired the architect he had recommended, the school addition would be built by now. Whom do you believe?</p>
        <p>I chose to put my faith in the school board and backed the bond.</p>
        <p>Maybe I was wrong. Most people know little of school board candidates when they cast their votes. We read reams of details, intimate and otherwise, about national politicians, but no investigative reporters swoop in to delve into the qualifications of school board candidates. It usually comes down to ''He seems like a decent person'' or ''Her credentials look good.''</p>
        <p>Don't get me wrong -- we've got a good school board. But they are volunteers, often squeezing this work into busy lives -- there's only so much energy they can devote to school issues. Even in the best of circumstances, there will be a certain haphazard quality to the whole business -- not just in Dobbs Ferry, but in any small town.</p>
        <p>The superintendent and assistant superintendent are, of course, paid to focus on these issues, but that's a big burden for two people who must also deal with all sorts of other district issues. An added complication in Dobbs Ferry is that we just got a new superintendent over the winter. The construction bond was a lot to throw at someone new, though to the superintendent's credit, he seems to have hit the hallways running.</p>
        <p>And voters, no matter how objective they try to be -- no matter how much they say, ''I want to do what's best for the district'' -- will find their own interests sneaking in. I, for instance, cannot help wondering whether the new gym will be ready for my son, a junior -- and how the changes will affect my daughter, a seventh grader. Those with younger children no doubt scrutinize the plans for the elementary school more closely.</p>
        <p>Those without children face a different choice. They could easily vote down every proposal to spend extra money on the schools, trying to keep their taxes as low as possible, but those who take the long view realize that quality schools are part of what keeps property values high in many suburbs. They cannot jeopardize that.</p>
        <p>But the childless are unlikely to scrutinize the process as closely as parents do. In the recent vote, I'm sure many of them said, ''Now they want more money? After we just voted $22 million? Forget it!''</p>
        <p>In the end, a relative handful of people decided the issue. In a town of some 10,000, only about 1,400 people turned out, rejecting the bond by 100 or so votes.</p>
        <p>For me, this is what it adds up to: Even after focusing a fair amount, it is frustrating to have so little understanding of an issue that will surely have as much, if not more, impact on my family than the actions of the national politicians we hear about ad nauseam.</p>
        <p>LESSONS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
