<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Plan to Fill Sotheby's Board Seat Is Faulted</title>
    <meta content="Y31SOT$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000601T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203697"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Boards of Directors</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sotheby's</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Justice Department</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Christie's</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Frantz, Douglas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Baron, Ronald</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Taubman, Robert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Taubman, A Alfred</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boards of Directors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000531T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E6DA143CF932A05756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="488" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Plan to Fill Sotheby's Board Seat Is Faulted</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DOUGLAS FRANTZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Frantz, Douglas</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ronald Baron, largest outside shareholder in Sotheby's Holdings, says electing Robert Taubman, son of former chairman A Alfred Taubman, to board seat would represent conflict of interest in face of continuing criminal investigation into price-fixing at auction house; Sotheby's and its rival, Christie's, are subjects of Justice Department investigation into accusations that two auction houses fixed commissions charged to buyers and sellers for several years; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The largest outside shareholder in Sotheby's Holdings says that electing the son of the former chairman to a board seat would represent a conflict of interest in the face of the continuing criminal investigation into price-fixing at the auction house.</p>
        <p>Sotheby's and its rival, Christie's, are the subjects of a Justice Department investigation into accusations that the two auction houses fixed commissions charged to buyers and sellers for several years. Christie's disclosed Jan. 28 that it had agreed to cooperate in exchange for leniency, and people involved in the case said prosecutors were in the late stages of evaluating possible criminal charges involving Sotheby's.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The largest outside shareholder in Sotheby's Holdings says that electing the son of the former chairman to a board seat would represent a conflict of interest in the face of the continuing criminal investigation into price-fixing at the auction house.</p>
        <p>Sotheby's and its rival, Christie's, are the subjects of a Justice Department investigation into accusations that the two auction houses fixed commissions charged to buyers and sellers for several years. Christie's disclosed Jan. 28 that it had agreed to cooperate in exchange for leniency, and people involved in the case said prosecutors were in the late stages of evaluating possible criminal charges involving Sotheby's.</p>
        <p>A. Alfred Taubman, 75, the wealthy real estate developer who owns a controlling interest in Sotheby's, resigned as its chairman in February after Christie's disclosure. Mr. Taubman retains voting control of the company and its board through stock ownership.</p>
        <p>His son, Robert, 46, was scheduled to take Mr. Taubman's place on the board in April, but the company's annual meeting was postponed at the last minute after objections by Ronald Baron, whose investment funds are the largest outside investors in Sotheby's.</p>
        <p>''I believe Robert Taubman's appointment to be inappropriate at this time,'' Mr. Baron wrote to investors in his funds in a quarterly report obtained yesterday. ''We believe Robert Taubman will soon recognize the enormous conflicts of interest he will face.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Baron also said other board members were exceptionally close to Albert Taubman, and Mr. Barron said he had been assured several times in recent months that there was no substance to the federal price-fixing investigation.</p>
        <p>Mr. Baron questioned the independence of Sotheby's board in a filing with the Securities and Exchange Commission in April, and he has been negotiating with the company over the makeup of the board. Mr. Baron's funds have invested nearly $500 million in Sotheby's stock, which has lost about half its value in recent months. But Mr. Baron sought to reassure his investors that Sotheby's long-term prospects would be strong after the conclusion of the federal investigation.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for Sotheby's declined to comment on Mr. Baron's remarks and said that the annual meeting had not been rescheduled. A lawyer for Albert Taubman also declined to comment, and a spokeswoman for Robert Taubman, president of the Taubman Company, said he would have no comment.</p>
        <p>In addition to the criminal inquiry, Sotheby's and Christie's are subjects of class-action litigation in Federal District Court in New York. On Friday, Judge Lewis A. Kaplan, who is presiding over the case, chose the law firm of Boies, Schiller &amp; Flexner as lead counsel in the combined suits.</p>
        <p>The firm, known for its role in the Microsoft suit, was chosen from among 20 that submitted bids to win the right to lead the effort to win damages from the auction houses.</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 1, 2000, Thursday  An article in Business Day yesterday about a large shareholder's objections to the election of Robert Taubman to the board of Sotheby's Holdings, where his father is a former chairman, misstated the father's given name. He is A. Alfred Taubman, not Albert.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 1, 2000, Thursday</p>
        <p>An article in Business Day yesterday about a large shareholder's objections to the election of Robert Taubman to the board of Sotheby's Holdings, where his father is a former chairman, misstated the father's given name. He is A. Alfred Taubman, not Albert.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
