<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mendoza Loses His Grip So Yanks Lose a Game</title>
    <meta content="31YANK$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203752"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Oakland Athletics</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Curry, Jack</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Oakland Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000531T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE4D6143CF932A05756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="994" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mendoza Loses His Grip So Yanks Lose a Game</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Curry, Jack</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Oakland Athletics defeat New York Yankees, 7-4; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ramiro Mendoza likes to work fast when he is pitching and he seemed as if he wanted to work even faster on a brisk night. Mendoza lined up on the extreme left side of the rubber, blew warm air into his right hand, tossed pitches and then quickly returned to his original position to start again.</p>
        <p>But the ball felt slippery to Mendoza and he could not throw strikes and he could not get comfortable. Usually, Mendoza does not have trouble enticing the umpire to lift his right arm and does not have problems performing as relaxed as someone  whipping a tennis ball around the yard. Except for last night.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ramiro Mendoza likes to work fast when he is pitching and he seemed as if he wanted to work even faster on a brisk night. Mendoza lined up on the extreme left side of the rubber, blew warm air into his right hand, tossed pitches and then quickly returned to his original position to start again.</p>
        <p>But the ball felt slippery to Mendoza and he could not throw strikes and he could not get comfortable. Usually, Mendoza does not have trouble enticing the umpire to lift his right arm and does not have problems performing as relaxed as someone  whipping a tennis ball around the yard. Except for last night.</p>
        <p>The normally precise and normally poised Mendoza was neither as he walked a career-high six batters, did not last beyond the fifth inning and just plain sputtered as the Oakland Athletics tamed the Yankees, 7-4.</p>
        <p>Mendoza followed up a 7-0 shutout over the White Sox last Thursday, the first time he had started in 18 days, by searching for strikes while pitching on the normal four days' rest.</p>
        <p>''I go to the bullpen and the ball felt good,'' Mendoza said after the game. ''I go to the mound and the ball felt slick. I didn't have control today.''</p>
        <p>It was startling to see Mendoza deteriorate into such an undependable pitcher. Even more than Orlando Hernandez or Andy Pettitte, Mendoza consistently throws strikes. He does not fool around, he uses a nasty sinker to induce ground balls and he had walked only eight batters in 33 innings, an average of 2.4 per nine innings.</p>
        <p>But that changed last night at Yankee Stadium because Mendoza could not get solid grips with the temperature in the upper 50's and almost matched his season total for walks in one sloppy game.</p>
        <p>''He didn't seem comfortable out there,'' Manager Joe Torre said. ''He was inconsistent. Too many pitches were belt-high.''</p>
        <p>Mendoza's last two walks in the fifth helped lead to the runs that enabled Oakland to tie the score, and Chuck Knoblauch's throwing error helped set up the tie-breaking run. With runners on first and second, Knoblauch moved to his left to corral Ben Grieve's grounder between first and second.</p>
        <p>Knoblauch bobbled the ball as he tried to pivot to second, his throw was low and it bounced off Derek Jeter's glove.</p>
        <p>''I could have caught it,'' Jeter said. ''I should have caught it.''</p>
        <p>Knoblauch's team-leading eighth error loaded the bases for the A's and the struggling Mendoza could not maintain the 4-2 lead. An infield groundout scored the third run and Matt Stairs lashed a two-run single into center to drive in two more runs, to put the A's ahead, 5-4, and end Mendoza's sluggish start.</p>
        <p>Mendoza threw 87 pitches and 43 were balls.</p>
        <p>The Yankees did not help the situation by going 1 for 11 with runners in scoring position, and Ricky Ledee's single in the second did not even knock in a run. It loaded the bases with no outs, but Kevin Appier struck out Scott Brosius and he got Knoblauch to ground to shortstop and into a double play.</p>
        <p>Instead of burying Appier, the Yankees might have buried themselves by only scoring once in that inning.</p>
        <p>Mendoza walked Terrance Long to start the game and that symbolized his night as he walked batters in four of the five innings he pitched. Still, he survived for a while because he secured double plays to end the first and the second.</p>
        <p>Knoblauch made a strong throw on a double play in the first, but Randy Velarde spiked Knoblauch in the left leg. When Knoblauch returned to the dugout, he cringed while a trainer treated his leg. Apparently, Knoblauch was not in too much pain because he led off by lining Appier's 1-1 fastball over the left-field fence.</p>
        <p>Tino Martinez hit a liner in the second that soared by the 314-foot sign in right for his first homer in 65 at-bats, giving the Yanks a 2-0 lead.</p>
        <p>After the A's used a walk and two doubles to tie it, 2-2, Bernie Williams doubled in a run in the third and Jeter continued his torrid hitting by drilling a homer to center that put the Yankees ahead, 4-2.</p>
        <p>But the ball never felt right to Mendoza. He did not throw strikes and he did not hold the lead.</p>
        <p>''It just wasn't a good day,'' Torre said. ''It was a bad day all around.''</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>DEREK JETER is 10 for 17 with one homer, two doubles and three runs batted in since being activated last Saturday, boosting his average from .266 to .305. ''I'm taking a lot better swings now than I was before I got hurt,'' Jeter said. . . . ROGER CLEMENS was dejected after losing to PEDRO MARTINEZ and the Red Sox, 2-0, on Sunday night, but he has been buoyed by the praise that he has received. ''I told my wife that I had more compliments that night then after Game 4 of the World Series,'' Clemens said. ''Like everybody says, you do it here and it's amazing.'' Clemens was obviously touched when LARRY BIRD, another former Boston great, congratulated him at the Knicks-Pacers game on Monday. Clemens will meet with a ring company representative today because his World Series ring has No. 33 on it, not his No. 22. DAVID WELLS, who was traded for Clemens, wore No. 33.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
