<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="31DIGE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203704"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000531T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CEFDA143CF932A05756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1005" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>F.C.C. Proposes Relaxing Some Broadcasting Rules  The Federal Communications Commission proposed easing several decades-old regulations on broadcasters, including one that prevents companies from owning a broadcast station and newspaper in the same city and another prohibiting a company from owning more than one national television network.</p>
        <p>The proposals may significantly affect several pending and recently completed mergers. Existing rules would have required significant divestitures after Viacom's acquisition of CBS and the Tribune Company's proposed purchase of Times Mirror. [Page A1.]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>F.C.C. Proposes Relaxing Some Broadcasting Rules  The Federal Communications Commission proposed easing several decades-old regulations on broadcasters, including one that prevents companies from owning a broadcast station and newspaper in the same city and another prohibiting a company from owning more than one national television network.</p>
        <p>The proposals may significantly affect several pending and recently completed mergers. Existing rules would have required significant divestitures after Viacom's acquisition of CBS and the Tribune Company's proposed purchase of Times Mirror. [Page A1.]</p>
        <p>Breakup Fees Detailed in Airline Deal  According to a copy of the proposed merger agreement between United Airlines and US Airways filed with the Securities and Exchange Commission, US Airways would have to pay $160 million to United's parent, UAL, if it breached the contract, while UAL would be forced to pay $50 million to US Airways if it withdrew. In addition, either company can terminate the agreement if the merger is not completed by Dec. 31. Shares of US Airways rose 6.25 cents, to $43.625, while UAL fell 81.25 cents, to $51.9375. [C2.]</p>
        <p>N.T.T. of Japan Is Urged to Cut Fees  Senior members of Japan's ruling party are pressing Nippon Telegraph and Telephone, the dominant telecommunications company, to reduce the high connection fees charged to competitors, an issue that has caused deep trade friction with the United States. [C4.]</p>
        <p>Consumer Confidence Resurfaces  Consumer confidence surged in May, according to the Conference Board, to 144.4, close to the record it reached in January despite the roller coaster stock market and six increases in interest rates in the last year. [C2.]</p>
        <p>Supreme Court Tackles Clean Air Act  The Supreme Court expanded its continuing review of the Clean Air Act to consider the economic costs. The court's action raised the stakes even higher in a case, to be argued next fall, that already promised to be one of the most important environmental and administrative law cases in years. [A19.]</p>
        <p>Meet the Nicest Man on Wall St.  It was luck that got him out of Nazi Germany in the 1930's, John H. Slade says, and luck that got him his first job in New York as a runner for Bear, Stearns at $15 a week. Decades later, he says, it was a lucky encounter on a train that led to romance and marriage. Today, Mr. Slade, 92, the honorary chairman of the executive committee at Bear, Stearns, puts in a four-day week and calls himself ''the luckiest man in the world.'' The Boss. [C10.]</p>
        <p>Sotheby's Board Choice Is Criticized  Ronald Baron, whose investment funds are the largest outside investors in Sotheby's Holdings, says electing Robert Taubman, the son of the company's former chairman, to its board, would represent a conflict of interest in the face of the continuing criminal investigation into price fixing at the auction house. [C2.]</p>
        <p>Internet Access for Road Warriors  Larry Brilliant, chairman of SoftNet Systems, empathizes with business travelers in need of computer access. A unit of his company plans to start a system of wireless networks in airports, hotels and convention centers that will sell high-speed Internet services and e-mail access. Joe Sharkey: Business Travel. [C11.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
