<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Poet of Reality Pries Open the Lid</title>
    <meta content="31BERN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203619"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lynch, Thomas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bernstein, Richard</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Bodies in Motion and at Rest (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000531T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07EFDC173CF932A05756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="963" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Poet of Reality Pries Open the Lid</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD BERNSTEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bernstein, Richard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Richard Bernstein reviews Thomas Lynch's Bodies in Motion and at Rest; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BODIES IN MOTION  AND AT REST  By Thomas Lynch  Illustrated. 277 pages. W. W. Norton. $23.95.</p>
        <p>Funerals and poetry are very similar, says Thomas Lynch, possibly the only person on the planet who combines the two, vocationally speaking. ''Whenever funeral directors get together they talk about the fact that no one likes funerals,'' Mr. Lynch writes in ''Bodies in Motion and at Rest,'' his richly idiosyncratic new book of essays. ''Whenever poets get together they talk about the fact that no one likes poetry.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BODIES IN MOTION  AND AT REST  By Thomas Lynch  Illustrated. 277 pages. W. W. Norton. $23.95.</p>
        <p>Funerals and poetry are very similar, says Thomas Lynch, possibly the only person on the planet who combines the two, vocationally speaking. ''Whenever funeral directors get together they talk about the fact that no one likes funerals,'' Mr. Lynch writes in ''Bodies in Motion and at Rest,'' his richly idiosyncratic new book of essays. ''Whenever poets get together they talk about the fact that no one likes poetry.''</p>
        <p>It is fair to say that Mr. Lynch likes both funerals and poetry and that he is good at both. His first book of essays, ''The Undertaking: Life Studies From the Dismal Trade,'' introduced this unusual writer to a public mostly unaware of the lyrical reflection that can be involved in the necessary and wholesome task of burying your fellow citizens. Mr. Lynch extends some of the themes that he introduced in that book, adding, for example, that ''good poems and good funerals are stories well told.'' In so doing he demonstrates once again his quizzical, gently cantankerous, free-minded Yeatsean charm. As he comments on the big and the small things of life Mr. Lynch engages the reader with a mixture of poetic and funerary elements, of ephemera and durables both.</p>
        <p>In his new book Mr. Lynch fills in some painful personal detail that was missing from the first, like the battle with alcoholism he fought for many years, a wrenching divorce, and the mostly pleasurable tribulations he experienced in raising four children largely by himself. ''Bodies in Motion and at Rest'' is less thematically focused than ''The Undertaking'' and it is angrier in places, as if Mr. Lynch has now decided to relax his hold on avuncular bemusement and confide to us his private agony. His description of alcoholism and the alcoholism of one of his sons makes for some searing and powerfully affecting passages. But those of Mr. Lynch's readers who are hoping for some striking new departures, some entirely new themes, will not find them in this book. They will find the pungent compassion, the unabashed lyricism and the homespun repudiation of vanity and banality that bathed Mr. Lynch's earlier writings in their considerable glow.</p>
        <p>The essays here are on a considerable variety of subjects, many of them prompted by some item in the news, which leads Mr. Lynch to a recollection of bygone days or to some meditation on what he sees as the spiritual flatness of the end of the millennium. (The essays were all written before the year 2000). In one of the longer sections of a book of generally brief and pithy chapters, for example, Mr. Lynch uses his hatred of a particular house cat to bring him into a reminiscence of the collapse of his first marriage. There, he freely reveals the fury and hurt that he experienced -- he describes a poem he wrote about the experience as ''venom done up as carefully off-rhymed birthday greetings.'' But as with all these essays, there is a moral foundation, a probing for some lesson about the essential condition of things, in this case the uselessness of pretending that divorce does not harm children.</p>
        <p>''Most divorces are difficult choices in a world that applauds the exercise of choice, even the bad ones,'' Mr. Lynch writes. ''And to have good reasons for divorce -- as I did, as my former spouse would, no doubt, say she did, as we always do -- does not make divorcing good. It is the children who pay, for the two sets of parents and households, holidays and disciplines. However equal and amicable they might be, they are always separate, covertly at odds, subtly competing, quietly instructing in the separate and subversive dialects of love.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lynch discourses, often with a kind of sulfuric humor, on the possibility that human life spans might soon be doubled by science; on the similarities, as he sees it, of coffins and condoms; on writer's block; on abortion; and on the contemporary value placed on having choices, options, endless possibilities. But an underlying philosophy is not difficult to detect. Mr. Lynch is an eloquent but old-fashioned moralist. He has a capacious understanding of human foibles and great tolerance for them. But he knows that it is easy to be distracted from the verities -- by rampant materialism, by fake piety, by all the cant that can be produced in an age of electronic reproduction. That our humanity can be diluted as a consequence is Mr. Lynch's underlying message.</p>
        <p>''What the networks offer us,'' he declares at one point, ''is the therapy of spectacle, excess and sedation -- our humanity dulled by megadoses, like too much pornography dulls real sex, too much volume eventually deafens, and too much information dulls the truth.''</p>
        <p>Actually, I'm not sure about the phrase about information. It seems to me that we suffer not from too much information but from not enough. One can argue with Mr. Lynch as he rambles eloquently and judgmentally through his life and ours. But it is impossible not to take him seriously, since he is deeply thoughtful and his thoughts have been hammered out on the anvil of experience. It is also impossible not to like him, because his voice is rich and generous.</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
