<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Signs of Life on the Stalled Israeli-Palestinian Diplomatic Front</title>
    <meta content="Y31ISR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203656"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hunger Strikes</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Lebanon</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barak, Ehud (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Orme, William A Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arafat, Yasir</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Lebanon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Lebanon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hunger Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000531T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E0D6173CF932A05756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="547" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Signs of Life on the Stalled Israeli-Palestinian Diplomatic Front</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM A. ORME Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Orme, William A Jr</byline>
      <dateline>JERUSALEM, May 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Prime Min Ehud Barak of Israel and Palestinian leader Yasir Arafat move to revive their stalled peace talks, overshadowed by Israel's abrupt withdrawal from southern Lebanon; Barak will brief Pres Clinton on developments at meeting in Germany; Arafat's presses efforts to defuse violent Palestinian protests; efforts to end hunger strike by Palestinian prisoners in Israeli jails noted (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Prime Minister Ehud Barak and the Palestinian Authority leader, Yasir Arafat, are taking steps to revive their stalled peace talks, which had been overshadowed for the last week by Israel's abrupt withdrawal from Lebanon.</p>
        <p>On Thursday, Mr. Barak is to fly  to Germany to see President Clinton and discuss the ''implications'' of the withdrawal and ''ways to advance the Israeli-Palestinian negotiations in particular,'' the prime minister's office announced today.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Prime Minister Ehud Barak and the Palestinian Authority leader, Yasir Arafat, are taking steps to revive their stalled peace talks, which had been overshadowed for the last week by Israel's abrupt withdrawal from Lebanon.</p>
        <p>On Thursday, Mr. Barak is to fly  to Germany to see President Clinton and discuss the ''implications'' of the withdrawal and ''ways to advance the Israeli-Palestinian negotiations in particular,'' the prime minister's office announced today.</p>
        <p>Mr. Arafat, meanwhile, has restrained the often violent Palestinian protest demonstrations of recent weeks, which are what had prompted Israel to suspend the talks. His emissaries were working tonight to persuade hunger-striking Palestinian prisoners in Israeli jails to resume eating in exchange for concessions on visiting rights and other issues, Palestinian sources said. Officials on both sides fear that the death of a hunger striker could detonate a new  round of violence.</p>
        <p>Negotiations are expected to resume this weekend or sooner, though it is not yet clear where.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, right-wing opposition leaders and one disgruntled Barak cabinet minister said today that Mr. Barak is prepared to give the Palestinians up to 95 percent of the West Bank, including fertile Jordan valley lands extending to the edge of the Dead Sea. Israel would retain Jewish-settled West Bank lands near its present eastern border, plus a narrow sliver of the West Bank border zone with Jordan for security purposes, according to opponents of the reported proposal. Israel currently controls more than half of the West Bank, which it seized from Jordan in the 1967 Arab-Israeli war.</p>
        <p>Interior Minister Natan Sharansky sent Mr. Barak a letter demanding a security cabinet discussion of the reported new negotiating offer, a ministry spokesman said tonight. Mr. Sharansky, who has repeatedly threatened to quit the government over territorial concessions in peace talks, said in his letter that the reported new proposal would require  up to 50,000 Jewish settlers to be relocated into Israel and award the Palestinians sovereign control over border crossings into Jordan and Egypt. But Mr. Barak's spokesman,  Gadi Baltianski, said the position ascribed to the prime minister ''does not represent the government's posture or the agreement that we are working on.'' A spokesman for Mr. Sharansky replied that the interior minister ''is confident that his information is accurate.''</p>
        <p>Negotiations in Stockholm aimed at drafting an outline for a final peace settlement were suspended last week after violent protests in Gaza and the West Bank on behalf of the Palestinian prisoners. The elastic deadline for the so-called framework agreement was most recently extended to June 23, but negotiators on both sides have expressed skepticism that they could resolve all outstanding issues in the next three weeks.</p>
        <p>Mr. Arafat said the sudden Israeli withdrawal from Lebanon last week has made it harder for him to compromise on territorial claims and the delicate issues of Palestinian refugees and Jerusalem.</p>
        <p>''My public sees Hezbollah as heroes who succeeded in getting the Israeli Army out of Lebanon, and believes that that is the route we should take as well,'' he told Dalia Izik, Israel's environment minister, in a meeting on Monday.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
