<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE MARKETS: Market Place; Sara Lee Plans To Reorganize Some Apparel And Food Units</title>
    <meta content="Y31PLAC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203683"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sara Lee Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Coach (Leather Goods Co)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">PYA/Monarch</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Champion (Apparel Co)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Courtaulds Textiles</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barboza, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bryan, John H</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcmillan, C Steven</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Market Place (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Market Place</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000531T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E2DC143CF932A05756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1283" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE MARKETS: Market Place; Sara Lee Plans To Reorganize Some Apparel And Food Units</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID BARBOZA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barboza, David</byline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO, May 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sara Lee Corp to reorganize its operations and divest itself of four divisions; expects to take two divisions public: Coach, its leather goods business, and PYA/Monarch, one of nation's largest food service distributors; also intends to sell Champion, athletic apparel maker, as well as international fabrics unit of Courtaulds Textiles, British retailer that Sara Lee acquired in March; four units generate about $4 billion in revenue; longtime chief executive John H Bryan is set to step down this summer; C Steven McMillan, president and chief operating officer, will take over as chief executive on July 1; chart; photo (Market Place column) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sara Lee, the giant consumer goods company that sells everything from Ball Park hot dogs to Playtex bras and Hanes underwear, said today that it would reorganize its operations and divest itself of four divisions.</p>
        <p>The company, which has annual revenue of about $20 billion, said that later this year it expected to take two of those divisions public: Coach, its leather goods business, and PYA/Monarch, one of the nation's largest food service distributors.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sara Lee, the giant consumer goods company that sells everything from Ball Park hot dogs to Playtex bras and Hanes underwear, said today that it would reorganize its operations and divest itself of four divisions.</p>
        <p>The company, which has annual revenue of about $20 billion, said that later this year it expected to take two of those divisions public: Coach, its leather goods business, and PYA/Monarch, one of the nation's largest food service distributors.</p>
        <p>Sara Lee executives say the company also intends to sell Champion, the athletic apparel maker, as well as the international fabrics unit of Courtaulds Textiles, the British retailer that Sara Lee acquired in March. Together, the four units generate about $4 billion in revenue.</p>
        <p>The moves, which executives say will narrow and sharpen the focus of the conglomerate, which is based in Chicago, are also expected to raise about $2.5 billion for Sara Lee, which could use the money to make acquisitions that better complement its core brands.</p>
        <p>Troubled by lackluster earnings growth and a belief that the stock price was undervalued, top executives moved today to re-energize Sara Lee with promises of a more centralized and efficient management structure, a more focused portfolio and a more aggressive investment strategy, particularly in emerging markets.</p>
        <p>For more than two decades, the company has been acquiring dozens of major brands. And now, with its longtime chief executive, John H. Bryan, set to step down this summer, the company says it would like to create a more streamlined global enterprise. ''We have a new vision for Sara Lee, a vision that will focus our business portfolio and resources,'' said C. Steven McMillan, the president and chief operating officer of Sara Lee, who will take over as chief executive on July 1.</p>
        <p>Shares of Sara Lee rose slightly today, up 31.25 cents, to $18.875, on the New York Stock Exchange. The gains may have been tempered because Sara Lee executives also warned today that earnings in the coming year could come in about 5 percent below expectations because of currency weakness in Europe, which accounts for about 40 percent of the company's earnings.</p>
        <p>Wall Street analysts, however, largely praised the move by Sara Lee. ''It was a good news, bad news day,'' said John McMillin, an analyst at Prudential Securities. ''But now that Sara Lee got a haircut, they should be a better-looking company. Sara Lee had clearly gotten into too many businesses.''</p>
        <p>Sara Lee executives said the company could divest itself of additional units in the coming year. And analysts said that might help remove some of the feeling in the investment community that the company was too diversified.</p>
        <p>''After the divestitures, they'll be a little less of a conglomerate, but much more so than other food companies,'' said Terry Bivens, an analyst at Bear, Stearns. ''They want to prune back operations they feel are no longer strategic.''</p>
        <p>The analysts, however, say the move does not set the stage for Sara Lee to enter into a major merger with another food or consumer goods giant, or make it likely that Sara Lee will acquire a major company.</p>
        <p>While other large food companies may get tangled up in the bidding war over Bestfoods -- Unilever and Diageo have expressed interest -- Sara Lee is a different kind of beast. The company is too diversified, the analysts say, and it is too much of a hodgepodge of food and consumer product companies to be attractive as a takeover target. And the company's depressed stock does not give it the currency to use to take over another food giant.</p>
        <p>But several analysts said they expected Sara Lee to continue to move aggressively in acquiring smaller companies. In the last year, Sara Lee acquired Chock Full o' Nuts, the nation's fourth-largest coffee roaster.</p>
        <p>Now, analysts say, there are rumors Sara Lee could take aim at Flowers Industries, the maker of Mrs. Smith's pies and Keebler cookies, or the Dial Corporation, the soap maker.</p>
        <p>In the meantime, Sara Lee is reorganizing itself into three units: food and beverages, intimates and underwear, and household products. The company previously had five units.</p>
        <p>Mr. McMillan, at a news conference today in New York, said the company would retain its long tradition of operating as a decentralized company but that he would begin to push the company into a slightly more centralized model to take advantage of the company's desire to capitalize on its global scale.</p>
        <p>The company chose to divest itself of Champion, Coach and the international fabric units of Courtaulds because they did not fit neatly into the company's strategy, and in some cases they were tied to the ups and downs of the fashion business.</p>
        <p>Mr. McMillan said the company would focus on ''inner-wear'' rather than outerwear, which is why Sara Lee will maintain Playtex, Hanes and other apparel.</p>
        <p>The company also said today that it had made investments in three small companies: the Uniao coffee business, the largest coffee business in Brazil; Sol y Oro, a leading intimate apparel business in Argentina; and a minority interest in the Johnsonville Sausage Company, one of the largest makers of fresh premium sausages in the United States.</p>
        <p>PYA/Monarch, the nation's fourth-largest food service distributor, with about $2.7 billion in sales, also did not fit into the company's strategy.</p>
        <p>But analysts say today's move was also aimed at reaping value for divisions that were locked in a company that is largely undervalued by the market. ''This is really to unlock value,'' said William Leach, an analyst at Donaldson, Lufkin &amp; Jenrette. ''Other food companies are trading at much higher multiples. Sysco is trading at 30 times earnings and Sara Lee trades at 12 times earnings. If they sold off all their brands, they'd probably get 25 times earnings.''</p>
        <p>The company said it hoped to take Coach and PYA/Monarch public by the end of the year, keeping an 80 percent stake in the companies. Within 18 months, however, the company hopes to sell off that stake if market conditions are favorable.</p>
        <p>Mr. McMillan, the incoming chief executive, said the company decided that a mix of public offerings and outright sales would be most beneficial to the company. He also said that the company was motivated by concerns about the stock's weakness.</p>
        <p>''Our decisions are frequently made because we are trying to drive value for our shareholders,'' he said. ''We think we are substantially undervalued right now.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
