<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Two Sylphs, Two Casts And Two Interpretations</title>
    <meta content="31SYLP" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203620"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">American Ballet Theater</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dunning, Jennifer</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000531T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E3DB173CF932A05756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="586" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Two Sylphs, Two Casts And Two Interpretations</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER DUNNING</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dunning, Jennifer</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jennifer Dunning reviews two casts in American Ballet Theater's production of La Sylphide; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Most supernatural women in 19th-century ballet are alluring, man-killing monsters. A lethal mischievousness is the worst thing about the title character in August Bournonville's midcentury ballet ''La Sylphide,'' presented by American Ballet Theater on Wednesday afternoon and evening at the Metropolitan Opera House in a staging by Erik Bruhn.</p>
        <p>The level of dancing at each performance was high. But the two casts of lead dancers, all but one new in their roles, offered somewhat different takes on the characters. In the afternoon, Yan Chen's Sylphide was as fragile and elusive as a butterfly, a small, dear creature who never seemed to be still. Maxim Belotserkovsky was a figure of heroic vigor as James, the Scotsman whom the sylph loves.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Most supernatural women in 19th-century ballet are alluring, man-killing monsters. A lethal mischievousness is the worst thing about the title character in August Bournonville's midcentury ballet ''La Sylphide,'' presented by American Ballet Theater on Wednesday afternoon and evening at the Metropolitan Opera House in a staging by Erik Bruhn.</p>
        <p>The level of dancing at each performance was high. But the two casts of lead dancers, all but one new in their roles, offered somewhat different takes on the characters. In the afternoon, Yan Chen's Sylphide was as fragile and elusive as a butterfly, a small, dear creature who never seemed to be still. Maxim Belotserkovsky was a figure of heroic vigor as James, the Scotsman whom the sylph loves.</p>
        <p>The quality of that vigor was more Russian than the Danish style that Bournonville's sunny, airy ballets created. But in general the performances looked as if they could use a little polishing by a Bournonville specialist.</p>
        <p>Julie Kent, who danced the sylph in the evening, came closest to the distinctive tilt and articulation of the upper body, though the nicely shaped, fleet footwork of Vladimir Malakhov, her James, also had a Bournonville look. Ms. Kent's arms were so lyrical that they seemed to evaporate as they reached softly into the air, giving her the look of a 19th-century ballet lithograph come alive. But Mr. Malakhov too often confused childlike pouting with youthful innocence in his interpretation.</p>
        <p>The witch Madge, whose fury at James drives her to trick him into killing the sylph, is a pivotal character. In the evening, Victor Barbee once more made Madge a nuanced blend of gnomelike scurrying and madly self-righteous vindictiveness. Guillaume Graffin, new to the role, was first-rate as the matinee Madge. Mr. Graffin performs the important but often unappreciated ballet character with a revelatory imagination and an infectious delight. His Madge was more unmistakably female, with a sly Gallic wit, though neither he nor Mr. Barbee rise to full physical height as unnervingly as others have in the part.</p>
        <p>Another high point was the softly buoyant, high-flying dancing of Herman Cornejo as the evening Gurn, who finally wins the hand of James's fiancee, Effie. Joaquin De Luz's comically earnest matinee Gurn was also a standout. Rosalie O'Connor was his sweet-natured Effie, with Jennifer Alexander giving the character a more piquant twist in the evening. David Lamarche conducted the lilting score by Herman Lovenskjold at each performance.</p>
        <p>The matinee opened with an eloquent performance of Martha Graham's ''Diversion of Angels,'' danced by the exquisite Stella Abrera, Marcelo Gomes, Sandra Brown, John Gardner, Erica Cornejo and Mr. Cornejo, her brother. Sean Stewart stood out for the resilient full-bodied stretch of his dancing as the fourth man. The evening's opening ballet was Robert Joffrey's ''Pas des Deesses,'' a fly-in-amber portrait of four great 19th-century dancers and of Romantic ballet in general.</p>
        <p>''Diversion of Angels'' bloomed on the comparatively large Met stage. ''Pas des Deesses'' looked small and lonely. Alessandra Ferri was not particularly ethereal as the floating Marie Taglioni, but she maintained a crucial distance from the choreography. Amanda McKerrow as the languid Lucile Grahn and Paloma Herrera as the merry Fanny Cerrito were beautiful American dancers performing beautiful dance. Julio Bocca was a stylish Arthur Saint-Leon, the ballerinas' ever-ready cavalier. Gladys Celeste was the piano soloist.</p>
        <p>DANCE REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
