<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Liberties; After the Fall</title>
    <meta content="31DOWD$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203705"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dowd, Maureen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lazio, Rick A (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/Maureen Dowd</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000531T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E7D9143CF932A05756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="756" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Liberties; After the Fall</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MAUREEN DOWD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dowd, Maureen</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Maureen Dowd Op-Ed column on Repr Rick Lazio, nominated by Republicans to oppose Hillary Rodham in race for US Senate from New York; pokes fun at what she sees as his overeagerness to advance his career (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Poor Little Ricky.</p>
        <p>He thought he could scamper away from the Clinton curse.</p>
        <p>But there was the curse, slouching towards Babylon. The day before the biggest day of Rick Lazio's life -- his speech in Buffalo accepting the Republican nomination for the Senate, with all the cameras zooming in for a close-up of that boyish grin -- Bam! Splat! Thwack!</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Poor Little Ricky.</p>
        <p>He thought he could scamper away from the Clinton curse.</p>
        <p>But there was the curse, slouching towards Babylon. The day before the biggest day of Rick Lazio's life -- his speech in Buffalo accepting the Republican nomination for the Senate, with all the cameras zooming in for a close-up of that boyish grin -- Bam! Splat! Thwack!</p>
        <p>The guy falls flat on his face at the  Babylon Memorial Day parade and cuts his lip so badly he has to get eight stitches, and the lip gets so swollen it's hard to talk and smile, and fuhgeddabout kissing babies with that scary kisser.</p>
        <p>David Letterman was already having a ball: ''Rick Lazio. One day you're a busboy at the Olive Garden, the next day you're running for Senate against Hillary Clinton. . . . Rick Lazio. Isn't he that Cuban kid's uncle?''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio is so obscure that his own campaign staff is unsure whether his first name is Enrico, as The Associated Press says, or Ricardo, as The Washington Post says.</p>
        <p>So then Ricky has to take his big bow to the theme from ''Rocky.''</p>
        <p>Somebody should just come out and ask Hillary if she's got one of those tannis-root charms, the kind Ralph Bellamy and Ruth Gordon made Mia Farrow wear in ''Rosemary's Baby.'' That gal has left way too many spooky casualties in her wake.</p>
        <p>In politics, you never want a misstep to be upgraded to metaphor.</p>
        <p>Gerald Ford was a college athlete. But when his stumbles were lampooned by Chevy Chase, the humor resonated because Americans deemed Mr. Ford politically clumsy. His first act as president had been a pratfall -- pardoning Richard Nixon.</p>
        <p>When Jimmy Carter collapsed while jogging in black socks, it crystallized the sense that he was a wimp. We were fine; he had malaise.</p>
        <p>When a railing gave way and Bob Dole tumbled off a stage in Chico, Calif., in '96, it reinforced the idea that his campaign was in free fall and his time had passed.</p>
        <p>By contrast, when Bill Clinton tore a tendon in the wee hours while visiting the golfer Greg Norman in Florida in 1997, it had no figurative echo. Everybody simply reckoned that the president had been cavorting a bit.</p>
        <p>But when Little Ricky went tumbling down, the stature issue came bubbling up.</p>
        <p>He looked like an eager puppy springing out of the gate and going all splay-legged. Republicans fretted again: Is he ready for the big show?</p>
        <p>It was the most overcaffeinated entry into a race since George Bush announced Dan Quayle as his running mate in New Orleans. Little Danny, another Congressional pup itching for the sun, raced up and hugged the startled Mr. Bush, looking, for one terrifying moment, as if he were going to lick the older man's cheek.</p>
        <p>Republicans had been leery of Little Ricky's gratingly unsubtle ambition. Couldn't he at least thinly veil it? The New York G.O.P. had had to yank at the 42-year-old's leash after he noisily gnawed Rudy Giuliani's leg before the mayor learned he was sick and dropped out.</p>
        <p>When the nomination suddenly fell into the Long Island Congressman's lap, he was off and running, fairly panting with charm, as Dorothy Parker might put it. At the parade on Monday he was doing so much dashing and bounding and nuzzling and zigzagging, you just wanted to call out, Down, boy, down.</p>
        <p>You'd think a face gushing blood would be a great excuse to get out of a parade. But the dazed Lazio tried to keep going as though nothing had happened until his wife, a nurse, made him go to the hospital. When he rushed back, stitched and swollen, for a second parade, sprinting and air-kissing, Mayor Giuliani patted him on the back. Down, boy, down.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio has the self-promoting energy of Chuck Schumer and Bob Torricelli without the craftiness. He came out swinging in Buffalo, joking about getting a rematch with the pavement, pillorying Hillary as the candidate of Hollywood and left-wing special interests.</p>
        <p>He has already accomplished the impossible: He has made the first lady, relentlessly ridiculed by conservatives as a panting-for-power yuppie, look laid back.</p>
        <p>''I am the underdog in this race,'' Ricky barked in Buffalo.</p>
        <p>Down, boy, down.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
