<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Uniting World Against Violence to Women</title>
    <meta content="31PROF" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203672"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PUBLIC LIVES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Social Activism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Violence</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Feminist Movement</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Charlotte Bunch</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Center For Women's Global Leadership</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gross, Jane</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bunch, Charlotte</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Public Lives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Feminist Movement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Violence</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000531T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E0DE143CF932A05756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="959" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Uniting World Against Violence to Women</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE GROSS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gross, Jane</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Public Lives column profiles career of Charlotte Bunch, director of Center for Women's Global Leadership; she discusses her mission to build worldwide network of feminists who will press their local governments to end violence against women; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CHARLOTTE BUNCH is an earnest woman with a mission: to build a worldwide network of feminists who will press their local governments to end violence against women, be it genital mutilation in Africa, bride burning in India, honor killing in the Middle East or rape on the battlefields of Bosnia.</p>
        <p>In certain hands, these are the topics of tabloid television. Picture women in exotic dress, with their backs to the camera, telling lurid tales of abuse. Picture prime-time promos, studded with exclamation marks.  Picture early Geraldo, braying outrage.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CHARLOTTE BUNCH is an earnest woman with a mission: to build a worldwide network of feminists who will press their local governments to end violence against women, be it genital mutilation in Africa, bride burning in India, honor killing in the Middle East or rape on the battlefields of Bosnia.</p>
        <p>In certain hands, these are the topics of tabloid television. Picture women in exotic dress, with their backs to the camera, telling lurid tales of abuse. Picture prime-time promos, studded with exclamation marks.  Picture early Geraldo, braying outrage.</p>
        <p>This is not Ms. Bunch's way. She makes her case with the measured convolutions of academia and diplomacy, verbal porridge to some but suitable to her position as director of the Center for Women's Global Leadership at Rutgers University and a key player in the movement for international human rights for women.</p>
        <p>On Sunday, Ms. Bunch will lead a symposium at Columbia University on the eve of a special session of the United Nations General Assembly, known as Beijing Plus Five, which will review the progress made since the 1995 World Conference on Women. That conference of 181 nations produced a ''platform for action,''  which women's groups hoped would become an international standard.</p>
        <p>Ms. Bunch's 10-year-old institute trains many of these international feminists in leadership skills and organizing techniques. What may be new to the women of Namibia or Guatemala is old hat to Ms. Bunch, who in the 1960's and 70's was quite the firebrand.</p>
        <p>It is hard to see the radical passion of youth in the 55-year-old woman who spends most of her time these days in conference rooms overlooking United Nations Plaza. Ms. Bunch is conservatively dressed, her hair cropped for convenience and her only accessory a utilitarian tote bag. She calls herself an activist and remains one, staid but fervent.</p>
        <p>Ms. Bunch came of age at Duke University, in the midst of the civil rights and antiwar movement, learning community organizing as a member of the World Student Christian Federation, one of many faith-based organizations of that era that schooled the leaders of the New Left.</p>
        <p>She took a path different from her family's, but came naturally to her social action. Her parents, Methodist missionaries, were studying to go to China when Pearl Harbor intervened. Instead, her father, a family doctor, volunteered for assignment in under-served rural areas.</p>
        <p>HE wound up in Artesia, N.M.,  far from Taos or Sante Fe, in a part of the state known as Little West Texas. ''We were liberals in a conservative small town,'' Ms. Bunch said. ''Professionals, when everyone else was working class.''</p>
        <p>Her mother was a social worker until her four children were born, then what Ms. Bunch calls a ''civic actor,'' the first woman to be president of the school board and later founder of the state's first community mental health program. Mrs. Bunch is 87, teaching English to immigrants and feeding the homeless.</p>
        <p>Ms. Bunch's two sisters are schoolteachers and her brother a small-town doctor. ''I'm the only one who made a career of being an activist,'' she said. ''But all of us made a life of service in the community.''</p>
        <p>After Duke, where Ms. Bunch studied history and political science and participated in the early sit-ins, she accepted a fellowship at the Institute for Policy Studies, a left-leaning research group in Washington. She had expected to be a full-fledged member of an intellectual community, as she had been in the Christian Federation, but instead encountered male chauvinism typical of the times.</p>
        <p>''I'd make a comment at a meeting and nobody would even acknowledge me,'' Ms. Bunch said. ''Then some man would say the same thing and they'd all nod and say, 'Good idea.' They turned me into a feminist because I was so frustrated. I'm grateful to them.''</p>
        <p>It was during her years at the institute, from 1969 to 1977, that Ms. Bunch identified herself as a lesbian, organized a radical women's discussion group and founded the Furies Collective, a lesbian newspaper, and Quest: A Feminist Quarterly.</p>
        <p>The discovery of her sexual orientation, after living as a member of the white, middle-class Protestant majority, clarified ''what it means to have privilege and what it means not to have privilege,'' she said. ''It enabled me to understand, emotionally as well as intellectually, what it feels like to be marginalized.''</p>
        <p>To be an American, Ms. Bunch knew, is to be privileged, so she turned her gaze toward the international arena, becoming, in effect, a feminist missionary. That meant nearly a decade organizing conferences around the world. In 1987, she accepted an invitation to bring her global perspective to Rutgers.</p>
        <p>The Center for Women's Global Leadership was the gleam of an idea, intended as an adjunct to the Center for American Women in Politics, an existing research and policy organization at Rutgers. Ms. Bunch was determined that it not take the predictable course as an incubator for international political leaders.</p>
        <p>''We need women leaders,'' she agreed. ''But we need them to have a vision for something.''</p>
        <p>That something, Ms. Bunch decided, should be an end to violence against women in all its permutations, from a battered executive wife in America to a starving Eastern European woman sold into prostitution. ''This is what women have in common,'' Ms. Bunch said, ''without pretending we are all the same.''</p>
        <p>PUBLIC LIVES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
