<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. SEEKS TO EASE SOME RESTRICTIONS ON  BROADCASTERS</title>
    <meta content="31BROA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Front Page; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203715"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Communications Commission</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Labaton, Stephen</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000531T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEED9143CF932A05756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1093" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. SEEKS TO EASE SOME RESTRICTIONS ON  BROADCASTERS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN LABATON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Labaton, Stephen</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Federal Communications Commission, in biennial review ordered by Congress as part of overhaul of telecommunications industry, prepares new rules to relax, but not eliminate, both cross-ownership and dual-network restrictions; specifically proposes easing decades-old regulations preventing broadcasters from owning broadcast station and newspaper in same city and from owning more than one national television network; proposes changing manner in which listening audience of local radio markets is measured by reegulators in way that could enable companies to own more stations than they do under current limits (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Federal Communications Commission proposed easing several decades-old regulations on broadcasters today, including one that prevents companies from owning a broadcast station and newspaper in the same city and another prohibiting a company from owning more than one national television network.</p>
        <p>In a biennial review that Congress ordered as part of its overhaul of the telecommunications industry four years ago, the F.C.C. said it had begun preparing new rules to relax, but not eliminate, both the cross-ownership and dual-network restrictions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Federal Communications Commission proposed easing several decades-old regulations on broadcasters today, including one that prevents companies from owning a broadcast station and newspaper in the same city and another prohibiting a company from owning more than one national television network.</p>
        <p>In a biennial review that Congress ordered as part of its overhaul of the telecommunications industry four years ago, the F.C.C. said it had begun preparing new rules to relax, but not eliminate, both the cross-ownership and dual-network restrictions.</p>
        <p>It also proposed changing the manner in which the listening audience of local radio markets is measured by regulators in a way that could enable companies to own more stations than they do under current limits.</p>
        <p>The proposals may have significant implications for several pending and recently completed mergers in the broadcast and newspaper industries. Existing rules would have required significant divestitures after Viacom's acquisition of CBS and the Tribune Company's proposed purchase of Times Mirror.</p>
        <p>Officials said some restrictions had become outdated as Americans increasingly turned to new technologies like satellite television and high-speed Internet services.</p>
        <p>At the same time, a wave of corporate deals has led to new levels of concentration in the broadcast, cable and telephone industries, testing the ownership limits imposed by both the F.C.C. and Congress in the Telecommunications Act of 1996.</p>
        <p>''The media marketplace has become increasingly dynamic and competitive, with an expanding number of information outlets and media platforms, and more Americans than ever before are using these options,'' said William E. Kennard, the commission's chairman. ''The report we issue today balances the public interest in diversity of ownership with the demands of a changing marketplace and the broadcast industries' need to realize economic efficiencies and remain competitive.''</p>
        <p>Both the cross-ownership and dual-network regulations were rooted in the idea of promoting diversity of the airwaves, and officials at the F.C.C. said that they were not planning on eliminating the restrictions but easing them in particular cases.</p>
        <p>While the proposed changes outlined today are more gradual than some large companies had sought, they would be a significant policy change for the agency, which has defended itself against legal attacks and criticisms over the rules.</p>
        <p>In the case of the cross-ownership rules, the commission said that there was still a need for restrictions in many areas to prevent a company from controlling both a newspaper and television station.</p>
        <p>But the commission also concluded that in some cities, particularly large ones with many media outlets, ''there might be situations in which the rule may not be necessary to protect the public interest in diversity and competition.''</p>
        <p>In the case of the dual-network rule, the agency said that two emerging television networks, UPN and Warner Brothers, were still developing and ought to be able to try to attract new investments from a major network. But commission officials said they would not alter rules that prevent the four majors -- ABC, CBS, Fox and NBC -- from acquiring one another.</p>
        <p>Officials expect the proposed rules to be issued in the next few months, and the commission would then consider them. The proposed changes come after heavy lobbying by some of the nation's largest broadcasting and newspaper companies, which have big stakes in trying to hold onto recently acquired TV companies.</p>
        <p>The cross-ownership restrictions have threatened to force the Tribune Company, which has agreed to buy Times Mirror, to sell some properties in three cities -- New York, Los Angeles and Hartford -- where the companies have newspapers and broadcasting properties. In New York, Tribune would own both WPIX, a WB affiliate, and Newsday, which is based in Long Island.</p>
        <p>The Tribune Company has also spent years trying to persuade the F.C.C. to permit it to own both a newspaper and a television station in Fort Lauderdale, Fla.</p>
        <p>The dual-network rule has threatened to force Viacom, which recently completed its acquisition of CBS, to sell its half interest in UPN. When it approved the deal four weeks ago, the F.C.C. gave Viacom one year to sell its stake in UPN. But if the agency finishes writing new rules before then, the company might not have to put the network up for sale.</p>
        <p>The commission stopped short of recommending any easing of the limitations that have prevented the stations owned by a company from reaching more than 35 percent of the national television audience, prompting Fox, which is at the limit and wants to expand, to immediately file a lawsuit against the agency.</p>
        <p>''The F.C.C. decision today is a textbook case of arbitrary and capricious government action,'' said Chase Carey, chairman and chief executive of Fox Television.</p>
        <p>''The national TV ownership cap, which may have served a purpose in the days when only three TV networks competed in local markets, long ago outlived its rationale and is now harming rather than promoting its original public-interest objectives of diversity, localism and competition,'' he said. ''In an era in which scores of nationwide programming networks are available to viewers from cable and satellite providers, it makes no sense to artificially limit the number of markets in which broadcasters can compete.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kennard said that Fox's argument had confused trends in the local market with trends in the national market and that there remained a compelling need to prevent any one company's stations from controlling the national market.</p>
        <p>''The majority of Americans still get most of their news and public affairs information from broadcast stations, and in a participatory democracy like ours, it is vitally important that we encourage the widest possible dissemination of this information from diverse and antagonistic sources,'' he said. ''Our structural ownership restrictions seek to promote this First Amendment principle.''</p>
        <p>Other critics said that Mr. Kennard's own observation that most Americans relied heavily on broadcasting to get their news demonstrated the need to keep the cross-ownership in place.</p>
        <p>''Broadcasting remains the single most important source of information at the local level for many, many voters, and most of the rest get their information from newspapers,'' said Andrew Jay Schwartzman, president of the Media Access Project, which promotes diversity on the airwaves.</p>
        <p>''To have these voices controlled by fewer and fewer owners cannot help democracy,'' he said. ''The evolution of the Internet has yet to make any significant change on how people decide to cast their vote for the mayor. The degree to which a few large economic powers in any community can control the debate is no less today than it has been in the past.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
