<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Metro Briefing</title>
    <meta content="31MBRF$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203762"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000531T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E0D6143CF932A05756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1741" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Metro Briefing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by Anthony Ramirez</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NEW YORK</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: PROBATION FOR DOCTOR  A Manhattan obstetrician, Allan Zarkin, 62, who carved his initials into a patient's abdomen after performing a Caesarean section in September, was sentenced yesterday to five years' probation and banned from practicing medicine as part of a plea bargain. Dr. Zarkin also was ordered to undergo psychiatric treatment.  David Rohde (NYT)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NEW YORK</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: PROBATION FOR DOCTOR  A Manhattan obstetrician, Allan Zarkin, 62, who carved his initials into a patient's abdomen after performing a Caesarean section in September, was sentenced yesterday to five years' probation and banned from practicing medicine as part of a plea bargain. Dr. Zarkin also was ordered to undergo psychiatric treatment.  David Rohde (NYT)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: MOTORIST SENTENCED  A drug addict who ran a red light on the Upper West Side last June, killing a man and critically injuring two pedestrians, was sentenced yesterday to 15 years to life in prison. The man, Pedro Robles, 39, who had taken the drug PCP before the incident, begged his victims and their families to forgive him. Justice Charles H. Solomon of State Supreme Court in Manhattan, noting that Mr. Robles had pleaded guilty to second-degree murder, sentenced him to the minimum term. David Rohde (NYT)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: BUS RULING EXPECTED  Judith Gould, the administrative law judge overseeing the New York Apple Tours case, said yesterday that she would decide ''as soon as humanly possible'' on whether to immediately suspend the bus company's operating license. Lawyers for the city have sought an immediate suspension, but a lawyer for Apple Tours said the company was being denied due process. A hearing to permanently revoke the company's license was scheduled for Friday. Last week, an Apple Tours bus struck and killed a man in Midtown. (NYT)</p>
        <p>QUEENS: ASIAN WOMEN PLAN MARCH  A group of South Asian women plan a march Saturday in Jackson Heights to focus attention on what they call the growing problem of domestic violence in the South Asian community. The group, Sakhi for South Asian Women, said it had received 129 telephone reports of domestic violence in the first four months of this year, compared with 252 reports for all of 1999. The group arranges shelter for victims of domestic violence. Stacy Albin (NYT)</p>
        <p>QUEENS: AIR TRAIN PROTEST  A group of Jamaica and South Ozone Park residents plan a second day of protest tomorrow against plans for the Air Train, an eight-mile-long light rail line to connect Kennedy International Airport to the A subway line and the Long Island Rail Road. The group, Southeast Queens Concerned Neighbors, says the Air Train would cause congestion and weaken the foundations of homes near the Van Wyck Expressway. A Port Authority spokesman said they were ''working closely with residents and community leaders.'' Jenny Holand (NYT)</p>
        <p>ALBANY: INSURGENT SEEKS RE-ELECTION  Michael Bragman, the former Assembly majority leader who failed to oust Speaker Sheldon Silver, said yesterday that he would seek re-election in November to an 11th term. ''I believe that this year will be the most important campaign of my career,'' said Mr. Bragman, a Syracuse-area Democrat, in a prepared statement. In the last two weeks, Mr. Bragman led a group of Assembly Democrats critical of Mr. Silver's leadership style in an unsuccessful attempt to overthrow him. Mr. Silver retaliated by stripping Mr. Bragman of his leadership post. (AP)</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY</p>
        <p>KEARNY: YOUTH DROWNS IN RIVER  A 15-year-old boy from Newark drowned in the Passaic River yesterday after he jumped in to fetch his sneaker, which witnesses said a friend had thrown in the water, the police said. The boy went into the river at a park at the end of Bergen Avenue around 6:15 p.m., L. John Gawronski said, and disappeared. A diver from the Wallington Fire Department found the boy in the water about an hour later and he was rushed to West Hudson Hospital, but he died soon after, Lieutenant Gawronski said. The boy's name was not released. Andy Newman (NYT)</p>
        <p>TRENTON: TRANSPORT PLAN CRITICIZED  Environmental groups criticized a constitutional amendment before a Senate committee yesterday, calling it a ''blank check'' for accelerated suburban sprawl. Jennifer Jaroski, a spokeswoman for the Tri-State Transportation Campaign, a coalition of environmental groups, said the amendment would encourage highway construction and lead to more development. The amendment authorizes the use of money from tolls, gasoline taxes and other sources to increase the Transportation Trust Fund to $1 billion annually. The fund is used for highway construction and mass transit. A Senate vote is scheduled for June 8. Richard M. Brand (NYT)</p>
        <p>TRENTON: FINANCIER LOSES COURT FIGHT  A judge ruled yesterday that money made by Robert E. Brennan, the fallen financier, from the sale of his homes in Brielle, N.J., and Saratoga Springs, N.Y., must be surrendered to creditors. It was the second legal setback for Mr. Brennan, the former penny-stock tycoon, in less than a week. Mr. Brennan, 56, was spared immediate eviction from a condominium in Juno Beach, Fla., however, when a bankruptcy judge decided she needed more evidence. The Securities and Exchange Commission charged that Mr. Brennan employed ''boiler room'' tactics at his firm, First Jersey Securities, and manipulated the market in shares of little-known companies. (AP)</p>
        <p>CONNECTICUT</p>
        <p>HARTFORD: FIREWORKS OPPOSED  A bill that could legalize sparklers in time for the Fourth of July has been passed by the Legislature, but state fire marshals want the governor to veto the measure. If approved, the bill would promote a fire hazard, according to David Roth, president of the Connecticut Fire Marshals Association. A spokesman for Gov. John G. Rowland said the governor planned to sign the bill. The measure allows the sale of nonexplosive fireworks that give off a shower of sparks. (AP)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
