<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>ABC Acquires Another Reality-Based Series</title>
    <meta content="Y20ABC$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208869"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Abc Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Morris, William, Agency</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Stone Stanley Entertainment</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">TTTi Productions</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carter, Bill</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Mole, The (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Talent Agencies/William Morris Agency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000620T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE3DB1231F933A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="470" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>ABC Acquires Another Reality-Based Series</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL CARTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Carter, Bill</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>ABC-TV concludes deal for program The Mole, voyeristic hit from Belgium; program sends group of 'real people' on cross-country trek, performing series of scavanger-hunt-like tasks; deal is brokered by agents from William Morris Agency on behalf of Stone Stanley Entertainment, an American company that bought rights from TTTi Productions of Belgium; no date is set for program's premiere (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Moving quickly to capitalize on the sizzling television trend toward reality shows, led by CBS's ''Survivor,'' ABC concluded a deal yesterday for yet another voyeuristic hit from Europe.</p>
        <p>''The Mole,'' an import from Belgium, sends a group of ''real people'' on a cross-country trek, performing a series of scavenger-hunt-like tasks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Moving quickly to capitalize on the sizzling television trend toward reality shows, led by CBS's ''Survivor,'' ABC concluded a deal yesterday for yet another voyeuristic hit from Europe.</p>
        <p>''The Mole,'' an import from Belgium, sends a group of ''real people'' on a cross-country trek, performing a series of scavenger-hunt-like tasks.</p>
        <p>The twist is that there is a saboteur in their midst, scheming to wreck their best efforts, and they do not know who it is. And, of course, everything takes place on camera.</p>
        <p>''The Mole'' had been the subject of intense negotiations among several networks. The deal was brokered by agents from the William Morris Agency on behalf of Stone Stanley Entertainment, an American company that bought the rights from TTTi Productions of Belgium. It was almost concluded several months ago, but the network involved in the deal at that point would not commit itself to putting the show on quickly enough, one executive connected to the talks said.</p>
        <p>After ''Survivor'' soared to record ratings for CBS, the negotiations resumed and ABC closed the deal yesterday for an undisclosed fee.</p>
        <p>ABC had been the earliest network pursuing the European reality genre, and found the first success by bringing ''Who Wants to Be a Millionaire'' from England last summer. That started the trend toward hits based on formats created in Europe.</p>
        <p>Even as ABC closed the deal yesterday, one other network was ready to pounce if ABC passed, the executive connected to the deal said.</p>
        <p>ABC's top program executives, Stu Bloomberg and Lloyd Braun, said yesterday that they had no date set for starting ''The Mole,'' other than to note, as Mr. Braun put it, ''it will go on when it's ready to go on.''</p>
        <p>But unlike both ''Survivor'' and ''Who Wants to Be a Millionaire,'' this show will not be held back until next summer. Mr. Bloomberg said that ''The Mole '' was ''built on a pre-existing format, so we could get it up and running fast.''</p>
        <p>That is likely to mean a start date some time early next year.</p>
        <p>Like both ''Survivor'' and ''Big Brother,'' the next example of the tele-voyeurism genre, which is set to start on CBS July 5, ''The Mole'' is an elimination contest, with a big financial prize for the winning contestant. The prize amount has not been set.</p>
        <p>Contestants will be eliminated after each show based on a quiz over who they think the mole is.</p>
        <p>The show was a hit in two iterations in Belgium and more recently in Australia. The format has now been sold in more than 40 countries.</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
