<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lazio Rebuts Mrs. Clinton With His Own Attack Ad</title>
    <meta content="20LAZI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208903"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Archibold, Randal C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lazio, Rick A (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000620T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807E0D91231F933A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="614" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lazio Rebuts Mrs. Clinton With His Own Attack Ad</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RANDAL C. ARCHIBOLD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Archibold, Randal C</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Repr Rick A Lazio, three days after Hillary Rodham Clinton began running television advertisements critical of him, shoots back with his own pointed advertisement, even as he promised to take the high road; accuses Clinton of running negative campaign (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Three days after Hillary Rodham Clinton began running television advertisements critical of him, Representative Rick A. Lazio shot back yesterday with his own pointed advertisement, even as he promised to take the high road.</p>
        <p>''Mrs. Clinton, you can run the negative campaign about tearing people down,'' Mr. Lazio says in a 30-second ad that will begin running this week. ''I'm going to run a campaign about building New York up.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Three days after Hillary Rodham Clinton began running television advertisements critical of him, Representative Rick A. Lazio shot back yesterday with his own pointed advertisement, even as he promised to take the high road.</p>
        <p>''Mrs. Clinton, you can run the negative campaign about tearing people down,'' Mr. Lazio says in a 30-second ad that will begin running this week. ''I'm going to run a campaign about building New York up.''</p>
        <p>At another point in the commercial, Mr. Lazio, the Republican nominee for the Senate, delivers his own jab at the Democratic nominee while smiling steadily into the camera. ''Why is she doing this? Because it's a lot easier for Mrs. Clinton to attack me than to name a single thing she has ever done for New York.''</p>
        <p>Far from the last word, Mr. Lazio's advertisement set off another round of brawling between the candidates, who even disputed the extent to which Mr. Lazio's commercial  would be seen.</p>
        <p>Dan McLagan, a spokesman for Mr. Lazio, said the campaign had spent a substantial amount to broadcast the advertisement across the state, but he refused to provide a dollar figure, calling it confidential information. Howard Wolfson, Mrs. Clinton's spokesman, said a check of television station logs showed the commercial would be run only once in some markets, including New York City. Mr. Wolfson said this suggested that the commercial's release was more a ploy for publicity than a significant advertising push.</p>
        <p>That was not the only example of rancor between the camps.</p>
        <p>Just as Mr. Lazio's campaign manager was beginning a news conference in Manhattan to announce the commercial, Mr. Lazio's second new advertisement in a week, Mrs. Clinton's press office was e-mailing reporters to attack it, accusing Mr. Lazio of initiating the negative tone last month in his nomination acceptance speech.</p>
        <p>It was one of two news releases that Mrs. Clinton put out yesterday criticizing Mr. Lazio. The other challenged Mr. Lazio's reputation for independence in the House by noting a report in Roll Call, a Capitol Hill newspaper, that quoted unidentified Republicans as saying Mr. Lazio has asked the Republican leadership for ''a pass'' to vote against Republican-sponsored legislation that might discredit his moderate credentials. Mr. McLagan called the report untrue.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio's ad came in response to ads that Mrs. Clinton began running Friday assailing Mr. Lazio for his previous opposition to recently approved state legislation that will stiffen penalties for hate crimes and his opposition to a Democratic-sponsored measure in the House known as the patients' bill of rights that would give people broader powers to sue health maintenance organizations. Mr. Lazio supported a Republican version that instead called for tax deductions to help people pay their medical premiums.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio has called Mrs. Clinton's commercials a distortion of his record, and in his new one, he says that Mrs. Clinton was trying to fool voters and that ''I voted for a patients' bill of rights and I oppose hate crimes.''</p>
        <p>Bill Dal Col, Mr. Lazio's campaign manager, addressed the attacks, vowing to rebut every advertisement Mr. Lazio perceives as negative.</p>
        <p>''We will meet her at the battlefield at every point,'' he said, though he maintained that Mr. Lazio's ads would not turn negative.</p>
        <p>''There is a way to do an ad where you educate voters without attacking,'' Mr. Dal Col said. ''We will take the most efficient, effective use of communication to get that message across so that the voters can clearly see who Hillary Clinton is.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
