<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Transcript of the Archbishop's Homily: Securing a Foundation of Faith</title>
    <meta content="20ETEX" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208912"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="A NEW ARCHBISHOP"/>
      <identified-content>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Roman Catholic Church</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Egan, Edward M (Bishop)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Text</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000620T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E5D81231F933A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1814" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Transcript of the Archbishop's Homily: Securing a Foundation of Faith</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Transcript of Archbishop Edward M Egan's homily in St Patrick's Cathedral; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Following is a transcript of Archbishop Edward M. Egan's homily  yesterday in St. Patrick's Cathedral, as recorded by The New York Times:</p>
        <p>My dear friends in Jesus Christ, 15 years ago I was consecrated a bishop in the Basilica of SS. John and Paul on the Caelian Hill in Rome. The consecration was a very New York event. One of the co-consecrators was our dear deceased and beloved John Cardinal O'Connor. All of the servers were seminarians from the Archdiocese of New York, the Diocese of Brooklyn and the Diocese of Rockville Centre. And the basilica? The Basilica of SS. John and Paul was New York's own. For it had been the titular Cardinalatial See of Francis Cardinal Spellman and Terence Cardinal Cooke, and soon thereafter it was to be the titular Cardinalatial See for John Cardinal O'Connor.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Following is a transcript of Archbishop Edward M. Egan's homily  yesterday in St. Patrick's Cathedral, as recorded by The New York Times:</p>
        <p>My dear friends in Jesus Christ, 15 years ago I was consecrated a bishop in the Basilica of SS. John and Paul on the Caelian Hill in Rome. The consecration was a very New York event. One of the co-consecrators was our dear deceased and beloved John Cardinal O'Connor. All of the servers were seminarians from the Archdiocese of New York, the Diocese of Brooklyn and the Diocese of Rockville Centre. And the basilica? The Basilica of SS. John and Paul was New York's own. For it had been the titular Cardinalatial See of Francis Cardinal Spellman and Terence Cardinal Cooke, and soon thereafter it was to be the titular Cardinalatial See for John Cardinal O'Connor.</p>
        <p>The basilica is one of the most interesting houses of worship in Rome for a number of reasons. First of all, a good part of it was actually built in the fourth century. Second, if you stand in the piazza in front of it and make a 360-degree turn, you'll see nothing that Dante Alighieri did not see 700 years before. Third, and most interestingly, the Basilica of SS. John and Paul is built on top of the house in which the saints lived.</p>
        <p>Here is the story: John and Paul were devoted followers of Jesus Christ. They served as palace guards for the daughter of the Emperor Constantine, a Christian emperor. In 361, a violently anti-Christian emperor by the name of Julian ascended to the throne. He knew of the faith commitment of John and Paul, and he tried to force them to offer sacrifices to pagan gods. John and Paul refused, and according to an ancient document known as ''The Passion of SS. John and Paul,'' they framed their refusal in these words: Our lives are in the service of the emperor. But our souls belong to God. Gladly would we die rather than forsake the truth of our lord and savior. Thus the two young Roman soldiers were murdered in their home on the Caelian Hill by order of the emperor.</p>
        <p>The following year, Julian died, and he was succeeded by a Christian emperor like Constantine. Hence the neighbors -- there were 20 in the neighborhood led by a senator by the name of Byzantius -- decided to turn their home into a church. And as the years and centuries went by, church upon church was built there, and the one you see today has as its foundation the home of SS. John and Paul.</p>
        <p>Today, if you wish, you can walk down a flight of stairs from the basilica and actually walk into the home of the saints. You can admire the frescoes on the wall, the frescoes that were there then and are there now. I love the Basilica of SS. John and Paul because it sums up for me what parishes and dioceses are all about. We are communities that are built on uncompromising acceptance of all that the Lord has revealed. This is our foundation. Our strength is grounded in our faith.</p>
        <p>This being the case, it is essential first that we know what the Lord has told us and that we embrace it with love and dedication. And this we will do as long as all the means of repeating and embracing revelation are firmly in place. Our focus must be relentlessly committed to announcing the Gospel completely, clearly, courageously. Our schools must be places in which the youth hear the word of God, proclaimed with joy and with the utmost of trust.</p>
        <p>Our catechetical programs must be sources of both inspiration and conviction. In a word, our basilica, the Archdiocese of New York, must rest upon the same foundation upon which the Basilica of SS. John and Paul stands today: courageous, joyful belief in all the Lord has told us.</p>
        <p>The first reading from the prophet Jeremiah points the way. The prophet had been appointed to speak to the nations of the Lord. He protests. He does not believe he has the credentials for this particular service. Ah, ah, ah, Lord, I am but a child. I know not how to speak, he says. And the Lord responds: ''What I command you, you shall speak. Have no fear. I am placing my words in your mouth.'' We do not announce ourselves. We do not announce our Gospel. We announce Jesus Christ, and him crucified. And when we announce him with confident faith, our basilica is strong.</p>
        <p>Still, my dear friends, it is a fact of human experience that proclaiming the Lord cannot be done effectively unless those who do the proclaiming and those who hear it as well are in contact with their God in prayer. Our basilica is indeed built upon faith, but it is sustained with prayer, with conversation with God -- God, who is at our elbow.</p>
        <p>A few years ago, a national pollster reported that he had spoken with a large number of Catholics across the nation and found that some were unsure about the central and essential prayer of our faith, the holy sacrifice of the Mass. Some, according to the pollster, were having doubts as to whether or not Jesus Christ, son of God, son of Mary, is really and truly present under the appearances of bread and wine on our altars and in our tabernacles.</p>
        <p>I do not know how valid that poll might have been. But I do know that we must be a prayerful people here in the Archdiocese of New York, a eucharistically prayerful people, if our basilica is to stand. There can be no hesitation, no compromise. We kneel before the Son of God we adore, we creatures whom he redeemed.</p>
        <p>Certainly St. Paul understood all of this. In his first letter to the Corinthians, our second reading this afternoon, he repeats with care and clarity what Matthew, Mark and Luke had reported in their Gospels and what all the followers of the Lord knew: This is the body of Jesus Christ. This is his blood. And when we receive him, we proclaim him until he comes. Our basilica, I repeat, will be strong if it rests on faith and is sustained by prayer. But that is not enough.</p>
        <p>Finally, our basilica, this splendid Archdiocese of New York, will thrive only if that prayerful faith is lived out in the works of justice and charity. Jesus Christ made this abundantly clear in his first sermon delivered in a humble synagogue in Nazareth. You heard part of it today in the Gospel. The spirit of the Lord is upon me. He has anointed me. He has sent me to bring glad tidings to the poor, to proclaim liberty to captives, recovery of sight to the blind, release to prisoners. We, his mystical body, his holy church, need to repeat those words in our hearts and in our lives.</p>
        <p>May we tolerate discrimination because of race or creed? May we accept the poverty of others as something unrelated to ourselves? May we allow the sick and disabled to be neglected? May we stand idly by while the being within the mother is killed, even though no one has ever been able to prove that it is other than a human being with an inalienable right to live? May we look the other way when the elderly are put [pausing for applause] -- may we look the other way when the elderly are put to death because someone questions the quality of their life?</p>
        <p>To all of these questions, the answer must be a resounding no. And the reason is crystal clear. The victim of discrimination, the impoverished, the sick, the disabled, the unborn, the elderly, are all images of God, mirrors held up to divinity, beings for whom a God would and did die. There can be no prayerful faith if there is wavering regarding the rights of those images of divinity.</p>
        <p>This afternoon, I thank you most sincerely for receiving me so warmly into this great archdiocese, this wonderful basilica. I feel very much at home. And I seize the opportunity to thank our apostolic administrator, Bishop Robert Brucato; our vicar general, Bishop Patrick Sheridan; our chancellor, Msgr. Edward O'Donnell; our secretary, Msgr. Gregory Mustaciuolo. And I thank as well all of the staff of the Catholic Center and the cathedral.</p>
        <p>I wish as well to thank in a very special way our apostolic nuncio, Archbishop Gabriel Montalvo, for being with us today and yesterday. He is a cherished friend of the Archdiocese of New York. Please, your excellency, tell the Holy Father of our gratitude for his kindness and yours as well.</p>
        <p>Just one final word. For centuries the Catholics of Rome and Catholics across the world had been given to understand that the Basilica of SS. John and Paul was indeed built on the foundation which was the house of the saints at the time of their martyrdom. However, it was not until 1950 that excavations were started under the basilica to prove that the tradition about the foundation of the basilica was indeed true. The person responsible for completing those excavations was, of course, a New Yorker: Francis Cardinal Spellman. In 1958, my last year in the seminary in Rome, the excavations were opened and it was possible to go down and walk in the neighborhood of SS. John and Paul. All doubt was removed. Cardinal Spellman, a New Yorker, had seen to that.</p>
        <p>My prayer today is that a new New Yorker may remove, with you, all the doubt about the foundation of our basilica. We are a people of faith. We are a people of prayer. We are a people of justice. We are a people of charity. That is our formula. That is why our basilica stands. How privileged am I, how honored am I, how humble am I to join you in our basilica.</p>
        <p>In the name of the Father and the Son and the Holy Spirit, amen.</p>
        <p>A NEW ARCHBISHOP</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
