<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Piazza Hits Hard by Keeping It Simple</title>
    <meta content="20PIAZ$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208926"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kepner, Tyler</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Piazza, Mike</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000620T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6D71231F933A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1314" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Piazza Hits Hard by Keeping It Simple</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kepner, Tyler</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses New York Mets catcher Mike Piazza's success at hitting; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When he is at the plate, Mike Piazza gives himself instant feedback. He processes the pitches he sees and the way his swing feels. Beyond that, he keeps it simple. There is too much analysis of hitting, Piazza believes, and he does not need it.</p>
        <p>''I go by total feel,'' Piazza, the Mets catcher, said. ''That's just the way I've always been. I've never really looked or bothered to analyze it.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When he is at the plate, Mike Piazza gives himself instant feedback. He processes the pitches he sees and the way his swing feels. Beyond that, he keeps it simple. There is too much analysis of hitting, Piazza believes, and he does not need it.</p>
        <p>''I go by total feel,'' Piazza, the Mets catcher, said. ''That's just the way I've always been. I've never really looked or bothered to analyze it.''</p>
        <p>Piazza never studies video. He just hits, and he has been extraordinary this season, with a .365 average, 18 home runs and 50 runs batted in. He leaves it to others to uncover the mysteries.</p>
        <p>When Piazza lashed a game-winning home run in San Diego last month, the Padres' right fielder, Tony Gwynn, put his head down and ran back. There was no way this ball was going out, Gwynn thought, but in an instant it was gone, crashing violently from a back wall to the trunk of a palm tree. Padres closer Trevor Hoffman, one of the many star pitchers Piazza destroys, was the victim.</p>
        <p>After the game, Gwynn watched the homer on video. Piazza had hit it off the end of the bat, with his backside pointing to the third-base dugout, and yet the ball carried as it would from a left-hander's bat. Gwynn was amazed: nobody else in the league would have hit that out, he thought. Gwynn asked Piazza how he did it, and Piazza was nonchalant. ''Hey, I don't know,'' he responded. ''I just got a good swing on it.''</p>
        <p>While the brute strength displayed in that home run was impressive, more impressive to Gwynn is how often Piazza hits the opposite way.</p>
        <p>Gwynn, who has won eight batting titles, thinks Piazza has the perfect temperament and the perfect stroke to win one himself. ''He keeps the barrel in the hitting zone like a contact hitter,'' Gwynn said. ''He stays in the hitting zone a lot longer than your average power hitter. Most of your power hitters are guys that get to the ball, through the ball, and then they cut their swing off. But he just stays through the ball.''</p>
        <p>That ability to angle the bat so it can meet the ball in any spot allows Piazza to hit to all fields, though he said it is not by design. His strength is not pulling, so Piazza naturally guards against that, staying inside the ball and giving himself more time to recognize the pitch because he knows he can hit to right.</p>
        <p>While other hitters use movement to generate power, Piazza often seems to hit from a standstill.</p>
        <p>Mets first baseman Todd Zeile, a teammate of Piazza's in three places, said Piazza has always had a simple swing. That is why he hits for such a high average. ''Less moving parts, less to go wrong,'' Zeile said.</p>
        <p>''Some of his swings are freakish,'' said Cubs second baseman Eric Young, a teammate of Piazza's with the Los Angeles Dodgers. ''He's able to go deep with just a flick of his bat. He can get fooled and still hit a line drive. We were just in awe of some of the things he can do with the bat. He puts good wood on the ball every single swing.''</p>
        <p>The Mets' hitting coach, Tom Robson, said posture is the most important thing for Piazza, and that he doesn't really flick his home runs. ''He uses his legs better than anybody, but he gives the illusion that he's using his hands,'' Robson said.</p>
        <p>When he finishes his swing, Piazza sometimes twirls his bat above his shoulders, like a conductor waving his wand after a show. That flourish comes from the enormous force of the ball hitting a bat moving so quickly with such mass behind it.</p>
        <p>Robson has never timed a player with better bat speed than that of Piazza, whom he has timed at 0.14 seconds from the moment he starts his swing until he makes contact. Paul Molitor, who had more than 3,000 career hits, is the only other player Robson has seen who can match that.</p>
        <p>Then there is Piazza's mass. He is 6 feet 3 inches, 215 pounds, and a sight to behold, especially for teammates watching him daily for the first time.</p>
        <p>Mets outfielder Jay Payton, who is muscular but smaller, marvels at the advantage Piazza gets from his size. ''First of all, he's just a good hitter,'' Payton said. ''Then he has remarkable strength, and he knows how to use it. He knows he can be very quiet at the plate and track the ball as long as he can. A lot of times you see him hit balls out, and it looks like he takes them right out of the catcher's mitt, because he's able to wait so long. As strong as Mike is, he can get away with doing things other guys can't.''</p>
        <p>The Mets starter Mike Hampton said no player is stronger from the forearms down than Piazza. Hampton compared Piazza's strength to Mark McGwire's.</p>
        <p>''But the difference is that Mike hits more balls on the sweet spot,'' Hampton said. ''He's less prone to a lot of different pitches; he doesn't have very many holes. He might have one spot where you might be able to get him three out of four times, but that fourth time might be a home run that could be the difference in the game.''</p>
        <p>To Piazza, who said he tries to humanize the game's top pitchers, the most important thing about hitting is discipline. He is not afraid to hit with two strikes, he said, and he knows the third strike is often toughest for a pitcher.</p>
        <p>He can tell he is swinging well when there is no tension at the plate, when he is not thinking about the count or the situation. When he is late on pitches or pulling balls foul, Piazza knows he must focus on hitting up the middle. But his basic tenet is simple, unbending: hit the ball hard.</p>
        <p>The thinking on Piazza is to challenge him inside, to make him pull the ball. Piazza can hit the inside pitch, but his preference is to follow advice from Ted Williams, the Hall of Famer, who visited the teen-age Piazza and famously remarked that the kid had a good swing.</p>
        <p>''Somebody was talking to Ted Williams one time, saying this particular hitter had trouble hitting the high pitch,'' Piazza said. ''And Ted Williams said, 'Well, tell him not to swing at it,' meaning it's a ball.</p>
        <p>''For me, I had trouble hitting the inside pitch for a time, so I said to myself: 'All right, well, don't swing at it. Or if you do, make sure you approach it the right way.' The inside part of the plate -- to get a strike, usually it's off the plate, because they don't want to miss on the plate. When they do miss on the plate, you can hit it a long way.''</p>
        <p>A hitter gets four at-bats a game, and the way Piazza sees it, that means he has 12 strikes to use. If he can't hit 4 balls hard out of 12 chances, Piazza said, something is very wrong.</p>
        <p>But he knows there are days that will not happen. It was Williams, after all, who said hitting a baseball is the most difficult task in sports. Piazza believes that, and it gives him perspective.</p>
        <p>As close as he is to perfecting his craft, he knows he will never master it.</p>
        <p>''You have to accept that you're going to have times where you don't feel like you can hit anything,'' Piazza said. ''You just try to be consistent and stay with what's been successful for you.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
