<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Need Elephant Repellent? Try This Hot Pepper Brew</title>
    <meta content="20ELEP$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208817"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elephants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Capsaicin</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Zimbabwe</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Wildlife Conservation Society</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Osborn, Ferrel Loki (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Revkin, Andrew C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Zimbabwe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Zimbabwe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000620T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE2D71531F933A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1607" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Need Elephant Repellent? Try This Hot Pepper Brew</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW C. REVKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Revkin, Andrew C</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dr Ferrel Loki Osborn, elephant expert, has devised multipronged array of elephant repellents for use by Zimbabwe farmers, including some farmers can concoct themselves; all use capsaicin, chemical that puts heat in hot peppers; describes his research into why elephants raid farms even when food is abundant in forests to staff members of Wildlife Conservation Society, Bronx, which has supported his work; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dr. Ferrel Loki Osborn loves elephants. But he also loves the villagers of the Zambezi River Valley in northern Zimbabwe, whose fields of carefully tended corn, cotton and banana crops have long tempted elephants looking for a convenient midnight snack.</p>
        <p>Therein lies the root of Dr. Osborn's years-long quest for the ultimate elephant repellent -- and a potential career shift from zoologist toward pepper-extract eco-entrepreneur. He has devised a multipronged array of repellents, some of which rural farmers can concoct themselves, all using capsaicin, the chemical that puts the heat in hot peppers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Dr. Ferrel Loki Osborn loves elephants. But he also loves the villagers of the Zambezi River Valley in northern Zimbabwe, whose fields of carefully tended corn, cotton and banana crops have long tempted elephants looking for a convenient midnight snack.</p>
        <p>Therein lies the root of Dr. Osborn's years-long quest for the ultimate elephant repellent -- and a potential career shift from zoologist toward pepper-extract eco-entrepreneur. He has devised a multipronged array of repellents, some of which rural farmers can concoct themselves, all using capsaicin, the chemical that puts the heat in hot peppers.</p>
        <p>This 33-year-old elephant expert, reared in Connecticut and educated at Cambridge, began seeking a solution after he found himself occasionally helping to shoot ''particularly cheeky'' young bulls that were repeat offenders, sometimes despoiling fields in an almost playful cat-and-mouse game with outraged, fearful farmers.</p>
        <p>To those who recoil at the thought of an elephant biologist killing an elephant, he points out that the clash between pachyderms and people has deadly consequences on both sides: nearly 200 people are crushed or gored by elephants in Zimbabwe each year, leaving a strong impression in the minds of rural residents whose hatred for elephants grows, as does the tendency to shoot.</p>
        <p>Crop-raiding elephants have even become issues in elections in several African countries, with rural communities demanding an armed response by the government. And the conflict also increases peoples' resentment toward the parks and preserves that are the elephants' haven.</p>
        <p>Several years ago, Dr. Osborn said, a park official visited a village that had seen the fruits of five months of tilling, planting and weeding trampled to dust one night. He was tied to a tree and beaten.</p>
        <p>So Dr. Osborn began studying why some elephants -- even at the height of the rainy season when there is plenty to eat -- leave forests and grasslands on moonless nights and pad silently into farms.</p>
        <p>On a visit to New York City last week, he described his findings to staff members at the Wildlife Conservation Society in the Bronx, which has supported his recent work with several grants.</p>
        <p>He said crop raids by wildlife had happened ever since humans first began practicing agriculture, with elephants being part of the problem both in Africa and Asia at least for centuries. ''There are Sanskrit records of this in India going back thousands of years,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But the problem has intensified in recent years, particularly in places like northern Zimbabwe, as farmers who have exhausted their fields have pushed farther into forests in a destructive cycle seeking fertile soil to grow cotton and corn for cash and  food crops.</p>
        <p>Along the Zambezi River, there is an annual rhythm to the raids, he said, which begin quite abruptly halfway through the wet growing season, which runs from October to May. ''The trouble usually starts in February,'' he said. ''They start coming out like someone's flipped a switch.''</p>
        <p>The raiders are usually young bull elephants that roam in small packs seeking females.</p>
        <p>He found that the nutrient level in wild grasses and brush was at its peak, so it is not a shortage of food that drives the animals to raid. In many cases, at least, it appears to be an indulgence, taking advantage of an easy snack, he said.</p>
        <p>''Not to be anthropomorphic,'' Dr. Osborn said, ''but their behavior is often like that of young human males.''</p>
        <p>With the aid of professional hunters, Dr. Osborn tested whether shooting a few elephants in a pack of crop-raiding bulls deterred the survivors from returning. When the presence of an elephant carcass did not dissuade the others from coming back, he used the findings to make a case to farming communities that shooting was not the solution.</p>
        <p>But what was?</p>
        <p>In some places, costly electric fences have been built, often with aid from conservation or international development groups, but Dr. Osborn has watched savvy elephants snap the upper wires with their tusks, then gingerly step over the lower ones.</p>
        <p>At more than $2,500 for a mile of fence, not counting repairs, this strategy is costly and impractical at best, he said.</p>
        <p>From days spent hiking in the American West, he said, he recalled how hot pepper extracts were used in bear repellents. In the East, they have been used to deter deer, skunks and squirrels. They are used in some ant repellents -- and in some self-defense sprays against human attackers, as well.</p>
        <p>Given elephants' reliance on smell and taste, he said, the theory was ''it must hurt them 10 times more.''</p>
        <p>In Africa, Dr. Osborn has been experimenting over the last seven years with ways to use a spray against invading elephants.</p>
        <p>The first efforts involved homemade contraptions resembling fire extinguishers that produced a peppery fog. But these required the operator to get dangerously close to elephants, and a change in wind direction meant trouble for the person as well as the animal.</p>
        <p>Jack Birochak, a designer of defensive spray devices in Wayne, Pa., devised a low-tech launcher using pressurized air -- pumped up with a bicycle pump -- to lob a small pepper-spray grenade 60 or 70 yards.</p>
        <p>But that fairly complicated device has since been reserved for the most recalcitrant elephants, Dr. Osborn said.</p>
        <p>For the main effort, he has gone several steps further down the technology ladder, devising a layered pepper defense that starts with the design of the farm itself.</p>
        <p>Many farms in the river valley are laid out rather haphazardly, with no clearly defined edge that elephants can recognize, he said.</p>
        <p>So he worked with some farmers to help them create a cleared path between forest and fields. He said elephants' behavior changes when they venture into fields, showing that they are cognizant that they are on hostile terrain.</p>
        <p>To make a raid more difficult, the farmers then plant hot peppers and dense, thorny thickets of sisal -- a source of poles and cord fiber -- around the field perimeter. Elephants tend to avoid unpalatable or thorny plants, Dr. Osborn said.</p>
        <p>Next comes the cash crop, generally cotton, which elephants eat grudgingly. Deepest in the field, the farmers plant the most desirable food crops, like corn.</p>
        <p>Around the edge, he helped villagers at six sites erect a flimsy pepper-coated fence, consisting only of lengths of rough twine strung between hand-hewn poles. The strings were smeared with a mixture of grease and an extremely concentrated extract of capsaicin from habanero peppers, the hottest of the hot.</p>
        <p>Pepper intensity is measured in Scoville units, a system devised in 1912 by Wilbur Scoville, a Detroit pharmacologist. Jalapeno peppers rate 2,500 to 5,000 units. The habanero extract used by Dr. Osborn registers 1,000,000 Scoville units.</p>
        <p>Initially, Dr. Osborn imported the substance from American hot-sauce suppliers, but he is planning to set up a small factory in Zimbabwe to begin producing the extract from locally grown peppers, hopefully creating a new market for the country's farmers and providing a local source of anti-elephant essence.</p>
        <p>A research assistant, Kinos Mariba, came up with another weapon: adobe-like briquettes of elephant dung and ground hot chilies.</p>
        <p>On the moonless nights that elephants prefer, farmers set small fires around their fields. When they hear intruding elephants, they poke the embers into a blaze, creating a haze of acrid, trunk-stinging smoke.  Generally, the nights are windless, he said, reducing the risk of a toxic cloud drifting into a village. (The dung does not seem to contribute to the repellent effect but is simply an abundant burnable medium, he said.)</p>
        <p>The operation, at least for the first year, was a success, he said. ''You'd see elephants looking with confusion at the tip of their trunk,'' he said. ''If they pushed through the fence, they got it on their sides and try to wipe it off with their trunk.''</p>
        <p>The response, almost invariably, was that the elephants would shuffle off in search of easier fare.</p>
        <p>This year, the goal is to see if the farmers at the test sites pursue the strategy on their own as the growing season approaches. ''This will only work if they want it,'' he said.</p>
        <p>While in the United States, he has bought a large supply of habanero and tabasco pepper seed to bring back to Zimbabwe.</p>
        <p>A secondary goal, he said, is to create a line of gourmet hot sauces that could be produced in northern Zimbabwe and sold internationally to raise money for the elephant research.</p>
        <p>''One of the frustrations of being a zoologist is that you don't really produce anything,'' he said. This way, he said, he may be able to create jobs, a market for a new crop, and perhaps save a few elephants -- and a few farmers.</p>
        <p>DUNG-PEPPER ANTI-ELEPHANT BRIQUETTES  (Courtesy of Kinos Mariba)</p>
        <p>1 pound hot chilies, crushed  2 pounds fresh elephant dung.</p>
        <p>1. Blend the dung and pounded peppers and form into a brick shape.</p>
        <p>2. Place in the sun for a day or two to harden and dry out.</p>
        <p>Yield: Makes one briquette.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
