<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Riches Hidden in Plain Sight</title>
    <meta content="20GALA$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208827"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ESSAY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Evolution</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Galapagos Islands</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yoon, Carol Kaesuk</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Darwin, Charles Robert (1809-82)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Columns/Essay</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Ecuador</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Ecuador/Galapagos Islands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Evolution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000620T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E3D61531F933A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1664" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Riches Hidden in Plain Sight</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAROL KAESUK YOON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Yoon, Carol Kaesuk</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Carol Kaesuk Yoon article notes Charles Darwin's first impressions of Galapagos Islands gave no hint that archipelago would inspire his world-changing revelation on evolution; notes islands are bleak and desertlike and inhabited by relatively few types of creatures; notes they are free of confusing excesses of species and so better display evolution's handwork; map; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When I was in graduate school, a friend who thought I needed to get out of the lab more often pointed out a newly arrived graduate student she thought I might find attractive. I remember saying, ''He looks like a bird.'' I did not mean this in a nice way.</p>
        <p>In fact, Merrill turned out to be rather a gem of a husband and for the life of me, I do not know why I said he looked like a bird.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When I was in graduate school, a friend who thought I needed to get out of the lab more often pointed out a newly arrived graduate student she thought I might find attractive. I remember saying, ''He looks like a bird.'' I did not mean this in a nice way.</p>
        <p>In fact, Merrill turned out to be rather a gem of a husband and for the life of me, I do not know why I said he looked like a bird.</p>
        <p>All this is by way of saying, great treasures are not always instantly recognizable as such.</p>
        <p>Even Charles Darwin, one of history's celebrated geniuses, did not recognize the importance of the Galapagos Islands -- the archipelago that would become forever enshrined in history as the inspiration for his world-changing revelation on evolution -- when he first set foot on their shores 165 years ago.</p>
        <p>Unbeknownst to Darwin, it was the animals he would observe and collect there that would provide his first inkling that species were not immutable as the theological thinking of the day proclaimed. Instead, he would realize that the species he beheld were continually being shaped and changed over time; that is, they evolved.</p>
        <p>It is tempting to imagine Darwin, then the naturalist aboard the ship known as the H.M.S. Beagle, walking into what would become the most important five weeks of his life as an eager explorer, thrilled by each animal and plant encountered, his mind afire with grand ideas.</p>
        <p>But Darwin himself told a rather different story, penning in his diary at the time: ''gloomy sky . . . The plants also smell unpleasantly . . . what we might imagine the cultivated parts of the Infernal regions to be . . . most disgusting, clumsy lizards . . . such insignificant, ugly little flowers as would better become an arctic than a tropical country. . . .''</p>
        <p>Our hero can hardly be blamed, however. For sheer biological exuberance and diversity, the Galapagos are no match for the rain forests of the South American mainland that Darwin also visited, with their green scenes full of towering trees, threaded with vines and overflowing with squawking, chittering, garish, noisy life.</p>
        <p>In stark contrast, the volcanic Galapagos are bleak and desertlike, dry and jagged scrapes of black lava dotted with unimpressive shrubs and cactuses and inhabited by a relative few types of creatures.</p>
        <p>But while these islands did not dazzle young Charles with tropical pizazz, they were free of confusing excesses of species, and so better displayed evolution's handiwork.</p>
        <p>The Galapagos' inhabitants had reached these remote islands by flying, swimming, riding on downed trees or being blown the 500 miles out from the mainland. And each had made the most of the solitude, diversifying into constellations of sometimes bizarre new species to take up new ways of life and fill the empty islands with creatures never before seen.</p>
        <p>With each new arrival, evolution had played out the same story. A different variety of giant tortoise (which give the islands their name, Galapagos meaning tortoises in Spanish) could be found on every island, each with its own style of oversized dome and comically scrawny neck. Land-loving iguanas had spun off the most curious of the island's unique species: a marine iguana that dives in the sea for its dinner, the only lizard in the world to do so.</p>
        <p>And all over the Galapagos blossomed a multitude of finches, apparently descended from one standard little seed-eating type of bird that made its way to these far reaches and whose descendants had evolved all manner of beak to feed on all manner of food. As scientists have since learned, these finches are no longer confined to seeds, but can make their living on nectar, by prying insects out of dead trees with sticks, by plucking ticks off tortoises and iguanas, or feasting on leaves and fruit.</p>
        <p>After returning home to England, Darwin hinted at the possibility of evolution in these finches in his book ''Voyage of the Beagle.''</p>
        <p>''Seeing this gradation and diversity of structure in one small, intimately related group of birds,'' he wrote, ''one might really fancy that from an original paucity of birds in this archipelago, one species had been taken and modified for different ends.'' His fully fleshed out notions of evolution and natural selection would not be published, however, until ''The Origin of Species'' came out 20 years later.</p>
        <p>Today, most of the Encantadas or Enchanted Islands as the Galapagos are also known are designated as Ecuadorean National Park. Tourists are asked to tread lightly as researchers work to restore what has been destroyed in these habitats.</p>
        <p>One of the biggest problems is the toll taken by visitors like those aboard the H.M.S. Beagle. In the 1800's, such islands were viewed, not as hallowed cathedrals of nature, but one-stop shopping centers, a kind of 7-Eleven for the sailing ships of the day.</p>
        <p>Hunting was easy as the animals of the Galapagos have always been strangely tame.</p>
        <p>''Little birds . . . not frightened by stones being thrown at them,'' Darwin wrote in his diary. ''Mr. King killed one with his hat and I pushed off a branch with the end of my gun a large hawk.''</p>
        <p>Giant tortoises were popular game as they could be kept alive on shipboard for weeks or months to provide fresh meat on demand.</p>
        <p>''The tortoise is so abundant that a single ship's company here caught 500-600 in a short time,'' Darwin noted. He himself could not resist the urge to meddle with the beasts. ''They were so heavy,'' he wrote, ''I could scarcely lift them off the ground.''</p>
        <p>It did not help either that many of the creatures were also quite tasty.</p>
        <p>''We lived on the meat of the tortoise fried in the transparent oil, which is procured from the fat,'' he wrote toward the end of his stay. ''Young tortoises make capital soup.''</p>
        <p>Today, scientists are working to save both the giant tortoises and the land iguanas, which have already disappeared off a number of the islands. (In contrast, Darwin described the iguanas as infinite in number, and he constantly tripped over their burrows while trying to find a place to camp.) Scientists are even searching for a mate for a tortoise known as ''Lonesome George,'' a centenarian thought to be the last of his subspecies, a kind of turtle found only on Pinta Island.</p>
        <p>Even as scientists work to save the species, the islands continue to give rise to new ideas and new research. Studies out of Princeton on Darwin's finches show these birds' beaks evolving before researchers' eyes. Studies from Wake Forest University on the masked boobies illuminate curious tendencies to kill siblings.</p>
        <p>From today's perspective, the species of the Galapagos seem to cry out ''Evolution!'' and Darwin's conclusions seem foregone.</p>
        <p>Yet when he set sail on the Beagle, he was 22, had little in the way of scientific training, and in his five-year round-the-world journey was bombarded with social, cultural, geological as well as biological information.</p>
        <p>Remember too that he was not in search of a universal theory to explain biological diversification. Add to that the fact that this was a man who had nearly passed up the journey of a lifetime because he did not want to miss the opening of partridge hunting season in England, and it all seems quite a miracle.</p>
        <p>In a very real sense, he was a young man, like any young man, on an adventure, a brief detour from the life his father had decreed for him of ministering in a quiet, country parsonage.</p>
        <p>One sees this, the simple humanity of Charles Darwin, most easily in the pocket notebooks in which he scrawled his thoughts on the journey, unedited. There he made memos to get his watch fixed or kept his shopping lists: ''Night-caps, black ribbon, pill-boxes, Bramah pens, 2 lbs. common soap, tobacco.'' He meditated for himself on the tropical scene: ''Twiners entwining twiners, tresses like hair, beautiful lepidoptera, silence . . .''</p>
        <p>Seen in this light, Darwin -- and other foolish youths as well -- may perhaps be forgiven their youthful inability to recognize the value of the very handsome opportunities life has set before them.</p>
        <p>For while the Galapagos may have signified little to Darwin as he first set foot on them, he surely understood their importance later in life when he attributed all his ideas to those lonely isles.</p>
        <p>''What fine opportunities for geology and for studying the infinite host of living beings!'' he would later say of his travels. ''If I was to throw it away, I don't think I should ever rest quiet in my grave. I certainly should be a ghost and haunt the British Museum.''</p>
        <p>ESSAY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
