<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Sheik of Chic And the Soul of Perfection</title>
    <meta content="20DRES$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Fashion Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208854"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Horyn, Cathy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Valentino (Designer)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000620T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E0DD1231F933A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1355" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Sheik of Chic And the Soul of Perfection</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CATHY HORYN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Horyn, Cathy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Cathy Horyn article discusses fashions of designer Valentino; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To give an idea just how perfect Valentino, the Roman designer, is, two people, both Americans who don't wish their names to be used, tell a similar story involving a hair dryer. Evidently, when Valentino and his business partner, Giancarlo Giammetti, were moored off Capri last summer in Valentino's 152-foot yacht, T. M. Blue One, there was a lot of coifing going on.</p>
        <p>''One of them would jump in the water for a swim, come back out, and suddenly you'd hear a blow-dryer going, 'Bzzzzzzz,' '' said one of the observers, who was on a boat nearby. ''In Capri, you're either wet from the water or from the heat. It's impossible to look your best all the time. But all day long, you'd hear the sound of a blow-dryer coming from their boat. 'Bzzzzzzz.' Ten times a day.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To give an idea just how perfect Valentino, the Roman designer, is, two people, both Americans who don't wish their names to be used, tell a similar story involving a hair dryer. Evidently, when Valentino and his business partner, Giancarlo Giammetti, were moored off Capri last summer in Valentino's 152-foot yacht, T. M. Blue One, there was a lot of coifing going on.</p>
        <p>''One of them would jump in the water for a swim, come back out, and suddenly you'd hear a blow-dryer going, 'Bzzzzzzz,' '' said one of the observers, who was on a boat nearby. ''In Capri, you're either wet from the water or from the heat. It's impossible to look your best all the time. But all day long, you'd hear the sound of a blow-dryer coming from their boat. 'Bzzzzzzz.' Ten times a day.''</p>
        <p>''Perfect'' was also the word Barry Diller, the media mogul and a guest at the party Mr. Giammetti gave last Wednesday night at the Four Seasons, used to describe what it's like to be in one of Valentino's homes (Capri, Gstaad, London, Rome, New York, Paris) or on his yacht, where everything -- from the Turkish towels to the delicious food to the mix of guests and even the uniforms of the staff -- is, well, perfect.</p>
        <p>''It reflects a remarkable level of discipline,'' Mr. Diller said.</p>
        <p>And perfect was certainly the impression Valentino hoped to give when he received me one morning last week in his Fifth Avenue apartment, whose decorator style, by Peter Marino -- French commodes, oil paintings, object upon object, all surrounded by yards of brown silk gingham on the walls -- might be summed up as Continental fancy-casual.</p>
        <p>Not a hair was out of place, not a well-shod foot put wrong as Valentino entered the room, settled into a chair and turned on the warmth like a rotisserie lamp.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Giammetti said to me afterward : ''We can be having a fight -- and our fights are not fights, they are dramas, with broken things. But suddenly you arrive, and he's'' -- Mr. Giammetti lowered a hand in front of his face -- ''a mask.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Giammetti, who was 21 when he met Valentino Garavani, then 28, in 1960, conceded that such immaculate composure was a useful quality in the fashion business, where image is everything. ''But sometimes,'' he said, ''I imagine people would also like to scream and say what they think.''</p>
        <p>This is Valentino's 40th year in fashion, and his achievement in a pantheon of glamorous self-made designers who came along in the go-go years of fashion, when the truly swell did set the pace, was acknowledged here last week in the usual ways.</p>
        <p>On Tuesday, Katherine Betts, editor in chief of Harper's Bazaar, gave him a dinner. Carolina Herrera, who wore his clothes in the 1970's before she wore her own designs, followed on Wednesday with a cocktail party at her Upper East Side town house. Everybody was there: Dominick Dunne; Judy Peabody; Pat Buckley; Henry and Louise Grunwald; Annette de la Renta; Graydon Carter, the editor of Vanity Fair; Patrick McCarthy, the editor of Women's Wear Daily; and C. Z. Guest, who vividly recalled giving Valentino a pair of her riding chaps after he had raved about how chic they were.</p>
        <p>On Thursday, the Council of Fashion Designers of America gave him its Lifetime Achievement Award. And, of course, there was the dinner at the Four Seasons, where Valentino, his right arm in a red sling from a fall at his house in France, moved from cheek to powdered cheek. He seemed tanner than he had that morning, when amid the oil paintings and decorator checks, he described his ideal day.</p>
        <p>''First of all,'' he said with a smile, ''you have to wake up and look at yourself in the mirror and say, 'I'm not really so bad.' I realize more and more that when you start your day in a good mood, things go a lot better.''</p>
        <p>He paused, reflecting on what seemed even to him to be a very blossomy Barbara Cartland sentiment, and went on: ''You know, I don't like to go out so much anymore. I love to see friends. I love to have little dinners.''</p>
        <p>This seemed surprising coming from a man with homes in five countries who lives lavishly and despite a reputation in the industry for working hard and maintaining one of the best couture ateliers in Europe, appears to be constantly playing.</p>
        <p>''No! No! Totally the opposite,'' Valentino exclaimed. ''In Rome, nobody invites me anymore because I always regret. Regret, regret, regret!'' (Valentino tends to speak in triplicate.)</p>
        <p>He continued: ''No, I love to stay with my dogs. I live a very, very cozy life. I have this home in France, and I love to go to see the garden, to walk and to think. I'm a very sensitive person, you know.''</p>
        <p>It was while rescuing a dog at this house in May that Valentino dislocated his shoulder. He was walking down a muddy slope when one of his pugs came under attack by a swan, and he fell as he went to the dog's aid. Nerve damage in the arm still gives him trouble, and he has been seeing a specialist here.</p>
        <p>In a sense, Valentino is one of the last embodiments of jet-set glamour. His designs -- the precisely tailored suits and coats, the pin-tucked blouses and entrance-making columns -- have always struck women as pretty and men as sexy, and rarely more than in the high-spending 1980's, when Women's Wear Daily labeled Valentino ''the Sheik of Chic'' (though the paper's editor at the time, John Fairchild, could needle him, too).</p>
        <p>One can't help wondering who among Val's gals left the deepest impression.</p>
        <p>''You want some names?'' he asked. He clasped his hands together and said, ''I have to say, not because she made me famous in the United States, but for me Jackie Kennedy was one of the icons.'' He looked thoughtful. ''You look like her.''</p>
        <p>I wondered if Valentino had had too much sun.</p>
        <p>He quickly added the qualifier, ''around the eyes,'' and then returned to his recollections in a purring voice: ''Jackie did a wonderful thing for my career. So did Babe Paley and Jayne Wrightsman. So many, many, many ladies.''</p>
        <p>At the awards party given by the Council of Fashion Designers of America, Carolina Herrera was asked if after all these years of knowing Valentino, she could really say she knew him at all. ''Ah, that's a tricky question,'' she said with a smile. ''He's very clever. I think he only lets people know what he wants them to know. He's always the same.''</p>
        <p>Which is not to say he is predictable. In fact, he told a story that says a great deal about what lies beneath the smooth corona of hair and the Caraceni suits.</p>
        <p>''One day, arriving at the airport in Rome, I saw outside the most terrible dog,'' he said. ''All dirty, not able to walk. I said to my people, 'Let's take the dog home in the car.' ''</p>
        <p>The designer, who also has three pugs and two French poodles, named the dog Stella. ''She's now the queen of the house,'' he said, beaming.</p>
        <p>Well, you have to like a man who loves animals.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
